<act><title>


The Trade Unions Act, 1926</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the 

    1[***] Trade Unions 
    Act, 1926.
 


    2[(2) It extends to 
    the whole of India 

    3[***].] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date4 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 
 








 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In this Act <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[“the appropriate 
Government” means, in relation to Trade Unions whose objects are not confined to 
one State, the Central Government, and in relation to other Trade Unions, the 
State Government, and], unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or 
context,— 
 <section><number>a</number> “executive'' means the body, by whatever name called, to which the 
management of the affairs of a Trade Union is entrusted; 
 <title>State Amendments </title>
 <subsection><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—In section 2, after clause (a), insert the 
following clause, namely:— 
 
 ‘(aa) “Industrial Court” means the Industrial Court constituted under the 
  Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1946, as in force in the State of Gujarat;' 
  
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 7 of 1962, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-1962 ).] 

 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—In section 2, renumber clause (a) as clause 
(a2) and before clause (a2) as so renumbered, insert the following clauses, 
namely:— 
 
 ‘(a) “approved list” means the list of approved unions maintained by the 
  Registrar under section 28A; 
 
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—In section 2, renumber clause (b) as clause 
(b2) and before clause (b2) as so renumbered, insert the following clauses, 
namely:— 
 ‘(b) “ Industrial Court ” shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Madhya 
Pradesh Industrial Relations Act, 1960; 
 † [***]' 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 ).] 

 † Clause (b1) omitted by Madhya Pradesh Act 26 of 1981, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
23-5-1981 ). 
 </subsection><subsection><number>a1</number> “approved union” means a registered Trade Union on the approved list.' 
  
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 
  ).] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[“office-bearer”], in the case of a Trade Union, includes 
  any member of the executive thereof, but does not include an auditor; 
</section><section><number>c</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by regulations made under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “registered office” means that office of a Trade Union which is 
registered under this Act as the head office thereof; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “registered Trade Union” means a Trade Union registered under this Act; 

 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>f</number> “Registrar” means— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a Registrar of Trade Unions appointed by the appropriate Government under 
section 3, and includes any Additional or Deputy Registrar of Trade Unions, and 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> in relation to any Trade Union, the Registrar appointed for the State in 
which the head or registered office, as the case may be, of the Trade Union is 
situated;] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>g</number> “trade dispute” means any dispute between employers and workmen or 
between workmen and workmen, or between employers and employers which is 
connected with the employment or non-employment, or the terms of employment or 
the conditions of labour, of any person, and “workmen” means all persons 
employed in trade or industry whether or not in the employment of the employer 
with whom the trade dispute arises; and 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “Trade Union” means any combination, whether temporary or permanent, 
formed primarily for the purpose of regulating the relations between workmen and 
employers or between workmen and workmen, or between employers and employers, or 
for imposing restrictive conditions on the conduct of any trade or business, and 
includes any federation of two or more Trade Unions: 
 Provided that this Act shall not affect— 
 
 











</section><section><number>i</number> any agreement between partners as to their own business; 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> any agreement between an employer and those employed by him as to such 
  employment; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> any agreement in consideration of the sale of the goodwill of a 
  business or of instruction in any profession, trade or handicraft. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Appointment of Registrars.—1[
<section><number>1</number>]
    

    2[The appropriate 
    Government] shall appoint a person to be the Registrar of Trade Unions for
    

    3[each State].
 


    4[(2) The appropriate 
    Government may appoint as many Additional and Deputy Registrars of Trade 
    Unions as it thinks fit for the purpose of exercising and discharging, under 
    the superintendence and direction of the Registrar, such powers and 
    functions of the Registrar under this Act as it may, by order, specify and 
    define the local limits within which any such Additional or Deputy Registrar 
    shall exercise and discharge the powers and functions so specified.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of any order under sub-section (2), where an 
    Additional or Deputy Registrar exercises and discharges the powers and 
    functions of a Registrar in an area within which the registered office of a 
    Trade Union is situated, the Additional or Deputy Registrar shall be deemed 
    to be the Registrar in relation to the Trade Union for the purposes of this 
    Act.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Mode of registration.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Any seven or more members of a Trade Union may, by subscribing their names 
    to the rules of the Trade Union and by otherwise complying with the 
    provisions of this Act with respect to registration, apply for registration 
    of the Trade Union under this Act: 
 


    2[Provided that no 
    Trade Union of workmen shall be registered unless at least ten per cent. or 
    one hundred of the workmen, whichever is less, engaged or employed in the 
    establishment or industry with which it is connected are the members of such 
    Trade Union on the date of making of application for registration:  
 
Provided 
    further that no Trade Union of workmen shall be registered unless it has on 
    the date of making application not less than seven persons as its members, 
    who are workmen engaged or employed in the establishment or industry with 
    which it is connected.]  
 


    3[(2) Where an 
    application has been made under sub-section (1) for the registration of a 
    Trade Union, such application shall not be deemed to have become invalid 
    merely by reason of the fact that, at any time after the date of the 
    application, but before the registration of the Trade Union, some of the 
    applicants, but not exceeding half of the total number of persons who made 
    the application, have ceased to be members of the Trade Union or have given 
    notice in writing to the Registrar dissociating themselves from the 
    applications.]
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Application for registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for 
registration of a Trade Union shall be made to the Registrar, and shall be 
accompanied by a copy of the rules of the Trade Union and a statement of the 
following particulars, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the names, occupations and addresses of the members making the 
  application; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> in the case of a Trade Union of workmen, the names, 
  occupations and addresses of the place of work of the members of the Trade 
  Union making the application;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the name of the Trade Union and the address of its head office; and 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the titles, names, ages, addresses and occupations of the 4 
  [office-bearers] of the Trade Union. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a Trade Union has been in existence for more than one year before 
the making of an application for its registration, there shall be delivered to 
the Registrar, together with the application, a general statement of the assets 
and liabilities of the Trade Union prepared in such form and containing such 
particulars as may be prescribed. 
  

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Provisions to be contained in the rules of a Trade Union. 
</title>—A Trade Union shall not be entitled to registration under this Act, 
unless the executive thereof is constituted in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act, and the rules thereof provide for the following matters, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the name of the Trade Union; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the whole of the objects for which the Trade Union has been 
  established; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the whole of the purposes for which the general funds of the Trade 
  Union shall be applicable, all of which purposes shall be purposes to which 
  such funds are lawfully applicable under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the maintenance of a list of the members of the Trade Union and 
  adequate facilities for the inspection thereof by the 
  <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[office-bearers] and members of Trade Union; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> the admission of ordinary members who shall be persons actually engaged 
  or employed in an industry with which the Trade Union is connected, and also 
  the admission of the number of honorary or temporary members as 
  <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[office-bearers] required under section 22 to form the executive 
  of the Trade Union; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>ee</number> the payment of a minimum subscription by members of the 
  Trade Union which shall not be less than— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> one rupee per annum for rural workers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> three rupees per annum for workers in other unorganised sectors; and 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> twelve rupees per annum for workers in any other case;] 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number> the conditions under which any member shall be entitled to any benefit 
  assured by the rules and under which any fine or forfeiture may be imposed on 
  the members; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> the manner in which the rules shall be amended, varied or rescinded; 
  
 </section><section><number>h</number> the manner in which the members of the executive and the other 
  <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[office-bearers] of the Trade Union shall be <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[elected] 
  and removed; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>hh</number> the duration of period being not more than three years, 
  for which the members of the executive and other office-bearers of the Trade 
  Union shall be elected;] 
 </section><section><number>i</number> the safe custody of the funds of the Trade Union, an annual audit, in 
  such manner as may be prescribed, of the accounts thereof, and adequate 
  facilities for the inspection of the account books by the 
  <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[office-bearers] and members of the Trade Union; and 
 </section><section><number>j</number> the manner in which the Trade Union may be dissolved. </section>
 <title>State Amendments </title>
 <section><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—In section 6, after clause (f), insert the 
following clause, namely:— 
 “(ff) the termination of membership of the Trade Union of persons whose 
subscription is in arrears for a period exceeding six months or for such lesser 
period as may be provided in the rules;” 
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 7 of 1962, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-1962 ).] 
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—In section 6, for clause (ee), substitute 
the following clause, namely:— 
 “(ee) the payment of subscription by members of the Trade Union which shall 
not be less than twenty-five naye paise per month per member: 
 Provided that the minimum rate of subscription in the case of members of a 
Trade Union of agricultural workers shall be five paise per month per member.” 

 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 16 of 1968, sec. 2.] 








</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Power to call for further particulars and to require alteration of 
name. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar may call for further information for the 
purpose of satisfying himself that any application complies with the provisions 
of section 5, or that the Trade Union is entitled to registration under section 
6, and may refuse to register the Trade Union until such information is 
supplied. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the name under which a Trade Union is proposed to be registered is 
identical with that by which any other existing Trade Union has been registered 
or, in the opinion of the Registrar, so nearly resembles such name as to be 
likely to deceive the public or the members of either Trade Union, the Registrar 
shall require the persons applying for registration to alter the name of the 
Trade Union stated in the application, and shall refuse to register the Union 
until such alteration has been made. </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Registration.—The 
    Registrar, on being satisfied that the Trade Union has complied with all the 
    requirements of this Act in regard to registration, shall register the Trade 
    Union by entering in a register, to be maintained in such form as may be 
    prescribed, the particulars relating to the Trade Union contained in the 
    statement accompanying the application for registration.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Certificate of registration.—The 
    Registrar, on registering a Trade Union under section 8, shall issue a 
    certificate of registration in the prescribed form which shall be conclusive 
    evidence that the Trade Union has been duly registered under this Act.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>9A</number> Minimum 
    requirement about membership of a Trade Union.—A 
    registered Trade Union of workmen shall at all times continue to have not 
    less than ten per cent. or one hundred of the workmen, whichever is less, 
    subject to a minimum of seven, engaged or employed in an establishment or 
    industry with which it is connected, as its members.]  
 
 




 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Cancellation of registration. </title>—A certificate of 
registration of a Trade Union may be withdrawn or cancelled by the Registrar— 

 
 <section><number>a</number> on the application of the Trade Union to be verified in such manner as 
  may be prescribed; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> if the Registrar is satisfied that the certificate has been obtained by 
  fraud or mistake, or that the Trade Union has ceased to exist or has wilfully 
  and after notice from the Registrar contravened any provision of this Act or 
  allowed any rule to continue in force which is inconsistent with any such 
  provision, or has rescinded any rule providing for any matter provision for 
  which is required by  section 6; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> if the Registrar is satisfied that a registered Trade 
  Union of workmen ceases to have the requisite number of members:] 
</section>
 Provided that not less than two months' previous notice in writing specifying 
the ground on which it is proposed to withdraw or cancel the certificate shall 
be given by the Registrar to the Trade Union before the certificate is withdrawn 
or cancelled otherwise than on the application of the Trade Union. 
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 <title>Section 10A </title>
 <section><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—After section 10, insert the following section, 
namely:— 
 “10A. Liability of existing registered Trade Unions to make certain 
provisions in their Rules. —(1) The rules of every Trade Union which was 
registered under this Act before the date of commencement of the Indian Trade 
Unions (Gujarat Amendment) Act, 1961, and the certificate of registration of 
which is in force on that date shall provide for the matter specified in clause 
(ff) of section 6. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> If no provision as required by sub-section (1) is made in the rules of 
any existing Trade Union before the expiry of six months from the date mentioned 
in sub-  section (1), the Registrar may cancel the registration of such Trade 
Union: 
 Provided that not less than two months' notice in writing specifying the 
grounds on which it is proposed to cancel the certificate shall be given by the 
Registrar to the Trade Union before the certificate is cancelled.” 
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 7 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1965 ).] 








</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<title><number>11</number> Appeal. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by any 
refusal of the Registrar to register a Trade Union or by the withdrawal or 
cancellation of a certificate of registration may, within such period as may be 
prescribed, appeal— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where the head office of the Trade Union is situated within the limits 
  of a Presidency town <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***] to the High Court, or 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> where the head office is situated in an area, falling 
  within the jurisdiction of a Labour Court or an Industrial Tribunal, to that 
  Court or Tribunal, as the case may be;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where the head office is situated in any area, to such Court, not 
  inferior to the Court of an additional or assistant Judge of a principal Civil 
  Court of original jurisdiction, as the <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[appropriate Government] 
  may appoint in this behalf for that area. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appellate Court may dismiss the appeal, or pass an order directing 
the Registrar to register the Union and to issue a certificate of registration 
under the provisions of section 9 or setting aside the order or withdrawal or 
cancellation of the certificate, as the case may be, and the Registrar shall 
comply with such order. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> For the purpose of an appeal under sub-section (1) an appellate Court 
shall, so far as may be, follow the same procedure and have the same powers as 
it follows and has when trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 
 (5 of 1908), and may direct by whom the whole or any part of the costs of 
the appeal shall be paid, and such costs shall be recovered as if they had been 
awarded in a suit under the said Code. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the event of the dismissal of an appeal by any Court appointed under 
clause (b) of sub-section (1) the person aggrieved shall have a right of appeal 
to the High Court, and the High Court shall, for the purpose of such appeal, 
have all the powers of an appellate Court under sub-sections (2) and (3), and 
the provisions of those sub-sections shall apply accordingly.] 
 <title>State Amendments </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—For section 11, substitute the following 
section, namely:— 
 “11. Appeal .—(1) Any person aggrieved by an order of the Registrar— 

 <subsection><number>a</number> refusing to register a Trade Union; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> withdrawing or cancelling a certificate of registration, 
 may within thirty days from the communication of such order to the Trade 
Union concerned, appeal to the Industrial Court whose decision shall be final: 

 Provided that in computing the period of thirty days, the time requisite for 
obtaining a copy of the order shall be excluded. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall comply with any order passed by the Industrial Court 
under sub-section (1).” 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 ).] 

 <title>Section 11A </title>
 <subsection><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—After section 11, insert the following section, 
namely:— 
 “11A. Appeal to Industrial Court in certain cases. —(1) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) of section 11 in the case 
of a Trade Union in relation to which the State Government is the appropriate 
Government, any person aggrieved by any refusal of the Registrar to register 
such Trade Union or by withdrawal or cancellation of a certificate of 
registration may within such period as may be prescribed, appeal to the 
Industrial Court. The decision of the Industrial Court in such appeal shall be 
final. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In respect of an appeal under sub-section (1), the Industrial Court shall 
have the same power and follow the same procedure as an appellate Court has and 
follows under sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 11.” 
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 7 of 1962, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-1962 ).] 








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Registered office.—All 
    communications and notices to a registered Trade Union may be addressed to 
    its registered office. Notice of any change in the address of the head 
    office shall be given within fourteen days of such change to the Registrar 
    in writing, and the changed address shall be recorded in the register 
    referred to in section 8.  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Incorporation of registered Trade Unions. </title>—Every 
registered Trade Union shall be a body corporate by the name under which it is 
registered, and shall have perpetual succession and a common seal with power to 
acquire and hold both movable and immovable property and to contract, and shall 
by the said name sue and be sued. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Certain Acts not to apply to registered Trade Unions. 
</title>—The following Acts, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> The Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> The Co-operative Societies Act, 1912 (2 of 1912); 
 </section><section><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> The Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)], </section>
 shall not apply to any registered Trade Union, and the registration of any 
such Trade Union under any such Act shall be void. 
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 <section><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—After Chapter II, insert the following Chapter, 
namely:— 
 <title>“Chapter IIA </title>
 <title>Disputes relating to office in, or Membership of  the 
Executive of, a Trade Union </title>
 “14A. Reference of certain disputes to Industrial Court. —(1) If 
there is any dispute as to who is the lawful officer of a Trade Union or a 
member of the executive thereof, any person who has been a member of the Trade 
Union for not less than six months immediately before the date on which the 
dispute arose, may, with the consent of Registrar and in such manner as may be 
prescribed, refer the dispute to the Industrial Court for a decision. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> On a reference being made under sub-section (1) the Industrial Court 
shall, after hearing the parties to such dispute, decide the dispute. The Court 
may in its discretion require the holding of fresh elections under its 
supervision to decide the dispute. The decision of the Industrial Court shall be 
final and shall not be called in question in any Court of law. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>3</number> Pending the disposal of the reference, the Industrial Court may make an 
interim order specifying the persons who shall be deemed to be the lawful 
officers of the Trade Union or the members of the executive thereof, as the case 
may be, until the decision of the dispute. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>4</number> No Civil Court shall entertain any civil suit or other proceeding in 
relation to disputes mentioned in this section.” 
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 7 of 1962, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-1962 ).] 
  

</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Objects on which general funds may be spent. </title>—The 
general funds of a registered Trade Union shall not be spent on any other 
objects than the following, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the payment of salaries, allowances and expenses to 
  <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[office-bearers] of the Trade Union; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the payment of expenses for the administration of the Trade Union, 
  including audit of the accounts of the general funds of the Trade Union; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the prosecution or defence of any legal proceeding to which the Trade 
  Union or any member thereof is a party, when such prosecution or defence is 
  undertaken for the purpose of securing or protecting any rights of the Trade 
  Union as such or any rights arising out of the relations of any member with 
  his employer or with a person whom the member employs; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the conduct of trade disputes on behalf of the Trade Union or any 
  member thereof; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> the compensation of members for loss arising out of trade disputes; 

 </section><section><number>f</number> allowances to members or their dependants on account of death, old age, 
  sickness, accidents or unemployment of such members; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> the issue of, or the undertaking of liability under, policies of 
  assurance on the lives of members, or under policies insuring members against 
  sickness, accident or unemployment; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> the provision of educational, social or religious benefits for members 
  (including the payment of the expenses of funeral or religious ceremonies for 
  deceased members) or for the dependants of members; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> the upkeep of a periodical published mainly for the purpose of 
  discussing questions affecting employers or workmen as such; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> the payment, in furtherance of any of the objects on which the general 
  funds of the Trade Union may be spent, of contributions to any cause intended 
  to benefit workmen in general, provided that the expenditure in respect of 
  such contributions in any financial year shall not at any time during that 
  year be in excess of one-fourth of the combined total of the gross income 
  which has up to that time accrued to the general funds of the Trade Union 
  during that year and of the balance at the credit of those funds at the 
  commencement of that year; and 
 </section><section><number>k</number> subject to any conditions contained in the notification, any other 
  object notified by the <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[appropriate Government] in the Official 
  Gazette. </section>
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 <section><title><number>Maharashtra</number> </title>—In Chapter III, in the Heading, after the 
words, ‘Trade Unions', insert the words “and Settlement of Certain Disputes”. 

 [ Vide Maharashtra Act 3 of 1968, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 10-10-1968 ).] 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Constitution of a separate fund for political purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A registered Trade Union may constitute a separate fund, from contributions 
    separately levied for or made to that fund, from which payments may be made, 
    for the promotion of the civic and political interests of its members, in 
    furtherance of any of the objects specified in sub-section (2). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    objects referred to in sub-section (1) are— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the payment of any expenses 
    incurred, either directly or indirectly, by a candidate or prospective 
    candidate for election as a member of any legislative body constituted under
    1[***]
    2[the 
    Constitution] or of any local authority, before, during, or after the 
    election in connection with his candidature or election; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the holding of any meeting or the 
    distribution of any literature or documents in support of any such candidate 
    or prospective candidate; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the maintenance of any person who 
    is a member of any legislative body constituted under 
1[***]
    2[the 
    Constitution] or for any local authority; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the registration of electors or 
    the selection of a candidate for any legislative body constituted under
    1[***]
    2[the 
    Constitution] or for any local authority; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the holding of political meetings 
    of any kind, or the distribution of political literature or political 
    documents of any kind. 
 


    3[(2A) In its 
    application to the State of Jammu and Kashmir, references in sub-section (2) 
    to any legislative body constituted under the Constitution shall be 
    construed as including references to the Legislature of that State.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    member shall be compelled to contribute to the fund constituted under 
    sub-section (1); and a member who does not contribute to the said fund shall 
    not be excluded from any benefits of the Trade Union, or placed in any 
    respect either directly or indirectly under any disability or at any 
    disadvantage as compared with other members of the Trade Union (except in 
    relation to the control or management of the said fund) by reason of his not 
    contributing to the said fund; and contribution to the said fund shall not 
    be made a condition for admission to the Trade Union. 
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Criminal conspiracy in trade disputes. </title>—No 
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[office-bearer] or member of a registered Trade Union shall be 
liable to punishment under sub-section (2) of section 120B of the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of 1860), in respect of any agreement made between the members for the 
purpose of furthering any such object of the Trade Union as is specified in 
section 15, unless the agreement is an agreement to commit an offence. 





</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Immunity from civil suit in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No suit or other legal proceeding shall be maintainable in any Civil Court 
    against any registered Trade Union or any 

    1[office-bearer] or 
    member thereof in respect of any act done in contemplation or furtherance of 
    a trade dispute to which a member of the Trade Union is a party on the 
    ground only that such act induces some other person to break a contract of 
    employment, or that it is in interference with the trade, business or 
    employment of some other person or with the right of some other person to 
    dispose of his capital or of his labour as he wills.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    registered Trade Union shall not be liable in any suit or other legal 
    proceeding in any Civil Court in respect of any tortious act done in 
    contemplation or furtherance of a trade dispute by an agent of the Trade 
    Union if it is proved that such person acted without the knowledge of, or 
    contrary to express instructions given by, the executive of the Trade Union.  
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Enforceability of agreements.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, an 
    agreement between the members of a registered Trade Union shall not be void 
    or voidable merely by reason of the fact that any of the objects of the 
    agreement are in restraint of trade:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this section shall enable any Civil Court to entertain any 
    legal proceeding instituted for the express purpose of enforcing or 
    recovering damages for the breach of any agreement concerning the conditions 
    on which any members of a Trade Union shall or shall not sell their goods, 
    transact business, work, employ or be employed.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Right to inspect books of Trade Union.—The 
    account books of a registered Trade Union and the list of members thereof 
    shall be open to inspection by an 

    1[office-bearer] or 
    member of the Trade Union at such times as may be provided for in the rules 
    of the Trade Union.  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Rights of minors to membership of Trade Unions.—Any 
    person who has attained the age of fifteen years may be a member of a 
    registered Trade Union subject to any rules of the Trade Union to the 
    contrary, and may, subject as aforesaid, enjoy all the rights of a member 
    and execute all instruments and give all acquittances necessary to be 
    executed or given under the rules:  
 


    1[***]
  




 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>31</footcitenum></title><title>[<number>21A</number> Disqualifications of 
office-bearers of Trade Unions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall be disqualified for 
being chosen as, and for being, a member of the executive or any other 
office-bearer of a registered Trade Union if— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> he has not attained the age of eighteen years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> he has been convicted by a Court in India of any offence involving 
  moral turpitude and sentenced to imprisonment, unless a period of five years 
  has elapsed since his release. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any member of the executive or other office-bearer of a registered Trade 
Union who, before the commencement of the Indian Trade Unions (Amendment) Act, 
1964, has been convicted of any offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced 
to imprisonment, shall on the date of such commencement cease to be such member 
or office-bearer unless a period of five years has elapsed since his release 
before that date.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> In its application to the State of Jammu and Kashmir, 
reference in sub-section (2) to the commencement of the Indian Trade Unions 
(Amendment) Act, 1964 (38 of 1964), shall be construed as reference to the 
commencement of this Act in the said State.] 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>22</number> Proportion of 
    office-bearers to be connected with the industry.—
<section><number>1</number> Not less than 
    one-half of the total number of the office-bearers of every registered Trade 
    Union in an unrecognised sector shall be persons actually engaged or 
    employed in an industry with which the Trade Union is connected:
 
Provided 
    that the appropriate Government may, by special or general order, declare 
    that the provisions of this section shall not apply to any Trade Union or 
    class of Trade Unions specified in the order.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “unorganised sector” means any sector which 
    the appropriate Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save 
    as otherwise provided in sub-section (1), all office-bearers of a registered 
    Trade Union, except not more than one-third of the total number of the 
    office-bearers or five, whichever is less, shall be persons acutally engaged 
    or employed in the establishment or industry with which the Trade Union is 
    connected.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, an employee who has retired or has been 
    retrenched shall not be construed as outsider for the purpose of holding an 
    office in a Trade Union.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    member of the Council of Ministers or a person holding an office of profit 
    (not being an engagement or employment in an establishment or industry with 
    which the Trade Union is connected), in the Union or a State, shall be a 
    member of the executive or other office-bearer of a registered Trade Union.]  
 





 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Change of name. </title>—Any registered Trade Union may, with 
the consent of not less than two-thirds of the total number of its members and 
subject to the provisions of section 25, change its name. </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Amalgamation of Trade Unions.—Any 
    two or more registered Trade Unions may become amalgamated together as one 
    Trade Union with or without dissolution or division of the funds of such 
    Trade Unions or either or any of them, provided that the votes of at least 
    one-half of the members of each or every such Trade Union entitled to vote 
    are recorded, and that at least sixty per cent. of the votes recorded are in 
    favour of the proposal. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Notice of change of name or amalgamation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notice in writing of every change of name and of every amalgamation signed, 
    in the case of a change of name, by the Secretary and by seven members of 
    the Trade Union changing its name, and in the case of an amalgamation, by 
    the Secretary and by seven members of each and every Trade Union which is a 
    party thereto, shall be sent to the Registrar and where the head office of 
    the amalgamated Trade Union is situated in a different State, to the 
    Registrar of such State.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the proposed name is identical with that by which any other existing Trade 
    Union has been registered or, in the opinion of the Registrar, so nearly 
    resembles such name as to be likely to deceive the public or the members of 
    either Trade Union, the Registrar shall refuse to register the change of 
    name.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save 
    as provided in sub-section (2), the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that 
    the provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
    with, register the change of name in the register referred to in section 8, 
    and the change of name shall have effect from the date of such registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar of the State in which the head office of the amalgamated Trade 
    Union is situated shall, if he is satisfied that the provisions of this Act 
    in respect of amalgamation have been complied with and that the Trade Union 
    formed thereby is entitled to registration under section 6, register the 
    Trade Union in the manner provided in section 8, and the amalgamation shall 
    have effect from the date of such registration.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Effects of change of name and of amalgamation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The change in the name of a registered Trade Union shall not affect any 
    rights or obligations of the Trade Union or render defective any legal 
    proceeding by or against the Trade Union, and any legal proceeding which 
    might have been continued or commenced by or against it by its former name 
    may be continued or commenced by or against it by its new name.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    amalgamation of two or more registered Trade Unions shall not prejudice any 
    right of any of such Trade Unions or any right of a creditor of any of them.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Dissolution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a registered Trade Union is dissolved, notice of the dissolution signed 
    by seven members and by the Secretary of the Trade Union shall, within 
    fourteen days of the dissolution be sent to the Registrar, and shall be 
    registered by him if he is satisfied that the dissolution has been effected 
    in accordance with the rules of the Trade Union, and the dissolution shall 
    have effect from the date of such registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the dissolution of a registered Trade Union has been registered and 
    the rules of the Trade Union do not provide for the distribution of funds of 
    the Trade Union on dissolution, the Registrar shall divide the funds amongst 
    the members in such manner as may be prescribed.  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Returns. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be sent annually to the 
Registrar, on or before such date as may be prescribed, a general statement, 
audited in the prescribed manner, of all receipts and expenditure of every 
registered Trade Union during the year ending on the 31st day of 
<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[December] next preceding such prescribed date, and of the assets 
and liabilities of the Trade Union existing on such 31st day of 
<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[December]. The statement shall be prepared in such form and shall 
comprise such particulars as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Together with the general statement there shall be sent to the Registrar 
a statement showing changes of <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[office-bearers] made by the Trade 
Union during the year to which the general statement refers, together also with 
a copy of the rules of the Trade Union corrected up to the date of the despatch 
thereof to the Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A copy of every alteration made in the rules of a registered Trade Union 
shall be sent to the Registrar within fifteen days of the making of the 
alteration. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> For the purpose of examining the documents referred to in 
sub-sections (1), (2) and (3), the Registrar, or any officer authorised by him, 
by general or special order, may at all reasonable times inspect the certificate 
of registration, account books, registers, and other documents, relating to a 
Trade Union, at its registered office or may require their production at such 
place as he may specify in this behalf, but no such place shall be at a distance 
of more than ten miles from the registered office of a Trade Union.] 
 <title>State Amendments </title>
 <title>Section 28-1A </title>
 <subsection><title><number>Maharashtra</number> </title>—After section 28, insert the following 
section, namely:— 
 “28-1A. Power of Industrial Court to decide certain disputes. —(1) 
Where there is a dispute as respects whether or not any person is an 
office-bearer or a member of a registered Trade Union (including any dispute 
relating to wrongful expulsion of any such office-bearer or member), or where 
there is any dispute relating to the property (including the account books) of 
any registered Trade Union, any member of such registered Trade Union for a 
period of not less than six months may, with the consent of the Registrar, and 
in such manner as may be prescribed, refer the dispute to the Industrial Court 
constituted under the Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1946, for decision. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Industrial Court shall, after hearing the parties to the dispute, 
decide the dispute; and may require an office-bearer or member of the Registered 
Trade Union to be appointed whether by election or otherwise under the 
supervision of such person as the Industrial Court may appoint in this behalf or 
removed, in accordance with the rules of the Trade Union: 
 Provided that the Industrial Court may, pending the decision of the dispute, 
make an interim order specifying or appointing any person or appointing a 
Committee of Administration for any purpose under the Act including the purpose 
of taking possession or control of the property in dispute and managing it for 
the purposes of the Union pending the decision. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The decision of the Industrial Court shall be final and binding on the 
parties and shall not be called in question in any Civil Court . 
 </section><section><number>4</number> No Civil Court shall entertain any suit or other proceedings in relation 
to the dispute referred to the Industrial Court as aforesaid, and if any suit or 
proceeding is pending in any such Court, the Civil Court shall, on receipt of an 
intimation from the Industrial Court that it is seized of the question, cease to 
exercise jurisdiction in respect thereof. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Save as aforesaid, the Industrial Court may, in deciding disputes under 
this section, exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it 
exercises or follows for the purpose of deciding industrial disputes under the 
Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1946.” 
 [ Vide Maharashtra Act 3 of 1968, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968 ).] 
 <title>Chapter IIIA </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—After Chapter III, insert the following new 
Chapter, namely:— 
 <title>“Chapter IIIA </title>
 <title>Approved Unions </title>
 </section></article><article><number>28A</number> Maintenance of list of approved unions .—It shall be the duty 
of the Registrar to maintain in such form as may be prescribed a list of 
approved unions. 
 </article><article><number>28B</number> Certain unions deemed to be approved unions. —A union entered 
on the approved list maintained under the Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1947 
as adopted in Madhya Bharat by the Madhya Bharat Industrial Relations 
(Adaptation) Act, Samvat 2006 (Madhya Bharat Act 31 of 1949), before the 
commencement of the Indian Trade Unions (Madhya Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1960 
(Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960), shall be deemed to be an approved union under 
this Act. 
 </article><article><number>28C</number> Application for and entry in the approved list. —
<section><number>1</number> Any 
Representative Union or where there is no Representative Union any registered 
Trade Union in any industry other than an industry for which the Central 
Government is the appropriate Government within the meaning of sub-clause (i) of 
clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), may 
apply in the prescribed form for being entered in the approved list. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of such application the Registrar shall hold such enquiry as 
is prescribed and if he is satisfied that such union fulfils the conditions 
necessary for its being entered in the approved list, he shall enter the name of 
such union in the approved list and shall issue a certificate of its entry in 
such form as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> where two or more unions fulfilling the conditions necessary for 
  registration specified in section 28D apply for their entry in the approved 
  list, the Union which has the largest membership of the employees employed in 
  the industry, shall alone be entered in the approved list; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the Registrar shall not enter any union in the approved list, if he is 
  satisfied for reasons to be recorded in writing that the application for entry 
  is not made bona fide in the interests of employees but is made in 
  the interests of the employer. </subsection>
 Explanation .—For the purposes of this section, the expression 
“Representative Union” shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Madhya 
Pradesh Industrial Relations Act, 1960 (Madhya Pradesh Act 27 of 1960). 
 </section></article><article><number>28D</number> Conditions of entry in the approved list .—
<section><number>1</number> No union shall 
be entered in the approved list under this Act, unless— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the union has for the whole of the period of three months next 
  preceding the date of application under section 28C a membership of not less 
  than fifteen per cent. of the employees employed in the industry in that local 
  area; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the constitution of the union shall be such as may be provided by or 
  under this Act, and in particular, shall require that— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> the subscription payable for membership shall be not less than four 
    annas a month or such other sum as may be fixed by the State Government 
    under sub-section (2) and that the accounts of the union shall be audited at 
    least once in each financial year by an auditor appointed or approved by the 
    State Government. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> the executive of the union shall meet at least once in three months 
    and that all resolutions passed by the executive or general body shall be 
    recorded in a minute book; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> the union shall not sanction a strike as long as conciliation and 
    arbitration are available and shall not declare a strike until a ballot is 
    taken and the majority of the members of the union vote in favour of the 
    strike. </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may, by notification, direct that in the case of any 
registered trade union of workmen or employees engaged in any employment 
specified in the Schedule to the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, the membership 
subscription may be less than four annas for such period as may be specified 
therein. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any registered Trade Union complying with the conditions specified in 
sub-section (1), and having a larger membership in an industry in a local area 
than an approved union for such industry shall on an application in that behalf 
be entered in the approved list in place of such approved union by the Registrar 
after holding such enquiry as he deems fit. 
 </section></article><article><number>28E</number> Approved union to continue to be so far altered local area for 
sometime. —Notwithstanding anything contained in section 28D, if there is 
any alteration in the local area or areas— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> an approved union in an industry in the altered local area or areas; or 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> where two or more approved unions exist in an industry in the altered 
  local area or areas, the union having the largest membership, whether by 
  agreement of the other approved unions or as determined by the Registrar after 
  such inquiry as he deems fit; </section>
 shall be deemed to be the approved union for the altered local area or areas, 
as the case may be, for a period of six months from the date on which such 
alteration is effected or where such approved union or any other union in the 
altered local area or areas makes an application under section 28C within such 
period until the disposal of such application by the Registrar. 
 </article><article><number>28F</number> Removal from approved list. —The Registrar shall remove a union 
from the approved list if its certificate of registration is cancelled under 
section 10, and may also so remove a union if after holding such enquiry, as he 
deems fit, he is satisfied that it— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> was entered in the list under mistake, misrepresentation or fraud; or 
  
 </section><section><number>ii</number> has, since being included in the approved list, ceased to fulfil the 
  conditions specified in section 28D. </section>
 </article><article><number>28G</number> Appeal .—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by the order of the 
Registrar— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> refusing to enter any registered trade union in the approved list; or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> removing a registered trade union from the approved list; 
</subsection>
 may, within thirty days from the communication of such order to the trade 
union concerned, appeal to the Industrial Court whose decision shall be final: 

 Provided that in computing the period of thirty days the period requisite for 
obtaining a copy of the order shall be excluded. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall comply with any order passed by the Industrial Court 
under sub-section (1). 
 </section></article><article><number>28H</number> Rights of officer of approved unions. —Such officers and 
members of an approved union as may be authorised by or under rules made in this 
behalf by the State Government, shall in such manner and subject to such 
conditions as may be prescribed, have a right— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> to collect sums payable by members to the union on the premises where 
  wages are paid to them; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> to put up or cause to be put up a notice board on the premises of the 
  undertaking in which its members are employed and affix or caused to be 
  affixed notices thereon; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> for the purpose of the prevention or settlement of a trade dispute— 

 
 <subsection><number>i</number> to hold discussions on the premises of the undertaking with the 
    employees concerned who are the members of the union; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> to meet and discuss with an employer or any person appointed by him 
    for the purpose of removing the grievances of its members employed in his 
    undertaking; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> to inspect, if necessary, in any undertaking, any place where any 
    member of the union is employed. </subsection></section>
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 ); 
Madhya Pradesh Act 16 of 1968, sec. 3.] 
 <title>Section 28HH </title>
 “28HH. Definitions .— In this Chapter,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “industry” shall have the meaning assigned to that expression in the 
  Madhya Pradesh Industrial Relations Act, 1960 (27 of 1960). 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “local area” means any area, notified by the Registrar as a local area 
  for any or all Industries for the purpose of this Chapter.” </section>
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 26 of 1981, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 23-5-1981 ).] 

 <title>Section 28-I to 28L </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—In Chapter IV, for the heading 
“Regulations”, substitute the heading “Miscellaneous” and before section 29 
insert the following sections, namely:— 
 <title>“ Chapter IV </title>
 <title>Miscellaneous </title>
 “28-I. Other powers of Registrar.— 
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of 
discharging his duties generally under the Act and verifying the correctness of 
the annual returns submitted under section 28, the Registrar shall have power to 
inspect the account books, the list of members and the minute book of a 
registered Trade Union: 
 Provided that an inspection made under this sub-section shall, as far as 
practicable, be done at the office of the registered Trade Union or at the place 
within a reasonable distance therefrom and after giving reasonable notice. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purposes of discharging his duties under Chapter IIIA, the 
Registrar shall, in addition to the powers mentioned in sub-section (1) have— 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the following powers of a Court of civil jurisdiction under the Code of 
  Civil Procedure, 1908, namely:— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> power to require or accept the proof of facts by affidavits; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> power to summon and enforce the attendance of any person and to 
    examine him on oath; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> power to compel the production of documents; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> power to issue commission for the examination of witnesses; 
  </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> power to enter and inspect any place used by a registered Trade Union 
  as office after giving reasonable notice; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> such other powers as may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section></article><article><number>28J</number> Dispute as to officer of registered Trade Union .—
<section><number>1</number> If there 
is any dispute as to who is the lawful officer of a registered Trade Union, any 
person claiming to be such an officer or the Registrar may refer the dispute to 
the Industrial Court in such manner *[and on payment of such fee not exceeding 
ten rupees] as may be prescribed: 
 *[Provided that no fee shall be payable by the Registrar.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On a reference being made under sub-section (1), the Industrial Court 
shall, after hearing the parties to such dispute and recording such evidence as 
it may consider necessary, decide the dispute and declare who is the lawful 
officer. The decision of the Industrial Court shall be final and shall not be 
called in question in any court of law. 
 *[(2a) The costs of and incidental to the provisions of this section shall be 
in the discretion of the Industrial Court and the Industrial Court shall have 
full power to determine by whom the whole or any part of such costs shall be 
paid. 
 </section><section><number>2b</number> If any proceeding under this section the Industrial Court is, after 
hearing the person making the reference, satisfied that the ground on which the 
claim has been preferred is false or vexatious, the Court may after recording 
its reasons for holding such claim to be false or vexatious, make an order for 
the payment of costs by way of compensation which shall not be less than fifty 
rupees and not exceeding two hundred rupees to such person or persons, as it may 
specify in the order.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No Civil Court shall entertain any suit or other proceedings in respect 
of any dispute which has been referred to the Industrial Court under sub-section 
(1) and is pending before such Court and if any such suit or proceeding is 
pending in a Civil Court on the date of the reference the Civil Court shall, on 
receipt of a notice from the Industrial Court, cease to exercise jurisdiction in 
respect thereof and shall forthwith transfer the record of such suit or 
proceeding to the Industrial Court.” 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 ); 
*Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of 1963, sec. 2.] 
 </section></article><article><number>28K</number> Certain officers to be public servants .—The Registrar, 
Additional Registrar and Deputy Registrar of Trade Unions appointed under 
section 3 and members of the staff of the offices of the aforesaid officers 
shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 </article><article><number>28L</number> Protection of action under the Act .—No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in 
good faith done or purported to be done under this Act. 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 16 of 1968, sec. 4.] 
  



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Power to make regulations. </title>—
<section><number>1</number><footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[***] The 
<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[appropriate Government] may make regulations for the purpose of 
carrying into effect the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters 
namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the manner in which Trade Unions and the rules of Trade Unions shall be 
  registered and the fees payable on registration; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the transfer of registration in the case of any registered Trade Union 
  which has changed its head office from one State to another; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the manner in which, and the qualifications by whom, the accounts of 
  registered Trade Unions or of any class of such Unions shall be audited; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the conditions subject to which inspection of documents kept by 
  Registrars shall be allowed and the fees which shall be chargeable in respect 
  of such inspections; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> any matter which is to be or may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Every notification made by the Central Government under 
sub-section (1) of section 22, and every regulation made by it under sub-section 
(1), shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may 
be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the notification or regulation, or both Houses agree that the notification or 
regulation should not be made, the notification or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that notification or 
regulation. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every notification made by the State Government under sub-section (1) of 
section 22 and every regulation made by it under sub-section (1) shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.] 
 <title>State Amendments </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—In section 29, in sub-section (2), after 
clause (d), insert the following clauses, namely:— 
 <title>“ </title>(d1) the form in which the approved list shall be 
maintained under section 28A; 
 <subsection><number>d2</number> the form of application under section 28C; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d3</number> the officers and members of approved unions to be authorized under 
section 28H and the manner in which and the conditions subject to which the 
rights of such officers under that section shall be exercised; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d4</number> the manner of enquiry required to be undertaken by the Registrar under 
this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d5</number> the manner in which the dispute shall be referred to Industrial Court 
*[and the fee payable therefor] under section 28J.” 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 ; 
*Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of 1963, sec. 3).] 
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>Maharashtra</number> </title>—In section 29, in sub-section (2),— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> in clause (d), omit the word “and”; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> after clause (d), insert thereafter the following clause, namely:— 
</subsubsection>
 “(dd) The manner in which the dispute may be referred to the Industrial Court 
under section 28-1A.” 
 [ Vide Maharashtra Act 3 of 1968, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968 ).] 







</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Publication of regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The power to make regulations conferred by section 29 is subject to the 
    condition of the regulations being made after previous publication.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    date to be specified in accordance with clause (3) of section 23 of the 
    General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), as that after which a draft of 
    regulations proposed to be made will be taken into consideration shall not 
    be less than three months from the date on which the draft of the proposed 
    regulations was published for general information.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Regulations as made shall be published in the Official Gazette, and on such 
    publication shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Failure to submit returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If default is made on the part of any registered Trade Union in giving any 
    notice or sending any statement or other document as required by or under 
    any provision of this Act, every 

    1[office-bearer] or 
    other person bound by the rules of the Trade Union to give or send the same, 
    or, if there is no such 

    1[office-bearer] or 
    person, every member of the executive of the Trade Union, shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to five rupees and, in the case of a 
    continuing default, with an additional fine which may extend to five rupees 
    for each week after the first during which the default continues:  
 
Provided 
    that the aggregate fine shall not exceed fifty rupees.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    person who wilfully makes, or causes to be made, any false entry in, or any 
    omission from, the general statement required by section 28 or in or from 
    any copy of rules or of alterations of rules sent to the Registrar under 
    that section, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
    rupees.  
 
 

 



 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Supplying false information regarding Trade Unions. </title>—Any 
person who, with intent to deceive, gives to any member of a registered Trade 
Union or to any person intending or applying to become a member of such Trade 
Union any document purporting to be a copy of the rules of the Trade Union or of 
any alterations to the same which he knows, or has reason to believe, is not a 
correct copy of such rules or alterations as are for the time being in force, or 
any person who, with the like intent, gives a copy of any rules of an 
unregistered Trade Union to any person on the pretence that such rules are the 
rules of a registered Trade Union, shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to two hundred rupees. 
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 <title>Section 32A </title>
 <title>Madhya Pradesh. </title>—After section 32, insert the following 
section, namely:— 
 
 “32A. Penalty for contravention of section 28H .—Any employer who 
  contravenes the provisions of section 28H shall be punishable with fine which 
  may extend to five hundred rupees.” 
 [ Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 28 of 1960, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 31-12-1960 
  ).] </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first class shall try any offence under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    Court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act, unless complaint 
    thereof has been made by, or with the previous sanction of, the Registrar 
    or, in the case of an offence under section 32, by the person to whom the 
    copy was given, within six months of the date on which the offence is 
    alleged to have been committed.  
 
 
State Amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as in 
      Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 11 of 
      1960, sec. 87.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the Pre-Reorganisation State of Bombay, in section 33, in 
      sub-section (2), insert the following words, namely:—
 
       “and in the case 
      of an offence under sub-section (2) of section 31, within six months next 
      after the alleged offence came to the knowledge of the Registrar.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 32 of 
      1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 7-6-1956).]
 
 
</subsection>
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 
1-4-1965 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 3, for clause (f) (w.e.f. 
21-9-1960 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Section 3 
    re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
    21-9-1960). tc 
    " 1. Section 3 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by the A. 
    O. 1937, for “Each Local Government”. tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A. O. 1937, for “Each 
    Local Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “the Province”. tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “the 
    Province”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Section 4 
    re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    21-9-1960). tc 
    " 5. Section 4 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 31 
    of 2001, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002). tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 2 
    (w.e.f. 9-1-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by Act 42 
    of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960). tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 5 
    (w.e.f. 21-9-1960)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
9-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officers” (w.e.f. 
1-4-1965 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Clause (ee) subs. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002 
). Earlier clause (ee) was inserted by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 4 for “appointed” (w.e.f. 
9-1-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Ins. by Act 31 
    of 2001, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002). tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 5 
    (w.e.f. 9-1-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
9-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by Act 15 of 1928, sec. 2, for section 11.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> The words “or of Rangoon ” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Subs. by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 7, for clause (e) (w.e.f. 
21-9-1960). Earlier clauses (c) and (d) were repealed by Act 25 of 1942, sec. 2 
and Sch. 1.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officers” (w.e.f. 
1-4-1965 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General in Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   The words and figures 
    “the Government of India Act, or the Government of India Act, 1935, or” 
    omitted by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960). tc 
    " 2. The words and figures “the 
    Government of India Act, or the Government of India Act, 1935, or” omitted 
    by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
    1950. tc 
    " 3. Ins. by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Ins. by Act 51 of 
    1970, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-9-1971). tc 
    " 4. Ins. by Act 51 of 1970, sec. 2 and 
    Sch. (w.e.f. 1-9-1971)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 
1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by Act 38 
    of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, 
    for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by Act 38 
    of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, 
    for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Proviso omitted 
    by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-4-1965). tc 
    " 2. Proviso omitted by Act 38 of 1964, 
    sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-4-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> Ins. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1965 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Ins. by Act 51 of 1970, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-9-1971 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Subs. by Act 31 
    of 2001, sec. 8, for section 22 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 8, 
    for section 22 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 6, for “March” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 
1-4-1965 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> Ins. by Act 42 of 1960, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 21-9-1960 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> The words “Subject to the control of the Governor-General in 
Council” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 2001, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 9-1-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965). tc 
    " 
    1. Subs. by Act 38 of 1964, sec. 2, for “officer” (w.e.f. 1-4-1965)."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>