<act><tid>11366</tid>
<title>[ THE BOMBAY HIGH COURT (LETTERS PATENT) ACT, <year>1866</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1866</year>
[ 17th May, <year>1866</year>.]

An Act to correct two clerical errors in the 2Letters Patent 
for 
the High Court of Judicature for the Presidency of Bombay.

Preamble.- WHEREAS the twenty- second section of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2Letters</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Patent for the High Court of Judicature for the Presidency of 
Bombay, 
dated the 28th December, <year>1865</year>, is as follows:-,, And we do 
further 
ordain that the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay shall 
have 
ordinary original criminal jurisdiction within the local limits of 
its 
ordinary original civil jurisdiction, and also in respect of all 
such 
persons beyond such limits over whom the said High Court of 
Judicature 
at Fort William in Bengal shall have criminal jurisdiction at the 
date 
of the publication of these presents;"

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to correct the two clerical errors 
in 
such section which are hereinbefore indicated by italics;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>442142</tid>
<number>1</number>Clause substituted for section 22 of revised Letters Patent 
of Bombay High Court.- In lieu of the said recited section, the 
following shall be substituted:-
" and we do further ordain that the said High Court of 
Judicature at Bombay shall have ordinary original 
criminal jurisdiction within the local limits of its 
ordinary original civil jurisdiction, and also in 
respect of all persons beyond such limits over whom the 
said High Court of Judicature at Bombay shall have 
criminal jurisdiction at the date of the publication of 
these presents."

-----------------


<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Bombay Short Titles Act, <year>1921</year> (Bom. 2 of  
  <year>1921</year>). 
2. See Gen. R. and O., Vol. 1, p. 120.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>