<act><title>The National Tiger Conservation Authority 
(Qualifications and Experience of Experts or Professional Members) Rules, 
20061
</title> 

    
    
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Tiger Conservation Authority (Qualifications and Experience 
of Experts or Professional Members) Rules, 2006.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.
  


</section></article> 

    
    
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>
“Act” means the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972);   
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“expert or professional member” means a member of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority, appointed under clause (d) of sub-section (2) of section 38L of the 
Act;   
 </section><section>
      <number>c</number> “Tiger Conservation Authority” means the 
National Tiger Conservation Authority constituted under section 38L of the 
Act.
 </section></article> 

    
    
 <article><number>3</number> Qualifications and experience for expert or professional 
members.—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall be eligible to be appointed to the 
Tiger Conservation Authority as an expert or professional member, if the 
following qualifications are met—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> (i)
having completed a five years course leading to a masters degree in arts 
or science of a recognised University or equivalent; or   
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>
having graduate level degree in engineering or technology or 
architecture, from a recognised Institute or University; or   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>
having degree in law from a recognised University or equivalent; or   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>
a fellow of the Institute of Chartered Accountants or Cost and Works 
Accountants or Company Secretaries, or Actuaries; or   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>
having a University degree and successfully completed the training in an 
academy established or recognised by the Department of Personnel and Training; 
and   
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> having fifteen years of 
experience in conservation of wildlife and welfare of people living in tiger 
reserve; or having a doctoral degree in concerned discipline with at least ten 
years of relevant experience.   
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A person preferably below the age of seventy years shall be 
considered for appointment as an expert or professional 
member.
 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The determination of eligibility of expert or professional 
members, their category and evaluation of eligibility and experience for 
selection in the Tiger Conservation Authority shall be made in accordance with 
the Tables and Appendix annexed to these rules.  </section></article> 

    
    
 <article><number>4</number> Conditions for serving as an expert or professional 
(non-official members).—The following conditions for serving as an expert or 
professional member in the Tiger Conservation Authority shall apply in the case 
of non-official members:
 
 <section>
<number>i</number>
Non-official members serving in individual capacity, irrespective of 
their institutional or organisational affiliation, may only serve as 
professional or expert member in the Tiger Conservation Authority;   
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> All 
others shall serve as representatives of institutions or organisations described 
in conditions (iii) and (iv).   
 </section><section>
 <number>iii</number> A Voluntary Organization having professionals, 
who are primarily engaged in providing, typically on non-profit basis, various 
services, including research, to the community, other institutions, or 
Government agencies, on sustainable development matters.   
 </section><section>
 <number>iv</number> A Voluntary Organization which is primarily 
engaged in the implementation of various sustainable development programs in the 
field, may or may not requiring some professional inputs.  
 
 Explanation.—For the purpose of these rules, “non-official” is a 
person who is presently not a holder of a Government post at any level (Central, 
State or Local level), whether in civil or judicial service or elected to any 
office (excluding persons holding faculty positions in Universities or 
autonomous institutions).
 </section></article> 

    
    
 <article><number>5</number> Tenure of expert or professional 
member.—An expert or professional member shall hold office 
for a period of three years, and his term of office shall be coterminus with the 
term of the Tiger Conservation Authority, and he shall be eligible for 
re-appointment:
 
 Provided that no member shall hold office as such for 
more than two consecutive terms.
 </article> 

   

 <article>   <number>6</number> Declaration of financial or 
other interest.—Every person, on his 
appointment as the expert or professional member of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority shall give a declaration in Form-I annexed to these rules, that he 
does not have any financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
prejudicially his functions as a member of the Authority.
 </article> 

   

     
 <article><number>7</number> Debarring a member temporarily or his removal from 
Authority.—If a non-official member of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority obstructs the meeting, or attempts through public statements or such 
other actions to frustrate the meetings or in achieving the objectives of the 
Authority, he shall be temporarily debarred by the Chairperson of the Authority 
from attending the meetings of the Authority and in case of such recurring 
behaviour, he shall be liable to be removed as a member of the Authority:
 
 Provided that before such removal, as a member he 
shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>