<act><tid>1747846</tid>
<title>THE PART B STATES MARRIAGES VALIDATING ACT, <year>1952</year></title>

NO. 1 OF <year>1952</year>
[ 15th February, <year>1952</year>.]

An Act to validate certain marriages solemnized in certain Part B 
States between the 26th day of January, <year>1950</year> and the 31st day of 
March, <year>1951</year>, under the Indian Christian Marriage Act, <year>1872</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows.-





<article><tid>1524747</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Part B States Marriages 
Validating Act, <year>1952</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1344254</tid>
<number>2</number>Validation of certain irregular marriages.- All marriages between 
persons one or both of whom is or are a Christian or Christians, which 
were solenized in any Part B State other than the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir between the 26th day of January, <year>1950</year> nd the 31st day of 
March, <year>1951</year>, under the Indian Christian Marriage Act, <year>1872</year> (XV of  
  <year>1872</year>), shall be, and shall be deemed to have been with effect from the 
date of solenization of each of them respectively, as good and valid 
in law as if such marriages had been solemnized by a person duly 
authorised under the said Act to solemnize such marriages in the Part 
B State concerned.


</article>



<article><tid>1234245</tid>
<number>3</number>Validation of records of marriages validated by section 
2.- Certificates of marriages which are declared by section 2 to be 
good and valid in law, and register books, and certified copies of 
true and duly authenticated extracts therefrom, deposited or urporting 
to be deposited in compliance with the provisions of the Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, <year>1872</year> (XV of <year>1872</year>), in so far as the register, 
books and extracts relate to such marriages as aforesaid, shall be 
received as evidence of such marriages as i such marriages had been 
duly solemnized under the said Act.

</article>



 </act>