<act><tid>1044174</tid>
<title>THE TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS (NATIONALISATION) ACT, <year>1995</year></title>

ACT NO. 39 OF <year>1995</year>
[ 8th September, <year>1995</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the textile 
undertakings, and the right, title and interest of the owners in 
respect of the textile undertakings, specified in the First Schedule 
with a view to augmenting the production and distribution of different 
varieties of cloth and yarn so as to subserve the interests of the 
general Public and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto,

WHEREAS the textile companies specified in column (3) of the 
First Schedule have, through their undertakings specified in column 
 (2) of the said Schedule, been engaged in the manufacture and 
production of different varieties of cloth and yarn;

AND WHEREAS, pending acquisition, the management of the said 
textile undertakings was taken over by the Central Government under 
section 3 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 
<year>1983</year>, (40 of <year>1983</year>.) or under section 3 of the Laxmirattan and 
Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1976</year>, (98  
  of <year>1976</year>.) as the case may be;

AND WHEREAS large sums of money have been invested with a view to 
making the said textile undertakings viable;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

AND WHEREAS further investment of very large Sums of money is 
necessary for the purpose of securing the optimum utilisation of the 
available facilities for the manufacture, production. and distribution 
of cloth and yarn by the said textile undertakings of the companies;

AND WHEREAS such investment is also necessary for securing the 
continued employment of the workmen employed in the said textile 
undertakings;

AND WHEREAS it is necessary in the public interest to acquire the 
said textile undertakings of the textile companies to ensure that the 
interest of the general public are served by the continuance by the 
said undertakings of the companies of the manufacture, Production and 
distribution of different varieties of cloth and yarn which are vital 
to the needs of the country;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>995231</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1489969</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Act, <year>1995</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1945524</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 31 and 32 shall come into force a 
once and the remaining provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have 
come into force on the 1st day of April, <year>1994</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1552654</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>478721</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Ordinance, unless the context  
otherwise requires,-

<subsection><tid>462786</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of April, <year>1994</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1504083</tid>
<number>b</number>" bank" means-

<subsubsection><tid>1287331</tid>
<number>i</number>the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank 
of India Act, <year>1955</year>; (23 of <year>1955</year>.)

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1522199</tid>
<number>ii</number>a subsidiary Bank as defined in the State Bank of India 
 (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year>; (38 of <year>1959</year>.)

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>600783</tid>
<number>iii</number>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of 
the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Under-  
  takings) Act. <year>1970</year>; (5 of <year>1970</year>.)

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1656357</tid>
<number>iv</number>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of 
the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Under-  
  takings) Act, <year>1980</year>; (40 of <year>1980</year>.)

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1933639</tid>
<number>v</number>any other bank, being a scheduled bank as defined in 
clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 
<year>1934</year>; (2 of <year>1934</year>.)

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>410905</tid>
<number>c</number>" Commissioner" means a Commissioner of Payments 
appointed under section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>820092</tid>
<number>d</number>" Custodian" means a Custodian appointed under section 4 
of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 
 <year>1983</year> (40 of <year>1983</year>.) or under section 4 of the Laxmirattan 
and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management) 
Act, <year>1976</year>, (98 of <year>1976</year>.) as the case may be;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1624467</tid>
<number>e</number>" National Textile Corporation" means the National Textile 
Corporation Limited formed and registered under the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>; (1 of <year>1956</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>431002</tid>
<number>f</number>" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>11494</tid>
<number>g</number>" owner", when used in relation to a textile undertaking, 
means any person or firm who or which is, immediately before the 
appointed day, the immediate proprietor or lessee or occupier of the 
textile undertaking or any part thereof, and in the case of a textile 
company which is being wound Lip or the business whereof is being 
carried' on by a liquidator or receiver, includes such liquidator or 
receiver, and also includes any agent or manager of such owner but 
does not include any person or body of persons authorised under the 
Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1983</year> (40 of  
  <year>1983</year>.) or under the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking  
  Over of Management) Act, <year>1976</year> (98 of <year>1976</year>.) to take over the 
management of the whole or any part of the textile undertaking;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1668337</tid>
<number>h</number>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>715673</tid>
<number>i</number>" specified date" means such date as the Central Government 
may, for the purpose of any provision of this Act, by notification, 
specify; and different dates may be specified for different provision 
of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1308472</tid>
<number>j</number>" subsidiary textile corporation" means the National Textile 
Corporation (South Maharashtra) Limited, the, National Textile Cor- 
poration (Uttar Pradesh) Limited or, any other textile corporation 
formed by the National Textile Corporation as its subsidiary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918156</tid>
<number>k</number>" textile" includes yarn or fabrics made either wholly or 
partly of cotton, wool, jute, synthetic and artificial (man- made) 
fibres;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>267878</tid>
<number>l</number>" textile company" means a company (being a company a company  
  a defined in the Companies Act. <year>1956</year>)  (1 of <year>1956</year>.) specified in 
column (3) of the First Schedule as owning the textile undertaking 
specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) of that Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520407</tid>
<number>m</number>" textile undertaking" or" the textile undertaking" means an 
undertaking specified in column (2) of the First Schedule, the 
management of which was before the appointed day, taken over by the 
Central. Government under the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of  
  Management) Act, <year>1983</year>, (40 of <year>1983</year>.) or is file case may be under the 
Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management) 
Act, <year>1976</year>; (98 of <year>1976</year>.)

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>734518</tid>
<number>2</number>Words and expressions used herein and rot defined but 
defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) shall have the- 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1409694</tid>
<number> 3</number> Acquisition of rights of owners and vesting of the textile 
undertakings.
<section><tid>1605110</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the right, title and interest  
of the owner in relation to every textile undertaking shall stand 
transferred to and shall and shall vest absolutely in, the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>685419</tid>
<number>2</number>Every textile undertaking which stands vested in the Central 
Government by virtue of sub- section (1) shall immediately after it has 
so vested, stand transferred to, and vested in, the National Textile 
Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1545504</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting.
<section><tid>963277</tid>
<number>1</number>The textile undertakings  
referred to in section 3 shall be deemed to include all assets, 
rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities and privileges and all 
property, movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, 
workshops, stores, instruments machinery and equipment, cash balances, 
cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and book debts pertaining to 
the textile undertakings and all other rights and interests, in, or 
arising out of, such property as were immediately before the appointed 
day in the ownership, possession, power or control of the textile 
company in relation to the said undertakings, whether within or 
outside India, and all books of account, registers and all other 
documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall also be deemed 
to include the liabilities and obligations specified in sub- section 
 (2) of section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>979331</tid>
<number>2</number>All property as aforesaid which have vested in the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 3 shall, by force of such 
vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation mortgage, 
charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting it and any 
attachment, injunction or decree or order of any court or other 
authority restricting, the use of such property in any manner shall 
be deemed to have been withdrawn.

</section>

<section><tid>437255</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any licence or other instrument in relation to a 
textile undertaking had been granted at any time before the appointed 
day to the owner by the Central Government or a State Government or 
any other authority, the National Textile Corporation shall, on and 
from such date, be deemed to be substituted in such licence or other 
instrument in place of the owner referred to therein as if such 
licence or such other instrument had been granted to it and shall hold 
such licence or the textile undertaking specified in such other 
instrument for the remainder of the period for which the owner would 
have held such licence or the textile undertaking under such other 
instrument.

</section>

<section><tid>799084</tid>
<number>4</number>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this 
act in the Central Government and every person holding any charge, 
lien or other interest in, or in relation to, any such property shall 
give, within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed. an 
intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, charge, lien or other 
interest.

</section>

<section><tid>376867</tid>
<number>5</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (2) or any other 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation 
to any such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with 
his rights and interest payment of the mortgage money or other dues, 
in whole

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or in part, out of the amounts specified in relation to such property 
in the First Schedule, but no such mortgage, charge, lien or other 
interest shall be enforceable against any property which has vested in 
the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>881514</tid>
<number>6</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other 
proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any property which has 
vested in the Central Government under section 3, instituted or 
preferred by or against the textile company is pending, the same shall 
not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially affected 
by reason of the transfer of the textile undertakings or of anything 
contained in this act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted or enforced by or against the National Textile 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1625296</tid>
<number>7</number>Any person who, on the date on which the Textile 
Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.) was 
promulgated, was in possession of, or had under his custody or 
control, the whole or any part of any textile undertaking referred to 
in section 3, the management of which could not be taken over by the 
Central Government by reason of any decree, order or injunction of any 
court or otherwise, shall deliver forwith the possession of such 
undertaking or part and all books of account, registers and all other 
documents of whatever nature relating to such undertaking or part to 
the Central Government or the National Textile Corporation, as the 
case may be, may specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>158484</tid>
<number> 5</number> Owner to be liable for contain prior liabilities.
<section><tid>803256</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
liability, other than the liability specified in sub- section (2), of 
the owner of a textile undertaking, in relation to the textile 
undertakings in respect of any period prior to the appointed day, 
shall be the liability of such owner and shall be enforceable against 
him and not against the Central Government or the National Textile 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>522947</tid>
<number>2</number>Any liability arising in respect of-

<subsection><tid>449455</tid>
<number>a</number>loans advanced by the Central Government, or a State 
Government, or both, to a' textile undertaking (together with  
  interest due thereon) after the management of such 
undertaking had been taken over by the Central Government 
under section 3 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of  
  Management) Act, <year>1983</year>, (49 of <year>1989</year>.) or as the case may be, 
under section 3 of the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton 
Mills (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1976</year>; (98 of <year>1976</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>895857</tid>
<number>b</number>amounts advanced to a textile undertaking[ after the 
management of such undertaking had been taken over by the 
Central Government under section 3 of the Textile 
Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1983</year>, (40 of  
  <year>1983</year>.) or as the case may be, under section 3 of the 
Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of  
  management) Act, <year>1976</year>], (98 of <year>1976</year>.) by the National 
Textile Corporation or by a state textile corporation, or by 
both, together with interest due thereon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1424063</tid>
<number>c</number>wages, salaries and other dues of employees of the 
textile undertaking, in repsect of any period after the 
management of such undertaking had been taken over by the 
Central Government,
shall, on and from the appointed day, be the liability of the Central 
Government and shall be discharged for and on behalf of that 
Government, by the National Textile Corporation as and when repayment 
of such


<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

loans or amounts becomes due or as and when such wages, salaries or 
other dues become due and payable.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>710848</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that,-

<subsection><tid>899534</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise expressly provided in this section or 
in any other section of this, act, no liability, other then 
the liability specified in sub- section (2), in relation to a 
textile undertaking, in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day, shall be enforceable against the Central 
Government or the National Textile Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1670557</tid>
<number>b</number>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other 
authority in relation to any textile undertaking, passed 
after the appointed day, in respect of any matter, claim or 
dispute in relation to any matter not referred to in sub- 
section (2), which arose before that day shall be enforceable 
against the Central Government or the National Textile 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1806973</tid>
<number>c</number>no liability of any textile undertaking or any owner 
thereof in relation to any textile undertaking before the 
appointed day, for the contravention of any provision of law 
for the time being in force, shall be enforceable against the 
Central Government or the National Textile Corporation;



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>371937</tid>
<number> 6</number> Transfer of any textile undertaking or part thereof to a 
subsidiary textile Corporation.
<section><tid>75915</tid>
<number>1</number>The National Textile Corporation  
may, by order in writing, transfer any textile undertaking specified 
at serial numbers 1 to 13 in the First Schedule or part of any such 
textile undertaking to the National Textile Corporation (South  
  Maharashtra) Limited and any textile undertaking specified at serial 
numbers 14 and 15 in the First Schedule or part of any such textile 
undertaking to the National Textile Corporation (Uttar Pradesh) 
Limited, as the case may be, or to any other subsidiary textile 
corporation and any such transfer shall be subject to such terms and 
conditions as may be, specified in the said order.

</section>

<section><tid>1293388</tid>
<number>2</number>The subsidiary textile corporation shall, on and from the 
date of such transfer, be deemed to be substituted in the licence or 
other instrument referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 in place 
of the National Textile Corporation as if such licence or other 
instrument had been granted to the subsidiary textile corporation, and 
shall hold such licence or other instrument for the remainder of the 
period for which the National Textile Corporation would have held such 
licence or other instrument.

</section>

<section><tid>663925</tid>
<number>3</number>On the transfer to a subsidiary textile, corporation of any 
textile undertaking or any part thereof, the liabilities of the 
National Textile Corporation, referred to in sub- section (2) of 
section 5, shall, in so far as they relate to the textile undertaking 
or part thereof so transferred to the subsidiary textile corporation, 
become on and from the date of such transfer, the liabilities of the 
subsidiary textile corporation and shall be discharged by the 
subsidiary textile corporation as and when any such liability is 
required to be discharged.

</section>

<section><tid>1841616</tid>
<number>4</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this act, references 
in this act to the National Textile Corporation shall, in respect of 
any textile undertaking or any part thereof which is transferred to a 
subsidiary textile corporation, be construed as references to the 
subsidiary textile corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1378792</tid>
<number> 7</number> Shares to be issued by the National Textile Corporation for 
the value of the assets transferred to it by the Central Government.

<section><tid>1515231</tid>
<number>1</number>An amount equal to the value of the assets of a textile  
undertaking transferred to, and vested in, the National Textile Cor- 
poration under sub- section (2) of section 3, shall be deemed to be 
contribution made by the Central Government to the equity capital of 
the National Textile Corporation; and for the contribution so made, 
the National Textile Corporation shall issue (if necessary, after  
  amending its memorandum and articles of association) to the Central 
Government paid- up shares, in its equity capital, having a face value 
equal to the amount specified against the textile undertaking in the 
corresponding entry in Column (4) of the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>802386</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any liability assumed by the Central Government under 
this Act, is taken over by the National Textile Corporation under 
section 27, the Central Government shall surrender to that Corporation 
the shares issued to it under sub- section (1) having the face value 
equal to the amount to the extent to which the liability has been so 
taken over by the National Textile Corporation and thereupon the share 
capital of the National Textile Corporation shall, to the extent of 
the face value of the shares so surrendered, stand reduced.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1987751</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment of amount to owners of textile undertakings. The owner 
of every textile undertaking shall be given by the Central Government, 
in Cash and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, for the transfer 
to, and vesting in, it, under sub- section
<section><tid>1981054</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3, of such  
textile undertaking and the right, title and interest of the owner in 
relation Lo such textile undertaking, an amount equal to the amount 
specified against it in the corresponding entry in column (4) of the 
First Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378395</tid>
<number> 9</number> Payment of further amount.
<section><tid>1581500</tid>
<number>1</number>In consideration of the  
retrospective operation of the provisions of sections 3, 4' and 5, 
there shall be given, in cash, by the Central Government, to the owner 
of every textile undertaking, the management of which was taken over 
by the Central Government an amount equal to an amount calculated at 
the rate specified in section 5 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking  
  Over of Management) Act, <year>1983</year>, or as the case may be, as specified in 
section 5 of the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking  
  Over of Management) Act, <year>1976</year> for the period commencing on the 
appointed day and ending on the date on which the' Textile 
Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> was promulgated. (40 of  
  <year>1983</year>., 98 of <year>1976</year>., Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>126028</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the amount referred to in section 8 there 
shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner of 
every textile undertaking, simple interest at the rate of four per 
cent per annum on the amount specified against such owner in the 
corresponding entry in column (4) of he First Schedule for the period 
commencing on the appointed day and ending on the date on which 
payment of such amount is made by the Central Government to the 
Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>384817</tid>
<number>3</number>The amount representing interest calculated at the rate 
specified in subsection (2) shall be given in addition Io the amount 
specified in the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1874144</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
liabilities of the owners in relation to the textile undertakings 
which

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

have vested in the Central Government under section 3 shall be dis- 
charged from the amount referred to in the First Schedule and also 
from the amounts determined under sub- sections (1) and (2) in 
accordance with the rights and interests of the creditors of the 
owner.

CHAP

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>252141</tid>
<number>10</number>Management, etc. of Textile undertakings. The National 
Textile Corporation or any person which that Corporation may, by order 
in writing, specify, shall be entitled to ex- excise the powers of 
general superintendence,. direction, control and management of the 
affairs and business of a textile undertaking, the right, title and 
interest of in owner in relation to which have vested in. that 
Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and do all such things 
as the owner of the textile undertaking is authorised to exercise and 
do.


</article>



<article><tid>1367098</tid>
<number>11</number>Special provision for disposal of assets of the textile 
undertakings in certain circumstances. If the National Textile 
Corporation considers It necessary or expedient for the better 
management, modernization, restructuring or revival of a textile 
undertaking so to do, it may, with the previous sanction of the 
Central Government, transfer, mortgage; sell or otherwise dispose of 
any land, plant, machinery or any other assets of any of the textile 
undertakings:
Provided that the proceed of no such transfer, mortgage, sale or 
disposal of assets shall be utilized for any purpose other than the 
purpose for which the sanction of the Central Government has been ob- 
tained.



</article>



<article><tid>1780336</tid>
<number>12</number>Duty of persons in charge of management of textile 
undertakings to deliver all assets etc. On the vesting of the 
management of a textile undertaking in the National Textile 
Corporation, all persons In charge of the management of such textile 
undertaking immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver 
to the National Textile Corporation all assets, documents In their 
custody relating to the textile undertaking.


</article>



<article><tid>1602002</tid>
<number>13</number>Accounts. The National Textile Corporation shall maintain 
the accounts of the textile undertakings in accordance with the 
provisions of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>. (1 of <year>1956</year>.)
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS

CHAPTER V

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS



</article>



<article><tid>893247</tid>
<number> 14</number> Employment of certain employees to continue.
<section><tid>545442</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
person who is a workman within the meaning of the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year>, (14 of <year>1947</year>.) and has been, immediately before the 
appointed day, in the employment of a textile undertaking shall 
become, on and from the appointed day, an employee of the National 
Textile Corporation, and shall hold office or service' in the National 
Textile Corporation with the same rights and privileges as to pension, 
gratuity and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

other matters as would have been admissible to him if the rights in 
relation to such textile undertaking had not been transferred to, and 
vested in, the National Textile Corporation, and shall continue to do 
so unless and until his employment in the National Textile Corporation 
is duly terminated or until his remuneration, terms and conditions of 
employment are duly altered by the National Textile Corporation.


</section>

<section><tid>1532181</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person who is not a workman within the meaning of the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year>, (14 of <year>1947</year>.) and who has been, 
immediately before the appointed day, in the employment of a textile 
undertaking shall, in so far as such person is employed in connection 
with the textile undertaking which has vested in the National Textile 
Corporation, become, as from appointed day, an employee of the 
National Textile Corporation and shall hold his office or service 
therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same 
terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to 
pension and gratuity and other matters as lie would have held the same 
under the textile undertaking if it had not vested in the National 
Textile Corporation and shall continue to do so unless and until his 
employment in the National Textile Corporation is duly terminated or 
until his remuneration, terms and conditions of employment are duly 
altered by the National Textile Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1996350</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year>, (14 of <year>1947</year>.) or in any other law for the time 
being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other 
employee of a textile undertaking to the National Textile Corporation 
shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation 
under this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no 
such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority.

</section>

<section><tid>910965</tid>
<number>4</number>Where, under the terms of any contract of service or 
otherwise, any person whose services become terminated or whose 
services become transferred to the National Textile Corporation by 
reason of the provisions of this Act is entitled to any arrears of 
salary or wages or any payment for any leave not availed of or other 
payment, not being payment by way of gratuity or pension, such person 
may, except to the extent such liability has been taken over by the 
Central Government under section 5, enforce his claim against the 
owner of the textile undertaking but not against the Central 
Government or the National Textile Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1374223</tid>
<number> 15</number> Provident and other funds.
<section><tid>1978271</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the owner of a textile  
undertaking has established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare 
or other fund' for the benefit of the persons employed in such textile 
undertaking the monies relatable to the employees, whose services have 
become transferred by or under this Act to the National Textile 
Corporation shall, out of the monies standing, on the appointed day, 
to the credit of such provident fund, superannuation, welfare or other 
fund, stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the National Textile 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1247726</tid>
<number>2</number>The monies which stand transferred, under sub- section (1), 
to the National Textile Corporation shall be dealt with by that 
Corporation in such manner as maybe prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1922812</tid>
<number> 16</number> Transfer of employees to a subsidiary textile corporation. 
Where any textile undertaking or any part thereof is transferred under 
this Act to a subsidiary textile corporation, every person referred to 
in sub- section
<section><tid>495848</tid>
<number>1</number>and sub- section (2) of section 14 shall, on and  
from the date of such transfer, become an employee of the subsidiary 
textile corporation, and the provisions of sections 14 and 15 shall 
apply to such employee as they apply to an employee of the National 
Textile Corporation as if references in the said sections to the 
National Textile Corporation were references to the subsidiary textile 
corporation.
CHAP

COMMISSIONERS OF PAYMENTS

CHAPTER VI

COMMISSIONERS OF PAYMENTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>237189</tid>
<number> 17</number> Appointment of Commissioners of Payments.
<section><tid>902299</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purpose of disbursing the amount payable to the owner of each textile 
undertaking, the Central Government shall, by notification in the 
official Gazette,-

<subsection><tid>15164</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint such number of persons as it may think fit to 
be Commissioners, of Payments; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>764226</tid>
<number>b</number>define the local limits within which the Commissioners of 
Payments shall exercise the powers conferred, and perform the 
duties imposed, on them by or under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>240441</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as if 
may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act, 
and, different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>518597</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any 
powers may exercise those powers in the same manner and with the same 
effect as if they have been conferred on that person directly by this 
Act and not by way of authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>339386</tid>
<number>4</number>The salaries and allowances of' the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1073204</tid>
<number>5</number>References in this Act to the Commissioner shall, where 
more than one Commissioner has been appointed,' be construed as 
references, to the Commissioner in relation to the textile undertaking 
within the local limits of the jurisdiction specified under clause (b) 
of sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>543651</tid>
<number> 18</number> Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>1196209</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, within fifty days from the specified 
date, pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to the owner of a 
textile undertaking, an amount equal to the amount specified against 
the textile undertaking in the First Schedule and shall also. pay to 
the Commissioner such sums as may be due to the owner of a textile 
undertaking under sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 9.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1430132</tid>
<number>2</number>In relation to the textile undertakings, the management of 
which was taken over by the Central Government under the Textile 
Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1983</year>, (40 of <year>1983</year>.) 
there shall be paid by the Central Government[ in addition to the 
amount referred to in sub- section (1)], to the Commissioner, in cash, 
such amount payable under section 5 of that Act as remains unpaid in 
relation Lo the period commencing on the date on which such management 
was taken over by the Central Government and ending on the appointed 
day.

</section>

<section><tid>543942</tid>
<number>3</number>In relation to the textile undertakings, the management of 
which was taken over by the Central Government under the Laxmirattan 
and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over or Management) Act, <year>1976</year>, 
 (98 of <year>1976</year>.) there shall be paid' by the Central Government[ in 
addition to the amount referred to in sub- section (1)], to the 
Commissioner, in cash, such amount payable under section 5, of that 
Act as remains unpaid in relation to the period commencing on the date 
on which such management was taken over by the Central Government and 
ending on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>603670</tid>
<number>4</number>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government, 
in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and 
every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be 
deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account in the 
Public Account of India, and thereafter the said deposit account shall 
be operated by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>288488</tid>
<number>5</number>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in 
respect of each textile undertaking in relation to which payments have 
been made to him under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1321002</tid>
<number>6</number>Interest accruing on the amounts standing to the credit of 
the deposit account referred to in sub- section (4) shall inure to the 
benefit of the owners of the textile undertakings.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779847</tid>
<number> 19</number> Certain powers of the National Textile Corporation.
<section><tid>859344</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
National Textile Corporation shall be entitled to receive, up to the 
specified date, to the exclusion of all other persons, any money due 
to the textile undertaking, realised after the appointed day, 
notwithstanding that the realisations pertain to a period prior to the 
appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>555866</tid>
<number>2</number>The National Textile Corporation may make a claim to the 
Commissioner with regard: to every payment made by the Custodian after 
the appointed day but before the date on which the Textile 
Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.) was 
promulgated for discharging any liability of the owner of textile 
undertaking in relation to any period prior to the appointed day, and 
every such claim shall have priority, in accordance with the 
Priorities attaching, under this Act, to the matter in relation to 
which such liability has been discharged by the Custodian.

</section>

<section><tid>1081927</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities in 
relation to a textile undertaking in respect of any period prior to 
the appointed day which have not been discharged by the Custodian 
shall be the liabilities of the owner of that textile undertaking.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1659818</tid>
<number>20</number>Claim to be made to the Commissioner. Every person having a 
claim against the owner of a textile undertaking shall prefer such 
claim before the Commissioner within thirty days from the specified 
date:
Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant 
was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the 
said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a 
further period of thirty days but not thereafter.



</article>



<article><tid>1441762</tid>
<number> 21</number> Priority of claims. The claims arising out of the matters 
specified in the Second Schedule shall have priorities in accordance 
with the following principles, namely:-
<section><tid>1752591</tid>
<number>a</number>category I shall have precedence over all other 
categories and category II shall have precedence over 
category III and so on;

</section>

<section><tid>1639930</tid>
<number>b</number>the claims specified in each of the categories, except 
category IV, shall rank equally and be paid in full, but if 
the amount is insufficient to meet such claims in full, they 
shall abate in equal proportions and be paid accordingly;.

</section>

<section><tid>1850830</tid>
<number>c</number>the liabilities specified in category IV shall be 
discharged, subject to the priorities specified in this 
section, in accordance with the terms of the secured loans 
and the priority, inter se, of such loans; and

</section>

<section><tid>97850</tid>
<number>d</number>the question of payment of a liability with regard to a 
matter specified in a lower category shall arise only if a 
surplus is left after meeting all the liabilities specified 
in the immediately higher category.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>705354</tid>
<number> 22</number> Examination of claims.
<section><tid>1806735</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of the claims under  
section 20, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the order of 
priority specified in the Second Schedule and examine the same in 
accordance with the said order.

</section>

<section><tid>1135634</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on examination of the claims, the Commissioner is of the 
opinion that the amount paid to him under this Act is not sufficient 
to meet the liabilities specified in any lower category, the shall not 
be required to examine the liabilities in respect of such lower 
category.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220833</tid>
<number> 23</number> Admission or rejection of claims.
<section><tid>672744</tid>
<number>1</number>After examining the  
claims with reference to the priority set out in the Second Schedule, 
the Commissioner shall fix a certain date on or before which every 
claimant shall file the proof of his claim or be excluded from the 
benefit of the disbursement made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>251675</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in 
the English language and one issue of the daily newspaper in the 
regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and 
every' such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of 
his claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the 
advertisement.

</section>

<section><tid>611697</tid>
<number>3</number>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the time specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from 
the disbursements made by the Commissioner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>457536</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary and after giving the owner of the textile 
undertaking an opportunity of, refuting the claim and after giving the 
claimants a reasonable opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit 
or reject the claim in whole or in part.

</section>

<section><tid>627986</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions 
including the place or places at which be may hold his sittings and 
shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act, 
have the same powers as are vested in a civil court tinder the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) while trying a suit, in respect 
of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>347479</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1122102</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other 
material object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254506</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1133105</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witnesses

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1523297</tid>
<number>6</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>.) and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter 
XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>. (2 of <year>1974</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1893303</tid>
<number>7</number>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the 
Commissioner may prefer an appeal against the decision to the 
principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits 
of whose jurisdiction the textile undertaking is situated:
Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is 
appointed to be the Commissioner, such appeal shall lie to the High 
Court for the State in which the textile undertaking is situated, and 
such appeal shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges 
of that High Court.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>689195</tid>
<number>24</number>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner to claimants. 
After admitting a claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of 
such claim shall be credited by the Commissioner to the relevant fund 
or be paid to the person or persons to whom such sums are due and on 
such credit or payment the liability of the owner in respect of such 
claim shall stand discharged.


</article>



<article><tid>1666312</tid>
<number> 25</number> Disbursement of amount to the owners.
<section><tid>1353306</tid>
<number>1</number>If, out of the  
monies paid to him in relation to a textile undertaking there is a 
balance left after meeting the liabilities as specified in the Second 
Schedule, the Commissioner shall disburse such balance to the owner of 
such textile undertaking.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1984314</tid>
<number>2</number>Before making any payment to the owner of any textile under- 
taking under sub- section (1), the Commissioner shall satisfy himself 
as to the right of such person to receive the whole or any part of 
such amount, and in the event of there being a doubt or dispute as to 
the right of the person to receive the whole or any part of the 
amount, referred to in sections 8 and 9, the Commissioner shall refer 
the matter to the court and make the disbursement accordance with 
the decision of that court.

</section>

<section><tid>1695063</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
entries in column (3) of the First Schedule shall not be deemed to be 
conclusive as to the right, title and interest of any person in 
relation to any textile undertaking specified in the corresponding 
entries in column (2) of the said Schedule and evidence shall be 
admissible to establish the right, title and interest of any person in 
relation to such textile undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>838742</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any machinery, equipment or other property in a 
textile undertaking has vested in the National Textile Corporation, 
but such machinery, equipment or other property does not belong to the 
owner of such textile undertaking, the amount specified in column (4) 
of the First Schedule against such textile undertaking shall, on a 
reference made to it by the Commissioner, be apportioned by the court 
between the owner of such textile undertaking and the owner of such 
machinery, equipment or other property having due regard to the value 
of such machinery, equipment or other property on the appointed day.
Explanation.- In this section," court", in relation to a a textile 
undertaking, means the principal civil court of original jurisdiction 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the textile undertaking 
is situated.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1615088</tid>
<number>26</number>Undisbursed or unclaimed amounts to be deposited to the 
general reserve account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which 
remains undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of three years from the 
last day on which the disbursement was made, shall be transferred by 
the Commissioner to the general revenue account of the Central 
Government but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to 
the Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and 
shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, the order 
if any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the 
refund of revenue.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1605513</tid>
<number> 27</number> Assumption of liability.
<section><tid>1886694</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any liability of the owner  
of a textile undertaking arising out of any item specified in 
category I of the Second Schedule is not discharged fully by the 
Commissioner out of the amount paid to him under this Act, the 
Commissioner shall intimate in writing to the Central Government the 
extent of the liability which remains undischarged, and that liability 
shall be assumed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>853952</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by order, direct the National 
Textile Corporation to take over any liability assumed by that Govern- 
ment under sub- section (1), and on receipt of such direction, it shall 
be the duty of the National Textile Corporation to discharge such 
liability.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1552315</tid>
<number> 28</number> Management to continue to vest in the Custodian until 
alternative arrangements are made. Notwithstanding the vesting, under 
this Act, of a textile undertaking in the National Textile 
Corporation,-
<section><tid>151426</tid>
<number>a</number>the Custodian who has been managing the affairs of such 
undertaking before the date on which the Textile Undertakings 
 (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.) was 
promulgated shall, until alternative arrangements have been 
made by the National Textile Corporation, continue to manage 
the affairs of such undertakings as if the Custodian had been 
authorised by the National Textile Corporation to manage the 
affairs of such undertaking; and

</section>

<section><tid>1022995</tid>
<number>b</number>the Custodian or any person authorised by him for this 
purpose shall until alternative arrangements have been made 
by the National Textile Corporation, continue to be 
authorised to operate, in relation to the textile 
undertaking, any account of such undertaking in a bank as if 
such Custodian or the person authorised by the Custodian had 
been authorised by the National Textile Corporation to 
operate such account.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1033724</tid>
<number>29</number>Act to override all other enactments. The provisions of this 
Act, shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or 
in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1446465</tid>
<number> 30</number> Contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the 
National Textile Corporation.
<section><tid>1382356</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract entered into by the  
owner or occupier of any textile undertaking for any service, sale or 
supply and in force immediately before the appointed day shall, on and 
from the expiry of one hundred and twenty days from the date on which 
the Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> (Ord. 6 of  
  <year>1995</year>.) was promulgated, cease to have effect unless such contract is 
before the expiry of that period, ratified, in writing, by the 
National Textile Corporation and in ratifying such contract the 
National Textile Corporation may make such alterations or 
modifications therein as it may think fit:
Provided that the National Textile Corporation shall not omit to 
ratify a contract, and shall not make may alteration or modification 
in a contract, unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly 
onerous or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the 
interests of the textile undertaking.


</section>

<section><tid>402752</tid>
<number>2</number>The National Textile Corporation shall not omit to ratify a 
contract or make any alteration or modification therein except after 
giving to the parties to the contract a reasonable opportunity of 
being hear and except after recording in writing its reasons for 
refusal to ratify the contract or for making any alteration or 
modification therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1442795</tid>
<number> 31</number> Penalties. Any person who,-
<section><tid>677673</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of a textile undertaking, wrongfully 
withholds such property from the Central Government or the 
National Textile Corporation, or any person authorised by 
that Government or Corporation, as the case may be, in this 
behalf, or

</section>

<section><tid>776488</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any property 
forming part of the textile undertaking or wilfully withholds 
or fails to furnish to the Central Government, the National 
Textile Corporation

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or any person specified by that Government, or Corporation, 
as the case may be, any document relating to such textile 
undertaking which may be in his possession, custody or 
control or fails to deliver to the National Textile 
Corporation or any person specified by that Corporation any 
assets, books of account, registers or other documents, in 
his custody relating to the textile undertaking, or


</section>

<section><tid>1644140</tid>
<number>c</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming 
part of any textile undertaking or prefers any claim under 
this Act which he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to 
be false or grossly inaccurate,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1000023</tid>
<number> 32</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>893982</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for, the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>803410</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and- it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>39961</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1465944</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>673690</tid>
<number>33</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer of that Government or the Custodian or the 
National Textile Corporation or any subsidiary textile corporation or 
any officer or other person authorised by either of such Corporations 
for anything which is in good, faith done or intended to be done under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>971374</tid>
<number>34</number>Textile companies not to be wound up by the Court. No 
proceeding for the winding up of a textile company, the right, title 
and interest in relation to the textile undertaking owned by which 
have vested in the National Textile Corporation under this Act or for 
the appointment of a receiver in respect of the business of the 
textile undertaking shall lie or be proceeded with in any court except 
with consent of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>629904</tid>
<number> 35</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>326</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act, other than the power under section 36, may also be 
exercised by any person or persons as may be specified in the 
notification.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1243352</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>433502</tid>
<number> 36</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>391354</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification. make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1936291</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>576328</tid>
<number>a</number>the time within which and the manner in which an 
intimation referred to in subsection (4) of section 4 shall 
be given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1805453</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which monies in any provident or other fund 
referred to in section 15 shall be dealt with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>463260</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>653069</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both, Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done tinder 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1592224</tid>
<number> 37</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>15035</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises  
in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove 
the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the date on which Textile Undertakings 
 (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.) was promulgated.


</section>

<section><tid>1730173</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid beore each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>732699</tid>
<number> 38</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>544115</tid>
<number>1</number>The Textile Undertakings  
 (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year>, (Ord. 6 of <year>1995</year>.) is hereby 
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>710859</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done' Or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions, of this Act,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>