<act><title>The 
      Repatriation of Prisoners act, 2003</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Repatriation of 
      Prisoners Act, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall come into force on such 
      date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, appoint.  
  
  





 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
      requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>  “contracting 
      State” means a Government of any country or place outside India in respect 
      of which arrangement has been made by the Central Government with the 
      Government of such country or place through a treaty or otherwise for 
      transfer of prisoners from India to such country or place and vice 
      versa and includes any other Government of such country or place 
      specified by the Central Government, by notification in the Official 
      Gazette, under sub‑section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>b</number>  “prescribed” 
      means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number>  “prisoner” means 
      a person undergoing a sentence of imprisonment under an order passed by a 
      criminal court including the courts established under the law for the time 
      being in force in contracting States;
 </section><section><number>d</number>  “warrant” means a 
      warrant issued under sub‑section (1) of section 7 or sub­-section (2) 
      of section 12, as the case may be;
 </section><section><number>e</number>  words and 
      expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Code of 
      Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) have the meanings respectively 
      assigned to them in that Code.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Application of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of this Act shall 
      apply to a country or place outside India as may be specified in the 
      notification.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the notification under sub‑section (1) 
      relates to a country or place outside India with which a treaty has been 
      entered into by India for the transfer of prisoners between that country 
      and India, then, such notification shall also set out the full text of the 
      said treaty and shall in no case remain in force longer than the period of 
      the said treaty.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Central Government is of the opinion 
      that, with respect to a country or place outside India, provisions of this 
      Act require to be modified to give effect to a treaty in relation to such 
      country, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the 
      application of this Act to such country shall be subject to such 
      conditions, exceptions and modifications specified in the 
      notification.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Application for transfer by a 
      prisoner.—Any prisoner who is a 
      citizen of a contracting State may make an application to the Central 
      Government for transfer of his custody from India to that contracting 
      State:
 Provided that if a prisoner is not able to make 
      an application himself because of his ill-health, mental condition, old 
      age or being a minor, then, the application may be made by any other 
      person entitled to act on his behalf.
  


 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Consideration of request by Central 
      Government.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of 
      the application under section 4, the Central Government shall direct the 
      officer in charge of the prison, where the prisoner is confined, to 
      furnish such information which in the opinion of that Government is 
      relevant for the purpose of transfer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of the information under 
      sub‑section (1), if the Central Government is satisfied that­—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  no inquiry, trial or any 
      other proceeding is pending against the prisoner;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  death penalty has 
      not been awarded to the prisoner;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  the prisoner has not been 
      convicted for an offence under the martial law; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  transfer of 
      custody of the prisoner to the contracting State shall not be prejudicial 
      to the sovereignty, security or any other interest of India,
 it shall pass an order for 
      forwarding the application of the prisoner to the contracting State.
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Comments of contracting 
      State.—
<section><number>1</number> The application of 
      the prisoner shall be forwarded by the Central Government through 
      prescribed means to the Government of the contracting State to deal with 
      such application along with the following information, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  a copy of the judgment and a 
      copy of the relevant provisions of the law under which the sentence has 
      been passed against the prisoner;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  the nature, duration and date 
      of commencement of the sentence of the prisoner;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  medical report or 
      any other report regarding the antecedents and character of the prisoner, 
      where it is relevant for the disposal of his application or for deciding 
      the nature of his confinement; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  any other information which 
      the Central Government may consider necessary.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where any application of a prisoner 
      forwarded by the Central Government has been accepted by the contracting 
      State, the Central Government may seek from such contracting State, all or 
      any of the following information or documents before taking decision to 
      transfer the prisoner to the contracting State, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  a statement or document 
      indicating that the prisoner is a citizen of the contracting State;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  a copy of the relevant law of 
      the contracting State constituting the act or omission as the offence, on 
      account of which the sentence has been passed in India, as if such act or 
      omission was an offence under the law of that State;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  a statement of the fact or 
      any law or regulation relating to the duration and enforcement of the 
      sentence of the prisoner in the contracting State upon his transfer;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  the willingness of the 
      contracting State to accept the transfer of the prisoner and an 
      undertaking to administer the remaining part of the sentence of the 
      prisoner;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>  an undertaking to comply with 
      the conditions, if any, specified by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> any other information 
      or document which the Central Government may consider necessary.
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Consideration of request by Central 
      Government.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Central 
      Government, on receipt of a communication from the concerned contracting 
      State,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  expressing its 
      willingness to accept the transfer of the prisoner; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  undertaking to 
      comply with the conditions specified in the warrant,
 is satisfied that the prisoner 
      should be transferred to the said State, the Central Government may, 
      notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
      force, issue a warrant in accordance with the provisions of section 8 in 
      such form as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where a warrant is issued under sub‑section 
      (1), the Central Government shall inform the contracting State accordingly 
      and request that State to specify the person to whom and the place within 
      India where custody of the prisoner shall be delivered.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Provision to issue warrant for 
      transfer.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
      Government shall authorise an officer not below the rank of a Joint 
      Secretary to a State Government, within the limits of whose jurisdiction 
      the place of imprisonment of the prisoner is situated, to issue a warrant 
      on behalf of the Central Government under sub‑section (1) of section 7 
      directing the officer in charge of the prison therein to deliver the 
      custody of the prisoner to the person authorised by the contracting State 
      to which the prisoner is to be transferred, presenting such person a copy 
      of the warrant together with all the records relating to the prisoner and 
      the personal effects taken from the prisoner at the time of his admission 
      in the prison.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon the presentation of a warrant referred 
      to in sub‑section (1), the officer in charge of the prison shall forthwith 
      comply with the warrant and obtain thereon the signature of the person to 
      whom delivery of the prisoner, records and the personal effects relating 
      to the prisoner to be removed from the prison is given.
 </section><section><number>3</number> After delivery of the prisoner to the person 
      authorised by the contracting State under sub‑section (2), the officer in 
      charge of the prison transferring the prisoner shall forward a copy of the 
      warrant to the court which committed the prisoner to the prison, along 
      with a statement that the prisoner has been delivered to the person 
      authorised by the contracting State under sub‑section (1).
 </section><section><number>4</number> The delivery of the prisoner in compliance 
      of the warrant issued under sub­-section (1) shall discharge the 
      officer in charge of the prison from the responsibility of keeping the 
      prisoner in his custody.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Operation of warrant and retaking 
      prisoner.—It shall be lawful 
      for the person authorised by the contracting State to whom the custody of 
      a prisoner is delivered under the provisions of sub‑section (2) of section 
      8 to receive and hold in custody such prisoner and to convey him out of 
      India and if the prisoner escapes from such custody within India, the 
      prisoner may be arrested without warrant by any person who shall without 
      undue delay deliver such prisoner to the officer in charge of the nearest 
      police station and the prisoner so arrested shall be liable for committing 
      an offence under section 224 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and 
      shall also be liable for such sentence of imprisonment in India which he 
      would have to undergo if the delivery of custody of such prisoner had not 
      been made under section 8.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Transfer of record.—Where a prisoner is or is to be transferred to 
      a contracting State under the provisions of this Act, the Central 
      Government may requisition the records of any proceeding, including 
      judicial proceedings relating to that prisoner from any court or office, 
      and may direct that such records shall be sent to the Government of the 
      contracting State.
  


 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Power of court and Central Government shall 
      not be affected.—The transfer 
      of a prisoner from India to a contracting State shall not affect the power 
      of the court which passed the judgment to review its judgment and power of 
      the Central Government or State Government to suspend, remit or commute 
      the sentence in accordance with any law for the time being in 
force.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Transfer into India.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may accept the 
      transfer of a prisoner, who is a citizen of India, from a contracting 
      State wherein he is undergoing any sentence of imprisonment subject to 
      such terms and conditions as may be agreed to between India and that 
      State.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Central Government accepts the 
      request for a transfer under sub‑section (1), then, notwithstanding 
      anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, it may 
      issue a warrant to detain the prisoner in prison in accordance with the 
      provisions of section 13 in such form as may be prescribed.
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Determination of prison and issue of warrant 
      for receiving transfer in India.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, in 
      consultation with a State Government, determine the prison situated within 
      the jurisdiction of such State Government where the prisoner with respect 
      to whom a warrant has been issued under sub‑section (2) of section 12, 
      shall be lodged and the officer who shall receive and hold him in 
      custody.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall authorise any 
      officer not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to that Government to 
      issue a warrant under sub‑section (2) of section 12 and to direct the 
      officer referred to in sub‑section (1) to receive and hold the prisoner, 
      with respect to whom the warrant is issued, in custody.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be lawful for the officer referred 
      to in sub‑section (1) to receive and hold in custody any prisoner 
      delivered to him under the direction made in the warrant issued under 
      sub‑section (2) of section 12 and to convey such prisoner to any prison 
      determined under sub‑section (1) for being dealt with in accordance with 
      the said warrant and if the prisoner escapes from such custody, the 
      prisoner may be arrested without warrant by any person who shall without 
      undue delay deliver such prisoner to the officer in charge of the nearest 
      police station and the prisoner so arrested shall be liable for committing 
      an offence under section 224 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and 
      shall also be liable to be dealt with in accordance with the said 
      warrant.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A warrant under sub‑section (2) of section 
      12 shall provide for­—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  the bringing of the prisoner 
      into India from a contracting State or a place outside India;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  the taking of such prisoner 
      in any part of India being a place at which effect may be given to the 
      provisions contained in the warrant;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  the nature and duration of 
      imprisonment of the prisoner in accordance with the terms and conditions 
      referred to in sub‑section (1) of section 12 and the imprisonment of such 
      prisoner in India in such manner as may be contained in the warrant; 
      and
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  any other matter which may be 
      prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in any 
      other law for the time being in force, the imprisonment of a prisoner in 
      compliance with a warrant issued under sub‑section (2) of section 12 shall 
      be deemed to be imprisonment under a sentence of a court competent to pass 
      such a sentence of imprisonment in India.
 </section><section><number>6</number> If the sentence of imprisonment passed 
      against the prisoner in the contracting State is incompatible with the 
      Indian law as to its nature, duration or both, the Central Government may, 
      by order, adapt the sentence of such punishment as to the nature, duration 
      or both, as the case may be, as is compatible to the sentence of 
      imprisonment provided for a similar offence had that offence been 
      committed in India:
 Provided that the sentence so adapted shall, as 
      far as possible, correspond with the sentence imposed by the judgment of 
      the contracting State to the prisoner and such adapted sentence shall not 
      aggravate the punishment, by its nature, duration or both relating to the 
      sentence imposed in the contracting State.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions 
      of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the 
      generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any 
      of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  the means through which an 
      application may be forwarded under sub­-section (1) of section 
      6;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  the form in which a warrant 
      may be issued under sub‑section (1) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  the form in which a warrant 
      may be issued under sub‑section (2) of section 12; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  any other matter which may be 
      prescribed under clause (d) of sub‑section (4) of section 13.
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Laying of rules, etc.—Every notification issued under sub‑sections 
      
<section><number>1</number> and (3) of section 3 and every rule made under section 14 shall be 
      laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
      while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
      comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
      before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
      successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in marking any 
      modification in the notification or rule or both Houses agree that the 
      notification or rule should not be made, the notification or rule shall 
      thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as 
      the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
      shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
      under that notification or rule.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Power to remove 
      difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
      difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
      Central  Government 
      may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not 
      ­ inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it 
      to be necessary for removing the difficulty:
 Provided that no such order shall be made after 
      the expiry of a period of two years from the date of commencement of this 
      Act,
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every order made under sub‑section (1) shall 
      be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
      Parliament.
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force 
      on 1-1-2004, vide S.O. 1464(E), dated 24-12-2003.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>