<act><tid>1625086</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT GRANTS ACT, <year>1895</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1895</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 10th October, <year>1895</year>.]

An Act to explain the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>, so far as 
relates to grants from the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government], and to remove certain 
doubts as to the powers of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] in relation to such 
grants.

WHEREAS doubts have arisen as to the extent and operation of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>), and as to the power of 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] to impose limitations and restrictions upon grants 
and other transfers of land made by it or under its authority, and it 
is expedient to remove such doubts; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>680204</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and extent.-
<section><tid>1425954</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] Grants Act, <year>1895</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>297005</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>907595</tid>
<number>2</number>Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>, not to apply to Government 
grants.- Nothing in the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>), 
contained shall apply or be deemed ever to have applied to any grant 
or other transfer of land or of any interest therein heretofore made 
or hereafter to be made <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> by or on behalf of the Government] to, or 
in favour of, any person whomsoever; but every such grant and transfer 
shall be construed and take effect as if the said Act had not been 
passed.


</article>



<article><tid>211108</tid>
<number>3</number>Government grants to take effect according to their tenor.- All 
provisions, restrictions, conditions and limitations over contained in 
any such grant or transfer as aforesaid shall be valid and take effect 
according to their tenor, any rule of law, statute or enactment of the 
Legislature to the contrary notwithstanding.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws 
Act, <year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>). 
The Act has been amended in- 
 (i) Uttar Pradesh by U. P. Act 9 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
 (ii) Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 16 of <year>1971</year>; 
 (iii) Mysore by Mysore Act 13 of <year>1973</year>. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Crown". 
3 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
4 The word" and" at the end of sub- section (2), and sub- section 
 (3), rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II. 
5 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" by or on behalf of Her Majesty the 
Queen Empress, Her heirs or successors, or by or on behalf of the 
Secretary of State for India in Council". 
Rep, in its application to Malabar District of Kerala by Kerala Act 30 
of <year>1960</year>.

The Act as been extended to, and brougght into force in Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 opf <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

The Act as been extended to-

(i) Goa, Daman Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch.;

(ii) Union territory of Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands 
 (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1970</year>), vide Reg. 2 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2 and Sch.









</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>