<act><tid>367007</tid>
<title>THE STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH ACT, <year>1970</year></title>

ACT NO. 53 OF <year>1970</year>
[ 25th December, <year>1970</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of the State of Himachal 
Pradesh and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1188963</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the State of Himachal 
Pradesh Act, <year>1970</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>40178</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>839735</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the administrator appointed by the 
President under article 239 of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>767251</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>78926</tid>
<number>c</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>227557</tid>
<number>d</number>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
appointed by the President under article 324;

</section>

<section><tid>1122627</tid>
<number>e</number>" existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh" means the 
Union territory of Himachal Pradesh as existing 
immediately before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>1230015</tid>
<number>f</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having, immediately before the appointed 
day, the force of law in the whole or any part of the 
existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>679846</tid>
<number>g</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislative Assembly of the 
existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh, means a 
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a 
member of that House or that Assembly;

</section>

<section><tid>1633661</tid>
<number>h</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1018</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 25- 1- <year>1971</year>: vide Notification No. G. S. R. 43, dated 6- 1- <year>1971</year>, see 
Gazette of India Exty., Part II, Sec, 3 (i), p. 11.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


PART

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH

PART II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1093102</tid>
<number>3</number>Establishment of State of Himachal Pradesh. On and from the 
appointed day, there shall be established a new State, to be known as 
the State of Himachal Pradesh, comprising the territories which 
immediately before that day were comprised in the existing Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1040839</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. On and from 
the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution,--
<section><tid>128685</tid>
<number>a</number>under the heading" I. THE STATES", after entry 17, the 
following entry shall be inserted, namely:--
" 18. Himachal Pradesh The territories which immediately 
before the commencement of this 
Constitution were being administered 
as if they were Chief Commissioners' 
Provinces under the names of Himachal 
Pradesh and Bilaspur and the 
territories specified in sub- section 
 (1) of section 5 of the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>.";


</section>

<section><tid>1611675</tid>
<number>b</number>under the heading" II. THE UNION TERRITORIES", entry 2 
relating to Himachal Pradesh shall be omitted and 
entries 3 to 10 shall be re- numbered as entries 2 to 9 
respectively.
PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>502168</tid>
<number> 6</number> Allocation of sitting members.
<section><tid>1463227</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed  
day, the three sitting members of the Council of States representing 
the existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh shall be deemed to 
have been duly elected under clause (4) of article 80 to fill the 
three seats allotted to the State of Himachal Pradesh in that Council.

</section>

<section><tid>837349</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of such sitting members shall remain 
unaltered.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1627020</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 27A of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. On and from the 
appointed day, in section 27A of the Representation of the People Act, 
<year>1950</year>, in sub- section (4), the words" Himachal Pradesh" shall be 
omitted.
The House of the People



</article>



<article><tid>1936866</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Provision as to sitting members.] Rep., ibid. (w. e. f. 5- 1-  
  <year>1971</year>).
The Legislative Assembly



</article>



<article><tid>129393</tid>
<number> 11</number> Duration of Legislative Assembly. The period of five years 
referred to in clause
<section><tid>505487</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 172 shall, in the case of the  
Legislative Assembly of the State of Himachal Pradesh, be deemed to 
have commenced on the day on which the duration of the existing 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh 
commenced under section 5 of the Government of Union Territories Act, 
 <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1920397</tid>
<number>12</number>Speaker and Deputy Speaker. The persons who immediately 
before the appointed day are the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh shall 
be the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, respectively, of the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Himachal Pradesh on and from that 
day.


</article>



<article><tid>928719</tid>
<number> 13</number> Rules of procedure. The rules of procedure and conduct of 
business of the Legislative Assembly of the existing Union territory 
of Himachal Pradesh as in force immediately before the appointed day 
shall, until rules are made under clause
<section><tid>1286424</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 208, be the  
rules of procedure and conduct of business of the Legislative Assembly 
of the State of Himachal Pradesh, subject to such modifications and 
adaptations as may be made therein by the Speaker thereof.
Delimitation of constituencies




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>882253</tid>
<number>15</number>Allocation of seats in the Legislative Assembly. The total 
number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Himachal 
Pradesh to be constituted at any time after the appointed day, to be 
filled by persons chosen by direct election from territorial 
constituencies, shall be sixty- eight of which sixteen seats shall be 
reserved for the Scheduled Castes and three seats shall be reserved 
for the Scheduled Tribes.


</article>



<article><tid>1019115</tid>
<number> 16</number> Amendment of First and Second Schedules to Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.

<section><tid>845574</tid>
<number>1</number>In the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year>,-- 

<subsection><tid>527803</tid>
<number>a</number>in the First Schedule,--

<subsubsection><tid>1847001</tid>
<number>i</number>under the heading" I. STATES", after 
entry 17, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 18. Himachal Pradesh............. 4 1....";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>455652</tid>
<number>ii</number>under the heading" II. UNION 
TERRITORIES", entry 6 relating to Himachal Pradesh 
shall be omitted;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1021</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1928214</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Second Schedule,--

<subsubsection><tid>366183</tid>
<number>i</number>under the heading" I. STATES", after 
entry 16, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 17. Himachal Pradesh............ 68 16 3";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1420412</tid>
<number>ii</number>under the heading" II. UNION 
TERRITORIES", entry 2 relating to Himachal Pradesh 
shall be omitted.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>321149</tid>
<number>2</number>The amendments made by clauses (a) and (b) of sub- section (1) 
shall have effect in relation to the House of the People and the 
Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh to be constituted at any time 
after the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>532168</tid>
<number> 17</number> Delimitation of constituencies.
<section><tid>1548343</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission  
shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute, whether before or 
after the appointed day, the seats in the House of the People allotted 
to the State of Himachal Pradesh under section 14 and the seats 
assigned to the Legislative Assembly of the State of Himachal Pradesh 
under section 15 to single- member territorial constituencies and 
delimit them on the basis of the latest census figures, having regard 
to the provisions of the Constitution and to the following provisions, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>687760</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas, and in delimiting them 
regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
boundaries of administrative units, facilities of 
communication and public convenience;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918487</tid>
<number>b</number>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to 
fall wholly within one parliamentary constituency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1063970</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes shall be distributed in different 
parts of the State and located, as far as practicable, 
in those areas where the proportion of their population 
to the total population is comparatively large; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1269909</tid>
<number>d</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be 
located in areas where the proportion of their 
population to the total population is the largest.
Explanation.-- In this section," latest census figures" mean the 
census figures with respect to the existing Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh or, as the case may be, of the State of Himachal 
Pradesh ascertainable from the latest census of which the finally 
published figures are available.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1022</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1551789</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of assisting it in the performance of its 
functions under sub- section (1), the Election Commission shall 
associate with itself as associate members,--

<subsection><tid>20785</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> all the persons (or as many of them as are available) 
who, having been elected from parliamentary 
constituencies in the Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh, were members of the House of the People 
immediately before its dissolution by the order of the 
President published with notification No. 37 2 70 T, 
dated the 27th December, <year>1970</year>, of the Lok Sabha 
Secretariat, in the Gazette of India, dated the 27th 
December, <year>1970</year>, or if the delimitation of any 
constituencies is taken up after the first 
constitution, following such dissolution, of the House 
of the People, all the members elected to such House 
 (or as many of them as are available) from 
parliamentary constituencies in the State of Himachal 
Pradesh; and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1072709</tid>
<number>b</number>such six of the members of the Legislative Assembly of 
the existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh or, as 
the case may be, of the State of Himachal Pradesh 
referred to in section 10 as the Speaker thereof may 
nominate:
Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to 
vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>384988</tid>
<number>3</number>If owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance 
with the provisions of sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1935393</tid>
<number>4</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>277641</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of 
constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals, 
if any, of any associate member who desires publication 
thereof, in the Official Gazette and in such other 
manner as the Commission may consider fit, together 
with a notice inviting objections and suggestions in 
relation to the proposals and specifying a date on or 
after which the proposals will be further considered by 
it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1113349</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>476323</tid>
<number>c</number>after considering all objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine by
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1023</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1971</year>, s. 3, for cl. (a)  (w. e. f. 5- 1- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


one or more orders the delimitation of constituencies 
and cause such order or orders to be published in the 
Official Gazette; and upon such publication, the order 
or orders shall have the full force of law and shall 
not be called in question in any court.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1922104</tid>
<number>5</number>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order 
relating to parliamentary constituencies shall be laid before the 
House of the People and every such order relating to assembly 
constituencies shall be laid before the Legislative Assembly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1483839</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders 
up- to- date.
<section><tid>209305</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  
notification in the Official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>783411</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistake in any order made under 
section 17 or any error arising therein from 
inadvertent slip or omission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>794544</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order are or is altered, make 
such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or 
expedient for bringing such order up- to- date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1869175</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under this section relating to a 
parliamentary or an assembly constituency shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is issued, before the House of the People or, as the 
case may be, the Legislative Assembly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1447668</tid>
<number> 19</number> Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.
<section><tid>616498</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>970077</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Castes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall stand amended as 
directed in the Second Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>409792</tid>
<number> 20</number> Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.
<section><tid>359640</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Third Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>34217</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Tribes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall stand amended as 
directed in the Fourth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1024</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

HIGH COURT

PART IV

HIGH COURT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1565267</tid>
<number> 21</number> High Court for Himachal Pradesh.
<section><tid>1467838</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, there shall be a separate High Court for the State of 
Himachal Pradesh (hereinafter referred to as the High Court of  
  Himachal Pradesh).

</section>

<section><tid>1382307</tid>
<number>2</number>The principal seat of the High Court of Himachal Pradesh 
shall be at Simla.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740132</tid>
<number> 22</number> Judges of High Court.
<section><tid>382457</tid>
<number>1</number>The President may, if he thinks  
fit, direct that such of the Judges of the High Court of Delhi holding 
office immediately before the appointed day as may be determined by 
him, shall on that day cease to be Judges of the High Court of Delhi 
and become Judges of the High Court of Himachal Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>948524</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons who by virtue of sub- section (1) become Judges of 
the High Court of Himachal Pradesh shall, except in the case where any 
such person is appointed to be the Chief Justice of the High Court, 
rank in that Court according to the priority of their respective 
appointments as Judges of the High Court of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>656402</tid>
<number>23</number>Jurisdiction of High Court. The High Court of Himachal 
Pradesh shall have, in respect of any part of the territories 
comprised in the State of Himachal Pradesh, all such jurisdiction, 
powers and authority as, under the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day, are exercisable in respect of that part of the said 
territories by the High Court of Delhi.


</article>



<article><tid>542991</tid>
<number> 24</number> Special provision relating to Advocates and Bar Council.
<section><tid>1402739</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court of 
Himachal Pradesh in this behalf, any person who immediately before the 
appointed day is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of 
Delhi shall be entitled to practise as an advocate in the High Court 
of Himachal Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>533029</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of audience in the High Court of Himachal Pradesh 
shall be regulated in accordance with the like principles as 
immediately before the appointed day are in force with respect to the 
right of audience in the High Court of Delhi.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1025</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>211289</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the appointed day, in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25  
  of <year>1961</year>). (hereafter in this section referred to as the Advocates  
  Act), in section 3,--

<subsection><tid>1546448</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for clause (d), the following 
clauses shall be substituted, namely:--
" (d) for the States of Punjab and Haryana and 
the Union territory of Chandigarh, to be known as 
the Bar Council of Punjab and Haryana;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>335541</tid>
<number>dd</number>for the State of Himachal Pradesh, to be 
known as the Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh;";

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>493492</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (b) of sub- section (2), after the words" Bar 
Council of Orissa", the words", the Bar Council of 
Himachal Pradesh" shall be inserted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>328849</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of section 17 of the Advocates Act shall have 
effect in respect of the roll of the Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh 
subject to the modifications that--

<subsection><tid>1154187</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (a) of sub- section (1) of the said section 
17, the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (a) all persons who were entered as 
advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Punjab 
and Haryana immediately before the day appointed 
under clause (b) of section 2 of the State of 
Himachal Pradesh Act, <year>1970</year>, and who within three 
months from that day express in such manner as the 
Bar Council of India may, by rules, prescribe an 
intention in writing to practise within the 
jurisdiction of the Bar Council of Himachal 
Pradesh;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>392519</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (a) of sub- section (3) of the said section 17, 
for the words and figures" with his date of enrollment 
under the Indian Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year>" (38 of <year>1926</year>), 
the words" with his seniority on the roll of the Bar 
Council of Punjab and Haryana" shall be substituted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>827754</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Advocates Act as 
amended or modified by sub- sections (3) and (4),--

<subsection><tid>1025493</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the first Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh 
under that Act, the fifteen members required to be 
elected under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 
 3 of that Act, as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1026</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

amended by sub- section (3), shall be nominated by the 
Chief Justice of the High Court of Himachal Pradesh 
from amongst advocates who are entitled as of right to 
practise in the High Court of Himachal Pradesh and are 
ordinarily practising within the territories comprised 
in the State of Himachal Pradesh and the term of office 
of the members so nominated shall be one year from the 
date of the first meeting of the Council or until their 
successors are duly elected in accordance with the 
provisions of the said Act, whichever is earlier;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>570007</tid>
<number>b</number>until the members of the first Bar Council of Himachal 
Pradesh required to be nominated under clause (a) are 
duly nominated in accordance with the provisions of 
that clause, the Bar Council of Punjab and Haryana 
shall function as the Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh 
and the provisions of the Advocates Act shall, so far 
as may be, apply accordingly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>567510</tid>
<number>c</number>the names of persons entered on the roll of the Bar 
Council of Himachal Pradesh in accordance with the 
provisions of clause (a) of sub- section (1) of section 
 17 of the Advocates Act, as modified by sub- section 
 (4), shall, as from the date or dates on which the 
names are so entered, stand removed from the roll of 
the Bar Council of Punjab and Haryana;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1961294</tid>
<number>d</number>any proceedings which may be pending or which may be 
instituted against any person before or by the Bar 
Council of Punjab and Haryana immediately before his 
name is removed under clause (c) from the roll of that 
Bar Council may after such removal be continued or 
instituted before or by the Bar Council of Himachal 
Pradesh;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>462796</tid>
<number>e</number>every person who immediately before his name stands 
removed from the roll of the Bar Council of Punjab and 
Haryana in accordance with the provisions of clause (c) 
is a member of the Bar Council of Punjab and Haryana 
shall cease to be a member of that Council as from the 
date on which his name stands so removed from the roll 
of that Bar Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1473753</tid>
<number>f</number>the rules made or deemed to have been made by the Bar 
Council of Punjab and Haryana and in force immediately 
before the date on which the first Bar Council of 
Himachal Pradesh is duly constituted in accordance with 
the provisions of clause (a) shall, subject to such 
modifications and adaptations as may be made therein by 
the Chairman of the Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh, be 
deemed to be rules made by the Bar Council of Himachal 
Pradesh and shall have effect accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1027</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>48280</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be, after the first Bar Council of Himachal 
Pradesh is duly constituted in accordance with the provisions of 
clause (a) of sub- section (5), the assets and liabilities of the Bar 
Council of Punjab and Haryana shall be apportioned between that Bar 
Council and the Bar Council of Himachal Pradesh in such manner and 
proportion as may be agreed upon by the two Bar Councils and in 
default of agreement with reference to any matter, the matter shall be 
referred to the Chairman of the Bar Council of India and his decision 
thereon shall be final.
Explanation.-- Expressions used in this section but not defined in 
this Act shall have the meanings assigned to them respectively in the 
Advocates Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>205737</tid>
<number>25</number>Practice and procedure in High Court. Subject to the 
provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Delhi shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to 
the High Court of Himachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1094360</tid>
<number>26</number>Custody of seal of High Court. The law in force immediately 
before the appointed day with respect to the custody of the seal of 
the High Court of Delhi shall, with the necessary modifications, apply 
with respect to the custody of the seal of the High Court of Himachal 
Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>948376</tid>
<number>27</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of Delhi 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with respect to the 
form of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High 
Court of Himachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1803764</tid>
<number>28</number>Powers of Judges. The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Delhi and with respect 
to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those powers shall, with 
the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the High Court of 
Himachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1115926</tid>
<number>29</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Delhi and the Judges and division 
courts thereof, shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in 
relation to the High Court of Himachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1215261</tid>
<number> 30</number> Transfer of proceedings from High Court of Delhi to High 
Court of Himachal Pradesh.
<section><tid>147451</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided, the  
High Court of Delhi shall, on and from the appointed day, have no 
jurisdiction in respect of the territories comprised in the State of 
Himachal Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>244880</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Delhi 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified, whether before 
or after that day, by the Chief Justice of that High Court, having 
regard to the place

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1028</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances, to be 
proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High Court of 
Himachal Pradesh shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the High Court of Himachal Pradesh.


</section>

<section><tid>1912651</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2) of this section or in section 23, but save as hereinafter 
provided, the High Court of Delhi shall have, and the High Court of 
Himachal Pradesh shall not have, jurisdiction to entertain, hear or 
dispose of appeals, applications for leave to appeal to the Supreme 
Court, applications for review and other proceedings where any such 
proceedings seek any relief in respect of any order passed by the High 
Court of Delhi before the appointed day:
Provided that if, after any such proceedings have been 
entertained by the High Court of Delhi, it appears to the Chief 
Justice of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the 
High Court of Himachal Pradesh, he shall order that they shall be so 
transferred, and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred 
accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>191012</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court of Delhi--

<subsection><tid>350100</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day, in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court of Himachal Pradesh by virtue of sub- 
section (2); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1767109</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
of Delhi retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section 
 (3),
shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of the High 
Court of Delhi, but also as an order made by the High Court of 
Himachal Pradesh.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>350100</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court 
until that court has disposed of all issues between the 
parties including any issues with respect to the 
taxation of the costs of the proceedings and shall 
include appeals, application for leave to appeal to the 
Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions for 
revisions and petitions for writs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1767109</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1029</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>491101</tid>
<number>31</number>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to High 
Court of Himachal Pradesh. Any person who, immediately before the 
appointed day, is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court 
of Delhi and was authorised to appear or to act in any proceedings 
transferred from that High Court to the High Court of Himachal Pradesh 
under section 30 shall have the right to appear or to act, as the case 
may be, in the High Court of Himachal Pradesh in relation to those 
proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>890514</tid>
<number>32</number>Savings. Nothing in this Part shall affect the application 
to the High Court of Himachal Pradesh of any provisions of the 
Constitution, and this Part shall have effect subject to any 
provisions that may be made on or after the appointed day with respect 
to that High Court by any Legislature or other authority having power 
to make such provision.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES



</article>



<article><tid>1984882</tid>
<number> 33</number> Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by the 
Legislature.
<section><tid>361183</tid>
<number>1</number>The President may, at any time before the appointed  
day, authorise by order such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of 
the State of Himachal Pradesh as he deems necessary for a period of 
not more than six months beginning with the appointed day, pending the 
sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative Assembly of the State 
of Himachal Pradesh:
Provided that the Governor of Himachal Pradesh may, after the 
appointed day, authorise by order such further expenditure as he deems 
necessary from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Himachal Pradesh 
for any period not extending beyond the said period of six months.


</section>

<section><tid>105776</tid>
<number>2</number>The President or, as the case may be, the Governor of 
Himachal Pradesh shall make separate orders under sub- section (1) in 
respect of periods falling in different financial years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1043024</tid>
<number> 34</number> Reports relating to the accounts of the existing Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh.
<section><tid>388737</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports of the Comptroller and  
Auditor- General of India referred to in section 49 of the Government 
of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>), relating to the accounts 
of the existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh in respect of any 
period prior to the appointed day, shall be submitted to the Governor 
of Himachal Pradesh who shall cause them to be laid before the 
Legislative Assembly of the State.

</section>

<section><tid>1377060</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governor may, by order,--

<subsection><tid>1122485</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated 
Fund of the existing Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh on any service in respect of any period prior 
to the appointed day during the financial year <year>1970</year>- 71 
or in respect of any earlier

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1030</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

financial year in excess of the amount granted for that 
service and for that year as disclosed in the reports 
referred to in sub- section (1) to have been duly 
authorised, and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>525792</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising 
out of the said reports.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>938351</tid>
<number>35</number>Allowances and privileges of Governor of Himachal Pradesh. 
The allowances and privileges of the Governor of Himachal Pradesh 
shall, until provision in that behalf is made by Parliament by law 
under clause (3) of article 158, be such as the President may, by 
order, determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1338049</tid>
<number>36</number>Distribution of revenues. The President shall, by order, 
determine the grants- in- aid of the revenues of the State of Himachal 
Pradesh and the share of that State in the Union duties of excise, 
estate duty and taxes on income and for that purpose amend thereby the 
relevant provisions of the Union Duties of Excise (Distribution) Act, 
 <year>1962</year> (3 of <year>1962</year>), the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special  
  Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>), the Estate Duty (Distribution) 
Act, <year>1962</year> (9 of <year>1962</year>), and the Constitution (Distribution of  
  Revenues) Order, <year>1969</year> (C. O. 87), in such manner as he thinks fit.
PART

ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>640493</tid>
<number> 37</number> Property, assets, rights, liabilities, obligations, etc.,
<section><tid>219068</tid>
<number>1</number> 
All such property and assets within the existing Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh as are held immediately before the appointed day by 
the Union for purposes of governance of that Union territory shall, on 
and from that day, pass to the State of Himachal Pradesh unless the 
purposes for which such property and assets are so held are Union 
purposes:
Provided that the cash balances in the treasuries in the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh before the appointed day shall, as from 
that day, vest in the State of Himachal Pradesh.


</section>

<section><tid>995729</tid>
<number>2</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations (other than those  
  relatable to, or in connection with, a Union purpose), whether arising 
out of any contract or otherwise, which are, immediately before the 
appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>310604</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights, liabilities and obligations of the Central 
Government arising out of, or in connection with, the 
governance of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550757</tid>
<number>b</number>the rights, liabilities and obligations of the 
Administrator of the existing Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh in his capacity as such, or of the 
Government of that Union territory,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1031</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall, on and from the appointed day, be the rights, liabilities and 
obligations of the Government of the State of Himachal Pradesh.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1880146</tid>
<number>3</number>The right to recover arrears of--

<subsection><tid>1954934</tid>
<number>a</number>any tax or duty being a tax or duty enumerated in the 
State List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1647944</tid>
<number>b</number>any duty referred to in article 268, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1515398</tid>
<number>c</number>any tax under the Central Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year> (74 of  
  <year>1956</year>),
which have fallen due in the existing Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh shall pass to the State of Himachal Pradesh.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>226496</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of this section shall not apply to or in 
relation to,--

<subsection><tid>51633</tid>
<number>a</number>any benefit or burden of any assets, rights, liabilities 
or obligations of the Union under the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of <year>1966</year>), attributable to 
the transferred territories as defined in the said Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753185</tid>
<number>b</number>any institution, undertaking or project the expenditure 
in relation to which is immediately before the 
appointed day met from out of the Consolidated Fund of 
India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563456</tid>
<number>c</number>any property which has been placed by the Union at the 
disposal of the Administration of the existing Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh subject to the condition 
that the ownership thereof will continue to vest in the 
Union.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>51633</tid>
<number>a</number>" liability" includes liability in respect of any civil 
deposit, local fund deposit, charitable or other 
endowment, provident fund account, pension or 
actionable wrong;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753185</tid>
<number>b</number>" Union purposes" mean the purposes of Government 
relatable to any of the matters mentioned in the Union 
List.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1276994</tid>
<number> 38</number> Special provision as to transfer of assets, rights, 
liabilities, etc., of Union in relation to transferred territories 
under Act 31 of <year>1966</year>.
<section><tid>814429</tid>
<number>1</number>In this section, the expressions" successor  
States" and" transferred territories" have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of <year>1966</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>155325</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by order, transfer to the State 
of Himachal Pradesh the benefit or burden of any assets, rights, 
liabilities or obligations of the Union under the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of <year>1966</year>), in so far as such benefit or 
burden is, in the opinion of the Central Government, attributable to 
the transferred territories.

</section>

<section><tid>1789915</tid>
<number>3</number>An order made under sub- section (2) may provide that the 
State of Himachal Pradesh shall be the successor State in relation to 
the transferred territories for all or any of the purposes of the 
Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of <year>1966</year>), or confer or impose on 
the State of Himachal Pradesh

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1032</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

rights and obligations which correspond so far as may be to the rights 
and obligations conferred or imposed on the successor States by or 
under that Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1651061</tid>
<number>4</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 49, the 
Central Government may, for the purpose of giving effect to the 
provisions of this section, by order, direct that the provisions of 
Part VI, Part VIII, Part VIII and Part IX and connected provisions of 
the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>, (31 of <year>1966</year>.) shall have effect 
subject to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in 
the order.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES

PART VII

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1857996</tid>
<number> 39</number> Provision relation to All- India Services.
<section><tid>793826</tid>
<number>1</number>In this  
section, the expression" State cadre",--

<subsection><tid>766498</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to the Indian Administrative Service, has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Indian Administrative 
Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>473338</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to the Indian Police Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Police Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682023</tid>
<number>c</number>in relation to the Indian Forest Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Forest Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1966</year>.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>813274</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, there shall be constituted for 
the State of Himachal Pradesh a State cadre of the Indian 
Administrative Service, a State cadre of the Indian Police Service and 
a State cadre of the Indian Forest Service.

</section>

<section><tid>1453965</tid>
<number>3</number>The initial strength and composition of each of the said 
State cadres shall be such as the Central Government may, by order 
determine before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>661718</tid>
<number>4</number>Such of the members of each of the said Services borne on the 
Union territories cadre thereof immediately before the appointed day, 
as the Central Government may, by order, specify, shall be allocated 
to the State cadre of Himachal Pradesh of the same Service with effect 
from such date or dates as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>522385</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
operation after the appointed day of the All- India Services Act, <year>1951</year> 
 (61 of <year>1961</year>), or the rules or regulations made thereunder in relation 
to the State cadres of the said Services referred to in sub- section 
 (2) or sub- section (4) and in relation to the members of those 
services borne on the State cadres.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1033</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>46375</tid>
<number> 40</number> Provision relating to certain Services.
<section><tid>1632597</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, there shall be constituted for the State of Himachal 
Pradesh the following Services, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1857221</tid>
<number>a</number>the Himachal Pradesh Administrative Service; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>189947</tid>
<number>b</number>the Himachal Pradesh Police Service.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1325791</tid>
<number>2</number>The initial strength and composition of the cadres of the 
said Services shall be such as the Administrator of the existing Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh may, with the approval of the Central 
Government, by order, determine before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1843807</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the appointed day, the existing Delhi, Himachal 
Pradesh and Andaman and Nicobar Islands Civil Service (hereinafter  
  referred to as the existing Civil Service) shall be known as the Delhi 
and Andaman and Nicobar Islands Civil Service and the Delhi, Himachal 
Pradesh and Andaman and Nicobar Islands Police Service (hereinafter  
  referred to as the existing Police Service) shall be known as the 
Delhi and Andaman and Nicobar Islands Police Service.

</section>

<section><tid>993825</tid>
<number>4</number>Such members of the existing Civil Service as the Central 
Government may, by order, specify shall be allocated to the cadre of 
the Himachal Pradesh Administrative Service and such members of the 
existing Police Service as the Central Government may, by order, 
specify, shall be allocated to the cadre of the Himachal Pradesh 
Police Service and any such order may specify the date or dates from 
which the allocation made thereunder shall be effective.

</section>

<section><tid>1001263</tid>
<number>5</number>All persons who are allocated under sub- section (4) and who 
immediately before the date on which they are allocated, are borne on 
a Select List for promotion to a State cadre of an All- India Service, 
shall be deemed to have been included in the same order as in that 
list in the Select List for promotion to the State cadre of the same 
Service constituted under sub- section (2) of section 39.

</section>

<section><tid>788982</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to the foregoing provisions of this section, the 
rules and regulations applicable to or in relation to the members of 
the existing Civil Service and the existing Police Service as in force 
immediately before the appointed day shall, so far as may be, apply 
respectively to and in relation to the members of the Himachal Pradesh 
Administrative Service and the Himachal Pradesh Police Service, until 
altered, repealed or amended by the competent authority.

</section>

<section><tid>40115</tid>
<number>7</number>Every member of the Central Health Service who immediately 
before the appointed day is holding any post in the existing Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh being a post included in the authorised 
strength

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1034</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of that Service, shall, until otherwise directed by the Central 
Government, be deemed to be on deputation, on and from the appointed 
day, to the Government of the State of Himachal Pradesh on the same 
terms and conditions of service as are applicable to him under the 
Central Health Service Rules, <year>1963</year>, but without any deputation 
allowance:

Provided that the period of such deputation shall in no case 
extend beyond a period of three years from the appointed day.

Explanation.-- In this sub- section," Central Health Service" means 
the Central Health Service constituted under the Central Health 
Service Rules, <year>1963</year>.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>270519</tid>
<number> 41</number> Provisions relating to other services.
<section><tid>172536</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who  
immediately before the appointed day is serving in connection with the 
affairs of the Union under the administrative control of the 
Administrator of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh shall, unless 
otherwise directed by an order of the Central Government, be deemed to 
have been allocated for service as from that day in connection with 
the affairs of the State of Himachal Pradesh:
Provided that no directions shall be issued under this section 
after the expiry of a period of one year from the appointed day:

Provided further that nothing in this section shall affect the 
operation of section 82 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of  
  <year>1966</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>1909285</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this section shall not apply in relation to 
persons to whom the provisions of sections 39 and 40 apply.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519088</tid>
<number> 42</number> Other provisions as to services.
<section><tid>1264191</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing in this section  
or sections 40 and 41 shall be deemed to affect on or after the 
appointed day the operations of the provisions of Chapter I of Part 
XIV of the Constitution in relation to determination of the conditions 
of service of persons serving in connection with the affairs of the 
State of Himachal Pradesh:
Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately 
before the appointed day in the case of any person referred to in 
section 40 or section 41 shall not be varied to his disadvantage 
except with the previous approval of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>591773</tid>
<number>2</number>All services prior to the appointed day rendered by a person 
allocated under section 40 or deemed to have been allocated under 
section 41 in connection with the administration of the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh, shall be deemed to have been rendered 
in connection with the affairs of the State of Himachal Pradesh for 
the purposes of the rules regulating his conditions of service.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1035</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>719289</tid>
<number>43</number>Provisions as to continuance of officers in same posts. Every 
person who immediately before the appointed day is holding or 
discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the 
administration of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh, shall 
continue to hold the same post or office in the State of Himachal 
Pradesh and shall be deemed, on and from that day, to have been duly 
appointed to the post or office by the Government of, or other 
appropriate authority in, the State of Himachal Pradesh:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
a competent authority on or after the appointed day from passing in 
relation to such person any order affecting his continuance in such 
post or office.



</article>



<article><tid>194385</tid>
<number> 44</number> Advisory Committees. The Central Government may, by order, 
establish one or more Advisory Committees for the purpose of assisting 
it in regard to--
<section><tid>1168651</tid>
<number>a</number>the discharge of its functions under this Part; and

</section>

<section><tid>1991398</tid>
<number>b</number>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all 
persons affected by the provisions of this Part and the 
proper consideration of any representations made by 
such persons.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297291</tid>
<number>45</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. The Central 
Government may give such directions to the Government of the State of 
Himachal Pradesh as may appear to it to be necessary for the purpose 
of giving effect to the foregoing provisions of this Part and also the 
provisions of Part IX of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of  
  <year>1966</year>), and the State Government shall comply with such directions.
PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART VIII

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1314159</tid>
<number> 46</number> Amendment of article 210 and article 239A. On and from the 
appointed day--
<section><tid>1129275</tid>
<number>a</number>in article 210, in clause (2), the following proviso 
shall be inserted at the end, namely:--
' Provided that in relation to the Legislature 
of the State of Himachal Pradesh this clause shall 
have effect as if for the words" fifteen years" 
occurring therein, the words" twenty- five years" 
were substituted';


</section>

<section><tid>1461959</tid>
<number>b</number>in article 239A, in clause (1), the words" Himachal 
Pradesh" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>875687</tid>
<number> 47</number> Amendment of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>. On and from the appointed day, 
in clause (a) of section 15 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>,--
<section><tid>329026</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word" Punjab", the words" Punjab, Himachal 
Pradesh" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1706178</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" Himachal Pradesh and Chandigarh", the 
words" and Chandigarh" shall be substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1036</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1127844</tid>
<number> 48</number> Amendment of Act 20 of <year>1963</year>. On and from the appointed day, 
in the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year>, in clause (h) of 
sub- section
<section><tid>1152811</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 2 and in sub- section (2) of section 44, the  
words" Himachal Pradesh" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1816238</tid>
<number> 49</number> Continuance of existing laws and their adaptation.
<section><tid>1187994</tid>
<number>1</number>All  
laws in force, immediately before the appointed day, in the existing 
Union territory of Himachal Pradesh shall continue to be in force in 
the State of Himachal Pradesh until altered, repealed or amended by a 
competent Legislature or other competent authority.

</section>

<section><tid>82377</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of facilitating the application in relation 
to the State of Himachal Pradesh of any law made before the appointed 
day, the appropriate Government may, within two years from that day, 
by order, make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether 
by way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and 
thereupon every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations 
and modifications so made until altered, repealed or amended by a 
competent Legislature or other competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means, as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated 
in the Union List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the 
Central Government; and as respects any other law, the Government of 
the State of Himachal Pradesh.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1908458</tid>
<number>50</number>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made under section 49 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Himachal Pradesh, construe the law in such manner not affecting the 
substance as may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before 
the court, tribunal or authority, as the case may be.


</article>



<article><tid>1269133</tid>
<number>51</number>Provisions as to continuance of courts, etc. All courts and 
tribunals and all authorities discharging lawful functions throughout 
the existing Union territory of Himachal Pradesh or any part thereof 
immediately before the appointed day shall, unless their continuance 
is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or until other 
provision is made by a competent Legislature or other competent 
authority, continue to exercise their respective functions.


</article>



<article><tid>1554082</tid>
<number>52</number>Effect of provisions of Act inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1037</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1815739</tid>
<number> 53</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1106182</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>819736</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>893490</tid>
<number> 54</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>496539</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1770480</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>