<act><title>

The 
    Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called The Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***].]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on the first day of April, 1925.
 
The Act has 
    been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry subject to the 
    modifications that (i) a reference to a law not in force or to a functionary 
    not in existence in Pondicherry shall be construed as a reference to 
    corresponding law in force or to corresponding functionary in existence, in 
    Pondicherry and (ii) sub-section (3) shall be omitted—See S.O. 4, Gazette of 
    India, 1963, Pt. II, section 3 (ii), p. 3.
 
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>    
    “Court” means a Court other than a Criminal Court and includes any such 
    tribunal or other authority as may be specified by the Central Government by 
    notification in the Official Gazette being a tribunal or authority which is 
    empowered by law to receive evidence on any matter pending before it and on 
    the basis of such evidence to determine, after hearing the parties before 
    it, the rights and obligations of the parties in relation to such matter];3[(a) 
    “Court” means a Court other than a Criminal Court and includes any such 
    tribunal or other authority as may be specified by the Central Government by 
    notification in the Official Gazette being a tribunal or authority which is 
    empowered by law to receive evidence on any matter pending before it and on 
    the basis of such evidence to determine, after hearing the parties before 
    it, the rights and obligations of the parties in relation to such matter];" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Indian soldier” means any person 
    subject to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the Army 
    Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act 1950], [or the Navy Act, 1957];
4[the 
    Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act 1950], [or the Navy Act, 1957];" 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; and
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “proceeding” includes any suit, appeal 
    or application.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>e</number>    any reference to a decree 
    or order of a Court shall be deemed to include a reference to a judgement, 
    determination or award of a Court.]
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Circumstances in which an Indian soldier shall be deemed to be serving under 
    special conditions.—For the 
    purposes of this Act, an Indian soldier shall be deemed to be or, as the 
    case may be, to have been serving— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    under special conditions (when he is or 
    has been serving under war conditions), or overseas, or at any place <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[beyond 
    India], <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[or any such place within India as may be specified by 
    the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette];
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    under war conditions—when he is or has 
    been, at any time during the continuance of any hostilities declared by the
    <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Central Government] by notification in the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Official 
    Gazette] to constitute a state of war for the purpose of this Act or at any 
    time during a period of six months thereafter,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    serving out of India, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    under orders to proceed on field 
    service, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    serving with any unit which is for 
    the time being mobilised, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    serving under conditions which, in the 
    opinion of the prescribed authority, preclude him from obtaining leave of 
    absence to enable him to attend a Court as a party to any proceeding or when 
    he is or has been at any other time serving under conditions service under 
    which has been declared by the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Central Government] by 
    notification in the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Official Gazette] to be service under war 
    conditions; and
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>    overseas—when he is or has 
    been serving in any place outside India (other than Ceylon) the journey 
    between which and <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[India] is ordinarily undertaken wholly or in 
    part by sea.]
  
 
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section and with effect from the 3rd day of September, 
    1939, a soldier who is or has been a prisoner of war shall be deemed to be 
    or to have been serving under war conditions.]
 
 
  










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Particulars to be furnished in plaints, applications or appeals to Court.—If 
    any person presenting any plaint, application or appeal to any Court has 
    reason to believe that any adverse party is an Indian soldier who is serving 
    under special conditions, he shall state the fact in his plaint, application 
    or appeal. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power of 
    Collector to intervene in case of unrepresented Indian soldier.—If 
    any Collector has reason to believe that any Indian soldier, who ordinarily 
    resides or has property in his district and who is a party to any proceeding 
    pending before any Court, is unable to appear therein, the Collector may 
    certify the facts in the prescribed manner to the Court. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Notice to be given in case of unrepresented Indian soldier.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a Collector has certified under Section 5, or if the Court has reason to 
    believe, that an Indian soldier, who is a party to any proceeding pending 
    before it, is unable to appear therein, and if the soldier is not 
    represented by any person duly authorised to appear, plead or act on his 
    behalf, the Court shall suspend the proceeding and shall give notice thereof 
    in the prescribed manner to the prescribed authority:—6[(1) 
    If a Collector has certified under Section 5, or if the Court has reason to 
    believe, that an Indian soldier, who is a party to any proceeding pending 
    before it, is unable to appear therein, and if the soldier is not 
    represented by any person duly authorised to appear, plead or act on his 
    behalf, the Court shall suspend the proceeding and shall give notice thereof 
    in the prescribed manner to the prescribed authority\:" 
 
Provided that 
    the Court may refrain from suspending the proceeding and issuing notice if— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the proceeding is a suit, appeal or 
    application instituted or made by the soldier, alone or conjointly with 
    others with the object of enforcing a right of pre-emption, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the interests of the soldier in the 
    proceeding are, in the opinion of the Court, either identical with those of 
    any other party to the proceeding and adequately represented by such other 
    party or merely of a formal nature. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    If it appear to the Court before which any proceeding is pending that an 
    Indian soldier though not a party to the proceeding is materially concerned 
    in the outcome of the proceeding and that his interests are likely to be 
    prejudiced by his inability to attend, the Court may suspend the proceeding 
    and shall give notice thereof in the prescribed manner to the prescribed 
    authority.]
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Postponement of proceedings.—If, 
    on receipt of a notice under section 6, the prescribed authority certifies 
    in the prescribed manner to the Court in which the proceedings is pending 
    that the soldier in respect of whom the notice was given is serving under 
    special conditions, and that a postponement of the proceedings in respect of 
    the soldier is necessary, in the interest of justice, the Court shall 
    thereupon postpone the proceeding in respect of the soldier for the 
    prescribed period, or, if no period has been prescribed, for such period as 
    it thinks fit. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Court 
    may proceed when no certificate received.—If, 
    after issue of notice under section 6, the prescribed authority either 
    certifies that the soldier is not serving under special conditions or that 
    such postponement is not necessary, or fails to certify, in the case of a 
    soldier resident in the district in which the Court is situate within two 
    months or, in any other case, within three months, from the date of the 
    issue of the notice that such postponement is necessary, the Court may, if 
    it thinks fit, continue the proceeding. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Postponement of proceedings against Indian soldier on leave.—When 
    any document purporting to be signed by the Commanding Officer of an Indian 
    soldier who is a party to any proceeding is produced by or on behalf of the 
    soldier before the Court in which the proceeding is pending and is to the 
    effect that the soldier— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    is on leave of absence for a period not 
    exceeding two months, and is on the expiration of his leave to rejoin his 
    unit with a view to proceeding on service under special conditions, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    is on sick leave for a period not 
    exceeding three months, and is on the expiration of his leave to rejoin his 
    unit with a view to proceeding on service under special conditions. 
 
the 
    proceeding in respect of such soldier may, in any case such as if referred 
    to in the proviso to <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[sub-section 
    (1) of section 6] and shall, in any other case, be postponed in the manner 
    provided in section 7.
 
 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Power to set aside decrees and orders, passed against an Indian soldier 
    serving under war or special conditions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any proceeding before a Court in which a decree or order has been passed 
    against any Indian soldier <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[***] 
    whilst he was serving under any special conditions, the soldier <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[or, 
    if he is dead, his legal representative] may apply to the Court which passed 
    the decree or order for an order to set aside the same, and, if the Court 
    after giving an opportunity to the opposite party of being heard, is 
    satisfied that the interests of justice require that the decree or order 
    should be set aside as against the soldier, the Court shall, subject to such 
    conditions, if any, as it thinks fit to impose, make an order accordingly.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The period of limitation for an application under sub-section (1) shall be 
    ninety days from the date of the decree or order, or where the summons or 
    notice was duly served on the soldier in the proceeding in which the decree 
    or order was passed, from the date on which the applicant had knowledge of 
    the decree or order; and the provisions of section 5 of the Indian 
    Limitation Act, 1908 shall apply to such applications.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the 
    decree or order in respect of which an application under sub-section (1) is 
    made is of such a nature that it cannot be set aside as against the soldier 
    only, it may be set aside as against all or any of the parties against whom 
    it has been made.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a 
    Court sets aside a decree or order under this section, it shall appoint a 
    day for proceeding with the suit, appeal or application, as the case may be. 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> 
    Modification of law of limitation where Indian soldier or his legal 
    representative is a party.—In 
    computing the period of limitation prescribed by sub-section (2) of section 
    10 of this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, 1908, or any other law for the 
    time being in force, for any suit, appeal or application to a Court, any 
    party to which is or has been an Indian soldier, or is the legal 
    representative of an Indian soldier, the period during which the soldier has 
    been serving under any special conditions, and, if the soldier has died 
    while so serving, the period from the date of his death to the date on which 
    official intimation thereof was sent to his next-of-kin by the authorities 
    in India, shall be excluded:5[11. 
    Modification of law of limitation where Indian soldier or his legal 
    representative is a party.—In 
    computing the period of limitation prescribed by sub-section (2) of section 
    10 of this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, 1908, or any other law for the 
    time being in force, for any suit, appeal or application to a Court, any 
    party to which is or has been an Indian soldier, or is the legal 
    representative of an Indian soldier, the period during which the soldier has 
    been serving under any special conditions, and, if the soldier has died 
    while so serving, the period from the date of his death to the date on which 
    official intimation thereof was sent to his next-of-kin by the authorities 
    in India, shall be excluded\:" 
 
Provided 
    that this section shall not apply in the case of any suit, appeal or 
    application instituted or made with the object of enforcing a right of 
    pre-emption 

    2[3[except 
    where the said right accrues in such circumstances, and is in respect of 
    agricultural land and village immovable property situated in any such area] 
    as the Central Government may, by notification4 in 
    the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf]. 
  










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> 
    Power of Court to refer questions to prescribed authorities.—If 
    any Court is in doubt whether, for the purposes of section 10 or section 11, 
    an Indian soldier is or was at any particular time serving under special 
    conditions, or has died while so serving, or as to the date of such death or 
    as to the date on which official intimation of such death was sent to his 
    next-of-kin by the authorities in India, the Court may refer the point for 
    the decision of the prescribed authority, and the certificate of that 
    authority shall be conclusive evidence on the point.]
 
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Rule-making power.—<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[Central Government] <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[***] may, by notification 
    in the [Official Gazette] make <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>rules to provide for all or any 
    of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner and form in which any notice 
    or certificate under this Act shall be given;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the period for which proceedings or any 
    class of proceedings shall be postponed under section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the persons who shall be the prescribed 
    authorities for the purpose of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any other matter which is to be or may 
    be prescribed; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    generally any matters incidental to the 
    purposes of this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
    is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
    total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
    or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.]
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Power to apply the provisions of the Act to other person in the 
      service of the Government.—<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
      <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[As respects the State Public Services, the <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[State 
      Government], and in other cases, the Central Government] may, by 
      notification in the <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Official Gazette], direct that all or any 
      of the provisions of this Act shall apply to any other class of persons in 
      the service of Government specified in such notification in the same 
      manner as they apply to Indian soldiers.
 </section><section><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Where, 
      under this section, the <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[State Government] has directed that 
      all or any of the provisions of this Act shall apply to any class of 
      persons in the service of Government, the powers vested in the Central 
      Government by section 3 and section 13 shall be exercised in respect of 
      that class of persons by the <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[State 
      Government].]
  








 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>14A</number> Power to apply the provisions of the Act to 
      members of the forces maintained by any Part B State.—[Rep. by 3 A.L.O., 1956 (w.r.e.f. 
      1-11-1956).]
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Repeal of Acts 9 of 1918 and 12 of 
      1924.—[Rep. by the Repealing 
      Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch.]
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by A.L.O. 1950, for 
    the former clause (w.e.f. 26-1-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   The words “except the State 
    of Jammu and Kashmir” were omitted by the Jammu and Kashmir (Extension of 
    Laws) Act, 1956 (62 of 1956), sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-11-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by Act 23 of 1970, 
    sec. 2, for former clause (a) (w.e.f. 29-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for “the Indian Army Act, 1911, or the Indian Air Force 
    Act, 1932” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by Act 23 of 1970, 
    sec. 2 (w.e.f. 29-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by A.L.O. 1950, for 
    the words beginning with “in Persia” and ending with “nearest railway 
    Station” (w.e.f. 26-1-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by Act 23 of 
    1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 29-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, 
    for “Governor General in Council” and “Gazette of India” (w.e.f. 1-4-1937).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   For such notification,
    see Vol. 2 of General Statutory Rules and Orders (1961), pp. 272, 
    273.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, 
    for the original clause (w.e.f. 1-4-1937).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by A.C.A.O., 
    1948, for “British India” (w.e.f. 23-3-1948).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Ins. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   The original section was 
    renumbered as sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) was ins. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 4, for “section 6”  (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   The words “whilst he was 
    serving under war conditions or at any time after the Ist day of April, 
    1925” were omitted by Ord. 64 of 1942, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Ins. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Subs. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 6, for the original (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Added by Ord. 14 of 
    1944, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 29-4-1944).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by Act 18 of 1946, 
    sec. 2, for “except in such areas, and subject to such modifications, if 
    any”  (w.e.f. 18-4-1946).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   For such notification,
    see Gazette of India, 1946, Pt. I, p. 1305.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by Ord. 64 of 
    1942, sec. 7, for the original  (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Section 13 renumbered as 
    sub-section (2) thereof by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 &amp; Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, for 
    “Local Government” and “local Official Gazette”, respectively.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Words “after consulting the 
    High Court concerned”, omitted by Act 23 of 1970, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 29-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   For Indian Soldiers 
    (Litigation) Rules, 1938, see Gazette of India, 1938, Pt. I, p. 968 
    and for the Indian Seamen (Litigation) Rules, see Gazette of India, 
    1945, Pt. I, p. 622. (See General Statutory Rules and Orders, Vol. 2 
    (1961), pp. 262-271.)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Sub-section (2) ins. by Act 
    4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Section 14 renumbered as sub-section (1) 
      of that section by Ord. 54 of 1942, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 12-12-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “The 
      Governor-General in Council” (w.e.f. 1-4-1937).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by A.L.O. 1950, for “Provincial 
      Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of 
      India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Ins. by Ord. 64 of 1942, sec. 
      8.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>