<act> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 19741
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Foreign Exchange Regulation Rules, 1974.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force at once.
 
 


</section></article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number> “Act” means the 
Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Schedule” means a 
Schedule appended to these rules.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Regulation Rules, 
1974
  
 <article><number>3</number> Service of direction, orders or notices made or 
issued under the Act, or these rules or under any order or notification made 
thereunder.—A direction, order or 
notice made or issued under the Act or these rules or any order or notification 
made thereunder shall be served on any person in the following manner, that is 
to say:—
 <section><number>a</number> by delivering or tendering 
it to that person or to his duly authorised agent; or
 </section><section><number>b</number> by sending it to him by 
registered post with acknowledgement due to the address of his place of 
residence or his last known place of residence or the place where he carries on, 
or last carried on, business, or personally works, or last worked, for gain; 
or
 </section><section><number>c</number> if it cannot be served in 
any of the manners aforesaid, by affixing it on the outer door or some other 
conspicuous part of the premises in which that person resides or is known to 
have last resided or carries on, or last carried on, business, or personally 
works, or last worked for gain and the written report whereof should be 
witnessed by two persons.</section></article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>4</number> Indication of import-export code 
number.—The import-export code 
number allotted by the Director General of Foreign Trade under section 7 of the 
Foreign Trade (Development and Regulation) Act, 1992 (22 of 1992) shall be 
indicated on all copies of the GR or PP or VP/COD forms completed and lodged by 
the exporter or his agent with the Customs or the Postal Authorities and in all 
correspondence of the exporter with its bank or the Reserve Bank, as the case 
may be.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Form of declarations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A declaration under section 18 of the Act shall be in one of the Forms set out 
in the Second Schedule and as specified therein according to the requirements of 
the case.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Declarations shall be executed in sets of 
such number as indicated on the forms.
</section></article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6</number> Authority to whom declaration 
to be furnished.—
<section><number>1</number> 
2[(a) in the case of specified customs 
offices, wherein the specified categories of Shipping Bills are processed 
electronically, the declaration Form SDF in respect of such Shipping Bills shall 
be submitted in duplicate to the Commissioner of Customs having jurisdiction 
over such specified customs offices. After duly verifying and authenticating the 
declaration Form SDF, the Commissioner of Customs shall hand over to the 
exporter one copy of such Shipping Bill marked as "Exchange Control Copy" in 
which declaration Form SDF had been appended for being submitted to the 
authorised dealer and order one copy of such Shipping Bill in which Form SDF had 
been appended to be kept in the records of the specified office.
 <subsection>
<number>aa</number> in the case of custom offices other than 
those specified custom offices, and in respect of Shipping Bills other than the 
specified categories of Shipping Bills the declaration Form GR shall be 
submitted in duplicate to the Commissioner of Customs. After duly verifying and 
authenticating the declaration form, the Commissioner of Customs shall forward 
the original declaration form to the nearest office of the Reserve Bank and hand 
over the duplicate form to the exporter for being submitted to the authorised 
dealer.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-rule, the expression—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  "specified custom 
office" means the office of the Commissioner of Customs specified by the 
Commissioner of Customs having jurisdiction to specify custom offices for the 
purpose of this sub-rule;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> "specified categories 
of Shipping Bills" means the categories of Shipping Bills processed 
electronically and specified by the Commissioner of Customs having jurisdiction 
to specify custom offices for the purpose of this sub-rule.]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The declaration Form PP shall be 
submitted in duplicate to the authorised dealer in foreign exchange named in the 
form. The authorised dealer shall, after countersigning the declaration form, 
hand over the original form to the exporter which shall be submitted to the 
postal authorities through which the goods are being despatched. The postal 
authorities, after despatch of the goods, shall forward the declaration form to 
the nearest office of the Reserve Bank.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> On realisation of the export proceeds, 
the authorised dealer shall, after due certification, submit the duplicate 
declaration form to the nearest office of the Reserve Bank.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> In the case of exports on value 
payable/cash on delivery basis, the declaration Form VP/COD shall be submitted 
to the postal authority with the relative parcel at the time of despatch. The 
postal authority shall send the form to the nearest office of the Reserve Bank.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The documents pertaining to export shall, 
within 21 days from the date of export, be submitted to the authorised dealer 
mentioned in the relevant declaration form, unless the Reserve Bank authorises 
otherwise.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Evidence in support of declaration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Reserve Bank or subject to such directions if any, as may be given by 
Reserve Bank, the 

1[Commissioner of Customs] or the 
postal authorities, may, to satisfy themselves of due compliance with section 18 
of the Act, require such evidence in support of the declaration as may satisfy 
them that the exporter is a person resident in India, and has a place of 
business in India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Reserve Bank, or subject to such 
directions, if any, as may be given by the Reserve Bank, the 

1[Commissioner of Customs], or the 
postal authorities may require any exporter to produce in support of the 
declaration such evidence as may be in his possession or power to satisfy them—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> that the destination 
stated on the declaration is the final place of destination of the goods 
exported;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> that the value stated 
in the declaration is—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the full export value of the goods;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    where the full export value of the 
goods is not ascertainable at the time of export the value which the exporter, 
having regard to the prevailing market conditions, expects to receive on the 
sale of the goods in the overseas market;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>          that the full 
export value of the goods (whether ascertainable at the time of export or not) 
has been or will within the prescribed period be paid in the prescribed manner.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule “final place of destination” means a place in a country 
in which the goods are ultimately imported and cleared through customs of that 
country.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8</number> Period within which export 
value of goods to be realised.—The amount representing the full export value 
of the goods exported shall be realised and be paid to the authorised dealer on 
the due date for payment or within six months from the date of shipment of the 
goods whichever is earlier:
 
Provided that, where the goods are exported 
to a warehouse established outside India with the permission of the Reserve 
Bank, the amount representing full export value of the goods exported shall be 
paid to the authorised dealer as soon as it is realised and in any case within 
fifteen months from the date of shipment of goods:
 
Provided further that the Reserve Bank may, 
for sufficient and reasonable cause shown, extend the said period.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Manner of payment of export value of 
goods.—Unless otherwise authorised 
by the Reserve Bank, the amount representing the full export value of goods 
exported to the countries specified in the Third Schedule shall be paid through 
an authorised dealer and in the manner specified in the said Schedule.
</article> 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 
 
The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 


 

1[***]
 
 


 
 The Foreign Exchange Regulation Rules, 
1974
  
 <article>1[<number>12</number> Application for permission to practise any 
profession or carry on any occupation, trade or business in India.—An 
application for permission under section 30 of the Act by a national of a 
foreign state to practise any profession or to carry on any occupation, trade or 
business in India shall be submitted in Form EFN specified in the Sixth 
Schedule.]
  


</article><form>
 


The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 


 
 


1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. First Schedule 
omitted by G.S.R. 503(E), dated 30th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-10-1996).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 


 
 



1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Fourth 
Schedule 
omitted by G.S.R. 
776(E), dated 27th December, 1993 (w.e.f. 27-12-1993).
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 


 
 



1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Fifth 
Schedule 
omitted by G.S.R. 
776(E), dated 27th December, 1993 (w.e.f. 27-12-1993).
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Foreign Exchange Regulation 
Rules, 1974
 


 
 



1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Seventh Schedule 
omitted by G.S.R. 
776(E), dated 27th December, 1993 (w.e.f. 27-12-1993).
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>