<act> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
    application commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Urban land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 
    1999. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It applies in the 
    first instance to the whole of the State of Haryana and Punjab and to all 
    the Union Territories; and it shall apply to such other State which adopts 
    this Act by resolution passed in that behalf under clause (2) of Article 252 
    of the Constitution. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be deemed 
    to have come into force in the States of Haryana and Punjab and in all the 
    Union territories on the 11th day of January, 1999 and in other State which 
    adopts this Act under clause (2) of Article 252 of the Constitution on the 
    date of such adoption; and the reference to repeal of the Urban Land 
    (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976 shall, in relation to any State or Union 
    Territory, mean the date on which this Act comes into force in such State or 
    Union Territory. 
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Repeal of Act 33 
    of 1976.—The Urban Land (Ceiling 
    and Regulation) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act) is 
    hereby repealed. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The repeal of the principal Act shall not affect—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the vesting of any vacant land under sub-section 
    (3) of Section 10, possession of which has been taken over the State 
    Government or any person duly authorised by the State Government in this 
    behalf or by the competent authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the validity of any order granting exemption 
    under sub-section (1) of Section 20 or any action taken thereunder, 
    notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the contrary;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any payment made to the State Government as a 
    condition for granting exemption under sub-section (1) of Section 20.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any land is deemed to have vested in the State 
    Government under sub-section (3) of Section 10 of the principal Act but 
    possession of which has not been taken over by the State Government or any 
    person duly authorised by the State Government in this behalf or by the 
    competent authority; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any amount has been paid by the State Government 
    with respect to such land  
     
 
then, such land shall not be restored unless the amount 
    paid, if any, has been refunded to the State Government.
  
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Abatement of 
    legal proceedings.—All 
    proceedings relating to any order made or purported to be made under the 
    principal Act pending immediately before the commencement of this Act, 
    before any court, tribunal or other authority shall abate: 
 
Provided that this 
    section shall not apply to the proceedings relating to sections 11, 12, 13 
    and 14 of the principal Act in so far as such proceedings are relatable to 
    the land, possession of which has been taken over by the State Government or 
    any person duly authorised by the State Government in this behalf or by the 
    competent authority.  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Repeal and 
    saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Urban Land 
    (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Ordinance, 1999 (Ord. 5 of 1999) is hereby 
    repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance 
    shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding 
    provisions of this Act.  

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>