<act><tid>1481639</tid>
<title>THE POLICE ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 64 OF <year>1949</year> 
[ 27th December, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to provide for the constitution of a general police- 
district embracing two or more <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Union territories] and for 
the 
establishment of a police force therefor.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a 
general police- district embracing two or more <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Union territories] 
and 
for the establishment of a police force therefor




<article><tid>861119</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1562852</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Police Act, <year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1055925</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to all the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Union territories].

</section>

<section><tid>1305167</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force in a <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Union territory] on such 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint in this behalf for <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> such territory].


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>266780</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act" general police- district" means the 
general police district constituted under section 3.

</article>



<article><tid>935809</tid>
<number>3</number>Constitution of general police- district embracing two or more 
Union territories. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Police 
Act, <year>1861</year> (5 of <year>1861</year>), the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, constitute a general police- district embracing 
two or more <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Union territories].

</article>



<article><tid>370696</tid>
<number>4</number>Constitution of one police force for general police- district. 
The entire police establishment in a general police- district shall be 
one police force and shall consist of such number of officers and men 
and shall be constituted in such manner as the Central Government may, 
by order, direct.

</article>



<article><tid>955826</tid>
<number> 5</number> Superintendence and administration of police.
<section><tid>279396</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
superintendence of the police throughout a general police- district 
shall vest in, and be exercised by, the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1965823</tid>
<number>2</number>The administration of the said police force shall vest in an 
officer, appointed in this behalf by the Central Government, who shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Chief 
Commissioners' Provinces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Part C States

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" Part C State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" such State".

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

exercise in respect of that police force such of the powers 
exercisable by an Inspector- General of Police under the Police Act, 
 <year>1861</year> (5 of <year>1961</year>), as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>993469</tid>
<number>6</number>Application of the Police Act, <year>1861</year>. Save as otherwise 
expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of the Police Act, 
 <year>1861</year> (5 of <year>1861</year>), shall apply to the police force constituted for the 
general police- district as if it were one police force constituted for 
a State, and members of the said police force shall have, in every 
part of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any territory] which is included in the general police- 
district, the same powers, duties and privileges, and shall be subject 
to the same liabilities, as they would have had, or would have been 
subject, to, as police officers if they had formed a police 
establishment under one State Government.

</article>



<article><tid>1493636</tid>
<number>7</number>Saving. Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the 
provisions contained in the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 
 <year>1946</year> (25 of <year>1946</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" any 
State".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>