<act><tid>367980</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN COUNCIL OF WORLD AFFAIRS ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 29 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 3rd September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act to declare the Indian Council of World Affairs to be an 
institution of national importance and to provide for its 
incorporation and matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>745165</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1963682</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Council of World Affairs Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1383553</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, it shall be deemed to have 
come into force on the 1st day of September, <year>2000</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>577595</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of the Indian Council of World Affairs as institution 
of national importance.- Whereas the objects of the Indian Council of 
World Affairs, a society registered under the Societies Registration 
Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>) are such as to make the nstitution one of 
national importance, it is hereby declared that the institution, known 
as the Indian Council of World Affairs, is an institution of national 
importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1973160</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>390013</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1240530</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Governing Body;

</section>

<section><tid>441073</tid>
<number>c</number>" Council" means the Indian Council of World Affairs incorporated 
under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>395692</tid>
<number>d</number>" Director- General" means the Director- General of the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>548262</tid>
<number>e</number>" existing Council" means the Indian Council of World Affairs, a 
society registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of  
  <year>1860</year>) and functioning as such immediately before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>593186</tid>
<number>f</number>" Fund" means the Fund of the Council referred to in section 18;

</section>

<section><tid>327966</tid>
<number>g</number>" Governing Body" means the Governing Body of the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>389731</tid>
<number>h</number>" member" means a member of the Council and includes the President 
and Vice- President;

</section>

<section><tid>794736</tid>
<number>i</number>" President" means the President of the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>181821</tid>
<number>j</number>" regulations" means the regulations made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>724779</tid>
<number>k</number>" rules" means the rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>344147</tid>
<number>l</number>" Vice- Presidents" means the Vice- Presidents of the Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1178370</tid>
<number> 4</number> Incorporation of the Council.-
<section><tid>1579545</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Council of World  
Affairs is hereby constituted as a body corporate by the name of the 
Indian Council of World Affairs and as such body corporate it shall 
have perpetual succession and a common seal with ower, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both 
movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by that name sue and 
be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>185703</tid>
<number>2</number>The head office of the Council shall be at Delhi and the Council 
may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, establish 
branches at other places in India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702179</tid>
<number> 5</number> Transfer of assets and liabilities of the existing Council to the 
Council.-
<section><tid>223701</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day,- 

<subsection><tid>546563</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties and other assets vested in the existing Council 
immediately before that day, shall vest in the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>103792</tid>
<number>b</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts 
entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or 
for the existing Council immediately before that day for or in 
connection with the purposes of the existing Council, shall be deemed 
to have been incurred, entered into and engaged to be done by, with or 
for the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>890450</tid>
<number>c</number>all sums of money due to the existing Council, immediately before 
that day, shall be deemed to be due to the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>109824</tid>
<number>d</number>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or which could 
have been instituted by or against the existing Council, immediately 
before that day, may be continued or instituted by or against the 
Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1690490</tid>
<number>e</number>every employee holding any office under the existing Council 
immediately before that day, shall, on that day, hold his office or 
service under the Council with the same rights and privileges as to 
pension, gratuity and other matters as would have bee admissible to 
him if there had been no such vesting; and shall continue to do so 
unless and until his employment under the Council is duly terminated 
or until his remuneration and other conditions of service are duly 
altered by the Council.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>182801</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
absorption of any employee by the Council in its regular service under 
this section shall not entitle such emplo ee to any compensation under 
that Act or any other law and no such claim shall be entertained by 
any court, tribunal or other authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>441734</tid>
<number> 6</number> Obligation to transfer property or assets.-
<section><tid>904402</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person having  
possession, custody or control of property forming part of the 
properties and other assets referred to in clause (a) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 5 shall deliver forthwith such proper y to the 
Director- General.

</section>

<section><tid>1406712</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person incharge of the property and other assets of the 
existing Council immediately before the commencement of this Act 
shall, within ten days from that day, furnish to the Director- General 
a complete inventory of all properties and assets (incl ding  
  particulars of book debts and investments and belongings) immediately 
before the commencement of this Act and also of all agreements entered 
into by the existing Council or any person on its behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1181153</tid>
<number> 7</number> Composition of the Council.-
<section><tid>1668233</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the 1st day of  
September, <year>2001</year> and until the appointment of date under sub- section 
 (2), the Council shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1028700</tid>
<number>a</number>the Vice- President of India, who shall be President, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1030032</tid>
<number>b</number>the Prime Minister of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>663068</tid>
<number>c</number>the speaker of the Lok Sabha;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>464978</tid>
<number>d</number>the Leader of the House, Rajya Sabha;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682461</tid>
<number>e</number>the Leader of the Opposition, Lok Sabha;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1966136</tid>
<number>f</number>the Leader of the Opposition, Rajya Sabha.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1691806</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from such date as may be appointed by the Central 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette which shall not be 
later than three months from the date of assent by the President of 
the Indian Council of World Affairs Bill, <year>2001</year>, the Cou cil shall 
consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1855311</tid>
<number>a</number>the Vice- President of India, who shall be the President, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1369512</tid>
<number>b</number>three Vice- Presidents as may be nominated by the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1544523</tid>
<number>c</number>a Director- General to be nominated by the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1250352</tid>
<number>d</number>five members of the Lok Sabha to be nominated by the Speaker of 
the Lok Sabha and three members of the Rajya Sabha to be nominated by 
the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1315664</tid>
<number>e</number>seven members, who are distinguished in the field of diplomacy, 
international affairs, international law, Multilateral or United 
Nations affairs, security and disarmament to be nominated by the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1108256</tid>
<number>f</number>seven members, who are representatives (of which at least two  
  shall be the Vice- Chancellors) of Universities or research 
institutions of higher learning from amongst experts in the fields of 
history, economics and other social sciences to be nominate by the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003516</tid>
<number>g</number>seven members, who are either media personalities or 
representatives of organisations such as India International Centre, 
Centre for Policy Research, Indian Council of Social Science Research, 
Institute of Defence Studies and Analyses, Indian Council of Cultural 
Relations, and interested in the work and objectives of the Council to 
be selected by the Governing Body of the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1441959</tid>
<number>h</number>five members who are representatives of Business or Chambers of 
Commerce, Federation of Indian Chambers of Commerce and Industry, 
Confederation of Indian Industry, Associated Chambers of Commerce and 
Industry of India, Federation of Indian Export Or anisations to be 
nominated by the Governing Body of the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>4117</tid>
<number>i</number>three members from the Ministry of External Affairs, ex officio[ 
Foreign Secretary, Financial Advisor, and Dean (Foreign Service  
  Institute)], to be nominated by the Chairperson of the Governing Body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177824</tid>
<number>j</number>five members to be nominated by the Central Government to 
represent respectively the Ministries of the Central Government 
dealing with Education, Culture, Urban Development, Science and 
Technology and Defence, ex officio.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1809811</tid>
<number>3</number>It is hereby declared that the office of the member of the Council 
shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a 
Member of either House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1853595</tid>
<number>4</number>A person shall be disqualified for being nominated or selected as 
a member if he-

<subsection><tid>1358522</tid>
<number>a</number>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence 
which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
turpitude; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1756162</tid>
<number>b</number>is an undischarged insolvent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1448153</tid>
<number>c</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>674554</tid>
<number> 8</number> Term of office and vacancies among members.-
<section><tid>1128338</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise  
provided in this section, the term of office of a member shall be 
three years from the date of his nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>1852391</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the member nominated to fill a casual 
vacancy shall continue for remainder of the term of the member in 
whose place he is nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>1441044</tid>
<number>3</number>A member shall, unless the Central Government otherwise directs, 
continue in office until another person is nominated as a member in 
his place.

</section>

<section><tid>1301386</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall remove a member if he-

<subsection><tid>1742427</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in 
sub- section (4) of section 7; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>675468</tid>
<number>b</number>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1942117</tid>
<number>c</number>is, without obtaining leave of absence from the Council, absent 
from three consecutive meetings of the Council; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>980658</tid>
<number>d</number>in the opinion of the Central Government, has so abused his 
position as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the 
public interest:
Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he 
has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1618667</tid>
<number>5</number>A member shall, unless disqualified under sub- section (4) of 
section 7, be eligible for re- nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>41062</tid>
<number>6</number>A member may resign from his office by writing under his hand 
addressed to the Central Government but shall continue in his office 
until his resignation is accepted by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1695839</tid>
<number>7</number>The manner of filling vacancies among members shall be such as may 
be prescribed by rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1112877</tid>
<number>9</number>Powers and functions of President.- The President shall exercise 
such powers and discharge such functions as are laid down in this Act 
or as may be prescribed by rules.


</article>



<article><tid>1697579</tid>
<number>10</number>Powers and functions of Vice- Presidents.- The Vice- Presidents 
shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the functions of 
the President as may be prescribed by rules or as may be delegated to 
him by the President.


</article>



<article><tid>1092603</tid>
<number>11</number>Allowances of members.- Members shall receive such allowances, if 
any, from the Council as may be prescribed by rules.


</article>



<article><tid>526910</tid>
<number>12</number>Meetings of Council.- The Council shall hold its first meeting at 
such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Government and 
shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
business at the first meeting as may be laid own by that Government; 
and thereafter the Council shall meet at such times and places and 
observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
business at its meetings as may be prescribed by regulations.


</article>



<article><tid>1736817</tid>
<number> 13</number> Objects of Council.- The objects of the Council shall be-
<section><tid>1021320</tid>
<number>a</number>to promote the study of Indian and international affairs so as to 
develop a body of informed opinion on international matters;

</section>

<section><tid>751265</tid>
<number>b</number>to promote India' s relations with other countries through study, 
research, discussion, lectures, exchange of ideas and information with 
other organisations within and outside India engaged in similar 
activities;

</section>

<section><tid>1902798</tid>
<number>c</number>to serve as a clearing house of information and knowledge 
regarding world affairs;

</section>

<section><tid>1274725</tid>
<number>d</number>to publish books, periodicals, journals, reviews, papers, 
pamphlets and other literature on subjects covered under clauses (a) 
and (b);

</section>

<section><tid>602510</tid>
<number>e</number>to establish contacts with organisations promoting objects 
mentioned in this section;

</section>

<section><tid>1900107</tid>
<number>f</number>to arrange conferences and seminars to discuss and study the 
Indian policy towards international affairs; and

</section>

<section><tid>1411645</tid>
<number>g</number>to undertake such other activities for the promotion of ideas and 
attainment of the above- mentioned objects.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>50110</tid>
<number> 14</number> Governing Body and other committees of Council.-
<section><tid>415802</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall  
be a Governing Body of the Council which shall be constituted by the 
Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1047103</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governing Body shall be the executive committee of the Council 
and shall exercise such powers and discharge such functions as the 
Council may, by regulations made in this behalf, confer or impose upon 
it.

</section>

<section><tid>171868</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from such date as may be appointed by the Central 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette, the Vice- President 
of India, ex officio shall be the Chairperson of the Governing Body 
and shall exercise such powers and discharge such func ions as may be 
prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1752717</tid>
<number>4</number>The procedure to be followed by the Governing Body in the exercise 
of its powers and discharge of its functions and the term of office 
of, and the manner of filling vacancies among the members of the 
Governing Body, shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1491240</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be prescribed by 
rules, the Council may constitute as many standing committees and as 
many ad hoc committees as it thinks fit for exercising any power or 
discharging any function of the Council or for i quiring into, or 
reporting or advising upon, any matter which the Council may refer to 
them.

</section>

<section><tid>1597006</tid>
<number>6</number>The Chairperson and members of the Governing Body or a standing 
committee or an ad hoc committee shall receive such allowances as may 
be prescribed by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1032030</tid>
<number> 15</number> Staff of Council.-
<section><tid>1220258</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a chief executive officer of  
the Council who shall be designated as the Director- General and shall 
be appointed by the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1228423</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director- General shall act as the Secretary to the Council as 
well as to the Governing Body.

</section>

<section><tid>1198241</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director- General shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
functions as may be prescribed by regulations or as may be delegated 
to him by the Council or the President or the Governing Body or the 
Chairperson.

</section>

<section><tid>1800372</tid>
<number>4</number>The Financial Advisor of the Ministry of External Affairs shall be 
the Financial Advisor of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1004794</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the Council 
may appoint such number of other officers and employees as may be 
necessary for the exercise of its powers and efficient discharge of 
its functions and may determine the designations an grades of such 
other officers and employees.

</section>

<section><tid>1408107</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the 
Director- General and other officers and employees of the Council shall 
be entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be governed by 
such conditions of service in respect of leave, pension gratuity, 
provident fund and other matters, as may be prescribed by regulations 
made in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1047554</tid>
<number>16</number>Functions of Council.- The Council shall undertake various plans 
to promote, organise and implement various programmes for efficiently 
achieving the objects of the Council specified in section 13 and shall 
also perform such other functions as the Cent al Government may, by 
rules, prescribe.


</article>



<article><tid>1824599</tid>
<number>17</number>Payment to Council.- The Central Government may, after due 
appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the 
Council in each financial year such sums as may be considered 
necessary for the exercise of powers and efficient discharge of 
functions of the Council under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1801892</tid>
<number> 18</number> Fund of Council.-
<section><tid>549710</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall maintain a Fund to which  
shall be credited to-

<subsection><tid>991339</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys received from the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1157268</tid>
<number>b</number>all moneys received by the Council by way of grants, gifts, 
donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>4283</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys received by the Council in any other manner or from any 
other source.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>546191</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such banks 
or invested in such manner as the Council may, subject to the approval 
of the Central Government, decide.

</section>

<section><tid>156568</tid>
<number>3</number>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the administrative and 
other expenses of the Council, including expenses incurred in the 
exercise of its powers and discharge of its functions under section 16 
or in relation to any of the activities referred to therein or for 
anything relatable thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1011295</tid>
<number>19</number>Budget of Council.- The Council shall prepare, in such form and at 
such time every year, as may be prescribed by rules, a budget in 
respect of the financial year next ensuing, showing the estimated 
receipts and expenditure of the Council and shall for ard to the 
Central Government such number of copies thereof as may be prescribed 
by rules.


</article>



<article><tid>491187</tid>
<number> 20</number> Accounts and audit.-
<section><tid>1950854</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as the Central 
Government may, by rules, prescribe and in accordance wi h such 
general directions as may be issued by that Government, in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1073740</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Council shall be audited by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in 
connection with such audit shall be payable by the Council to the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>856411</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Council shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor General of 
India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and, 
in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect the office or offices of t e Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1479914</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Council as certified by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this 
behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded 
annually to the Central Government and that Gover ment shall cause the 
same to be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1480570</tid>
<number>21</number>Annual report.- The Council shall prepare every year, in such form 
and at such time as may be prescribed by rules, an annual report 
giving a true and full account of its activities during the previous 
year and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the entral Government 
and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House 
of Parliament.


</article>



<article><tid>635300</tid>
<number>22</number>Authentication of orders and instruments of Council.- All orders 
and decisions of the Council shall be authenticated by the signature 
of the President or the Vice- President and all other instruments 
issued by the Council shall be authenticated by the ignature of the 
Director- General or any other officer of the Council authorised by the 
Council in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>148194</tid>
<number> 23</number> Vacancy, etc. not to invalidate proceedings of the Council.- No 
act or proceeding of the Council, Governing Body or any standing or ad 
hoc committee under this Act shall be invalid merely by reason of-
<section><tid>536411</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Council; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1705906</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of 
the Council; or

</section>

<section><tid>1088829</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Council not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>914397</tid>
<number>24</number>Reports, returns and information.- The Council shall furnish to 
the Central Government such reports, returns and other information as 
that Government may require from time to time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to make rules.

</article>



<article><tid>755734</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1812644</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1771721</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1557940</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of filling vacancies among members under sub- section 
 (7) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>403236</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the 
President and the Vice- Presidents under sections 9 and 10, as the case 
may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>227449</tid>
<number>c</number>the allowances to be paid to the members under section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>939761</tid>
<number>d</number>the control and restrictions in relation to the constitution of 
standing and ad hoc committees under sub- section (5) of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>618253</tid>
<number>e</number>the number of other officers and employees that may be appointed 
by the Council and the manner of such appointment under sub- section 
 (5) of section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1217037</tid>
<number>f</number>the salaries and allowances payable to the Director- General and 
other officers and employees of the Council under sub- section (6) of 
section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1487610</tid>
<number>g</number>such other functions to be performed by the Council under section 
16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>119781</tid>
<number>h</number>the form in which and the time at which the budget shall be 
prepared by the Council and the number of copies thereof to be 
forwarded to the Central Government under section 19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>481980</tid>
<number>i</number>the form in which an annual statement of accounts including the 
balance- sheet shall be prepared by the Council under sub- section (1) 
of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1223308</tid>
<number>j</number>the form in which and the time at which the annual report of the 
activities of the Council shall be submitted to the Central Government 
under section 21;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>100199</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed by rules.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1180619</tid>
<number> 26</number> Power to make regulations.-
<section><tid>574781</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council may make regulations  
consistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules to carry out 
the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>656277</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1376262</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and holding of meetings, other than the first 
meeting of the Council, the time and place where such meetings are to 
be held and the transaction of business at such meetings under section 
12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1468879</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the 
Governing Body and the Chairperson under sub- sections (2) and (3) of 
section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1879927</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure to be followed by the Governing Body in exercise of 
its powers and discharge of its functions and the term of office of, 
and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of the 
Governing Body under sub- section (4) of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754156</tid>
<number>d</number>the allowances to be paid to the Chairperson and members of the 
Governing Body, standing and ad hoc committees under sub- section (6) 
of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1133703</tid>
<number>e</number>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the 
Director- General under sub- section (3) of section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1849284</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of the Director- General and other 
officers and employees of the Council under sub- section (6) of section 
15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>836116</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed by 
regulations.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>479200</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the first 
regulations under this Act shall be made by the Governing Body and any 
regulations so made may be altered or rescinded by the Council in 
exercise of its powers under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1418072</tid>
<number>27</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule 
and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days wh ch may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulat on or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be w thout prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.


</article>



<article><tid>912262</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1852547</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act s may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of two years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>283793</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>926837</tid>
<number> 29</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>631195</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Council of World Affairs  
 (Second) Ordinance, <year>2001</year> (Ord. 3 of <year>2001</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1493320</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance, anything done or 
any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>