<act> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 20061
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises Rules, 2006.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 2nd day of October, 2006.
  


</section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises Development Act, 2006 (27 of 2006);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  “Advisory Committee” means the committee 
constituted by the Central Government under sub-section (2) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  “Board” means the National Board for Micro, 
Small and Medium Enterprises established under sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the 
Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  “member” means a member of the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  “Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson of 
the Board.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used 
and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Term of office of members.—Save 
as otherwise hereinafter provided,—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  a member, other than an ex officio 
member, shall hold office for a period not exceeding two years from the date of 
his appointment;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  a member elected under clause (d) of 
sub-section (3) of section 3 shall cease to be a member of the Board if he 
ceases to be a member of the House of Parliament by which he was so elected; and
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  a member appointed under clauses (k), (l), (m) 
and (n) of sub-section (3) of section 3 shall cease to be a member of the Board 
if he ceases to represent the category or interest from which he was so 
appointed:
 Provided that a member shall be 
eligible for re-appointment.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>4</number> Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The office of a member, other than an ex officio member, shall fall 
vacant from the date on which his resignation is accepted or on the expiry of 
thirty days from the date of receipt of intimation of resignation, whichever is 
earlier.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The power to accept the 
resignation of a member shall vest in the Chairperson who, on accepting the 
resignation, shall report to the Board at its next meeting.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>5</number> Change of address.—If 
a member changes his address, he shall notify his new address to the 
Member-Secretary of the Board who shall thereupon enter his new address in the 
official records:
 Provided that if a member fails 
to notify his new address, the address in the official records shall for all 
purposes be deemed to be the member’s correct address.
</article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>6</number> Manner of filling 
vacancies among members.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may evolve such criteria and hold such consultations as it 
may think fit, before appointing members from among the representatives 
specified in clauses (l), (m) and (n) of sub-section (3) of section 3, each time 
the Board is constituted.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a member dies or 
resigns or is deemed to have resigned or is removed from office or becomes 
incapable of acting, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint a person to fill that vacancy:
 Provided that where the vacancy 
occurs in a membership which was held by an outgoing member by virtue of his 
membership in the Parliament under clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 3, 
the appointment of the next incumbent of that vacancy shall be on the basis of a 
fresh election by that House of Parliament to which the outgoing member 
belonged.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>7</number> Procedure to be followed 
in the discharge of their function by the members of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Agenda.—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  The agenda to be considered at a meeting of the 
Board shall be approved by the Chairperson and shall ordinarily be issued by the 
Member-Secretary fourteen days before the approved day of the meeting and shall 
be left at, or posted to the address of every member of the Board.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  The Board may take up any item outside the 
agenda with the permission of the Chairperson.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall meet at 
least once in every three months at Delhi:
 Provided that if it is deemed 
necessary and expedient to hold a meeting of the Board outside its headquarters 
at Delhi, the reasons for holding such meeting shall be recorded in writing with 
prior approval of the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson may at any 
time call a special meeting of the Board in case of urgency, after informing the 
members in advance about the subject-matter of discussion and the reasons of 
urgency.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chairperson or, in his 
absence, the Vice-Chairperson, shall preside over the meetings of the Board.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The quorum for any meeting 
of the Board shall be twelve.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government may 
debar any member, other than ex officio members, from taking part in the 
meetings of the Board if—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  he absents himself from two consecutive meetings 
of the Board without written information to and consent of the Chairperson and, 
in any case, from three consecutive meetings, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in the view of the Central Government, the act 
of a member is or is likely to be detrimental to the policies and programmes of 
the Government for promotion, development and enhancing competitiveness of 
micro, small and medium enterprises.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises 
Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>8</number> Powers and functions of 
Member-Secretary of the Board.—The 
Member-Secretary shall—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  act as the Head of the office of the Board;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  sanction necessary expenditure on 
contingencies, supplies, services and articles required for the working of the 
Board and its office, execution of the functions assigned to the Board and 
furtherance of the objects of the Act, subject to provisions being made in the 
annual budget for this purpose;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  maintain or cause to be maintained an account 
of the receipts and expenditures of the Board in such form as may be notified by 
the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
of India;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  assist the Chairperson in all administrative 
matters relating to the Board;
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  keep or cause to be kept a record of names of 
members and their addresses;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>  make arrangements for the meetings of the 
Board; and
 </section><section>      <number>vii</number>  issue minutes of the meetings of the Board, as 
approved by the Chairperson.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>