<act><title>


The Bureau of energy efficiency (Appointment 
    of Secretary) Rules, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Bureau of Energy Efficiency (Appointment of 
    Secretary) Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Number of 
    post, classification and scale of pay.—The 
    number of post, its classification and the scale of pay attached thereto 
    shall be as specified in columns 2 to 4 of the Schedule annexed to these 
    rules.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Method of 
    recruitment, age limit, qualifications, etc.—The 
    method of recruitment to the said post, age limit, qualifications and other 
    matters relating thereto shall be as specified in columns 5 to 14 of the 
    said Schedule aforesaid.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Disqualification.—No person,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    who has entered into or contracted a 
    marriage with a person having a spouse living; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    who, having a spouse living, has 
    entered into or contracted a marriage with any person,  
 
shall be eligible for appointment to the said 
    post:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, if satisfied that such marriage is permissible 
    under the personal law applicable to such person and the other party to the 
    marriage and that there are other grounds for so doing, exempt any person 
    from  the operation of this rule.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    The conditions of service for which the provisions have not been made in 
    these rules, including entitlement of leave salary, leave travel concession, 
    travelling allowances, medical facilities, shall be such as are admissible 
    to a Group ‘A’ officer of the corresponding status in the Central 
    Government.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to 
    relax.—Where the Central 
    Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it 
    may, by order, for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax any of the 
    provisions of these rules with respect to any class or category of persons.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Savings.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall affect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other 
    concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled 
    Tribes and other special categories of persons in accordance with the orders 
    issued by the Central Government from time to time in this regard.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>