<act><tid>722532</tid>
<title>THE PENSIONS' ACT, <year>1871</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1871</year>
[ 8th August, <year>1871</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Pensions 
and 
Grants by Government of money or land- revenue.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend 
the 
law relating to pensions and grants by Government of money or land- 
revenue; it is hereby enacted as follows:-

I.- PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1913461</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the' Pensions' Act, <year>1871</year>.
Extent of Act.- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In so far as it relates to Union pensions, it 
extends to the whole of India and in so far as it relates to other 
pensions, it extends] to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the whole of India except <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States]].

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1095871</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Enactments repealed. Saving of Rules] Rep. by the Repealing 
Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>1489093</tid>
<number>3</number>Interpretation- section.- In this Act, the expression" grant 
of money or land- revenue" includes anything payable on the part of 
Government in respect of any right, privilege, perquisite or office.
</article>



<article><tid>1093499</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Definition.- The expression" the appropriate Government" 
means, in relation to <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Union] pensions, the Central Government, and 
in relation to other pensions, the State Government.]
II.- RIGHTS TO PENSIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1300504</tid>
<number>4</number>Bar of suits relating to pensions.- Except as hereinafter 
provided no Civil Court shall entertain any suit relating to any 
pension or grant of money or land- revenue conferred or made by the 
[ Government or by] any former Government, whatever may have been the 
consideration for any such pension or grant and whatever may have 
been the nature of the payment, claim or right for which such pension 
or grant may have been substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>106928</tid>
<number>5</number>Claims to be made to collector or other authorized officer.- 
Any person having a claim relating to any such pension or grant may 
prefer such claim to the Collector of the District or Deputy 
Commissioner or other officer authorized in this behalf by the 
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> appropriate Government] and such Collector, Deputy Commissioner or 
other officer shall dispose of such claim in accordance with such 
rules as the Chief Revenue authority may, subject to the general 
control of the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> appropriate Government], from time to time prescribe 
in this behalf.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>It has been ended in its application to U. P. by U. P. Act 12 of 
<year>1922</year>. Rep. in part in West Bengal by West Bengal Act 7 of <year>1948</year>.

The Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 1 (w. e. f. 1- 7- 1265) and 
extended to the whole of the Union Territory of Lakshadweep by Reg. 8 
of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).

The Act has been repealed in its application to Bellary District 
by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2, for" it extends".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. for" all the Provinces of India" which had 
been subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" the whole of British India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" And it shall come into force on the date of the 
passing thereof" rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3. and Sch. 11.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words" but not so as to affect any suit in respect of a 
pension or grant of money or land- revenue which may have men 
instituted before such date" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>, S. 2 and Sch. 1.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Sub. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. for" federal'.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, as amended by C. O. 29, for" British or".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>10</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 (II.- Rights to Pensions. III. Mode of Payment. IV.- Miscellaneous)



</article>



<article><tid>9524</tid>
<number>6</number>Civil Court empowered to take cognizance of such claims.- A 
Civil Court, otherwise competent to try the same, shall take 
cognizance of any such claim upon receiving a certificate from such 
Collector, Deputy Commissioner or other officer authorized in that 
behalf that the case may be so tried, but shall not make any order or 
decree in any suit whatever by which the liability of Government to 
pay any such pension or grant as aforesaid is affected directly or 
indirectly.


</article>



<article><tid>412406</tid>
<number> 7</number> Pensions for lands held under grants in perpetuity.- Nothing 
in sections 4 and 6 applies to-
<section><tid>250867</tid>
<number>1</number>any inam of the class referred to in section 1 of Madras Act 
No. IV of 18621;

</section>

<section><tid>1787058</tid>
<number>2</number>pensions heretofore granted by Government in the territories 
respectively subject to the Lieutenant- Governors of Bengal and the 
North- Western Provinces, either wholly or in part as an indemnity for 
loss sustained by the resumption by a Native Government of lands held 
under sanads purporting to confer a right in perpetuity. Such 
pensions shall not be liable to resumption on the death of the 
recipient, but every such pension shall be capable of alienation and 
descent, and may be sued for and recovered in the same manner as any 
other property.
III.- MODE OF PAYMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1574808</tid>
<number>8</number>Payment to be made by Collector or other authorized 
officer.- All pensions or grants by Government of money or land- revenue 
shall be paid by the Collector or the Deputy Commissioner or other 
authorized officer, subject to such rules as may, from time to time, 
be prescribed by the Chief Controlling Revenue- authority.


</article>



<article><tid>978161</tid>
<number>9</number>Saving of rights of grantees of land- revenue.- Nothing in 
sections 4 and 8 shall affect the right of a grantee of land- revenue, 
whose claim to such grant is admitted by Government, to recover such 
revenue from the persons liable to pay the same under any law for the 
time being in force for the recovery of the rent of land.


</article>



<article><tid>1401088</tid>
<number>10</number>Commutation of pensions.- The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, 
with the consent of the holder, order the whole or any part of his 
pension or grant of money or land- revenue to be commuted for a lump 
sum on such terms as may seem fit.
IV.- MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>486329</tid>
<number>11</number>Exemption of pension from attachment.- No pension granted or 
continued by Government on political considerations, or on account of 
past services or present infirmities or as a compassionate allowance,
and no money due or to become due on account of any such pension 
or allowance,

shall be liable to seizure, attachment or sequestration by 
process of any Court at the instance of a creditor, for any demand 
against the pensioner, or in satisfaction of a decree or order of any 
such Court.

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> This section applies <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> also to pensions granted or continued", 
after the separation of Burma from India, by the Government of Burma.]



</article>



<article><tid>1397062</tid>
<number>12</number>Assignments, etc., in anticipation of pension, to be void. 
All assignments, agreements' orders, sales, and securities of every 
kind made by the person entitled to any pension, Pay or allowance 
mentioned in section 11, in respect of any money not payable at or 
before the making thereof, on account of any such pension, Pay or 
allowance, or for giving or assigning any future interest therein, are 
null and void.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>I. e.," inams of the classes described in cl. 1, s. 2,[ Mad.] 
Regulation 4 of <year>1831</year>, which have been, or shall be, enfranchised by 
the Inam Commissioner and converted into freeholds in perpetuity, or 
into absolute freeholds in perpetuity". The classes so described are 
" hereditary or personal grants of money or of land- revenue, however, 
denominated, conferred by the authority of the Governor in Council[ or 
which, having been made by any Native Govt. have been confirmed or 
continued by the British Govt.- Act 31 of <year>1836</year>] in consideration of 
services rendered to the State or in lieu of resumed offices or 
privileges, or of zamindars or paleiyams forfeited or held under 
attachment or management by the officers of Govt., or as a yaumia or 
charitable allowance, or as a pension".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for' L. G."

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>See also s. 60, cl (g) of the Code of Civil Procedure <year>1908</year> (Act 5  
  of <year>1908</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" in Part A States and Part C States" omitted by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>. The words" Part A States and 
Part C States" were subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces" which 
had been subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" British India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>I. e., on or after the 1st April, <year>1937</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 (IV.- Miscellaneous.)

</article>



<article><tid>162676</tid>
<number> 12A</number> Nomination by Pensioner to receive moneys outstanding on 
account of pension.-.-. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 
 12 or in any other law for the time being in force,-
<section><tid>139748</tid>
<number>a</number>any person to whom any pension mentioned in 
section 11 is payable by the Government of India or out of 
the Consolidated Fund of India (such person being hereinafter  
  referred to as the pensioner) may nominate any other person 
 (hereinafter referred to as the nominee), in such manner and 
in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government 
by rules, to receive after the death of the pensioner, all 
moneys payable to the pensioner on account of such pension 
at, before or after the date of such nomination and which 
remain unpaid immediately before the death of the pensioner; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>176826</tid>
<number>b</number>the nominee shall be entitled, on the death of the 
pensioner, to receive, to the exclusion of all other persons, 
all such moneys which have so remained unpaid:
provided that if the nominee predeceases the pensioner, the 
nomination shall, so far as it relates to the right conferred upon the 
said nominee, become void and of no effect:

provided further that where provision has been duly made in the 
nomination, in accordance with the rules made by the Central 
Government, conferring upon some other person the right to receive all 
such moneys, which have so remained unpaid, in the event of the 
nominee predeceasing the pensioner, such right shall, upon the decease 
as aforesaid of the nominee, pass to such other person.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1510087</tid>
<number>13</number>Reward to informers.- Whoever proves to the satisfaction of 
the. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government] that any pension is fraudulently or 
unduly received by the person enjoying the benefit thereof shall be 
entitled to a reward equivalent to the amount of such pension for the 
period of six months.


</article>



<article><tid>1981266</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules.-"[ In each State] the Chief Controlling 
Revenue Authority may, with the consent of the[ appropriate 
Government], from time to time make rules consistent with this Act 
respecting all or any of the following matters:-
<section><tid>758926</tid>
<number>1</number>the place and times at which, and the person to whom, any 
pension shall be paid; 
 (2) inquiries into the identity of claimants; 
 (3) records to be kept on the subject of pensions; 
 (4) transmission of such records; 
 (5) correction of such records; 
 (6) delivery of certificates to pensioners; 
 (7) registers of such certificates; 
 (8) reference to the Civil Court, under section 6, of persons 
claiming a right of succession to, or participation in, pensions or 
grants of money or land- revenue payable by Government;
and generally for the guidance of officers under this Act.

All such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette, and shall 
thereupon have the force of law.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>424478</tid>
<number> 15</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Power of Central Government to make rules.- The Central 
Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules to 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1900408</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner and form in which any nomination may be made 
under section 12A and the manner and form in which such nomination may 
be cancelled or varied by another nomination;

</section>

<section><tid>1926445</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which provision may be made, for the purposes 
of the second proviso to section 12A, in any such nomination for 
conferring on some person other than the nominee the right to receive 
moneys payable to the nominee if such nominee predeceases the 
pensioner,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ibs. by Act 20 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs, by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G". 
3. Ins., ibid. 
4. Subs. ibid., for" L. G.". 
5. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 (IV- Miscellaneos. Schedule)


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1156041</tid>
<number>16</number>Laying of rules.- Every rule made by the Central Government 
under this Act and every rule made under section 14 by a Chief 
Controlling Revenue Authority with the consent of the Central 
Government, shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]
[ SCHEDULE.] Rep. by the repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.

-----------------


</article>



 </act>