<act><title>

The Foreign 
    Marriage Rules, 19701</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Foreign Marriage Rules, 1970.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Foreign Marriage Act, 
    1969 (33 of 1969); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “form” means a form appended to these 
    rules; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Marriage Officer” means a person 
    appointed under section 3 of the Act to be a Marriage Officer; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “section” means a section of the Act. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Particulars regarding name, etc., of Marriage Officer to be displayed 
    in his office building.—Every 
    Marriage Officer shall arrange to have his name, designation and the working 
    hours of his officer to be written in English, Hindi and the language of the 
    country, place or area in which he functions as such, and displayed in a 
    conspicuous part of the building in which his office is situated. 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Notice of intended marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a marriage is intended to be solemnized under the Act by or before a 
    Marriage Officer, the parties to the intended marriage shall give notice 
    thereof in writing in the form specified in the First Schedule to the Act to 
    such Officer either in person or by registered post. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    notices shall be accompanied by a statement containing the following 
    particulars,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Present addresses of the parents of the 
    parties to the in­tended marriage; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Name or names of the country or 
    countries in which the parties are ordinarily resident; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    State or States in India to which the 
    parties or, as the case may be, the Indian party, to the marriage belong or 
    belongs. 
 
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Payment of fee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the notice is delivered in person, the fee prescribed therefore in 
    rule 15 shall be paid in cash to the Marriage Officer. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the notice is sent by registered post, the fee shall be remitted by 
    money order at the remitter’s expense and the receipt issued to the remitter 
    by the post office through which the remittance is made shall be attached to 
    the notice. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Procedure after notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As some of the notice is received by the Marriage Officer, a distinctive 
    serial number shall be entered on it and such number and the date of receipt 
    of the notice shall be attested by the signature of the Marriage Offic­er. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the notice is in conformity with the requirements of the Act, it shall be 
    entered in the Marriage Notice Book which shall be a bound volume, the pages 
    of which are machine-numbered conse­cutively with a normal index attached. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the notice is not in conformity with the requirements of the Act, it shall 
    be got rectified by the parties if they are present, or returned to them by 
    post for rectification and re­transmission within a date to be fixed for 
    this purpose, if they are not present. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Marriage Officer shall have every item of rectification attested by both the 
    parties. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Publication of notice.—The 
    Marriage Officer shall cause the notice to be published,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    by affixing a true copy thereof under 
    his seal and signature to some conspicuous place in his office;
 

1[(b)    
    by serving, personally, or by registered post acknowledg­ment due true 
    copies thereof under his seal and signature on the parents of the parties to 
    the marriage; and] 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    by publishing it in a newspaper having 
    circulation,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in the State or States in India to 
    which the parties or, as the case may be, the Indian party, to the marriage 
    belong or belongs; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in the country or countries in which 
    the parties are ordi­narily resident. 
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Procedure for inquiry into objection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any objection to the solemnisation of the intended marriage (together 
    with the fee prescribed therefore in rule 15) is received by the Marriage 
    Officer, he shall record the nature of the objection in his Marriage Notice 
    Book and fix the date and time for inquiry into the objection 

    1[and cause notice 
    thereof to be served, personally or by registered post acknowledgment due, 
    in Form I on the per­son] who has made the objection and also the parties to 
    the intended marriage. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the 
    date so fixed or on any other date to which the in­quiry may be adjourned, 
    the Marriage Officer shall make an in­quiry into the objection and record in 
    his own hand in the manner prescribed in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 
    (5 of 1908), the evidence given.
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>


    1[<number>8A</number> Acknowledgment 
    in case of personal service.—Where 
    a notice is personally served under rule 7 or rule, 8, the person on whom 
    such notice is served shall sign an acknowledgment of service of the 
    notice.] 
  
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Time and place of solemnisation.—The 
    intended marriage may be solemnised at any time during office hours of the 
    Marriage Offic­er or at any other time convenient to him,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    at the official house of residence of 
    the Marriage Officer, or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    at the office in which the business of 
    the Marriage Officer is transacted, or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    at such other place within a reasonable 
    distance from such official house or office as the Marriage Officer may in 
    his dis­cretion approve: 
 
Provided 
    that additional fees as specified in rule 15 shall be payable for the 
    solemnisation of any marriage at a place referred to in clause (c). 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Manner of registration of marriages.—Registration 
    of a mar­riage under section 17 shall be effected by the Marriage Officer by 
    entering a certificate of the marriage in Form II in the Marriage 
    Certificate Book.
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Appeals to the Central Government.—An 
    appeal to the Central Government under sub-section (3) of section 11 or 
    sub-section (4) of section 17 shall be in the form of a memorandum which 
    shall be accompanied by a certified copy of:— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    the notice of the intended marriage or, 
    as the case may be, of the application for registration of the marriage;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    the statement of the reasons for which 
    the Marriage Officer refused to solemnise or, as the case may be, register 
    the marriage.
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Language for purposes of section 24.—The 
    language for purpos­es of sub-clause (ii) of clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> 
    of section 24 shall be English, Hindi or any other language, approved by the 
    Marriage Officer. 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Transmission of copies of entries in marriage records.—The 
    Marriage Officer shall send to the Secretary to the Government of India, 
    Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi, three true copies certified in Form 
    III of all entries or corrections made by him in the Marriage Certificate 
    Book at intervals of three months on, or as early as possible after, the 1st 
    day of January, April, July and October in each year and one such copy shall 
    be trans­mitted by the said Secretary to the Registrar-General or to each of 
    the Registrars-General of Births, Deaths and Marriages of the State or 
    States in India to which the parties to the marriage belong. 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Form of Marriage Certificate Book.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Marriage Certifi­cate Book shall be a bound volume. The pages of which 
    are ma­chine-numbered consecutively with a nominal index attached. Every 
    marriage certificate entered therein during each calendar year shall be 
    consecutively numbered and every authenticated copy of a certificate issued 
    to the parties shall bear the number and date, month and year in which the 
    certificate was entered. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the removal of doubts it is hereby provided that the Marriage Certificate 
    Book maintained under the Special Marriage (Diplomatic and Consular Officer) 
    Rules, 1955 may be continued to be used with necessary adaptations as the 
    Marriage Certificate Book for the purposes of these rules and the Act. 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15</number> Scale of fees.—The 
    matters in respect of which fee is levi­able and the amount of fee payable 
    therefore shall be as speci­fied in the Table below—
 
Table
 
 
 
Matter in 
        respect of which a fee is leviable 
 
Amount of 
        Fee  
        (in rupees)

 
 
1
 
2

 
 
 <section><number>i</number> 
        
For every notice of an intended marriage
 
120.00

 
 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> For publication on 
        notice
 
Actual Charges

 
 
 Note : A 
        suitable amount will be taken as an advance towards cost of Publication 
        of notice in newspapers.
  

 
 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> For 
        receiving and processing or dealing with an objection.
 
300.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> For 
        solemnizing a marriage.
 
240.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>v</number> For 
        solemnizing a marriage at a place referred to in rule 9(c).
 
90.

 
 
 Note : 
        This will be in addition to the fee referred to in item (iv) above.
  

 
 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> For 
        receiving notice of a caveat
 
240.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>vii</number> For 
        certificate by Marriage Officer of notice having been given and posted 
        up.
 
45.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> For a 
        certified copy of reasons recorded under section 11 or section 17 for 
        refusal to solemnise or, as the case may be for refusal to register, a 
        marriage
 
25.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> For 
        certified copy of an entry : -
  

 
 
 <subsection>           
        <number>a</number> in the marriage Notice Book
 
25.00

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>           
        <number>b</number> in the marriage Certificate Book
 
25.00

 
 
 </subsection></section><section><number>x</number> For 
        certification of document referred to in sub-section (1) section 24
 
10.00

 
 
 </section><section><number>xi</number> For making 
        aa search
  

 
 
 <subsection>     
        <number>a</number> if the entry is of the current year
 
25.00

 
        
        (b) if the entry relates to any previous year of years
 
45.00]

 
  






 



</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>