<act><tid>1408110</tid>
<title>THE TOBACCO CESS ACT, <year>1975</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1975</year>
[ 12th May, <year>1975</year>]

An Act to provide for the levy and collection, by way of cess, of 
a 
duty of excise on virginia tobacco and a duty of customs on 
tobacco, 
for the development of tobacco industry and for matters 
connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1175056</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1372183</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Tobacco Cess Act, <year>1975</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1738867</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>676557</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and 
different dates may be appointed for different provisions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1464817</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition.
<section><tid>30661</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires,-

<subsection><tid>1678880</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" auction platform" means an auction platform registered with the 
Board in accordance with the rules made under the Tobacco Board Act, 
 <year>1975</year> or established by the Board under that Act:]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1847805</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" Board" means the Tobacco Board established under section 4 of 
the Tobacco Board Act, <year>1975</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>249801</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>151</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 1- <year>1976</year>; Vide Notifn. No. S. O. 5419, dt. 17- 12- <year>1975</year> (except  
  see. 3).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Re- lettered ins. and omitted by Act 36 of <year>1978</year>, s- 7.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1772484</tid>
<number>2</number>All words and expressions used in this Act and not defined, 
but defined in the Tobacco Board Act, <year>1975</year> (4 of <year>1975</year>.), shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1505135</tid>
<number> 3</number> Duties of excise on virginia tobacco.
<section><tid>889537</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
levied and collected, by way of a cess for the purposes of the Tobacco 
Board Act, <year>1975</year> (4 of <year>1975</year>.), a duty of excise at the rate of one 
paisa per kilogram on virginia tobacco which is produced in India and 
sold at a[ an auction platform] 2.

</section>

<section><tid>1970393</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be in 
addition to any cess or duty leviable on virginia tobacco under any 
other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1477702</tid>
<number>3</number>The duty of excise payable under sub- section (1) in respect 
of any virginia tobacco sold at,[ an auction platform] 1 shall be pay- 
able by the seller thereof to the person or authority prescribed in 
respect of such platform.

</section>

<section><tid>204347</tid>
<number>4</number>The person or authority prescribed in respect of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an auction 
platform] shall collect the duty of excise payable on virginia tobacco 
sold at such platform and pay the amount so collected to the Central 
Government in such manner and within such time as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>348346</tid>
<number>5</number>If any duty of excise payable under this section, or if any 
amount collected under this section by way of such duty, has not been 
paid to the Central Government within the period prescribed under sub- 
section (4), the Central Government may recover such duty or amount in 
the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1905315</tid>
<number> 4</number> Duties of customs on tobacco.
<section><tid>1606625</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and  
collected, by way of a cess for the purposes of the Tobacco Board Act, 
 <year>1975</year> (4 of <year>1975</year>.), a duty of customs at such rate not exceeding one 
per cent. ad valorem as the Central Government may specify, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, on all tobacco, which is 
exported.
Explanation.-" Exported" means taken out of India by land, sea or 
air.


</section>

<section><tid>851963</tid>
<number>2</number>The duties of customs levied under sub- section (1) shall be 
in addition to any cess or duty leviable on tobacco under any other 
law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1647951</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>.) and the 
rules and regulations made thereunder, including those relating to 
refunds and exemptions from duty, shall, as far as may be, apply in 
relation to, the levy and collection of the duty of customs leviable 
under sub- section (1) as they apply in relation to the levy and 
collection of duties of customs under that Act or those rules and 
regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1977853</tid>
<number>5</number>Crediting proceeds of duties to Consolidated Fund of India. 
The proceeds of the duties, of excise and customs levied under sec- 
tions 3 and 4 respectively shall first be credited to the Consolidated 
Fund of India and the Central Government may, if Parliament, by 
appropriation made by law in this behalf, so provides, pay to the 
Board, from time to time, from out of such proceeds, after deducting 
the expenses on collection, such sums of money as it may think fit for 
being utilised for the purposes of the Tobacco Board Act, <year>1975</year> (4 of  
  <year>1975</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>152</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1978</year>, s. 7.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1334499</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalty for evasion of duty of excise payable under section 3. 
Whoever wilfully or intentionally evades or attempts to evade the 
payment of any duty of excise payable by him under section 3, or the 
payment of any amount collected by way of duty under that section 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1377009</tid>
<number> 7</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>432967</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act has  
been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company 
for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company 
shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all 
due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1402879</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or conni- 
vance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1089727</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517670</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>606002</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>547320</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>685333</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>153</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<subsection><tid>129139</tid>
<number>a</number>the assessment and collection of the duties of excise levied under 
section 3 and the functions and powers which may be exercised and the 
duties which may be discharged in connection therewith by the Board or 
any officers or other employees of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1258999</tid>
<number>b</number>the persons or authorities who may collect duties of excise under 
sub- sections (3) and (4) of section 3, the time within which and the 
manner in which the proceeds of such duties of excise shall be paid to 
the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1954160</tid>
<number>c</number>the returns which the persons or authorities referred to in clause 
 (b) shall furnish to the Central Government and the form and the 
manner in which and the intervals at which such returns shall be 
furnished;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>266664</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed by, or 
provided for, by rules, under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>865472</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under this section, the Central Government 
may direct that a contravention thereof shall be punishable with im- 
prisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both, and in the case 
of a continuing contravention, with an additional fine which may ex- 
tend to fifty rupees for every day during which such contravention 
continues after conviction for the first such contravention.

</section>

<section><tid>249977</tid>
<number>4</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>