<act><title>

The
Prevention of Damage to Public Property Act, 1984</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Prevention of Damage to Public Property Act, 1984.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 28th day of January, 1984.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“mischief” shall have the same meaning as in section 425 of the
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860);
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“public property” means any property, whether immovable or movable
(including any machinery) which is owned by, or in the possession of, or under
the control of—
 <subsection><number>i</number> the
Central Government; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> any
State Government; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> any
local authority; or
 </subsection><subsection> <number>iv</number> any
corporation established by, or under, a Central, Provincial or State Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> any
company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); or
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> any
institution, concern or undertaking which the Central Government may, by
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf:
 Provided
that the Central Government shall not specify any institution, concern or
undertaking under this sub-clause unless such institution, concern or
undertaking is financed wholly or substantially by funds provided directly or
indirectly by the Central Government or by one or more State Governments, or
partly by the Central Government and partly by one or more State Governments.

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Mischief causing damage to public property.—
<section><number>1</number>
Whoever commits mischief by doing any act in respect of any public property,
other than public property of the nature referred to in sub-section (2), shall
be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and with
fine.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Whoever commits mischief by doing any act in respect of any public property
being—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
any building, installation or other property used in connection with the
production, distribution or supply of water, light, power or energy;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
any oil installations;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
any sewage works;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
any mine or factory;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
any means of public transportation or of tele-communications, or any
building, installation or other property used in connection therewith,
 shall
be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than
six months, but which may extend to five years and with fine:
 Provided
that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in its judgment, award a sentence
of imprisonment for a term of less than six months.
  




  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Mischief causing damage to public property by fire or explosive substance.—Whoever
commits an offence under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (2) of section 3 by fire
or explosive substance shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term
which shall not be less than one year, but which may extend to ten years and
with fine:
 Provided
that the court may, for special reasons to be recorded in its judgment, award a
sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than one year. 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Special provisions regarding bail.—No
person accused or convicted of an offence punishable under section 3 or section
4 shall, if in custody, be released on bail or on his own bond unless the
prosecution has been given an opportunity to oppose the application for such
release. 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Saving.—The provisions of this Act
shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of any other
law for the time being in force, and nothing contained in this Act shall exempt
any person from any proceeding (whether by way of investigation or otherwise)
which might apart from this Act, be instituted or taken against him.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Prevention of Damage to Public Property Ordinance, 1984 (Ord. 3 of 1984), is
hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding
provisions of this Act. 

  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>