<act><tid>1958646</tid>
<title>THE INDUSTRIAL FINANCE CORPORATION ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <footcitenum>1948</footcitenum> 1
[ 27th March, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to establish the Industrial Finance Corporation of India.

WHEREAS it is expedient to establish an Industrial Finance 
Corporation for the purpose of making medium and long- term credits 
more readily available to industrial concerns in India, particularly 
in circumstances where normal banking accommodation is inappropriate 
or recourse to capital issue methods is impracticable;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1239972</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1244637</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Industrial Finance Corporation Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1830944</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.]

</section>

<section><tid>1129857</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804822</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation. In this Act, unless there is anything 
repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>232351</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Board of Directors of the 
Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>512783</tid>
<number>b</number>" Corporation" means the Industrial Finance Corporation 
of India established by this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>91785</tid>
<number>ba</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" Court" means the High Court (or where there is no  
High Court and the powers of the High Court are 
exercised by the Court of Judicial Commissioner, such 
  Court) with in the local limits of whose jurisdiction,-

<subsection><tid>294442</tid>
<number>i</number>the defendant or respondent, or where there is 
more than one defendant or respondent, any one of 
them-

<subsubsection><tid>966086</tid>
<number>1</number>has his registered office; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1808603</tid>
<number>2</number>carries on the whole or part of his business, 
at the time of the commencement of any legal 
proceedings against him under this Act; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1153010</tid>
<number>ii</number>the cause of action for such legal proceedings, 
wholly or in part, arises;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch.; Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 
and Sch. I, and to the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 
8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch., Extended to Kohima and Mokokchung districts 
in the State of Nagaland by Act 52 or <year>1975</year>, s. 21. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for sub- section (2). 
3. The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2. 
4.  1st July, <year>1948</year>, vide Notification No. F- 10 (1)  (a)- F. 1 48, dated 
the 15th June, <year>1948</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1948</year>, p. 853. 
5. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1842875</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Development Bank" means the Industrial Development 
Bank of India established under the Industrial 
Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year> (18 of <year>1964</year>);]

</section>

<section><tid>1216010</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" industrial concern" means any limited company 
operative society incorporated by a Central Act or an 
Act of the Legislature of a State or under any law for 
the time being in force and registered in India which 
is engaged or to be engaged in-

<subsection><tid>1265696</tid>
<number>i</number>the manufacture, preservation or processing of 
goods;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645897</tid>
<number>ii</number>shipping;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>71692</tid>
<number>iii</number>mining;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1609749</tid>
<number>iv</number>the hotel industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>79311</tid>
<number>v</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the generation, storage or distribution of 
electricity or any other form of energy;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1150788</tid>
<number>vi</number>the transport of passengers or goods by road or by 
water or by air or by ropeway or by lift;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486569</tid>
<number>vii</number>the maintenance, repair, testing or servicing of 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> machinery or equipment] of any description or 
vehicles or vessels or motorboats or trailers or 
tractors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>341308</tid>
<number>viii</number>assembling, repairing or packing any article with 
the aid of machinery or power;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>904678</tid>
<number>ix</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the setting up of, or development of, an 
industrial area or an industrial estate;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1785205</tid>
<number>x</number>fishing or providing shore facilities for fishing 
or maintenance thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079754</tid>
<number>xi</number>providing special or technical knowledge or other 
services for the promotion of industrial growth; 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1457236</tid>
<number>xii</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> providing engineering, technical, financial, 
management, marketing or other services or 
facilities for industry;

</section>

<section><tid>1877438</tid>
<number>xiii</number>providing medical, health or other allied 
services;

</section>

<section><tid>20639</tid>
<number>xiv</number>providing services relating to information 
technology, tele- communication or electronics;

</section>

<section><tid>1762233</tid>
<number>xv</number>leasing, sub- leasing or giving on hire or hire- 
purchase of industrial plants, equipments, 
machinery or other assets, including vehicles, 
ships and aircraft;

</section>

<section><tid>864834</tid>
<number>xvi</number>such other activity as the Central Government may, 
having regard to the objects of this Act, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
this behalf; or

</section>

<section><tid>572851</tid>
<number>xvii</number>the research and development of any concept, 
technology, design, process or product, whether in 
relation to any of the matters aforesaid, 
including any activities specified under sub- 
clause (xvi), or any other matter.
Explanation.- For the purposes of sub- clause (i), the 
expression" processing of goods" includes any art 
or process for producing, preparing or making an 
article by subjecting any material to a manual, 
mechanical, chemical, electrical or any other like 
operation;]


</section>

<section><tid>1753168</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules or regulations 
made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1943719</tid>
<number>e</number>" Reserve bank" menas the Reserve Bank of India:

</section>

<section><tid>582408</tid>
<number>f</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank for the time being 
included in the second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1419476</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" State co- operative bank" has the same meaning as in 
the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>.);]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act. 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
4. Omitted by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 2


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>77404</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment and incorporation of Corporation.
<section><tid>1432118</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
Corporation to be called the Industrial Finance Corporation of India 
shall be established for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>100375</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall be a body corporate by the name of the 
Industrial Finance Corporation of India, having perpetual succession 
and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, 
to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> acquire, hold or dispose of] property, both movable and 
immovable, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1399400</tid>
<number> 4</number> Share capital and share- holders.
<section><tid>1166779</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorized capital of  
the Corporation shall be ten crores of rupees divided into twenty 
thousand fully paid- up shares of five thousand rupees each of which 
ten thousand shares of the total value of five crores of rupees shall 
be issued in the first instance, and the remaining shares may be 
issued with the sanction of the Central Government from time to time 
as and when the Corporation may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>594108</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> On and from the commencement of the Industrial Finance 
Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1972</year>, (74 of <year>1972</year>.) the authorised 
capital of the Corporation shall stand increased to twenty crores of 
rupees, divided into forty thousand shares of five thousand rupees 
each, and the shares representing the capital so increased may be 
issued, with the sanction of the Central Government, as and when the 
Corporation may deem fit.]

</section>

<section><tid>855049</tid>
<number>1B</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> On or after the commencement of the Industrial Finance 
Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1982</year> (2 of <year>1982</year>), the authorised 
capital of the Corporation may be increased to such amount not 
exceeding one hundred 
crores of rupees as the Central Government may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1672809</tid>
<number>1C</number>The authorised capital increased under sub- section (1B) 
shall be divided into such number of shares of five thousand rupees 
each as may be necessary and the shares representing the capital so 
increased may be issued with the sanction of the Central Government as 
and when the Corporation may deem fit."]

</section>

<section><tid>22925</tid>
<number>1D</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> On or after the commencement of the Industrial Finance 
Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1986</year> (50 of <year>1986</year>), the authorised capital 
of the Corporation may be increased to such amount not exceeding two 
hundred and fifty crores of rupees as the Central Government may, from 
time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1900734</tid>
<number>1E</number>The authorised capital increased under sub- section (1D) 
shall be divided into such number of shares of five thousand rupees 
each a may be necessary and the shares representing the capital so 
increased may be issued with the sanction of the Central Government as 
and when the Corporation may deem fit."]

</section>

<section><tid>719632</tid>
<number>2</number>Of the capital issued in the first instance, the Central 
Government and the Reserve Bank shall each subscribe for two thousand 
shares.

</section>

<section><tid>1868356</tid>
<number>3</number>On application made before such date as may be notified by 
the Central Government in the Official Gazette in this behalf, 
scheduled banks may subscribe for two thousand five hundred shares, 
and insurance companies, investment trusts and other like financial 
institutions for two thousand five hundred shares, and co- operative 
banks for one thousand shares of the Corporation:
Provided that no institution shall be allotted more than ten 
percent of the shares reserved for the class of institutions to which 
it belongs.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 4, for" acquire and hold". 
3. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 3. 
4. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year> s. 3 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1088609</tid>
<number>4</number>The allotment of shares to the applicants mentioned in sub- 
section (3) shall be made by the Board in accordance with the 
regulations made in this behalf.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1106360</tid>
<number>7</number>Shares of the Corporation shall not be transferable except to 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Development Bank], <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Reserve Bank], any scheduled bank, 
any insurance company, any investment trust or any other like 
financial institution or any co- operative bank in accordance with the 
regulations made in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>626291</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> In this section and in section 4A] the expression 
" insurance companies" or" insurance company" includes the Life 
Insurance Corporation of India established under section 3 of the Life 
Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1956</year> (31 of <year>1956</year>) <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>, the General Insurance 
Corporation of India formed and registered under the Companies Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), its subsidiaries and such other institution or 
institutions dealing with general insurance business as may be 
notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette in this 
behalf"]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>824566</tid>
<number> 4A</number> <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Transfer of shares and increase of capital.
<section><tid>661346</tid>
<number>1</number>On such  
date <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint-

<subsection><tid>813039</tid>
<number>a</number>all shares of the Corporation held by the Central Government 
and the Reserve Bank shall stand transferred to and vest in 
the Development Bank and as compensation therefor the 
Development Bank shall pay to the Central Government and to 
the Reserve Bank respectively the face value of the shares 
held by that Government and by that Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1056830</tid>
<number>b</number>the capital issued by the Corporation shall be increased by 
such number of shares as the Central Government may specify 
in this behalf and all such shares shall stand allotted to 
and be subscribed by the Development Bank, so however that 
after such increases the Development Bank holds not less 
than fifty per cent. of the paid- up capital of the 
Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1169740</tid>
<number>2</number>If and when the remaining shares in the capital of the 
Corporation, or any part thereof, are issued, such further shares 
shall be offered to the holders of the shares of the Corporation in 
proportion,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- sections (5) and (6) omitted by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and 
Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 38 and Sch. II, ibid., for" the Central Government, 
the Reserve Bank" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 3. 
4. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3. 
5. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
6. Ins. by s. 3 ibid. (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
7. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, S. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1964</year>). 
8.  1- 8- <year>1964</year> vide Notification No. S. O. 2662, dated 29- 7- <year>1964</year>, see 
Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part II, sec. 3 (ii), p. 643.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as nearly as circumstances admit, to the capital paid- up on those 
shares at the date of such further issue:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that such holders shall have the right to renounce 
the shares so offered to them in favour of any scheduled bank, any 
insurance company, any investment trust or any other like financial 
institution or any co- operative bank, whether or not any such 
institution is a shareholder:

Provided further that if any such holder does not accept the 
shares so offered or does not exercise the right of renunciation in 
respect of any such shares in favour of any institution referred to in 
the preceding proviso within the time fixed therefor, the Board may 
allot such shares to any such institution with the concurrence of the 
Development Bank:

Provided also that"] if any such shares remain unallotted, they shall 
be subscribed for by the Development Bank.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>565798</tid>
<number>5</number>Guarantee by Central Government. The shares of the Corporation 
shall be guaranteed by the Central Government as to the repayment of 
the principal and the payment of the annual dividend at such minimum 
rate as may be fixed by the Central Government by notification 
published in the Official Gazette at the time of issuing the shares.


</article>



<article><tid>368967</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Shares of the Corporation to be deemed to be securities 
for certain purposes. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Acts 
hereinafter mentioned in this section, the shares of the Corporation 
shall be deemed to be included among the securities enumerated in 
section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1982</year>, (2 of <year>1882</year>.) and also 
deemed to be approved secrities for the purposes of the Insurance Act, 
<year>1938</year>, (4 of <year>1938</year>.) and the Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>).]


</article>



<article><tid>1385868</tid>
<number> 6</number> Management.
<section><tid>1330906</tid>
<number>1</number>The general superintendence and direction of  
the affairs and business of the Corporation shall be entrusted to a 
Board of Directors which <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> may exercise all powers and do all acts 
and things which may be exercised or done by the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1793455</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board in discharging its functions shall act on business 
principles due regard being had by it to the interests of industry, 
commerce and the general public.

</section>

<section><tid>145253</tid>
<number>3</number>In the discharge of its said functions, the Board shall be 
guided by such instructions on questions of policy as may be given to 
it by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Development Bank].

</section>

<section><tid>770887</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> If any dispute arises between the Development Bank and the 
Board as to whether a question is or is not a question of policy, the 
dispute shall be referred to the Central Government whose decision 
thereon shall be final.]

</section>

<section><tid>1215707</tid>
<number>5</number>If the Board fails to carry out the instructions on the 
question of policy <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> given by the Development Bank], the Central 
Government shall have the power to supersede the Board and appoint a 
new
<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>) 
2. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1949</year>, s. 2. 
3. The words" with the assistance of an Executive Committee and a 
Managing Director" omitted by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 5. 
4. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Central 
Government" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
5. Subs. by 38 and Sch. II, ibid., for sub- section (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
6. Subs. by s. 38 and Sch. II, ibid., for" laid down by the Central 
Government" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Board in its place to function until a properly constituted Board is 
set up. The decision of the Central Government as to the grounds for 
superseding the Board shall not be questioned in any Court of law.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1484031</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Powers of Executive Committee.] Rep. by the Industrial and 
State Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, <year>1955</year> (28 of <year>1955</year>), s. 6.


</article>



<article><tid>1683515</tid>
<number>8</number>[ Advisory Committee.] Rep., ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>1131104</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Managing Director.] Rep., ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>533017</tid>
<number> 10</number>  <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1533649</tid>
<number>1</number>] Board of Directors. The Board of Directors shall  
consist of the following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1578233</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a Chairman and a Managing director to be appointed by the 
Central Government after consultation with the Development Bank:
Provided that the same person may be appointed to function both 
as Chairman an das Managing Director;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>210578</tid>
<number>aa</number>four Directors nominated by <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Development Bank];]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1062548</tid>
<number>b</number>two Directors nominated by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Central Government];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>950660</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> one Director nominated by the Reserve Bank;"]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1666501</tid>
<number>c</number>two Directors elected in the prescribed manner by the 
scheduled banks who are shareholders of the 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>324934</tid>
<number>d</number>two Directors elected in the prescribed manner by the 
shareholders of the Corporation, other than <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the 
Development Bank], the scheduled banks and co- operative 
banks;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1454667</tid>
<number>e</number>two Directors elected in the prescribed manner by the 
co- operative banks who are shareholders of the 
Corporation.
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 10 re- numbered as subsection (1) of that section by Act 78 of 
<year>1952</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year> s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Central 
Government" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 38 and Sch. II, ibid., for" the Central Board of the 
Reserve Bank" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
6. Subs. by Acy 18 of <year>1964</year> s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Central 
Government, the Reserve Bank" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
7. Cls. (f) and (g) and provisos omitted by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 7.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>489554</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> On the date appointed under sub- section (1) of section 4A, 
the Directors holding office under clause (aa) or clause (b) 
immediately before the said date shall be deemed to have vacated their 
offices as such.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1793512</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Chairman of the Board.
<section><tid>1869105</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman of the Board  
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or the Managing Director and, in a case where the same person is 
appointed to function both as Chairman and as Managing Director, such 
person] shall receive such salary and allowances as may be determined 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> by the Development Bank] with the approval of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>585679</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Chairman and the Managing Director shall hold office 
for such term not exceeding five years as the Central Government may 
specify in this behalf and shall be eligible for reappointment.]

</section>

<section><tid>1829406</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), 
the Central Government shall have the right to terminate the term of 
office of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Chairman or the Managing Director] at any time before 
the expiry of the term[ specified under] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> sub- section (2) by giving 
him notice of not less than three months in writing or three months' 
salary and allowances in lieu of such notice; and the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Chairman or 
the Managing Director] shall also have the right to relinquish his 
office at any time before the expiry of the term[ specified under] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
sub section (2) by giving to the Central Government notice of not less 
than three months in writing.]

</section>

<section><tid>1075010</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
duties as are assigned to him by this Act or as may be delegated to 
him by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1282468</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The Managing Director shall exercise such powers and 
discharge such duties as are assigned to him by this Act or as may be 
delegated to him by the Board or the Chairman.]

</section>

<section><tid>597358</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), 
the Chairman or, in his absence, the Managing Director, is of opinion 
that circumstances exist which render it necessary for him to take 
immediate action in respect of any matter which is within the 
competence of the Board and that the interests of the Corporation may 
be prejudicially affected if such action is deferred until after the 
next meeting of the Board, then he may take such action"] in respect 
of that matter as he deems necessary and for such purpose, he may 
exercise all powers and do all acts and things which may be exercised 
or done by the Board
<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
Former sub- section (2) was omitted by Art. 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 7. 
2. Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 8. 
3. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" by the Board" 
  w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 73 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3. 
6. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1956</year> s. 5 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


but in every such case, he shall, as soon as may be, after the 
action is taken, make a written report to the Board <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> containing a 
statement of the action taken and the circumstances under which it was 
taken.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>601122</tid>
<number> 11</number> Term of office and retirement of Directors.
<section><tid>1226940</tid>
<number>1</number>A nominated  
Director shall hold office during the pleasure of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the authority 
appointing him].

</section>

<section><tid>1947963</tid>
<number>2</number>An elected Director shall hold office for <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> three years]:
Provided that one out of the two Directors elected to represent 
the shareholders referred to in each of the clauses (c), (d) and (e) 
of section 10 shall retire at the end of two years after the first 
election; the Directors so to retire shall be determined by lot:

Provided further that an elected Director shall be required to 
continue in his office until his successor has been elected:

Provided further that <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> such] a Director shall be eligible for 
re- election for not more than two full consecutive terms after the 
rotation of elected Directors has begun.


</section>

<section><tid>1720829</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy in the office of an elected Director shall 
be filled by election and a Director so elected shall hold office for 
the unexpired portion of the term of his predecessor:
Provided that no casual vacancy occurring within <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[ six months] 
of the date of expiry of the normal term of office of an elected 
Director need be filled under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>1121943</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Directors shall be paid such fees as may be prescribed for 
attending the meetings of the Board and, if they are members of <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> any 
Committee] appointed by the Corporation, for attending meetings of 
such Committee:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to the 
Chairman <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>, Managing Director] or to any other Director who is a 
servant of the Government <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> or of the Development Bank].]


</section>

<section><tid>1785143</tid>
<number>5</number>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be questioned on the 
ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
constitution of, the Board.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or the Central Committee" omitted by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, 
s. 4. 
2. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 4. for" the Central Government". 
3. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year> s. 4. 
5. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
6. Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1960</year>, s. 4. for sub- section (4). 
7. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 5, for" the Central Committee or any 
other Committee". 
8. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 6 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
9. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f 1- 8- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1301039</tid>
<number> 12</number> Disqualification. No person shall be a Director who--
<section><tid>75106</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> except in the case of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Chairman[ <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or the 
Managing Director], is a salaried official of the 
Corporation; or]

</section>

<section><tid>431264</tid>
<number>b</number>is, or at any time has been, adjudicated insolvent or 
has suspended payment <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> of his debts] or has 
compounded with his creditors; or

</section>

<section><tid>1799271</tid>
<number>c</number>is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound mind; or

</section>

<section><tid>326710</tid>
<number>d</number>is or has been convicted of any offence involving moral 
turpitude.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1526722</tid>
<number> 13</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Removal of Director from office. <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
<section><tid>472298</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> after consultation with the Development Bank] at any 
time remove the Chairman <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> or the Managing Director] from office:]
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Provided that no person shall be removed from his office, 
under this sub- section, unless he has been given an opportunity of 
showing cause against his removal.]


</section>

<section><tid>569951</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may remove from office any Director who--

<subsection><tid>1822322</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has become, subject to any of the 
disqualifications mentioned in section 12; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1604297</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the Board from more than 
three consecutive meetings of the Board without excuse 
sufficient in the opinion of the Board to exonerate the 
absence.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631671</tid>
<number>13A</number><footcitenum>10</footcitenum> Casual vacancy of Chairman. If the Chairman of the Board 
 <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> or the Managing Director] is by infirmity or otherwise rendered 
incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave or 
otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of his 
appointment, the Central Government may, after consultation <footcitenum>12</footcitenum> with 
the Development Bank], appoint another person to act in his place 
during his absence.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 5 for cl. (a). 
2. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 10, for" the Managing Director or the 
Deputy Managing Director". 
3. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 5. 
5. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for s. 13. 
6. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 11, for sub- section (1). (w. e. f.  
  18- 9- <year>1955</year>). 
7. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
8. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 8 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
9. Ins. by Act 73 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3. 
10. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 12, for s. 13A, ins. by Act 78 of 
<year>1952</year>, s. 7. (w. e. f. 18- 9- <year>1955</year>). 
11. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 9 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
12. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" with the Board" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>967262</tid>
<number>14</number>[ Central Committee.] Rep. by the Industrial Finance 
Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1972</year> (74 of <year>1972</year>), s. 6.


</article>



<article><tid>460320</tid>
<number>15</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Advisory Committees. The Corporation may from time to time 
appoint one or more Advisory Committee or Committees for the purpose 
of assisting the Corporation in the efficient performance of its 
functions and in particular, for the purpose of securing that those 
functions are exercised with due regard to the circumstances of, 
conditions prevailing in, and requirements of, particular areas or 
industries.


</article>



<article><tid>562398</tid>
<number>16</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Staff of Corporation. The Corporation may appoint such 
number of officers and other employees as it considers necessary or 
desirable for the efficient performance of its functions and determine 
the terms and conditions of their appointment and service.]


</article>



<article><tid>1037078</tid>
<number> 17</number> Meetings of the Board.
<section><tid>1846913</tid>
<number>1</number>Meetings of Board <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> shall be  
held at such times and at such places as may be prescribed:
Provided that until regulations have been made in this behalf 
such meetings shall be convened by <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Chairman].


</section>

<section><tid>1554584</tid>
<number>2</number>To constitute a quorum at a meeting of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Board, not 
less than five Directors shall be present, of whom not less than two 
shall be nominated Directors and at least one an elected Director.
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>331131</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> At a meeting of the Board <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> each Director] shall have one 
vote, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairman or, in 
his absence, any other person presiding shall have a second or casting 
vote.]

</section>

<section><tid>1621303</tid>
<number>4</number>No Director shall vote on any matter concerning an industrial 
concern in which he is directly or indirectly interested.

</section>

<section><tid>1594398</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> The Chairman or, if for any reason he is unable to attend 
a meeting of the Board, the Managing Director or, in the event of both 
the Chairman and the Managing, Director being unable to attend such 
meeting, any other Director nominated by the Chairman in this behalf 
and in the absence of such nomination any Director elected by the 
Directors present from among themselves, shall preside at the 
meeting.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 13, for the former sections, 
2. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>) 
3. The words" and of the Central Committee" omitted by Act 74 of 
<year>1972</year>, s. 7. 
4. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 14, for" the Managing Director" 
5. The brackets and letter" (a)" and cl. (b) omitted by Act 74 of 
<year>1972</year>, s. 7. 
6. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 14, for the former sub- section. 
7. Subs, by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 7, for certain words. 
8. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1389256</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If, for any reason, a Director nominated under clause 
 (aa) of clause (b) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or clause (bb)] of section 10 is unable to 
attend any meeting of the Board, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Development Bank or the 
Central Government] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or the Reserve Bank], as the case may be, may 
depute any other person to attend the said meeting and such person 
shall, for all purposes of the said meeting, be deemed to be a 
Director nominated under clause (aa) or clause (b) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or clause 
 (bb)], as the case be, of the said section.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1510288</tid>
<number>18</number>Offices and agencies. The Corporation shall establish its 
head office in Delhi and offices in Bombay, Calcutta, Kanpur and 
Madras, and may, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> establish offices or agencies in other places 
in India.


</article>



<article><tid>27766</tid>
<number>19</number>Deposit Accounts. The Corporation may open Deposit Accounts 
with the Reserve Bank or with any agency of the Reserve Bank other 
than a Government treasury <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> with a scheduled bank or a 
State Co- operative Bank <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, 
with any bank outside India]


</article>



<article><tid>1336302</tid>
<number>20</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Investment of funds. The Corporation may invest its funds 
in the securities of the Central Government or of any State Government 
and may, with the approval of the Central Government, contribute to 
the initial capital of the Unit Trust of India established under the 
Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> (52 of <year>1963</year>), <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> and the Corporation may 
also subscribe to, or purchase, <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> the units of the said Unit Trust 
of India, or the shares, bonds or debentures of any financial or 
development institution or organisation]


</article>



<article><tid>1346522</tid>
<number> 21</number> Borrowing powers.
<section><tid>418113</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation may issue and sell  
bonds and debentures carrying interest for the purpose of raising its 
working capital.
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>48</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3. 
2. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Central 
Government or the Reserve Bank" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 10. 
6. Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year> s. 8 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
7. Added by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 11 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1963</year>, s. 44 and Sch. II, for s. 20 (w. e. f. 1-  
  2- <year>1964</year>). 
9. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 8. 
10. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 12 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
11. Omitted by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1630793</tid>
<number>2</number>Bonds and debentures of the Corporation shall be guaranteed 
by the Central Government as to the repayment of principal and the 
payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by the Central 
Government on the recommendation of the Board at the time the bonds 
and debentures are issued:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that no such guarantee by the Central Government 
shall be required in respect of such bonds and debentures of the 
Corporation as are issued to the Development Bank.]


</section>

<section><tid>118537</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying out its 
functions under this Act, borrow money from the Reserve Bank,-

<subsection><tid>952633</tid>
<number>a</number>repayable on demand or on the expiry of fixed periods not 
exceeding ninety days from the date on which the money is so 
borrowed, against securities of the Central Government or of 
any State Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400733</tid>
<number>b</number>repayable on the expiry of fixed periods not exceeding 
eighteen months from the date on which the money is so 
borrowed, against securities of the Central Government of 
any maturity or against bonds and debentures issued by the 
Corporation under sub- section (1) and guaranteed by the 
Central Government and maturing within a period not 
exceeding eighteen months from the date on which the money 
is so borrowed:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>390615</tid>
<number>4</number>The Corporation may also, for the purpose of carrying out its 
functions under this Act, borrow money from the Central Government 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or the Development Bank], <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Life Insurance Corporation of 
India established under section 3 of the Life Insurance Corporation 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), the General Insurance Corporation of India 
formed and registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, the Unit Trust of 
India established under section 3 of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> 
 (52 of <year>1963</year>), or, with the general or special approval of the Central 
Government, from any other authority, institution, organisation or 
trust within or outside India] on such terms and conditions as may be 
agreed upon.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>49</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 9. 
2. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 15, for sub- section (3), ins. by Act 
78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 11. 
3. Omitted by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>) 
4. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>) 
5. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>969157</tid>
<number>21A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Bonds and debentures to be approved securities. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, the bonds and debentures issued or sold by the Corporation 
shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been, approved securities 
for the purpose of the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>), the 
Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of <year>1938</year>), and the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> 
 (10 of <year>1949</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>933445</tid>
<number>21B</number>Power to transfer rights. The rights and interests of the 
Corporation (including any other rights incidental thereto) in 
relation to any loan or advance granted, or any amount recoverable, by 
it may be transferred by the Corporation, either in whole or in part, 
by the execution or issue of any instrument, or by the transfer of any 
instrument by endorsement or in any other manner in which the rights 
and interests in relation to such loan or advance may be lawfully 
transferred, and the Corporation may, notwithstanding such transfer, 
act as the trustee for the transferee.]


</article>



<article><tid>1808991</tid>
<number>21C</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power to acquire rights. The Corporation shall have the 
right to acquire, by transfer or assignment, the rights and interests 
of any public financial institution as defined in section 4A of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), (including any other rights incidental  
  thereto), in relation to any loan or advance granted, or any amount 
recoverable, by such institution, either in whole or in part, by the 
execution or issue of any instrument, or by the transfer of any 
instrument by endorsement or in any other manner.]


</article>



<article><tid>186705</tid>
<number>22</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Deposits with the Corporation. The Corporation may accept 
deposits repayable after the expiry of a period which shall not be 
less than twelve months from the date of the making of the deposit on 
such terms and conditions as may, generally or specially, be approved 
by the Development Bank.]


</article>



<article><tid>1334704</tid>
<number> 23</number> Business which the Corporation may transact. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The 
Corporation shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, be 
authorised to carry on and transact the following kinds of business, 
namely:-
<section><tid>33665</tid>
<number>a</number>guaranteeing <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

<subsection><tid>819002</tid>
<number>i</number>loans raised by industrial concerns which <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> are 
floated in the public market;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1982</year>, s. 10. 
3. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 10. (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5, for sub- section (1). 
6. Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12. (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>616031</tid>
<number>ii</number>loans raised by industrial concerns from scheduled 
banks <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Co- operative Banks or such other 
financial institutions as may be notified by the 
Central Government in this behalf]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1922961</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> guaranteeing deferred payments due from any 
industrial concern;]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>487524</tid>
<number>c</number>guaranteeing <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> xxx loans raised from, or credit 
arrangements made with, any banks or financial 
institution in any country outside India by industrial 
concerns in foreign currency:
Provided that no such guarantee shall be given without the 
prior approval of the Central Government;


</section>

<section><tid>1127181</tid>
<number>d</number>underwriting the issue of stock, shares, bonds or 
debentures by industrial concerns <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and retaining as 
part of its assets, any stocks, shares, bonds or 
debentures which it may have to take up in fulfilment 
of its obligations thereto];

</section>

<section><tid>392977</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> transferring for consideration any instrument 
relating to loans and advances granted by it to 
industrial concerns;]

</section>

<section><tid>942323</tid>
<number>e</number>acting as agent for the Central Government or, with its 
approval, for the International Bank for Reconstruction 
and Development <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> or any other international or 
national institution or organisation] in the 
transaction of any business with an industrial concern 
in respect of loans or advances granted, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or stocks, 
shares, bonds or debentures subscribed, by any of them 
or on their behalf]

</section>

<section><tid>1438567</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subscribing to, or purchasing, the stock, shares or 
bonds of any industrial concern;]

</section>

<section><tid>139709</tid>
<number>g</number>receiving in consideration of the services mentioned in 
clauses (a) to (f), such commission as may be agreed 
upon;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
2. Omitted by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 2. 2. 87). 
3. Proviso omitted by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 11. 
4. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year> s. 11. 
6. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 14 (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
7. Subs. by s. 14, ibid. (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
8. Cl. (h) omitted by s. 11, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



<subsection><tid>702868</tid>
<number>i</number>granting loans or advances to, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or subscribing to, or 
purchasing, debentures of industrial concerns:]
Provided that nothing contained in this clause shall be 
deemed to preclude the Corporation from granting loans 
or advances to, or subscribing to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, or purchasing,] 
debentures of, an industrial concern, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the amounts 
outstanding thereon may be convertible at the option of 
the Corporation] into stock or shares of that concern 
within the period the loan, advance or debenture is 
repayable.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Explanation.- In this clause, the expression" the amounts 
outstanding thereon", used in relation to any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> loan, 
advance or debenture shall mean the principal, interest 
and other charges payable on such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> loan, advance or 
debenture] as at the time when the amounts are sought 
to be converted into stocks or shares;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>755341</tid>
<number>j</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> undertaking research and surveys for evaluating or 
dealing with marketing or investments and undertaking 
and carrying on techno- economic studies in connection 
with the development of industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>967846</tid>
<number>k</number>providing technical,[ legal, marketing] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and 
administrative assistance to any industrial concern for 
the promotion, management or expansion of any industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383730</tid>
<number>l</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> providing consultancy and merchant banking services 
in and outside India;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1856563</tid>
<number>m</number>Performing functions entrusted to, or required of, the 
Corporation by this Act or by any other law for the 
time being in force;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>490426</tid>
<number>n</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>] acquiring with the approval of the Development 
Bank the undertaking including the business, assets 
and liabilities of any institution the principal 
object of which is the promotion or development of 
industry in India, or the grant of financial 
assistance for such promotion or development;] <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1340053</tid>
<number>o</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>] doing any kind of business which the Central 
Government may, on the recommendation of the 
Development Bank, authorise; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>239095</tid>
<number>p</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>] generally, the doing of all such matters and things 
as may be incidental to or consequential upon the 
exercise of its powers or the discharge of its duties 
under this Act. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or under any other law for the time 
being in force]
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 
2. Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 11, for certain words. 
4. Ins. by s. 11, ibid. 
5. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
6. Relettered by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 
 (w. e. f. 12. 3. 82). 
7. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 11. for certain words. 
8. The word" and" omitted by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>). 
9. Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 12- 3- <year>1982</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1140836</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to impose conditions for accommodation.
<section><tid>1864652</tid>
<number>1</number>In entering  
into any arrangement under section 23 with an industrial concern, the 
Corporation may impose such conditions as it may think necessary or 
expedient for protecting the interest of the Corporation, and securing 
that the accommodation granted by it is put to the best use by the 
industrial concern.

</section>

<section><tid>1285784</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where any arrangement entered into by the Corporation with 
an inustrial concern provides for the appointment by the Corporation 
of one or more Directors of such industrial concern, such provision 
and any appointment of Directors made in pursuance thereof shall be 
valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained 
in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any other law for the 
time being in force or in the memorandum, articles of association or 
any other instrument relating to the industrial concern, and any 
provision regarding share qualification, age limit, number of 
directorships, removal from office of Directors and such like 
conditions contained in any such law or instrument aforesaid, shall 
not apply to any Director appointed by the Corporation in pursuance of 
the arrangement as aforesaid.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 13 for sub- section (2).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1596638</tid>
<number>3</number>Any Director appointed in pursuance of sub- section (2) shall-

<subsection><tid>560591</tid>
<number>a</number>hold office during the pleasure of the Corporation and 
may be removed or substituted by any person by order in 
writing by the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>775413</tid>
<number>b</number>not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of 
his being a Director or for anything done or omitted to 
be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as 
a Director of anything in relation thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1703366</tid>
<number>c</number>not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not 
be taken into account for computing the number of 
Directors liable to such retirement.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>762387</tid>
<number> 26</number>  <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>407784</tid>
<number>1</number>] Prohibited business. The Corporation shall not- 

<subsection><tid>121798</tid>
<number>a</number>accept deposits except as provided by this Act;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1716603</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> grant any loan or advance on the security of its own 
shares.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>630975</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The Corporation shall not enter into any kind of 
business with any industrial concern of which any of the Directors of 
the Corporation is a Director, manager, agent, employee or guarantor 
or in which one or more Directors of the Corporation together hold 
substantial interest;
Provided that this sub- section shall not apply to any industrial 
concern if any Director of the Corporation-


<subsection><tid>328210</tid>
<number>i</number>is nominated as a Director on the Board of such concern by 
Government, or a Government company as defined in section 
 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or by a 
Corporation established by any other law, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1401199</tid>
<number>ii</number>is elected on the Board of such concern by virtue of shares 
held in the concern by Government, or a Government company 
as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), or by a Corporation established by any other law,
by reason only of such nomination or election, as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 14. 
2. Cl. (b) and the proviso omitted by Act 66 of <year>1960</year>, s. 7. 
3. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 15. 
4. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 14.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Explanation.-" Substantial interest", in relation to an industrial 
concern, means the beneficial interest held by one or more of the 
Directors of the Corporation or by any relative[ as defined in clause 
 (41) of section 2 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>] (1 of <year>1956</year>) of such 
Director, whether singly or taken together, in the shares of the 
industrial concern, the aggregate amount paid- up on which either 
exceeds five lakhs of rupees or five per cent. of the paid- up share 
capital of the industrial concern, whichever is less.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>506490</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub section (2)-

<subsection><tid>1949114</tid>
<number>i</number>shall not apply to any transaction relating to the 
business entered into prior to the commencement of the 
Industrial Finance Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1972</year> 
 (74 of <year>1972</year>), and all such business and any transaction 
in relation thereto may be implemented or continued as 
if that Act had not come into force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1354313</tid>
<number>ii</number>shall apply only so long as the conditions precedent to 
such disability as set out in the said sub- section 
continue.]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>94613</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall not apply to any industrial concern in respect 
of which the Corporation is satisfied that it is 
necessary, in the public interest, to enter into 
business with that concern:
Provided that such business shall be entered into in 
accordance with and subject to such conditions and 
limitations as may be prescribed by regulations made in 
this behalf.]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1800218</tid>
<number> 27</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Loans in foreign currency.
<section><tid>224141</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1947</year> (7 of <year>1947</year>), or 
in any other enactment for the time being in force relating to foreign 
exchange, the Corporation may, for the purpose of granting loans or 
advances to industrial concerns, borrow, with the previous consent of 
the Central Government, foreign currency from the International Bank 
for Reconstruction and Development <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or any bank or financial 
institution in India or in any foreign country] or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>1500449</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, where necessary, guarantee all 
loans taken by the Corporation under sub- section (1) as to the 
repayment of the principal and the payment of the interest and other 
incidental charges.

</section>

<section><tid>1872484</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> All loans and advances granted to industrial concerns by 
the Corporation out of foreign currency borrowed under sub- section (1) 
shall be expressed in terms of foreign currency as equivalent of 
Indian currency, calculated in accordance with the rate of exchange 
prevailing at the time of grant thereof, and the amount due there- 
under shall be repayable in equivalent Indian currency, calculated
<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 16, for s. 27. 
3. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 8. 
4. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 15, for sub- sections (3) and (4).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in accordance with the rate of exchange prevailing at the time of 
repayment of such loan or advance.


</section>

<section><tid>1110303</tid>
<number>4</number>Any loss or profit in connection with any borrowing of 
foreign currency under sub- section (1) for the purpose of granting 
loans and advances under this Act or with its repayment to the 
concerned foreign lending agency, on account of any fluctuations in 
the rate of exchange accruing-

<subsection><tid>1740435</tid>
<number>a</number>during the period within which the loan or advance is 
repayable by the industrial concern or the period of 
actual repayment thereof by the concern, whichever is 
longer, shall be reimbursed by, or paid to, as the case 
may be, the recipients of such loans and advances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1219993</tid>
<number>b</number>after the expiry of the period specified in clause 
 (a),-

<subsubsection><tid>1458220</tid>
<number>i</number>shall be borne by the Corporation in respect of 
normal market fluctuations in foreign exchange;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>645296</tid>
<number>ii</number>shall be reimbursed by, or paid to, as the case 
may be, the Central Government in respect of 
fluctuations other than the normal market 
fluctuations in foreign exchange.
Explanation.- If any question arises as to whether any fluctuation 
as aforesaid is a normal market fluctuation or not, the same shall be 
decided by the Central Government whose decision thereon shall be 
final.]




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>605405</tid>
<number> 28</number> Right of Corporation in case of default.
<section><tid>1993676</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
industrial concern which is under a liability to the Corporation under 
an agreement makes any default in repayment <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of any loan or advance 
or any instalment thereof] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or in meeting its obligations in 
relation to any guarantee given by the Corporation] or otherwise fails 
to comply with the terms of its agreement with the Corporation, the 
Corporation shall have the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> right to take over the management, or 
possession, or both, of the concern], as well as the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> right to 
transfer by way of lease or sale] and realise the property pledged, 
mortgaged, hypothecated or assigned to the Corporation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 9. 
2. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 16. 
3. Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for certain words. 
4. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 19, for" right to sell".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>221583</tid>
<number>2</number>Any transfer of property made by the Corporation in exercise 
ofits powers <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under sub- section (1) shall vest in the transferee 
all rights in or to the property transferred <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as if the transfer] 
had been made by the owner of the property.

</section>

<section><tid>1339968</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation shall have the same rights and powers with 
respect to goods manufactured or produced wholly or partly from goods 
forming part of security held by it, as it had with respect to the 
original goods.

</section>

<section><tid>1850383</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where any action has been taken against an industrial 
concern] under the provisions of sub- section (1), all costs, charges 
and expenses <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> which, in the opinion of the Corporation, have been 
properly incurred by it] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as incidental thereto] shall be 
recoverable from the industrial concern, and the money which is 
received by it <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> shall, in the absence of any contract to the 
contrary, be held by it in trust to be applied, firstly, in payment of 
such costs, charges and expenses and, secondly, in discharge of the 
debt due to the Corporation, and the residue of the money so received 
shall be paid to the person entitled thereto.]

</section>

<section><tid>1199261</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the Corporation takes over the management <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or 
possession] of a concern under the provisions of sub- section (1), it 
shall be deemed to be the owner of such concern for purposes of suits 
by or against such concern and shall sue and be sued in the name <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> 
of the concern.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1852388</tid>
<number> 29</number> Power to call for repayment before agreed period. 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything in any agreement to the contrary, the 
Corporation may, by notice in writing, require any industrial concern 
to which it has granted any loan or advance to discharge forthwith in 
full its liabilities to the Corporation,-]
<section><tid>624964</tid>
<number>a</number>if it appears to the Board that false or misleading 
information in any material particular was given in the 
application for the loan or advance; or

</section>

<section><tid>1352638</tid>
<number>b</number>if the industrial concern has failed to comply with the 
terms of its contract with the Corporation in the matter of 
the loan or advance; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>57</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" of sale and realisation" omitted by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 
19. 
2. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for" as if the sale". 
3. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 17. 
4. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 16, for certain words. 
5. Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 9, for" properly incurred by it". 
6. Certain words omitted by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 16. 
7. Ins. by s. 16, ibid. 
8. The words" of the owner" omitted by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 9. 
9. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 18, for certain original words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>298021</tid>
<number>c</number>if there is a reasonable apprehension that the industrial 
concern is unable to pay its debts or that proceedings for 
liquidation may be commenced in respect thereof; or

</section>

<section><tid>1875445</tid>
<number>d</number>if the property pledged, mortgaged, hypothecated or assigned 
to the Corporation as security for the loan or advance is 
not insured and kept insured by the industrial concern to 
the satisfaction of the Corporation; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or depreciates in 
value to such an extent that, in the opinion of the Board, 
further security to the satisfaction of the Board should be 
given and such security is not given;] or

</section>

<section><tid>1795567</tid>
<number>e</number>if without the permission of the Board, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any machinery, 
plant or other equipment], whether forming part of the 
security or otherwise, is removed from the premises of the 
industrial concern without being replaced; or

</section>

<section><tid>958808</tid>
<number>f</number>if for any reason it is necessary <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to protect the 
interests of the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>424250</tid>
<number> 30</number> Special provisions for enforcement of claims by the 
Corporation.
<section><tid>1520950</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where an industrial concern, in breach of any  
agreement, makes any default in repayment of any loan or advance or 
any instalment thereof <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or in meeting its obligations in relation to 
the guarantee given by the Corporation] or otherwise fails to comply 
with the terms of its agreement with the Corporation or where the 
Corporation requires an industrial concern to make immediate repayment 
of any loan or advance under section 29 and the industrial concern 
fails to make such repayment, then, without prejudice to the 
provisions <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> of section 28 of this Act and] of section 69 of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>)], any officer of the 
Corporation generally or especially authorized by the Board in this 
behalf may apply to <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the Court] for one or more of the following 
reliefs, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1319553</tid>
<number>a</number>for an order for the sale of the property pledged, 
mortgaged, hypothecated or assigned to the Corporation as 
security for the loan or advance, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>692492</tid>
<number>b</number>for transferring the management of the industrial concern to 
the Corporation, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1857264</tid>
<number>c</number>for an ad interim injunction where there is apprehension of 
the machinery or the equipment being removed from
<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 18, for certain original words. 
2. The words" in the opinion of the Board' omitted by s. 18, ibid. 
3. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for certain original words. 
4. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17. 
5. Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 20. 
6. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17, for certain words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the premises of the industrial concern without the 
permission of the Board.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1113389</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under sub- section (1) shall state the nature 
and extent of the liability of the industrial concern to the 
Corporation, the ground on which it is made and such other particulars 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>438740</tid>
<number>3</number>When the application is for the reliefs mentioned in sub- 
clauses (a) and (c) of sub- section (1) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] shall pass an ad 
interim order attaching the security or so much of the property of the 
industrial concern as would on being sold realise <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in its 
estimation] an amount equivalent in value to the outstanding liability 
of the industrial concern to the Corporation together with the costs 
of the proceedings taken under this section with or without an ad 
interim injunction restraining the industrial concern from 
transferring or removing its machinery or equipment.

</section>

<section><tid>542123</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the application is for the relief mentioned in sub- 
clause (b) of sub- section (1) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] shall grant an ad interim 
injunction restraining the industrial concern from transferring or 
removing its machinery or equipment and issue a notice calling upon 
the industrial concern to show cause on a date to be specified in the 
notice why the management of the industrial concern should not be 
transferred to the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1006283</tid>
<number>5</number>Before passing any order under sub- section (3) or sub- section 
 (4), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] may, if <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> it] thinks fit, examine the officer 
making the application.

</section>

<section><tid>1806334</tid>
<number>6</number>At the same time as <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> it] passes an order sub- section (3), 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] shall issue to the industrial concern a notice 
accompanied by copies of the order, the application <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and the 
evidence, if any, recorded by it calling upon the industrial concern 
to show cause] on a date to be specified in the notice why the ad 
interim order of attachment should not be made absolute or the 
injunction confirmed.

</section>

<section><tid>1694849</tid>
<number>7</number>If no cause is shown on or before the date specified in the 
notice under sub- sections (4) and (6), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] shall forthwith 
make the ad interim order absolute and direct the sale of the attached 
property or transfer the management of the industrial concern to the 
Corporation or confirm the injunction.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17, for" the District Judge". 
2. Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3 and Sch II, for" in his 
estimation". 
3. Subs. by s. 3 and Sch. II, ibid., for" he". 
4. Ins. by s. 3 and Sch. II, ibid., for certain words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1837184</tid>
<number>8</number>If cause is shown <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] shall proceed to investigate 
the claim of the Corporation and the provision of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), shall as far as practicable apply to 
such proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>1385088</tid>
<number>9</number>On an investigation made under sub- section (8) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Court] 
shall pass an order-

<subsection><tid>1004325</tid>
<number>a</number>confirming the order of attachment and directing the 
sale of the attached property, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1580767</tid>
<number>b</number>varying the order of attachment so as to release a 
portion of the property from attachment and directing 
the sale of the remainder of the attached property, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788199</tid>
<number>c</number>releasing the property from attachment, if <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> it] is 
satisfied that it is not necessary in the interest of 
the Corporation, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1216785</tid>
<number>d</number>confirming or dissolving the injunction, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614154</tid>
<number>e</number>transferring the management of the industrial concern 
to the Corporation of rejecting the claim made in this 
behalf:
Provided that when making any order under clause (c), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Court] may make such further orders as <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> it] thinks necessary to 
protect the interests of the Corporation, and may apportion the costs 
of the proceedings in such manner as <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> it] thinks fit:

Provided further that unless the Corporation intimates to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Court] that it will not appeal against any order releasing any 
property from attachment, such order shall not be given effect to 
until the expiry of the period fixed under sub- section (11) within 
which an appeal may be preferred, or if an appeal is preferred, 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> unless the Court empowered to hear appeals from the decisions of 
the said Court otherwise directs], until the appeal is disposed of.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1289486</tid>
<number>10</number>An order of attachment or sale of property under this 
section shall be carried into effect as far as may be practicable in 
the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), 
for the attachment of sale of property in execution of a decree, as if 
the Corporation were the decree- holder.

</section>

<section><tid>790304</tid>
<number>10A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> An order under this section transferring the management 
of an industrial concern to the Corporation shall be carried into 
effect,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>60</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17, for" the District Judge". 
2. Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year> s. 3 and Sch. II, for" he". 
3. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 7 for unless the High Court otherwise 
directs". 
4. Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 20.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as far as may be practicable, in the manner provided in the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), for the possession of immovable 
property or the delivery of movable property in execution of a decree, 
as if the Corporation were the decree- holder.]


</section>

<section><tid>572316</tid>
<number>11</number>Any party aggrieved by an order under sub- section (7) or 
sub- section (9) may, within thirty days from the date of the order, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appeal to the Court empowered to hear appeals from the decisions of 
the Court which passed the order and the appellate Court may] after 
hearing the parties pass such orders as it thinks proper.

</section>

<section><tid>861123</tid>
<number>12</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed, where 
proceedings for liquidation in respect of the industrial concern have 
commenced before an application is made under sub- section (1) as 
giving to the Corporation any preference over the other creditors of 
the industrial concern not conferred on it by any other law.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1683322</tid>
<number>14</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any 
Court competent to grant an ad interim injunction under this section 
shall also have the power to appoint a receiver and to exercise all 
other powers incidental thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1041737</tid>
<number>15</number>All proceedings (whether by way of suits or appeals or other  
  proceedings) under this Act pending before a District Judge or an 
Additional District Judge of a High Court at the commencement of the 
Industrial Finance Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1972</year> (74 of <year>1972</year>), 
shall, on such commencement, be proceeded with and disposed of as if 
this section had not been amended by the said Act.

</section>

<section><tid>980890</tid>
<number>16</number>Every suit or other proceedings which are disposed of in 
accordance with the provisions contained in sub- section (15) or in 
respect of which time for appeal has not expired at the commencement 
of the Industrial Finance Corporation (Amendment) Act, <year>1972</year> (74 of  
  <year>1972</year>), may, on such commencement, be appealed against as if this 
section had not been amended by the said Act.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>61</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17, for" appeal to the High Court, 
and upon such appeal, the High Court may". 
2. Sub- section (13) omitted by s. 17, ibid. 
3. Ins. by s. 17, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1134085</tid>
<number> 30A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power of Corporation to appoint Directors of an 
industrial concern when management is taken over.
<section><tid>1329412</tid>
<number>1</number>When the  
management of an industrial concern is taken over the Corporation, the 
Corporation may, by order notified in the Official Gazette, appoint as 
many persons as it thinks fit to be the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Directors, or, as the case 
may be, the Administrator of that industrial concern"] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and nothing 
in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any such law or 
instrument relating to the industrial concern in so far as it makes, 
in relation to a director any provision for the holding of any share 
qualification, age limit, restrictions on the number or directorships, 
retirement by rotation or removal from office shall apply to any 
Director appointed by the Corporation under this section].

</section>

<section><tid>367337</tid>
<number>2</number>The power to appoint Directors under this section includes 
the power to appoint any individual <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to be the Manager] of the 
industrial concern on such terms and conditions as the Corporation may 
think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1831815</tid>
<number> 30B</number> Effect of notified order appointing Directors. On the issue 
of a notified order under section 30A,-
<section><tid>887791</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> all persons holding, immediately before the issue of the 
notified order, office as Directors of the industrial 
concern or any other offices entitling them to exercise 
powers of superintendence, direction and control of the 
industrial concern, shall be deemed to have vacated their 
offices as such;

</section>

<section><tid>291056</tid>
<number>b</number>any contract of management between the industrial concern 
and <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> any Director thereof holding office as such 
immediately before the issue of the notified order shall be 
deemed to have terminated;

</section>

<section><tid>1505613</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Manager, if any, appointed under section 30A, shall be 
deemed to have been appointed in pursuance of the provisions 
of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and the memorandum 
and articles of association of the industrial concern or, 
as the case may be, of any law for the time being in 
force relating to co- operative societies and the 
memorandum or other instrument of the industrial concern, 
and the provisions of the said Act or law, and of the 
memorandum and articles of association or, as the case 
may be, memorandum or other instrument shall, subject to 
the other provisions contained in this Act, apply 
accordingly; but no such Manager shall be removed from 
office except with the previous consent of the Corporation;]

</section>

<section><tid>537315</tid>
<number>d</number>the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Directors or, as the case may be, Administrator] 
appointed under section 30A shall take such steps as may be 
necessary to take into their custody or under their control 
all the property, effects and actionable claims to which the 
industrial concern is, or appears to be, entitled, and all 
the property and effects of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. 30A to 30E ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 20. 
2. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 11. 
4. Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year> s. 15 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
5. Omitted by s. 16, ibid. (w. e. f. 2- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


industrial concern shall be deemed to be in the custody of 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Directors or, as the case may be, Administrator] as 
from the date of the notified order;


</section>

<section><tid>1808504</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Directors appointed under section 30A shall, for all 
purposes, be the Directors of the industrial concern duly 
constituted under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or 
under anylaw for the time being in force relating to 
co- operative societies, and such Directors or, as the 
case may be, the Administrator appointed under section 
30A, shall alone be entitled to exercise all the powers 
of the Directors (by whatever name called) of the 
industrial concern, whether such powers are derived from 
the said Act or law or the memorandum or articles of 
association or, as the case may be, the memorandum or 
other instrument of the industrial concern;]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1445876</tid>
<number> 30C</number> Powers and duties of Directors.
<section><tid>833708</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the control  
of the Corporation, the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Directors or Administrator] appointed under 
section 30A shall take such steps as may be necessary for the purpose 
of efficiently managing the business of the industrial concern and 
shall exercise such powers and have such duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>485931</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the powers vested in 
them under sub- section (1), the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Directors or Administrator] 
appointed under section 30A may, with the previous approval of the 
Corporation, make an application to a Court for the purpose of 
cancelling or varying any contract of agreement entered into, at any 
time before the issue of the notified order under section 30A, between 
the industrial concern and any other person and the Court may, if 
satisfied after due inquiry that such contract or agreement had been 
entered into in bad faith and is detrimental to the interests of the 
industrial concern, make an order cancelling or varying (either  
unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may think fit to 
  impose) that contract or agreement and the contract or agreement shall 
have effect accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1149017</tid>
<number> 30D</number> No right to compensation for termination contract of 
managing agents.
<section><tid>672150</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for  
the time being in force, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> no Managing Director or any other Director 
or Manager or holder of any office having the powers of 
superintendence, direction and control of an industrial concern] shall 
be entitled to any compensation for the loss of office or for the 
premature termination under this Act of any contract of management 
entered into by him with such concern.

</section>

<section><tid>441075</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the right 
of any such <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Managing Director or any other Director or Manager or 
holder of office referred to in that sub- section] to recover from the 
industrial concern moneys recoverable otherwise than by way of such 
compensation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 17, ibid. (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 18, ibid. (w. e. f 2. 2. <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>171069</tid>
<number> 30E</number> Application of Act 1 of <year>1956</year>.
<section><tid>1258240</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the management of an  
industrial concern, being a company as defined in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)], is taken over by the Corporation, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in the said Act or in the 
memorandum or articles of association of such concern,-

<subsection><tid>1333610</tid>
<number>a</number>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of such concern 
or any other person to nominate or appoint any person to be 
a Director of the concern;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1633292</tid>
<number>b</number>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders of 
such concern shall be given effect to unless approved by the 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1217777</tid>
<number>c</number>no proceeding for the winding up of such concern or for the 
appointment of a receiver in respect thereof shall lie in 
any Court, except with the consent of the Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>557106</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) and to 
the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such other 
exceptions, restrictions and limitations, if any, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
this behalf, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)], shall continue 
to apply to such concern in the same manner as it applied thereto 
before the issue of the notified order under section 30A.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1894335</tid>
<number>31</number>Act 18 of <year>1891</year> to apply to the books of the Corporation. The 
Corporation shall be deemed to be a bank for the purposes of the 
Banker' s Books Evidence Act, <year>1891</year> (18 of <year>1891</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1769470</tid>
<number> 32</number> Disposal of profits.
<section><tid>67875</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall establish a  
reserve fund.

</section>

<section><tid>770966</tid>
<number>2</number>After making provision for bad and doubtful debts, 
depreciation of assets and all other matters which are usually 
provided for by bankers, the Corporation may out of its net annual 
profits declare a dividend:
Provided that for so long as the reserve fund is less than the 
paid up share capital of the Corporation and until there has been 
repaid to the Central Government such sums, if any, as that Government 
may have paid under the guarantee given in pursuance of section 5 or 
under any guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section (2) of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>62B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 12, for" Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


section 21 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or sub- section (2) of section 27], the rate of such 
dividend shall not exceed the rate guaranteed by the Central 
Government under section 5.

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1714763</tid>
<number> 32A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Special reserve fund.
<section><tid>959292</tid>
<number>1</number>All dividends accruing on the  
shares of the Corporation held by the Central Government and the 
Reserve Bank immediately before the date appointed by the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 4A in respect of any 
completed accounting period, whether declared or not, shall be 
credited to a special reserve fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1967733</tid>
<number>2</number>All dividends accruing to the Development Bank shall, instead 
of being paid to it, be also credited to the said fund until the 
aggregate of the sums credited to the fund under sub- section (1) and 
this sub- section exceeds one crore of rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>578857</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government, the Reserve Bank and the Development 
Bank only shall have claims to the said fund.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1535000</tid>
<number> 32B</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Benevolent reserve fund.
<section><tid>703769</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall  
establish a special fund, to be called the benevolent reserve fund.

</section>

<section><tid>720180</tid>
<number>2</number>To the benevolent reserve fund shall be credited-

<subsection><tid>1815104</tid>
<number>a</number>any part of the annual profit which may, from time to time, 
be allocated to the fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1574884</tid>
<number>b</number>all amounts received for the purposes of the fund by way of 
loans, gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from 
Government or any other source;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>182330</tid>
<number>c</number>income or profits from investments made from the fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>330684</tid>
<number>d</number>income accruing or arising to the fund by way of interest or 
otherwise.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1522140</tid>
<number>3</number>The benevolent reserve fund shall be used by the 
Corporation-

<subsection><tid>1429991</tid>
<number>a</number>for meeting the cost of feasibility studies, project 
reports, market and techno- economic surveys and such other 
purposes which, in the opinion of the Corporation, may 
promote the development of industries;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 21. 
2. Second proviso omitted by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 18. 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for s. 32A (w. e. f. 1-  
  8- <year>1964</year>). ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 22. 
4. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 19.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1391920</tid>
<number>b</number>in the field of development banking and in financial and 
industrial management-

<subsubsection><tid>529078</tid>
<number>i</number>for undertaking and promoting research;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1673582</tid>
<number>ii</number>for training in India or abroad of personnel of 
financial institutions; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>350364</tid>
<number>iii</number>for creating chairs in universities, academic 
institutions and research foundations;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767934</tid>
<number>c</number>for assisting projects promoted by technologists and new 
entrepreneurs-

<subsubsection><tid>999575</tid>
<number>i</number>by subsidising the normal lending rate of interest of 
the Corporation in respect of loans or advances 
sanctioned to them;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1538638</tid>
<number>ii</number>by providing technical and managerial assistance to 
projects promoted by them especially in less 
industrially developed regions;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>365166</tid>
<number>d</number>for rendering any assistance that may be ancillary or 
incidental to the aforementioned purposes.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>33605</tid>
<number> 33</number> General meetings.
<section><tid>529554</tid>
<number>1</number>A general meeting (hereinafter referred   
  to as the annual general meeting) shall be held annually at a place in 
India where there is an office of the Corporation within <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> four 
months] from the date on which the annual accounts of the Corporation 
are closed; and a general meeting may be convened by the Board at any 
other time.

</section>

<section><tid>285943</tid>
<number>2</number>The shareholders present at the annual general meeting shall 
be entitled to discuss the annual accounts, the report of the Board on 
the working of the Corporation throughout the year and the auditors' 
report on the annual balance- sheet and accounts.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49498</tid>
<number> 34</number> Audit. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>358886</tid>
<number>1</number>] The affairs of the Corporation shall be  
audited by not less than two auditors duly qualified to act as 
auditors of companies under sub- section (1) of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> section 226 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)], one of whom shall be appointed by 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Development Bank] and <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the other auditor or auditors] elected 
in the prescribed manner by
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 23, for" two". 
2. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 24, ibid., for sub- section (1). 
4. Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 13, for" section 144 of the Indian 
Companies Act, <year>1913</year>". 
5. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for certain words 
 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
6. Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 13, for" the other".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the parties mentioned in sub- section (3) of section 4, and such 
remunerations as <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Development Bank] may fix shall be paid to the 
auditors by the Corporation.]


</section>

<section><tid>1046294</tid>
<number>2</number>Every auditor shall be supplied with a copy of the annual 
balance- sheet of the Corporation, and it shall be his duty to examine 
it together with the accounts and vouchers relating thereto; and every 
auditor shall have a list delivered to him of all books kept by the 
Corporation, and shall at all reasonable times have access to the 
books, accounts and other documents of the Corporation, and may in 
relation to such accounts examine any Director or officer of the 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1483046</tid>
<number>3</number>The auditors shall make a report to the shareholders upon the 
annual balance- sheet and accounts, and in every such report they shall 
state whether in their opinion the balance- sheet is a full and fair 
balance- sheet containing all necessary particulars and properly drawn 
up so as to exhibit a true and correct view of the state of the 
affairs of the Corporation, and in case they have called for any 
explanation or information from the Board whether it has been given 
and whether it is satisfactory.

</section>

<section><tid>1147942</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in consultation with <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
Development Bank]] at any time issue directions to the auditors 
requiring them to report to it upon the adequacy of measures taken by 
the Corporation for the protection of its shareholders and creditors 
or upon the sufficiency of their procedure in auditing the affairs of 
the Corporation, and may at any time enlarge or extend the scope of 
the audit or direct that a different procedure in audit be adopted or 
direct that any other examination be made by the auditors if in its 
opinion the public interest so requires.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>62E</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Central 
Government" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 24. 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" the Comptroller 
and Auditor General of India" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Sub- section (5) omitted by s. 38 and Sch. II, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1970330</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Without prejudice to anything contained in the preceding 
sub- sections, the Central Government may, at any time, appoint the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India to examine and report upon 
the accounts of the Corporation and any expenditure incurred by him in 
connection with such examination and report shall be payable by the 
Corporation to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.]

</section>

<section><tid>159604</tid>
<number>7</number>Every audit report shall be forwarded to the Central 
Government and the Government shall cause the same to be laid before 
both Houses of Parliament.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>574635</tid>
<number>34A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appointment of local auditors. The Board may, in 
consultation with the auditors appointed under section 34, appoint 
local auditors to audit the affairs of any office or agency of the 
Corporation and the report of such auditors shall be taken into 
consideration by the auditors appointed under section 34 for the 
purpose of auditing the affairs of the Corporation."]


</article>



<article><tid>1158132</tid>
<number> 35</number> Returns.
<section><tid>369506</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall furnish a statement in the  
prescribed form of its assets and liabilities as at the close of 
business on the last Friday of each month, or if that day is a public 
holiday under the Negotiable Instruments Act <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>), as at 
the close of business on the preceding working day, to[ the 
Development Bank] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> within ten days from the date to which the 
statement relates.

</section>

<section><tid>607812</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall furnish in the prescribed form to the 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Development Bank] and to the Reserve Bank at least once in every 
year or as frequently as the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Development Bank] or the Reserve Bank 
may require <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> a statement showing the classification] of its loans 
and investments and of loans guaranteed by it and underwriting 
agreements entered into by it.

</section>

<section><tid>1661593</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation shall furnish to the Central Government, 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the Reserve Bank and the Development Bank] within <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> five months] 
of the close of the financial year a statement in the prescribed form 
of its assets and liabilities as at the close of that year together 
with a profit and loss account for the year and a report of the 
working of the Corporation during the year, and copies of the said 
statement, account and report shall be published in the Official 
Gazette and shall be laid before <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Parliament].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62F</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for sub- section (6) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 17, ibid. (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" Central 
Government" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 25, for" a classification". 
6. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, for" and the Reserve 
Bank" (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
7. Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 14, for" three months". 
8. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Central Legislature".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1845366</tid>
<number> 36</number> Acquisition of shares by the Central Government. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1500250</tid>
<number>1</number>] In  
the event of the Central Government at any time deciding to acquire 
the shares held by shareholders <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> other than the Development Bank] 
the shareholders shall be paid for the shares so acquired an amount 
equal to the paid- up value of the shares together with a premium 
calculated at the rate of one per cent. of the paid- up value for every 
year from the date of issue to the date of acquisition, subject to a 
maximum of ten per cent.

</section>

<section><tid>213291</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> After the acquisition of the shares as provided by sub- 
section (1), the Central Government shall transfer the shares to the 
Development Bank on that bank paying an amount equal to the amount 
paid by the Central Government for such acquisition.

</section>

<section><tid>599264</tid>
<number>3</number>After the transfer of the shares by the Central Government to 
the Development Bank under sub- section (2), the Central Government may 
direct by notification in the Official Gazette that with effect from 
such date as may be specified in the notification the entire 
undertaking of the Corporation, including all business, property, 
assets and liabilities, rights (including the right to recover loans  
and advances granted by the Corporation in accordance with the 
  provisions of this Act), interests, privileges and obligations of 
whatever nature, shall stand transferred to and vest in the 
Development Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1139317</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of giving effect to the transfer of the 
undertaking of the Corporation to the Development Bank, the Central 
Government shall, by order in writing, frame a scheme providing for 
all matters for which provision is necessary, and the scheme so framed 
shall be binding upon the Corporation, its creditors and employees and 
the Development Bank and shall have effect notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force or in 
any contract or other instrument.

</section>

<section><tid>235368</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law or any 
instrument having force by virtue of such Act or other law.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030632</tid>
<number>37</number>Liquidation of Corporation. No provision of law relating to 
the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to the 
Corporation, and the Corporation shall not be placed in liquidation 
save by order of the Central Government and in such manner as it may 
direct.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62G</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 36 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 18 of 
<year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch, II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 38 and Sch II, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 38 and Sch. II, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1001755</tid>
<number> 38</number> Indemnity of Directors.
<section><tid>265621</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Director, shall be  
indemnified by the Corporation against all losses and expenses 
incurred by him in or about the discharge of his duties, except such 
as are caused by his own wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>1098555</tid>
<number>2</number>A Director shall not be responsible for any other Director or 
for any officer <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or other employee] of the Corporation or for any 
loss or expense resulting to the Corporation by the insufficiency of 
deficiency of value of, or title to, any property or security acquired 
or taken on behalf of the Corporation, or by the wrongful act of any 
person under obligation to the Corporation, or by anything done in 
good faith in the execution of the duties of his office or in relation 
thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1484059</tid>
<number>38A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Protection of actiont aken by Directors appointed under 
sections 25 and 30A. No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding 
shall lie against any Director[ or Admistrator] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of an industrial 
concern appointed by the Corporation under section 25 or section 30A 
for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done by 
him as such Director. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or Administrator]].


</article>



<article><tid>1375948</tid>
<number> 39</number> Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1473791</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation  
shall not, except as otherwise required by this Act or any other law 
for the time being in force, divulge any information relating to, or 
to the affairs of its constituents except in circumstances in which it 
is, in accordance with the law or practice and usage, customary among 
bankers, necessary or appropriate for the Corporation to divulge such 
information.

</section>

<section><tid>1325545</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation may, for the purpose of efficient discharge 
of its functions under this Act, collect from, or furnish to-

<subsection><tid>221429</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>701913</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Bank of India constituted under section 3 of 
the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>), any subsidiary 
bank within the meaning of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary  
  Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>), any corresponding new bank 
constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
 (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of  
  <year>1970</year>) or under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition  
  and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1980</year> (40 of <year>1980</year>), any other 
scheduled bank, any State cooperative bank or the Development 
Bank,
such credit information or other information as it may consider useful 
for the purpose, in such manner and at such time as it may think fit.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub- section, the expression 
" credit information" shall have the same meaning as in clause (c) of 
section 45A of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>), 
subject to the modification that the banking company referred to 
therein shall mean a bank referred to in clause (b) of this 
subsection.]

[ (3)] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Every Director, <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> member of any Advisory or other 
Committee,] auditor,[ local auditor,] <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> officer <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> or other employee] 
of the Corporation shall, before entering upon his duties, make a 
declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the 
Schedule.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1627827</tid>
<number>40</number>Provision relating to income- tax and supertrtax. For the 
purposes of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), the 
Corporation shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of that 
Act and shall be liable to income- tax and super- tax accordingly on its 
income, profits and gains:
Provided that any sum paid by the Central Government under the 
guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section 5 or under any guarantee 
given in pursuance of sub- section (2) of section 21 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> or sub- section 
 (2) of section 27] shall not be treated as the income, profit and 
gains of the Corporation, and any interest on debentures or bonds 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> or on foreign currency borrowed under sub- section (1) of section 
27] paid by the Corporation out of such sum shall not be treated as 
expenditure incurred by it:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>62H</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 26, for" or servant". 
2. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1957</year>, s. 15. 
3. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1983</year>, s. 5. 
5. Re- numbered by s. 5, ibid. 
6. Ins. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 20. 
7. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 27, for" or servant". 
9. Ins. by s. 28, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided further that in the case of any shareholder, such 
portion of a dividend as has been paid out of any such sum advanced by 
the Central Government, shall be deemed to be his income from 
" interest on securities", declared to be income- tax free within the 
meaning of section 8 of the said Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1975782</tid>
<number>40A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Delegation of powers. The Board may, by general or 
special order, delegate to the Chairman[, Managing Director] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or any 
officer of the Corporation, subject to such conditions and 
limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its 
powers and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary.]


</article>



<article><tid>1302022</tid>
<number> 40B</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Removal of difficulties.
<section><tid>1495512</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act as appear to it 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1117745</tid>
<number>2</number>An order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to have 
retrospective effect from a date not earlier than the date appointed 
under sub- section (1) of section 4A.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150338</tid>
<number> 41</number> Offences.
<section><tid>1667449</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever in any bill of lading, warehouse  
receipt or other instrument given to the Corporation where by security 
is given or is purported to be given to the Corporation for any 
accommodation granted by it under this Act wilfully makes any false 
statement, or knowingly permits any false statement to be made, shall 
be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two 
years or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees or with 
both.

</section>

<section><tid>1378569</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever without the consent in writing of the Corporation 
uses the name of the Corporation in any prospectus or advertisement 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or 
with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1299199</tid>
<number>3</number>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable 
under this Act otherwise than on a complaint in writing signed by an 
officer of the Corporation authorized by the Board in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1068121</tid>
<number>41A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act 
and of any rules or orders made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other 
law for the time being in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62I</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 21. 
2. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 29.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


force or in the memorandum or articles of association of an industrial 
concern or in any other instrument having effect by virtue of any law 
other than this Act, but save as aforesaid the provisions of this Act 
shall be in addition to, and in derogation of, any other law for the 
time being applicable to an industrial concern.]



</article>



<article><tid>440106</tid>
<number> 42</number> Power of Central Government to make rules. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>394775</tid>
<number>1</number>] The  
Central Government may, in consultation with the Development Bank and 
by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules not inconsistent 
with the provisions of this Act, to give effect to the provisions of 
this Act, and where there is any inconsistency between the rules and 
the regulations made under this Act the rules shall prevail.

</section>

<section><tid>494438</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
from or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1201455</tid>
<number> 43</number> Power of Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>1569810</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may,  
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> with the previous approval of the Development Bank],[ and by 
notification in the official Gazette] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> make regulations not 
inconsistent with this Act <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> and the rules made thereunder] to 
provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient 
for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>635399</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for-

<subsection><tid>527241</tid>
<number>a</number>the holding and conduct of elections under this Act, 
including the final decision of doubts or disputes regarding 
the validity of elections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1007117</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which the 
first allotment of shares of the Corporation shall be made;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62J</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 42 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 66 of 
<year>1960</year>. s. 8. 
2. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1975</year>, s. 23, for certain words (w. e. f. 16- 2-  
  <year>1976</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1960</year>, s. 8. 
4. Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 21, for certain words. 
5. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
6. Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 30.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>749707</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which the 
shares of the Corporation may be held and transferred, and 
generally all matters relating to the rights and duties of 
shareholders;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>146029</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which general meetings shall be convened, the 
procedure to be followed thereat and the manner in which 
voting rights may be exercised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225638</tid>
<number>e</number>the calling of meetings of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board], fees for attending 
meetings thereof and the conduct of business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337595</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the delegation of powers and functions of the Board to 
the Chairman <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, Managing Director] or to officers of the 
Corporation;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1062466</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner and terms of issue and redemption of bonds and 
debentures by the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693926</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions which the Corporation may impose in granting 
loans or advances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1448448</tid>
<number>h</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the conditions and limitations subject to which the 
Corporation may enter into business under the proviso to 
clause (iii) of sub- section (3) of section 26;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>395001</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner and conditions subject to which the Corporation 
may borrow in foreign currency from foreign lenders;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1375532</tid>
<number>j</number>the forms of returns and statements required under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>951989</tid>
<number>k</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the duties and conduct, salaries, allowances and 
conditions of service of officers and other employees and of 
advisers and agents of the Corporation;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>523178</tid>
<number>kk</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the establishment and maintenance of provident or other 
benefit funds for employees of the Corporation;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>319728</tid>
<number>l</number>the disclosure of interest, direct or indirect, of a 
Director in any industrial concern;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1208065</tid>
<number>m</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the taking over of the management of any industrial 
concern on a breach of its agreement with the Corporation 
and the powers and duties of Directors <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or Administrator] 
under section 30C;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62K</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1972</year>, s. 21, for" Board and of the Central 
Committee". 
2. Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 22. 
3. Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1986</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 2. 2. <year>1987</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1982</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 12. 3. <year>1982</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1955</year>, s. 22, for the former cl. (k). 
6. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1949</year>, s. 3. 
7. Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1952</year>, s. 30, for the former cl. (m).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>68699</tid>
<number>n</number>appointment of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> advisory] committees for technical and 
other advice for purposes of this Act, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fees for attending 
meetings thereof and the conduct of business thereat];
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162157</tid>
<number>nn</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the election of an auditor under sub- section (1) of 
section 34;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>610465</tid>
<number>o</number>generally, the efficient conduct of the affairs of the 
Corporation.
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>630386</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>