<act><title>

THE 
    POLICE (INCITEMENT TO DISAFFECTION) ACT, 1922</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Police (Incitement to Disaffection) Act, 1922. 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India, except 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the territories 
    which immediately before 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B 
    States].]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in any State or part of a State on such date<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as 
    the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct.
  
 

State amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
    sub-section (2) of section 1, after the expression ‘except the territories 
    which immediately before the 1st November, 1956 were comprised in Part B 
    States’ add ‘other than the territories specified in sub-section (1) of 
    section 3 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956’.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh Act 
    23 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch. (1-2-1960)]
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
    section 1—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  in sub-section 
    (2), after ‘Part B States’, add ‘other than the Madhya Bharat and Sironja 
    regions of the State of Madhya Pradesh’;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  
    for sub-section (3), substitute the following:—
 
        “(3) 
    It shall be in force in all such areas in Madhya Pradesh in which it was in 
    force immediately before the commencement of Madhya Pradesh Second Extension 
    of Laws Act, 1961 (40 of 1961), and shall come into force in other areas, on 
    such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint”.
 
[Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 
    40 of 1961 First Schedule, Part A, Item 5.]
 
Maharashtra, Gujarat.—In 
    its application to the State of Maharashtra in section 1.—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  To sub-section 
    (2), add the following proviso:—
 
        “Provided that on the commencement of the Police (Incitement to 
    Disaffection) (Bombay Extension and Amendment) Act, 1958, it shall extend to 
    the Saurashtra and Hyderabad areas of the State of Bombay”.
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>ii</number>  To sub-section 
    (3), add the following proviso:—
 
        “Provided that on the commencement of the Police (Incitement to 
    Disaffection) (Bombay Extension and Amendment) Act, 1958, it shall come into 
    force in that part of the Saurashtra area of the State of Bombay in which 
    the Police (Incitement to Disaffection) Act, 1922, as modified and applied 
    to that area by the State of Saurashtra (Application of Central and Bombay 
    Acts) Ordinance, 1948, was in force immediately before such commencement.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 77 of 
    1958, sec. 3 (7-10-1958): Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87  
    (1-5-1960)]
 <subsubsection>
<number>Meghalaya</number>—In section 1 
    omit the sub-section (3)
 
[Vide Meghalaya A.L.O. 
    (No. 1) of 1974, Sch. (w.r.e.f. 21-1-1972)]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In its 
    application to the added territories in the State of Madras, in sub-section 
    (2) of section 1, omit ‘other than the territories specified in sub-section 
    (1) of section 3 of the State Reorganisation Act, 1956’.
 
[Vide Madras (Ad Terr.) 
    A.L.O. 1961]
 
 







 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In this Act, the 
    expression “member of a police-force” means any person appointed or enrolled 
    for the performance of police duties under any enactment specified in the 
    Schedule. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Penalty for causing disaffection, etc.—Whoever, 
    intentionally causes or attempts to cause, or does any act which he knows is 
    likely to cause disaffection towards <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] 
    the Government establishment by law in <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[India] amongst the 
    members of a police-force, or induces or attempts to induce or does any act 
    which he knows is likely to induce, any member of a police-force to withhold 
    his services or to commit a breach of discipline, shall be punished with 
    imprisonment which may extend to six months,  or with fine which may extend 
    to two hundred rupees, or with both.
 

    Explanation.—Expression of 
    disapprobation of the measures of the Government with a view to obtain their 
    alteration by lawful means, or of disapprobation of the administrative or 
    other action of the Government, do not constitute an offence under this 
    section unless they cause or are made for the purpose of causing or are 
    likely to cause disaffection.
  
 

state amendment
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—(a) Section 
    3 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof and in sub-section (1) so renumbered 
    for the portion beginning with the words “shall be punished” and ending with 
    the words “or with both” the following portion substituted, namely:—
 
        “shall, on conviction, 
    be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or 
    with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both:
 
        Provided that, in the 
    absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be mentioned in 
    the judgment of the Court, such imprisonment shall not be less than six 
    months and such time shall not be less than five hundred rupees”.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> After sub-section (1) of 
    section 3 add the following sub-section (2), namely:—
 
        “(2) All 
    offences under this Act shall be cognisable and non-bailable”.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 23 
    of 1983, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 18-1-1983)]
  









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Saving of acts done by police associations 
      and other persons for certain purposes.—Nothing shall be deemed to be an offence under 
      this Act which is done in good faith.—  
 <section><number>a</number>    for the 
      purposes of promoting the welfare or interest of any member of a 
      police-force by inducing him to withhold his services in any manner 
      authorised by law; or  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    by or on 
      behalf of any association formed for the purpose of furthering the 
      interests of members of a police-force as such where the association has 
      been authorised or recognised by the Government and the act done is done 
      under any rules or articles of association which have been approved by the 
      Government.  
  
 state amendment
 Madhya Pradesh.—After section 4 
      insert the following section, namely:—
  “4A. 
      Offences to be cognizable and non-bailable.—(1) Every offence under 
      this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
 <subsection>        <number>2</number> No bail 
      shall be granted by any Court under this section unless prosecution has 
      been afforded reasonable opportunity of being heard in the 
      matter.”
 [Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 15 
      of  1981, sec. 4 (5-5-1981)]
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Sanction to trial of offences by subordinate Courts.—No 
    Court shall proceed to the trial of any offence under this Act except with 
    the previous sanction, or on the complaint, of the District Magistrate or, 
    in the case of a Presidency-town, 

    1[***] of the 
    Commissioner of Police. —No 
    Court shall proceed to the trial of any offence under this Act except with 
    the previous sanction, or on the complaint, of the District Magistrate or, 
    in the case of a Presidency-town, 

    1[***] of the 
    Commissioner of Police." 
  
 

State amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
    section 5 for the words ‘of the District Magistrate or, in the case of a 
    Presidency-town, of the Commissioner of Police’, substitute ‘of the District 
    Collector or, in the case of the cities of Hyderabad and Secunderabad, of 
    the Commissioner of Police’.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh Act 
    23 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch. (1-2-1960)]
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
    5—
 
             a)  after the words 
    a Presidency-town, insert “or any other area under the charge of a 
    Commissioner of Police”.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 56 of 
    1959, sec. 3 and Sch. (4-1-1960)]
 <subsection>
           <number>b</number>  delete the words 
    “or on the complaint”
 
[Vide Maha. Act 23 of 
    1983, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 18-1-1983)]
 
Tamil Nadu.—(i) In 
    section 5 (as amended by Andhra Pradesh Act 23 of 1958), for the words “the 
    cities of Hyderabad and Secunderabad”, substitute the words ‘a 
    Presidency-town.’
 
[Vide Mad. (Added 
    Territorie) A.L.O., 1961]
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> In section 5 (as amended by 
    Andhra Pradesh Act 23 of 1958, for the words, “District Collector”, 
    substitute the words “District Magistrate”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 8 of 
    1964, sec. 4 and Sch. II (10-6-1964)]
  








 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Trial of 
    cases.—
<section><number>1</number> No Court inferior to 
    that of a Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class shall try 
    and offence under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything, contained in Chapter XXII of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898 (Act 5 of 1898), no offence under this Act shall be triable 
    summarily.  
  
 

State amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
    sub-section (1) of section 6, omit the words ‘Presidency Magistrate or’.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh Act 
    23 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch. (1-2-1960)]
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For section 
    6 substitute the following section 6.
 
        “6. Trial of 
    cases.—(1) No Court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or 
    Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence uner this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, any Metropolitan 
    Magistrate or any Judicial Magistrate of the first class may, if he thinks 
    fit, try in a summary way all or any of the offences under this Act, and the 
    provisions of sections 262 to 265 (both inclusive) of the said code shall, 
    so far as may apply to such trial:
 
        Provided that where any 
    case is tried summarily and the accused is convicted under this Act, no 
    sentence of imprisonment for a term exceeding three months shall be passed 
    by the Magistrate concerned and the provision for awarding punishment of 
    minimum amount of fine under this Act shall not apply”.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 23 
    of 1983, sec. 6 (w.r.e.f 18-1-1983)]
 
Maharashtra, Gujarat.—After 
    section 6, insert the following section:—
 
        “7. Repeal 
    and saving.—The Police (Incitement to Disaffection) Act, 1922, as 
    modified and applied to the Saurashtra area of the State of Bombay by the 
    State of Saurashtra (Application of Central and Bombay Acts) Ordinance, 
    1948, is hereby repealed:
 
           Provided that such 
    repeal shall not affect—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  the previous 
    operation of the law so repealed, or
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>b</number>  any punishment 
    incurred in respect of any offence committed against any of the provisions 
    of the law so repealed, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>c</number>  any 
    investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of such punishment as 
    aforesaid; and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
    instituted, continued or enforced, and any such punishment may be imposed as 
    if this Act had not been passed.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 77 of 
    1958, sec. 5 (7-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 89 (1-5-1960)]
 
Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh.—In 
    section 6, in its application to the State of Punjab (including Haryana and 
    Chandigarh), for the words ‘Magistrate of the first class’, substitute the 
    words ‘Judicial Magistrate of the first class’.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 25 of 
    1964, sec. 2 and Sch. (2-10-1964)]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In its 
    application to territories added to Tamil Nadu by C.A. 56 of 1959, section 
    6, before “Magistrate of the first class’, insert the words ‘Presidency 
    Magistrate or’ which were omitted by Andhra Pradesh Act 23 of 1958.
 
[Vide Madras (Added 
    Territories) A.L.O., 1961 (w.r.e.f 1-4-1960)]

 
  


</subsection></section></article><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    THE POLICE (INCITEMENT TO DISAFFECTION) ACT, 1922
 



 



 THE 
    SCHEDULE
 


(See section 2)
 
 
 
Year
 
No.
 
Short Title

 
  
 Acts of the 
        Governor-General in Council

 
 1859
 XXV
 The Madras District Police 
        Act, 1859

 
 1861
 V
 The Police Act, 1861

 
 1[***]
 1[***]
 1[***]

 
 1888
 III
 The Police Act, 1861

 
 1892
 V
 The Bengal Military Police 
        Act, 1892

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Madras Act

 
 1888
 III
 The Madras City Police 
        Act, 1888

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Bombay Acts

 
 1890
 IV
 The Bombay District Police 
        Act, 1890

 
 1902
 IV
 The City of Bombay Police 
        Act, 1890

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Bengal Acts

 
 1866
 II
 The Calcutta Suburban 
        Police Act, 1866

 
 1866
 IV
 The Calcutta Police Act, 
        1866

 
 1890
 III
 The Calcutta Port Act, 
        1890

 
 1920
 II
 The Eastern Frontier 
        Rifles (Bengal Battalion) Act, 1920

 
 2[***]
 2[***]
 2[***]

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Assam Act

 
 1920
 I
 The Assam Rifles Act, 1920

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Regulation by the 
        Governor-General in Council

 
 1888
 II
 The Andaman and Nicobar 
        Islands Military Police Regulation, 1988


 

 
 



State Amendments
 


Maharashtra, Gujarat.—I. In the 
    Schedule, under the heading ‘Bombay Acts’, for the entries—
 


‘1890                     
    IV                       The Bombay District Police Act, 1890
 


1902                      
    IV                       The City of Bombay Police Act, 1902’
 


Substitute—
 


      
    “1951                    XXII                      The Bombay Police Act, 
    1951”
 


[Vide Bombay Act 21 of 1954, sec. 3 and 
    Sch. II (8-4-1954); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87]
 


II. In the Schedule, under the heading ‘Bombay 
    Acts’, add the following:—
 


      
    “1951                  XXXVIII                    The Bombay State Reserve 
    Police Force  

         Act, 1951”
 


[Vide Bombay Act 77 of 1958, sec. 6 
    (7-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87]
 

 
 


-------------------------------
 


     1.   The entry relating to 
    the Burma Military Police Act, 1887 omitted by the A.C.A.O. 1948.
 


     2.   The entry relating to 
    the Rangoon Police Act, 1899 omitted by the A.C.A.O. 1948.
 



    ---------------------------------
 

 
  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
    sub-section (2).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1956, for 
    “Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Came into force in Assam on 
    25-1-1923 (vide Assam Gazette, 1923, Pt. II, p. 113); in Himachal Pradesh on 
    1-6-1974 (vide H.P. Gazette, 1974, Pt. I, p. 1144); in Punjab on 
    13-3-1930 (Vide Punjab Gazette, 1930, Pt. I, p. 342); in Bihar and 
    Orissa (including the Santhal Parganas) on 15-5-1930 (vide Bihar and 
    Orissa, Gazette, Extra., 1930); in the Bombay Presidency on 5-6-1930); (vide 
    Bombay Gazette, 1930, Pt. I, p. 1394); in the Union Territory, of Andaman 
    and Nicobar Islands on 1-5-1966 (vide  Andaman and Nicobar Gazette, 
    Extra., 1966); in the Union Territory of Delhi on 13-3-1975 (vide 
    Delhi Gazette, Extra., 1975, Pt. IV, p. 75); in Madhya Bharat and Sironja 
    regions of Madhya Pradesh on 1-1-1966 (vide M.P. Gazette, 1965, Pt. 
    I, p. 1818); in Madhya Pradesh on 2-6-1979 (vide M.P. Gazette, 
    Extra., p. 1927); in the Union Territory of Goa, Daman and Diu on 1-2-1965 (vide 
    Goa Gazette, 1965, Sr. I, p. 3); in the Union Territory of Laccadive, 
    Minicoy and Amindivi Islands on 1-10-1967 (vide Gazette of India, 
    Extra, Pt-II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 1527); in the Union Territory of Pondicherry 
    on 1-8-1968 (vide Pondicherry Gazette, Extra., 1968); in West Bengal 
    on 15-9-1976 (vide Calcutta Gazette, Extra.; 1976, Pt. I. p. 2755).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   The words “His Majesty 
    or” omitted by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by the A.C.A.O. 
    1948, for “British India or British Burma”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   The words “or the town 
    of Rangoon” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>