<act><tid>1691092</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT MANAGEMENT OF PRIVATE ESTATES ACT, <year>1892</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1892</year>
[ 25th October, <year>1892</year>.]

An Act to provide for the levy of a rate on private estates under the 
management of the Government to meet the cost of supervision and 
management.





<article><tid>1386506</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and extent.
<section><tid>1535527</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Government  
Management Private Estates Act, <year>1892</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1733359</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>498903</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1881446</tid>
<number>1</number>" immoveable property" includes land, buildings, 
hereditary allowances, rights to ways, lights, ferries, 
fisheries or any other benefit to arise out of land, 
and things attached to the earth or permanently 
fastened to anything which is attached to the earth but 
not standing timber, growing crops or grass;

</section>

<section><tid>1171559</tid>
<number>2</number>" gross income" includes all receipts of every kind in 
produce or cash, except money borrowed, recoveries of 
principal and the proceeds of sale of immoveable 
property or of moveable property properly classed as 
capital; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>140</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This sub- section has been successively amended by Act 13 of <year>1898</year> 
and adapted by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, A. O. <year>1950</year> and the Adaptation of Laws 
 (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> to read as above. 
2 The word" and" and sub- section (3), rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>623498</tid>
<number>3</number>" private estates under Government management" include--

<subsection><tid>1014742</tid>
<number>a</number>estates under the Court of Wards;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162224</tid>
<number>b</number>encumbered estates under Government 
management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>735089</tid>
<number>c</number>estates attached for default of payment 
of Government revenue;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>280056</tid>
<number>d</number>minors' estates placed under the 
guardianship of a revenue- officer of the 
Government by a Civil Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1476201</tid>
<number>e</number>estates managed by a Collector in 
pursuance of any order made under the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of 
Civil Procedure; and (14 of <year>1882</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1167925</tid>
<number>f</number>all other estates made over to or taken 
under the management of a revenue- officer of the 
Government as such under any law for the time 
being in force or in virtue of any agreement.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1615657</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to levy rate. It shall be lawful for the State 
Government--
<section><tid>1234104</tid>
<number>1</number>to levy on all private estates under Government 
management a rate, not exceeding five per cent. on the 
gross income, calculated, as nearly as may be possible, 
to cover--

<subsection><tid>1332496</tid>
<number>a</number>the cost of all Government establishments 
in so far as they may be employed in the 
supervision or management of such estates other 
than establishments specially entertained for the 
supervision or management of any particular estate 
or group of estates, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1606187</tid>
<number>b</number>all contingent expenditure incurred in 
consequence of such supervision or management;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>842324</tid>
<number>2</number>from time to time to vary such rate; and

</section>

<section><tid>895751</tid>
<number>3</number>to reduce or remit such rate in any special case or 
cases as may be equitable;
Provided that, in deciding the amount of the rate to be levied 
under this Act on any particular estate or group of estates, the State 
Government shall consider the expenditure incurred on special 
establishments for such estate or estates.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>803705</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to levy special charges. In cases where an officer of 
the Government is employed to give legal advice or to audit accounts 
on behalf of any estate, the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>141</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>). 
2 For instance of notification issued under this section, see C. P. 
R. and O.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


State Government, if it considers the services rendered to be of a 
special nature, may, in its discretion, direct a special charge to be 
made against that estate on account of such services, irrespective of 
the rate leviable under the last foregoing section.



</article>



<article><tid>1296226</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving as to special expenditure. Nothing in this act shall 
apply to the cost of establishments specially entertained or to 
expenditure of any description specially incurred in respect of any 
particular estate or estates.


</article>



<article><tid>1555454</tid>
<number>6</number>Validation of levy of past rates. All rates for general 
supervision or management levied by any State Government before the 
commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been levied under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1774637</tid>
<number>7</number>Power to make rules. The State Government may make any rules 
and issue any orders which may be necessary for carrying this Act into 
effect, and which are consistent therewith.


</article>



<article><tid>1997322</tid>
<number>8</number>Exemption from jurisdiction of Courts. Where any Government 
establishment is employed in such supervision as aforesaid, the State 
Government shall be the sole judge of the cost attributable to such 
employment, and its decision thereon shall not be questioned in any 
Court of Law or otherwise.


</article>



<article><tid>364795</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Repeal.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1914</year> (10 of  
  <year>1914</year>), s. 3 and Sch. II.
</article>



 </act>