<act><tid>1265882</tid>
<title>THE REMITTANCES OF FOREIGN EXCHANGE AND INVESTMENT IN FOREIGN 
EXCHANGEBONDS (IMMUNITIES AND EXEMPTIONS) ACT, <year>1991</year></title>

NO. 41 OF <year>1991</year> 
[ 18th September, <year>1991</year>.]
An Act to provide for certain immunities to persons receiving 
remittances in foregin exchange and to persons owning the Foreign 
Exchange Bonds and for certain exemptions from direct taxes in 
relation to such remittances and bonds and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS the position relation to balance of payments has become 
difficult and it is necessary to attract large inflow of foreign 
exchange;

AND WHEREAS With a view to attracting such inflow of foreign 
exchange, it is expedient to provide for certain immunities and 
exemptions to render it possible for certain persons to receive the 
said remittances in foreign exchange and to own the said Bonds;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>245942</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1328371</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Remittances of Foreign Exchange and Investment in Foreign Exchange 
Bonds (Immunities and Exemptions) Act, <year>1991</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1497314</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.
CHAP 
REMITTANCES OF FOREIGN EXCHANGE

CHAPTER II

REMITTANCES OF FOREIGN EXCHANGE



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1942531</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Chapter, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>910256</tid>
<number>a</number>" recipient" means a person as defined in clause (31) of 
section 2 of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>.) who receives 
any remittance under this Chapter;

</section>

<section><tid>545713</tid>
<number>b</number>" remittance" means remittance made in foreign exchange 
by any person resident outside India to a person resident in 
India on or after the date of commencement of this Act but before 
the specified date, in the form of draft, traveller' s cheques, 
cheques drawn on banks situated outside India telegraphic 
transfers, mail transfers, money orders or by way of transfer 
from Non- resident (External) Account, Foreign Currency Non- 
resident Account or Foreign Currency Non- resident Special Deposit 
Account maintained in India under the rules made under the 
Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>. (46 of <year>1973</year>.)
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause," specified 
date" means the 1st day of December, <year>1991</year> or such other later 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;


</section>

<section><tid>615732</tid>
<number>c</number>all other words and expressions used in this Chapter but 
not defined and defined in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 
 <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>.) shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in that Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1259018</tid>
<number> 3</number> Immunities.
<section><tid>668115</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any  
other law for the time being in force,--

<subsection><tid>1075089</tid>
<number>a</number>no recipient, who claims immunity under this Chapter in 
accordance with such scheme as the Reserve Bank of India may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify for the purposes of 
receiving remittances under this Chapter, shall be required to 
disclose, for any purpose whatsoever, the nature and source of 
the remittance made to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1676497</tid>
<number>b</number>no inquiry or investigation shall be commenced against 
the recipient under any such law on the ground that he has 
received such remittance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>629429</tid>
<number>c</number>the fact that the recipient has received a remittance 
shall not be taken into account and shall be inadmissible as 
evidence in any proceedings relating to any offence or the 
imposition of any penalty under any such law.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>488356</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply--

<subsection><tid>455910</tid>
<number>a</number>to any foreign exchange which is required to be brought 
into India under any of the provisions of--

<subsubsection><tid>1519995</tid>
<number>i</number>the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>; (46 of  
  <year>1973</year>.) or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>591440</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) read with 
the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>, (46 of <year>1973</year>.) if 
the period within which such foreign exchange is to be 
brought into India has not expired or where such period has 
been extended, in any manner, by the Central Government or 
the Reserve Bank of India or any other authority, such 
extended period has not expired on the date of commencement 
of this Act;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>418337</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to prosecution for any offence punishable 
under Chapter IX or Chapter XVII of the Indian Penal Code, (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.) the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, <year>1985</year>, 
 (61 of <year>1985</year>.) the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities 
 (Prevention) Act, <year>1987</year>, (28 of <year>1987</year>.) the Prevention of 
Corruption Act, <year>1988</year> (49 of <year>1988</year>.) or for the purpose of 
enforcement of any civil liability.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1509875</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall cause the scheme notified under 
clause (a) of sub- section (1) to be laid, as soon as may be after it 
is notified, before each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1391222</tid>
<number> 4</number> Remittances not to be taken into account in certain cases. 
Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of section 3,--
<section><tid>424102</tid>
<number>a</number>any remittance received under this Chapter shall not be 
taken into account for the purpose of any proceeding under the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>.) and, in particular, the 
recipient shall not be entitled to claim any set- off or relief in 
any assessment, re- assessment, appeal, reference or other 
proceeding under that Act or to re- open any assessment or re- 
assesment made under that Act on the ground that he has received 
such remittance.
Explanation.-- For the avoidance of doubt, it is hereby 
declared that the provisions of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>.) will apply to any income which accrues or arises or is 
deemed to accrue or arise to the recipient from the amount of the 
remittance;


</section>

<section><tid>1200891</tid>
<number>b</number>any remittance received under this Chapter shall not 
form part of the assets of any assessee for the purposes of 
computing his net wealth under the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of  
  <year>1957</year>.) in relation to any assessment year commencing before the 
 1st day of April, <year>1992</year>.
CHAP 
INVESTMENT IN FOREIGN EXCHANGE BONDS

CHAPTER III

INVESTMENT IN FOREIGN EXCHANGE BONDS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>82169</tid>
<number> 5</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>1296986</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Chapter, unless the context otherwise  
requires,--

<subsection><tid>1880839</tid>
<number>a</number>" Foreign Exchange Bonds" means the Bonds, issued by the 
State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank of India 
Act, <year>1955</year> (28 of <year>1955</year>.) in accordance with such scheme as the 
Reserve Bank of India may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify in this behalf, the investment wherein is made 
on or after the date of commencement of this Act but before the 
specified date.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause," specified 
date" means the 1st day of December, <year>1991</year> or such other later 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>61015</tid>
<number>b</number>" non- resident Indian" means an individual, being a 
citizen of India or a person of Indian origin who is resident 
outside India.
Explanation 1.-- A person shall be deemed to be of Indian 
origin if--


<subsubsection><tid>1445652</tid>
<number>i</number>he, or either of his parents or any of his grand- 
parents, was a citizen of India by virtue of the 
Constitution or the Citizenship Act, <year>1955</year>; (57 of <year>1955</year>.) or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>239832</tid>
<number>ii</number>he at any time held an Indian passport:
Provided that the nationals of Pakistan or Bangladesh shall 
not be deemed to be of Indian origin.

Explanation 2.-- A spouse (not being a national of Pakistan  
  or Bangladesh) of a person of Indian origin shall also be deemed 
to be of Indian origin;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>938568</tid>
<number>c</number>" overseas corporate body" means any institution, 
association or body, whether incorporated or not, established 
under the laws of a country outside India wherein any non- 
resident Indian has any interest;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>392154</tid>
<number>d</number>all other words and expressions used in this Chapter but 
not defined and defined in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 
<year>1973</year>, (46 of <year>1973</year>.) shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in that Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1094783</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall cause the scheme notified under 
clause (a) of sub- section (1) to be laid, as soon as may be after it 
is notified, before each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1896291</tid>
<number> 6</number> Immunities.
<section><tid>940750</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the  
Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, (27 of <year>1957</year>.) the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year>, (18 of  
  <year>1958</year>.) the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act, <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>.) and the Foreign Contribution 
 (Regulation) Act, <year>1976</year>,-- (46 of <year>1976</year>.)

<subsection><tid>290601</tid>
<number>a</number>no non- resident Indian or overseas corporate body who or 
which owns the Foreign Exchange Bonds or any person resident in 
India to whom a gift of such Bonds has been made by such 
nonresident Indian or overseas corporate body, shall be required 
to disclose, for any purpose whatsoever, the nature and source of 
the investment in such Bonds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1703931</tid>
<number>b</number>no inquiry or investigation shall be commenced against 
any of the persons referred to in clause (a) under any of the 
said Acts on the ground that such person owns such Bonds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>411971</tid>
<number>c</number>the fact that any of the persons referred to in clause 
 (a) owns such Bonds shall not be taken into account and shall be 
inadmissible as evidence in any proceedings relating to any 
offence or the imposition of any penalty under any of the said 
Acts.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>364909</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply to foreign exchange 
which is required to be brought into India under any of the provisions 
of--

<subsection><tid>496089</tid>
<number>i</number>the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>; (46 of <year>1973</year>.) 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1478114</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) read with the 
Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>, (46 of <year>1973</year>.) if the 
period within which such foreign exchange is to be brought into 
India has not expired or where such period has been extended, in 
any manner, by the Central Government or the Reserve Bank of 
India or any other authority, such extended period has not 
expired on the date of commencement of this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1767283</tid>
<number> 7</number> Foreign Exchange Bonds not to be taken into account in certain 
cases. Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of 
section 6,--
<section><tid>1883592</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>.) 
shall not apply to any interest accruing in relation to the 
Foreign Exchange Bonds;

</section>

<section><tid>457401</tid>
<number>b</number>the provisions of the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>.) 
shall not apply in relation to the Foreign Exchange Bonds;

</section>

<section><tid>1880439</tid>
<number>c</number>the provisions of the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>.) 
shall not apply where any non- resident Indian becomes a resident 
in India and makes a gift of the Foreign Exchange Bonds.
V. S. RAMA DEVI, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>