<act> 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
 

 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the State  Financial Corporations (Appeal to the Central Government) 
Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  


</section></article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the State Financial Corporations 
Act, 1951 (63 of 1951);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “appellant” means any person aggrieved against 
the order of refusal of the Board made under sub-section (4) of section 5 of 
the Act and preferring appeal in terms of section 5(5) of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Authorised representative” means a person duly 
authorised by the appellant or the Board or any other party to the appeal to 
appear, plead and act, or to file the appeal or reply or any information or 
document, as the case may be, on their respective behalf before the Central 
Government;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “Form” means a Form appended hereto;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “party” means the appellant, or any other 
opposite party to the appeal including the Board, or any other person who is 
otherwise opposite party to the appeal, and includes their respective 
authorised representative;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  all other expressions used but not defined in 
these rules, but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.

</section></article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>3</number> Procedure for filing 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every appeal under 
sub-section (5) of section 5 of the Act shall be preferred by the appellant or 
his authorised representative to the Central Government as nearly as possible 
in Form.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal under sub-rule 
(1) shall be deemed to have been preferred to the Central Government on the 
date on which it is received in the office of the Secretary to the Government 
of India in the department dealing with Economic Affairs, New Delhi.

</section></article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>4</number> Time within which appeal 
is to be preferred.—An appeal shall 
be preferred by the appellant within a period of thirty days from the date of 
receipt of the order of refusal of the Board made under sub-section (4) of 
section 5 of the Act:
 Provided that the Central 
Government may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of 
thirty days if it is satisfied, based on such cogent materials on record, that 
there was sufficient cause for not preferring appeal within that period.

</article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>5</number> Payment of fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 500.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The amount of fees shall be 
deposited by means of a Bank Draft drawn in favour of Pay &amp; Accounts Officer 
(Banking) and deposited with State Bank of India, Parliament Street, New Delhi 
under the Major Head:
               “0070—Other 
Administrative Services”
               “502—Service and 
Service Fees”

</section></article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>6</number> Contents of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal filed under rule 3 shall be written in English or Hindi 
accompanied by the certified copy of the order of refusal of the Board appealed 
against and authority of the authorised representative and shall set forth 
concisely, under distinct heads, the grounds of appeal which shall be numbered 
consecutively and whole memorandum of appeal along with supporting documents or 
annexures thereof  shall be on due affidavit and copy of the appeal shall be 
served on the other party to the appeal and acknowledgement thereof filed with 
the memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal, reference, 
application, representation, document or other matters contained in any 
language other than English or Hindi shall be accepted by the Central 
Government, unless the same is accompanied by a certified true translation 
thereof in English or Hindi.

</section></article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
 <article></article><article><number>7</number> Furnishing of information 
or documents.—The Central Government 
may, while considering the appeal, require any party to the appeal, to furnish 
such further information and documents, as it considers necessary within such 
time as may be granted by the Central Government.

</article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
 <article></article><article><number>8</number> Date and place of hearing 
of appeal to be communicated.—The 
Central Government shall communicate, while considering the appeal, to the 
parties concerned, the date and place of the hearing  of the appeal.

</article> 
 
 
 

The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>9</number> Hearing of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, after giving the parties to the appeal, an 
opportunity of being heard and, hearing the appeal on the day fixed or any 
other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, pass such orders thereon as it 
thinks fit to meet the ends of justice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case the appellant does 
not appear in person or through an authorised representative when the appeal is 
called for hearing, the Central Government may either dismiss the appeal for 
default or dispose of the appeal  on merits ex-parte:
 Provided that if the appellant 
on an application satisfies the Central Government that there was sufficient 
cause for his non-appearance, when the appeal was called for hearing, the 
Central Government shall make an order setting aside the ex-parte order 
and restore the appeal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The order passed under 
sub-rules (1) and (2) shall be in writing and shall be signed and dated and 
shall be communicated to the parties.

</section></article><form>
 


 


 



The State Financial CorporationS (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 2003
 

 
 

Form
 

(see rule 3)
 

Appeal under sub-section (5) of section 5 of the State 
Financial  

CorporationS Act, 1951 (63 of 
1951)
 

Date of Filing ........................................
 

Registration No. ....................................    
 

Before the Secretary to the Government of India in the  

Department of  Economic Affairs, New Delhi
 

Between
 


A.B.........................................        Appellant(s)
 

And
 


The Board [mention here name of the  

      State Financial Corporation/other(s)...............................  
        Opposite party(ies)          
 

[mention the name and address of the party(ies) here]
 

The appellant(s) named above, begs to prefer the appeal under 
sub-section (5) of section 5 of the State Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 
of 1951), against the order of refusal of the Board of (Mention the name of the 
State Financial Corporation) passed under section 5 (4) of the said Act, on the 
following facts and grounds
 


Facts
 

(Mention briefly the facts of the case here. Enclose 
certified copy of the order of refusal by the Board, and copies of other 
relevant documents, if any)
 


Grounds
 

(Mention here the grounds on which the appeal is preferred)
 

Matter not pending with any other court etc.—The appellant 
declares that the matter regarding which this appeal has been made is not 
pending before any court of law or any other authority or Tribunal.
 


Prayer
 

In the light of what is stated above, the appellant(s) prays 
that he/she/it may be granted the following relief.
 


Relief Sought
 

(specify the relief sought)
 

The amount of Rs. ........................ as fees for this 
appeal has been deposited vide challan No. ............ 
dated.............. with ................... branch of the State Bank of India.
 

List of Enclosures: 
 

         1.  Certified copy 
of the order of refusal passed by the Board under section 5 (4) of the Act.
 

         2. Authority of the 
Authorised Representative.
 

         3.  
Receipt/acknowledgement showing service of copy of appeal on the other 
party(ies) to the appeal.
 

         4.  Other document(s) etc...........
 


Verification
 

I do hereby solemnly affirm and state that all the averments 
contained above are true to the best of my belief, knowledge and information.
 

Place.....................
 


Date...................... Signature of Appellant(s) or 
 

his/their Authorised 
representative.
 


Affidavit
 

 

</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>