<act> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 19571
  
 <article><number>1</number> Title and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Industrial Disputes (Central) Rules, 1957.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They extend to Union 
territories in relation to all industrial disputes and to the States in relation 
only to an industrial dispute concerning—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  any industry 
carried on by or under the authority of the Central Government or by a railway 
company; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>  a banking or an 
insurance company, a mine, an oilfield, or a major port; or 
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>  any such 
controlled industry as may be specified under section 2(a)(i) of the Act by the 
Central Government:
 

        2[***]
  



</subsection></section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>2</number> Interpretation.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>        <number>a</number> “Act” means the 
Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947);
 </section><section>        <number>b</number> “Chairman” means 
the Chairman of a Board or Court or, if the Court consists of one person only, 
such person;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number> “Committee” 
means a Works Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the 
Act;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number> “form” means a 
form in the Schedule to these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number> “section” means 
a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number> in relation to 
an industrial dispute in a Union territory, for which the appropriate Government 
is the Central Government, reference to the Central Government or the Government 
of India shall be construed as a reference to the Administrator of the 
territory, and reference to the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central), Regional 
Labour Commissioner (Central) and the 

1[Assistant Labour Commissioner 
(Central)] shall be construed as reference to the appropriate authority, 
appointed in that behalf by the Administrator of the territory;
 

         2[(g)  with reference to clause 
(g) of section 2, it is hereby prescribed that—
 <subsection>              <number>i</number>  in relation to an industry, not being an 
industry referred to in sub-clause (ii), carried on by or under the authority of 
a Department of the Central or a State Government, the officer-in-charge of the 
industrial establishment shall be the ‘employer’ in respect of that 
establishment; and
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>ii</number>  in relation to an industry concerning 
railways, carried on by or under the authority of a Department of the Central 
Government,—
 <subsubsection>                  <number>a</number>  in the case of establishment of a 
Zonal Railway, the General Manager of that Railway shall be the ‘employer’ in 
respect of regular railway servants other than casual labour;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                  <number>b</number>  in the case of an establishment 
independent of a Zonal Railway, the officer-in-charge of the establishment shall 
be the ‘employer’ in respect of regular railway servants other than casual 
labour; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                  <number>c</number>  the District Officer-in-charge or the 
Divisional Personnel Officer or the Personnel Officer shall be the ‘employer’ in 
respect of casual labour employed on Zonal Railway or any other railway 
establishment independent of a Zonal Railway.]
  



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>3</number> Application.—An 
application under sub-section (2) of section 10 for the reference of an 
industrial dispute to a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal shall be made in Form A and shall be delivered personally or forwarded 
by registered post 

1[to the Secretary to the Government of 
India in the Ministry of Labour and Employment (in triplicate)] the Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central), New Delhi, and the Regional Labour Commissioner 
(Central), and the Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned. The 
application shall be accompanied by a statement setting forth—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  the parties to 
the dispute;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  the specific 
matters in dispute;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  the total 
number of workmen employed in the undertaking affected;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>  an estimate of 
the number of workmen affected or likely to be affected by the dispute; and
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>  the efforts 
made by the parties themselves to adjust the dispute.
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>4</number> Attestation of 
application.—The application and the 
statement accompanying it shall be signed—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  in the case of 
an employer by the employer himself, or when the employer is an incorporated 
company or other body corporate, by the agent, manager or other principal 
officer of the Corporation;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  in the case of 
workmen, either by the President and Secretary of a trade union of the workmen, 
or by five representatives of the workmen duly authorised in this behalf at a 
meeting of the workmen held for the purpose;
 

         1[(c)  in the case of an 
individual workman, by the workman himself or by any officer of the trade union 
of which he is a member or by another workman in the same establishment duly 
authorised by him in this behalf:
 Provided that such workman is 
not a member of a different trade union.]
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>5</number> Notification of appointment 
of Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal.—The appointment of a Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal together with the names of persons constituting 
the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal shall be notified 
in the Official Gazette.</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>6</number> Notice to parties to 
nominate representatives.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
Central Government proposes to appoint a Board, it shall send a notice in Form B 
to the parties requiring them to nominate within a reasonable time, persons to 
represent them on the Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The notice to the employer 
shall be sent to the employer personally, or if the employer is an incorporated 
company or a body corporate, to the agent, manager or other principal officer of 
such company or body.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The notice to the workmen 
shall be sent—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  in the case of 
workmen who are members of a trade union, to the President or Secretary of the 
trade union; and 
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>  in the case of 
workmen who are not members of a trade union, to any one of the five 
representatives of the workmen who have attested the application made under rule 
3; and in this case a copy of the notice shall also be sent to the employer who 
shall display copies thereof on notice boards in a conspicuous manner at the 
main entrance to the premises of the establishment.
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>7</number> Arbitration agreement.—An 
arbitration agreement for the reference of an industrial dispute to an 
arbitrator or arbitrators shall be made in Form C and shall be delivered 
personally or forwarded by registered post 

1[to the Secretary to the Government of 
India in the Ministry of Labour (in triplicate)] the Chief Labour Commissioner 
(Central), New Delhi, and the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) and the 
Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned. The agreement shall be 
accompanied by the consent, in writing, of the arbitrator or arbitrators.
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>8</number> Attestation of the 
arbitration agreement.—The 
arbitration agreement shall be signed—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  in the case of 
an employer, by the employer himself, or when the employer is an incorporated 
Company or other body corporate by the agent, manager, or other principal 
officer of the Corporation;
 

         1[(b)  in the case of the 
workmen, by any officer of a trade union of the workmen or by five 
representatives of the workmen duly authorised in this behalf at a meeting of 
the workmen held for the purpose;]
 

         2[(c)  in the case of an 
individual workman, by the workman himself or by any officer of a trade union of 
which he is a member or by another workman in the same establishment duly 
authorised by him in this behalf:
 Provided that such workman is 
not a member of a different trade union.]
 Explanation.—In 
this rule “officer” means any of the following officers, namely:—
 </section><section>        <number>a</number>  the President;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  the 
Vice-President;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  the Secretary 
(including the General Secretary);
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>  a Joint 
Secretary;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>  any other 
officer of the trade union authorised in this behalf by the President and 
Secretary of the Union.
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>8A</number> Notification regarding 
arbitration agreement by majority of each party.—Where an industrial dispute 
has been referred to arbitration and the Central Government is satisfied that 
the persons making the reference represent the majority of each party, it shall 
publish a notification in this behalf in the Official Gazette for the 
information of the employers and workmen who are not parties to the arbitration 
agreement but are concerned in the dispute.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>9</number> Conciliation proceedings 
in public utility service.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The Conciliation Officer, on receipt of a notice of a strike or lock-out given 
under rule 71 or rule 72, shall forthwith arrange to interview both the employer 
and the workmen concerned with the dispute at such places and at such times as 
he may deem fit and shall endeavour to bring about a settlement of the dispute 
in question 5.
 

2[(2) Where the Conciliation Officer 
receives no notice of a strike or lock-out under rule 71 or rule 72 but he 
considers it necessary to intervene in the dispute he may give formal intimation 
in writing to the parties concerned declaring his intention to commence 
conciliation proceedings with effect from such date as may be inserted therein.]
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>10</number> Conciliation proceedings in 
non-public utility service.—Where the 
Conciliation Officer receives any information about an existing or apprehended 
industrial dispute which does not relate to public utility service and he 
considers it necessary to intervene in the dispute, he shall give formal 
intimation in writing to the parties concerned declaring his intention to 
commence conciliation proceedings with effect from such date as may be specified 
therein.</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>10A</number> Parties to submit statements.—The 
employer or the party representing workmen 

2[or in the case of individual workman, 
the workman himself] involved in an industrial dispute shall forward a statement 
setting forth the specific matters in dispute to the Conciliation Officer 
concerned whenever his intervention in the dispute is required.]
  



</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article>1[<number>10B</number> Proceeding before the Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> While 
referring an industrial dispute for adjudication to a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal, the Central Government shall direct the party raising the 
dispute to file a statement of claim complete with relevant documents, list of 
reliance and witnesses with the Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal 
within fifteen days of the receipt of the order of reference and also forward a 
copy of such statement to each one of the opposite parties involved in the 
dispute.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal after ascertaining that copies of statement of claim are 
furnished to the other side by party raising the dispute shall fix the first 
hearing on a date not beyond one month from the date of receipt of the order of 
reference and the opposite party or parties shall file their written statement 
together with documents, list of reliance and witnesses within a period of 15 
days from the date of first bearing and simultaneously forward a copy thereof to 
the other party.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may be, finds that the party raising 
the dispute though directed did not forward the copy of the statement of claim 
to the opposite party or parties, it shall give direction to the concerned party 
to furnish the copy of the statement to the opposite party or parties and for 
the said purpose or for any other sufficient cause, extend the time limit for 
filing the statement under sub-rule (1) or written statement under sub-rule (2) 
by an additional period of 15 days.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The party raising a dispute 
may submit a rejoinder if it chooses to do so, to the written statement(s) by 
the appropriate party or parties within a period of fifteen days from the filing 
of written statement by the latter.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal, as the case may be, shall fix a date for evidence within one 
month from the date of receipt of the statements, documents, list of witnesses, 
etc., which shall be ordinarily within sixty days of the date on which 
the dispute was referred for adjudication.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Evidence shall be recorded 
either in court or on affidavit but in the case of affidavit the opposite party 
shall have the right to cross-examine each of the deponents filing the 
affidavit. As the oral examination of each witness proceeds, the Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal shall make a memorandum of the substance of what 
is being deposed. While recording the evidence the Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal shall follow the procedure laid down in rule 5 of Order XVIII 
of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908.
 </section><section><number>7</number> On completion of evidence 
either arguments shall be heard immediately or a date shall be fixed for 
arguments oral hearing which shall not be beyond a period of fifteen days from 
the close of evidence.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal, as the case may be, shall not ordinarily grant an adjournment 
for a period exceeding a week at a time but in any case not more than three 
adjournments in all at the instance of the parties to the dispute:
 Provided that the Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may be, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, grant an adjournment exceeding a week at a time but in any case not 
more than three adjournments at the instance of any one of the parties to the 
dispute.
 </section><section><number>9</number> In case any party defaults or 
fails to appear at any stage the Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, as 
the case may be, may proceed with the reference ex parte and decide the 
reference application in the absence of the defaulting party:
 Provided that the Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may be, may on the application of 
either party filed before the submission of the award revoke the order that the 
case shall proceed ex parte, if it is satisfied that the absence of the 
party was on justifiable grounds.
 </section><section><number>10</number> The Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal, as the case may be, shall submit its award to the Central 
Government within one month from the date of arguments oral hearing or within 
the period mentioned in the order of reference whichever is earlier.
 </section><section><number>11</number> In respect of reference under 
section 2A, the Labour Court or Tribunal, National Tribunal, as the case may be, 
shall ordinarily submit its awards within a period of three months:
 Provided that the Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal, may, as and when necessary, extend the period of 
three months and shall record its reasons in writing to extend the time for 
submission of the award for another specified period.]
  

</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>11</number> 
The Conciliation Officer may hold a meeting of 
the representatives of both parties jointly or of each party separately.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>12</number> 
The Conciliation Officer shall conduct the 
proceedings expeditiously and in such manner as he may deem fit.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>13</number> Place and time of 
hearing.— 

1[Subject to the provisions contained in 
rules 10A and 10B] the sittings of a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal or of an Arbitrator shall be held at such times and places as 
the Chairman or the Presiding Officer or the Arbitrator, as the case may be, may 
fix and the Chairman, Presiding Officer or Arbitrator, as the case may be, shall 
inform the parties of the same in such manner as he thinks fit.
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>14</number> Quorum for Boards and 
Courts.—The quorum necessary to 
constitute a sitting of a Board or Court shall be as follows—
 <section><number>i</number>  
in the case of Board                                        Quorum
      
where the number of members is 3                          2
      
where the number of members is 5                          3
 </section><section><number>ii</number> 
in the case of court
      
where the number of members is more than 2           1
      
where the number of members is more than 2 
      
but less than 5                                                   2
      
where the number of members is 5 or more               3
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>15</number> Evidence.—A 
Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal or an arbitrator may 
accept, admit or call for evidence at any stage of the proceedings before it/him 
and such manner as it/he may think fit.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>16</number> Administration of oath.—Any 
member of a Board or Court or Presiding Officer of a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal or an arbitrator may administer an oath.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>17</number> Summons.—Summons 
issued by a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal shall be 
in Form D and may require any person to produce before it any books, papers or 
other documents and things in the possession of or under the control of such 
person in any way relating to the matter under investigation or adjudication by 
the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal which the Board, 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal thinks necessary for the purposes of such 
investigation or adjudication.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>18</number> Service of summons or notice.—Subject 
to the provisions contained in rule 20, any notice, summons, process or order 
issued by a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or an 
Arbitrator empowered to issue such notice, summons, process or order, may be 
served either personally or by registered post and in the event of refusal by 
the party concerned to accept the said notice, summons, process or order, the 
same shall be sent again under certificate of posting.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>19</number> Description of parties in 
certain cases.—Where in any 
proceeding before a Board, Court, Labour Tribunal or National Tribunal or an 
Arbitrator, there are numerous persons arrayed on any side, such persons shall 
be described as follows:—
 <section>        <number>1</number> all such persons 
as are members of any trade union or association shall be described by the name 
of such trade union or association; and 
 </section><section>        <number>2</number> all such persons 
as are not members of any trade union or association shall be described in such 
manner as the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or 
Arbitrator, as the case may be, may determine.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>20</number> Manner of service in the 
case of numerous persons as parties to a dispute.—
<section><number>1</number> Where there are numerous persons as parties to 
any proceedings before a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal or an Arbitrator and such persons are members of any trade union or 
association, the service of notice on the Secretary, or where there is no 
Secretary, on the principal officer, of the trade union or association shall be 
deemed to be service on such persons.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where there are numerous 
persons as parties to any proceeding before a Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal or an Arbitrator and such persons are not members 
of any trade union or association, the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal, 
National Tribunal or Arbitrator, as the case may be, shall, where personal 
service is not practicable, cause the service of any notice to be made by 
affixing the same at or near the main entrance of the establishment 
concerned.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A notice served in the manner 
specified in sub-rule (2) shall also be considered as sufficient in the case of 
such workmen as cannot be ascertained and found.</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>21</number> Procedure at the first 
sitting.—At the first sitting of a 
Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, the Chairman or the 
Presiding Officer, as the case may be, shall call upon the parties in such order 
as he may think fit to state their case.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>22</number> Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal, National Tribunal or Arbitrator may proceed ex 
parte.—If without sufficient 
cause being shown, any party to proceeding before a Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal, National Tribunal or Arbitrator fails to attend or to be represented, 
the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or Arbitrator may 
proceed, as if the party had duly attended or had been 
represented.</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>23</number> Power of entry and 
inspection.—A Board, or Court, or any 
member thereof, or a conciliation officer, a Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal, or any person authorised in writing by the Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal in this behalf may, for the purposes of any 
conciliation, investigation, enquiry or adjudication entrusted to the 
conciliation officer, Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal 
under the Act, at any time between the hours of sunrise and sunset and in the 
case of a person authorised in writing by a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal after he has given reasonable notice enter any building, 
factory, workshop, or other place or premises whatsoever, and inspect the same 
or any work, machinery, appliance or article therein or interrogate any person 
therein in respect of anything situated therein or any matter relevant to the 
subject-matter of the conciliation, investigation, enquiry or adjudication.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>24</number> Power of Boards, Courts, 
Labour Courts, Tribunals and National Tribunals.—In addition to the powers conferred by the Act, 
Boards, Courts, Labour Courts, Tribunals and National Tribunals shall have the 
same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
1908, when trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
namely:—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  
discovery and inspection;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  
granting adjournment;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  
reception of evidence taken on affidavit,
 and the Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal may 
summon and examine any person whose evidence appears to it to be material and 
shall be deemed to be a civil court within the meaning of sections 480 and 482 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898.</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>25</number> Assessors.—Where 
assessors are appointed to advise a Tribunal or National Tribunal under 
sub-section (4) of section 7A or sub-section (4) of section 7B or by the Court, 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal under sub-section (5) of section 11, 
the Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal as the case may be, 
shall, in relation to proceeding before it, obtain the advice of such assessors, 
but such advice shall not be binding on it.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>26</number> Fees for copies of awards 
or other documents of Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal.—1[
<section><number>1</number> Fees for making a copy of an award or an order of 
a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal or any document filed in any 
proceedings before a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal be charged at 
the rate of Re. 1 per page.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> For certifying a copy of any 
such award or order or document, a fee of Re. 1 shall be payable.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Copying and certifying fees 
shall be payable in cash in advance.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where a party applies for 
immediate delivery of a copy of any such award or order or document, an 
additional fee equal to one-half of the fee leviable under this rule shall be 
payable.
  

</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>27</number> Decision by majority.—All 
questions arising for decision at any meeting of a Board or Court, save where 
the Court consists of one person, shall be decided by a majority of the vote of 
the members thereof (including the Chairman) present at the meeting. In the 
event of an equality of votes the Chairman shall also have a casting vote.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>28</number> Correction of errors.—The 
Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or Arbitrator may correct any clerical 
mistake or error arising from an accidental slip or omission in any award it/he 
issues.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>29</number> Right of representatives.—The 
representatives of the parties appearing before a Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal or an Arbitrator shall have the right of 
examination, cross-examination and of addressing the Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal or Arbitrator when an evidence has been called
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>30</number> Proceedings before a Board, 
Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal.—The proceedings before a Board, Court, Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal shall be held in public:
 Provided that the Board, Court, 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal may at any stage direct that any 
witness shall be examined or its proceedings be held in 
camera.</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>31</number> Travelling allowance.—The 
Chairman or a member of a Board or Court or the Presiding Officer or an Assessor 
of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, if a non-official, shall be 
entitled to draw travelling allowance and halting allowance, for any journey 
performed by him in connection with the performance of his duties, at the rates 
admissible and subject to the conditions applicable to a Government servant of 
the first grade under the Supplementary Rules issued by the Central Government 
from time to time.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>32</number> Fees.—The 
Chairman and a member of a Board or Court, the Presiding Officer and an Assessor 
of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal wherever he is not a salaried 
officer of Government may be granted such fees as may be sanctioned by the 
Central Government in each case.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>33</number> Expenses of witnesses.—Every 
person who is summoned and duly attends or otherwise appears as a witness before 
a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal or an Arbitrator 
shall be entitled to an allowance for expenses according to the scale for the 
time being in force with respect to witnesses in civil courts in the State where 
the investigation, enquiry, adjudication or arbitration is being conducted.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>34</number> Notice of change.—Any 
employer intending to effect any change in the conditions of service applicable 
to any workman in respect of any matter specified in the Fourth Schedule 

1[to the Act] shall give notice of such 
intention in Form E.
 

1[The notice shall be displayed 
conspicuously by the employer on a notice board at the main entrance to the 
establishment in the Manager’s Office:
 Provided that where any 
registered trade union of workmen exists, a copy of the notice shall also be 
served by registered post on the secretary of such union.]


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
  1[***]
  


 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>36</number> Form of authority under 
section 36.—The authority in favour 
of a person or persons to represent a workman or group of workmen or an employer 
in any proceeding under the Act shall be in Form F.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>37</number> Parties bound by acts of 
representative.—A party appearing by 
a representative shall be bound by the acts of that representative.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>38</number> Constitution.—Any 
employer to whom an order made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3 relates shall 
forthwith proceed to constitute a Works Committee in the manner prescribed in 
this part.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>39</number> Number of members.—The 
number of members constituting the Committee shall be fixed so as to afford 
representation to the various categories, groups and class of workmen engaged 
in, and to the sections, shops or departments of the establishment:
 Provided that the total number 
of members shall not exceed twenty:
 Provided further that the number 
of representatives of the workmen shall not be less than the number of 
representatives of the employer.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>40</number> Representatives of 
employer.—Subject to the provisions 
of these rules, the representatives of the employer shall be nominated by the 
employer and shall, as far as possible, be officials in direct touch with or 
associated with the working of the establishment.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>41</number> Consultation with trade 
unions.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any workmen of an 
establishment are members of a registered trade union the employer shall ask the 
union to inform him in writing—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  how many of the 
workmen are members of the union; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>  how their 
membership is distributed among the sections, shops or departments of the 
establishment.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where an employer has reason 
to believe that the information furnished to him under sub-rule (1) by any trade 
union is false, he may, after informing the union, refer the matter to the 
Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned for his decision; and the 
Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central), after hearing the parties, shall decide 
the matter and his decision shall be final.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>42</number> Group of workmen’s 
representatives.—On receipt of the 
information called for under rule 41, the employer shall provide for the 
election of workmen’s representative on the Committee in two groups—
 <section>        <number>1</number>  those to be 
elected by the workmen of the establishment who are members of the registered 
trade unions, and 
 </section><section>        <number>2</number>  those to be 
elected by the workmen of the establishment who are not members of the 
registered trade union or unions,
 bearing the same proportion to each other as the union members in 
the establishment bear to the non-members:
 Provided that where more than 
half the workmen are members of the union or any one of the unions, no such 
division shall be made:
 Provided further that where a 
registered trade union neglects or fails to furnish the information called for 
under sub-rule (1) of rule 41 within one month of the date of the notice 
requiring it to furnish such information such union shall for the purpose of 
this rule be treated as if it did not exist:
 Provided further that where any 
reference has been made by the employer under sub-rule (2) of rule 41, the 
election shall be held on receipt of the decision of Assistant Labour 
Commissioner (Central).
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>43</number> Electoral constituencies.—Where 
under rule 42 the workmen’s representatives are to be elected in two groups, the 
workmen entitled to vote shall be divided into two electoral constituencies, the 
one consisting of those who are members of a registered trade union and the 
other of those who are not:
 Provided that the employer may, 
if he thinks fit, sub-divide the 

1[electoral constituency or 
constituencies, as the case may be] and direct that workmen shall vote in either 
by groups, sections, shops or departments.
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>44</number> Qualification of 
candidates for election.—Any workman 
of not less than 19 years of age and with a service of not less than one year in 
the establishment may, if nominated as provided in these rules, be a candidate 
for election as a representative of the workmen on the Committee:
 Provided that the service 
qualification shall not apply to the first election in an establishment which 
has been in existence for less than a year.
 

1[Explanation.—A workman who has 
put in a continuous service of not less than one year in two or more 
establishments belonging to the same employer shall be deemed to have satisfied 
the service qualification prescribed under this rule.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>45</number> Qualifications for 
voters.—All workmen 

1[***] who are not less than 18 years of 
age and who have put in not less than 6 months’ continuous service in the 
establishment shall be entitled to vote in the election of the representative of 
workmen.
 

2[Explanation.—A workman who has 
put in continuous service of not less than 6 months in two or more 
establishments belonging to the same employer shall be deemed to have satisfied 
the service qualification prescribed under this rule.]
  



</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>46</number> Procedure for election.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall fix a date as the closing date for receiving nominations from 
candidates for election as workmen’s representatives on the committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number> For holding the election, 
the employer shall fix a date which shall not be earlier than three days and 
later than fifteen days after the closing date for receiving nominations.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The dates so fixed shall be 
notified at least seven days in advance to the workmen and the registered trade 
union or unions concerned. Such notice shall be affixed on the notice board or 
given adequate publicity amongst the workmen. The notice shall specify the 
number of seats to be elected by the groups, sections, shops or departments and 
the number to be elected by the members of the registered trade union or unions 
and by the non-members.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A copy of such notice shall 
be sent to registered trade union or unions concerned.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>47</number> Nomination of candidates 
for election.—
<section><number>1</number> Every nomination 
shall be made on a nomination paper in Form G copies of which shall be supplied 
by the employer to the workmen requiring them.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each nomination paper shall 
be signed by the candidate to whom it relates and attested by at least two other 
voters belonging to the group, section, shop or department the candidate seeking 
election will represent, and shall be delivered to the employer.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>48</number> Scrutiny of nomination 
papers.—
<section><number>1</number> On the day following the 
last day fixed for filing nomination papers, the nomination papers shall be 
scrutinised by the employer in the presence of the candidates and the attesting 
persons and those which are not valid shall be rejected.
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of sub-rule 
(1), a nomination paper shall be held to be not valid if (a) the candidate 
nominated is ineligible for membership under rule 44, or (b) the requirements of 
rule 47 have not been complied with:
 Provided that where a candidate 
or an attesting person is unable to be present at the time of scrutiny, he may 
send a duly authorised nominee for the purpose.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>48A</number> Withdrawal of candidates 
validly nominated.—Any candidate 
whose nomination for election has been accepted may withdraw his candidature 
within 48 hours of the completion of scrutiny of nomination papers.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>49</number> Voting in election.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the number of candidates who have been validly nominated is equal to the 
number of seats, the candidates shall be forthwith declared duly elected.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If in any constituency the 
number of candidates is more than the number of seats allotted to it, voting 
shall take place on the day fixed for election.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The election shall be held 
in such manner as may be convenient for each electoral constituency.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The voting shall be 
conducted by the employer, and if any of the candidates belong to a union such 
of them as the union may nominate shall be associated with the election.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every workman entitled to 
vote at an electoral constituency shall have as many votes as there are seats to 
be filled in the constituency:
 Provided that each voter shall 
be entitled to cast only one vote in favour of any one candidate.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>50</number> Arrangements for 
election.—The employer shall be 
responsible for all arrangements in connection with the election.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>51</number> Officers of the 
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Committee shall 
have among its office-bearers a Chairman, a Vice-Chairman, a Secretary and a 
Joint-Secretary. The Secretary and the Joint-Secretary shall be elected every 
year.
 

1[(2) The Chairman shall be nominated by 
the employer from amongst the employer’s representatives on the Committee and he 
shall, as far as possible, be the head of establishment.
 </section><section><number>2A</number> The Vice-Chairman shall be 
elected by the members on the Committee representing the workers, from amongst 
themselves:
 Provided that in the event of 
equality of votes in the election of the Vice-Chairman, the matter shall be 
decided by draw of a lot.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee shall elect 
the Secretary and the Joint Secretary provided that where the Secretary is 
elected from amongst the representatives of the employers, the Joint Secretary 
shall be elected from amongst the representatives of the workmen and vice 
versa:
 Provided that the post of the 
Secretary or the Joint Secretary, as the case may be, shall not be held by a 
representative of the employer or the workmen for two consecutive years:
 

2[Provided that the representatives of 
the employer shall not take part in the election of the Secretary or Joint 
Secretary, as the case may be, from amongst the representatives of the workmen 
and only the representatives of the workmen shall be entitled to vote in such 
elections.]
 

2[(4) In any election under sub-rule (3), 
in the event of equality of votes, the matter shall be decided by a draw of 
lot.]
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>52</number> Term of office.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The term of office of the representatives on the committee other than a member 
chosen to fill a casual vacancy shall be two years.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> A member chosen to fill a 
casual vacancy shall hold office for the unexpired term of his predecessor.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A member who without 
obtaining leave for the Committee, fails to attend three consecutive meetings of 
the Committee shall forfeit his membership.
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>53</number> Vacancies.—In 
the event of workmen’s representative ceasing to be a member under sub-rule (3) 
of rule 52 or ceasing to be employed in the establishment or in the event of his 
resignation, death or otherwise, his successor shall be elected in accordance 
with the provisions of this part from the same group, section, shop or 
department to which the member vacating the seat belonged.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>54</number> Power to co-opt.—The 
Committee shall have the right to co-opt in a consultative capacity persons 
employed in the establishment having particular or special knowledge of a matter 
under discussion. Such co-opted member shall not be entitled to vote and shall 
be present at meetings only for the period during which the particular question 
is before the Committee.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>55</number> Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Committee may meet as often as necessary but not less often than once in 
three months (a quarter).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Committee shall at its 
first meeting regulate its own procedure.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>56</number> Facilities for meeting, 
etc.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The employer shall provide accommodation for holding meetings of the Committee. 
He shall also provide all necessary facilities to the Committee and to the 
members thereof for carrying out the work of the Committee. The Committee shall 
ordinarily meet during working hours of the establishment concerned on any 
working day and the representative of the workmen shall be deemed to be on duty 
while attending the meeting.
 

2[(2) The Secretary of the Committee may 
with the prior concurrence of the Chairman, put up notice regarding the work of 
the Committee on the notice board of the establishment.]
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>56A</number> Submission of returns.—The 
employer shall submit half yearly returns as in Form G 1 in triplicate to the 
Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned not later than the 20th day of 
the month following the half-year.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>57</number> Dissolution of Works 
Committee.—The Central Government, or 
where the power under section 3 has been delegated to any officer or authority 
under section 39, such officer or authority may, after making such inquiry as it 
or he may deem fit, dissolve any Works Committee at any time, by an order in 
writing, if he or it is satisfied that the Committee has not been constituted in 
accordance with these rules or that not less than two-thirds of the number of 
representatives of the workmen have without any reasonable justification failed 
to attend three consecutive meetings of the Committee or that the Committee has, 
for any other reason, ceased to function:
 Provided that where a Works 
Committee is dissolved under this rule the employer may, and if so required by 
the Central Government or, as the case may be, by such officer or authority, 
shall take steps to re-constitute the Committee in accordance with these rules.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>58</number> Memorandum of settlement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A settlement arrived at in the course of conciliation proceedings or otherwise, 
shall be in Form H.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The settlement shall be 
signed by—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  in the case of 
an employer, by the employer himself, or by his authorised agent, or when the 
employer is an incorporated company or other body corporate, by the agent, 
manager or other principal officer of the corporation;
 

         1[(b)  in the case of the 
workmen, by any officer of a trade union of the workmen or by five 
representatives of the workmen duly authorised in this behalf at meeting of the 
workmen held for the purpose;]
 

         2[(c)  in the case of the 
workman in an industrial dispute under section 2A of the Act, by the workman 
concerned.]
 Explanation.—In 
this rule “officer” means any of the following officers, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>a</number>  the President;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>  the 
Vice-President;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>  the Secretary 
(including the General Secretary);
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>  a Joint 
Secretary;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>e</number>  any other 
officer of the trade union authorised in this behalf by the President and 
Secretary of Union.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Where a settlement is 
arrived at in the course of conciliation proceeding the Conciliation Officer 
shall send a report thereof to the Central Government together with a copy of 
the memorandum of settlement signed by the parties to the dispute.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where a settlement is 
arrived at between an employer and his workmen otherwise than in the course of 
conciliation proceeding before a Board or a Conciliation Officer, the parties to 
the settlement shall jointly send a copy thereof to the Central Government, the 
Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) New Delhi, and the Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central) and to the Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) 
concerned.
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>59</number> Complaints regarding 
change of conditions of service, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every complaint under section 33A of the Act shall be presented in triplicate in 
Form I and shall be accompanied by as many copies of the complaint as there are 
opposite parties to the complaint.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every complaint under 
sub-rule (1) shall be verified at the foot by the workmen making it or by some 
other person proved to the satisfaction of the Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal to be acquainted with the facts of the case.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The person verifying shall 
specify, by references to the numbered paragraphs of the complaint, what he 
verifies of his own knowledge and what he verifies upon information received and 
believed to be true.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The verification shall be 
signed by the person making it and shall state the date on which and the place 
at which it was signed.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>60</number> Application under section 
33.—
<section><number>1</number> An employer intending to 
obtain the express permission in writing of the Conciliation Officer, Board, 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may be, under 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) of section 33 shall present an application in 
Form J in triplicate to such Conciliation Officer, Board, Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal and shall file along with the application as many copies 
thereof as there are opposite parties.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An employer seeking the 
approval of the Conciliation Officer, Board, Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal, as the case may be, of any action taken by him under clause (a) or 
clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 33 shall present an application in Form 
K in triplicate to such Conciliation Officer, Board, Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal and shall file along with the application as many copies 
thereof as there are opposite parties.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every application under 
sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) shall be verified at the foot by the employer 
making it or by some other person proved to the satisfaction of the Conciliation 
Officer, Board, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal to be acquainted 
with the facts of the case.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The person verifying shall 
specify by reference to the numbered paragraphs of the application, what he 
verifies of his own knowledge and what he verifies upon information received and 
believed to be true.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The verification shall be 
signed by the person making it and shall state the date on which and the place 
at which it was signed.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>61</number> Protected workmen.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every registered trade union connected with an industrial establishment, to 
which the Act applies, shall communicate to the employer before the 

1[30th April] every year, the names and 
addresses of such of the officers of the union who are employed in that 
establishment and who, in the opinion of the union should be recognised as 
“protected workmen”. Any change in the incumbency of any such officer shall be 
communicated to the employer by the union within fifteen days of such change.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The employer shall, subject 
to section 33, sub-section (4), recognise such workmen to be “protected workmen” 
for the purposes of sub-section (3) of the said section and communicate to the 
union, in writing, within fifteen days of the receipt of the names and addresses 
under sub-rule (1), the list of workmen recognised as protected workmen 

2[for the period of twelve months from 
the date of such communication].
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the total number of 
names received by the employer under sub-rule (1) exceeds the maximum number of 
protected workmen, admissible for the establishment, under section 33, 
sub-section (4), the employer shall recognise as protected workmen only such 
maximum number of workmen:
 Provided that where there is 
more than one registered trade union in the establishment, the maximum number 
shall be so distributed by the employer among the unions that the numbers of 
recognised protected workmen in individual unions bear roughly the same 
proportion to one another as the membership figures of the unions. The employer 
shall in that case intimate in writing to the President or the Secretary of the 
union the number of protected workmen allotted to it:
 Provided further that where the 
number of protected workmen allotted to a union under this sub-rule falls short 
of the number of officers of the union seeking protection, the union shall be 
entitled to select the officers to be recognised as protected workmen. Such 
selection shall be made by the union and communicated to the employer within 
five days of the receipt of the employer’s letter.
 </section><section><number>4</number> When a dispute arises 
between an employer and any registered trade union in any matter connected with 
the recognition of ‘protected workmen’ under this rule, the dispute shall be 
referred to the 

3[any Regional Labour Commissioner 
(Central) or] Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned, whose decision 
thereon shall be final.
  




</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>62</number> Application for recovery of 
dues.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any money is due from 
an employer to a workman or a group of workmen under a settlement or an award or 
under the provisions of Chapter VA, 

2[Chapter VB], the workman or the group 
of workmen, as the case may be, may apply in Form K 1 for the recovery of the 
money due:
 Provided that in the case of a 
person authorised in writing by the workman, or in the case of the death of the 
workman the assignee or heir of the deceased workman, the application shall be 
made in Form K 2.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where any workman or a group 
of workmen is entitled to receive from the employer any money or any benefit 
which is capable of being computed in terms of money, the workman or the group 
of workmen, as the case may be, may apply to the specified Labour Court in Form 
K 3 for the determination of the amount due or, as the case may be, the amount 
at which such benefit should be computed:]
 

2[Provided that in the case of the death 
of a workman, application shall be made in Form K 4 by the assignee or heir of 
the deceased workman].
  



</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>63</number> Appointment of 
Commissioner.—Where it is necessary 
to appoint a Commissioner under sub-section (3) of section 33C of the Act, the 
Labour Court may appoint a person with experience in the particular industry, 
trade or business involved in the industrial dispute or a person with experience 
as a judge of civil court, or as a stipendiary magistrate or as a Registrar or 
Secretary of a Labour Court, or Tribunal constituted under any Provincial Act or 
State Act or of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal constituted under 
the Act or of the Labour Appellate Tribunal constituted under the Industrial 
Disputes (Appellate Tribunal) Act, 1950.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>64</number> Fees for the 
Commissioner, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Labour Court shall, after consultation with the parties, estimate the probable 
duration of the enquiry and fix the amount of the Commissioner’s fees and other 
incidental expenses and direct the payment thereof into the nearest treasury, 
within a specified time, by such party or parties and in such proportation as it 
may consider fit. The Commission shall not issue until satisfactory evidence of 
the deposit into the treasury of the sum fixed is filed before the Labour Court:
 Provided that the Labour Court 
may from time to time direct that any further sum or sums be deposited into the 
treasury within such time and by such parties as it may consider fit:
 Provided further that the Labour 
Court may in its discretion, extend the time for depositing the sum into the 
treasury.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Labour Court may, at any 
time, for reasons to be recorded in writing, vary the amount of the 
Commissioner’s fees in consultation with the parties.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Labour Court may direct 
that the fees shall be disbursed to the Commissioner in such instalments and on 
such date as it may consider fit.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The undisbursed balance, if 
any, of the sum deposited shall be refunded to the party or parties who 
deposited the sum in the same proportion as that in which it was deposited.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>65</number> Time for submission of 
report.—
<section><number>1</number> Every order for the issue 
of a Commission shall appoint a date, allowing sufficient time, for the 
Commissioner to submit his report.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If for any reason the 
Commissioner anticipates that the date fixed for the submission of his report is 
likely to be exceeded he shall apply, before the expiry of the said date, for 
extension of time setting forth grounds thereof and the Labour Court shall take 
such grounds into consideration in passing orders on the application:
 Provided that the Labour Court 
may grant extension of time notwithstanding that no application for such 
extension has been received from the Commissioner within the prescribed time 
limit.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>66</number> Local investigation.—In 
any industrial dispute in which the Labour Court deems a local investigation to 
be requisite or proper for the purpose of computing the money value of a 
benefit, the Labour Court may issue a commission to a person referred to in rule 
63 directing him to make such investigation and to report thereon to it.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>67</number> Commissioner’s report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Commissioner after such local inspection as he deems necessary and after 
reducing to writing the evidence taken by him, shall return such evidence 
together with his report in writing signed by him to the Labour Court.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The report of the 
Commissioner and the evidence taken by him (but not evidence without the report) 
shall be evidence in the industrial dispute and shall form part of the record of 
the proceedings in the industrial dispute; but the Labour Court or, with the 
permission of Labour Court any of the parties to the industrial dispute may 
examine the Commissioner personally before the Labour Court regarding any of the 
matters referred to him or mentioned in his report or as to his report, or, as 
to the manner in which he had made the investigation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Labour Court is 
for any reason dissatisfied with the proceedings of the Commissioner it may 
direct such further enquiry to be made as it shall think fit.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>68</number> Powers of Commissioner.—Any 
Commissioner appointed under these rules may unless otherwise directed by the 
order of appointment—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  examine the 
parties themselves and any witnesses whom they or any of them may produce, and 
any other person whom the Commissioner thinks proper to call upon to give 
evidence in the matter referred to him;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  call for and 
examine documents and other things relevant to the subject of enquiry;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  at any 
reasonable time enter upon or into any premises mentioned in the order.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>69</number> Summoning of witnesses, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of the 
Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) relating to the summoning, attendance, 
examination of witnesses and penalties to be imposed upon witnesses, shall apply 
to persons required to give evidence or to produce documents before the 
Commissioner under these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every person who is summoned 
and appears as a witness before the Commissioner shall be entitled to payment by 
the Labour Court out of the sum deposited under rule 64, of an allowance for 
expenses incurred by him in accordance with the scale for the time being in 
force for payment of such allowance to witnesses appearing in the Civil Courts.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>70</number> Representation of parties 
before the Commissioner.—The parties 
to the Industrial Dispute shall appear before the Commissioner, either in person 
or by any other person who is competent to represent them in the proceedings 
before the Labour Court.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>70A</number> Preservation of records by the 
National Industrial Tribunals, Industrial Tribunals or Labour Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The records of the National Industrial Tribunals, Industrial Tribunals or Labour 
Courts specified in Column 1 of the Table below shall be preserved, for the 
periods specified in the corresponding entry in column 2 thereof after the 
proceedings are finally disposed of by such National Tribunals, Industrial 
Tribunals, Labour Courts.
 
TABLE
 
 

  Records                                                         Number of 
  years for 

 
                                                                      which the 
records
 
                                                                      shall be 
preserved
 
 
      
  1                                                                          2
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Orders and Judgments of 
National                         10 years 
      Industrial Tribunals, Industrial  
      Tribunals or Labour Courts. 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  Exhibited documents in the above  
      mentioned Tribunals or Courts.                             10 years
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Other papers. 
                                                     7 years
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (1) the records of the National Industrial Tribunals, 
Industrial Tribunals or Labour Courts, connected with writ petitions, if any, 
filed in the High Courts or Supreme Court, or connected with appeals by special 
leave, if any, filed in the Supreme Court shall be preserved at least till the 
final disposal of such writ petitions or appeal by special leave.]
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>71</number> Notice of strike.— 

<section><number>1</number> The notice of strike to be given by workmen in public utility service shall 
be in Form L.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of a notice of a 
strike under sub-rule (1), the employer shall forthwith intimate the fact to the 
Conciliation Officer having jurisdiction in the matter.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>72</number> Notice of lock-out.—The 
notice of lock-out to be given by an employer carrying on a public utility 
service shall be in Form M. 

1[The notice shall be displayed 
conspicuously by the employer on a notice board at the main entrance to the 
establishment and in the Manager’s Office:
 Provided that where a registered 
trade union exists, a copy of the notice shall also be served on the Secretary 
of the Union.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>73</number> Report of lock-out or 
strike.—The notice of lock-out or 
strike in a public utility service to be submitted by the employer under 
sub-section (3) of section 22, shall be in Form N.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>74</number> Report of notice of 
strike or lock-out.—The report of 
notice of a strike or lock-out to be submitted by the employer under sub-section 
(6) of section 22, shall be sent by registered post or given personally to the 
Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) appointed for local area concerned, with 
copy by registered post to—
 <section>        <number>1</number>  The 
Administrative Department of the Government of India concerned,
 </section><section>        <number>2</number>  The Regional 
Labour Commissioner (Central) for the Zone,
 </section><section>        <number>3</number>  Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central),
 </section><section>        <number>4</number>  Ministry of 
Labour of the Government of India,
 </section><section>        <number>5</number>  Labour 
Department of the State Government concerned, and 
 </section><section>        <number>6</number>  The District 
Magistrate concerned.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>75</number> Register of settlements.—The 
Conciliation Officer shall file all settlements effected under this Act in 
respect of disputes in the area within his jurisdiction in a register maintained 
for the purpose as in Form O.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>75A</number> Notice of lay-off.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any workmen employed in an industrial establishment as defined in the 
explanation below section 25A not being an industrial establishment referred to 
in sub-section (1) of that section is laid-off, then, the employer concerned 
shall give notices of commencement and termination of such lay-off in Forms O 1 
and O 2 respectively within seven days of such commencement or termination, as 
the case may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such notices shall be given 
by an employer in every case irrespective of whether, in his opinion, the 
workman laid off is or is not entitled to compensation under section 25C.]
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>75B</number> Application for permission for 
lay-off under section 25M.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Application for permission to lay-off any workman under sub-section (1), or for 
permission to continue a lay-off under 

2[sub-section (3)] (ia) of section 25M 
shall be made in Form O 3 and delivered to the authority specified under 
sub-section (1) either personally or by registered post acknowledgement due and 
where the application is sent by registered post the date on which the same is 
delivered to the said authority shall be deemed to be the date on which the 
application is made, for the purposes of 

2[sub-section (5)] of the said section.
 

3[(2) The application for permission 
shall be made in triplicate and copies of such application shall be served by 
the employer on the workmen concerned and a proof to that effect shall also be 
submitted by the employer along with the application.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The employer concerned shall 
furnish to the authority to whom the application for permission has been made 
such further information as the authority considers necessary for arriving at a 
decision on the application, as and when called for by such authority, so as to 
enable the authority to communicate the permission or refusal to grant 
permission within the period specified in 

4[sub-section (5)] of section 25M.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the permission to 
lay-off has been granted by the said authority, the employer concerned shall 
give to the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) concerned, a notice of 
commencement and termination of such lay-off in Forms O 1 and O 2 respectively 
and where permission to continue a lay-off has been granted by the said 
authority, the employer shall give to the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) 
concerned, a notice of commencement of such lay-off in Form O 1, in case such a 
notice has not already been given under sub-rule (1) of rule 75A, and a notice 
of termination of such lay-off in Form O 2.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The notice of commencement 
and termination of lay-off referred to in sub-rule (4) shall be given within the 
period specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 75A.]
  





</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>76</number> Notice of retrenchment.—If 
any employer desires to retrench any workman employed in his industrial 
establishment who has been in continuous service for not less than one year 
under him (hereinafter referred to as ‘workman’ in this rule and in rules 77 and 
78), he shall give notice of such retrenchment as in Form P to the Central 
Government, the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) and Assistant Labour 
Commissioner (Central) and the Employment Exchange concerned and such notice 
shall be served on that Government, the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central), 
the Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central), and the Employment Exchange 
concerned by registered post in the following manner:—
 <section>        <number>a</number>  where notice is 
given to the workman, notice of retrenchment shall be sent within three days 
from the date on which notice is given to the workman;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  where no notice 
is given to the workman and he is paid one month’s wages in lieu thereof, notice 
of retrenchment shall be sent within three days from the date on which such 
wages are paid; and
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  where 
retrenchment is carried out under an agreement which specifies a date for the 
termination of service, notice of retrenchment shall be sent so as to reach the 
Central Government, the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central), the Assistant 
Labour Commissioner (Central), and the Employment Exchange concerned, at least 
one month before such date:
 Provided that if the date of 
termination of service agreed upon is within 30 days of the agreement, the 
notice of retrenchment shall be sent to the Central Government, the Regional 
Labour Commissioner (Central), the Assistant Commissioner (Central), and the 
Employment Exchange concerned, within 3 days of the agreement.
</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>76A</number> Notice of, and application for, 
retrenchment.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice 

2[or, as the case may be, the application 
under] sub-section (1) of section 25N for retrenchment shall be served in Form 
PA and served on the Central Government or such authority as may be specified by 
the Government under the said clause either personally or by registered post 
acknowledgement due and where the notice is served by registered post, the date 
on which the same is delivered to the Central Government or the authority shall 
be deemed to be date of service of the notice for the purposes of 

2[sub-section (4)] of the said section.
 

3[***]
 

4[5[(2)] 
The notice or, as the case may be, the application, shall be made in triplicate 
and copies of such notice or, as the case may be, the application, shall be 
served by the employer on the workmen concerned and a proof to that effect shall 
also be submitted by the employer along with the notice or, as the case may be, 
the application.
 

6[(3)] The employer concerned shall 
furnish to the Central Government or the authority to whom the notice for 
retrenchment has been given or the application for permission for retrenchment 
has been made, under sub-section (1) of section 25N, such further information as 
the Central Government or, as the case may be, the authority considers necessary 
for arriving at a decision on the notice or, as the case may be, the 
application, as and when called for by such authority so as to enable the 
Central Government or the authority to communicate its permission or refusal to 
grant permission within the period specified in sub-section (4) of section 25N.]
  







</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>76B</number> Notice of closure.—If 
an employer intends to close down an undertaking he shall give notice of such 
closure in Form Q to the Central Government, the Regional Labour Commissioner 
(Central), the Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central), and the Employment 
Exchange concerned, by registered post.]
  


</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>76C</number> Notice of, and application for 
permission for, closure.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice 
under sub-section (1) of section 25-O of intended closure shall be given in Form 
QA and served on the Central Government either personally or by registered post 
acknowledgement due.
 

2[A copy of such application shall be 
served simultaneously by registered post on the President or Secretary of 
registered trade union(s) functioning in the establishment and a notice in this 
regard shall also be displayed conspicuously by the employer on a notice board 
at the main entrance to the establishment for the information of all the 
concerned workmen at the same time when applications are served on the Central 
Government.]
 

3[(2)] The notice, or, as the case may 
be, the application shall be made in triplicate.
 

2[(3)] The employer concerned shall 
furnish to the Central Government to whom the notice of intended closure has 
been given or the application for permission to close down has been made such 
further information as that Government considers necessary, for arriving at a 
decision on the notice, or, as the case may be, the application, and calls for 
from such employer.
  





</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>77</number> Maintenance of seniority 
list of workmen.—The employer shall 
prepare a list of all workmen in the particular category from which retrenchment 
is contemplated arranged according to the seniority of their service in that 
category and cause a copy thereof to be pasted on a notice board in a 
conspicuous place in the premises of the industrial establishment at least seven 
days before the actual date of retrenchment.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>78</number> Re-employment of 
retrenched workmen.—
<section><number>1</number> At least ten 
days before the date on which vacancies are to be filled, the employer shall 
arrange for the display on a notice board in a conspicuous place in the premises 
of the industrial establishment details of those vacancies and shall also give 
intimation of those vacancies by registered post to every one of all the 
retrenched workmen eligible to be considered thereof, to the address given by 
him at the time of retrenchment or at any time thereafter:
 Provided that where the number 
of such vacancies is less than the number of retrenched workmen, it shall be 
sufficient if intimation is given by the employer individually to the 
senior-most retrenched workmen in the list referred to in rule 77 the number of 
such senior-most workmen being double the number of such vacancies:
 Provided further that where the 
vacancy is of a duration of less than one month there shall be no obligation on 
the employer to send intimation of such vacancy to individual retrenched 
workmen:
 

1[Provided also that if a retrenched 
workman, without sufficient cause being shown in writing to the employer, does 
not offer himself for re-employment on the date or dates specified in the 
intimation sent to him by the employer under this sub-rule, the employer may not 
intimate to him the vacancies that may be filled on any subsequent occasion.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Immediately after complying 
with the provisions of sub-rule (1), the employer shall also inform the trade 
unions connected with the industrial establishment, of the number of vacancies 
to be filled and names of the retrenched workmen to whom intimation has been 
sent under that sub-rule:
 Provided that the provisions of 
this sub-rule need not be complied with by the employer in any case where 
intimation is sent to every one of the workmen mentioned in the list prepared 
under rule 77.
  


</section></article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>79</number> Penalties.—Any 
breach of these rules shall be punishable with fine not exceeding fifty rupees.
</article> 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1957
  
 <article><number>80</number> Repeal.—The 
Industrial Disputes (Central) Rules, 1947, are hereby repealed:
 Provided that any order made or action taken under the rules so 
repealed shall be deemed to have been made or taken under the corresponding 
provisions of these rules.
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>