<act><tid>1841878</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL AGRICULTURAL UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1992</year></title>

NO. 40 OF <year>1992</year> 
[ 26th December, <year>1992</year>.]
An Act to provide for the establishment and incorporation of a Univer- 
sity for the North- Eastern region for the development of agricu- 
lture and for the furtherance of the advancement of learning and 
prosecution of reserch in agriculture and allied sciences in that 
region.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--




<article><tid>798451</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencemen.
<section><tid>1803204</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Central Agricultural University Act, <year>1992</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1987897</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088766</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, 
unless the context otherwise requires,--
<section><tid>948885</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>187135</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are 
designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>1635430</tid>
<number>c</number>" agriculture" means the basic and applied sciences of 
the soil and water management, crop production including 
production of all garden crops, control of plants, pests and 
diseases, horticulture including floriculture, animal husbandry 
including veterinary and dairy science, fisheries, forestry 
including farm forestry, homescience, agricultural engineering 
and technology, marketing and processing of agricultural and 
animal husbandry products, land use and management;

</section>

<section><tid>220739</tid>
<number>d</number>" Board" means the Board of Management of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1501644</tid>
<number>e</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1840774</tid>
<number>f</number>" Chancellor" means the Chancellor of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1674460</tid>
<number>g</number>" college" means a constituent college of the University 
whether located at the headquarters, campus or elsewhere;

</section>

<section><tid>1333660</tid>
<number>h</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies of the 
University;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>284</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number>   1. 26- 1- <year>1993</year>: Vide Notfin. NO. S. O. 72 (E), dated 25- 1- <year>1993</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1481684</tid>
<number>i</number>" employee" means any person appointed by the University 
and includes teachers and other staff of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1879351</tid>
<number>j</number>" extension education" means the educational activities 
concerned with the training of orchardists, farmers and other 
groups serving agriculture, horticulture, fisheries and improved 
practices related thereto and the various phases of scientific 
technology related to agriculture and agricultural production 
including post harvest technology and marketing;

</section>

<section><tid>69717</tid>
<number>k</number>" Faculty" means Faculty of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1958812</tid>
<number>l</number>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region of 
India comprising the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur, 
Meghalaya, Mizoram, Sikkim and Tripura;

</section>

<section><tid>389833</tid>
<number>m</number>" Ordinances" means the Ordinances of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1517513</tid>
<number>n</number>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any 
authority of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>301751</tid>
<number>o</number>" Research Advisory Committee" means the Research 
Advisory Committee of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1133489</tid>
<number>p</number>" Statutes" means the Statutes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1418483</tid>
<number>q</number>" student" means a person enrolled in the University for 
undergoing a course of studies for obtaining a degree, diploma or 
other academic distinction duly instituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1400433</tid>
<number>r</number>" teachers" means Professors, Associate Professors, 
Assistant Professors, Teaching Faculty Members and their 
equivalent appointed for imparting instruction or conducting 
research or extension education programmes or combination of 
these in the University, college or any institute maintained by 
the University and designated as teachers by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>1161046</tid>
<number>s</number>" University" means the Central Agricultural University 
established under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1229008</tid>
<number>t</number>" Vice- Chancellor" means the Vice- Chancellor of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>75615</tid>
<number>u</number>" Visitor" means the Visitor of the University.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1082247</tid>
<number> 3</number> The University.
<section><tid>1316012</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a University by  
the name of the" Central Agricultural University".

</section>

<section><tid>902273</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Imphal in the 
State of Manipur and it may also establish compuses at such other 
places within its jurisdiction as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1399149</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the 
first members of the Board, the Academic Council and all persons who 
may hereafter become such officers or members, so long as they 
continue to hold such office or membership are hereby constituted a 
body corporate by the name of the Central Agricultural University.

</section>

<section><tid>17051</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal and shall sue and be sued by the said name.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>285</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>874328</tid>
<number> 4</number> Objects of the University. The objects of the University shall 
be--
<section><tid>503955</tid>
<number>a</number>to impart education in different branches of 
agricultural and allied sciences as it may deem fit;

</section>

<section><tid>665294</tid>
<number>b</number>to further the advancement of learning and prosecution 
of research in agriculture and allied sciences;

</section>

<section><tid>1125676</tid>
<number>c</number>to undertake programmes of extension education in the 
States under its jurisdiction; and

</section>

<section><tid>129017</tid>
<number>d</number>to undertake such other activities as it may, from time 
to time, determine.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>445802</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:--
<section><tid>1437894</tid>
<number>i</number>to make provision for instructions in agricultural and 
allied sciences;

</section>

<section><tid>1640674</tid>
<number>ii</number>to make provision for conduct of research in 
agricultural and allied branches of learning;

</section>

<section><tid>1114036</tid>
<number>iii</number>to make provision for dissemination of the findings of 
research and technical information through extension programmes;

</section>

<section><tid>333852</tid>
<number>iv</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as it may 
determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or 
other academic distinctions on the basis of examination, 
evaluation or any other method of testing, on persons, and to 
withdraw any such diplomas, certificates, degrees or other 
academic distinction for good and sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>1786278</tid>
<number>v</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>876757</tid>
<number>vi</number>to provide lectures and instructions for field workers, 
village leaders and other persons not enrolled as regular 
students of the University and to grant certificates to them as 
may be prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1049520</tid>
<number>vii</number>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any 
other University or authority or institution of higher learning 
in such manner and for such purposes as the University may 
determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1917862</tid>
<number>viii</number>to establish and maintain colleges relating to 
agriculture, fisheries, dairying, veterinary medicine and animal 
science, homescience, agricultural engineering, forestry and 
allied sciences;

</section>

<section><tid>1652351</tid>
<number>ix</number>to establish and maintain such campuses, special 
centres, specialised laboratories, libraries, museums or other 
units for research and instruction as are, in its opinion, 
necessary for the furtherance of its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>795703</tid>
<number>x</number>to create teaching, research and extension education 
posts and to make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>41738</tid>
<number>xi</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts 
and to make appointments thereto;

<subsection><tid>1654322</tid>
<number>xii</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>286</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>164327</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to determine standards of admission to the 
University, which may include examination, evaluation or any 
other method of testing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>969097</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to provide and maintain residential accommodation for 
students and employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802023</tid>
<number>xv</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the 
University and to make arrangements for promoting their health 
and general welfare;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>758800</tid>
<number>xvi</number>to lay down conditions of service of all categories of 
employees, including their code of conduct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881232</tid>
<number>xvii</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students 
and the employees, and to take such disciplinary measures in this 
regard as it may deem necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901362</tid>
<number>xviii</number>to fix, demand and receive such fees and other 
charges as may be prescribed by the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1481703</tid>
<number>xix</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government 
on the security of its property, money for the purpose of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>567651</tid>
<number>xx</number>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to 
acquire, hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or 
immovable, including trust and endowment properties for its 
purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1033008</tid>
<number>xxi</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be 
necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or 
any of its objects.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1442953</tid>
<number> 6</number> Jurisdiction.
<section><tid>1568659</tid>
<number>1</number>The jurisdiction and responsibility of the  
University with respect to teaching, research and programmes of 
extension education at the University level, in the field of 
agricultural shall extend to the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur, 
Meghalaya, Mizoram, Sikkim and Tripura.

</section>

<section><tid>142136</tid>
<number>2</number>All colleges, research and experimental stations or other 
institutions coming under the jurisdiction and authority of the 
University shall be its constituent units under the full management 
and control of its officers and authorities and no such units shall be 
recognised as affiliated units.

</section>

<section><tid>1891079</tid>
<number>3</number>The University may assume responsibility for the training of 
field extension workers and others and may develop such training 
centres as may be required in various parts of the States under its 
jurisdiction.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1766390</tid>
<number>7</number>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The 
University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
caste, creed, race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the 
University to adopt or impose on any person, any test whatsoever of 
religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be appointed 
as a teacher of the University or to hold any other office therein or 
be admitted as a student in the University or to graduate thereat or 
to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the University from making special provisions for the employment or 
admission of women, handicapped or of persons belonging to the weaker 
sections of the society and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes 
and the Scheduled Tribes.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>287</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>317522</tid>
<number> 8</number> The Visitor.
<section><tid>335003</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor  
of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1534197</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), the 
Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be made, by 
such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, its 
buildings, laboratories, libraries, museums, workshops and equipments, 
and of any institution or college and also of the examination, 
instruction and other work conducted or done by the University, and to 
cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter 
connected with the administration and finances of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1868847</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice to the 
University of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be 
made and the University shall, on receipt of such notice, have the 
right to make, within thirty days from the date of receipt of the 
notice or such other period as the Visitor may determine, such 
representations to him as it may consider necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>239669</tid>
<number>4</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or 
inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1797584</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by 
the Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a 
representative who shall have the right to appear in person and to be 
heard on such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>424067</tid>
<number>6</number>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to 
the results of such inspection or inquiry together with such views and 
advice with regard to the action to be taken thereon as the Visitor 
may be pleased to offer and on receipt of the address made by the 
Visitor, the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate forthwith to the 
Board the results of the inspection or inquiry and the views of the 
Visitor and the advice tendered by him upon the action to be taken 
thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1634996</tid>
<number>7</number>The Board shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to 
the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to take or has been 
taken by it upon the results of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>330496</tid>
<number>8</number>Where the Board does not, within a reasonable time, take 
action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, after 
considering any explanation furnished or representation made by the 
Board, issue such directions as he may think fit and the Board shall 
be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>1927406</tid>
<number>9</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this 
section, the Visitor may, by an order in writing, annul any proceeding 
of the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the 
Statutes or the Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon 
the University to show cause why such an order should not be made and, 
if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the 
same.


</section>

<section><tid>1671053</tid>
<number>10</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be specified 
by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>288</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>786697</tid>
<number> 9</number> Officers of the University. The following shall be the 
officers of the University, namely:--
<section><tid>992609</tid>
<number>1</number>the Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1459075</tid>
<number>2</number>the Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1217045</tid>
<number>3</number>Deans;

</section>

<section><tid>145625</tid>
<number>4</number>Directors;

</section>

<section><tid>911803</tid>
<number>5</number>the Registrar;

</section>

<section><tid>369842</tid>
<number>6</number>the Comptroller; and

</section>

<section><tid>1372139</tid>
<number>7</number>such other officers as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>637094</tid>
<number> 10</number> The Chancellor.
<section><tid>327714</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the  
Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>659873</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>799774</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations 
of the University held for conferring degrees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>736822</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>697164</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>484741</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and 
academic officer of the University and shall exercise general 
supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give 
effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>456876</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate 
action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such matter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University 
who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the 
Board within three months from the date on which decision on such 
action is communicated to him and thereupon the Board may confirm, 
modify or reverse the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>1159001</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of opinion that any decision of 
any authority of the University is beyond the powers of the authority 
conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the 
Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of the 
University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision 
within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to 
review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken 
by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>177632</tid>
<number>5</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and 
perform such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>289</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1415609</tid>
<number>12</number>Deans and Directors. Every Dean and every Director shall be 
appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>511082</tid>
<number> 13</number> The Registrar.
<section><tid>977850</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1772225</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements, 
sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University 
and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>351368</tid>
<number>14</number>The Comptroller. The Comptroller shall be appointed in such 
manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may 
be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>1730199</tid>
<number>15</number>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and 
duties of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by 
the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>623077</tid>
<number> 16</number> Authorities of the University. The following shall be the 
authorities of the University, namely:--
<section><tid>982098</tid>
<number>1</number>the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>296370</tid>
<number>2</number>the Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1791347</tid>
<number>3</number>the Finance Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>599693</tid>
<number>4</number>the Research Programme Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>831299</tid>
<number>5</number>the Extension Education Advisory Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>1837851</tid>
<number>6</number>the Board of Studies; and

</section>

<section><tid>188391</tid>
<number>7</number>such other authorities as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>700096</tid>
<number> 17</number> The Board.
<section><tid>762256</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall be the principal executive  
body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1516121</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Board, the term of office of its 
members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>440901</tid>
<number> 18</number> The Academic Council.
<section><tid>1544704</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, have the control 
and general regulation of, and be responsible for, the maintenance of 
standards of learning, education, instruction, evaluation and 
examination within the University and shall exercise such other powers 
and perform such other functions as may be conferred or imposed upon 
it by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1504751</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Academic Council and the term of 
office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1080531</tid>
<number>19</number>The Finance Committee. The constitution, powers and functions 
of the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>1368566</tid>
<number>20</number>The Research Programme Committee. The constitution, powers 
and functions of the Research Programme Committee shall be prescribed 
by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>290</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>306922</tid>
<number>21</number>The Extension Education Advisory Committee. The constitution, 
powers and functions of the Extension Education Advisory Committee 
shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>745416</tid>
<number>22</number>The Board of Studies. The constitution, powers and functions 
of the Board of Studies shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>418643</tid>
<number>23</number>Faculties. The University shall have such Faculties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>477962</tid>
<number>24</number>Other authorities. The constitution, powers and functions of 
other authorities of the University referred to in clause (7) of 
section 16 shall be such as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>1992508</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:--
<section><tid>1183411</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of the 
authorities of the University, as may be constituted from time to 
time;

</section>

<section><tid>1977629</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment and continuance in office of the members 
of the said authorities, the filling up of vacancies of members, 
and all other matters relating to those authorities for which it 
may be necessary or desirable to provide;

</section>

<section><tid>936829</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of 
the University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>1870544</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff and other 
employees of the University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>176759</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers and academic staff working 
in any other University or organisation for a specific period for 
undertaking a joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>472193</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including 
provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner 
of termination of service and disciplinary action;

</section>

<section><tid>1658329</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing the seniority of service of the 
employees of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1787600</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute 
between employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>939035</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Board by any employee or 
student against the action of any officer or authority of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1656580</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment and abolition of Departments, Centres, 
colleges and institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>709084</tid>
<number>k</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1448925</tid>
<number>l</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>291</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1582102</tid>
<number>m</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1511519</tid>
<number>n</number>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or 
officers of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1083808</tid>
<number>o</number>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and 
students;

</section>

<section><tid>339832</tid>
<number>p</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may 
be, prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031086</tid>
<number> 26</number> Statutes how to be made.
<section><tid>1761378</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set  
out in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1128728</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may from time to time make Statutes or may amend or 
repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1):
Provided that the Board shall not make, amend or repeal any 
Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any authority 
of the University until such authority has been given an opportunity 
of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed changes, and any 
opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Board.


</section>

<section><tid>985011</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Statute or any amendment or repeal of a Statute shall 
require the assent of the Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold 
assent therefrom or remit it to the Board for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>407551</tid>
<number>4</number>A Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>445282</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, the Visitor may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
sub- section (1), during the period of three years immediately after 
the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>625241</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in 
the Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the 
Board is unable to implement such direction within sixty days of its 
receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reasons, if any, 
communicated by the Board for its inability to comply with such 
direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319060</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to make Ordinances.
<section><tid>1503092</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any 
of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1382046</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1061597</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1770632</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259015</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and the 
means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining of the 
same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1670482</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>292</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897339</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions for award of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>849230</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of 
office and manner of appointment and the duties of examining 
bodies, examiners and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>194640</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1192726</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and the 
prescribing of special courses of studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>612812</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than 
those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1005064</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment of special centres, specialized 
laboratories and other committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>476088</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities and authorites including learned bodies or 
associations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1948414</tid>
<number>m</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other 
body which is considered necessary for improving the academic 
life of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687214</tid>
<number>n</number>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers 
and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630860</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of colleges and institutions established 
by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1054339</tid>
<number>p</number>the setting up of a machinery for redressal of 
grievances of employees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1823684</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may 
be provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>13733</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor 
with the previous approval of the Central Government and the 
Ordinances so made may be amended or repealed at any time by the Board 
in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>376413</tid>
<number>28</number>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the committees 
appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>847602</tid>
<number> 29</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1167161</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall  
be prepared under the direction of the Board, which shall include, 
among other matters, the steps taken by the University towards the 
fulfilment of its objects and shall be submitted to the Board on or 
after such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes and the Board 
shall consider the report in its annual meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1319981</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along 
with its comments, if any.

</section>

<section><tid>1146325</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the annual report as prepared under sub- section 
 (1), shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall, 
as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>293</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>76136</tid>
<number> 30</number> Annual accounts.
<section><tid>1390076</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts of the University  
shall be prepared under the directions of the Board and shall, once at 
least every year and at intervals of not more than fifteen months, be 
audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or by such 
persons as he may authorise in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1652164</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
thereon shall be submitted to the Board and the Visitor along with the 
observations of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1164892</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts 
shall be brought to the notice of the Board and the observations of 
the Board, if any, shall be submitted to the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>441625</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
as submitted to the Visitor, shall also be submitted to the Central 
Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1744160</tid>
<number>5</number>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before 
both Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Official Gazette.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1034329</tid>
<number> 31</number> Conditions of service of employees.
<section><tid>845636</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee of the  
University shall be appointed under a written contract, which shall be 
lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be furnished to 
the employee concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1223741</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the 
University and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member 
appointed by the Board, one member nominated by the employee concerned 
and an umpire appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1343821</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final, and no suit 
shall lie in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the 
Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1669535</tid>
<number>4</number>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2) 
shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of 
this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (2 of  
  <year>1940</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1883261</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall 
be prescribed by the Statutes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1177216</tid>
<number> 32</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases 
against students.
<section><tid>528257</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination  
whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the 
orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or 
Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred 
from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one 
year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or 
copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Board and the Board may 
confirm, modify or reverse the decision of the Vice- Chancellor or the 
Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1145264</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by 
the University against a student shall, at the request of such 
student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions 
of sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 31 shall, as far as 
may be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>294</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>390543</tid>
<number>33</number>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University 
or of a college or institution maintained by the University shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, have a right to 
appeal, within such time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the 
Board against the decision of any officer or authority of the 
University or any college or an institution, as the case may be, and 
thereupon the Board may confirm, modify or reverse the decision 
appealed against.

</article>



<article><tid>1263350</tid>
<number> 34</number> Provident and pension funds.
<section><tid>1616700</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension 
fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1099271</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so 
constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provision of 
the Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such fund, 
as if it were a Government provident fund.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414107</tid>
<number>35</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities. If any 
question arises as to whether any person has been duly appointed as, 
or is entitled to be, a member of any authority of the University, the 
matter shall be referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall 
be final.

</article>



<article><tid>961780</tid>
<number>36</number>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint 
Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist 
of the members of the authority concerned and of such other person, if 
any, as the authority in each case may think fit.

</article>



<article><tid>790194</tid>
<number>37</number>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex officio members) of any authority of the 
University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person who 
appointed or co- opted the member whose place has become vacant and 
person appointed or co- opted to a casual vacancy shall be a member of 
such authority or body for the residue of the term for which the 
person whose place he fills would have been a member.

</article>



<article><tid>1807594</tid>
<number>38</number>Proceedings of University authorities not invalidated by 
vacancy. No act or proceedings of any authority of the University 
shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of a vacancy or 
vacancies among its members.

</article>



<article><tid>875738</tid>
<number>39</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Board, 
any authority or officer or other employee of the University for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>295</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>173479</tid>
<number>40</number>Mode of proof of University records. A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if verified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, 
proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the 
register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and 
transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced, 
have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>.) or in any other law for 
the time being in force.

</article>



<article><tid>1623797</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1594935</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made under this section 
after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1663736</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>158914</tid>
<number> 42</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act and the Statutes,--
<section><tid>538312</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor shall 
be appointed by the Visitor and shall hold office for a term of 
five years;

</section>

<section><tid>255834</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Registrar and the first Comptroller shall be 
appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall hold 
office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1565829</tid>
<number>c</number>the first members of the Board shall be nominated by the 
Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>858596</tid>
<number>d</number>the first members of the Academic Council shall be 
nominated by the Visitor and shall hold office for a term of 
three years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or 
nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in 
whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if 
such vacancy had not occurred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>321306</tid>
<number> 43</number> Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the 
Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.
<section><tid>1422396</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Statute,  
Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the 
Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1682490</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
Statute, Ordinance or Regulation or both Houses agree that the 
Statute, Ordinance or Regulation should not be made, the Statute, 
Ordinance or Regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice

<pagefootnote><pagenum>296</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to the validity of anything previously done under that Statute, 
Ordinance or Regulation.


</section>

<section><tid>665696</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinances 
or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be 
given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudicially 
affect the interests of any person to whom such Statutes, Ordinances 
or Regulations may be applicable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>297</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>