<act><tid>165229</tid>
<title>THE ARMY ACT, <year>1950</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>1950</year>
[ 20th May, <year>1950</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the government of 
the regular Army.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY.

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>662624</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>20211</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Army Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1358695</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>397677</tid>
<number> 2</number> Persons subject to this Act.
<section><tid>652111</tid>
<number>1</number>The following persons shall be  
subject to this Act wherever they may be, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1726707</tid>
<number>a</number>officers, junior commissioned officers and warrant 
officers of the regular Army;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1991135</tid>
<number>b</number>persons enrolled under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1607015</tid>
<number>c</number>persons belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1425974</tid>
<number>d</number>persons belonging to the Indian Supplementary Reserve 
Forces when called out for service or when carrying out the 
annual test;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>412438</tid>
<number>e</number>officers of the Territorial Army, when doing duty as 
such officers, and enrolled persons of the said Army when 
called out or embodied or attached to any regular forces, 
subject to such adaptations and modifications as may be made 
in the application of this Act to such persons under sub- 
section (1) of section 9 of the Territorial Army Act, <year>1948</year> 
 (56 of <year>1948</year>.)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to-

Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. Assam Rifles as modified by S. R. O. 318, dated 6- 12- <year>1962</year>, 
Gazette of India, Part II, Section 4, page 223.

Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1963</year>).

And brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 22nd July, <year>1950</year>, see Notification No,. S. R. 0 120, dated the 
22nd July, <year>1950</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 4, p. 86.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140776</tid>
<number>f</number>persons holding commissions in the Army in India 
Reserve of Officers, when ordered on any duty or service for 
which they are liable as members of such reserve forces;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1979296</tid>
<number>g</number>officers appointed to the Indian Regular Reserve of 
Officers, when ordered on any duty or service for which they 
are liable as members of such reserve forces;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


<subsubsection><tid>228348</tid>
<number>i</number>persons not otherwise subject to military law who, on 
active service, in camp, on the march or at any frontier post 
specified by the Central Government by notification in this 
behalf, are employed by, or are in the service of, or are 
followers of, or accompany any portion of, the regular Army

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1052957</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person subject to this Act under clauses (a) to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (g) 
of sub- section (1) shall remain so subject until duly retired, dis- 
charged, released, removed, dismissed or cashiered from the service.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>502161</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>90591</tid>
<number>i</number>" active service", as applied to a person subject to 
this Act, means the time during which such person-

<subsection><tid>150933</tid>
<number>a</number>is attached to, or forms part of, a force which is 
engaged in operations against an enemy, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>664570</tid>
<number>b</number>is engaged in military operations in, or is on the 
line of march to, a country or place wholly or partly 
occupied by an enemy, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>624992</tid>
<number>c</number>is attached to or forms part of a force which is 
in military occupation of a foreign country;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1741034</tid>
<number>ii</number>" civil offence" means an offence which is triable by a 
Criminal Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1442603</tid>
<number>iii</number>" civil prison" means any jail or place used for 
the detention of any criminal prisoner under the Prisons Act, 
<year>1894</year>, (9 of <year>1894</year>.) or under any other law for the time being 
in force;

</section>

<section><tid>829316</tid>
<number>iv</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Chief of the Army Staff" means the officer commanding 
the regular Army;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (h) omitted by the Adaption of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" (h)"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>. s. 2 and Sch., for cl. (iv)




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>506646</tid>
<number>v</number>" commanding officer", when used in any provision of 
this Act, with reference to any separate portion of the 
regular Army or to any department thereof, means the officer 
whose duty it is under the regulations of the regular Army, or 
in the absence of any such regulations, by the custom of the 
service, to discharge with respect to that portion of the 
regular Army or that department, as the case may be, the 
functions of a commanding officer in regard to matters of the 
description referred to in that provision;

</section>

<section><tid>1358799</tid>
<number>vi</number>" corps" means any separate body of persons subject to 
this Act, which is prescribed as a corps for the purposes of 
all or any of the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1748417</tid>
<number>vii</number>" court- martial" means a court- martial held under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1120502</tid>
<number>viii</number>" Criminal Court" means a Court of ordinary criminal 
justice in any part of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>;

</section>

<section><tid>367054</tid>
<number>ix</number>" department" includes any division or branch of a 
department;

</section>

<section><tid>1693972</tid>
<number>x</number>" enemy" includes all armed mutineers, armed rebels, 
armed rioters, pirates and any person in arms against whom it 
is the duty of any person subject to military law to act;

</section>

<section><tid>561972</tid>
<number>xi</number>" the Forces" means the regular Army, Navy and Air Force 
or any part of any one or more of them;

<subsection><tid>977567</tid>
<number>xii</number>" junior commissioned officer" means a person 
commissioned, gazetted or in pay as a junior commissioned 
officer in the regular Army or the Indian Reserve Forces, and 
includes a person holding a junior commission in the Indian 
Supplementary Reserve Forces. or the Territorial Army, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
who is for the time being subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>384991</tid>
<number>xiii</number>" military custody" means the arrest or confinement 
of a person according to the usages of the service and 
includes naval or air force custody;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" other than the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted 
by Act 13 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 25- 1- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" or a junior or equivalent commission in the land 
forces of a Part B State" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) 
Order, <year>1956</year>,





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1191942</tid>
<number>xiv</number>" military reward" includes any gratuity or annuity for 
long service or good conduct, good service pay or pension, 
and any other military pecuniary reward;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413348</tid>
<number>xv</number>" non- commissioned officer" means a person holding a 
non- commissioned rank or an acting non- commissioned rank in 
the regular Army or the Indian Reserve Forces, and includes a 
non- commissioned officer or acting noncommissioned officer of 
the Indian Supplementary Reserve Forces or the Territorial 
Army, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> who is for the time being subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850948</tid>
<number>xvi</number>" notification" means a notification published in 
the Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1810912</tid>
<number>xvii</number>" offence" means any act or omission punishable 
under this Act and includes a civil offence as hereinbefore 
defined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1143218</tid>
<number>xviii</number>" officer" means a person commissioned, gazetted are 
in pay as an officer in the regular Army, and includes-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1151230</tid>
<number>a</number>an officer of the Indian Reserve Forces;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1193559</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer holding a commission in the Territorial 
Army granted by the President with designation of rank 
corresponding to that of an officer of the regular Army 
who is for the time being subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>195666</tid>
<number>c</number>an officer of the Army in India Reserve of 
Officers who is for the time being subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>664235</tid>
<number>d</number>an officer of the Indian Regular Reserve of 
Officers who is for the time being subject to this Act;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>754041</tid>
<number>f</number>in relation to a person subject to this Act when 
serving under such conditions as may be prescribed, an 
officer of the Navy or Air Force;
but does not include a junior commissioned officer, warrant 
officer, petty officer or non- commissioned officer;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1193241</tid>
<number>xix</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>217</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or the land forces of a Part B State" omitted, by 
the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order. <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Sub- clause (e) omitted, ibid,




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>570226</tid>
<number>xx</number>" provost- marshal" means a person appointed as such 
under section 107 and includes any of his deputies or 
assistants or any other person legally exercising authority 
under him or on his behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1513763</tid>
<number>xxi</number>" regular Army" means officers, junior commissioned 
officers, warrant officers, non- commissioned officers and 
other enrolled persons who, by their commission, warrant, 
terms of enrolment or otherwise, are liable to warrant, terms 
of enrolment or otherwise, are liable to Union in any part of 
the world, including persons belonging to the Reserve Forces 
and the Territorial Army when called out on permanent 
service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>834373</tid>
<number>xxii</number>" regulation" includes a regulation made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1456832</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>" superior officer", when used in relation to a 
person subject to this Act, includes a junior commissioned 
officer, warrant officer and a non- commissioned officer, and, 
as regards persons placed under his orders, an officer, 
warrant officer, petty officer and non- commissioned officer 
of the Navy or Air Force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774173</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>" warrant officer" means a person appointed, 
gazetted or in pay as a warrant officer of the regular Army 
or of the Indian Reserve Forces, and includes a warrant 
officer of the Indian Supplementary Reserve Forces or of the 
Territorial Army <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> who is for the time being subject 
to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>593981</tid>
<number>xxv</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> all words (except the word" India")] and 
expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) shall be deemed to have 
the meanings assigned to them in that Code.
CHAP

SPECIAL PROVISIONS FOR THE APPLICATION OF ACT IN CERTAIN CASES.

CHAPTER II

SPECIAL PROVISIONS FOR THE APPLICATION OF ACT IN CERTAIN CASES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>481827</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application of Act to certain forces under Central Government.

<section><tid>493495</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification, apply, with or  
without modifications, all or any of the provisions of this Act to any 
force raised and maintained in India under the authority of that 
Government, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and suspend the operation of any other enactment 
for the time being applicable to the said force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>218</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or of the land forces of a Part B State" omitted by 
the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3. for" all words" (w. e. f. 25- 1-  
  <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" including any force maintained by a Part B State" 
omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1219238</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this Act so applied shall have effect in 
respect of persons belonging to the said force as they have effect in 
respect of persons subject to this Act holding in the regular Army the 
same or equivalent rank as the aforesaid persons hold for the time 
being in the said force.

</section>

<section><tid>441978</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this Act so applied shall also have effect 
in respect of persons who are employed by or are in the service of or 
are followers of or accompany any portion of the said force as they 
have effect in respect of persons subject to this Act under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clause 
 (i) of sub- section (1) of section (2)].

</section>

<section><tid>1222215</tid>
<number>4</number>While any of the provisions of this Act apply to the said 
force, the Central Government may, by notification, direct by what 
authority any jurisdiction, powers or duties incident to the operation 
of these provisions shall be exercised or performed in respect of the 
said force.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1796049</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Application of Act to forces of Part B States.] Rep. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>775728</tid>
<number> 6</number> Special provision as to rank in certain cases.
<section><tid>1654472</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification, direct that any persons or class of 
persons subject to this Act under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clause (i), of sub- section (1) of 
section 2] shall be so subject as officers, junior commissioned 
officers, warrant officers or non- commissioned officers and may 
authorise any officer to give a like direction and to cancel such 
direction.

</section>

<section><tid>515816</tid>
<number>2</number>All persons subject to this Act other than officers, junior 
commissioned officers, warrant officers and non- commissioned officers 
shall, if they are not persons in respect of whom a notification or 
direction under sub- section (1) is in force, be deemed to be of a rank 
inferior to that of a non- commissioned officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>752145</tid>
<number> 7</number> Commanding officer of persons subject to military law under 
clause (i) of section 2.
<section><tid>1823757</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person subject to this Act under  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clause (i) of subsection (1) of section 2] shall, for the purposes 
of this Act, be deemed to be under the commanding officer of the 
corps, department of detachment, if any, to which he is attached, and, 
if he is not so attached, under the command of any officer who may for 
the time being be named as his commanding officer by the officer 
commanding the force with which such person for the time being is 
serving, or any other prescribed officer, or, if no such officer is 
named or prescribed, under the command of the said officer commanding 
the force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>218A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" clause (i) of 
section".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1487569</tid>
<number>2</number>An officer commanding a force shall not place a person 
subject to this Act under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clause (i) of sub- section (1) of section 
2] under the command of an officer of rank inferior to that of such 
person, if there is present at the place where such person is any 
officer of a higher rank under whose command he can be placed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1765126</tid>
<number> 8</number> Officers exercising powers in certain cases.
<section><tid>755709</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever  
persons subject to this Act are serving under an officer commanding 
any military Organisation, not in this section specifically named and 
being in the opinion of the Central Government not less than a 
brigade, that Government may prescribe the officer by whom the powers, 
which under this Act may be exercised by officers commanding armies, 
army corps, divisions and brigades, shall, as regards such, persons, 
be exercised.

</section>

<section><tid>639535</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may confer such powers, either 
absolutely or subject to such restrictions, reservations, exceptions 
and conditions, as it may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>196874</tid>
<number>9</number>Power to declare persons to be on active service. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i) of section 3, the 
Central Government may, by notification, declare that any person or 
class of persons subject to this Act shall, with reference to any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>219</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 58 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" clause (i) of 
section 2".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

area in which they may be serving or with reference to any provision 
of this Act or of any other law for the time being in force, be deemed 
to be on active service within the meaning of this Act.

CHAP

COMMISSION, APPOINTMENT AND ENROLMENT.

CHAPTER III

COMMISSION, APPOINTMENT AND ENROLMENT



</article>



<article><tid>1996924</tid>
<number>10</number>Commission and appointment. The President may grant, to such 
person as he thinks fit, a commission as, an officer, or as a junior 
commissioned officer or appoint any person, as a warrant officer of 
the regular Army.


</article>



<article><tid>1752960</tid>
<number>11</number>Ineligibility of aliens for enrolment. No person who is not a 
citizen of India shall, except with the consent of the Central 
Government signified in writing, be enrolled in the regular Army:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall bar the 
enrolment of the subjects of Nepal in the regular Army.



</article>



<article><tid>1805862</tid>
<number>12</number>Ineligibility of females for enrolment or employment. No 
female shall be eligible for enrolment or employment in the regular 
Army, except in such corps, department, branch or other body forming 
part of, or attached to any portion of, the regular Army as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect the 
provisions of any law for the time being in force providing for the 
raising and maintenance of any service auxiliary to the regular Army 
, or any branch thereof in which females are eligible for enrolment or 
employment.



</article>



<article><tid>1617363</tid>
<number>13</number>Procedure before enrolling officer. Upon the appearance 
before the prescribed enrolling officer of any person desirous of 
being enrolled, the enrolling officer shall read and explain to him, 
or cause to be read and explained to him in his presence, the 
conditions of the service for which he is to be enrolled; and shall 
put to him the questions set forth in the prescribed form of 
enrolment, and shall, after having cautioned him that if he makes a 
false answer to any such question, he will be liable to punishment 
under this Act, record or cause to be recorded his answer to each such 
question.


</article>



<article><tid>1361327</tid>
<number>14</number>Mode of enrolment. If, after complying with the provisions of 
section 13, the enrolling officer is satisfied that the person 
desirous of being enrolled fully understands the questions put to him 
and consents to the conditions of service, and if such officer 
perceives no impediment, he shall sign and shall also cause such 
person to sign the enrolment paper, and such person shall thereupon be 
deemed to be enrolled.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>220</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1107875</tid>
<number>15</number>Validity of enrolment. Every person who has for the space of 
three months been in receipt of pay as a person enrolled under this 
Act and been borne on the rolls of any corps or department shall be 
deemed to have been duly enrolled, and shall not be entitled to claim 
his discharge on the ground of any irregularity or illegality in his 
enrolment or on any other ground whatsoever; and if any person, in 
receipt of such pay and borne on the rolls as aforesaid, claims his 
discharge before the expiry of three months from his enrolment, no 
such irregularity or illegality or other ground shall, until he is 
discharged in pursuance of his claim, affect his position as an 
enrolled person under this Act or invalidate any proceeding, act or 
thing taken or done prior to his discharge.


</article>



<article><tid>1494229</tid>
<number> 16</number> Persons to be attested. The following persons shall be 
attested, namely:-
<section><tid>1572690</tid>
<number>a</number>all persons enrolled as combatants;

</section>

<section><tid>543724</tid>
<number>b</number>all persons selected to hold a non- commissioned or 
acting non- commissioned rank; and

</section>

<section><tid>954476</tid>
<number>c</number>all other persons subject to this Act as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>434036</tid>
<number> 17</number> Mode of attestation.
<section><tid>1455977</tid>
<number>1</number>When a person who is to be attested  
is reported fit for duty, or has completed the prescribed period of 
probation, an oath or affirmation shall be administered to him in the 
prescribed form by his commanding officer in front of his corps or 
such portion thereof or such members of his department as may be 
present, or by any other prescribed person.

</section>

<section><tid>385532</tid>
<number>2</number>The form of oath or affirmation prescribed under this 
section shall contain a promise that the person to be attested will 
bear true allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law 
established, and that he will serve in the regular Army and go 
wherever he is ordered by land, sea or air, and that he will obey all 
commands of any officer set over him, even to the peril of his life.

</section>

<section><tid>1159685</tid>
<number>3</number>The fact of an enrolled person having taken the oath or 
affirmation directed by this section to be taken shall be entered on 
his enrolment paper, and authenticated by the signature of the officer 
administering the oath or affirmation.
CHAP

CONDITIONS OF SERVICE.

CHAPTER IV

CONDITIONS OF SERVICE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1715267</tid>
<number>18</number>Tenure of service under the Act. Every person subject to this 
Act shall hold office during the pleasure of the President.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>221</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1386225</tid>
<number>19</number>Termination of service by Central Government. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act and the rules and regulations made thereunder 
the Central Government may dismiss, or remove from the service, any 
person subject to this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1939328</tid>
<number> 20</number> Dismissal, removal or reduction by the Chief of the Army Staff 
and by other officers.
<section><tid>430</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Chief of the Army Staff] may dismiss  
or remove from the service any person subject to this Act other than 
an officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1992526</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Chief of the Army Staff] may reduce to a lower grade 
or rank or the ranks, any warrant officer or any non- commissioned 
officer.

</section>

<section><tid>400093</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer having power not less than a brigade or 
equivalent commander or any prescribed officer may dismiss or remove 
from the service any person serving under his command other than an 
officer or a junior commissioned officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1361242</tid>
<number>4</number>Any such officer as is mentioned in sub- section (3) may 
reduce to a lower grade or rank or the ranks, any warrant officer or 
any noncommissioned officer under his command.

</section>

<section><tid>1185720</tid>
<number>5</number>A warrant officer reduced to the ranks under this section 
shall not, however, be required to serve in the ranks as a sepoy.

</section>

<section><tid>949730</tid>
<number>6</number>The commanding officer of an acting non- commissioned officer 
may order him to revert to his permanent grade as a non- commissioned 
officer, or if he has no permanent grade above the ranks, to the 
ranks.

</section>

<section><tid>87288</tid>
<number>7</number>The exercise of any power under this section shall be subject 
to the said provisions contained in this Act and the rules and regula- 
tions made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>346835</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power to modify certain fundamental rights in their 
application to persons subject to this Act. Subject to the provisions 
of any law for the time being in force relating to the regular Army or 
to any branch thereof, the Central Government may, by notification, 
make rules restricting to such extent and in such manner as may be 
necessary the right of any person subject to this Act-
<section><tid>745541</tid>
<number>a</number>to be a member of, or to be associated in any way with, 
any trade union or labour union, or any class of trade or 
labour unions or any society, institution or association, or 
any class of societies, institutions or associations

</section>

<section><tid>1110214</tid>
<number>b</number>to attend or address any meeting or to take part in any 
demonstration organised by any body of persons for any 
political or other purposes

</section>

<section><tid>1755370</tid>
<number>c</number>to communicate with the press or to publish or cause to 
be published any book, letter or other document.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>302971</tid>
<number>22</number>Retirement, release or discharge. Any person subject to this 
Act may be retired, released or discharged from the service by such 
authority and in such manner as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>222</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" The Commander- in- 
Chief".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1175180</tid>
<number> 23</number> Certificate on termination of service. Every junior 
commissioned officer, warrant officer, or enrolled person who is 
dismissed, removed, discharged, retired or released from the service 
shall be furnished by his commanding officer with a certificate, in 
the language which is the mother tongue of such person and also in the 
English language setting forth-
<section><tid>1733067</tid>
<number>a</number>the authority terminating his service

</section>

<section><tid>1187025</tid>
<number>b</number>the cause for such termination; and

</section>

<section><tid>1730267</tid>
<number>c</number>the full period of his service in the regular Army.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>790847</tid>
<number> 24</number> Discharge or dismissal when out of India.
<section><tid>1472365</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person  
enrolled under this Act who is entitled under the conditions of his 
enrolment to be discharged, or whose discharge is ordered by competent 
authority, and who, when he is so entitled or ordered to be 
discharged, is serving out of India, and requests to be sent to India, 
shall, before being discharged, be sent to India with all convenient 
speed.

</section>

<section><tid>493234</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person enrolled under this Act who is dismissed from the 
service and who, when he is so dismissed, is serving out of India, 
shall be sent to India with all convenient speed.

</section>

<section><tid>686468</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any such person as is mentioned in sub- section (2) is 
sentenced to dismissal combined with any other punishment, such other 
punishment, or, in the case of a sentence of transportation or 
imprisonment, a portion of such sentence may be inflicted before he is 
sent to India.

</section>

<section><tid>1268065</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section, the word" discharge" 
shall' include release, and the word" dismissal" shall include 
removal.
CHAP

SERVICE PRIVILEGES.

CHAPTER V

SERVICE PRIVILEGES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>227838</tid>
<number>25</number>Authorised deductions only to be made from pay. The pay of 
every person subject to this Act due to him as such under any 
regulation for the time being in force shall be paid without any 
deduction other than the deductions authorised by or under this or any 
other Act.


</article>



<article><tid>670896</tid>
<number> 26</number> Remedy of aggrieved persons other than officers.
<section><tid>1643254</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
person subject to this Act other than an officer who deems himself 
wronged by any superior or other officer may, if not attached to a 
troop or company, complain to the officer under whose command or 
orders he is serving; and may, if attached to a troop or company, 
complain to the officer commanding the same.

</section>

<section><tid>1151538</tid>
<number>2</number>When the officer complained against is the officer to whom 
any complaint should, under sub- section (1), be preferred, the 
aggrieved person may complain to such officer' s next superior officer.

</section>

<section><tid>599271</tid>
<number>3</number>Every officer receiving any such complaint shall make as 
complete an investigation into it as may be possible for giving full 
redress

<pagefootnote><pagenum>223</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to the complainant; or, when necessary, refer the complaint to 
superior authority.


</section>

<section><tid>652871</tid>
<number>4</number>Every such complaint shall be preferred in such manner as 
may from time to time be specified by the proper authority.

</section>

<section><tid>923533</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may revise any decision by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Chief of the Army Staff] under sub- section (2), but, subject thereto, 
the decision of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1482926</tid>
<number>27</number>Remedy of aggrieved officers. Any officer who deems himself 
wronged by his commanding officer or any superior officer and who on 
due application made to his commanding officer does not receive the 
redress to which he considers himself entitled, may complain to the 
Central Government in such manner as may from time to time be 
specified by the proper authority.


</article>



<article><tid>756937</tid>
<number>28</number>Immunity from attachment. Neither the arms, clothes, 
equipment, accoutrements or necessaries of any person subject to this 
Act, nor any animal used by him for the discharge of his duty, shall 
be seized, nor shall the pay and allowances of any such person or any 
part thereof be attached, by direction of any civil or revenue court 
or any revenue officer in satisfaction of any decree or order 
enforceable against him.


</article>



<article><tid>532731</tid>
<number> 29</number> Immunity from arrest for debt.
<section><tid>47958</tid>
<number>1</number>No person subject to this  
Act shall, so long as he belongs to the Forces, be liable to be 
arrested for debt under any process issued by, or by the authority of, 
any civil or revenue court or revenue officer.

</section>

<section><tid>287668</tid>
<number>2</number>The judge of any such court or the said officer may examine 
into any complaint made by such person or his superior officer of the 
arrest of such person contrary to the provisions of this section and 
may, by warrant under his hand, discharge the person, and award 
reasonable costs to the complainant, who may recover those costs in 
like manner as he might have recovered costs awarded to him by a 
decree against the person obtaining the process.

</section>

<section><tid>1022261</tid>
<number>3</number>For the recovery of such costs no court- fee shall be payable 
by the complainant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1229672</tid>
<number> 30</number> Immunity of persons attending courts- martial from arrest.
<section><tid>145274</tid>
<number>1</number> 
No presiding officer or member of a court- martial, no judge advocate, 
no party to any proceeding before a court- martial, or his legal 
practitioner or agent, and no witness acting in obedience to a summons 
to attend a court- martial shall, while proceeding to, attending or 
returning from, a court- martial, be liable to arrest under civil or 
revenue process.

</section>

<section><tid>1717322</tid>
<number>2</number>If any such person is arrested under any such process, he 
may be discharged by order of the court- martial.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>224</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and sch. for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804475</tid>
<number>31</number>Privileges of reservists. Every person belonging to the Indian 
Reserve Forces shall, when called out for or engaged in or returning 
from, training or service, be entitled to all the privileges accorded 
by sections 28 and 29 to a person subject to this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1980534</tid>
<number> 32</number> Priority in respect of army personnel' s litigation.
<section><tid>536485</tid>
<number>1</number>On the  
presentation to any court by or on behalf of any person subject to 
this Act of a certificate from the proper military authority of leave 
of absence having been granted to or applied for by him for the 
purpose of prosecuting or defending any suit or other proceeding in 
such court, the court shall, on the application of such person, 
arrange, so far as may be possible, for the hearing and final disposal 
of such suit or other proceeding within the period of the leave so 
granted or applied for.

</section>

<section><tid>290033</tid>
<number>2</number>The certificate from the proper military authority shall 
state the first and last day of the leave or intended leave, and set 
forth a description of the case with respect to which the leave was 
granted or applied for.

</section>

<section><tid>1742530</tid>
<number>3</number>No fee shall be payable to the court in respect of the 
presentation of any such certificate, or of any application by or on 
behalf of any such person, for priority for the hearing of his case.

</section>

<section><tid>1352933</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the court is unable to arrange for the hearing and 
final disposal of the suit or other proceeding within the period of 
such leave or intended leave as aforesaid, it shall record its reasons 
for its inability to do so, and shall cause a copy thereof to be 
furnished to such person on his application without any payment 
whatever by him in respect either of the application for such copy or 
of the copy itself.

</section>

<section><tid>441512</tid>
<number>5</number>If in any case a question arises as to the proper military 
authority qualified to grant such certificate as aforesaid, such 
question shall at once be referred by the court to an officer having 
power not less than a brigade or equivalent commander whose decision 
shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>75012</tid>
<number>33</number>Saving of rights and privileges under other laws. The rights 
and privileges specified in the preceding sections of this Chapter 
shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other rights 
and privileges conferred on persons subject to this Act or on members 
of the regular Army, Navy and Air Force generally by any other law for 
the time being in force.
CHAP

OFFENCES.

CHAPTER VI

OFFENCES



</article>



<article><tid>873394</tid>
<number> 34</number> Offences in relation to the enemy and punishable with death. 
Any person subject to this Act who commits any of the following 
offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1384196</tid>
<number>a</number>shamefully abandons or delivers up any garrison, 
fortress, post, place or guard, committed to his charge, or 
which

<pagefootnote><pagenum>225</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

it is his duty to defend, or uses any means to compel or 
induce any commanding officer or other person to commit any 
of the said acts; or


</section>

<section><tid>1390449</tid>
<number>b</number>intentionally uses any means to compel or induce any 
person subject to military, naval or air force law to abstain 
from acting against the enemy, or to discourage such person 
from acting against the enemy; or

</section>

<section><tid>1641955</tid>
<number>c</number>in the presence of the enemy, shamefully casts away his 
arms, ammunition, tools or equipment or misbehaves in such 
manner as to show cowardice; or

</section>

<section><tid>106625</tid>
<number>d</number>treacherously holds correspondence with, or 
communicates intelligence to, the enemy or any person in arms 
against the Union; or

</section>

<section><tid>1904123</tid>
<number>e</number>directly or indirectly assists the enemy with money, 
arms., ammunition, stores or supplies; or

</section>

<section><tid>1999983</tid>
<number>f</number>treacherously or through cowardice sends a flag of 
truce to the enemy; or

</section>

<section><tid>502760</tid>
<number>g</number>in time of war or during any military operation, 
intentionally occasions a false alarm in action, camp, 
garrison or quarters, or spreads reports calculated to create 
alarm or despondency; or

</section>

<section><tid>1275780</tid>
<number>h</number>in time of action leaves his commanding officer or his 
post, guard, picquet, patrol or party without being regularly 
relieved or without leave; or

</section>

<section><tid>1998182</tid>
<number>i</number>having been made a prisoner of war, voluntarily serves 
with or aids the enemy; or

</section>

<section><tid>1280717</tid>
<number>j</number>knowingly harbours or protects an enemy not being a 
prisoner; or

</section>

<section><tid>619891</tid>
<number>k</number>being a sentry in time of war or alarm, sleeps upon his 
post or is intoxicated; or

</section>

<section><tid>285662</tid>
<number>l</number>knowingly does any act calculated to imperil the 
success of the military, naval or air forces of India or any 
forces co- operating therewith or any part of such forces;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer death or 
such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1640944</tid>
<number> 35</number> Offences in relation to the enemy and not punishable with 
death. Any person subject to this Act who commits any of the following 
offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>109732</tid>
<number>a</number>is taken prisoner, by want of due precaution, or 
through disobedience of orders, or wilful neglect of duty, or 
having been taken prisoner, fails to rejoin his service when 
able to do so; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>226</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1880471</tid>
<number>b</number>without due authority holds correspondence with or 
communicates intelligence to the enemy or having come by the 
knowledge of any such correspondence or communication, 
wilfully omits to discover it immediately to his commanding 
or other superior officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1514608</tid>
<number>c</number>without due authority sends a flag of truce to the 
enemy;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such 
less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1606949</tid>
<number> 36</number> Offences punishable more severely on active service than at 
other times. Any person subject to this Act who commits any of the 
following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1504872</tid>
<number>a</number>forces a safeguard, or forces or uses criminal force to 
a sentry; or

</section>

<section><tid>1534024</tid>
<number>b</number>breaks into any house or other place in search of 
plunder; or

</section>

<section><tid>326150</tid>
<number>c</number>being a sentry sleeps upon his post, or is intoxicated; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1435112</tid>
<number>d</number>without orders from his superior officer leaves his 
guard, picquet, patrol or post; or

</section>

<section><tid>51675</tid>
<number>e</number>intentionally or through neglect occasions a false 
alarm in camp, garrison, or quarters; or spreads reports 
calculated to create unnecessary alarm or despondency; or

</section>

<section><tid>984188</tid>
<number>f</number>makes known the parole, watchword or countersign to any 
person not entitled to receive it; or knowingly gives a 
parole, watchword or countersign different from what he 
received;
shall, on conviction by court- martial,

if he commits any such offence when on active service, be 
liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and

if he commits any such offence when not on active service, 
be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>91372</tid>
<number> 37</number> Mutiny. Any person subject to this Act who commits any of the 
following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1145486</tid>
<number>a</number>begins, incites, causes, or conspires with any other 
persons to cause any mutiny in the military, naval or air 
forces of India or any forces co- operating therewith; or

</section>

<section><tid>1860054</tid>
<number>b</number>joins in any such mutiny; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>227</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>994989</tid>
<number>c</number>being present at any such mutiny, does not use his 
utmost endeavours to suppress the same; or

</section>

<section><tid>419985</tid>
<number>d</number>knowing or having reason to believe in the existence of 
any such mutiny, or of any intention to mutiny or of any such 
conspiracy, does not, without delay, give information thereof 
to his commanding or other superior officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>261892</tid>
<number>e</number>endeavours to seduce any person in the military, naval. 
or air forces of India from his duty or allegiance to the 
Union;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer death or 
such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>865944</tid>
<number> 38</number> Desertion and aiding desertion.
<section><tid>1886219</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person subject to this  
Act who deserts or attempts to desert the service shall, on 
conviction by court- martial,
if he commits the offence on active service or when under 
orders for active service, be liable to suffer death or such 
less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and

if he commits the offence under any other circumstances, be 
liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.


</section>

<section><tid>1418070</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person subject to this Act who, knowingly harbours any 
such deserter shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such 
less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.

</section>

<section><tid>549883</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person subject to this Act who, being cognizant of any 
desertion or attempt at desertion of a person subject to this Act, 
does not forthwith give notice to his own or some other superior 
officer, or take any steps in his power to cause such person to be 
apprehended, shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such 
less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>816402</tid>
<number> 39</number> Absence without leave. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>204073</tid>
<number>a</number>absents himself without leave; or

</section>

<section><tid>791245</tid>
<number>b</number>without sufficient cause overstays leave granted to him; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1602118</tid>
<number>c</number>being on leave of absence and having received 
information from proper authority that any corps, or portion 
of a corps, or any department, to which he belongs, has been 
ordered on active service, fails, without sufficient cause, 
to rejoin without delay; or

</section>

<section><tid>1563040</tid>
<number>d</number>without sufficient cause fails to appear at the time 
fixed at the parade or place appointed for exercise or duty; 
or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>228</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>217075</tid>
<number>e</number>when on parade, or on the line of march, without 
sufficient cause or without leave from his superior officer, 
quits the parade or line of march; or

</section>

<section><tid>818193</tid>
<number>f</number>when in camp or garrison or elsewhere, is found beyond 
any limits fixed, or in any place prohibited, by any general, 
local or other order, without a pass or written leave from 
his superior officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1629693</tid>
<number>g</number>without leave from his superior officer or without due 
cause, absents himself from any school when duly ordered to 
attend there;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>346650</tid>
<number> 40</number> Striking or threatening superior officers. Any person subject 
to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,-
<section><tid>1712149</tid>
<number>a</number>uses criminal force to or assaults his superior 
officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>65544</tid>
<number>b</number>uses threatening language to such officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1951032</tid>
<number>c</number>uses insubordinate language to such officer;
shall, on conviction by court- martial,

if such officer is at the time in the execution of his 
office or, if the offence is committed on active service, be 
liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and

in other cases, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to ten years or such less punishment as is 
in this Act mentioned:

Provided that in the case of an offence specified in clause (c), 
the imprisonment shall not exceed five years.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1128184</tid>
<number> 41</number> Disobedience to superior officer.
<section><tid>883256</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person subject to  
this Act who disobeys in such manner as to show a wilful defiance of 
authority any lawful command given personally by his superior officer 
in the execution of his office whether the same is given orally, or in 
writing or by signal or otherwise shall on conviction by court- 
martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.

</section>

<section><tid>165048</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person subject to this Act who disobeys any lawful com- 
mand given by his superior officer shall, on conviction by court- 
martial,
if he commits such offence when on active service, be liable 
to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to


<pagefootnote><pagenum>229</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and

if he commits such offence when not on active service, be 
liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>197182</tid>
<number> 42</number> Insubordination and obstruction. Any person subject to this 
Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>18933</tid>
<number>a</number>being concerned in any quarrel, affray, or disorder, 
refuses to obey any officer, though of inferior rank, who 
orders him into arrest, or uses criminal force to or assaults 
any such officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1605339</tid>
<number>b</number>uses criminal force to, or assaults any person, whether 
subject to this Act or not, in whose custody he is lawfully 
placed, and whether he is or is not his superior officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1051412</tid>
<number>c</number>resists an escort whose duty it is to apprehend him or 
to have him in charge; or

</section>

<section><tid>842890</tid>
<number>d</number>breaks out of barracks, camp or quarters; or

</section>

<section><tid>1143948</tid>
<number>e</number>neglects to obey any general, local or other order; or

</section>

<section><tid>367618</tid>
<number>f</number>impedes the provost- marshal or any person lawfully 
acting on his behalf, or when called upon, refuses to assist 
in the execution of his duty a provost- marshal or any person 
lawfully acting on his behalf; or

</section>

<section><tid>1641168</tid>
<number>g</number>uses criminal force to or assaults any person bringing 
provisions or supplies to the forces;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend, in the case of the offences 
specified in clauses (d) and (e) to two years, and in the case of the 
offences specified in the other clauses to ten years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1764071</tid>
<number> 43</number> Fraudulent enrolment. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>203150</tid>
<number>a</number>without having obtained a regular discharge from 
the corps or department to which he belongs, or otherwise 
fulfilled the conditions enabling him to enrol or enter, 
enrols himself in, or enters the same or any other corps or 
department or any part of the naval or air forces of India or 
the Territorial Army; or

</section>

<section><tid>295271</tid>
<number>b</number>is concerned in the enrolment in any part of the Forces 
of any person when he knows or has reason to believe such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>230</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

person to be so circumstanced that by enrolling he commits 
an offence against this Act;

shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>247219</tid>
<number>44</number>False answers on enrolment. Any person having become subject 
to this Act who is discovered to have made at the time of enrolment a 
wilfully false answer to any question set forth in the prescribed form 
of enrolment which has been put to him by the enrolling officer before 
whom he appears for the purpose of being enrolled shall, on conviction 
by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>816289</tid>
<number>45</number>Unbecoming conduct. Any officer, junior commissioned officer 
or warrant officer who behaves in a manner unbecoming his position and 
the character expected of him shall, on conviction by court- martial, 
if he is an officer, be liable to be cashiered or to suffer such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and, if he is a junior 
commissioned officer or a warrant officer, be liable to be dismissed 
or to suffer such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1335226</tid>
<number> 46</number> Certain forms of disgraceful conduct. Any person subject to 
this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1814319</tid>
<number>a</number>is guilty of any disgraceful conduct of a cruel, 
indecent or unnatural kind; or

</section>

<section><tid>1882288</tid>
<number>b</number>malingers, or feigns, or produces disease or infirmity 
in himself, or intentionally delays his cure or aggravates 
his disease or infirmity; or

</section>

<section><tid>1287754</tid>
<number>c</number>with intent to render himself or any other person unfit 
for service, voluntarily causes hurt to himself or that 
person;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1094773</tid>
<number>47</number>Ill- treating a subordinate. Any officer, junior commissioned 
officer, warrant officer or non- commissioned officer who uses criminal 
force to or otherwise illtreats any person subject to this Act, being 
his subordinate in rank or position, shall, on conviction by court- 
martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>6366</tid>
<number> 48</number> Intoxication.
<section><tid>899646</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person subject to this Act who is found  
in a state of intoxication, whether on duty or not, shall, on 
conviction by court- martial, if he is an officer, be liable to be 
cashiered or to suffer such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and, if he is not an

<pagefootnote><pagenum>231</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officer, be liable, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such 
less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</section>

<section><tid>1467553</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an offence of being intoxicated is committed by a 
person other than an officer when not on active service or not on 
duty, the period of imprisonment awarded shall not exceed six months.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1798492</tid>
<number> 49</number> Permitting escape of person in custody. Any person subject to 
this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1439671</tid>
<number>a</number>when in command of a guard, picquet, patrol or post, 
releases without proper authority, whether wilfully or 
without reasonable excuse, any person committed to his 
charge, or refuses to receive any prisoner or person so 
committed; or

</section>

<section><tid>1939281</tid>
<number>b</number>wilfully or without reasonable excuse allows to escape 
any person who is committed to his charge, or whom it is his 
duty to keep or guard;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable, if he has acted 
wilfully to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; 
and if he has not acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years or such less punishment as is in this 
Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1307549</tid>
<number> 50</number> Irregularity in connection with arrest or confinement. Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, 
that is to say,-
<section><tid>1319888</tid>
<number>a</number>unnecessarily detains a person in arrest or confinement 
without bringing him to trial, or fails to bring his case 
before the proper authority for investigation; or

</section>

<section><tid>1843744</tid>
<number>b</number>having committed a person to military custody fails 
without reasonable cause to deliver at the time of such com- 
mittal, or as soon as practicable, and in any case within 
forty- eight hours. thereafter, to the officer or other person 
into whose custody the person arrested is committed, an 
account in writing signed by himself of the offence with 
which the person so committed is charged;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1779031</tid>
<number>51</number>Escape from custody. Any person subject to this Act who, being 
in lawful custody, escapes or attempts to escape, shall, on conviction 
by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>232</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1551960</tid>
<number> 52</number> Offences in respect of property. Any person subject to this 
Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>386591</tid>
<number>a</number>commits theft of any property belonging to the 
Government, or to any military, naval or air force mess, band 
or institution, or to any person subject to military, naval 
or air force law; or

</section>

<section><tid>1336406</tid>
<number>b</number>dishonestly misappropriates or converts to his own use 
any such property; or

</section>

<section><tid>512305</tid>
<number>c</number>commits criminal breach of trust in respect of any such 
property; or

</section>

<section><tid>291901</tid>
<number>d</number>dishonestly receives or retains any such property in 
respect of which any of the offences under clauses (a), (b) 
and (c) has been committed, knowing or having reason to 
believe the commission of such offence; or

</section>

<section><tid>606364</tid>
<number>e</number>wilfully destroys or injures any property of the 
Government entrusted to him; or

</section>

<section><tid>469905</tid>
<number>f</number>does any other thing with intent to defraud, or to 
cause wrongful gain to one person or wrongful loss to another 
person;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend to ten years or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1665585</tid>
<number> 53</number> Extortion and corruption. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>413013</tid>
<number>a</number>commits extortion; or

</section>

<section><tid>153170</tid>
<number>b</number>without proper authority exacts from any person money, 
provisions or service;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631293</tid>
<number> 54</number> Making away with equipment. Any person subject to this Act 
who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>304326</tid>
<number>a</number>makes away with, or is concerned in making away with, 
any arms, ammunition, equipment, instruments. tools, clothing 
or any other thing being the property of the Government 
issued to him for his use or entrusted to him; or

</section>

<section><tid>1157244</tid>
<number>b</number>loses by neglect anything mentioned in clause (a); or

</section>

<section><tid>863238</tid>
<number>c</number>sells, pawns, destroys or defaces any medal or 
decoration granted to him;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>233</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend in the case of the offences specified 
in clause (a) to ten years, and in the case of the offences specified 
in the other clauses to five years, or such less punishment as is in 
this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>832561</tid>
<number> 55</number> Injury to property. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1755795</tid>
<number>a</number>destroys or injures any property mentioned in clause 
 (a) of section 54 or any property belonging to any military, 
naval or air force mess, band or institution, or to any 
person subject to military, naval or air force law, or 
serving with, or attached to, the regular Army; or

</section>

<section><tid>1428086</tid>
<number>b</number>commits any act which causes damage to, or destruction 
of, any property of the Government by fire; or

</section>

<section><tid>1325586</tid>
<number>c</number>kills, injures, makes away with, ill- treats or loses 
any, animal entrusted to him;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable, if he has acted wil- 
fully, to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen 
years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and if he 
has acted without reasonable excuse, to suffer imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this 
Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1288893</tid>
<number> 56</number> False accusations. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1709285</tid>
<number>a</number>makes a false accusation against any person subject to 
this Act, knowing or having reason to believe such accusation 
to be false; or

</section>

<section><tid>871596</tid>
<number>b</number>in making a complaint under section 26 or section 27 
makes any statement affecting the character of any person 
subject to this Act, knowing or having reason to believe such 
statement to be false or knowingly and wilfully suppresses 
any material facts;
shall, on conviction by court- martial be liable to suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to five years or such less punishment as 
is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>368957</tid>
<number> 57</number> Falsifying official documents and false declaration. Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, 
that is to say,-
<section><tid>1631348</tid>
<number>a</number>in any report, return, list, certificate, book or other 
document made or signed by him, or of the contents of which 
it is his duty to ascertain the accuracy, knowingly makes,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>234</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or is privy to the making of any false or fraudulent 
statement; or


</section>

<section><tid>1631850</tid>
<number>b</number>in any document of the description mentioned in clause 
 (a) knowingly makes, or is privy to the making of, any 
omission, with intent to defraud; or

</section>

<section><tid>1044764</tid>
<number>c</number>knowingly and with intent to injure any person, or 
knowingly and with intent to defraud, suppresses, defaces, 
alters or makes away with any document which it is his duty 
to preserve or produce; or

</section>

<section><tid>1539032</tid>
<number>d</number>where it is his official duty to make a declaration 
respecting any matter, knowingly makes a false declaration; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>322950</tid>
<number>e</number>obtains for himself, or for any other person, any 
pension, allowance or other advantage or privilege by a state- 
ment which is false, and which he either knows or believes to 
be false or does not believe to be true, or by making or 
using a false entry in any book or record or by making any 
document containing a false statement, or by omitting to make 
a true entry or document containing a true statement;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1670042</tid>
<number> 58</number> Signing in blank and failure to report. Any person subject 
to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,-
<section><tid>110395</tid>
<number>a</number>when signing any document relating to pay, arms, 
ammunition, equipment, clothing, supplies or stores, or 
any,. property of the Government fraudulently leaves in blank 
any material part for which his signature is a voucher; or

</section>

<section><tid>1036532</tid>
<number>b</number>refuses or by culpable neglect omits to make or send a 
report or return which it is his duty to make or send;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>52867</tid>
<number> 59</number> Offences relating to courts- martial. Any person subject to 
this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>841717</tid>
<number>a</number>being duly summoned or ordered to attend as a witness 
before a court martial, wilfully or without reasonable 
excuse, makes default in attending; or

</section>

<section><tid>1286449</tid>
<number>b</number>refuses to take an oath or make an affirmation legally 
required by a court- martial to be taken or made; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>235</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1442828</tid>
<number>c</number>refuses to produce or deliver any document in his power 
or control legally required by a court- martial to be produced 
or delivered by him; or

</section>

<section><tid>1183141</tid>
<number>d</number>refuses when a witness to answer any question which he 
is by law bound to answer; or

</section>

<section><tid>909886</tid>
<number>e</number>is guilty of contempt of court- martial by using 
insulting or threatening language, or by causing any 
interruption or disturbance in the proceedings of such court;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend to three years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1760606</tid>
<number>60</number>False evidence. Any person subject to this Act who, having 
been duly sworn or affirmed before any court- martial or other court 
competent under this Act to administer an oath or affirmation, makes 
any statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes to 
be false or does not believe to be true, shall, on conviction by 
court- martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1330028</tid>
<number>61</number>Unlawful detention of pay. Any officer, junior commissioned 
officer, warrant officer or non- commissioned officer who, having 
received the pay of a person subject to this Act unlawfully detains 
or refuses to pay the same when due, shall, on conviction by court- 
martial, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1560558</tid>
<number> 62</number> Offences in relation to aircraft and flying. Any person 
subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is 
to say,-
<section><tid>528775</tid>
<number>a</number>wilfully or without reasonable excuse damages, destroys 
or loses any aircraft or aircraft material belonging to the 
Government: or

</section>

<section><tid>1616130</tid>
<number>b</number>is guilty of any act or neglect likely to cause such 
damage, destruction or loss; or

</section>

<section><tid>1570794</tid>
<number>c</number>without lawful authority disposes of any aircraft or 
aircraft material belonging to the Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>566906</tid>
<number>d</number>is guilty of any act or neglect in flying, or in the 
use of any aircraft, or in relation to any aircraft or 
aircraft material, which causes or is likely to cause loss of 
life or bodily injury to any person; or

</section>

<section><tid>34052</tid>
<number>e</number>during a state of war, wilfully and without proper 
occasion, or negligently, causes the sequestration, by or 
under the authority of a neutral State, or the destruction in 
a neutral State of any aircraft, belonging to the Government

<pagefootnote><pagenum>236</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable, if he has acted wil- 
fully, to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen 
years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned, and, in any 
other case, to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to five 
years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>348987</tid>
<number>63</number>Violation of good order and discipline. Any person subject 
to this Act who is guilty of any act or omission which, though not 
specified in this Act, is prejudicial to good order and military 
discipline shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1225704</tid>
<number> 64</number> Miscellaneous offences. Any person subject to this Act who 
commits any of the following offences, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1751905</tid>
<number>a</number>being in command at any post or on the march, and 
receiving a complaint that any one under his command has 
beaten or otherwise maltreated or oppressed any person, or 
has disturbed any fair or market, or committed any riot or 
trespass, fails to have due reparation made to the injured 
person or to report the case to the proper authority; or

</section>

<section><tid>1391300</tid>
<number>b</number>by defiling any place of worship, or otherwise, 
intentionally insults the religion or wounds the religious 
feelings of any person; or

</section>

<section><tid>432556</tid>
<number>c</number>attempts to commit suicide, and in such attempt does 
any act towards the commission of such offence; or

</section>

<section><tid>1701744</tid>
<number>d</number>being below the rank of warrant officer, when off duty, 
appears without proper authority, in or about camp or 
cantonments, or in or about, or when going to or returning 
from, any town or bazar, carrying a rifle, sword or other 
offensive weapon; or

</section>

<section><tid>1886763</tid>
<number>e</number>directly or indirectly accepts or obtains, or agrees to 
accept or attempts to obtain, for himself or for any other 
person, any gratification as a motive or reward for procuring 
the enrolment' of any person, or leave of absence, promotion 
or any other advantage or indulgence for any person in the 
service; or

</section>

<section><tid>385014</tid>
<number>f</number>commits any offence against the property or person of 
any inhabitant of, or resident in, the country in which he is 
serving;
shall, on conviction by court- martial, be liable to suffer imprison- 
ment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>237</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1027705</tid>
<number>65</number>Attempt. Any person subject to this Act who attempts to 
commit any of the offences specified in sections 34 to 64 inclusive 
and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the 
offence, shall, on conviction by court- martial, where no express 
provision is made by this Act for the punishment of such attempt, be 
liable,
if the offence attempted to be committed is punishable with 
death, to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and

if the offence attempted to be committed is punishable with 
imprisonment, to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one- half of the longest term provided for that 
offence or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.



</article>



<article><tid>696941</tid>
<number>66</number>Abetment of offences that have been committed. Any person 
subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
specified in sections 34 to 64 inclusive shall, on conviction by 
court- martial, if the Act abetted is committed in consequence of the 
abetment and no express provision is made by this Act for the 
punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer the punishment 
provided for that offence or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1549270</tid>
<number> 67</number> Abetment of offences punishable with death and not 
committed. Any person subject to this Act who abets the commission of 
any of the offences punishable with death under sections 34, 37 and 
sub- section
<section><tid>1547655</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 38 shall, on conviction by court-  
martial, if that offence be not committed in consequence of the 
abetment, and no express provision is made by this Act for the 
punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is 
in this Act mentioned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>623225</tid>
<number>68</number>Abetment of offences punishable with imprisonment and not 
committed. Any person subject to this Act who abets the commission of 
any of the offences specified in sections 34 to 64 inclusive and 
punishable with imprisonment shall, on conviction by court- martial, if 
that offence be not committed in consequence of the abetment, and no 
express provision is made by this Act for the punishment of such 
abetment, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one- half of the longest term provided for that offence or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>234068</tid>
<number> 69</number> Civil offences. Subject to the provisions of section 70, 
any person subject to this Act who at any place in or beyond India 
commits any civil

<pagefootnote><pagenum>238</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

offence shall be deemed to be guilty of an offence against this Act 
and, if charged therewith under this section, shall be liable to be 
tried by a court- martial and, on conviction, be punishable as follows, 
that is to say,-

<section><tid>484319</tid>
<number>a</number>if the offence is one which would be punishable under 
any law in force in India with death or with transportation, 
he shall be liable to suffer any punishment, other than 
whipping, assigned for the offence, by the aforesaid law and 
such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and

</section>

<section><tid>1023874</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, he shall be liable to suffer any 
punishment, other than whipping, assigned for the offence by 
the law in force in India, or imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to seven years, or such less punishment as is in 
this Act mentioned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>226490</tid>
<number> 70</number> Civil offence not triable by court- martial. A person subject 
to this Act who commits an offence of murder against a person not 
subject to military, naval or air force law, or of culpable homicide 
not amounting to murder against such a person or of rape in relation 
to such a person, shall not be deemed to be guilty of an offence 
against this Act and shall not be tried by a court- martial, unless he 
commits any of the said offences-
<section><tid>1423103</tid>
<number>a</number>while on active service, or

</section>

<section><tid>1621358</tid>
<number>b</number>at any place outside India, or

</section>

<section><tid>437362</tid>
<number>c</number>at a frontier post specified by the Central Government 
by notification in this behalf.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

CHAP

PUNISHMENTS.

CHAPTER VII

PUNISHMENTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>432283</tid>
<number> 71</number> Punishments awardable by courts- martial. Punishments may be 
inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons subject to this 
Act and convicted by courts- martial, according to the scale following, 
that is to say,-
<section><tid>1224475</tid>
<number>a</number>death;

</section>

<section><tid>1810866</tid>
<number>b</number>transportation for life or for any period not less than 
seven years;

</section>

<section><tid>1901115</tid>
<number>c</number>imprisonment, either rigorous or simple, for any period 
not exceeding fourteen years;

</section>

<section><tid>1102919</tid>
<number>d</number>cashiering, in the case of officers;

</section>

<section><tid>891043</tid>
<number>e</number>dismissal from the service;

</section>

<section><tid>400629</tid>
<number>f</number>reduction to the ranks or to a lower rank or grade or 
place in the list of their rank, in the case of warrant 
officers;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>239</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Explanation omitted by Act 13, of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1975</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and reduction to the ranks or to a lower rank or grade, 
in the case of non- commissioned officers:

Provided that a warrant officer reduced to the ranks shall 
not be required to serve in the ranks as a sepoy;


</section>

<section><tid>171899</tid>
<number>g</number>forfeiture of seniority of rank, in the case of 
officers, junior commissioned officers, warrant officers and 
noncommissioned officers; and forfeiture of all or any part 
of their service for the purpose of promotion, in the case of 
any of them whose promotion depends upon length of service;

</section>

<section><tid>1469464</tid>
<number>h</number>forfeiture of service for the purpose of increased pay, 
pension or any other prescribed purpose;

</section>

<section><tid>43258</tid>
<number>i</number>severe reprimand or reprimand, in the case of 
officers, junior commissioned officers, warrant officers and 
noncommissioned officers;

</section>

<section><tid>1213119</tid>
<number>j</number>forfeiture of pay and allowances for a period not 
exceeding three months for an offence committed on active 
service;

</section>

<section><tid>30202</tid>
<number>k</number>forfeiture in the case of a person sentenced to 
cashiering or dismissal from the service of all arrears of 
pay and allowances and other public money due to him at the 
time of such cashiering or dismissal;

</section>

<section><tid>1737321</tid>
<number>l</number>stoppage of pay and allowances until any proved loss or 
damage occasioned by the offence of which he is convicted is 
made good.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>633683</tid>
<number>72</number>Alternative punishments awardable by court- martial. Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, a court- martial may, on convicting a 
person subject to this Act of any of the offences specified in 
sections 34 to 68 inclusive, award either the particular punishment 
with which the offence is stated in the said sections to be 
punishable, or, in lieu thereof, any one of the punishments lower in 
the scale set out in section 71, regard being had to the nature and 
degree of the offence.


</article>



<article><tid>1680583</tid>
<number>73</number>Combination of punishments. A sentence of a court- martial 
may award in addition to, or without any one other punishment, the 
punishment specified in clause (d) or clause (e) of section 71 and any 
one or more of the punishments specified in clauses (f) to (l) of that 
section.


</article>



<article><tid>1645842</tid>
<number>74</number>Cashiering of officers. An officer shall be sentenced to be 
cashiered before he is awarded any of the punishments specified in 
clauses (a) to (c) of section 71.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>240</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 2






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1471451</tid>
<number>77</number>Result of certain punishments in the case of a warrant 
officer or non- commissioned officer. A warrant officer or a non- 
commissioned officer sentenced by a court- martial to transportation, 
imprisonment, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or dismissal from the service, shall be deemed to 
be reduced to ranks.


</article>



<article><tid>1204420</tid>
<number>78</number>Retention in the ranks of a person convicted on active 
service. When., on active service, any enrolled person has been sen- 
tenced by a court- martial to dismissal, or to transportation or im- 
prisonment whether combined with dismissal or not, the prescribed 
officer may direct that such person may be retained to serve in the 
ranks, and such service shall be reckoned as part of his term of 
transportation or imprisonment, if any.


</article>



<article><tid>701513</tid>
<number>79</number>Punishments otherwise than by court- martial. Punishments 
may also be inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons 
subject to this Act without the intervention of a court- martial and in 
the manner stated in sections 80, 83, 84 and 85.


</article>



<article><tid>266175</tid>
<number> 80</number> Punishment of persons other than officers, junior 
commissioned officers and warrant officers. Subject to the provisions 
of section 81, a commanding officer or such other officer as is, with 
the consent of the Central Government, specified by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the 
Army Staff], may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against a person 
subject to this Act other. wise than as an officer, junior 
commissioned officer or warrant officer who is charged with an offence 
under this Act and award such person, to the extent prescribed, one or 
more of the following punishments, that is to say,-
<section><tid>809695</tid>
<number>a</number>imprisonment in military custody up to twenty- eight 
days;

</section>

<section><tid>1035</tid>
<number>b</number>detention up to twenty- eight days;

</section>

<section><tid>1292087</tid>
<number>c</number>confinement to the lines up to twenty- eight days;

</section>

<section><tid>395461</tid>
<number>d</number>extra guards or duties;

</section>

<section><tid>292523</tid>
<number>e</number>deprivation of a, position of the nature of an 
appointment or of corps or working pay, and in the case of 
noncommissioned officers, also deprivation of acting rank or 
reduction to a lower grade of pay;

</section>

<section><tid>538788</tid>
<number>f</number>forfeiture of good service and good conduct pay

</section>

<section><tid>24404</tid>
<number>g</number>severe reprimand or reprimand

</section>

<section><tid>1530066</tid>
<number>h</number>fine up to fourteen days' pay in any one month;

</section>

<section><tid>1564489</tid>
<number>i</number>penal deductions under clause (g) of section 91

<pagefootnote><pagenum>241</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>. s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- 
in- Chief".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 3.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182463</tid>
<number> 81</number> Limit of punishments under section 80. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.
<section><tid>1565392</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of an award of two or more of the punishments 
specified in clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of the said section, the 
punishment specified in clause (c) or clause (d) shall take effect 
only at the end of the punishment specified in clause (a) or clause 
 (b).

</section>

<section><tid>1387090</tid>
<number>3</number>When two or more of the punishments specified in the said 
clauses (a), (b) and (c) are awarded to a person conjointly, or when 
already undergoing one or more of the said punishments, the whole 
extent of the punishments shall not exceed in the aggregate forty- two 
days.

</section>

<section><tid>895892</tid>
<number>4</number>The punishments specified in clauses <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> (a), (b) and (c)] of 
section 80 shall not be awarded to any person who is of the rank of 
non- commissioned officer or was, at the time of committing the offence 
for which he is punished, of such rank.

</section>

<section><tid>408376</tid>
<number>5</number>The punishment specified in clause (g) of the said section 
shall not be awarded to any person below the rank of a non- 
commissioned officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1477610</tid>
<number>82</number>Punishments in addition to those specified in section 80. 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Chief of the Army Staff] may, with the consent of the Central 
Government, specify such other punishments as may be awarded under 
section 80 in addition to or without any of the punishments specified 
in the said section, and the extent to which such other punishments 
may be awarded.


</article>



<article><tid>562439</tid>
<number> 83</number> Punishment of officers, junior commissioned officers and 
warrant officers by brigade commanders and others. An officer having 
power not less than a brigade, or an equivalent commander or such 
other officer as is, with the consent of the Central Government, 
specified by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] may in the prescribed 
manner, proceed against an officer below the rank of a field officer, 
a junior commissioned officer or a warrant officer, who is charged 
with an offence under this Act, and award one or more of the following 
punishments, that is to say,-
<section><tid>515202</tid>
<number>a</number>severe reprimand or reprimand;

</section>

<section><tid>299004</tid>
<number>b</number>stoppage of pay and, allowances until any proved loss 
or damage occasioned by the offence of which he is convicted 
is made good.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1458846</tid>
<number> 84</number> Punishment of officers, junior commissioned officers and 
warrant officers by area commanders and others. An officer having 
power not less than an area commander or an equivalent commander or an 
officer empowered to convene a general court- martial or such other 
officer as is, with the consent of the Central Government, specified 
by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>242</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief". 
2 Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 4. 
3 Omitted by s. 5, ibid. 
4 Subs. by s. 5, ibid.









</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against an officer below the 
rank of lieutenant- colonel, a junior commissioned officer or a warrant 
officer, who is charged with an offence under this Act, and award one 
or more of the following punishments, that is to say,-

<section><tid>461717</tid>
<number>a</number>forfeiture of seniority, or in the case of any of them 
whose promotion depends upon length of service, forfeiture of 
service for the purpose of promotion for a period not 
exceeding twelve months, but subject to the right of the 
accused previous to the award to elect to be tried by a 
court- martial;

</section>

<section><tid>1027836</tid>
<number>b</number>severe reprimand or reprimand;

</section>

<section><tid>979694</tid>
<number>c</number>stoppage of pay and allowances until any proved loss or 
damage occasioned by the offence of which he is convicted is 
made good.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977730</tid>
<number> 85</number> Punishment of junior commissioned officers. A commanding 
officer or such other officer as is, with the consent of the Central 
Government, specified by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] may, in the 
prescribed manner, proceed against a junior commissioned officer who 
is charged with an offence under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and award one or more of 
the following punishments, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1161413</tid>
<number>i</number>severe reprimand or reprimand;

</section>

<section><tid>1157480</tid>
<number>ii</number>stoppage of pay and allowances until any proved loss or 
damage occasioned by the offence of which he is convicted is 
made good:
Provided that the punishment specified in clause (i) shall not be 
awarded if the commanding officer or such other officer is below the 
rank of Colonel]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1433907</tid>
<number>86</number>Transmission of proceedings. In every case in which 
punishment has been awarded under any of the sections 83, 84 and 85, 
certified true copies of the proceedings shall be forwarded, in the 
prescribed manner, by the officer awarding the punishment, to a 
superior military authority as defined in section 88.


</article>



<article><tid>1233815</tid>
<number>87</number>Review of proceedings. If any punishment awarded under any 
of the sections 83, 84 and 85 appears to a superior military authority 
as defined in section 88 to be illegal, unjust or excessive, such 
authority may cancel, vary or remit the punishment and make such other 
direction as may be appropriate in the circumstances of the case.


</article>



<article><tid>687941</tid>
<number> 88</number> Superior military authority. For the purpose of sections 86 
and 87, a" superior military authority" means-
<section><tid>1177450</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of punishments awarded by a commanding 
officer, any officer superior in command to such commanding 
officer;

</section>

<section><tid>834803</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of punishments awarded by any other 
authority, the Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army 
Staff] or other officer specified by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army 
Staff]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>243</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for the Commander- in- 
Chief".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 6.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1576778</tid>
<number> 89</number> Collective fines.
<section><tid>1568067</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever any weapon or part of a  
weapon forming part of the equipment of a half squadron, battery, 
company or other similar unit is lost or stolen, the officer 
commanding the army, army corps, division or independent brigade to 
which such unit belongs may, after obtaining the report of a court of 
inquiry, impose a collective fine upon the junior commissioned 
officers, warrant officers, non- commissioned officers and men of such 
unit, or upon so many of them as, in his judgment, should be held 
responsible for such loss or theft.

</section>

<section><tid>1559377</tid>
<number>2</number>Such fine shall be assessed as a percentage on the pay of 
the individuals on whom it falls.
CHAP

PENAL DEDUCTIONS.

CHAPTER VIII

PENAL DEDUCTIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1904762</tid>
<number> 90</number> Deductions from pay and allowances of officers. The 
following penal deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of 
an officer, that is to say,-
<section><tid>1422531</tid>
<number>a</number>all pay and allowances due to an officer for every day 
he absents himself without leave, unless a satisfactory 
explanation has been given to his commanding officer and has 
been approved by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1375522</tid>
<number>b</number>all pay and allowances for every day while he is in 
custody or under suspension from duty on a charge for an 
offence for which he is afterwards convicted by a criminal 
court or a court- martial or by an officer exercising 
authority under section 83 or section 84;

</section>

<section><tid>665020</tid>
<number>c</number>any sum required to make good the pay of any person 
subject to this Act which he has unlawfully retained or 
unlawfully refused to pay;

</section>

<section><tid>1623264</tid>
<number>d</number>any sum required to make good such compensation for any 
expenses, loss, damage or destruction occasioned by the 
commission of an offence as may be determined by the court- 
martial by whom he is convicted of such offence, or by an 
officer exercising authority under section 83 or section 84

</section>

<section><tid>1399793</tid>
<number>e</number>all pay and allowances ordered by a court- martial <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
to be forfeited or stopped;

</section>

<section><tid>791584</tid>
<number>f</number>any sum required to pay a fine awarded by a criminal 
court or a court- martial exercising jurisdiction under 
section 69;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>244</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 7.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>958596</tid>
<number>g</number>any sum required to make good any loss, damage, or 
destruction of public or regimental property which, after due 
investigation, appears to the Central Government to have been 
occasioned by the wrongful act or negligence on the part of 
the officer;

</section>

<section><tid>335494</tid>
<number>h</number>all pay and allowances forfeited by order of the 
Central Government if the officer is found by a court of 
inquiry constituted by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] in 
this behalf, to have deserted to the enemy, or while in enemy 
hands, to have served with, or under the orders of, the 
enemy, or in any manner to have aided the enemy, or to have 
allowed himself to be taken prisoner by the enemy through 
want of due precaution or through disobedience of orders or 
wilful neglect of duty, or having been taken prisoner by the 
enemy, to have failed to rejoin his service when it was 
possible to do so;

</section>

<section><tid>1602811</tid>
<number>i</number>any sum required by order of the Central Government 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or any prescribed officers] to be paid for the maintenance 
of his wife or his legitimate or illegitimate child or 
towards the cost of any relief given by the said Government 
to the said wife or child.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1983662</tid>
<number> 91</number> Deductions from pay and allowances of persons other than 
officers. Subject to the provisions of section 94 the following penal 
deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of a person subject 
to this, Act other than an officer, that is to say,-
<section><tid>38944</tid>
<number>a</number>all pay and allowances for every day of absence either 
on desertion or without leave, or as a prisoner of war, and 
for every day of transportation or imprisonment awarded by a 
criminal court, a court- martial or an officer exercising 
authority under section 80 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>1433856</tid>
<number>b</number>all pay and allowances for every day while he is in 
custody on a charge for an offence of which he is afterwards 
convicted by a criminal court or a court- martial, or on a 
charge of absence without leave for which he is afterwards 
awarded imprisonment <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> by an officer exercising authority 
under section 80;

</section>

<section><tid>1637630</tid>
<number>c</number>all pay and allowances for every day on which he is in 
hospital on account of sickness certified by the medical 
officer attending on him to have been caused by an offence 
under this Act committed by him;

</section>

<section><tid>1070393</tid>
<number>d</number>for every day on which he is in hospital on account of 
sickness certified by the medical officer attending on him

<pagefootnote><pagenum>245</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- 
in- Chief".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 7

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Omitted by s. 8, ibid.








</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

to have been caused by his own misconduct or imprudence, such 
sum as may be specified by order of the Central Government 
or such officer as may be specified by that Government;


</section>

<section><tid>1354052</tid>
<number>e</number>all pay and allowances ordered by a court- martial or by 
an officer exercising authority under any of the sections 80, 
83, 84 and 85, to be forfeited or stopped;

</section>

<section><tid>160837</tid>
<number>f</number>all pay and allowances for every day between his being 
recovered from the enemy and his dismissal from the service 
in consequence of his conduct when being taken prisoner by, 
or while in the hands of, the enemy;

</section>

<section><tid>1312811</tid>
<number>g</number>any sum required to make good such compensation for any 
expenses, loss, damage or destruction caused by him to the 
Central Government or to any building or property as may be 
awarded by his commanding officer;

</section>

<section><tid>779235</tid>
<number>h</number>any sum required to, pay a fine awarded by a criminal 
court, a court- martial exercising jurisdiction under section 
69, or an officer exercising authority under any of the 
sections 80 and 89;

</section>

<section><tid>1626956</tid>
<number>i</number>any sum required by order of the Central Government or 
any prescribed officer to be paid for the maintenance of his 
wife or his legitimate or illegitimate child or towards the 
cost of any relief given by the said Government to the said 
wife or child.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1899009</tid>
<number> 92</number> Computation of time of absence or custody. For the purposes 
of clauses (a) and (b) of section 91,-
<section><tid>452507</tid>
<number>a</number>no person shall be treated as absent or in custody for 
a day unless the absence or custody has lasted, whether 
wholly in one day, or partly in one day and partly in 
another, for six consecutive hours or upwards;

</section>

<section><tid>875750</tid>
<number>b</number>any absence or custody for less than a day may be 
reckoned as absence or custody for a day if such absence or 
custody prevented the absentee from fulfilling any military 
duty which was thereby thrown upon some other person;

</section>

<section><tid>472428</tid>
<number>c</number>absence or custody for twelve consecutive hours or 
upwards may be reckoned as absence or custody for the whole 
of each day during any portion of which the person was absent 
or in custody;

</section>

<section><tid>1126097</tid>
<number>d</number>a period of absence, or imprisonment, which commences 
before, and ends after, midnight may be reckoned as a day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747960</tid>
<number>93</number>Pay and allowances during trial. In the case of any person 
subject to this Act who is in custody or under suspension from duty on 
a charge for an offence, the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>246</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

prescribed officer may direct that the whole or any part of the pay 
and allowances of such person shall be withheld, pending the result of 
his trial on the charge against him, in order to give effect to the 
provisions of clause (b) of sections 90 and 91.



</article>



<article><tid>984400</tid>
<number>94</number>Limit of certain deductions. The total deductions from the 
pay and allowances of a person made under clauses (e), (g) to (i) of 
section 91 shall not, except where he is sentenced to dismissal, 
exceed in any one month one- half of his pay and allowances for that 
month.


</article>



<article><tid>1911437</tid>
<number>95</number>Deduction from public money due to a person. Any sum 
authorised by this Act to be deducted from the pay and allowances of 
any person may, without prejudice to any other mode of recovering the 
same, be deducted from any public money due to him other than a 
pension.


</article>



<article><tid>121981</tid>
<number>96</number>Pay and allowances of prisoner of war during inquiry into 
his conduct. Where the conduct of any person subject to this Act when 
being taken prisoner by, or while in the hands of, the enemy, is to be 
inquired into under this Act or any other law, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army 
Staff] or any officer authorised by him may order that the whole or 
any part of the pay and allowances of such person shall be withheld 
pending the result of such inquiry.


</article>



<article><tid>1885756</tid>
<number>97</number>Remission of deductions. Any deduction from pay and 
allowances authorised by this Act may be remitted in such manner and 
to such extent, and by such authority, as may from time to time be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1505044</tid>
<number>98</number>Provision for dependants of prisoner of war from remitted 
deductions. In the case of all persons subject to this Act, being 
prisoners of war, whose pay and allowances have been forfeited under 
clause (h) of section 90 or clause (a) of section 91, but in respect 
of whom a remission has been made under section 97, it shall be lawful 
for proper provision to be made by the prescribed authorities out of 
such pay and allowances for any dependants of such persons, and any 
such remission shall in that case be deemed to apply only to the 
balance thereafter remaining of such pay and allowances.


</article>



<article><tid>984573</tid>
<number>99</number>Provision for dependants of prisoner war from his pay and 
allowances. It shall be lawful for proper provision to be made by the 
prescribed authorities for any dependants of any person subject to 
this Act who is a prisoner of war or is missing, out of his pay and 
allowances.


</article>



<article><tid>929781</tid>
<number>100</number>Period during which a person is deemed to be a prisoner of 
war. For the purposes of sections 98 and 99, a person shall be deemed 
to continue to be a prisoner of war until the conclusion of any 
inquiry into his conduct such as is referred to in section 96, and if 
he is cashiered or dismissed from the service in consequence of such 
conduct, until the date of such cashiering or dismissal.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>247</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ARREST AND PROCEEDINGS BEFORE TRIAL.

CHAPTER IX

ARREST AND PROCEEDINGS BEFORE TRIAL



</article>



<article><tid>1105898</tid>
<number> 101</number> Custody of offenders.
<section><tid>1179638</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person subject to this Act who  
is charged with an offence may be taken into military custody.

</section>

<section><tid>1562579</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such person may be ordered into military custody by any 
superior officer.

</section>

<section><tid>524264</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer may order into military custody any officer, though he 
may be of a higher rank, engaged in a quarrel, affray or disorder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1245914</tid>
<number> 102</number> Duty of commanding officer in regard to detention.
<section><tid>545805</tid>
<number>1</number>It  
shall be the duty of every commanding officer to take care that a 
person under his command when charged with an offence is not detained 
in custody for more than forty- eight hours after the committal of such 
person into custody is reported to him, without the charge being 
investigated, unless investigation within that period seems to him to 
be impracticable having regard to the public service.

</section>

<section><tid>1034078</tid>
<number>2</number>The case of every person being detained in custody beyond a 
period of forty- eight hours, and the reason thereof, shall be reported 
by the commanding officer to the general or other officer to whom 
application would be made to convene a general or district court- 
martial for the trial of the person charged.

</section>

<section><tid>568484</tid>
<number>3</number>In reckoning the period of forty- eight hours specified in 
sub- section (1), Sundays and other public holidays shall be excluded.

</section>

<section><tid>593767</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Central 
Government may make rules providing for the manner in which and the 
period for which any person subject to this Act may be taken into and 
detained in military custody, pending the trial by any competent 
authority for any offence committed by him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252561</tid>
<number>103</number>Interval between commital and court- martial. In every case 
where any such person as is mentioned in section 101 and as is not on 
active service remains in such custody for a longer period than eight 
days, without a court- martial for his trial being ordered to assemble, 
a special report giving reasons for the delay shall be made by his 
commanding officer in the manner prescribed, and a similar report 
shall be forwarded at intervals of every eight days until a court- 
martial is assembled or such person is released from custody.


</article>



<article><tid>1778118</tid>
<number>104</number>Arrest by civil authorities. Whenever any person subject to 
this Act, who is accused of any offence under this Act, is within the 
jurisdiction of any magistrate or police officer, such magistrate or 
police officer shall aid in the apprehension and delivery to military 
custody of such person upon receipt of a written application to that 
effect signed by his commanding officer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>248</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1762794</tid>
<number> 105</number> Capture of deserters.
<section><tid>1177958</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever any person subject to  
this Act deserts, the commanding officer of the corps, department or 
detachment to which he belongs, shall give written information of the 
desertion to such civil authorities as, in his opinion, may be able to 
afford assistance towards the capture of the deserter; and such 
authorities shall thereupon take steps for the apprehension of the 
said deserter in like manner as if he were a person for whose 
apprehension a warrant had been issued by a magistrate, and shall 
deliver the deserter. when apprehended, into military custody.

</section>

<section><tid>595240</tid>
<number>2</number>Any police officer may arrest without warrant any person 
reasonably believed to be subject to this Act, and to be a deserter or 
to be travelling without authority, and shall bring him without delay 
before the nearest magistrate, to be dealt with according to law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>981329</tid>
<number> 106</number> Inquiry into absence without leave.
<section><tid>284563</tid>
<number>1</number>When any person  
subject to this Act has been absent from his duty without due 
authority for a period of thirty days, a court of inquiry shall, as 
soon as practicable, be assembled, and such court shall, on oath or 
affirmation administered in the prescribed manner, inquire respecting 
the absence of the person, and the deficiency, if any, in the property 
of the Government entrusted to his care, or in any arms, ammunition, 
equipment, instruments, clothing or necessaries; and if satisfied of 
the fact of such absence without due authority or other sufficient 
cause, the court shall declare such absence and the period thereof, 
and the said deficiency, if any, and the commanding officer of the 
corps or department to which the person belongs shall enter in the 
court- martial book of the corps or department a record of the 
declaration.

</section>

<section><tid>1545886</tid>
<number>2</number>If the person declared absent does not afterwards surrender 
or is not apprehended, he. shall, for the purposes of this Act, be 
deemed to be a deserter.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>70968</tid>
<number> 107</number> Provost- marshals.
<section><tid>942235</tid>
<number>1</number>Provost- marshals may be appointed by  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] or by any prescribed officer.

</section>

<section><tid>112666</tid>
<number>2</number>The duties of a provost- marshal are to take charge of 
persons confined for any offence, to preserve good order and 
discipline, and to prevent breaches of the same by persons serving in, 
or attached to, the regular Army.

</section>

<section><tid>1430117</tid>
<number>3</number>A provost- marshal may act any time arrest and detain for 
trial any person subject to this Act who commits, or is charged with, 
an offence, and may also carry into effect any punishment to be 
inflicted in pursuance of the sentence awarded by a court- martial, or 
by an officer exercising authority under section 80 but shall not 
inflict any punishment on his own authority:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>249</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no officer shall be so arrested or detained 
otherwise than on the order of another officer.


</section>

<section><tid>571133</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of sub- sections (2) and (3), a provost- 
marshal shall be deemed to include a provost- marshal appointed under 
any law for the time being in force relating to the Government of the 
Navy or Air Force, and any person legally exercising authority under 
him or on his behalf.
CHAP

COURTS- MARTIAL.

CHAPTER X

COURTS- MARTIAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1195410</tid>
<number> 108</number> Kinds of courts- martial. For the purposes of this Act there 
shall be four kinds of courts- martial, that is to say,-
<section><tid>462345</tid>
<number>a</number>general courts- martial;

</section>

<section><tid>1451852</tid>
<number>b</number>district courts- martial;

</section>

<section><tid>81626</tid>
<number>c</number>summary general courts- martial; and

</section>

<section><tid>1838229</tid>
<number>d</number>summary courts- martial.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>758191</tid>
<number>109</number>Power to convene a general court- martial. A general court- 
martial may be convened by the Central Government or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of 
the Army Staff] or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant 
of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff].


</article>



<article><tid>1118517</tid>
<number>110</number>Power to convene a district court- martial. A district court- 
martial may be convened by an officer having power to convene a 
general court- martial or by any officer empowered in this behalf by 
warrant of any such officer.


</article>



<article><tid>978809</tid>
<number>111</number>Contents of warrants issued under sections 109 and 110. A 
warrant issued under section 109 or section 110 may contain such 
restrictions, reservations or conditions as the officer issuing, it 
may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1110992</tid>
<number> 112</number> Power to convene a summary general court- martial. The 
following authorities shall have power to convene a summary general 
court- martial, namely,-
<section><tid>41368</tid>
<number>a</number>an officer empowered in this behalf by an order of the 
Central Government or of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff];

</section>

<section><tid>605723</tid>
<number>b</number>on active service, the officer commanding the forces in 
the field, or any officer empowered by him in this behalf;

</section>

<section><tid>1527093</tid>
<number>c</number>an officer commanding any detached portion of the 
regular Army on active service when, in his opinion, it is 
not practicable, with due regard to discipline and the exi- 
gencies of the service, that an offence should be tried by a 
general court- martial.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747826</tid>
<number>113</number>Composition of general court- martial. A general court- 
martial shall consist of not less than five officers, each of whom has 
held a commission for not less than three

<pagefootnote><pagenum>250</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2, and Sch., for." the 
Commander- in- Chief".





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

whole years and of whom not less than four are of a rank not below 
that of captain.



</article>



<article><tid>523525</tid>
<number>114</number>Composition of district court- martial. A district court- 
martial shall consist of not less than three officers, each of whom 
has held a commission for not less than two whole years.


</article>



<article><tid>1936806</tid>
<number>115</number>Composition of summary general court- martial. A summary 
general court- martial shall consist of not less than three officers.


</article>



<article><tid>1655055</tid>
<number> 116</number> Summary court- martial.
<section><tid>1623529</tid>
<number>1</number>A summary court- martial may be  
held by the commanding officer of any corps, department or detachment 
of the regular Army, and he shall alone constitute the court.

</section>

<section><tid>1929628</tid>
<number>2</number>The proceedings shall be attended throughout by two other 
persons who shall be officers or junior commissioned officers or one 
of either, and who shall not as such, be sworn or affirmed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1857067</tid>
<number> 117</number> Dissolution of courts- martial.
<section><tid>95984</tid>
<number>1</number>If a court- martial after  
the commencement of a trial is reduced below the minimum number of 
officers required by this Act, it shall be dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>1776625</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on account of the illness of the judge advocate or of 
the accused before the finding, it is impossible to continue the 
trial, a court- martial shall be dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>1908648</tid>
<number>3</number>The officer who convened a court- martial may dissolve such 
court- martial if it appears to him that military exigencies or the 
necessities of discipline render it impossible or inexpedient to 
continue the said court- martial.

</section>

<section><tid>1766653</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a court- martial is dissolved under this section, the 
accused may be tried again.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>375135</tid>
<number>118</number>Powers of general and summary general courts- martial. A 
general or summary general court- martial shall have power to try any 
person subject to this Act for any offence punishable therein and to 
pass any sentence authorised thereby.


</article>



<article><tid>873335</tid>
<number>119</number>Powers of district courts- martial. A district court- 
martial shall have power to try any person subject to this Act 
other than an officer or a junior commissioned officer for any offence 
made punishable therein, and to pass any sentence authorised by this 
Act other than a sentence of death, transportation, or imprisonment 
for a term exceeding two years:
Provided that a district court- martial shall not sentence a 
warrant officer to imprisonment.



</article>



<article><tid>1485696</tid>
<number> 120</number> Powers of summary courts- martial.
<section><tid>24380</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), a summary court- martial may try any 
offence punishable under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1516821</tid>
<number>2</number>When there is no grave reason for immediate action and 
reference can without detriment to discipline be made to the officer 
empowered to convene a district court- martial or on active service

<pagefootnote><pagenum>251</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

a summary general court- martial for the trial of the alleged offender, 
an officer holding a summary court- martial shall not try without such 
reference any offence punishable under any of the sections 34, 37 and 
69, or any offence against the officer holding the court.


</section>

<section><tid>1250490</tid>
<number>3</number>A summary court- martial may try any person subject to this 
Act and under the command of the officer holding the court, except an 
officer, junior commissioned officer or warrant officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1670968</tid>
<number>4</number>A summary court- martial may pass any sentence which may be 
passed under this Act, except a sentence of death or transportation, 
or of imprisonment for a term exceeding the limit specified in sub- 
section (5).

</section>

<section><tid>1970713</tid>
<number>5</number>The limit referred to in sub- section (4) shall be one year 
if the officer holding the summary court- martial is of the rank of 
lieutenantcolonel and upwards, and three months if such officer is 
below that rank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1914649</tid>
<number>121</number>Prohibition of second trial. When any person subject to this 
Act has been acquitted or convicted of an offence by a court- martial 
or by a criminal court, or has been dealt with under any of the 
sections 80, 83, 84 and 85, he shall not be liable to be tried again 
for the same offence by a court- 
martial or dealt with under the said sections.


</article>



<article><tid>1984588</tid>
<number> 122</number> Period of limitation for trial.
<section><tid>623224</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as provided by  
sub- section (2), no trial by court- martial of any person subject to 
this Act for any offence shall be commenced after the expiration of a 
period of three years <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and such period shall commence,-

<subsection><tid>1563833</tid>
<number>a</number>on the date of the offence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1324454</tid>
<number>b</number>where the commission of the offence was not known to 
the person aggrieved by the offence or to the authority com- 
petent to initiate action, the first day on which such 
offence comes to the knowledge of such person or authority, 
whichever is earlier; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>915710</tid>
<number>c</number>where it is not known by whom the offence was com- 
mitted, the first day on which the identity of the offender 
is known to the person aggrieved by the offence or to the 
authority competent to initiate action, whichever is earlier.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>794046</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply to a trial 
for an offence of desertion or fraudulent enrolment or for any of the 
offences mentioned in section 37.

</section>

<section><tid>633493</tid>
<number>3</number>In the computation of the period of time mentioned in sub- 
section (1), any time spent by such person as a prisoner of war, or in 
enemy territory, or in evading arrest after the commission of the 
offence, shall be excluded.

</section>

<section><tid>1045586</tid>
<number>4</number>No trial for an offence of desertion other than desertion on 
active service or of fraudulent enrolment shall be commenced if the 
person in question, not being an officer, has subsequently to the 
commission of the offence, served continuously in an exemplary manner 
for not less than three years with any portion of the regular Army.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>755884</tid>
<number> 123</number> Liability of offender who ceases to be subject to Act.
<section><tid>150912</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act had been committed by any person while 
subject to this Act, and he has ceased to be so subject, he may be 
taken into and kept in military custody, and tried and punished for 
such offence as if he continued to be so subject.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>252</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 9.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1155293</tid>
<number>2</number>No such person shall be tried for an offence, unless his 
trial commences <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> within a period of three years after he had ceased 
to be subject to this Act; and in computing such period, the time 
during which such person has avoided arrest by absconding or 
concealing himself or where the institution of the proceeding in 
respect of the offence has been stayed by an injunction or order, the 
period of the continuance of the injunction or order, the day on which 
it was issued or made, and the day on which it was withdrawn, shall be 
excluded:]
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to the trial of any such person for an offence of desertion or 
fraudulent enrolment or for any of the offences mentioned in section 
 37 or shall affect the jurisdiction of a criminal court to try any 
offence triable by such court as well as by a court- martial.


</section>

<section><tid>727423</tid>
<number>3</number>When a person subject to this Act is sentenced by a court- 
martial to transportation or imprisonment, this Act shall apply to him 
during the term of his sentence, though he is cashiered or dismissed 
from the regular Army, or has otherwise ceased to be subject to this 
Act, and he may be kept, removed, imprisoned and punished as if he 
continued to be subject to this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1723248</tid>
<number>4</number>When a person subject to this Act is sentenced by a court- 
martial to death, this Act shall apply to him till the sentence is 
carried out.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>639545</tid>
<number>124</number>Place of trial. Any person subject to this Act who commits 
any offence against it may be tried and punished for such offence in 
any place whatever.


</article>



<article><tid>440590</tid>
<number>125</number>Choice between criminal court and court- martial. When a 
criminal court and a court- martial have each jurisdiction in respect 
of an offence, it shall be in the discretion of the officer commanding 
the army, army corps, division or independent brigade in which the 
accused person is serving or such other officer as may be prescribed 
to decide before which court the proceedings shall be instituted, and, 
if that officer decides that they should be instituted before a court- 
martial, to direct that the accused person shall be detained in 
military custody.


</article>



<article><tid>1701462</tid>
<number> 126</number> Power of criminal court to require delivery of offender.
<section><tid>542147</tid>
<number>1</number> 
When a criminal court having jurisdiction is of opinion that 
proceedings shall be instituted before itself in respect of any 
alleged offence, it may, by written notice, require the officer 
referred to in section 125 at his option, either to deliver over the 
offender to the nearest magistrate to be proceeded against according 
to law, or to postpone proceedings pending a reference to the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1225878</tid>
<number>2</number>In every such case the said officer shall either deliver 
over the offender in compliance with the requisition, or shall 
forthwith refer the question as to the court before which the 
proceedings are to be instituted for the determination of the Central 
Government, whose order upon such reference shall be final.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>253</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 10.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted by s. 11, ibid.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

PROCEDURE OF COURTS- MARTIAL.

CHAPTER XI

PROCEDURE OF COURTS- MARTIAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1011993</tid>
<number>128</number>Presiding officer. At every general, district or summary 
general court- martial the senior member shall be the presiding 
officer.


</article>



<article><tid>1665963</tid>
<number>129</number>Judge advocate. Every general court- martial shall, and 
every district or summary general court- martial may, be attended by a 
judge advocate, who shall be either an officer belonging to the 
department of the Judge Advocate General, or if no such officer is 
available, an officer approved of by the Judge Advocate General or any 
of his deputies.


</article>



<article><tid>1371298</tid>
<number> 130</number> Challenges.
<section><tid>126733</tid>
<number>1</number>At all trials by general, district or  
summary general court- martial, as soon as the court is assembled, the 
names of the presiding officer and members shall be read over to the 
accused, who shall thereupon be asked whether he objects to being 
tried by any officer sitting on the court.

</section>

<section><tid>1923418</tid>
<number>2</number>If the accused objects to any such officer, his objection, 
and also the reply thereto of the officer objected to, shall be heard 
and recorded, and the remaining officers of the court shall, in the 
absence of the challenged officer decide on the objection.

</section>

<section><tid>1960805</tid>
<number>3</number>If the objection is allowed by one- half or more of the votes 
of the officers entitled to vote, the objection shall be allowed, and 
the member objected to shall retire, and his vacancy may be filled in 
the prescribed manner by another officer subject to the same right of 
the accused to object.

</section>

<section><tid>1183639</tid>
<number>4</number>When no challenge is made, or when challenge has been made 
and disallowed, or the place of every officer successfully challenged 
has been filled by another officer to whom no objection is made or 
allowed, the court shall proceed with the trial.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>641271</tid>
<number> 131</number> Oaths of member, judge advocate and witness.
<section><tid>1876071</tid>
<number>1</number>An oath or  
affirmation in the prescribed manner shall be administered to every 
member of every court- martial and to the judge advocate before the 
commencement of the trial.

</section>

<section><tid>530314</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person giving evidence before a court- martial shall be 
examined after being duly sworn or affirmed in the prescribed form.

</section>

<section><tid>1267539</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) shall not apply where the 
witness is a child under twelve years of age and the court- martial is 
of opinion that though the witness understands the duty of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>254</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

speaking the truth, he does not understand the nature of an oath or 
affirmation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485273</tid>
<number> 132</number> Voting by members.
<section><tid>481744</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub-  
sections (2) and (3), every decision of a court- martial shall be 
passed by an absolute majority of votes; and where there is an 
equality of votes on either the finding or the sentence, the decision 
shall be in favour of the accused.

</section>

<section><tid>649978</tid>
<number>2</number>No sentence of death shall be passed by a general court- 
martial without the concurrence of at least two- thirds of the members 
of the court.

</section>

<section><tid>1821823</tid>
<number>3</number>No sentence of death shall be passed by a summary general 
court- martial without the concurrence of all the members.

</section>

<section><tid>1014821</tid>
<number>4</number>In matters, other than a challenge or the finding or 
sentence, the presiding officer shall have a casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1812052</tid>
<number>133</number>General rule as to evidence. The Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, 
 (1 of <year>1872</year>.) shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, apply to 
all proceedings before a court- martial.


</article>



<article><tid>1776290</tid>
<number>134</number>Judicial notice. A court- martial may take judicial notice 
of any matter within the general military knowledge of the members.


</article>



<article><tid>1907307</tid>
<number> 135</number> Summoning withnesses.
<section><tid>718037</tid>
<number>1</number>The convening officer, the  
presiding officer of a court- martial, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or courts of inquiry] the 
judge advocate or the commanding officer of the accused person may, by 
summons under his hand, require the attendance, at a time and place to 
be mentioned in the summons, of any person either to give evidence or 
to produce any document or other thing.

</section>

<section><tid>1368801</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of a witness amenable to military authority, the 
summons shall be sent to his commanding officer, and such officer 
shall serve it upon him accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1240259</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of any other witness, the summons shall be sent 
to the magistrate within whose jurisdiction he may be or reside, and 
such magistrate shall give effect to the summons as if the witness 
were required in the court of such magistrate.

</section>

<section><tid>1848766</tid>
<number>4</number>When a witness is required to produce any particular 
document or other thing in his possession or power, the summons shall 
describe it with reasonable precision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>81157</tid>
<number> 136</number> Documents exempted from production.
<section><tid>149108</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing in section  
 135 shall be deemed to affect the operation of sections 123 and 124 of 
the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, (1 of <year>1872</year>.) or to apply to any letter, 
postcard, telegram or other document in the custody of the postal or 
telegraph authorities.

</section>

<section><tid>1593359</tid>
<number>2</number>If any document in such custody is, in the opinion of any 
district magistrate, chief presidency magistrate, High Court or Court 
of Session, wanted for the purpose of any court- martial, such magis- 
trate or Court may require the postal or telegraph authorities, as the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>255</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 12.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

case may be, to deliver such document to such person as such 
magistrate or Court may direct.


</section>

<section><tid>1171204</tid>
<number>3</number>If any such document is, in the opinion of any other 
magistrate or of any commissioner of police or district superintendent 
of police, wanted for any such purpose, he may require the postal or 
telegraph authorities, as the case may be, to cause search to be made 
for and to detain such document pending the orders of any such 
district magistrate, chief presidency magistrate or High Court or 
Court of Session.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>871030</tid>
<number> 137</number> Commissions for examination of withness.
<section><tid>344266</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever, in  
the course of a trial by court- martial, it appears to the Court that 
the examination of a witness is necessary for the ends of justice, and 
that the attendance of such witness cannot be procured without an 
amount of delay, expense or inconvenience which, in the circumstances 
of the case, would be unreasonable, such Court may address the Judge 
Advocate General in order that a commission to take the evidence of 
such witness may be issued.

</section>

<section><tid>1210010</tid>
<number>2</number>The Judge Advocate General may then, if he thinks necessary, 
issue a commission to any district magistrate or magistrate of the 
first class, within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such 
witness resides, to take the evidence of such witness.

</section>

<section><tid>676019</tid>
<number>3</number>The magistrate or officer to whom the commission is issued, 
or, if he is the district magistrate, he or such magistrate of the 
first class as he appoints in this behalf, shall proceed to the place 
where the witness is or shall summon the witness before him and shall 
take down his evidence in the same manner, and may for this purpose 
exercise the same powers, as in trials of warrant- cases under the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2 of <year>1974</year>.) on any corresponding 
law in force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State of Jammu and Kashmir].

</section>

<section><tid>1857205</tid>
<number>4</number>When the witness resides in a tribal area or in any place 
outside India, the commission may be issued in the manner specified in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Chapter XXII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2 of <year>1974</year>.) 
or of any corresponding law om force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir].

</section>

<section><tid>326756</tid>
<number>5</number>In this and the next succeeding section, the expression 
" Judge Advocate General" includes a Deputy Judge Advocate General.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>532888</tid>
<number> 138</number> Examination of a withness on commission.
<section><tid>1303525</tid>
<number>1</number>The prosecutors  
and the accused person in any case in which a commission is issued 
under section 137 may respectively forward any interrogatories in 
writing which the Court may think

<pagefootnote><pagenum>256</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" a 
Part B State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 13.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

relevant to the issue, and the magistrate or officer executing the 
commission shall examine the witness upon such interrogatories.


</section>

<section><tid>432187</tid>
<number>2</number>The prosecutor and the accused person may appear before such 
magistrate or officer by counsel or, except in the case of an accused 
person in custody, in person, and may examine, cross- examine and re- 
examine, as the case may be, the said witness.

</section>

<section><tid>626838</tid>
<number>3</number>After a commission issued under section 137 has been duly 
executed, it shall be returned, together with the deposition of the 
witness examined thereunder, to the Judge Advocate General.

</section>

<section><tid>889076</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of a commission and deposition returned under 
subsection (3), the Judge Advocate General shall forward the same to 
the Court at whose instance the commission was issued or, if such 
Court has been dissolved, to any other Court convened for the trial of 
the accused person; and the commission, the return thereto and the 
deposition shall be open to inspection by the prosecutor and the 
accused person, and may, subject to all just exceptions, be read in 
evidence in the case by either the prosecutor or the accused, and 
shall form part of the proceedings of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1744902</tid>
<number>5</number>In every case in which a commission is issued under section 
137, the trial may be adjourned for a specified time reasonably 
sufficient for the execution and return of the commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1968575</tid>
<number> 139</number> Conviction of offence not charged.
<section><tid>1073129</tid>
<number>1</number>A person charged  
before a court- martial with desertion may be found guilty of 
attempting to desert or of being absent without leave.

</section>

<section><tid>1829436</tid>
<number>2</number>A person charged before a court- martial with attempting to 
desert may be found guilty of being absent without leave.

</section>

<section><tid>1361818</tid>
<number>3</number>A person charged before a court- martial with using criminal 
force may be found guilty of assault.

</section>

<section><tid>731472</tid>
<number>4</number>A person charged before a court- martial with using 
threatening language may be found guilty of using insubordinate 
language.

</section>

<section><tid>1948813</tid>
<number>5</number>A person charged before a court- martial with any one of the 
offences specified in clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of section 52 may 
be found guilty of any other of these offences with which he might 
have been charged.

</section>

<section><tid>1483003</tid>
<number>6</number>A person charged before a court- martial with an offence 
punishable under section 69 may be found guilty of any other offence 
of which he might have been found guilty if the provisions of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2 of <year>1974</year>.) were applicable.

</section>

<section><tid>770208</tid>
<number>7</number>A person charged before a court- martial with any offence 
under this Act, may, on failure of proof of an offence having been 
committed in circumstances involving a more severe punishment, be 
found guilty of the same offence as having been committed in 
circumstances involving a less severe punishment.

</section>

<section><tid>1419301</tid>
<number>8</number>A person charged before a court- martial with any offence 
under this Act may be found guilty of having attempted or abetted

<pagefootnote><pagenum>257</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the commission of that offence, although the attempt or abetment is 
not separately charged.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1495934</tid>
<number>140</number>Presumption as to signatures. In any proceeding under this 
Act, any application, certificate, warrant, reply or other document 
purporting to be signed by an officer in the service of the Government 
shall, on production, be presumed to have been duly signed by the 
person by whom and in the character in which it purports to have been 
signed, until the contrary is shown.


</article>



<article><tid>471869</tid>
<number> 141</number> Enrolment paper.
<section><tid>1281466</tid>
<number>1</number>Any enrolment paper purporting to be  
signed by an enrolling officer shall, in proceedings under this Act, 
be evidence of the person enrolled having given the answers to 
questions which he is therein represented as having given.

</section>

<section><tid>1449072</tid>
<number>2</number>The enrolment of such person may be proved by the production 
of the original or a copy of his enrolment paper purporting to be 
certified to be a true copy by the officer having the custody of the 
enrolment paper.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>204340</tid>
<number> 142</number> Presumption as to certain documents.
<section><tid>1416192</tid>
<number>1</number>A letter, return or  
other document respecting the service of any person in, or the 
cashiering, dismissal or discharge of any person from, any portion of 
the regular Army, or respecting the circumstance of any person not 
having served in, or belonged to, any portion of the Forces, if 
purporting to be signed by or on behalf of the Central Government or 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff], or by any prescribed officer, shall be 
evidence of the facts stated in such letter, return or other document.

</section>

<section><tid>1952070</tid>
<number>2</number>An Army, Navy or Air Force List or Gazette purporting to be 
published by authority shall be evidence of the status and rank of the 
officers, junior commissioned officers or warrant officers therein 
mentioned, and of any appointment held by them and of the corps, 
battalion or arm or branch of the services to which they belong.

</section>

<section><tid>1829132</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a record is made in any regimental book in pursuance 
of this Act or of any rules made thereunder or otherwise in pursuance 
of military duty, and purports to be signed by the commanding officer 
or by the officer whose duty it is to make such record, such record 
shall be evidence of the facts therein stated.

</section>

<section><tid>1864065</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of any record in any regimental book purporting to 
be certified to be a true copy by the officer having custody of such 
book shall be evidence of such record.

</section>

<section><tid>4233</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any person subject to this Act is being tried on a 
charge of desertion or of absence without leave, and such person has 
surrendered himself into the custody of any officer or other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>258</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

person subject to this Act, or any portion of the regular Army, or has 
been apprehended by such officer or person, a certificate purporting 
to be signed by such officer, or by the commanding officer of that 
portion of the regular Army, or by the commanding officer of the 
corps, department or detachment to which such person belongs, as the 
case may be, and stating the fact, date and place of such surrender or 
apprehension, and the manner in which he was dressed, shall be 
evidence of the matters so stated.


</section>

<section><tid>1856160</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any person subject to this Act is being tried on a 
charge of desertion or of absence without leave, and such person has 
surrendered himself into the custody of, or has been apprehended by, a 
police officer not below the rank of an officer in charge of a police 
station, a certificate purporting to be signed by such police officer 
and stating the fact, date and place of such surrender or apprehension 
and the manner in which he was dressed shall be evidence of the 
matters so stated.

</section>

<section><tid>135902</tid>
<number>7</number>Any document purporting to be a report under the hand of any 
Chemical Examiner or Assistant Chemical Examiner to Government 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or any of the Government scientific experts namely, the Chief 
Inspector of the Explosives, the Director of Finger Print Bureau, the 
Director, Haffkeine Institute, Bombay, the Director of a Central 
Forensic Science Laboratory or a State Forensic Science Laboratory and 
the Serologist to the Government.] upon any matter or thing duly 
submitted to him for examination or analysis and report may be used as 
evidence in any proceeding under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1249721</tid>
<number> 143</number> Reference by accused to Government officer.
<section><tid>958553</tid>
<number>1</number>If at any  
trial for desertion or absence without leave, overstaying leave or not 
rejoining when warned for service, the person tried states in his 
defence any sufficient or reasonable excuse for his unauthorised 
absence, and refers in support thereof to any officer in the service 
of the Government, or if it appears that any such officer is likely to 
prove or disprove the said statement in the defence, the court shall 
address such officer and adjourn the proceedings until his reply is 
received.

</section>

<section><tid>322631</tid>
<number>2</number>The written reply of any officer so referred to shall, if 
signed by him be received in evidence and have the same effect as if 
made on oath before the court.

</section>

<section><tid>700458</tid>
<number>3</number>If the court is dissolved before the receipt of such reply, 
or if the court omits to comply with the provisions of this section, 
the convening officer may, at his discretion, annul the proceedings and 
order a, fresh trial.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>680488</tid>
<number> 144</number> Evidence of previous convictions and general character.
<section><tid>1440774</tid>
<number>1</number> 
When any person subject to this Act has been convicted by a court- 
martial of any offence, such court- martial may inquire into, and 
receive and record evidence of any previous convictions of such 
person, either by a court- martial or by a criminal court, or any 
previous award of punishment under any of the sections 80, 83, 84 and 
85, and may further inquire into and record the general character of 
such person and such other matters as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>259</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s, 15.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>839251</tid>
<number>2</number>Evidence received under this section may be either oral, or 
in the shape of entries in, or certified extracts from, court- martial 
books or other official records; and it shall not be necessary to 
give notice before trial to the person tried that evidence as to his 
previous convictions or character will be received.

</section>

<section><tid>917554</tid>
<number>3</number>At a summary court- martial the officer holding the trial 
may, if he thinks fit, record any previous convictions against the 
offender, his general character, and such other matters as may be 
prescribed, as of his own knowledge, instead of requiring them to be 
proved under the foregoing provisions of this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1821917</tid>
<number> 145</number> Lunacy of accused.
<section><tid>634004</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever, in the course of a trial by  
a court- martial, it appears to the court that the person charged is by 
reason of unsoundness of mind incapable of making his defence, or that 
he committed the act alleged but was by reason of unsoundness of mind 
incapable of knowing the nature of the act or knowing that it was 
wrong or contrary to law, the court shall record a finding 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1117069</tid>
<number>2</number>The presiding officer of the court, or, in the case of a 
summary court- martial, the officer holding the trial, shall forthwith 
report the case to the confirming officer, or to the authority 
empowered to deal with its finding under section 162, as the case may 
be.

</section>

<section><tid>444652</tid>
<number>3</number>The confirming officer to whom the case is reported under 
subsection (2) may, if he does not confirm the finding, take steps to 
have the accused person tried by the same or another court- martial for 
the offence with which he was charged.

</section>

<section><tid>1168231</tid>
<number>4</number>The authority to whom the finding of a summary court- martial 
is reported under sub- section (2), and a confirming officer confirming 
a finding in any case so reported to him shall order the accused 
person to be kept in custody in the prescribed manner and shall 
report the case for the orders of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>649374</tid>
<number>5</number>On receipt of a report under sub- section (4) the Central 
Government may order the accused person to be detained in a lunatic 
asylum or other suitable place of safe custody.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>919055</tid>
<number> 146</number> Subsequent fitness of lunatic accused for trial. Where any 
accused person, having been found by reason of unsoundness of mind to 
be incapable of making his defence, is in custody or under detention 
under section 145, the officer commanding the army, army corps, 
division or brigade within the area of whose command the accused is in 
custody or is detained, or any other officer prescribed in this 
behalf, may-
<section><tid>1128443</tid>
<number>a</number>if such person is in custody under sub- section (4) of 
section 145, on the report of a medical officer that he is 
capable of making his defence, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>260</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>270894</tid>
<number>b</number>if such person is detained in a jail under sub- section 
 (5) of section 145, on a certificate of the Inspector General 
of Prisons, and if such person is detained in a lunatic 
asylum under the said sub- section on a certificate of any two 
or more of the visitors of such asylum that he is capable of 
making his defence,
take steps to have such person tried by the same or another court- 
martial for the offence with which he was originally charged or, if 
the offence is a civil offence, by a criminal court.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1295174</tid>
<number>147</number>Transmission to Central Government of orders under section 
146. A copy of every order made by an officer under section 146 for 
the trial of the accused shall forthwith be sent to the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1296300</tid>
<number> 148</number> Release of lunatic accused. Where any person is in custody 
under sub- section (4) of section 145 or under detention under sub- 
section (5) of that section-
<section><tid>26539</tid>
<number>a</number>if such person is in custody under the said sub- section 
 (4), on the report of a medical officer, or

</section>

<section><tid>1821600</tid>
<number>b</number>if such person is detained under the said sub- section 
 (5), on a certificate from any of the authorities mentioned 
in clause (b) of section 146 that, in the judgment of such 
officer or authority such person may be released without 
danger of his doing injury to himself or to any other person,
the Central Government may order that such person be released or 
detained in custody, or transferred to a public lunatic asylum if he 
has not already been sent to such an asylum.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>687929</tid>
<number>149</number>Delivery of lunatic accused to relatives. Where any 
relative or friend of any person who is in custody under sub- section 
 (4) of section 145 or under detention under sub- section (5) of that 
section desires that he should be delivered to his care and custody, 
the Central Government may upon application by such relative or friend 
and on his giving security to the satisfaction of that Government that 
the person delivered shall be properly taken care of and prevented 
from doing injury to himself or any other person, and be produced for 
the inspection of such officer, and at such times and places, as the 
Central Government may direct, order such person to be delivered to 
such relative or friend.


</article>



<article><tid>1496437</tid>
<number>150</number>Order for custody and disposal of property pending trial. 
When any property regarding which any offence appears to have been 
committed, or which appears to have been used for the commission of 
any offence, is produced before a court- martial during a trial, the 
court may make such order as it thinks fit for the proper custody of 
such property pending the conclusion of the trial, and if the property 
is subject to speedy or natural decay may, after recording such 
evidence as it thinks necessary, order it to be sold or otherwise 
disposed of.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>261</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1005001</tid>
<number> 151</number> Order for disposal of property regarding which offence is 
committed.
<section><tid>515424</tid>
<number>1</number>After the conclusion of a trial before any court-  
martial, the Court or the officer confirming the finding or sentence 
of such court- martial, or any authority superior to such officer, or, 
in the case of a court- martial whose finding or sentence does not 
require confirmation, the officer commanding the army, army corps, 
division or brigade within which the trial was held, may make such 
order as it or he thinks fit for the disposal by destruction, 
confiscation, delivery to any person claiming to be entitled to 
possession thereof, or otherwise, of any property or document produced 
before the Court or in its custody, or regarding which any offence 
appears to have been committed or which has been used for the 
commission of any offence.

</section>

<section><tid>939040</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any order has been made under sub- section (1) in res- 
pect of property regarding which an offence appears to have been 
committed, a copy of such order signed and certified by the authority 
making the same may, whether the trial was held within India or not, 
be sent to a magistrate within whose jurisdiction such property for 
the time being is situated, and such magistrate shall thereupon cause 
the order to be carried into effect as if it were an order passed by 
him under the provisions of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2  
  of <year>1974</year>), or any corresponding law in force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir].

</section>

<section><tid>855688</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section the term" property" includes, in the case 
of property regarding which an offence appears to have been committed, 
not only such property as has been originally in the possession or 
under the control of any person, but also any property into or for 
which the same may have been converted or exchanged, and anything 
acquired by such conversion or exchange whether immediately or 
otherwise.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>95512</tid>
<number>152</number>Powers of court- martial in relation to proceedings under 
this Act. Any trial by a court- martial under the provisions of this 
Act shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of 
sections 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), and the 
court- martial shall be deemed to be a Court within the meaning of 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Sections 345 and 346 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>)
CHAP

CONFIRMATION AND REVISION.

CHAPTER XII

CONFIRMATION AND REVISION



</article>



<article><tid>1450427</tid>
<number>153</number>Finding and sentence not valid, unless confirmed. No finding 
or sentence of a general, district or summary general, court- martial 
shall be valid except so far as it may be confirmed as provided by 
this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>262</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year> for" a 
Part B State'.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 14.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 16, ibid.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>560899</tid>
<number>154</number>Power to confirm finding and sentence of general court- 
martial. The findings and sentences of general courts- martial may be 
confirmed by the Central Government, or by any officer empowered in 
this behalf by warrant of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1845008</tid>
<number>155</number>Power to confirm finding and sentence of district court- 
martial. The findings and sentences of district courts- martial may be 
confirmed by any officer having power to convene a general court- 
martial or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant of such 
officer.


</article>



<article><tid>1240396</tid>
<number>156</number>Limitation of powers of confirming authority. A warrant 
issued under section 154 or section 155 may contain such restrictions, 
reservations or conditions as the authority issuing it may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1634151</tid>
<number>157</number>Power to confirm finding and sentence of summary general 
court- martial. The findings and sentences of summary general courts- 
martial may be confirmed by the convening officer or if he so directs, 
by an authority superior to him.


</article>



<article><tid>900539</tid>
<number> 158</number> Power of confirming authority to mitigate, remit or commute 
sentences.
<section><tid>1540690</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such restrictions, reservations or  
conditions as may be contained in any warrant issued under section 154 
or section 155 and to the provision of sub- section (2), a confirming 
authority may, when confirming the sentence of a court- martial, 
mitigate or remit the punishment thereby awarded, or commute that 
punishment for any punishment or punishments lower in the scale laid 
down in section 71.

</section>

<section><tid>52480</tid>
<number>2</number>A sentence of transportation shall not be commuted for a 
sentence of imprisonment for a term exceeding the term of trans- 
portation awarded by the Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>451674</tid>
<number>159</number>Confirming of findings and sentences on board a ship. When 
any person subject to this Act is tried and sentenced by a court- 
martial while on board a ship, the finding and sentence so far as not 
confirmed and executed on board the ship, may be confirmed and 
executed in like manner as if such person had been tried at the port 
of disembarkation.


</article>



<article><tid>138051</tid>
<number> 160</number> Revision of finding or sentence.
<section><tid>1945050</tid>
<number>1</number>Any finding or sentence  
of a court- martial which requires confirmation may be once revised by 
order of the confirming

<pagefootnote><pagenum>262A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

authority and on such revision, the Court, if so directed by the con- 
firming authority, may take additional evidence.


</section>

<section><tid>732097</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court, on revision, shall consist of the same officers 
as were present when the original decision was passed, unless any of 
those officers are unavoidably absent.

</section>

<section><tid>529880</tid>
<number>3</number>In case of such unavoidable absence the cause thereof shall 
be duly certified in the proceedings, and the Court shall proceed

<pagefootnote><pagenum>263</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

with the revision, provided that, if a general court- martial, it still 
consists of five officers, or, if a summary general or district court- 
martial, of three officers.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>160306</tid>
<number> 161</number> Finding and sentence of a summary court- martial.
<section><tid>1424645</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise provided in sub- section (2), the finding and sentence of a 
summary court- martial shall not require to be confirmed, but may be 
carried out forthwith.

</section>

<section><tid>872524</tid>
<number>2</number>If the officer holding the trial is of less than five years 
service, he shall not, except on active service, carry into effect any 
sentence until it has received the approval of an officer commanding 
not less than a brigade.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1114044</tid>
<number>162</number>Transmission of proceedings of summary court- martial. The 
proceedings of every summary court- martial shall without delay be 
forwarded to the officer commanding the division or brigade within 
which the trial was held, or to the prescribed officer; and such 
officer, or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff], or any officer empowered 
in this behalf by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff], may, for reasons 
based on the merits of the case, but not any merely technical grounds, 
set aside the proceedings or reduce the sentence to any other sentence 
which the court might have passed.


</article>



<article><tid>1993658</tid>
<number> 163</number> Alteration of finding or sentence in certain cases.
<section><tid>738449</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a finding of guilty by a court- martial, which has been 
confirmed, or which does not require confirmation, is found for any 
reason to be invalid or cannot be supported by the evidence, the 
authority which would have had power under section 179 to commute the 
punishment awarded by the sentence, if the finding had been valid, may 
substitute a new finding and pass a sentence for the offence specified 
or involved in such finding:
Provided that no such substitution shall be made unless such 
finding could have been validly made by the court- martial on the 
charge and unless it appears that the court- martial must have been 
satisfied of the facts establishing the said offence.


</section>

<section><tid>743036</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a sentence passed by a court- martial which has been 
confirmed, or which does not require confirmation, not being a sen- 
tence passed in pursuance of a new finding substituted under sub- 
section (1), is found for any reason to be invalid, the authority 
referred to in sub- section (1) may pass a valid sentence.

</section>

<section><tid>997177</tid>
<number>3</number>The punishment awarded by a sentence passed under sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) shall not be higher in the scale of punishments 
than, or in excess of, the punishment awarded by, the sentence for 
which a new sentence is substituted under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>469909</tid>
<number>4</number>Any finding substituted, or any sentence passed, under this 
section shall, for the purposes of this Act and the rules made

<pagefootnote><pagenum>264</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

thereunder, have effect as if it were a finding or sentence, as the 
case may be, of a court- martial.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1154592</tid>
<number> 164</number> Remedy against order, finding or sentence of court- martial.

<section><tid>1690069</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person subject to this Act who considers himself aggrieved by  
any order passed by any court- martial may present a petition to the 
officer or authority empowered to confirm any finding or sentence of 
such court- martial, and the confirming authority may take such steps 
as may be considered necessary to satisfy itself as to the 
correctness, legality or propriety of the order passed or as to the 
regularity of any proceeding to which the order relates.

</section>

<section><tid>1906530</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person subject to this Act who considers himself 
aggrieved by a finding or sentence of any court- martial which has been 
confirmed, may present a petition to the Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Chief of the Army Staff] or any prescribed officer superior in com- 
mand to the one who confirmed such finding or sentence, and the 
Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] or other officer, 
as the case may be, may pass such order thereon as it or he thinks 
fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1615380</tid>
<number>165</number>Annulment of proceedings. The Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Chief of the Army Staff] or any prescribed officer may annul the 
proceedings of any court- martial on the ground that they are illegal 
or unjust.
CHAP

EXECUTION OF SENTENCES.

CHAPTER XIII

EXECUTION OF SENTENCES



</article>



<article><tid>1186784</tid>
<number>166</number>Form of sentence of death. In awarding a sentence of death a 
court- martial shall, in its discretion, direct that the offender shall 
suffer death by being hanged by the neck until he be dead, or shall 
suffer death by being shot to death.


</article>



<article><tid>1968672</tid>
<number>167</number>Commencement of sentence of transportation or imprisonment. 
Whenever any person is sentenced by a court- martial under this Act to 
transportation or imprisonment, the term of his sentence shall, 
whether it has been revised or not, be reckoned to commence on the day 
on which the original proceedings were signed by the presiding officer 
or, in the case of a summary court- martial, by the court.


</article>



<article><tid>669152</tid>
<number>168</number>Execution of sentence of transportation. Whenever any 
sentence of transportation is passed under this Act or whenever any 
sentence of death is commuted to transportation, the commanding 
officer of the person under sentence or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>265</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".









</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

such other officer as may be prescribed shall forward a warrant in the 
prescribed form to the officer in charge of the civil prison in which 
such person is to be confined and shall arrange for his despatch to 
such prison with the warrant.



</article>



<article><tid>347359</tid>
<number> 169</number> Execution of sentence of imprisonment.
<section><tid>1230904</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever any  
sentence of imprisonment is passed under this Act by a court- martial 
or whenever any sentence of death or transportation is commuted to 
imprisonment, the confirming officer or in case of a summary court- 
martial the officer holding the Court or such other officer as may be 
prescribed, shall, save as otherwise provided in sub- sections (3) and 
 (4), direct either that the sentence shall be carried out by 
confinement in a military prison or that it shall be carried out by 
confinement in a civil prison.

</section>

<section><tid>410327</tid>
<number>2</number>When a direction has been made under sub- section (1) the 
commanding officer of the person under sentence or such other officer 
as may be prescribed shall forward a warrant in the prescribed form to 
the officer in charge of the prison in which such person is to be 
confined and shall arrange for his despatch to such prison with the 
warrant.

</section>

<section><tid>1392683</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of a sentence of imprisonment for a period not 
exceeding three months and passed under this Act by a court- martial, 
the appropriate officer under sub- section (1) may direct that the 
sentence shall be carried out by confinement in military custody 
instead of in a civil or military prison.

</section>

<section><tid>1253227</tid>
<number>4</number>On active service, a sentence of imprisonment may be carried 
out by confinement in such place as the officer commanding the 
forces in the field may from time to time appoint.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>169A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Period of custody undergone by the officer of person to be set off against 
the imprisonment.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>689194</tid>
<number>169A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Period of custody undergone by the officer or person to 
be set off against the imprisonment. When a person or officer subject 
to this Act is sentenced by a court- martial to a term of imprisonment, 
not being an imprisonment in default of payment of fine, the period 
spent by him in civil or military custody during investigation, 
inquiry or trial of the same case, and before the date of order of 
such sentence, shall be set off against the term of imprisonment 
imposed upon him, and the liability of such person or officer to 
undergo imprisonment on such order of sentence shall be restricted to 
the remainder, if any, of the term of imprisonment imposed upon him.]


</article>



<article><tid>510071</tid>
<number>170</number>Temporary custody of offender. Where a sentence of 
transportation or imprisonment is directed to be undergone in a civil 
prison the offender may be kept in a military prison or in military 
custody or in any other fit place, till such time as it is possible 
send him to a civil prison.


</article>



<article><tid>1622057</tid>
<number>171</number>Execution of sentence of imprisonment in special cases. 
Whenever, in the opinion of an officer commanding an army, army corps, 
division or independent brigade, any sentence or portion of a sentence 
of imprisonment cannot for special reasons, conveniently be carried 
out in a military prison or in military custody in accordance with the 
provision of section 169 such officer may direct that such sentence or 
portion of sentence shall be carried out by confinement in any civil, 
prison or other fit place.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>266</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 17.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1730040</tid>
<number>172</number>Conveyance of prisoner from place to place. A person under 
sentence of transportation or imprisonment may during his conveyance 
from place to place, or when on board ship, aircraft, or otherwise, be 
subjected to such restraint as is necessary for his safe conduct and 
removal.


</article>



<article><tid>1272422</tid>
<number>173</number>Communication of certain orders to prison officers. Whenever 
an order is duly made under this Act setting aside or varying any 
sentence, order or warrant under which any person is confined in a 
civil or military prison, a warrant in accordance with such order 
shall be forwarded by the officer making the order or his staff 
officer or such other person as may be prescribed to the officer in 
charge of the prison in which such person is confined.


</article>



<article><tid>706188</tid>
<number>174</number>Execution of sentence of fine. When a sentence of fine is 
imposed by a court- martial under section 69 whether the trial was 
held within India or not, a copy of such sentence, signed and 
certified by the confirming officer, or where no confirmation is 
required, by the officer holding the trial may be sent to any 
magistrate in India, and such magistrate shall thereupon cause the 
fine to be recovered in accordance with the provision of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code 
of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>] (2 of <year>1974</year>), or any corresponding law in 
force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State of Jammu and Kashmir] for the levy of fines as 
if it were a sentence of fine imposed by such magistrate.


</article>



<article><tid>1476787</tid>
<number>175</number>Establishment and regulation of military prisons. The 
Central Government may set apart any building or part of a building, 
or any place under its control, as a military prison for the 
confinement of persons sentenced to imprisonment under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1167729</tid>
<number>176</number>Informality or error in the order or warrant. Whenever any 
person is sentenced to transportation or imprisonment under this Act, 
and is undergoing the sentence in any place or manner in which he 
might be confined under a lawful order or warrant in pursuance of this 
Act, the confinement of such person shall not be deemed to be illegal 
only by reason of any informality or error in or as respects the 
order, warrant or other document, or the authority by which,' or in 
pursuance whereof such person was brought into or is confined in any 
such place, and any such order, warrant or document may be amended 
accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1826280</tid>
<number> 177</number> Power to make rules in respect of prisons and prisoners. The 
Central Government may make rules providing-
<section><tid>1188768</tid>
<number>a</number>for the government, management and regulation of 
military prisons;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>266A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation Of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" a 
Part B State". 
2. Subs by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, S. 14






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1650591</tid>
<number>b</number>for the appointment, removal and powers of inspectors, 
visitors, governors and- officers thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>310168</tid>
<number>c</number>for the labour of prisoners undergoing confinement 
therein, and for enabling persons to earn, by special 
industry and good conduct, a remission of a portion of their 
sentence;

</section>

<section><tid>98625</tid>
<number>d</number>for the safe custody of prisoners and the maintenance 
of discipline among them and the punishment, by personal 
correction, restraint or otherwise, of offences committed by 
prisoners;

</section>

<section><tid>115103</tid>
<number>e</number>for the application to military prisons of any of the 
provisions of the Prisons Act, <year>1894</year> (9 of <year>1894</year>), relating 
to the duties of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>267</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officers of prisons and the punishment of persons not being 
prisoners;


</section>

<section><tid>557434</tid>
<number>f</number>for the admission into any prison, at proper times and 
subject to proper restrictions, of persons with whom pri- 
soners may desire to communicate, and for the consultation by 
prisoners under trial with their legal advisers without the 
presence as far as possible of any third party within hearing 
distance.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1286188</tid>
<number>178</number>Restriction of rulemaking power in regard to corporal 
punishment. Rules made under section 177 shall not authorise corporal 
punishment to be inflicted for any offence, nor render the imprison- 
ment more severe than it is under the law for the time being in force 
relating to civil prisons.
CHAP

PARDONS, REMISSIONS AND SUSPENSIONS.

CHAPTER XIV

PARDONS, REMISSIONS AND SUSPENSIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1840070</tid>
<number> 179</number> Pardon and remission. When any person subject to this Act 
has been convicted by a court- martial of any offence, the Central 
Government or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff] or, in the case of a 
sentence, which he could have confirmed or which did not, require 
confirmation, the officer commanding the army, army corps, division or 
independent brigade in which such person at the time of conviction was 
serving, or the prescribed officer may-
<section><tid>836561</tid>
<number>a</number>either with or without conditions which the person 
sentenced accepts, pardon the person or remit the whole or 
any part of the punishment awarded; or

</section>

<section><tid>539113</tid>
<number>b</number>mitigate the punishment awarded; or

</section>

<section><tid>341335</tid>
<number>c</number>commute such punishment for any less punishment or 
punishments mentioned in this Act:
Provided that a sentence of transportation shall not be 
commuted for a sentence of imprisonment for a term 
exceeding the term of transportation awarded by the 
court; or


</section>

<section><tid>1506449</tid>
<number>d</number>either with or without conditions which the person 
sentenced accepts, release the person on parole.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>268</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the 
Commander- in- Chief".








</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>276618</tid>
<number> 180</number> Cancellation of conditional pardon, release on parole or 
remission.
<section><tid>12165</tid>
<number>1</number>If any condition on which a person has been pardoned or  
released on parole or a punishment has been remitted is, in the 
opinion of the authority which granted the pardon, release or re- 
mission, not fulfilled, such authority may cancel the pardon, release 
or remission, and thereupon the sentence of the court shall be carried 
into effect as if such pardon, release or remission had not been 
granted.

</section>

<section><tid>1490781</tid>
<number>2</number>A person whose sentence of transportation or imprisonment is 
carried into effect under the provisions of sub- section (1) shall 
undergo only the unexpired portion of his sentence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1806963</tid>
<number>181</number>Reduction of warrant officer or non- commissioned officer. 
When under the' provisions of section 77 a warrant officer or a non- 
commissioned officer is deemed to be reduced to the ranks, such 
reduction shall, for the purpose of section 179, be treated as a 
punishment awarded by a sentence of a court- martial.


</article>



<article><tid>1029947</tid>
<number> 182</number> Suspension of sentence of transportation or imprisonment.

<section><tid>1058714</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a person subject to this Act is sentenced by a court- martial  
to transportation or imprisonment, the Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief 
of the Army Staff] or any officer empowered to convene a general or a 
summary general court- martial may suspend the sentence whether or not 
the offender has already been committed to prison or to military 
custody.

</section>

<section><tid>550652</tid>
<number>2</number>The authority or officer specified in sub,- section (1) may 
in the case of an offender so sentenced direct that, until the orders 
of such authority or officer have been obtained the offender shall not 
be committed to prison or to military custody.

</section>

<section><tid>1527892</tid>
<number>3</number>The powers conferred by sub- sections (1) and (2) may be 
exercised in the case of any such sentence which has been confirmed, 
reduced or commuted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>418316</tid>
<number> 183</number> Orders pending suspension.
<section><tid>1811095</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the sentence referred to  
in section 182 is imposed by a court- martial other than a summary 
court- martial, the confirming officer may, when confirming the 
sentence, direct that the offender be not committed to prison or to 
military custody until the orders of the authority or officer 
specified in section 182 have been obtained.

</section>

<section><tid>1307228</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a sentence of imprisonment is imposed by a summary 
court- martial, the officer holding the trial or the officer authorised 
to approve of the sentence under sub- section (2) of section 161 may 
make the direction referred to in sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>952371</tid>
<number>184</number>Release on suspension. Where a sentence is suspended under 
section 182, the offender shall forthwith be released from custody.


</article>



<article><tid>286462</tid>
<number>185</number>Computation of period of suspension. Any period during which 
the sentence is under suspension shall be reckoned as part of the term 
of such sentence.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>269</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the Commander- in- 
Chief".







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>370085</tid>
<number> 186</number> Order after suspension. The authority or officer specified 
in section 182 may, at any time while a sentence is suspended, order-
<section><tid>1802194</tid>
<number>a</number>that the offender be committed to undergo the unexpired 
portion of the sentence, or

</section>

<section><tid>1087643</tid>
<number>b</number>that the sentence be remitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>69299</tid>
<number> 187</number> Reconsideration of case after suspension.
<section><tid>1202851</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a  
sentence has been suspended, the case may at any time, and shall at 
intervals of not more than four months, be reconsidered by the 
authority or officer specified in section 182, or by any general or 
other officer not below the rank of field officer duly authorised by 
the authority or officer specified in section 182.

</section>

<section><tid>1246000</tid>
<number>2</number>Where on such reconsideration by the officer so authorised 
it appears to him that the conduct of the offender since his 
conviction has been such as to justify a remission of the sentence, he 
shall refer the matter to the authority or officer specified in 
section 182.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1138291</tid>
<number> 188</number> Fresh sentences after suspension. Where an offender, while a 
sentence on him is suspended under this Act, is sentenced for any 
other offence, then-
<section><tid>417012</tid>
<number>a</number>if the further sentence is also suspended under this 
Act, the two sentences shall run concurrently;

</section>

<section><tid>1237559</tid>
<number>b</number>if the further sentence is for a period of three months 
or more and is not suspended under this Act, the offender 
shall also be committed to prison or military custody for the 
unexpired portion of the previous sentence, but both 
sentences shall run concurrently; and

</section>

<section><tid>1588059</tid>
<number>c</number>if the further sentence is for a period of less than 
three months and is not suspended under this Act, the 
offender shall be so committed on that sentence only, and the 
previous sentence shall, subject to any order which may be 
passed under section 186 or section 187, continue to be 
suspended.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>305484</tid>
<number>189</number>Scope of power of suspension. The powers conferred by 
sections 182 and 186 shall be in addition to and not in derogation of 
the power of mitigation, remission and commutation.


</article>



<article><tid>912139</tid>
<number> 190</number> Effect of suspension and remission on dismissal.
<section><tid>762046</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
in addition to any other sentence the punishment of dismissal has been 
awarded by a court- martial, and such other' sentence is suspended 
under section 182, then, such dismissal shall not take effect until so 
ordered by the authority or officer specified in section 182.

</section>

<section><tid>168375</tid>
<number>2</number>If such other sentence is remitted under section 186, the 
punishment of dismissal shall also be remitted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>270</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

RULES.

CHAPTER XV

RULES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1445586</tid>
<number> 191</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1183307</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1818227</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the power conferred 
by sub- section (1), the rules made thereunder may provide for-

<subsection><tid>1456565</tid>
<number>a</number>the removal, retirement, release or discharge from the 
service of persons subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1601147</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount and incidence of fines to be imposed under 
section 89;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1885415</tid>
<number>d</number>the assembly and procedure of courts of inquiry, the 
recording of summaries of evidence and the administration of 
oaths or affirmations by such courts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1362180</tid>
<number>e</number>the convening and constituting of courts- martial and 
the appointment of prosecutors at trials by courts- martial;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1333113</tid>
<number>f</number>the adjournment, dissolution and sitting of courts- 
martial;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1437301</tid>
<number>g</number>the procedure to be observed in trials by courts- 
martial and the appearance of legal practitioners thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918518</tid>
<number>h</number>the confirmation, revision and annulment of, and 
petitions against, the findings and sentences of courts- 
martial;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929417</tid>
<number>i</number>the carrying into effect of sentences of courts- 
martial;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>695768</tid>
<number>j</number>the forms of orders to be made under the provisions of 
this Act relating to courts- martial, transportation and im- 
prisonment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1061945</tid>
<number>k</number>the constitution of authorities to decide for what 
persons, to what amounts and in what manner, provision should 
be made for dependants under section 99, and the due carrying 
out of such decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1939928</tid>
<number>l</number>the relative rank of the officers, junior commissioned 
officers, warrant officers, petty officers and non- commis- 
sioned officers of the regular Army, Navy and Air Force when 
acting together;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>809923</tid>
<number>m</number>any other matter directed by this Act to be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1793481</tid>
<number>192</number>Power to make regulations. The Central Government may make 
regulations for all or any of the purposes of this Act other than 
those specified in section 191.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>271</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See Army Rules, <year>1954</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. II, sec. 4, 
p. 291.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 18.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1660930</tid>
<number>193</number>Publication of rules and regulations in Gazette. All rules 
and regulations made under this Act shall be published in the 
Official Gazette and on such publication, shall have effect as if 
enacted in this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>231382</tid>
<number>193A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made by the Central Government under this 
Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session, or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
regulation should not be made the rule or regulation on shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.]
</article>



<article><tid>1187583</tid>
<number>194</number>[ Repeals] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1957</year> 
 (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.
[ THE SCHEDULE.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1957</year> 
 (36 of <year>1957</year>) s. 2 and Sch. I


<pagefootnote><pagenum>272</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 3. <year>1984</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1992</year>, s. 19.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>