<act><title>THE CONDUCT OF ELCTIONS RULES, 1961
</title> 
 The Conduct of 
Elections Rules, 19611
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 25th day of April, 1961:
 
Provided that these rules 
shall not apply to or in relation to any election called but not completed 
before that date and the Representation of the People (Conduct of Elections and 
Election Petitions) Rules, 1956, shall continue to apply to or in relation to 
any such election as if these rules had not been made.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Conduct of 
Elections Rules, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Representation 
of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951);
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  “ballot box” includes any box, 
bag or other receptacle used for the insertion of ballot paper by voters;
 
 

1[(ba)  “counterfoil” means the 
counterfoil attached to a ballot paper printed under the provisions of these 
rules;]
 
 

2[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  “election by assembly members” 
means an election to the Council of States by the elected members of the 
Legislative Assembly of a State by the members of the electoral college of a 
Union territory, or an election to the Legislative Council of a State by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of that State;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  “elector”, in relation to an 
election by assembly members, means any person entitled to vote at that 
election;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  “electoral roll”, in relation to 
an election by assembly members, means the list maintained under section 152 by 
the returning officer for that election;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  “electoral roll number” of a 
person means—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  the serial number of the 
entry in the electoral roll in respect of that person;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  the serial number of the 
part of the electoral roll in which such entry occurs; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  the name of the 
constituency to which the electoral roll relates;
 
 

3[(g)  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules and in respect of any election in a State, includes a translation 
thereof in any of the languages used for official purposes of the State;]
 
 

4[(gg)  “marked copy of the electoral 
roll” means the copy of the electoral roll set apart for the purpose of marking 
the names of electors to whom ballot papers are issued at an election;]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  “polling station”, in relation 
to an election by assembly members, means the place fixed under section 29 for 
taking the poll at that election;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  “presiding officer” includes—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  any polling officer 
performing any of the functions of a presiding officer under sub-section (2) or 
sub-section (3) of section 26; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  any returning officer 
while presiding over an election under sub-section (2) of section 29;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  “returning officer” includes 
any assistant returning officer performing any function he is authorised to 
perform under sub-section (2) of section 22;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
the Act or these rules, a person who is unable to write his name shall, unless 
otherwise expressly provided in these rules, be deemed to have signed an 
instrument or other paper if—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  he has placed a mark on such 
instrument or other paper in the presence of the returning officer or the 
presiding officer or such other officer as may be specified in this behalf by 
the Election Commission, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  such officer on being satisfied 
as to his identity has attested the mark as being the mark of that person.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any requirement under 
these rules that a notification, order, declaration, notice or list issued or 
made by any authority shall be published in the Official Gazette shall, unless 
otherwise expressly provided in these rules, be construed as a requirement that 
it shall be published in the Gazette of India if it relates to an election to, 
or membership of, either House of Parliament or an electoral college, and in the 
Official Gazette of the State, if it relates to an election to or membership of, 
the House or either House of the State Legislature.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The General Clauses 
Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) shall apply for the interpretation of these rules as it 
applies for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament.
 
 







</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Public notice of 
intended election.—The 
public notice of an intended election referred to in section 31 shall be in Form 
1 and shall, subject to any directions of the Election Commission, be published 
in such manner as the returning officer thinks fit.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Nomination paper.—Every 
nomination paper presented under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 33 shall be 
completed in such one of the Forms 2A to 2E as may be appropriate:
 
Provided that a failure to 
complete or defect in completing, the declaration as to symbols in a nomination 
paper in Form 2A or Form 2B shall not be deemed to be a defect of a substantial 
character within the meaning of sub-section (4) of section 36.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>4A</number> Form of 
affidavit to be filed at the time of delivering nomination paper.—The 
candidate or his proposer, as the case may be, shall, at the time of delivering 
to the returning officer the nomination paper under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
33 of the Act, also deliver to him an affidavit sworn by the candidate before a 
Magistrate of the first class or a Notary in Form 26.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Symbols for elections 
in parliamentary and assembly constituencies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Election Commission shall, by notification in the Gazette of India, and in 
the Official Gazette of each State, specify the symbols that may be chosen by 
candidates at elections in parliamentary or assembly constituencies and the 
restrictions to which their choice shall be subject.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 

1[Subject to any 
general or special direction issued by the Election Commission either under 
sub-rule (4) or sub-rule (5) of rule 10, where at any such election], more 
nomination papers than one are delivered by or on behalf of a candidate, the 
declaration as to symbols made in the nomination paper first delivered, and no 
other declaration as to symbols, shall be taken into consideration under rule 10 
even if that nomination paper has been rejected.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Authentication of 
certificates issued by the Election Commission.—A 
certificate issued by the Election Commission under 

1[sub-section (2) 
of section 9] or under sub-section (3) of section 33 shall be signed by the 
Secretary to the Election Commission and shall bear its official seal.
 
 



</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Notice of nominations.—The 
notice of nominations under section 35 shall be in such one of the Forms 3A to 
3C as may be appropriate.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8</number> List of 
validly nominated candidates.—
<section><number>1</number> The list of validly nominated candidates 
referred to in sub-section (8) of section 36 shall be in Form 4.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The name of every such 
candidate shall be shown in said list as it appears in his nomination paper:
 
Provided that if a 
candidate considers that his name is incorrectly spelt or is otherwise 
incorrectly shown in his nomination paper or is different from the name by which 
he is popularly known, he may, at any time before the list of contesting 
candidates is prepared furnish in writing to the returning officer the proper 
form and spelling of his name and the returning officer shall, on being 
satisfied as to the genuineness of the request, make the necessary correction or 
alteration in the list in Form 4 and adopt that form and spelling in the list of 
contesting candidates].
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Notice of withdrawal of 
candidature.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notice of withdrawal of candidature under sub-section (1) of section 37 shall 
be in Form 5 and shall contain the particulars set out therein; and on receipt 
of such notice, the returning officer shall note thereon the date and time at 
which it was delivered.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice under 
sub-section (3) of section 37 shall be in Form 6.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Preparation of list of 
contesting candidates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The list of contesting candidates referred to in sub-section (1) of section 38 
shall be in Form 7A or Form 7B as may be appropriate and shall contain the 
particulars set out therein and shall be prepared in such language or languages 
as the Election Commission may direct.
 

1[***]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the list is 
prepared in more languages than one, the names of candidates therein shall be 
arranged alphabetically according to the script of such one of those languages 
as the Election Commission may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> At an election in a 
parliamentary or assembly constituency, where a poll becomes necessary, the 
returning officer shall consider the choice of symbols expressed by the 
contesting candidates in their nomination papers and shall, subject to any 
general or special direction issued in this behalf by the Election Commission,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  allot a different symbol to each 
contesting candidate in conformity, as far as practicable, with his choice; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if more contesting candidates 
than one have indicated their preference for the same symbol decide by lot to 
which of such candidates the symbol will be allotted.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The allotment by the 
returning officer of any symbol to a candidate shall be final except where it is 
inconsistent with any direction issued by the Election Commission in this behalf 
in which case the Election Commission may revise the allotment in such manner as 
it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every candidate or his 
election agent shall forthwith be informed of the symbol allotted to the 
candidate and be supplied with a specimen thereof by the returning officer.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>11</number> 
Publication of list of contesting candidates and declaration of result in 
uncontested election.—
<section><number>1</number> The returning officer shall, immediately after its 
preparation, cause a copy of the list of contesting candidates to be affixed in 
some conspicuous place in his office and where the number of contesting 
candidates is equal to, or less than, the number of seats to be filled, he 
shall, immediately after such affixation, declare under sub-section (2) or, as 
the case may be, sub-section (3) of section 53 the result of the election in 
such one of the Forms 21 to 21B as may be appropriate and send signed copies of 
the declaration to the appropriate authority, the Election Commission and the 
chief electoral officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a poll becomes 
necessary under sub-section (1) of section 53, the returning officer shall 
supply a copy of the list of contesting candidates to each such candidate or his 
election agent, and then shall also publish the list in the Official Gazette.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Appointment of 
election agent.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Any appointment of an election agent under section 40 shall be made in Form 8 
and the notice of such appointment shall be given by forwarding the same in 
duplicate to the returning officer who shall return one copy thereof to the 
election agent after affixing thereon his seal and signature in token of his 
approval of the appointment.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The revocation of the 
appointment of an election agent under sub-section (1) of section 42 shall be 
made in Form 9.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Appointment of polling 
agents.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
number of polling agents that may be appointed under section 46 shall be one 
agent and two relief agents.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such appointment 
shall be made in Form 10 and shall be made over to the polling agent for 
production at the polling station or the place fixed for the poll, as the case 
may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No polling agent shall 
be admitted into the polling station or the place fixed for the poll unless he 
has delivered to the presiding officer the instrument of his appointment under 
sub-rule (2) after duly completing and signing before the presiding officer the 
declaration contained therein.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Revocation of the 
appointment of a polling agent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The revocation of the appointment of a polling agent under sub-section (1) of 
section 48 shall be made in Form 11 and lodged with the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of any 
such revocation the candidate or his election agent may, at any time before the 
poll is closed, make a fresh appointment in the manner specified in rule 13 and 
the provisions of that rule shall apply to every such agent.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Publication of the 
hours fixed for polling.—The 
hours fixed for polling under section 56 shall be published by notification in 
the Official Gazette.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Voting normally to be 
in person.—Save 
as hereinafter provided, all electors voting at an election shall do so in 
person at the polling station provided for them under section 25 or, as the case 
may be, at the place of polling fixed under section 29.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part,—
 
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>  “service voter” means any 
person specified in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> or clause (b) of section 60, but does not include 
“classified service voter” defined in rule 27M;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  “special voter” means any person 
holding an office to which the provisions of sub-section (4) of section 20 of 
the Representation of the People Act, 1950 are declared to apply or the wife of 
such person, if he or she has been registered as an elector by virtue of a 
statement made under sub-section (5) of the said section;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  “voter on election duty” means 
any polling agent, any polling officer, presiding officer or other public 
servant, who is an elector in the constituency and is by reason of his being on 
election duty unable to vote as the polling station where he is entitled to 
vote.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Persons entitled to 
vote by post.—The 
following persons shall, subject to their fulfilling the requirements 
hereinafter specified, be entitled to vote by post, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  at an election in parliamentary 
or assembly constituency—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  special voters;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  service voters:
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  voters on election duty; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iv</number>  electors subjected to 
preventive detention;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>b</number>  at an election in a council 
constituency—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  voters on election duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  electors subjected to 
preventive detention; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  electors in the whole or 
any specified parts, of the constituency if directed by the Election Commission 
in this behalf under clause (b) of rule 68;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>c</number>  at an election by a assembly 
members—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  electors subjected to 
preventive detention; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  all electors if directed 
by the Election Commission in this behalf under clause (a) of rule 68.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Intimation by special 
voters.—A 
special voter who wishes to vote by post at an election shall send an intimation 
in Form 12 to the returning officer so as to reach him at least ten days before 
the date of poll; and on receipt of the intimation the returning officer shall 
issue a postal ballot paper to him.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Intimation by voters 
on election duty.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
A voter on election duty who wishes to vote by post at an election shall send an 
application in Form 12 to the returning officer so as to reach him at least 
seven days or such shorter period as the returning officer may allow before the 
date of poll; and if the returning officer is satisfied that the applicant is a 
voter on election duty, he shall issue a postal ballot paper to him.
 

2[(2) Where such 
voter, being a polling officer, presiding officer or other public servant on 
election duty in the constituency of which he is an elector, wishes to vote in 
person at an election 

3[in a 
parliamentary or assembly constituency] and not by post, he shall send an 
application in Form 12A to the returning officer so as to reach him at least 
four days, or such shorter period as the returning officer may allow, before the 
date of poll; and if the returning officer is satisfied that the applicant is 
such public servant and voter on election duty in the constituency, he shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  issue to the applicant an 
election duty certificate in Form 12B,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  mark ‘EDC’ against his name in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll to indicate that an election duty 
certificate has been issued to him, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  ensure that he is not allowed to 
vote at the polling station where he would otherwise have been entitled to 
vote.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Electors under 
preventive detention.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The appropriate Government shall, within 15 days of the calling of an election, 
ascertain and intimate to the returning officer the names of the electors, if 
any, subjected to preventive detention together with their addresses and 
electoral roll numbers and the particulars about their places of detention.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any elector subjected 
to preventive detention may, within 15 days of the calling of an election, send 
an intimation to the returning officer that he wishes to vote by post, 
specifying his name, address, electoral roll number and place of detention.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall issue a postal ballot paper to every elector subjected to preventive 
detention whose name has been intimated to him under sub-rule (1) or under 
sub-rule (2).
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Form of ballot paper.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every postal ballot paper shall have a counterfoil attached thereto, and the 
said ballot paper and the counterfoil shall be in such form, and the particulars 
therein shall be in such language or languages, as the Election Commission may 
direct.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names of the 
candidates shall be arranged 

2[on the postal 
ballot paper] in the order in which they appear in the list of contesting 
candidates.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If two or more 
candidates bear the same name, they shall be distinguished by the addition of 
their occupation or residence or in some other manner.
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Issue of ballot paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A postal ballot paper shall be sent by post under certificate of posting to the 
elector together with—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  a declaration in Form 13A;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  a cover in Form 13B;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  a large cover addressed to the 
returning officer in Form 13C; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  instructions for the guidance of 
the elector in Form 13D:
 
Provided that the 
returning officer may, in the case of a special voter or a voter on election 
duty, deliver the ballot paper and forms, or cause them to be delivered, to such 
voter personally.
 

1[(2) The returning 
officer shall at the same time—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number>  record on the counterfoil of the 
ballot paper the electoral roll number of the electoral as entered in the marked 
copy of the electoral roll;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  mark the name of the elector in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll to indicate that a ballot paper has been 
issued to him, without however recording therein the serial number of the ballot 
paper issued to that elector; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  ensure that that elector is not 
allowed to vote at a polling station.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Before any ballot 
paper is issued to an elector at an election in a local authorities’ 
constituency or by assembly members, the serial number of the ballot paper shall 
be effectively concealed in such manner as the Election Commission may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every officer under 
whose care or through whom a postal ballot paper is sent shall ensure its 
delivery to the addressee without delay.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After ballot papers 
have been issued to all the electors entitled to vote by post, the returning 
officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  at an election in a 
parliamentary or assembly constituency, 

2[subject to the provisions of rule 
27P, seal up in a packet] that part of the marked copy of the electoral roll 
which relates to service voters and record on the packet a brief description of 
its contents and the date on which it was sealed and send the other relevant 
parts of the marked copy of the several presiding officers 

3[or marking the names of elector to 
whom ballot papers are issued at the polling stations without however recording 
therein the serial numbers of the ballot papers issued to the electors]; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  at any other election, seal up 
in a packet the marked copy of the electoral roll and record on the packet a 
brief description of its contents and the date on which it was sealed.
 

4[(6) The returning 
officer shall also seal up in a separate packet the counterfoils of the ballot 
papers issued to electors entitled to vote by post and record on the packet a 
brief description of its contents and the date on which it was sealed.]
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Recording of vote.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An elector who has received a postal ballot paper and desires to vote shall 
record his vote on the ballot paper in accordance with the directions contained 
in Part I of Form 13D and then enclose it in the cover in Form 13B.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The elector shall sign 
the declaration in Form 13A in the presence of, and have the signature attested 
by, a stipendiary magistrate or such other officer specified below, as may be 
appropriate, to whom he is personally known or to whose satisfaction he has been 
identified—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  in the case of a service voter, 
such officer as may be appointed in this behalf by the Commanding Officer of the 
unit, ship or establishment in which the voter or her husband, as the case may 
be, is employed or such officer as may be appointed in this behalf by the 
diplomatic or consular representative of India in the country in which such 
voter is resident;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  in the case of a special voter, 
an officer not below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  in the case of a voter on 
election duty, any gazetted officer 

1[or the presiding officer of the 
polling station at which he is on election duty];
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  in the case of an elector under 
preventive detention, the Superintendent of the Jail or the Commandant of the 
detention camp in which the elector is under detention; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  in any other case, such officer 
as may be notified in this behalf by the Election Commission.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Assistance to 
illiterate or infirm voters.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If an elector is unable through illiteracy, blindness or other physical 
infirmity to record his vote on a postal ballot paper and sign the declaration, 
he shall take the ballot paper, together with the declaration and the covers 
received by him to an officer competent to attest his signature under sub-rule 
(2) of rule 24 and request the officer to record his vote and sign his 
declaration on his behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such officer shall 
thereupon mark the ballot paper in accordance with the wishes of the elector in 
his presence, sign the declaration on his behalf and complete the appropriate 
certificate contained in Form 13A.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Re-issue of ballot 
paper.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
a postal ballot paper and other papers sent under rule 23 are for any reason 
returned undelivered, the returning officer may re-issue them by post under 
certificate of posting or deliver them or cause them to be delivered to the 
elector personally on a request being made by him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any elector has 
inadvertently dealt with the ballot paper or any of the other papers sent to him 
under rule 23 in such a manner that they cannot conveniently be used, a second 
set of the papers shall be issued to him after he has returned the spoiled 
papers and satisfied the returning officer of the inadvertence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall cancel the spoiled papers so returned and keep them in a separate packet 
after noting thereon the particulars of the election and the serial numbers of 
the cancelled ballot papers.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Return of ballot 
paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After an elector has recorded his vote and made his declaration under rule 24 or 
rule 25, he shall return the ballot paper and declaration to the returning 
officer in accordance with the instructions communicated to him in Part II of 
Form 13D so as to reach the returning officer before 

1[the hour fixed 
for the commencement of counting of votes.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any cover 
containing a postal ballot paper is received by the returning officer after the 
expiry of the time fixed in sub-rule (1), he shall note thereon the date and 
time of its receipt and shall keep all such covers together in a separate 
packet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall keep in safe custody until the commencement of the counting of votes all 
covers containing postal ballot papers received by him.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27A</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  ‘Assistant Returning Officer’, 
for the notified class of electors, means an Assistant Returning Officer 
notified by the Election Commission for the purposes of this Part;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  ‘notified elector’ means an 
elector who belongs to a class of persons notified by the Election Commission 
under clause (c) of section 60 of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27B</number> Special provisions 
for voting by the notified class of electors.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in Part III, the provisions of this Part shall apply to a 
notified elector who wishes to vote by post at an election.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27C</number> Intimation by a 
notified elector.—A 
notified elector who wishes to vote by post at an election shall send an 
application in Form 12C to the Assistant Returning Officer for the notified 
class of electors so as to reach him at least ten days before the date of the 
poll and on receipt of the intimation such Assistant Returning Officer shall 
issue a postal ballot paper to him:
 
Provided that an 
application which does not furnish complete particulars as required in Form 12C 
may be rejected if such Assistant Returning Officer, despite making reasonable 
efforts, is not in a position to ascertain the requisite information:
 
Provided further that an 
application in Form 12C without a certificate from the authorised officer as 
required under Part II of Form 12C shall be rejected.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27D</number> Form of ballot paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every postal ballot paper shall have a counterfoil attached thereto and the said 
ballot paper and the counterfoil shall be in such form and the particulars 
therein shall be in such language or languages as the Election Commission may 
direct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names of the 
candidates shall be arranged on the postal ballot paper in the order in which 
they appear in the list of contesting candidates.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If two or more 
candidates bear the same name, they shall be distinguished by the addition of 
their occupation or residence or in some other manner.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27E</number> Issue of ballot 
paper.—A postal 
ballot paper shall be sent by post under certificate of posting to the notified 
elector together with—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  a declaration in Form 13A;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  a cover in Form 13B;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  a large cover addressed to the 
Returning Officer in Form 13C; and
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  instructions for the guidance of 
the elector in Form 13E:
 
Provided that the 
Assistant Returning Officer of the notified class of electors may deliver, or 
cause to be delivered, the ballot paper and the Forms to the notified elector 
personally.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> The Assistant 
Returning Officer for the notified class of electors shall at the same time—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>a</number>  record on the counterfoil of the 
ballot paper the electoral roll number of the elector as entered in the marked 
copy of the electoral roll;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>b</number>  mark the name of the elector in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll to indicate that a ballot paper has been 
issued to him without, however, recording therein the serial number of the 
ballot paper issued to that elector;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>c</number>  ensure that the elector is not 
allowed to vote at a polling station.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> Every officer under 
whose care or through whom a postal ballot paper is sent shall ensure its 
delivery to the addressee without delay.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> The Assistant 
Returning Officer for the notified class of electors shall ensure that ballot 
papers are issued to all such electors whose intimation has been received in 
accordance with rule 27C and who are entitled to vote by post before eight days 
from the date of poll in the constituency and shall on expiry of the said period 
of eight days keep the marked copies of the electoral rolls in sealed envelopes 
and record on the envelopes a brief description of its contents and the date on 
which it was sealed and send the sealed envelopes to the Returning Officer 
concerned.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> The Assistant 
Returning Officer for the notified class of electors shall also seal in a 
separate packet the counterfoils of the ballot papers issued to electors 
entitled to vote by post and record on the packet a brief description of its 
contents and the date on which it was sealed and send the sealed packet to the 
Returning Officer concerned.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27F</number> Recording of vote.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notified elector who has received a postal ballot paper and desires to vote 
shall record his vote on the ballot paper in accordance with the instructions 
contained in Form 13E and then enclose it in the cover in Form 13B.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notified elector 
shall sign the declaration in Form 13A in the presence of, and have the 
signature attested by, an officer authorised under sub-rule (2) of rule 27J.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27G</number> Assistance to 
illiterate or infirm electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a notified elector is unable through illiteracy, blindness or other physical 
infirmity to record his vote on a postal ballot paper and sign the declaration, 
he shall take the ballot paper together with the declaration and the covers 
received by him to an officer authorised under sub-rule (2) of rule 27J and 
request the officer to record his vote and sign his declaration on his behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such officer shall 
thereupon mark the ballot paper in accordance with the wishes of the elector in 
his presence, sign the declaration on his behalf and complete all the 
requirements to be made in this behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27H</number> Re-issue of ballot 
paper.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
a postal ballot paper and other papers sent under rule 27E are for any reason 
returned undelivered, the Assistant Returning Officer for the notified class of 
electors may re-issue them by post under certificate of posting or deliver them 
or cause them to be delivered to the elector personally either on a request 
being made by him or of his own.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any notified 
elector has inadvertently dealt with the ballot paper or any of the other papers 
sent to him under rule 27E in such a manner that they cannot conveniently be 
used, a second set of the papers shall be issued to him after he has returned 
the spoiled papers and satisfied the Assistant Returning Officer for the 
notified class of electors of the inadvertence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Assistant 
Returning Officer for the notified class of electors shall cancel the spoiled 
papers so returned and keep them in a separate packet after noting thereon the 
particulars of the election and the serial numbers of the cancelled ballot 
papers.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27-I</number> Return of ballot 
paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After a notified elector has recorded his vote and made his declaration under 
rule 27F or rule 27G, he shall return the ballot paper and the declaration to 
the Returning Officer concerned before the hour fixed for the commencement of 
counting of votes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any cover 
containing a postal ballot paper is received by the Returning Officer after the 
expiry of the time fixed in sub-rule (1), he shall note thereon the date and 
time of its receipt and shall keep all such covers together in a separate 
packet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Returning Officer 
shall keep in safe custody until the commencement of the counting of votes all 
covers containing postal ballot papers received by him.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27J</number> Officers authorised 
to perform certain functions under this Part.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The officers mentioned in sub-rule (2) shall be authorised officers for the 
purpose of—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  sub-rule (2) of rule 27G;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  issuing certificate in Part II 
of Form 12C.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any of the following 
officers shall be the authorised officers for the purpose of sub-rule (1):—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  an officer in charge of a 
migrant camp/area;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  an officer in charge of an 
office from where the migrant elector draws his salary as a migrant employee;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  an officer in charge of 
treasury/bank from where the migrant elector draws his pension as a pensioner;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  any gazetted officer.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
 <number>27K</number> Marked copy of 
the electoral roll.—The Returning Officer shall ensure that the marked copy 
of the electoral roll received by him from the Assistant Returning Officer for 
the notified class of electors is used during the poll in the constituency that 
such electors who have been supplied with a postal ballot paper do not cast the 
vote again.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
  
 <article><number>27L</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in rule 54A, the Election Commission may direct, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, that the postal ballot papers may be mixed with the 
ordinary ballot papers at the time of mixing of ordinary ballot papers under 
rule 59A and, in that case, the Election Commission may also prescribe, by 
directions to the Returning Officers, the manner in which the mixing of postal 
ballot papers shall be done with the ordinary ballot papers in the 
constituency.]
  </article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27M</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number> “classified service voter” means 
any person specified in clause (a) of section 60, who opts to give his vote by 
proxy;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number> “proxy” means the person 
appointed by a classified service voter as his proxy under rule 27N to give vote 
on his behalf and in his name;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number> “service voter” means any person 
specified in clause (a) of section 60 and registered as an elector in the last 
part of the electoral roll for the constituency.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27N</number> Appointment of proxy 
by a classified service voter.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A service voter may opt to give his vote by proxy appointed in the manner 
provided in sub‑rules 
(2) to (4).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any service voter 
opting to vote by proxy may appoint any person as his proxy to give vote on his 
behalf and in his name at an election in a parliamentary or assembly 
constituency:
 
Provided that such proxy 
shall be an ordinary resident in the constituency concerned and of not less than 
18 years of age and shall not be disqualified for registration as an elector in 
an electoral roll under section 16 of the Representation of the People Act, 1950 
(43 of 1950).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The appointment of 
proxy under sub‑rule (2) shall be made by the classified service voter in Form 
13F.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any appointment of 
proxy made under sub‑rule (3) shall be deemed to be valid so long as the person 
making it continues to be a service voter or till the date he revokes such 
appointment, or dies, whichever is earlier:
 
Provided that any 
revocation of appointment shall be made in Form 13G and shall be effective from 
the date on which it is received by the returning officer:
 
Provided further that 
where he revokes such appointment, or the proxy appointed by him dies, while he 
remains a service voter, he may appoint another person as proxy under these 
rules, as a substitute proxy in Form 13G and the substitute proxy so appointed 
shall be the proxy appointed by such classified service voter under sub‑rule (3) 
from the date of receipt of the Form 13G by the returning officer.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27-O</number> Intimation of name 
of proxy by the classified service voter.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The name of the proxy appointed by a classified service voter under sub‑rule 
(3), or, as the case may be, under the second proviso to sub‑rule (4) of rule 
27N, shall be intimated by him to the returning officer as soon as may be after 
such appointment is made, and such intimation must reach the returning officer 
not later than the last date for making nominations for the earliest 
election in the constituency after such appointment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub‑rule (1), if any intimation under that sub-rule 
reaches the returning officer after the last date for making nominations in the 
constituency, such intimation shall not be valid for the election then in 
progress, but shall, subject to the provisions of sub‑rule (4) of rule 27N, be 
valid for any future election in the constituency.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27P</number> Action by returning 
officer on intimation of name of proxy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of intimation under rule 27‑0 from a classified service voter in 
regard to his proxy, the returning officer shall mark “CSV” against the name of 
such voter in the last part of the electoral roll containing the names of all 
service voters so as to indicate that the said voter has appointed his proxy, 
and the returning officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  if it is an intimation received 
before the last date for making nominations in the constituency, ensure that no 
postal ballot paper is issued to such classified service voter; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if it is an intimation received 
after the said last date, ensure that a postal ballot paper is issued to such 
classified service voter for the election then in progress, in accordance with 
the provisions contained in Part III of these rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall also prepare, and maintain up‑to‑date, a separate list of all classified 
service voters who have given intimation of their proxies under rule 27‑O, and 
also of all such proxies with their complete addresses, in such form and such 
manner as the Election Commission may specify from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> As soon as may be 
after the last date for making nominations in the constituency, the returning 
officer shall, on the basis of the list maintained under sub‑rule (2) and 
subject to such further direction as the Election Commission may give in this 
behalf, prepare or cause to be prepared polling station‑wise sub‑lists of all 
classified service voters and their proxies having regard to the residential 
address of each such classified service voter as given in the electoral roll.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Each sub‑list prepared 
under sub‑rule (3) shall thereafter be caused to be added by the returning 
officer at the end to the relevant part of the electoral roll pertaining to each 
polling station concerned, and such relevant part of the electoral roll together 
with the said sub‑list shall be deemed to be the copy of the electoral roll to 
be used as the marked copy of the electoral roll under rule 33A or, as the case 
may be, under rule 49F during the poll at the polling station concerned.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>27Q</number> Recording of votes of 
proxy.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
person voting as proxy for a classified service voter shall do so in person at 
the polling station concerned in the electoral roll of which the name of such 
classified service voter is added under sub‑rule (4) of rule 27P.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The person voting as 
proxy shall record the vote on behalf of the classified service voter at the 
said polling station, in the same manner as any other elector assigned to that 
polling station and the provisions of rules 34, 35 and 36 to 43 or, as the case 
may be, rules 49G, 49K, 49J to 49R shall apply in relation to the recording of 
vote by such proxy as they apply to any other elector at the polling station:
 
Provided that any 
reference to left forefinger of elector in rule 37 or, as the case may be, rule 
49K shall be construed as reference to left middle finger of the person voting 
as a proxy under this rule.]
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Definitions.—1[In 
this Chapter and Chapter II], unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “candidate” means a contesting 
candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “constituency” means a 
parliamentary or assembly constituency; and 
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “polling agent”, in relation to 
a polling station, means a polling agent of a candidate duly appointed under 
section 46 for the polling station and includes a candidate and the election 
agent of a candidate when present at the polling station.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Design of ballot 
boxes.—Every 
ballot box shall be of such design as may be approved by the Election 
Commission.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Form of ballot papers.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every ballot paper shall have a counterfoil attached thereto, and the said 
ballot paper and the counterfoil shall be in such form, and the particulars 
therein shall be in such language or languages, as the Election Commission may 
direct.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names of the 
candidates shall be arranged on the ballot paper in the same order in which they 
appear in the list of contesting candidates.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If two or more 
candidates bear the same name, they shall be distinguished by the addition of 
their occupation or residence or in some other manner.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Arrangements at 
polling stations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Outside each polling station there shall be displayed prominently—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  a notice specifying the polling 
area the electors of which are entitled to vote at the polling station and, when 
the polling area has more than one polling station, the particulars of the 
electors so entitled; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  a copy of the list of contesting 
candidates.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> At each polling 
station, there shall be set up 

1[one or more 
voting compartments] in which electors can record their votes screened from 
observation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall provide at each polling station a sufficient number of ballot boxes, 
copies of the relevant part of the electoral roll, ballot papers, instruments 
for stamping the distinguishing mark on ballot papers and articles, necessary 
for electors to mark the ballot papers.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Admission to polling 
stations.—The 
presiding officer shall regulate the number of electors, to be admitted at any 
one time inside the polling station and shall exclude therefrom all persons 
other than—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  polling officers;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  public servants on duty in 
connection with the election;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  persons authorised by the 
Election Commission;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  candidates, their election 
agents and subject to the provisions of rule 13, one polling agent of each 
candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  a child in arms accompanying an 
elector;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  a person accompanying a blind 
or infirm elector who cannot move without help; and 
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  such other persons as the 
returning officer or the presiding officer may employ under sub-rule (2) of rule 
34 or sub-rule (1) of rule 35.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Preparation of ballot 
boxes for poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a paper seal is used for securing a ballot box, the presiding officer 
shall affix his own signature on the paper seal and obtain thereon the 
signatures of such of the polling agents present as are desirous of affixing the 
same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall thereafter fix the paper seal so signed in the space meant therefor in the 
ballot box and shall then secure and seal the box in such manner that the slit 
for the insertion of ballot paper thereinto remains open.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The seals used for 
securing a ballot box shall be affixed in such manner that after the box has 
been closed it is not possible to open it without breaking the seals.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where it is not 
necessary to use paper seals for securing the ballot boxes, the presiding 
officer shall secure and seal the ballot box in such manner that the slit for 
the insertion of ballot papers remains open and shall allow the polling agents 
present to affix, if they so desire, their seals.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every ballot box used 
at a polling station shall bear labels, both inside and outside, marked with—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the serial number, if any, and 
name of the constituency;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the serial number and name of 
the polling station;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the serial number of the ballot 
box (to be filled in at the end of the poll on the label outside the ballot box 
only); and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the date of poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Immediately before the 
commencement of the poll, the presiding officer shall demonstrate to the polling 
agents and other persons present that the box is empty and bears the labels 
referred to in sub-rule (5).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The ballot box shall 
then be closed, sealed and secured and placed in full view of the presiding 
officer and the polling agents.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>33A</number> Marked 
copy of electoral roll.—Immediately before the commencement of the poll the 
presiding officer shall also demonstrate to the polling agents and others 
present that the marked copy of the electoral roll to be used during the poll 
does not contain—
 
 

2[
<section><number>a</number>  any entry other than those made 
in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule (2) of rule 20 or clause (b) of sub-rule 
(2) of rule 27E; and]
 
 

3[(b)  any mark other than the mark 
made in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule (2) of rule 23 or clause (b) of 
sub-rule (2) of rule 27E.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Facilities for women 
electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a polling station is for both men and women electors, the presiding 
officer may direct that they shall be admitted into the polling station 
alternately in separate batches.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
or the presiding officer may appoint a woman to serve as an attendant at any 
polling station to assist women electors and also to assist the presiding 
officer generally in taking the poll in respect of women electors, and, in 
particular, to help in searching any woman elector in case it becomes necessary.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Identification of 
electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer may employ at the polling station such persons as he 
thinks fit to help in the identification of the electors or to assist him 
otherwise in taking the poll.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As each elector enters 
the polling station, the presiding officer or the polling officer authorised by 
him in this behalf shall check the elector’s name and other particulars with the 
relevant entry in the electoral roll and then call out the serial number, name 
and other particulars of the elector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the polling 
station is situated in a constituency, electors of which have been supplied with 
identity cards under the provisions of the Registration of Electors Rules, 1960, 
the elector shall produce his identity card before the presiding officer or the 
polling officer authorised by him in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In deciding the right 
of a person to obtain a ballot paper, the presiding officer or the polling 
officer, as the case may be, shall overlook merely clerical or printing errors 
in an entry in the electoral roll, if he is satisfied that such person is 
identical with the elector to whom such entry relates.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>35A</number> 
Facilities for public servants on election duty.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of rule 
35 shall not apply to any person who produces at the polling station an election 
duty certificate in Form 12B and asks for the issue of a ballot paper to him 
although the polling station is different from the one where he is entitled to 
vote.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On production of such 
certificate the presiding officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  obtain thereon the signature of 
the person producing it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  have the person’s name and 
electoral roll number as mentioned in the certificate entered at the end of the 
marked copy of the electoral roll; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  issue to him a ballot paper, and 
permit him to vote, in the same manner as for an elector entitled to vote at 
that polling station.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Challenging of 
identity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any polling agent may challenge the identity of a person claiming to be a 
particular elector by first depositing a sum of two rupees in cash with the 
presiding officer for each such challenge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On such deposit being 
made, the presiding officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  warn the person challenged of 
the penalty for personation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  read the relevant entry in the 
electoral roll in full and ask him whether he is the person referred to in that 
entry;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  enter his name and address in 
the list of challenged votes in Form 14; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  require him to affix his 
signature in the said list.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The presiding officer 
shall thereafter hold a summary inquiry into the challenge and may for that 
purpose—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  require the challenger to adduce 
evidence in proof of the challenge and the person challenged to adduce evidence 
in proof of his identity;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  put to the person challenged any 
questions necessary for the purpose of establishing his identity and require him 
to answer them on oath; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  administer an oath to the person 
challenged and any other person offering to give evidence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If, after the inquiry, 
the presiding officer considers that the challenge has not been established he 
shall allow the person challenged to vote; and if he considers that the 
challenge has been established, he shall debar the person challenged from 
voting.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the presiding 
officer is of the opinion that the challenge is frivolous or has not been made 
in good faith, he shall direct that the deposit made under sub-rule (1) be 
forfeited to Government and in any other case, he shall return to the challenger 
at the conclusion of the inquiry.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Safeguards against 
personation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every elector about whose identity the presiding officer or the polling officer, 
as the case may be, is satisfied, shall allow his left forefinger to be 
inspected by the presiding officer or polling officer and an indelible ink mark 
to be put on it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any elector—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  refuses to allow his left 
forefinger to be inspected or marked in accordance with sub-rule (1) or has 
already such a mark on his left forefinger or does any act with a view to 
removing the ink mark, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  fails or refuses to produce his 
identity card as required by sub-rule (3) of rule 35, he shall not be supplied 
with any ballot paper or allowed to vote.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a poll is taken 
simultaneously in a parliamentary constituency and an assembly constituency, an 
elector whose left forefinger has been marked with indelible ink or who has 
produced his identity card at one such election shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rules (1) and (2), be supplied with a ballot paper for the 
other election.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any reference in this 
rule to the left forefinger of an elector shall, in the case where the elector 
has his left forefinger missing, be construed as a reference to any other finger 
of his left hand, and shall, in the case where all the fingers of his left hand 
are missing, be construed as a reference to the forefinger or any other finger 
of his right hand, and shall in the case where all his fingers of both the hands 
are missing be construed as a reference to such extremity of his left or right 
arm as he possesses.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>38</number> Issue of 
ballot papers to electors.—
<section><number>1</number> Every ballot paper before it is issued to an 
elector, and the counterfoil attached thereto shall be stamped on the back with 
such distinguishing mark as the Election Commission may direct, and every ballot 
paper, before it is issued, shall be signed in full on its back by the presiding 
officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At the time of issuing 
a ballot paper to an elector, the polling officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  record on its counterfoil the 
electoral roll number of the elector as entered in the marked copy of the 
electoral roll;
 
 

2[(b)  obtain the signature or thumb 
impression of that elector on the said counterfoil; and]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  mark the name of the elector in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll to indicate that a ballot paper has been 
issued to him, without however recording therein the serial number of the ballot 
paper issued to that elector:
 

2[Provided that no 
ballot paper shall be delivered to an elector unless he has put his signature or 
thumb impression on the counterfoil of that ballot paper.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2) of rule 2, it shall not be necessary for any 
presiding officer or polling officer or any other officer to attest the thumb 
impression of the elector on the counterfoil.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No person in the 
polling station shall note down the serial numbers of the ballot papers issued 
to particular electors.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>39</number> 
Maintenance of secrecy of voting by electors within polling station and voting 
procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> Every elector to whom a ballot paper has been issued under 
rule 38 or under any other provision of these rules, shall maintain secrecy of 
voting within the polling station and for that purpose observe the voting 
procedure hereinafter laid down.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The elector on 
receiving the ballot paper shall forthwith—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  proceed to one of the voting 
compartments;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  there make a mark on the ballot 
paper with the instrument supplied for the purpose on or near the symbol of the 
candidate for whom he intends to vote;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  fold the ballot paper so as to 
conceal his vote;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  if required, show to the 
presiding officer the distinguishing mark on the ballot paper;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  insert the folded ballot paper 
into the ballot box; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  quit the polling station.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every elector shall 
vote without undue delay.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No elector shall be 
allowed to enter a voting compartment when another elector is inside it.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If an elector to whom 
a ballot paper has been issued, refuses, after warning given by the presiding 
officer, to observe the procedure as laid down in sub-rule (2), the ballot paper 
issued to him shall, whether he has recorded his vote thereon or not, be taken 
back from him by the presiding officer or a polling officer under the direction 
of the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> After the ballot paper 
has been taken back, the presiding officer shall record on its back the words 
“Cancelled: voting procedure violated” and put his signature below those words.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All the ballot papers 
on which the words “Cancelled: voting procedure violated” are recorded, shall be 
kept in a separate cover which shall bear on its face the words “Ballot papers: 
voting procedure violated”.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Without prejudice to 
any other penalty to which an elector, from whom a ballot paper has been taken 
back under sub-rule (5), may be liable, the vote, if any, recorded on such 
ballot paper shall not be counted.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>40</number> Recording 
of votes of blind or infirm electors.—
<section><number>1</number> If the presiding officer is 
satisfied that owing to blindness or other physical infirmity an elector is 
unable to recognise the symbols on the ballot paper or to make a mark thereon 
without assistance, the presiding officer shall permit the elector to take with 
him a companion of not less than 

2[eighteen] years 
of age to the voting compartment for recording the vote on the ballot paper on 
his behalf and in accordance with his wishes, and, if necessary, for folding the 
ballot paper so as to conceal the vote and inserting it into the ballot box:
 
Provided that no person 
shall be permitted to act as the companion of more than one elector at any 
polling station on the same day:
 
Provided further that 
before any person is permitted to act as the companion of an elector on any day 
under this rule, the person shall be required to declare that he will keep 
secret the vote recorded by him on behalf of the elector and that he has not 
already acted as the companion of any other elector at any polling station on 
that day.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall keep a record in Form 14A of all cases under this rule.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Spoilt and returned 
ballot papers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An elector who has inadvertently dealt with his ballot paper in such manner that 
it cannot be conveniently used as a ballot paper may, on returning it to the 
presiding officer and on satisfying him of the inadvertence, be given another 
ballot paper, and 

1[the ballot paper 
so returned and the counterfoil of such ballot paper] shall be marked “Spoilt: 
cancelled” by the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If an elector after 
obtaining a ballot paper decides not to use it, he shall return it to the 
presiding officer, and 

1[the ballot paper 
so returned and the counterfoil of such ballot paper] shall be marked as 
“Returned: cancelled” by the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All ballot paper 
cancelled under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) shall be kept in a separate packet.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Tendered votes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a person representing himself to be a particular elector applies for a ballot 
paper after another person has already voted as such elector, he shall, on 
satisfactorily answering such questions relating to his identity as the 
presiding officer may ask, be entitled, subject to the following provisions of 
this rule, to mark a ballot paper (hereinafter in these rules referred to as a 
“tendered ballot paper”) in the same manner as any other elector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such person 
shall, before being supplied with a tendered ballot paper, sign his name against 
the entry relating to him in a list in Form 15.
 

1[(3) A tendered 
ballot paper shall be the same as the other ballot paper used at the polling 
except that—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  such tendered ballot paper shall 
be serially the last in the bundle of ballot papers issued for use at the 
polling station; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  such tendered ballot paper and 
its counterfoil shall be endorsed on the back with the words “tendered ballot 
paper” by the presiding officer in his own hand and signed by him.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The elector, after 
marking a tendered ballot paper in the voting compartment and folding it, shall, 
instead of putting it into the ballot box, give it to the presiding officer, who 
shall place it in a cover specially kept for the purpose:
 

2[Provided that 
where such elector is a member of a political party in an election to fill a 
seat or seats in the Council of States, the presiding officer shall, before 
placing the tendered ballot paper in the said cover, allow the authorised agent 
of that political party to verify as to which candidate the elector has cast his 
vote.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, “authorised agent”, in respect of a political party, 
means an authorised agent appointed, under sub-rule (2) of rule 39AA as made 
applicable, by clause (ii) of rule 70, to election, in a council constituency 
and, by assembly members other than by postal ballot under clause (a) of rule 
68, by that political party.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Closing of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall close a polling station at the hour fixed in that 
behalf under section 56 and shall not thereafter admit any elector into the 
polling station:
 
Provided that all electors 
present at the polling station before it is closed shall be allowed to cast 
their votes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
whether an elector was present at the polling station before it was closed, it 
shall be decided by the presiding officer and his decision shall be final.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Sealing of ballot 
boxes after poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as practicable after the closing of the poll, the presiding officer 
shall close the slit of the ballot box, and where the box does not contain any 
mechanical device for closing the slit, he shall seal up the slit and also allow 
any polling agent present to affix his seal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The ballot box shall 
thereafter be sealed and secured.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where it becomes 
necessary to use a second ballot box by reason of the first ballot box getting 
full, the first box shall be closed, sealed and secured as provided in sub-rules 
(1) and (2) before another ballot box is put into use.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The foregoing 
provisions of this rule shall not apply at a polling station to the presiding 
officer of which the Election Commission has issued a direction asking him to 
proceed in accordance with sub-rule (5).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> At any such polling 
station, as soon as practicable after the close of poll, the presiding officer 
shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  transfer all the ballot papers 
contained in the ballot box or boxes used at that polling station, without 
examining or counting them and with due regard to the secrecy of the ballot, 
into a cloth bag or cloth-lined cover after demonstrating to the polling agents 
present that the bag or cover is empty;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  allow the polling agents present 
to inspect each ballot box and demonstrate to them that is has been emptied;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  record on the bag or cover the 
name of the constituency, the name of the polling station and the date of the 
poll; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  seal the bag or cover and allow 
any polling agent present to affix his seal thereon.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Account of ballot 
papers.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The presiding officer shall at the close of the poll prepare a ballot paper 
account in Form 16 and enclose it in a separate cover with the words “Ballot 
Paper Account” superscribed thereon.
 

2[(2) The presiding 
officer shall furnish to every polling agent present at the close of the poll a 
true copy of the entries made in the ballot paper account after obtaining a 
receipt from the said polling agent therefor and shall also attest it as a true 
copy.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Sealing of other 
packets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall then make into separate packets—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the marked copy of the electoral 
roll;
 
 

1[(aa)  the counterfoils of the used 
ballot paper;]
 
 

2[(b)  the ballot papers signed in 
full by the presiding officer under sub-rule (1) of rule 38 but not issued to 
the voters;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>bb</number>  and other ballot papers not 
issued to the voters;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the ballot papers cancelled for 
violation of voting procedure under rule 39;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>cc</number>  any other cancelled ballot 
papers;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the cover containing the 
tendered ballot papers and the list in Form 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the list of challenged votes; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  any other papers directed by 
the Election Commission to be kept in a sealed packet.
 

2[(2) Each such 
packet shall be sealed with the seals of the presiding officer and with the 
seals either of the candidate or of his election agent or of his polling agent 
who may be present at the polling station and may desire to affix his seals 
thereon.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Transmission of ballot 
boxes, etc., to the returning officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall then deliver or cause to be delivered to the 
returning officer at such place as the returning officer may direct—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the ballot boxes or, as the case 
may be, the bags or covers referred to in rule 44;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the ballot paper account;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the sealed packets referred to 
in rule 46; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  all other papers used at the 
poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall make adequate arrangements for the safe transport of all ballot boxes, 
packets and other papers and for their safe custody until the commencement of 
the counting of votes.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Procedure on 
adjournment of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the poll at any polling station is adjourned under sub-section (1) of section 
57, the provisions of rules 44 to 47 shall, as far as practicable, apply as if 
the poll was closed at the hour fixed in that behalf under section 56.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When an adjourned poll 
is recommenced under sub-section (2) of section 57, the electors who have 
already voted at the poll so adjourned shall not be allowed to vote again.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall provide the presiding officer of the polling station at which such 
adjourned poll is held, with the sealed packet containing the marked copy of the 
electoral roll and a new ballot box.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The presiding officer 
shall open the sealed packet in the presence of the polling agents present and 
use the marked copy of the electoral roll 

1[for marking the 
names of the electors to whom the ballot papers are issued at the adjourned 
poll, without however recording therein the serial number thereof].
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The provisions of 
rules 28 to 47 shall apply in relation to the conduct of an adjourned poll as 
they apply in relation to the poll before it was so adjourned.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49-I</number> Facilities for 
public servants on election duty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The provision of rule 49H shall not apply to any person who produces at the 
polling station an election duty certificate in Form 12B and seeks permission to 
cast his vote at that polling station although it is different from the one 
where he is entitled to vote.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On production of such 
certificate, the presiding officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  obtain thereon, the signature of 
the person producing it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  have the person’s name and 
electoral roll number as mentioned in the certificate entered at the end of the 
marked copy of the electoral roll; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  permit him to cast his vote in 
the same manner as for an elector entitled to vote at that polling station.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49-O</number> Elector deciding not 
to vote.—If an 
elector, after his electoral roll number has been duly entered in the register 
of voters in Form 17A and has put his signature or thumb impression thereon as 
required under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 49L, decides not to record his vote, a 
remark to this effect shall be made against the said entry in Form 17A by the 
presiding officer and the signature or thumb impression of the elector shall be 
obtained against such remark.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Voting by ballot at 
notified polling stations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the preceding provisions of this Part, the 
Election Commission may, by notification published in the Official Gazette at 
least 15 days before the date, or the first of the dates, of poll appointed for 
an election, direct that the method of voting by ballot shall be followed in 
that election at such polling stations as may be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such polling 
station is hereafter in these rules referred to as a “notified polling station”.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of 
rules 28 to 48 shall apply in relation to every notified polling station subject 
to the following modifications, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  in lieu of rule 30, the 
following rule shall apply:—
 
                   “30A. Form of ballot 
paper.—Every ballot paper shall be of such design as the Election Commission 
may decide”;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  in lieu of sub-rules (2) and (3) 
of rule 31, the following sub-rules shall apply:—
 
                       “(2) At each notified 
polling station there shall be set up one voting compartment in which the ballot 
boxes, one for each candidate, shall be placed for the reception of ballot 
papers during the poll and which shall be so designed that an elector can insert 
a ballot paper in any of the ballot boxes without being observed by any person 
outside the compartment.
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>3</number> The returning 
officer shall provide at each notified polling station a sufficient number of 
ballot boxes, copies of the relevant part of the electoral roll, ballot papers 
and such other election materials as may be required for taking the poll.”;
 <subsection>
        <number>c</number>  in lieu of sub-rules (5), (6) 
and (7) of rule 33, the following sub-rules shall apply:—
 
                       “(5) The symbol 
allotted to each candidate under rule 10 shall be printed on labels which shall 
be affixed both inside and outside the ballot box and such ballot box shall 
thereafter be deemed to have been allotted to that candidate.
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>6</number> Each ballot box 
shall also be marked with such other distinguishing marks as the Election 
Commission may direct.
 </section><section>
                       <number>7</number> Immediately before 
the commencement of the poll, the presiding officer shall allow inspection of 
each ballot box by the polling agents present and demonstrate to them that (a) 
it is empty, (b) proper labels have been affixed both inside and outside the 
box, and (c) the ballot box is marked in accordance with sub-rule (6).
 </section><section>
                       <number>8</number> After all the 
ballot boxes have been labelled, secured and sealed, they shall be placed in the 
voting compartment side by side the same order in which the names of the 
candidates to whom they have respectively been allotted appear in the list of 
contesting candidates.”;
 
 

1[(cc)  in lieu of rule 38, the 
following rule shall apply:—
 
                       “38B. Issue of 
ballot papers to electors.—(1) Every ballot paper shall before issue to an 
elector be—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  stamped with such 
distinguishing mark as the Election Commission may direct; and
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  signed in full on its 
back by the presiding officer.
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>2</number> At the time of 
issuing a ballot paper to an elector, the polling officer shall record the 
serial number thereof against the entry relating to the elector in the marked 
copy of the electoral roll.
 </section><section>
                       <number>3</number> Save as provided 
in sub-rule (2), no person in the polling station shall note down the serial 
numbers of the ballot papers issued to particular electors.”;]
 <subsection>
        <number>d</number>  in lieu of 

2[sub-rule (2) of rule 39], the 
following sub-rule shall apply:—
 
                       “(1) On receiving the 
ballot paper, the elector shall forthwith go into the voting compartment and 
insert the ballot paper through the slit into the ballot box allotted to the 
candidate for whom he wishes to vote”;
 
 

3[(e)  in lieu of sub-rule (1) of rule 
40, the following sub-rule shall apply:—
 
                       “(1) If the presiding 
officer is satisfied that owing to blindness or other physical infirmity an 
elector is unable to recognise the symbols on the ballot boxes or to insert the 
ballot paper into a ballot box, the presiding officer shall permit the elector 
to take with him a companion of not less than 

4[eighteen] years of age to the voting 
compartment for ascertaining from him the name of the candidate for whom he 
wishes to vote and for inserting the ballot paper into the ballot box of such 
candidate in accordance with the wishes of such elector:
 
                       Provided that no 
person shall be permitted to act as the companion of more than one elector at 
any polling station on the same day:
 
                       Provided further that 
before any person is permitted to act as the companion of an elector on any day 
under this rule, the person shall be required to declare that he will keep 
secret the name of the candidate for whom the elector has voted and that he has 
not already acted as the companion of any other elector at any polling station 
on that day.”];
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  in lieu of rule 42, the 
following rules shall apply:—
 
                       ‘42A. Tendered 
votes.—(1) If a person representing himself to be a particular elector 
applies for a ballot paper after another person has already voted as such 
elector, he shall, on satisfactorily answering such questions relating to his 
identity as the presiding officer may ask, be supplied with a ballot paper in 
Form 17 (hereafter in these rules referred to as a “tendered ballot paper”).
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>2</number> Every such person 
shall, before being supplied with a tendered ballot paper, sign his name against 
the entry relating to him in a list in Form 15.
 </section><section>
                       <number>3</number> Such person shall 
thereafter record on the tendered ballot paper the name of the candidate for 
whom he wishes to vote; but if owing to illiteracy, blindness, physical 
infirmity or any other reason he is unable to make such record, the presiding 
officer shall do so in accordance with his wishes.
 </section><section>
                       <number>4</number> The procedure laid 
down in sub-rule (3) shall be followed with due regard to secrecy.
 </section><section>
                       <number>5</number> Every such 
tendered ballot paper shall forthwith be placed in a cover specially kept for 
the purpose:
 

                                      5[Provided 
that where the person referred to in sub-rule (3) is a member of a political 
party in an election to fill a seat or seats in the Council of States, the 
presiding officer, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3), shall, 
before the tendered ballot paper is placed in the said cover, allow the 
authorised agent of that political party to verify as to whom such person has 
cast his vote.
 
                       Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, “authorised agent”, in respect of a political party, 
means an authorised agent appointed, under sub-rule (2) of rule 39AA as made 
applicable, by clause (ii) of rule 70, to election, in a council constituency 
and, by assembly members other than by postal ballot under clause (a) of rule 
68, by that political party.]
 </section><section>
                       <number>42B</number> Presiding 
officer’s entry into voting compartment during poll.—(1) The presiding 
officer may, whenever he considers it necessary to do so, enter the voting 
compartment during poll and take such steps as may be necessary to ensure that 
the ballot boxes therein are not tampered or interfered with in any way.
 </section><section>
                       <number>2</number> If the presiding 
officer has reason to suspect that an elector who has entered the voting 
compartment is tampering or otherwise interfering with any ballot box or has 
remained inside the voting compartment unduly long, he shall enter the voting 
compartment and take such steps as may be necessary to ensure the smooth and 
prompt progress of the poll.
 </section><section>
                       <number>3</number> Whenever the 
presiding officer enters the voting compartment under this rule he shall permit 
the polling agents present to accompany him.
 </section><section>
                       <number>42C</number> Disposal of 
ballot papers found wholly or partly outside ballot boxes.—(1) If any ballot 
paper which has been issued to an elector has not been inserted by him into any 
ballot box but is found anywhere in or near the polling station, whether within 
or outside the voting compartment it shall be deemed to have been returned to 
the presiding officer under sub-rule (2) of rule 41 and dealt with accordingly.
 </section><section>
                       <number>2</number> If a ballot paper 
is found partly inserted into the ballot box of a candidate, it shall be 
presumed that the intention of the elector was to cast that vote for that 
candidate and the presiding officer shall accordingly push the ballot paper into 
the ballot box.’;
 <subsection>
        <number>g</number>  in lieu of rule 44, the 
following rule shall apply:—
 
                       “44A. Sealing of 
ballot boxes after poll.—(1) As soon as practicable after the closing of the 
poll, the presiding officer shall close the slit of each ballot box and where 
the boxes do not contain any mechanical device for closing the slit, he shall 
seal up the slit and also allow any polling agent present to affix his seals.
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>2</number> All the ballot 
boxes shall thereafter be sealed and secured.”;
 

 6[***]
 
 

7[(i)  clause (aa) of sub-rule (1) of 
rule 46 shall not apply; and
 <subsection>
         <number>j</number>  in lieu of sub-rules (3) and 
(4) of rule 48, the following sub-rules shall apply:—
 
                       “(3) The returning 
officer shall provide the presiding officer of the polling station at which such 
adjourned poll is held with the sealed packet containing the marked copy of the 
electoral roll and a set of new ballot boxes.
 </subsection></section><section>
                       <number>4</number> The presiding 
officer shall open the sealed packet in the presence of the polling agents 
present and use the marked copy of the electoral roll for recording the serial 
numbers of the ballot papers issued to elector at the adjourned poll.”]
 
 









</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49A</number> Design of electronic 
voting machines.—Every 
electronic voting machine (hereinafter referred to as the voting machine) shall 
have a control unit and a balloting unit and shall be of such designs as may be 
approved by the Election Commission.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49B</number> Preparation of voting 
machine by the returning officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The balloting unit of the voting machine shall contain such particulars and in 
such language or languages as the Election Commission may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names of the 
candidates shall be arranged on the balloting unit in the same order in which 
they appear in the list of the contesting candidates.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If two or more 
candidates bear the same name, they shall be distinguished by the addition of 
their occupation or residence or in some other manner.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to the 
foregoing provisions of this rule, the returning officer shall,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  fix the label containing the 
names and symbol of the contesting candidates in the balloting unit and secure 
that unit with his seal and the seals of such of the contesting candidates or 
their election agents present as are desirous of affixing the same;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  set the number of contesting 
candidates and close the candidate set section in the control unit and secure it 
with his seal and the seals of such of the contesting candidates or their 
election agents present as are desirous of affixing the same.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49C</number> Arrangements at the 
polling stations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Outside each polling station there shall be displayed prominently—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  a notice specifying the polling 
area, the electors of which are entitled to vote at the polling station and, 
when the polling area has more than one polling station, the particulars of the 
electors so entitled; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  a copy of the list of contesting 
candidates.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> At each polling 
station there shall be set up one or more voting compartments in which the 
electors can record their votes free from observation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall provide at each polling station one voting machine and copies of relevant 
part of the electoral roll and such other election material as may be necessary 
for taking the poll.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Without prejudice to 
the provisions of sub-rule (3), the returning officer may, with the previous 
approval of the Election Commission, provide one common voting machine for two 
or more polling stations located in the same premises.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49D</number> Admission to polling 
stations.—The 
presiding officer shall regulate the number of electors, to be admitted at any 
one time inside the polling station and shall exclude therefrom all persons 
other than—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  polling officers;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  public servants on duty in 
connection with the election;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  persons authorised by the 
Election Commission;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  candidates, their election 
agents and subject to the provisions of rule 13, one polling agent of each 
candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  a child in arms accompanying as 
elector;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  a person accompanying a blind 
or infirm elector who cannot move without help; and
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  such other person as the 
returning officer or the presiding officer may employ under sub-rule (2) of rule 
49G or sub-rule (1) of rule 49H.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49E</number> Preparation of voting 
machine for poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The control unit and balloting unit of every voting machine used at polling 
station shall bear a label marked with—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the serial number, if any, and 
the name of the constituency;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the serial number and name of 
the polling station or stations, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the serial number of the unit; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the date of poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Immediately before the 
commencement of the poll, the presiding officer shall demonstrate to the polling 
agents and other persons present that no vote has been already recorded in the 
voting machine and it bears the label referred to in sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A paper seal shall be 
used for securing the control unit of the voting machine, and the presiding 
officer shall affix his own signature on the paper seal and obtain thereon the 
signature of such of the polling agents present as are desirous of affixing the 
same.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The presiding officer 
shall thereafter fix the paper seal so signed in the space meant therefor in the 
control unit of the voting machine and shall secure and seal the same.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The seal used for 
securing the control unit shall be fixed in such manner that after the unit has 
been sealed, it is not possible to press the “result button” without breaking 
the seal.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The control unit shall 
be closed and secured and placed in full view of the presiding officer and the 
polling agents and the balloting unit placed in the voting compartment.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49F</number> Marked copy of 
electoral roll.—Immediately 
before the commencement of the poll, the presiding officer shall also 
demonstrate to the polling agents and others present that the marked copy of the 
electoral roll to be used during the poll does not contain—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  any entry other than that made 
in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule (2) of rule 20; and 
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  any mark other than the mark 
made in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule (2) of rule 23.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49G</number> Facilities for women 
electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a polling station is for both men and women electors, the presiding 
officer may direct that they shall be admitted into the polling station 
alternately in separate batches.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
or the presiding officer may appoint a woman to serve as an attendant at any 
polling station to assist women electors and also to assist the presiding 
officer generally in taking the poll in respect of women electors, and in 
particular, to help in frisking any woman elector in case it becomes necessary.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49H</number> Identification of 
electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer may employ at the polling station such persons as he 
thinks fit to help in the identification of the electors or to assist him 
otherwise in taking the poll.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As each elector enters 
the polling station, the presiding officer or the polling officer authorised by 
him in this behalf shall check the elector’s name and other particulars with the 
relevant entry in the electoral roll and then call out the serial number, name 
and other particulars of the elector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the polling 
station is situated in a constituency electors of which have been supplied with 
identity cards under the provisions of the Registration of Electors Rules, 1960, 
the elector shall produce his identity card before the presiding officer or the 
polling officer authorised by him in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In deciding the right 
of a person to cast his vote, the presiding officer or the polling officer, as 
the case may be, shall over-look the clerical or printing errors in an entry in 
the electoral roll if he is satisfied that such person is identical with the 
elector to whom such entry relates.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49J</number> Challenging of 
identity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any polling agent may challenge the identity of a person claiming to be a 
particular elector by first depositing a sum of two rupees in cash with 
presiding officer for each such challenge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On such deposit being 
made, the presiding officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  warn the person challenged of 
the penalty for personation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  read the relevant entry in the 
electoral roll in full and ask him whether he is the person referred to in that 
entry;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  enter his name and address in 
the list of challenged votes in Form 14; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  require him to affix his 
signature in the said list.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The presiding officer 
shall thereafter hold a summary inquiry into the challenge and may for that 
purpose—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  require the challenger to adduce 
evidence in proof of the challenge and the person challenged to adduce evidence 
of proof of his identity;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  put to the person challenged any 
questions necessary for the purpose of establishing his identity and require him 
to answer them on oath; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  administer an oath to the person 
challenged and any other person offering to give evidence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If, after the inquiry, 
the presiding officer considers that the challenge has not been established he 
shall allow the person challenged to vote; and if he considers that the 
challenge has been established, he shall debar the person challenged from 
voting.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the presiding 
officer is of the opinion that the challenge is frivolous or has not been made 
in good faith, he shall direct that the deposit made under sub-rule (1) be 
forfeited to Government and in any other case, returned to the challenger at the 
conclusion of the inquiry.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49K</number> Safeguards against 
personation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every elector about whose identity the presiding officer or the polling officer, 
as the case may be, is satisfied, shall allow his left forefinger to be 
inspected by the presiding officer or polling officer and an indelible ink mark 
to be put on it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any elector—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  refuses to allow his left 
forefinger to be inspected or marked in accordance with sub-rule (1) or has 
already such a mark on his left forefinger or does any act with a view to 
removing the ink mark, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  fails or refuses to produce his 
identity card as required by sub-rule (3) of rule 49H he shall not be allowed to 
vote.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a poll is taken 
simultaneously in a Parliamentary constituency and an assembly constituency, an 
elector whose left forefinger has been marked with indelible ink or who has 
produced his identity card at one such election, shall notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rules (1) and (2) be permitted to cast his vote for the other 
election.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any reference in this 
rule to the left forefinger of an elector shall, in the case where the elector 
has his left forefinger missing, be construed as a reference to any other finger 
to his left hand, and shall, in the case where all the fingers of his left hand 
are missing, be construed as a reference to the forefinger or any other finger 
of his right hand, and shall in the case where all his fingers of both the hands 
are missing be construed as a reference to such extremity of his left or right 
arm as he possesses.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49L</number> Procedure for voting 
by voting machines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before permitting an elector to vote, the polling officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  record the electoral roll number 
of the elector as entered in the marked copy of the electoral roll in a register 
of voters in Form 17A;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  obtain the signature or the 
thumb impression of the elector on the said register of voters; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  mark the name of the elector in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll to indicate that he has been allowed to 
vote:
 
Provided that no elector 
shall be allowed to vote unless he has put his signature or thumb impression on 
the register of voters.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2) of rule 2, it shall not be necessary for any 
presiding officer or polling officer or any other officer to attest the thumb 
impression of the elector on the register of voters.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49M</number> Maintenance of 
secrecy of voting by electors within the polling station and voting procedures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every elector who has been permitted to vote under rule 49L shall maintain 
secrecy of voting within the polling station and for that purpose observe the 
voting procedure hereinafter laid down.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Immediately on being 
permitted to vote the elector shall proceed to the presiding officer or the 
polling officer incharge of the control unit of the voting machine who shall, by 
pressing the appropriate button on the control unit, activate the balloting 
unit; for recording of elector’s vote.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The elector shall 
thereafter forthwith—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  proceed to the voting 
compartment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  record his vote by pressing the 
button on the balloting unit against the name and symbol of the candidate for 
whom he intends to vote; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  come out of the voting 
compartment and leave the polling station.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every elector shall 
vote without undue delay.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No elector shall be 
allowed to enter the voting compartment when another elector is inside it.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If an elector who has 
been permitted to vote under rule 49L, or rule 49P refuses after warning given 
by the presiding officer to observe the procedure laid down in sub-rule (3) of 
the said rules, the presiding officer or a polling officer under the direction 
of the presiding officer shall not allow such elector to vote.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where an elector is 
not allowed to vote under sub-rule (6), a remark to the effect that voting 
procedure has been violated shall be made against the elector’s name in the 
register of voters in Form 17A by the presiding officer under his signature.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49N</number> Recording of votes of 
blind or infirm electors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the presiding officer is satisfied that owing to blindness or other physical 
infirmities an elector is unable to recognise the symbol on the balloting unit 
of the voting machine or unable to record his vote by pressing the appropriate 
button thereon without assistance the presiding officer shall permit the elector 
to take with him a companion of not less than eighteen years of age to the 
voting compartment for recording the vote on his behalf and in accordance with 
his wishes:
 
Provided that no person 
shall be permitted to act as the companion of more than one elector at any 
polling station on the same day:
 
Provided further that 
before any person is permitted to act as the companion of an elector on any day 
under this rule that person shall be required to declare that he will keep 
secret the vote recorded by him on behalf of the elector and that he has not 
already acted as the companion of any other elector at any other polling station 
on that day.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall keep a record in Form 14A of all cases under this rule.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49P</number> Tendered votes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a person representing himself to be a particular elector seeks to vote after 
another person has already voted as such elector, he shall, on satisfactorily 
answering such questions relating to his identity as the presiding officer may 
ask, be, instead of being allowed to vote through the balloting unit, supplied 
with a tendered ballot paper which shall be of such design, and the particulars 
of which shall be in such language or languages as the Election Commission may 
specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such elector 
shall before being supplied with a tendered ballot paper write his name against 
the entry relating to him in Form 17B.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receiving the 
ballot paper he shall forthwith—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  proceed to the voting 
compartment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  record there his vote on the 
ballot paper by placing a cross mark ‘X’ with the instrument or article supplied 
for the purpose on or near the symbol of the candidate for whom he intends to 
vote;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  fold the ballot paper so as to 
conceal his vote;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  show to the presiding officer, 
if required, the distinguishing mark on the ballot paper;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  give it to the presiding officer 
who shall place it in a cover specially kept for the purpose; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  leave the polling station.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If owing to blindness 
or physical infirmities, such elector is unable to record his vote without 
assistance; the presiding officer shall permit him to take with him a companion, 
subject to the same conditions and after following the same procedure as laid 
down in rule 49N for recording the vote in accordance with his wishes.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49Q</number> Presiding officer’s 
entry in the voting compartment during poll.— 

<section><number>1</number> The presiding officer may whenever he considers it necessary so to do, enter 
the voting compartment during poll and take such steps as may be necessary to 
ensure that the balloting unit is not tampered or interfered with in any way.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the presiding 
officer has reason to suspect that an elector who has entered the voting 
compartment is tampering or otherwise interfering with the balloting unit or has 
remained inside the voting compartment for unduly long period, he shall enter 
the voting compartment and take such steps as may be necessary to ensure the 
smooth and orderly progress of the poll.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever the presiding 
officer enters the voting compartment under this rule, he shall permit the 
polling agents present to accompany him if they so desire.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49R</number> Closing of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall close a polling station at the hour fixed in that 
behalf under section 56 and shall not thereafter admit any elector into the 
polling station:
 
Provided that all electors 
present at the polling station before it is closed shall be allowed to cast 
their votes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
whether an elector was present at the polling station before it was closed it 
shall be decided by the presiding officer and his decision shall be final.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49S</number> Account of votes 
recorded.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall at the close of the poll prepare an account of votes 
recorded in Form 17C and enclose it in a separate cover with the words ‘Account 
of Votes Recorded’ superscribed thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall furnish to every polling agent present at the close of the poll a true 
copy of the entries made in Form 17C after obtaining a receipt from the said 
polling agent therefor and shall attest it as a true copy.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49T</number> Sealing of voting 
machine after poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as practicable after the closing of the poll, the presiding officer 
shall close the control unit to ensure that no further votes can be recorded and 
shall detach the balloting unit from the control unit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The control unit and 
the balloting unit shall thereafter be sealed, and secured separately in such 
manner as the Election Commission may direct and the seal used for securing them 
shall be so affixed that it will not be possible to open the units without 
breaking the seals.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The polling agents 
present at the polling station, who desire to affix their seals, shall also be 
permitted to do so.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49U</number> Sealing of other 
packets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall then make into separate packet,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the marked copy of electoral 
roll;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the register of voters in Form 
17A;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the cover containing the 
tendered ballot papers and the list in Form 17B;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the list of challenged votes; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  any other papers directed by the 
Election Commission to be kept in a sealed packet.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each packet shall be 
sealed with the seal of the presiding officer and with the seal either of the 
candidate or of his election agent or of his polling agent who may be present at 
the polling station and may desire to affix his seal thereon.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49V</number> Transmission of 
voting machines, etc., to the returning officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall then deliver or cause to be delivered to the 
returning officer at such place as the returning officer may direct,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the voting machine;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the account of votes recorded in 
Form 17C;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the sealed packets referred to 
in rule 49U; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  all other papers used at the 
poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall make adequate arrangements for the safe transport of the voting machine, 
packets and other papers for their safe custody until the commencement of the 
counting of votes.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49W</number> Procedure on 
adjournment of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the poll at any polling station is adjourned under sub-section (1) of section 
57, the provision of rules 49S to 49V shall, as far as practicable, apply as if 
the poll was closed at the hour fixed in that behalf under section 56.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When an adjourned poll 
is recommenced under sub-section (2) of section 57, the electors who have 
already voted at the poll so adjourned shall not be allowed to vote again.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall provide the presiding officer of the polling station at which such 
adjourned poll is held, with the sealed packet containing the marked copy of the 
electoral roll, register of voters in Form 17A and a new voting machine.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The presiding officer 
shall open the sealed packet in the presence of the polling agents present and 
use the marked copy of the electoral roll for marking the names of the electors 
who are allowed to vote at the adjourned poll.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The provisions of rule 
28 and rules 49A to 49V shall apply in relation to the conduct of an adjourned 
poll before it was so adjourned.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>49X</number> Closing of voting 
machine in case of booth capturing.—Where 
the presiding officer is of opinion that booth capturing is taking place at a 
polling station or at a place fixed for the poll, he shall immediately close the 
control unit of the voting machine to ensure that no further votes can be 
recorded and shall detach the balloting unit from the control unit.]
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “candidate” means a contesting 
candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “constituency” means a 
parliamentary or assembly constituency;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “counting agent” means a 
counting agent duly appointed under section 47 and includes a candidate and the 
election agent of a candidate when present at the counting;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “notified polling station” means 
a polling station notified under rule 49;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “polling station” means a 
polling station provided under section 25 other than a notified polling station.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Time and place for 
counting of votes.—The 
returning officer shall, at least one week before the date, or the first of the 
dates, fixed for the poll, appoint the place or places where the counting of 
votes will be done and the date and time at which the counting will commence and 
shall give notice of the same in writing to each candidate or his election 
agent:
 
Provided that if for any 
reason the returning officer finds it necessary so to do, he may alter the date, 
time and place or places so fixed, or any of them, after giving notice of the 
same in writing to each candidate or his election agent.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Appointment of 
counting agents and revocation of such appointments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The number of counting agents that a candidate may appoint under section 47 
shall, subject to such general or special direction as the Election Commission 
may issue in this behalf, not exceed sixteen at the place or each of the places, 
fixed for counting under rule 51.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such appointment 
shall be made in Form 18 in duplicate, one copy of which shall be forwarded to 
the returning officer while the other copy shall be made over to the counting 
agent for production before the returning officer 

1[not later than 
one hour before the time fixed] for counting under rule 51.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No counting agent 
shall be admitted into the place fixed for counting unless he has delivered to 
the returning officer the second copy of his appointment under sub-rule (2) 
after duly completing and signing the declaration contained therein and 
receiving from the returning officer an authority for entry into the place fixed 
for counting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The revocation of 
appointment of a counting agent under sub-section (2) of section 48 shall be 
made in Form 19 and lodged with the returning officer.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of any 
such revocation before the commencement of the counting of votes, the candidate 
or his election agent may make a fresh appointment in accordance with sub-rule 
(2).
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Admission to the place 
fixed for counting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The returning officer shall exclude from the place fixed for counting of votes 
all persons except—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  

1[such persons (to be known as 
counting supervisors and counting assistants)] as he may appoint to assist him 
in the counting;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  persons authorised by the 
Election Commission;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  public servants on duty in 
connection with the election; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  candidates, their election 
agents and counting agents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No person who has been 
employed by or on behalf of, or has been otherwise working for, a candidate in 
or about the election shall be appointed under clause (a) of sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall decide which counting agent or agents shall watch the counting at any 
particular counting table or group of counting tables.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person who during 
the counting of votes misconducts himself or fails to obey the lawful directions 
of the returning officer may be removed from the place where the votes are being 
counted by the returning officer or by any police officer on duty or by any 
person authorised in this behalf by the returning officer.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Maintenance of secrecy 
of voting.—The 
returning officer shall, before he commences the counting, read out the 
provisions of section 128 to such persons as may be present.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>54A</number> Counting 
of votes received by post.—
<section><number>1</number> The returning officer shall first deal with 
the postal ballot papers in the manner hereinafter provided.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No cover in Form 13C 
received by the returning officer after the expiry of the time fixed in that 
behalf shall be opened and no vote contained in any such cover shall be counted.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The other covers shall 
be opened one after another and as each cover is opened, the returning officer 
shall first scrutinise the declaration in Form 13A contained therein.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the said 
declaration is not found, or has not been duly signed and attested, or is 
otherwise substantially defective, or if the serial number of the ballot paper 
as entered in it differs from the serial number endorsed on the cover in Form 
13B, that cover shall not be opened, and after making an appropriate endorsement 
thereon, the returning officer shall reject the ballot paper therein contained.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Each cover so endorsed 
and the declaration received with it shall be replaced in the cover in Form 13C 
and all such covers in Form 13C shall be kept in a separate packet which shall 
be sealed and on which shall be recorded the name of the constituency, the date 
of counting and a brief description of its content.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The returning officer 
shall then place all the declarations in Form 13A which he has found to be in 
order in a separate packet which shall be sealed before any cover in Form 13B is 
opened and on which shall be recorded the particulars referred to in sub-rule 
(5).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The covers in Form 13B 
not already dealt with under the foregoing provisions of this rule shall then be 
opened one after another and the returning officer shall scrutinise each ballot 
paper and decide the validity of the vote recorded thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A postal ballot paper 
shall be rejected—
 
 

2[(a)  if it bears any mark (other 
than the mark to record the vote) or writing by which the elector can be 
identified; or]
 
 

3[(aa)]  if no vote is recorded 
thereon; or
 <subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if notes are given on it in 
favour of more candidates than one; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  if it is a spurious ballot 
paper; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  if it is so damaged or mutilated 
that its identity as a genuine ballot paper cannot be established; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  if it is not returned in the 
cover sent along with it to the elector by the returning officer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> A vote recorded on a 
postal ballot paper shall be rejected if the mark indicating the vote is placed 
on the ballot paper in such manner as to make it doubtful to which candidate the 
vote has been given.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> A vote recorded on a 
postal ballot paper shall not be rejected merely on the ground that the mark 
indicating the vote is indistinct or made more than once, if the intention that 
the vote shall be for a particular candidate clearly appears from the way the 
paper is marked.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The returning officer 
shall count all the valid votes given by postal ballot in favour of each 
candidates, record the total thereof in the result sheet in Form 20 and announce 
the same.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> Thereafter, all the 
valid ballot papers and all the rejected ballot papers shall be separately 
bundled and kept together in a packet which shall be sealed with the seals of 
the returning officer and of such of the candidates, their election agents or 
counting agents as may desire to affix their seals thereon and on the packet so 
sealed shall be recorded the name of the constituency, the date of counting and 
a brief description of its contents.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Scrutiny and opening 
of ballot boxes.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The returning officer may have the ballot box or boxes used at more than one 
polling station opened and the ballot papers found in such box or boxes counted 
simultaneously.]
 

2[***]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before any ballot box 
is opened at a counting table, the counting agents present at that table shall 
be allowed to inspect the paper seal or such other seal as might have been 
affixed thereon and to satisfy themselves that it is intact.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall satisfy himself that none of the ballot boxes has in fact been tampered 
with.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the returning 
officer is satisfied that any ballot box has in fact been tampered with, he 
shall not count the ballot papers contained in that box and shall follow the 
procedure laid down in section 58 in respect of that polling station.
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> 

1[Counting of 
votes].—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The ballot papers taken out of each ballot box shall be arranged in convenient 
bundles and scrutinized.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall reject a ballot paper—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  if it bears any mark or writing 
by which the elector can be identified, or 
 
 

2[(b)  if it bears no mark at all or, 
to indicate the vote, it bears a mark elsewhere than on or near the symbol of 
one of the candidates on the face of the ballot paper or, it bears a mark made 
otherwise than with the instrument supplied for the purpose, or]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  if votes are given on it in 
favour of more than one candidates, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  if the mark indicating the vote 
thereon is placed in such manner as to make it doubtful to which candidate the 
vote has been given, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  if it is a spurious ballot 
paper, or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  if it is so damaged or 
mutilated that its identity as a genuine ballot paper cannot be established, or

 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  if it bears a serial number, or 
is of a design, different from the serial numbers, or, as the case may be, 
design, of the ballot authorised for use at the particular polling station, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  if it does not bear 

3[both the mark and the signature] 
which it should have borne under the provisions of sub-rule (l) of rule 38:
 
Provided that where the 
returning officer is satisfied that any such defect as is mentioned in clause 
(g) or clause (h) has been caused by any mistake or failure on the part of a 
presiding officer or polling officer, the ballot paper shall not be rejected 
merely on the ground of such defect:
 
Provided further that a 
ballot paper shall not be rejected merely on the ground that the mark indicating 
the vote is indistinct or made more than once, if the intention that the vote 
shall be for a particular candidate clearly appears from the way the paper is 
marked.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Before rejecting any 
ballot paper under sub-rule (2), the returning officer shall allow each counting 
agent present a reasonable opportunity to inspect the ballot paper but shall not 
allow him to handle it or any other ballot paper.
 

4[(4) The returning 
officer shall endorse on every ballot paper which he rejects the word “Rejected” 
and the grounds of rejection in abbreviated form either in his own hand or by 
means of a rubber stamp and shall initial such endorsement.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All ballot papers 
rejected under this rule shall be bundled together.
 

5[(6) Every ballot 
paper which is not rejected under this rule shall be counted as one valid vote:
 
Provided that no cover 
containing tendered ballot papers shall be opened and no such paper shall be 
counted.
 

6[(7) After the 
counting of all ballot papers contained in all the ballot boxes used at a 
polling station has been completed,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the counting supervisor shall 
fill in and sign Part II—Result of Counting, in Form 16, which shall also be 
signed by the returning officer; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the returning officer shall make 
the entries in a result sheet in Form 20 and announce the particulars.]]
 

7[***]
 
 









</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>57</number> Sealing of 
used ballot papers.—The valid ballot papers of each candidate and the 
rejected ballot papers shall thereafter be bundled separately and the several 
bundles made up into a separate packet which shall be sealed with the seals of 
the returning officer and of such of the candidates, their election agents or 
counting agents as may desire to affix their seals thereon; and on the packets 
so sealed shall be recorded the following particulars, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the name of the constituency;
 
 

2[(b)  the particulars of the polling 
station where the ballot papers have been used; and]
 
 

3[(c)  the date of counting.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Counting of ballot 
papers transferred to bags or covers under rule 44.—The 
provisions of rules 55, 56 and 57 shall apply so far as may be in relation to 
counting of ballot papers and votes, if any, which have been transferred from 
ballot boxes to cloth bags or cloth-lined covers under sub-rule (5) of rule 44:
 
Provided that every 
reference in the said rules to a ballot box shall be construed as a reference to 
a bag or cover to which the contents of a ballot box have been transferred.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Counting of votes at 
notified polling stations.—In 
relation to the counting of ballot papers found in ballot boxes used at notified 
polling stations, 

1[rules 50 to 54] 
and, in lieu of rules 55, 56 and 57, the following rules shall apply, namely:—
 
                  “55A. Scrutiny and 
opening of ballot boxes.—
<section><number>1</number> All ballot boxes used at a notified polling 
station shall be opened at the same time but every ballot box shall be dealt 
with in such manner that its contents do not get mixed up with the contents of 
any other ballot box.
 </section><section>
                  <number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-rule (1), the returning officer may have the ballot boxes used 
at more notified polling stations than one opened and their contents counted 
simultaneously.
 </section><section>
                  <number>3</number> Before any ballot box 
is opened, the counting agents present shall be allowed to inspect the paper 
seal or any other seal that might have been affixed thereon and to satisfy 
themselves that it is intact.
 </section><section>
                  <number>4</number> The returning officer 
shall satisfy himself that none of the ballot boxes has in fact been tampered 
with.
 </section><section>
                  <number>5</number> If the returning 
officer is satisfied that any of the ballot boxes has in fact been tampered 
with, he shall not count the ballot papers contained in any of the ballot boxes 
used at the polling station at which such box was used and shall proceed as laid 
down in section 58 in respect of that polling station.
 </section><section>
                  <number>6</number> After each ballot box 
is opened, the counting agents present shall be allowed to inspect the ballot 
box and satisfy themselves that it bears the proper symbol inside and has been 
duly marked in accordance with the provisions of sub-rule (6) of rule 33 as 
modified by clause (c) of sub-rule (3) of rule 49.
 </section><section>
                  <number>7</number> If any question arises 
as to the candidates to whom a particular ballot box was allotted at the poll, 
the returning officer shall decide such question by a reference to the symbol 
inside the box:
 
                  Provided that—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  if there is no symbol 
inside the box, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  if the symbol inside 
the box has been damaged or mutilated beyond recognition, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>c</number>  if the same symbol is 
found on two or more boxes used at the same polling station, the returning 
officer, shall, wherever possible, decide the question by reference to all 
relevant circumstances including the distinguishing marks on the ballot box, and 
where he does not consider it possible to decide the question, he shall 
immediately refer it to the Election Commission for its decision.
 </subsection></section><section>
                  <number>56A</number> 

2[Counting of votes].—(1) The 
ballot papers taken out of each ballot box shall be arranged in convenient 
bundles and scrutinised.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall reject a ballot paper—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  if it bears any mark 
or writing by which the elector can be identified; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  if it is a spurious 
ballot paper; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>c</number>  if it is so damaged or 
mutilated that its identity as a genuine ballot paper cannot be established; or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>d</number>  if it bears a serial 
number, or is of a design, different from the serial numbers or, as the case may 
be, design, of the ballot papers authorised for use at the particular polling 
station; or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>e</number>  if it does not bear


3[both the mark and the signature] 
which it should have borne under the provisions of sub-rule (1) of rule 38:
 
                  Provided that where the 
returning officer is satisfied that any such defect as is mentioned in clause 
(d) or clause (e) has been caused by any mistake or failure on the part of a 
presiding officer or polling officer, the ballot paper shall not be rejected 
merely on the ground of such defect.
 </subsection></section><section>
                  <number>3</number> Before rejecting any 
ballot paper under sub-rule (2), the returning officer shall allow the counting 
agents present a reasonable opportunity to inspect the ballot paper but shall 
not allow them to handle it or any other ballot paper.
 </section><section>
                  <number>4</number> The returning officer 
shall record on every ballot paper which he rejects the letter ‘R’ and the 
grounds of rejection in abbreviated form either in his own hand or by means of a 
rubber stamp.
 </section><section>
                  <number>5</number> All ballot papers taken 
out of any one ballot box and rejected under this rule shall be made into a 
separate bundle.
 

                             4[(6) 
Every ballot paper which is not rejected under this rule shall be counted as one 
valid vote:
 
                  Provided that no cover 
containing tendered ballot papers shall be opened and no such ballot paper shall 
be counted.]
 

                             5[(7) 
After the counting of all ballot papers contained in all the ballot boxes used 
at a polling station has been completed,—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the counting 
supervisor shall fill in and sign Part II—Result of Counting in 

6[Form 16 which shall also be signed 
by the returning officer; and
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  the returning officer 
shall make the entries in a result sheet in Form 20 and announce the 
particulars.]
 

                             7[57A. 
Sealing of used ballot papers.—(1) The valid ballot papers found in each 
ballot box, shall thereafter be bundled together and kept along with the bundle 
of rejected ballot papers, if any found in that box in a separate packet which 
shall be sealed with the seals of the returning officer and of such of the 
candidates, their election agents or counting agents as may desire to affix 
their seals thereon and on the packet so sealed there shall be recorded the 
following particulars, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the name of the 
constituency,
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  the particulars of the 
polling station where the ballot papers have been used,
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>c</number>  the name of the 
candidate to whom the ballot box was allotted, and
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>d</number>  the date of counting.
 </subsection></section><section>
                  <number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall then place together all the packets made up under sub-rule (1) in respect 
of each candidate in a separate container which shall be sealed with the seals 
of the returning officer and of such of the candidates, their election agents or 
their counting agents as may desire to affix their seals thereon and on the 
container so sealed shall be recorded the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the name of the 
constituency,
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  the names of the 
candidates, and
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>c</number>  the date of 
counting.]”.
 
 









</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>59A</number>


2[Counting of 
votes in specified constituencies.—Where the Election Commission apprehends 
intimidation and victimisation of electors in any constituency and it is of the 
opinion that it is absolutely necessary that the ballot papers taken out of all 
boxes used in that constituency should be mixed before counting, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify such constituency and for counting 
of such ballot papers, in lieu of rules 55, 56, 57 and 59, the following rules 
shall apply], namely:—
 
                  ‘55B. Scrutiny and 
opening of ballot boxes.—
<section><number>1</number> The returning officer shall open, or cause to 
be opened, simultaneously the ballot box or boxes used at more than one polling 
station and shall have the total number of ballot papers found in such box or 
boxes counted and recorded in Part II of Form 16:
 
                  Provided that discrepancy, 
if any, between the total number of such ballot papers recorded as aforesaid and 
the total number of ballot papers shown against item No. 5 of Part I shall also 
be recorded in Part II of Form 16.
 </section><section>
                  <number>2</number> Before any ballot box 
is opened at a counting table, the counting agents present at that table shall 
be allowed to inspect the paper seal or such other seal as might have been 
affixed thereon and to satisfy themselves that it is intact.
 </section><section>
                  <number>3</number> The returning officer 
shall satisfy himself that none of the ballot boxes has in fact been tampered 
with.
 </section><section>
                  <number>4</number> If the returning 
officer is satisfied that any ballot box has in fact been tampered with, he 
shall not count the ballot papers contained in that box and shall follow the 
procedure laid down in section 58 in respect of that polling station.
 </section><section>
                  <number>56B</number> Counting of votes.—(1) 
Subject to such general or special directions, if any, as may be given by the 
Election Commission in this behalf, the ballot papers taken out of all boxes


3[used at more than one polling 
station in a constituency,] shall be mixed together and then arranged in 
convenient bundles and scrutinised.
 </section><section>
                  <number>2</number> The returning officer 
shall reject a ballot paper—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  if it bears any mark 
or writing by which the elector can be identified, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  if it bears no mark at 
all or, to indicate the vote, it bears a mark elsewhere than on or near the 
symbol of one of the candidates on the face of the ballot paper or, it bears a 
mark made otherwise than with the instrument supplied for the purpose, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>c</number>  if votes are given on 
it in favour of more than one candidate, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>d</number>  if the mark indicating 
the vote thereon is placed in such manner as to make it doubtful to which 
candidate the vote has been given, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>e</number>  if it is a spurious 
ballot paper, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>f</number>  if it is so damaged or 
mutilated that its identity as a genuine ballot paper cannot be established, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>g</number>  if it bears a serial 
number, or is of a design, different from the serial numbers, or, as the case 
may be, design, of the ballot papers authorised for use at the particular 
polling station, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>h</number>  if it does not bear 
both the mark and the signature which it should have borne under the provisions 
of sub-rule (1) of rule 38:
 
                  Provided that where the 
returning officer is satisfied that any such defect as is mentioned in clause 
(g) or clause (h) has been caused by any mistake or failure on the part of a 
presiding officer or polling officer, the ballot paper shall not be rejected 
merely on the ground of such defect:
 
                  Provided further that a 
ballot paper shall not be rejected merely on the ground that the mark indicating 
the vote is indistinct or made more than once, if the intention that the vote 
shall be for a particular candidate clearly appears from the way the paper is 
marked.
 </subsection></section><section>
                  <number>3</number> Before rejecting any 
ballot paper under sub-rule (2), the returning officer shall allow each counting 
agent present a reasonable opportunity to inspect the ballot paper but shall not 
allow him to handle it or any other ballot paper.
 </section><section>
                  <number>4</number> The returning officer 
shall endorse on every ballot paper which he rejects the word “Rejected” and the 
grounds of rejection in abbreviated form either in his own hand or by means of a 
rubber stamp and shall initial such endorsement.
 </section><section>
                  <number>5</number> All ballot papers 
rejected under this rule shall be bundled together.
 </section><section>
                  <number>6</number> Every ballot paper 
which is not rejected under this rule shall be counted as one valid vote:
 
                  Provided that no cover 
containing tendered ballot shall be opened and no such paper shall be counted.
 </section><section>
                  <number>7</number> After the counting of 
all ballot papers contained in all the ballot boxes used in a constituency has 
been completed, the returning officer shall make the entries in a result sheet 
in From 20A and announce the particulars.
 
                  Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule, the expression “constituency” shall, in relation to an 
election from a parliamentary constituency, mean the assembly constituency 
comprised therein.
 </section><section>
                  <number>57B</number> Sealing of used 
ballot papers.—The valid ballot papers of each candidate and the rejected 
ballot papers shall thereafter be bundled separately and the several bundles 
made up into a separate packet which shall be sealed with the seals of the 
returning officer and of such of the candidates, their election agents or 
counting agents as may desire to affix their seals thereon and on the packets so 
sealed shall be recorded the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the name of the 
constituency; and
 </subsection><subsection>
                  <number>b</number>  the date of 
counting.’.
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Counting to be 
continuous.—The 
returning officer shall, as far as practicable proceed continuously with the 
counting and shall, during any intervals when the counting has to be suspended, 
keep the ballot papers, packets and all other papers relating to the election 
sealed with his own seal and the seals of such candidates or election agents as 
may desire to affix their seals and take sufficient precaution for their safe 
custody during such intervals.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Recommencement of 
counting after fresh poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a fresh poll is held under section 58, the returning officer shall, after 
completion of that poll, recommence the counting of votes on the date and at the 
time and place which have been fixed by him in that behalf and of which notice 
has been previously given to the candidates and their election agents.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
rules 56 and 57 shall apply so far as may be to such further counting.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Re-count of votes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the completion of the counting, the returning officer shall record in the 
result sheet in Form 20 the total number of votes polled by each candidate and 
announce the same.
 

1[(2) After such 
announcement has been made, a candidate or, in his absence, his election agent 
or any of his counting agents may apply in writing to the returning officer to 
re-count the votes either wholly or in part stating the grounds on which he 
demands such re-count.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On such an application 
being made the returning officer shall decide the matter and may allow the 
application in whole or in part or may reject it in toto if it appears to 
him to be frivolous or unreasonable.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every decision of the 
returning officer under sub-rule (3) shall be in writing and contain the reasons 
therefor.
 

1[(5) If the 
returning officer decides under sub-rule (3) to allow a re-count of the votes 
either wholly or in part, he shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  do the re-counting in accordance 
with 

2[rule 54A,] rule 56 or rule 56A, as 
the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  amend the result sheet in Form 
20 to the extent necessary after such re-count; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  announce the amendments so made 
by him.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> After the total number 
of votes polled by each candidate has been announced under sub-rule (1) or 
sub-rule (5), the returning officer shall complete and sign the result sheet in 
Form 20 and no application for a re-count shall be entertained thereafter:
 
Provided that no step 
under this sub-rule shall be taken on the completion of the counting until the 
candidates and election agents present at the completion thereof have been given 
a reasonable opportunity to exercise the right conferred by sub-rule (2).
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>64</number> 
Declaration of result of election and return of election.—The returning 
officer shall, subject to the provisions of section 65 if and so far as they 
apply to any particular case, then—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  declare in Form 21C or Form 21D, 
as may be appropriate, the candidate to whom the largest number of valid votes 
have been given, to be elected under section 66 and send signed copies thereof 
to the appropriate authority, the Election Commission and the chief electoral 
officer; and 
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  complete and certify the return 
of election in Form 21E, and send signed copies thereof to the Election 
Commission and the chief electoral officer.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Counting at two or 
more places.—If 
ballot papers are counted at more places than one, the provisions of 

1[rules 53, 54 and 
55 to 60] shall apply to the counting at each such place, but the provisions of


2[rules 54A, 63 and 
64] shall apply only to the counting at the last of such places.
 
 



</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Grant of certificate 
of election to returned candidate.—As 
soon as may be after a candidate has been declared by the returning officer 
under the provisions of section 53, or section 66, to be elected, the returning 
officer shall grant to such candidate a certificate of election in Form 22 and 
obtain from the candidate an acknowledgment of its receipt duly signed by him 
and immediately send the acknowledgment by registered post to the Secretary of 
the House of the People or, as the case may be, the Secretary of the Legislative 
Assembly.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>66A</number> Counting 
of votes where electronic voting machines have been used.—In relation to the 
counting of votes cast at a polling station, where voting machine has been 
used,—
 <section>
         <number>i</number>  the provisions of rules 50 to 
54 and in lieu of rules 55, 56 and 57, the following rules shall respectively 
apply, namely:—
 
                       “55C. Scrutiny and 
inspection of voting machines.—(1) The returning officer may have the 
control units of the voting machines used at more than one polling station taken 
up for scrutiny and inspection and votes recorded in such units counted 
simultaneously.
 <subsection>
                       <number>2</number> Before the votes 
recorded in any control unit of voting machine are counted under sub-rule (1), 
the candidate or his election agent or his counting agent present at the 
counting table shall be allowed to inspect the paper seal and such other vital 
seals as might have been affixed on the unit and to satisfy themselves that the 
seals are intact.
 </subsection><subsection>
                       <number>3</number> The returning 
officer shall satisfy himself that none of the voting machines has in fact been 
tampered with.
 </subsection><subsection>
                       <number>4</number> If the returning 
officer is satisfied that any voting machine has in fact been tampered with he 
shall not count the votes recorded in that machine and shall follow the 
procedure laid down in section 58, or section 58A or section 64A, as may be 
applicable in respect of the polling station or stations where that machine was 
used.
 </subsection><subsection>
                       <number>56C</number> Counting of 
votes.—(1) After the returning officer is satisfied that a voting machine 
has in fact not been tempered with, he shall have the votes recorded therein 
counted by pressing the appropriate button marked “Result” provided in the 
control unit whereby the total votes polled and votes polled by each candidate 
shall be displayed in respect of each such candidate on the display panel 
provided for the purpose in the unit.
 </subsection><subsection>
                       <number>2</number> As the votes 
polled by each candidate are displayed on the control unit, the returning 
officer shall have,—
 <subsubsection>
                       <number>a</number>  the number of 
such votes recorded separately in respect of each candidate in Part II of Form 
17C;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>b</number>  Part II of Form 
17C completed in other respects and signed by the counting supervisor and also 
by the candidates or their election agents or their counting agents present; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>c</number>  corresponding 
entries made in a result sheet in Form 20 and the particulars so entered in the 
result sheet announced.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
                       <number>57C</number> Sealing of 
voting machines.—(1) After the result of voting recorded in a control unit 
has been ascertained candidate-wise and entered in Part II of Form 17C and Form 
20 under rule 56C, the returning officer shall reseal the unit with his seal and 
the seals of such of the candidates or their election agents present who may 
desire to affix their seals thereon so however that the result of voting 
recorded in the unit is not obliterated and the unit retains the memory of such 
result.
 </subsection><subsection>
                       <number>2</number> The control unit 
so sealed shall be kept in specially prepared boxes on which the returning 
officer shall record the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsubsection>
                       <number>a</number>  the name of the 
constituency;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>b</number>  the particulars 
of polling station or stations where the control unit has been used;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>c</number>  serial number of 
the control unit;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>d</number>  date of poll; and

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>e</number>  date of 
counting.”
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  the provisions of rules 60 to 
66 shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to voting by voting machines and 
any reference in those rules to,—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  ballot paper shall be 
construed as including a reference to such voting machine;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  any rule shall be construed 
as a reference to the corresponding rule in Chapter II of Part IV or, as the 
case may be, to rule 55C or 56C or 57C].
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>67</number> 
Definition.—Unless the context otherwise requires, in this Part—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  and in rule 84, “authorised 
agent”, in respect of a political party, means an authorised agent appointed, 
under sub-rule (2) of rule 39AA as made applicable, by clause (ii) of rule 70, 
to election, in a council constituency and, by assembly members other than by 
postal ballot under clause (a) of rule 68, by that political party;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “election” means an election by 
assembly members or an election in a council constituency.]
 
 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>68</number> Notification as to postal ballot.—</title>The Election Commission may, by notification published in the Official Gazette at any time before the last date for the withdrawal of candidatures at an election, direct that the method of voting by postal ballot shall be followed:—

 
 <section><number>a</number> at that election, if it is an election by assembly members; or  
 </section><section><number>b</number> in the whole or any specified parts of the constituency, if it is an election in a council constituency.
</section>
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
  
 <article>1[<number>69</number> Notice to electors at 
election by assembly members.—At an election by assembly members where a 
poll becomes necessary, the returning officer for such election shall, as soon 
as may be after the last date for the withdrawal of candidatures, send to each 
elector a notice informing him of the date, time and place fixed for 
polling.]
  


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Rules for conduct of 
poll.—The 
provisions of 

1[rules 28 to 35 
and 36 to 48] shall apply—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  to every election by assembly 
members in respect of which no direction has been issued under clause (a) of 
rule 68, and
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  to every election in a council 
constituency unless voting by postal ballot has been directed in the whole of 
that constituency under clause (b) of rule 68,
 
subject to the following modifications, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  clause (a) of sub-rule (l) of 
rule 31 shall not apply to an election by assembly members; 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  

2[in lieu of rules 37 to 40], the 
following rules shall apply:—
 
                       “37A. Method of 
voting.—(1) Every elector has only one vote at an election irrespective of 
the number of seats to be filled.
 
 

3[(1A) The provisions of sub-rules 
(1), (2) and (4) of rule 37 shall apply in relation to electors in the 
graduates’ constituencies and teachers’ constituencies as they apply in relation 
to electors in the Parliamentary constituencies and Assembly constituencies.]
 <subsubsection>
                       <number>2</number> An elector in 
giving his vote—
 <subsubsubsection>
                       <number>a</number>  shall place on 
his ballot paper the figure 1 in the space opposite the name of the candidate 
for whom he wishes to vote in the first instance; and 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                       <number>b</number>  may, in addition, 
place on his ballot paper the figure 2 or the figures 2 and 3, or the figures 2, 
3 and 4 and so on, in the space opposite the names of the other candidates in 
the order of his preference.
 
 

4[Explanation.—The figures 
referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of this sub-rule may be marked in the 
international form of Indian numerals or in the Roman form or in the form used 
in any Indian language but shall not be indicated in words.]
 
 

5[38A. Issue of ballot papers to 
electors.—(1) Every ballot paper, before it is issued to an elector, and the 
counterfoil attached thereto shall be stamped on the back with such 
distinguishing mark as the Election Commission may direct, and every ballot 
paper, before it is issued, shall be signed in full on its back by the presiding 
officer.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
                       <number>2</number> At the time of 
issuing a ballot paper to an elector, the polling officer shall—
 <subsubsubsection>
                      <number>a</number>  record on its 
counterfoil the electoral roll number of the elector as entered in the marked 
copy of the electoral roll;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      <number>b</number>  obtain the 
signature or thumb impression of that elector on the said counterfoil; and
 

                                6[(c) 
mark the name of the elector in the marked copy of the electoral roll to 
indicate that a ballot paper has been issued to him,—
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
                        <number>i</number>  and record in 
the marked copy of the electoral roll, the serial number of the ballot paper 
issued to that elector, in the case of an election to fill a seat or seats in 
the Council of States;
 </subsection><subsection>
                        <number>ii</number>  without 
recording therein the serial number of the ballot paper issued to that elector, 
in the case of an election to fill a seat or seats in the Legislative Council of 
a State:
 
                       Provided that no 
ballot paper shall be delivered to an elector unless he has put his signature or 
thumb impression on the counterfoil of that ballot paper.]
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2) of rule 2, it shall not be necessary for any 
presiding officer or polling officer or any other officer to attest the thumb 
impression of the elector on the counterfoil.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>4</number> 

7[Subject to rule 39AA, no person in 
the polling station shall note down the serial numbers of the ballot papers 
issued to particular electors.
 
 

8[(5) Before any ballot paper is 
delivered to an elector at an election to fill a seat or seats in the 
Legislative Council of a State by assembly members or in a local authorities 
constituency, the serial number of the ballot papers shall be effectively 
concealed in such manner as the Election Commission may direct.]
 
 

9[39A. Maintenance of secrecy of 
voting by electors within polling station and voting procedure.—(1) Every 
elector, to whom a ballot paper has been issued under rule 38A or under any 
other provision of these rules, shall maintain secrecy of voting within the 
polling station and for that purpose observe the voting procedure hereinafter 
laid down.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>2</number> The elector on 
receiving the ballot paper shall forthwith—
 <subsubsubsection>
                  <number>a</number>  proceed to one of the 
voting compartments;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                  <number>b</number>  record his vote in 
accordance with sub-rule (2) of rule 37A with the article supplied for the 
purpose;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                  <number>c</number>  fold the ballot paper 
so as to conceal his vote;
 
 

10[(d)  if required, show to the 
presiding officer, the distinguishing mark on the ballot paper;]
 
 

11[(e)]  insert the folded paper into 
the ballot box; and
 
 

11[(f)]  quit the polling station.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>3</number> Every elector shall 
vote without undue delay.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>4</number> No elector shall be 
allowed to enter a voting compartment when another elector is inside it.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>5</number> If an elector to whom a 
ballot paper has been issued, refuses, after warning given by the presiding 
officer to observe the procedure as laid down in sub-rule (2), the ballot paper 
issued to him shall, whether he has recorded his vote thereon or not, be taken 
back from him by the presiding officer or a polling officer under the direction 
of the presiding officer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>6</number> After the ballot paper 
has been taken back, the presiding officer shall record on its back the words 
“Cancelled: voting procedure violated” and put his signature below those words.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>7</number> All the ballot papers 
on which the words “Cancelled: voting procedure violated” are recorded, shall be 
kept in a separate cover which shall bear on its face the words “Ballot papers: 
voting procedure violated”.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>8</number> Without prejudice to 
any other penalty to which an elector, from whom a ballot paper has been taken 
back under sub-rule (5), may be liable, vote, if any, recorded on such ballot 
paper shall not be counted.]
 

                             12[39AA. 
Information regarding casting of votes.—(1) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in rule 39A, the presiding officer shall, between the period when an 
elector being a member of a political party records his vote on a ballot paper 
and before such elector inserts that ballot paper into the ballot box, allow the 
authorised agent of that political party to verify as to whom such elector has 
cast his vote:
 
                  Provided that if such 
elector refuses to show his marked ballot paper to the authorised agent of his 
political party, the ballot paper issued to him shall be taken back by the 
presiding officer or a polling officer under the direction of the presiding 
officer and the ballot paper so taken back shall then be further dealt with in 
the manner specified in sub-rules (6) to (8) of rule 39A as if such ballot paper 
had been taken back under sub-rule (5) of that rule.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>2</number> Every political party, 
whose member as an elector casts a vote at a polling station, shall, for the 
purposes of sub-rule (1), appoint, in Form 22A, two authorised agents.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>3</number> An authorised agent 
appointed under sub-rule (2) shall be present throughout the polling hours at 
the polling station and the other shall relieve him when he goes out of the 
polling station or vice versa.]
 
 

13[40A. Recording of votes of 
illiterate, blind or infirm electors.—(1) If an elector is unable to read 
the ballot paper or to record his vote thereon in accordance with rule 37A by 
reason of illiteracy, blindness or other infirmity, the presiding officer shall, 
on being satisfied about such illiteracy, blindness or infirmity, permit the 
elector to take with him a companion of not less than 

14[eighteen] years of age who is able 
to read the ballot paper and record the vote thereon on behalf of, and in 
accordance with the wishes of, the elector and, if necessary, to fold the ballot 
paper so as to conceal the vote and insert it into the ballot box:
 
                  Provided that no person 
shall be permitted to act as the companion of more than one elector at any 
polling station on the same day:
 
                  Provided further that 
before any person is permitted to act as the companion of an elector on any day 
under this rule, the person shall be required to declare that he will keep 
secret the vote recorded by him on behalf of the elector and that he has not 
already acted as the companion of any other elector at any polling station on 
that day:
 
 

15[Provided also that at an election 
by assembly members no such companion shall be an elector at that election.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall keep a record in Form 14A of all the cases under this rule.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>3</number> The presiding officer 
shall, when he is so requested by the companion of an elector, explain to him 
the instructions for the recording of votes.]”;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  in lieu of rule 44, the 
following rule shall apply:—
 
                  “44B. Sealing of ballot 
box after poll.—As soon as practicable after the close of the poll, the


16[presiding officer] shall, in the 
presence of any polling agents who may be present, close the slit for insertion 
of ballot papers of each ballot box or where the box does not contain any 
mechanical device for closing the slit, seal up the slit and secure the ballot 
box:
 
                  Provided that it shall not 
be necessary to seal the slit or secure the ballot box if the counting of votes 
is to begin immediately after the close of the poll.”;
 
 

17[(iv)  in rule 46, in sub-rule (1), 
in lieu of clauses (b) and (c), the following clauses shall apply:—
 
            “(b)  the ballot papers signed in 
full by the presiding officer under sub-rule (1) of rule 38A but not issued to 
the voters;
 </subsection></section><section>
             <number>c</number>  the ballot papers cancelled 
for violation of voting procedure under rule 39A.”]
 
 






















</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part,—
 <section>
        <number>1</number>  “continuing candidate” means any 
candidate not elected and not excluded from the poll at any given time;
 </section><section>
        <number>2</number>  “count” means—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  all the operations involved 
in the counting of the first preferences recorded for candidates; or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  all the operations involved 
in the transfer of the surplus of an elected candidate; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>c</number>  all the operations 
involved, in the transfer of the total value of votes of an excluded candidate;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>3</number>  “exhausted paper” means a ballot 
paper on which no further preference is recorded for a continuing candidate, 
provided that a paper shall also be deemed to have become exhausted whenever—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  the names of two or more 
candidates, whether continuing or not, are marked with the same figure and are 
next in order of preference; or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  the name of the candidate 
next in order of preference, whether continuing or not, is marked by a figure 
not following consecutively after some other figure on the ballot paper or by 
two or more figures;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>4</number>  “first preference” means the 
figure 1 set opposite the name of a candidate; “second preference” means the 
figure 2 set opposite the name of a candidate; “third preference” means the 
figures 3 set opposite the name of a candidate, and so on;
 </section><section>
        <number>5</number>  “original vote”, in relation to 
any candidate, means a vote derived from a ballot paper on which a first 
preference is recorded, for such candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>6</number>  “surplus” means the number by 
which the value of the votes, original and transferred, of any candidate exceeds 
the quota;
 </section><section>
        <number>7</number>  “transferred vote”, in relation 
to any candidate, means a vote the value or the part of the value of which is 
credited to such candidate and which is derived from a ballot paper on which a 
second or a subsequent preference is recorded for such candidate; and
 </section><section>
        <number>8</number>  “unexhausted paper” means a 
ballot paper on which a further preference is recorded for a continuing 
candidate.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Application of certain 
rules.—The 
provisions of rules 51 to 54 shall apply to the counting of votes at any 
election by assembly members or in a council constituency as they apply to the 
counting of votes at an election in a parliamentary or assembly constituency.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Scrutiny and opening 
of ballot boxes and packets of postal ballot papers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The returning officer shall—
 
 

1[(a)  first deal with the covers 
containing the postal ballot papers, if any, in the manner provided in sub-rules 
(2) to (7) of rule 54A;
 <subsection>
        <number>b</number>  then open the ballot boxes, take 
out from each box and count the ballot papers contained therein, and record 
their number in a statement;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  scrutinise the ballot papers 
taken out of the ballot boxes as well as the postal ballot papers taken out from 
the covers; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  separate the ballot papers which 
he deems valid from those which he rejects endorsing on each of the latter the 
word “Rejected” and the ground of rejection.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 

2[Subject to rule 
38A as made applicable, by clause (ii) of rule 70, to election, in a council 
constituency and, by assembly members other than by postal ballot under clause 
(a) of rule 68, a ballot paper shall] be invalid on which—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the figure 1 is not marked; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the figure 1 is set opposite the 
name of more than one candidate or is so placed as to render it doubtful to 
which candidate it is intended to apply; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the figure 1 and some other 
figures are set opposite the name of the same candidate; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  there is any mark or writing by 
which the elector can be identified; 

3[or]
 
 

4[(e)  there is any figure marked 
otherwise than with the article supplied for the purpose:
 
Provided that this clause 
shall not apply to a postal ballot paper:
 
Provided further that 
where the returning officer is satisfied that any such defect as is mentioned in 
this clause has been caused by any mistake or failure on the part of a presiding 
officer or polling officer, the ballot paper shall not be rejected, merely on 
the ground of such defect.]
 

5[Explanation.—The 
figures referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of this sub-rule may be marked 
in the international form of Indian numerals or in the Roman form or in the form 
used in any Indian language, but shall not be indicated in words.]
 
 







</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Arrangement of valid 
ballot papers in parcels.—After 
rejecting the ballot papers which are invalid, the returning officer shall—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  arrange the remaining ballot 
papers in parcels according to the first preference recorded for each candidate;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  count and record the number of 
papers in each parcel and the total number; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  credit to each candidate the 
value of the papers in his parcel.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Counting of votes 
where only one seat is to be filled.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At any election where only one seat is to be filled, every valid ballot paper 
shall be deemed to be of the value of 1 at each count, and the quota sufficient 
to secure the return of a candidate at the election shall be determined as 
follows:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  add the values credited to all 
the candidates under clause (c) of rule 74;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  divide the total by 2; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  add 1 to the quotient ignoring 
the remainder, if any, and the resulting number is the quota.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If, at the end of the 
first or any subsequent count, the total value of the ballot papers credited to 
any candidate is equal to, or greater than, the quota or there is only one 
continuing candidate, that candidate shall be declared elected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, at the end of any 
count, no candidate can be declared elected, the returning officer shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  exclude from the poll the 
candidate who up to that stage has been credited with the lowest value;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  examine all the ballot papers in 
his parcels and sub-parcels, arrange the unexhausted papers in sub-parcels 
according to the next available preferences recorded thereon for the continuing 
candidates, count the number of papers in each such sub-parcel and credit it to 
the candidate for whom such preference is recorded, transfer the sub-parcel to 
that candidate, and make a separate sub-parcel of all the exhausted papers; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  see whether any of the 
continuing candidates has, after such transfer and credit, secured the quota.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If, when a candidate 
has to be excluded under clause (a) of sub-rule (3), two or more candidates have 
been credited with the same value and stand lowest on the poll, the candidate 
for whom the lowest number of original votes are recorded shall be excluded, and 
if this number also is the same in the case of two or more candidates, the 
returning officer shall decide by lot which of them shall be excluded.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Ascertainment of 
quota.—At any 
election where more than one seat is to be filled, every valid ballot paper 
shall be deemed to be of the value of 100, and the quota sufficient to secure 
the return of a candidate at the election shall be determined as follows:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  add the values credited to all 
the candidates under clause (c) of rule 74;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  divide the total by a number 
which exceeds by 1 the number of vacancies to be filled; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  add 1 to the quotient ignoring 
the remainder, if any, and the resulting number is the quota.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> General instruction.—In 
carrying out the provisions of rules 78 to 82, the returning officer shall 
disregard all fractions and ignore all preferences recorded for candidates 
already elected or excluded from the poll.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Candidates with quota 
elected.—If at 
the end of any count or at the end of the transfer of any parcel or sub-parcel 
of an excluded candidate the value of ballot papers credited to a candidate is 
equal to, or greater than the quota, that candidate shall be declared elected.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Transfer of surplus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If at the end of any count the value of the ballot papers credited to a 
candidate is greater than the quota, the surplus shall be transferred, in 
accordance with the provisions of this rule, to the continuing candidates 
indicated on the ballot papers of that candidates as being next in order of the 
elector’s preference.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If more than one 
candidate have a surplus, the largest surplus shall be dealt with first and the 
others in order of magnitude:
 
Provided that every 
surplus arising on the first count shall be dealt with before those arising on 
the second count and so on.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where there are more 
surpluses, than one to distribute and two or more surpluses are equal, regard 
shall be had to the original votes of each candidate and the candidate for whom 
most original votes are recorded shall have his surplus first distributed; and 
if the values of their original votes are equal, the returning officer shall 
decide by lot which candidate shall have his surplus first distributed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) If the surplus of 
any candidate to be transferred arises from original votes only, the returning 
officer shall examine all the papers in the parcel belonging to that candidate, 
divide the unexhausted papers into sub-parcels according to the next preferences 
recorded thereon and make a separate sub-parcel of the exhausted papers.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> He shall ascertain the 
value of the papers in each sub-parcel and of all the unexhausted papers.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> If the value of the 
unexhausted papers is equal to or less than the surplus, he shall transfer all 
the unexhausted papers at the value at which they were received by the candidate 
whose surplus is being transferred.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> If the value of the 
unexhausted papers is greater than the surplus, he shall transfer the 
sub-parcels of unexhausted papers and the value at which each paper shall be 
transferred shall be ascertained by dividing the surplus by the total number of 
unexhausted papers.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If the surplus of any 
candidate to be transferred arises from transferred as well as original votes, 
the returning officer shall re-examine all the papers in the sub-parcel last 
transferred to the candidate, divide the unexhausted papers into sub-parcels 
according to the next preferences recorded thereon, and then deal with the 
sub-parcels in the same manner as is provided in the case of sub-parcels 
referred to in sub-rule (4).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The papers transferred 
to each candidate shall be added in the form of a sub-parcel to the papers 
already belonging to such candidate.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All papers in the 
parcel or sub-parcel of an elected candidate not transferred under this rule 
shall be set apart as finally dealt with.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Exclusion of 
candidates lowest on the poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If after all surplus have been transferred as hereinbefore provided, the number 
of candidates elected is less than the required number, the returning officer 
shall exclude from the poll the candidate lowest on the poll and shall 
distribute his unexhausted papers among the continuing candidates according to 
the next preferences recorded thereon; and any exhausted papers shall be set 
apart as finally dealt with.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The papers containing 
original votes of an excluded candidate shall first be transferred, the transfer 
value of each paper being one hundred.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The papers containing 
transferred votes of an excluded candidate shall then be transferred in the 
order of the transfers in which, and at the value at which, he obtained them.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Each of such transfers 
shall be deemed to be a separate transfer but not a separate count.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, as a result of the 
transfer of papers, the value of votes obtained by the candidate is equal to or 
greater than the quota, the count then proceeding shall be completed but no 
further papers shall be transferred to him.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The process directed 
by this rule shall be repeated on the successive exclusions one after another of 
the candidates lowest on the poll until such vacancy is filled either by the 
election of a candidate with the quota or as hereinafter provided.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If at any time it 
becomes necessary to exclude a candidate and two or more candidates have the 
same value of votes and are the lowest on the poll, regard shall be had to the 
original votes of each candidate and the candidate for whom fewest original 
votes are recorded shall be excluded; and if the values of their original votes 
are equal the candidates with the smallest value at the earliest count at which 
these candidates had unequal values shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If two or more 
candidates are lowest on the poll and each has the same value of votes at all 
counts the returning officer shall decide by lot which candidate shall be 
excluded.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Filling the last 
vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When at the end of any count the number of continuing candidates is reduced to 
the number of vacancies remaining unfilled, the continuing candidates shall be 
declared elected.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When at the end of any 
count only one vacancy remains unfilled and the value of the papers of some one 
candidate exceeds the total value of the papers of all the other continuing 
candidates together with any surplus not transferred, that candidate shall be 
declared elected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When at the end of any 
count only one vacancy remains unfilled and there are only two continuing 
candidates and each of them has the same value of votes and no surplus remains 
capable of transfer, the returning officer shall decide by lot which of them 
shall be excluded; and after excluding him in the manner aforesaid, declare the 
other candidate to be elected.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Provision for 
re-counts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any candidate or, in his absence, his election agent or counting agent may, at 
any time during the counting of the votes either before the commencement or 
after the completion of any transfer of votes (whether surplus or otherwise) 
request the returning officer to re-examine and re-count the papers of all or 
any candidates (not being papers set aside at any previous transfer as finally 
dealt with), and the returning officer shall forthwith re-examine and re-count 
the same accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
may in his discretion re-count the votes either once or more than once in any 
case in which he is not satisfied as to the accuracy of any previous count:
 
Provided that noting in 
this sub-rule shall make it obligatory on the returning officer to re-count the 
same votes more than once.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Illustration of the 
procedure as to the counting of votes under rules 76 to 81.—An 
illustration of the procedure as to the counting of votes in accordance with the 
provisions of 

1[rules 76 to 81] 
is given in the Schedule to these rules.
 
 



</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> 

1[Declaration of 
result and return by returning officers.—
<section><number>1</number> Upon the completion of 
counting, the returning officer shall, subject to the provisions of sub-rule (3) 
of rule 81,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  declare the result under section 
66 in Form 23 or Form 23A as may be appropriate, and send signed copies thereof 
to the appropriate authority, the Election Commission and the chief electoral 
officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  prepare and certify a return of 
the election in Form 23B and after reporting the result of the election under 
section 67, send signed copies of the said Form to the Election Commission and 
the chief electoral officer; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  permit any candidate or his 
election agent or counting agent to take a copy of, or extract from, such return 
in Form 23B.]
 

2[(2) The returning 
officer shall thereafter—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number>  place the valid ballot papers in 
one packet and the rejected ballot papers in another;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  seal with the seals of the 
returning officer and of such of the candidates, their election agents or 
counting agents as may desire to affix their seals, each of the packets referred 
to in clause (a) and the packet containing the declarations by electors and 
attestations of their signatures; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  record on each of the sealed 
packets the description of its contents and the date of election:]
 

3[Provided that 
where such counting relates to an election to fill a seat or seats in the 
Council of States, the returning officer shall, before sealing the packets under 
clause (b), allow the authorised agent of a political party to verify as to whom 
the electors being members of that political party have cast their votes.]
 

4[***]
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Grant of certificate 
of election to returned candidate.—As 
soon as may be after a candidate has been declared to be elected the returning 
officer shall grant to such candidate a certificate of election in Form 24 and 
obtain from the candidate an acknowledgment of its receipt duly signed by him 
and immediately send the acknowledgment by registered post to the Secretary of 
the Council of States or, as the case may be, the Secretary of the Legislative 
Council.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>85A</number> Definitions.—In 
this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “cable television network” and 
“cable operator” have the meanings respectively assigned to them in clause (b) 
of Explanation to section 39A;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “electronic media” has the 
meaning assigned to it in clause (a) of Explanation to section 39A;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “political party” has the 
meaning assigned to it in clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 2;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “recognized political party” has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) 
Order, 1968.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>85B</number> Form of contributions 
report.—The 
report for a financial year under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 29C shall be 
submitted in Form 24A by the treasurer of a political party or any other person 
authorised by the political party in this behalf, before the due date for 
furnishing a return of its income of that financial year under section 139 of 
the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), to the Election Commission.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>85C</number> Allocation of 
equitable sharing of time on electronic media.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Election Commission shall, for the purposes of allocating equitable sharing 
of time on the cable television network and other electronic media under 
sub-section (1) of section 39A, categorise the cable television networks and 
electronic media into the two separate categories that is to say one category 
which is owned or controlled or financed wholly or substantially by funds 
provided to them by the Central Government and the other which is not owned or 
controlled or financed wholly or substantially by funds provided to them by the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For allocating 
equitable sharing of time on the cable television network and other electronic 
media owned or controlled or financed wholly or substantially by funds provided 
to them by the Central Government referred to in sub-rule (1), the Election 
Commission shall determine, in consultation with the Ministry of the Government 
of India dealing with the concerned subject, the maximum time period available 
on such cable television network and other electronic media and allocate such 
time period proportionately among the recognized political parties contesting 
the election on the basis of their past performances for the purposes of 
displaying or propagating any election matter or to address public in connection 
with the election under sub-section (1) of section 39A.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purposes of 
this rule, “past performance of a recognized political party” shall be 
calculated,—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  in relation to the election to 
fill a seat or seats in the House of the people, on the basis of the percentage 
of votes cast in the last preceding general election in favour of that 
recognized political party with reference to the total votes cast in that 
general election, to fill the seats in that House;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in relation to the election to 
fill a seat or seats in the Legislative Assembly of a State (except the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir), on the basis of the percentage of the votes cast in the last 
preceding general election in favour of that recognized political party with 
reference to the total votes cast in that general election, to fill the seats in 
that Assembly.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>85D</number> Supply of material by 
the Government.—The 
Central Government shall, at the time of any general election to be held for the 
purposes of constituting the House of the People or the Legislative Assembly of 
a State provide to the Election Commission such number of copies of electoral 
roll, as finally published under the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 
of 1950), as the Election Commission may require for supplying the same free of 
cost to the candidate of recognized political parties through such officers as 
may be specified by the Election Commission and such officer shall act in 
accordance with such general or special directions as may be issued by the 
Election Commission in this behalf.]
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Particulars of account 
of election expenses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The account of election expenses to be kept by a candidate or his election agent 
under section 77 shall contain the following particulars in respect of each item 
of expenditure from day to day, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the date on which the 
expenditure was incurred or authorised;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the nature of the expenditure 
(as for example, travelling, postage or printing and the like);
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the amount of the expenditure—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  the amount paid;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  the amount outstanding;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the date of payment; 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the name and address of the 
payee;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  the serial number of vouchers, 
in case of amount paid;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  the serial number of bills if 
any, in case of amount outstanding;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  the name and address of the 
person to whom the amount outstanding is payable.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A voucher shall be 
obtained for every item of expenditure unless from the nature of the case, such 
as postage, travel by rail and the like, it is not practicable to obtain a 
voucher.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All vouchers shall be 
lodged along with the account of election expenses, arranged according to the 
date of payment and serially numbered by the candidate or his election agent and 
such serial numbers shall be entered in the account under item (f) of sub-rule 
(1).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall not be 
necessary to give the particulars mentioned in item (e) of sub-rule (1) in 
regard to items of expenditure for which vouchers have not been obtained under 
sub-rule (2).
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>87</number> Notice by 

1[district election 
officer] for inspection of accounts.—The


1[district election 
officer] shall, within two days from the date on which the account of election 
expenses has been lodged by a candidate under section 78, cause a notice to be 
affixed to his notice board, specifying—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the date on which the account 
has been lodged;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the name of the candidate; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the time and place at which such 
account can be inspected.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Inspection of account 
and the obtaining of copies thereof.—Any 
person shall on payment of a fee of one rupee be entitled to inspect any such 
account and on payment of such fee as may be fixed by the Election Commission in 
this behalf be entitled to obtain attested copies of such account or of any part 
thereof.
 


</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>89</number> Report by the 

1[district election 
officer] as to the lodging of the account of election expenses and the decision 
of the Election Commission thereon.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as may be after the expiration of the time specified in section 78 for 
the lodging of the accounts of election expenses at any election, the 

1[district election 
officer] shall report to the Election Commission— 
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the name of each contesting 
candidate;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  whether such candidate has 
lodged his account of election expenses and if so, the date on which such 
account has been lodged; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  whether in his opinion such 
account has been lodged within the time and in the manner required by the Act 
and these rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 

2[district election 
officer] is of the opinion that the account of election expenses of any 
candidate has not been lodged in the manner required by the Act and these rules, 
he shall with every such report forward to the Election Commission the account 
of election expenses of that candidate and the vouchers lodged along with it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Immediately after the 
submission of the report referred to in sub-rule (1) the 

2[district election 
officer] shall publish a copy thereof by affixing the same to his notice board.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> As soon as may be 
after the receipt of the report referred to in sub-rule (1) the Election 
Commission shall consider the same and decide whether any contesting candidate 
has failed to lodge the account of election expenses within the time and in the 
manner required by the Act and these rules.
 

2[(5) Where the 
Election Commission decides that a contesting candidate has failed to lodge his 
account of election expenses within the time and in the manner required by the 
Act and these rules it shall by notice in writing call upon the candidate to 
show cause why he should not be disqualified under section 10A for the failure.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any contesting 
candidate who has been called upon to show cause under sub-rule (5) may within 
twenty days of the receipt of such notice submit in respect of the matter a 
representation in writing to the Election Commission, and shall at the same time 
send to the district election officer a copy of his representation together with 
a complete account of his election expenses if he had not already furnished such 
an account.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The district election 
officer shall, within five days of the receipt thereof, forward to the Election 
Commission the copy of the representation and the account (if any) with such 
comments as he wishes to make thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If, after considering 
the representation submitted by the candidate and the comments made by the 
district election officer and after such inquiry as it thinks fit, the Election 
Commission is satisfied that the candidate has no good reason or justification 
for the failure to lodge his account, it shall declare him to be disqualified 
under section 10A for a period of three years from the date of the order, and 
cause the order to be published in the Official Gazette.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>90</number> Maximum 
election expenses.—The total of the expenditure of which account is to be 
kept under section 77 and which is incurred or authorized in connection with an 
election in a State or 
Union territory mentioned 
in column 1 of the Table below shall not exceed—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  in any one parliamentary 
constituency of that State or Union territory, the amount specified in the 
corresponding column 2 of the said Table; and 
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in any one assembly 
constituency, if any, of that State or Union territory, the amount specified in 
the corresponding column 3 of the said Table—
 

2[Table
 
 
Name 
  of State or 
Union 
  territory                                            Maximum limit of election
 
 

                                                                                                    
  expenses in any one
 

                                                                                  
Parliamentary                  Assembly 
 

                                                                                   
constituency                constituency
 
 

             
  1                                                                                     
  2                                  3
 <subsection>
 
<number>I</number>
   States                                                                            
Rs.                               Rs.
 <subsubsection>
     <number>1</number>  
Andhra Pradesh....................................                     
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>2</number>  
Arunachal Pradesh...............................                      
17,00,000                      6,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>3</number> 

Assam.....................................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>4</number> 

Bihar.......................................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>5</number> 

Goa.........................................................                   
14,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>6</number> 

Gujarat....................................................                  
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>7</number>  
Haryana..................................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>8</number>  
Himachal Pradesh................................                      
25,00,000                      7,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>9</number> 

Jammu and Kashmir............................                       
25,00,000                                 —
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>10</number>  
Karnataka...............................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>11</number>  
Kerala.....................................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>12</number>  
Madhya Pradesh..................................                      
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>13</number> 

Maharashtra..........................................                    
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>14</number>  
Manipur.................................................                     
22,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>15</number>  
Meghalaya.............................................                    
22,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>16</number>  
Mizoram.................................................                    
20,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>17</number>  
Nagaland................................................                   
25,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>18</number>  
Orissa......................................................                  
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>19</number> 

Punjab....................................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>20</number>  
Rajasthan................................................                  
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>21</number> 

Sikkim....................................................                    
17,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>22</number>  
Tamil Nadu............................................                     
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>23</number>  
Tripura....................................................                   
25,00,000                      5,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>24</number>  
Uttar Pradesh........................................                    
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>25</number>  
West 
Bengal...........................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


<number>26</number> 
Chhattisgarh..........................................                    
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>27</number>  
Uttaranchal.............................................                   
25,00,000                      7,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>28</number>  
Jharkhand...............................................                   
25,00,000                    10,00,000
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>II</number>  

Union


Territories
 <subsubsection>
     <number>1</number>  
Andaman and 
Nicobar 
Islands..........                         
17,00,000                                 —
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>2</number> 

Chandigarh............................................                    
14,00,000                                 —
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>3</number>  
Dadra and Nagar Haveli....................                         
10,00,000                                 —
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>4</number> 

Daman 
and Diu....................................                      
10,00,000                                 —
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>5</number> 

Delhi.......................................................                   
25,00,000                      9,00,000
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>6</number> 

Lakshadweep........................................                    
10,00,000                                 —
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
  <number>7</number>  

  Pondicherry............................................                    
  20,00,000                     5,00,000]
 
 




 

 



 





































 


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>91</number> Resignation of seats 
in case of election to more seats than one in a House.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The time within which a person may resign all but one of the seats in either 
House of Parliament or in the House or either House of the Legislature of a 
State, to which he has been elected shall be—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  fourteen days from the date of 
his election under section 67A; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  where the dates of his election 
are different in respect of different seats, fourteen days from the last of 
those dates.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Such resignation shall 
be addressed—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  to the Speaker or the Chairman 
of the House concerned; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  whether the office of the 
Speaker or Chairman is for the time being vacant or is, or is deemed to be, in 
abeyance, to the Deputy Speaker or the Deputy Chairman of the House concerned; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  where the post of the Deputy 
Speaker or Deputy Chairman is also for the time being vacant or is, deemed to 
be, in abeyance, to the Election Commission.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the resignation 
has been addressed to the Election Commission under sub-rule (2) the Election 
Commission shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the resignation, send a 
copy thereof to the Secretary of the House concerned.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>92</number> Custody of ballot 
boxes and papers relating to election.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All ballot boxes used at an election shall be kept in such custody as the chief 
electoral officer may direct.
 

1[(1A) All voting 
machines used at an election shall be kept in the custody of the concerned 
district election officer.]
 

2[(2) The district 
election officer shall keep in safe custody—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the packets of unused ballot 
papers with counterfoils attached thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the packets of used ballot 
papers whether valid, tendered or rejected;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the packets of the counterfoils 
of used ballot papers;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the packets of the marked copy 
of the electoral roll or, as the case may be, the list maintained under 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 152;
 
 

1[(dd)  the packets containing 
registers of voters in Form 17A;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the packets of the declarations 
by electors and the attestation of their signatures; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  all other papers relating to 
the election:
 
Provided that in the case 
of an election in an assembly constituency or a parliamentary constituency or a 
council constituency which extends over more districts than one, the said papers 
shall be kept in the custody of such one of the district election officers 
having jurisdiction over the constituency as the Election Commission may direct:
 
Provided further that in 
the case of an election by assembly members the said papers shall be kept in the 
custody of the returning officer.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>93</number> Production 
and inspection of election papers.—
<section><number>1</number> While in the custody of the district 
election officer or, as the case may be, the returning officer—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the packets of unused ballot 
papers with counterfoils attached thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the packets of used ballot 
papers whether valid, tendered or rejected;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the packets of the counterfoils 
of used ballot papers;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the packets of the marked copy 
of the electoral roll or, as the case may be, the list maintained under 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 152; and
 
 

2[(dd)  the packets containing 
registers of voters in Form 17A;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the packets of the declarations 
by electors and the attestation of their signatures;
 
shall not be opened and their contents shall 
not be inspected by, or produced before, any person or authority except under 
the order of a competent court.
 

2[(1A) The control 
units sealed under the provisions of rule 57C and kept in the custody of the 
district election officer shall not be opened and shall not be inspected by, or 
produced before, any person or authority except under the orders of a competent 
court.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to such 
conditions and to the payment of such fee as the Election Commission may 
direct,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  all other papers relating to the 
election shall be open to public inspection; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  copies thereof shall on 
application be furnished.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Copies of the returns 
by the returning officer forwarded under rule 64, or as the case may be, under 
clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 84 shall be furnished by the returning 
officer, district election officer, chief electoral officer or the Election 
Commission on payment of a fee of two rupees for each copy.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>94</number> Disposal of election 
papers.—Subject 
to any direction to the contrary given by the Election Commission or by a 
competent court or tribunal—
 
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>  the packets of unused ballot 
papers shall be retained for a period of six months and shall thereafter be 
destroyed in such manner as the Election Commission may direct;]
 
 

2[(aa)  the voting machines kept in 
the custody of the district election officer under sub-rule (1A) of rule 92 
shall be retained intact for such period as the Election Commission may direct 
and shall not be used at any subsequent election without the previous approval 
of the Election Commission;]
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the other packets referred to in 
sub-rule (1) of rule 93 shall be retained for a period of one year and shall 
thereafter destroyed:
 

3[Provided that 
packets containing the counterfoils of used ballot papers shall not be destroyed 
except with the previous approval of the Election Commission;]
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  all other papers relating to the 
election shall be retained for such period as the Election Commission may 
direct.
 
 





</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>94A</number> Form of 
affidavit to be filed with election petition.—The affidavit referred to in 
the proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 83 shall be sworn before a magistrate 
of the first class or a notary or a commissioner of oaths and shall be in Form 
25.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>95</number> Power of 
the Election Commission to issue directions.—Subject to the other provisions 
of these rules, the Election Commission may issue such directions as it may 
consider necessary to facilitate the proper use and operation of the voting 
machines.]
 
 



</article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>96</number> List of Members of 
State Assemblies and electoral colleges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The returning officer for an election by the members of the Legislative Assembly 
of a State, to fill a seat or seats in the Council of States or in the 
Legislative Council of a State, shall maintain a list of members of that 
Assembly with their addresses corrected up-to-date in such form as the Election 
Commission may direct.
 
Explanation.—In 
this sub-rule any reference to the members of the Legislative Assembly of a 
State shall, in relation to an election to the Council of States, be construed 
as a reference to the elected members of that Legislative Assembly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The returning officer 
for an election by the members of the electoral college of a Union territory to 
fill a seat or seats in the Council of States shall maintain a list of members 
of that electoral college with their addresses corrected up-to-date in such form 
as the Election Commission may direct.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>97</number> Number of votes 
sufficient to secure the return of a candidate in relation to return of 
forfeiture of deposits in certain cases.—For 
the purpose of the proviso to sub-section (4) of section 158—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  a candidate who is not elected 
shall be deemed to get,—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  if he is a continuing 
candidate, the votes obtained by him at the end of the final count, and
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  if he is a candidate 
excluded from the poll, the votes obtained by him at the end of the count 
immediately preceding his exclusion;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the quota referred to in rule 75 
or rule 76 shall be deemed to be the number of votes sufficient to secure the 
return of a candidate.
 


</section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>98</number> Manner of serving the 
order of requisition of premises, vehicles, etc.—An 
order of requisition under section 160 shall be served—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  where the person to whom such 
order is addressed is a corporation or firm in the manner provided for the 
service of summons in rule 2 of Order XXIX or rule 3 of Order XXX, as the case 
may be, in the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act V of 
1908); and 
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  where the person to whom such 
order is addressed is an individual—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  personally by delivering 
or tendering the order, or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  by registered post, or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  if the person cannot be 
found, by leaving an authentic copy of the order with any adult member of his 
family or by affixing such copy to some conspicuous part of the premises in 
which he is known to have last resided or carried on business or personally 
worked for gain.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 
 
 <article>
<number>99</number> Time for application 
for reference to arbitration under section 161.—The 
time within which any person interested who is aggrieved by the amount of 
compensation determined under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 168 or within which the 
owner of a vehicle, vessel or animal who is aggrieved by the amount of 
compensation determined under sub-section (2) of that section may make an 
application for referring the manner to arbitration shall be fourteen days from 
the date of determination of the amount of such compensation or where the amount 
of such compensation has been determined in the absence of the person interested 
or, as the case may be, the owner, fourteen days from the date on which the 
intimation of such determination is sent to that person or owner.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 

THE CONDUCT OF 
ELECTIONS RULES, 1961
 





 




1[Form 
1 
 


(See rule 3)
 




Notice of Election
 


Notice is hereby given 
that—
 


(1) an election is to be 
held of a member to the House of the People/..............Legislative 
Assembly/.............Legislative Council in 
the.....................Constituency;
 



or
 


(1) an election is to be 
held of a member(s) to the Council of States/..............Legislative 
Council/by the elected members of the.................. Legislative Assembly;
 


(2) nomination papers may 
be delivered by a candidate or by any of his proposers to the Returning Officer 
or to.................. Assistant Returning Officer, at .................... 
between 11A.M. and 3 P.M. on any day (other than public holiday) not later than 
the..................;
 


(3) forms of nomination 
paper may be obtained at the place and time aforesaid;
 


(4) the nomination papers 
will be taken up for scrutiny at ...................... on 
............................... at ...............;
 


(5) notice of withdrawal of 
candidature may be delivered either by a candidate or by any of his proposers or 
by his election agent who has been authorised in writing by the candidate to 
deliver it to either of the officers specified in paragraph (2) above at his 
office before 3 P.M. on the ....................................;
 


(6) in the event of the 
election being contested, the poll will be taken on.......................... 
between the hours of ............................. and 
....................................
 



Place..............................
 



Date...............................      Returning Officer]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by S.O. 558 (E), dated 9th 
August, 1996.
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




1[Form 
13D
 


[See rule 23 (1) 
(d)]
 




Instructions for the Guidance of Electors 
 



(To be used at an election to the House of the People or to the Legislative 
Assembly of a State)
 


Election to the 
*........................................from the.........................................................................
 


The persons whose names are 
printed on the ballot paper sent herewith are candidates at the above election. 
Record your vote by placing clearly a mark opposite the name of the candidate to 
whom you wish to give your vote. The mark should be so placed as to indicate 
clearly and beyond doubt to which candidate you are giving your vote. If the 
mark is so placed as to make it doubtful to which candidate you have given your 
vote, your vote will be invalid.
 


The number of members to be 
elected is one. Please remember that you have only one vote. Accordingly you 
should not vote for more than one candidate. If you do so, your ballot paper 
will be rejected.
 


Do not put your signature 
or write any word or mark any mark, sign or writing whatsoever on the ballot 
paper other than the mark required to record your vote.
 


After you have recorded 
your vote on the ballot paper, place the ballot paper in the smaller cover 
marked ‘A’ sent herewith. Close the cover and secure it by seal or otherwise.
 


(1) You may then sign the 
declaration in Form 13A also sent herewith in the presence of a stipendiary 
magistrate and obtain the attestation of your signature by such stipendiary 
magistrate.
 


(2) If you are a member of 
the armed forces of the Union or of an armed police force of a State but is 
serving outside that State, the attestation may be obtained by such officer as 
may be appointed in this behalf by the Commanding Officer of the Unit, ship or 
establishment in which you or your husband, as the case may be, are employed.
 


(3) If you are employed 
under the Government of India in a post outside India the attestation may be 
obtained by such officer as may be appointed in this behalf by the diplomatic or 
consular representative of India in country in which you are resident.
 


(4) If you hold an office 
like the office of the (i) President, (ii) Vice-President, (iii) Governors of 
States, (iv) Cabinet Ministers of the Union or of any State, (v) The Deputy 
Chairman and Members of the Planning Commission, (vi) The Minister of State of 
the Union or of any State, (vii) Deputy Minister of the Union of any State, 
(viii) The Speaker of the House of the People or of any State Legislative 
Assembly, (ix) The Chairman of any State Legislative Council, (x) Lieutenant 
Governors of Union Territories, (xi) The Deputy Speaker of the House of the 
People or of any State Legislative Assembly, (xii) The Deputy Chairman of the 
Council of States or of any State Legislative Council, (xiii) Parliamentary 
Secretaries of the Union or of any State, the attestation may be obtained by an 
officer not below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to the Government of the Union 
or the State, as the case may be.
 


(5) If you are on an 
election duty, attestation may be obtained by any gazetted officer or by the 
Presiding Officer of the polling station in which you are on election duty.
 


(6) If you are under 
preventive detention, the attestation may be obtained by Superintendent of the 
jail or the Commandant of the detention camp in which you are under detention.
 


In all the above cases you 
may take the declaration to the authorised officer and sign it in his presence 
after he has satisfied himself about your identity. The officer will attest your 
signature and return the declaration to you. You must not show your ballot paper 
to the attesting officer nor tell him how you have voted.
 


If you are unable to mark 
the ballot paper and sign the declaration yourself in the manner indicated above 
by reason of illiteracy, blindness or other infirmity, you are entitled to have 
your vote marked and declaration signed on your behalf by any of the authorised 
officer mentioned above. Such an officer will, at your request mark the ballot 
paper in your presence and in accordance with your wishes. He will also complete 
the necessary certificate in this behalf.
 


After your declaration has 
been signed and your signature has been attested, place the declaration in Form 
13A as also the smaller cover marked ‘A’ containing the ballot paper in the 
larger cover marked ‘B’. After closing the larger cover, send it to returning 
officer by post or by messenger. You have to give your full signature in the 
space provided on the cover marked ‘B’. No postage stamp need be affixed by you, 
if the cover is posted in India. If, however, you are an elector employed under 
the Government of India in a post outside India, you should return the cover to 
the returning officer concerned direct by air mail service after the requisite 
postage stamp is duly affixed thereon by the office in which you are serving 
except where it is sent by diplomatic bag.
 


You must ensure that the 
cover reaches the returning officer before** 
......................................... 
**on........................................
 


Please note that—
 


         (i)  if you fail 
to get your declaration attested or certified in the manner indicated above, 
your ballot paper will be rejected; and
 


        (ii)  if the cover 
reaches the returning officer 
after**................................................. on 
the**...................................... your vote will not be counted.
 


* Appropriate particulars 
of the election to be inserted here.
 


** (Here specify the hour 
and date fixed for the commencement of counting of votes).]
 




Form 13D
 


[See
rule 23 (1) (d)]
 




Instructions for the Guidance of Electors
 



(To be used at an election to the Council of States or to the Legislative 
Council of a State)
 


Election to the Council of 
States/.............................Legislative Council.
 


The persons whose names are 
printed on the ballot paper sent herewith are candidates at the above election. 
Record your vote by placing the figure 1 in the space opposite the name of the 
candidate to whom you want to vote. Place the figure 1 opposite the name of one 
candidate only *(although there are more members than one to be elected) You may 
indicate your relative preference for the other candidates by placing in the 
spaces opposite their names the figures 2, 3, 4 etc., in order of such 
preference. Do not place more than one figure opposite the name of any candidate 
and do not place the same figure opposite the names of more candidates than one.
 


The number of members to be 
elected is.....................................
 


After you have recorded 
your vote on the ballot paper, place the ballot paper in the smaller cover 
marked ‘A’ sent herewith. Close the cover and secure it by seal or otherwise.
 


You have then to sign the 
declaration in Form 13A also sent herewith in the presence of an officer 
competent to attest your signature. If you are under preventive detention the 
attestation of your signature on the declaration in Form 13A shall be obtained 
by the Superintendent of the jail or the Commandant of the detention camp in 
which you are under such detention. If you are not under preventive detention, 
the attestation may be obtained by a stipendiary magistrate to whom you are 
personally known or to whose satisfaction you have been identified, or in the 
case of an election to a Council Constituency by any of the following categories 
of officers who have been notified in this behalf by the Election Commission, 
namely:—
 



...................................................................................................................................................
 



...................................................................................................................................................
 


Take the declaration to any 
such officer and sign it in his presence after he has been satisfied about your 
identity. The officer will attest your signature and return the declaration to 
you. You must not show your ballot paper to the attesting officer nor tell him 
how you have voted.
 


If you are unable to mark 
the ballot paper and sign the declaration yourself in the manner indicated above 
by reason of illiteracy, blindness or other infirmity, you are entitled to have 
your vote marked and the declaration signed on your behalf by an officer 
competent to attest your signature. Such an officer will, at your request, mark 
the ballot paper in your presence and in accordance with your wishes. He will 
also complete the necessary certificate in this behalf.
 


After the declaration has 
been signed and your signature has been attested, place the declaration in Form 
13A as also the smaller cover marked ‘A’ containing the ballot paper in the 
larger cover marked ‘B’. After closing the larger cover, send it to the 
Returning Officer by registered post or by messenger.
 


You must ensure that the 
cover reaches the returning officer before** 
......................................... on 
the**................................
 


Please note that—
 


         (i)  if you fail 
to get your declaration attested or certified in the manner indicated above your 
ballot paper will be rejected; and
 


        (ii)  if the cover 
reaches the returning officer 
after**.............................................. on the 
......................................** your vote will not be counted.
 


Any ballot paper on which 
the figure 1 is not marked or on which the figure 1 is set opposite the name of 
more than one candidate, or is so placed as to render it doubtful to which 
candidate it is intended to apply, or on which the figure 1 and some other 
figures are set opposite the name of the same candidate or on which the same 
figure is set opposite the name of more candidates than one or on which the 
signature of the elector is not duly attested or the number of which does not 
agree with the number of the ballot paper entered on the cover in which it is 
placed, will be rejected.]
 


* To be deleted when only 
one member is to be elected.
 


** Here specify the hour 
and date fixed for the commencement of counting of votes.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by S.O. 961 (E), dated 29th 
December, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




1[Form 
13E
 


(See
rule 27F)
 




Instructions for Guidance of notified class of electors
 



(To be used at an election to the House of the People/State Legislative 
Assembly)
 


Election to the House of 
the People/Legislative Assembly of ............................. from the 
..............................
 


The persons whose names are 
printed on the ballot paper sent herewith are candidates at the above election. 
Record your vote by placing clearly a mark opposite the name of the candidate to 
whom you wish to give your vote. The mark should be so placed as to indicate 
clearly and beyond doubt to which candidate you are giving your vote. If the 
mark is so placed as to make it doubtful to which candidate you have given your 
vote, your vote will be invalid.
 


The number of members to be 
elected is one. Accordingly, you should not vote for more than one candidate, if 
you do so, your ballot paper will be rejected.
 


Do not put your signature 
or write any word or mark any mark, sign or writing whatsoever on the ballot 
paper other than the mark required to record your vote.
 


After you have recorded 
your vote on the ballot paper, place the ballot paper in the smaller cover 
marked ‘A’ sent herewith. Close the cover and secure it by seal or otherwise.

 


You may then sign the 
declaration in Form 13A which is sent herewith in the presence of the officer as 
defined in rule 27J of the Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961 and obtain the 
attestation of your signature by such authorised officer. Extracts of rule 27J 
of the Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961 are enclosed herewith.
 


If you are unable to mark 
the ballot paper and sign the declaration yourself in the manner indicated above 
by reason of illiteracy, blindness or other infirmity, you are entitled to have 
your vote marked and declaration signed on your behalf by any of the authorised 
officers as mentioned above. Such an officer will, at your request, mark the 
ballot paper in your presence and in accordance with your wishes. He will also 
complete the necessary certificate in this behalf.
 


After your declaration has 
been signed and your signature has been attested, place the declaration in Form 
13A as also the smaller cover marked ‘A’ containing the ballot paper in the 
larger cover marked ‘B’. After closing the larger cover, send it to the 
Returning Officer by post or by messenger. You have to give your full signature 
in the provided on the cover marked ‘B’. No postage stamp need be affixed by 
you, if the cover is posted in India. If, however, you are an elector employed 
under the Government of India on a post outside India, you should return the 
cover to the Returning Officer concerned direct by air mail service after the 
requisite postage stamp is duly affixed thereon by the office in which you are 
serving except where it is sent by diplomatic bag. You must ensure that the 
cover reaches the Returning Officer before .......................... (hour) on 
.................. (date).
 


Please note that—
 


         (i)  if you fail 
to get your declaration attested or certified in the manner indicated above, 
your ballot paper will be rejected; and
 


        (ii)  if the cover 
reaches the Returning Officer after.................(hour) on 
................................ (date) your vote will not be counted.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 321 (E), dated 1st May, 
1996 (w.e.f. 1-5-1996) and subs. by S.O. 628 (E), dated 4th August, 1999 (w.e.f. 
4-8-1999). Ed. In S.O. 628 (E), dated 4th August, 1999 in clause 5 it is stated 
that after Form 13D of the principal rules, the following form, i.e., 
Form 13E shall be inserted, whereas Form 13E has already been inserted by S.O. 
321 (E), dated 1st May, 1966, vide clause 5, hence Form 13E has been 
substituted.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




 



1[Form 
13F
 


[See
rule 27N (3)]
 


Serial 
No ...............
 




Appointment of proxy by classified service voter to give vote
 


I 
......................................................................(name of 
the classified service voter), aged about.............................. s/o, 
d/o, w/o ............................... r/o ................................, 
presently working as................................ and posted at 
................................, am entitled to appoint proxy under sub‑rule 
(2) of rule 27N of the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961. I hereby appoint 
..................................(name of the proxy), aged about 
................................ s/o, d/o, w/o ................................ 
r/o ............................... as my proxy to give vote on my behalf and in 
my name in .............................. Assembly constituency and/or 
................................ Parliamentary constituency of the State/Union 
territory of ................................ in which I am entitled to give 
vote under the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951) and the rules 
made thereunder.
 



.................................................................       
...................................................................
 



(Signature of proxy)                                  (Signature of classified 
service voter)
 


 
 


Serial 
number of his name                        Serial number of his name in the last
 


and part 
no. of electoral roll of the           part of electoral roll of the concerned
 



concerned constituency....................        
constituency...............................................
 



                                                                 Service 
Identity Card No. ....................
 



                                                                 Name of the 
Force to which he 
 



                                                                 
belongs........................................................
 


Note.—(1) 
The person to be appointed as proxy shall be an ordinary resident in the 
constituency concerned and of not less than eighteen years of age and shall not 
be a person disqualified for registration as an elector in an electoral roll 
under section 16 of the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950).
 


(2) The 
signature of the classified service voter and the proxy shall be made before a 
First Class Magistrate or Notary or the Commanding Officer of the Unit concerned 
who shall verify the signatures under his hand and seal. In case of First Class 
Magistrate or Notary verifying the signature, he shall personally check the 
service identity card of the classified service voter to authenticate veracity 
of the classified service voter.
 


(3) 
Score out the word (s) which are not applicable.
 


 
 



Receipt of Form 13F for the appointment of proxy by classified service voter
 


(To be 
handed over to the person depositing the said form)
 


Serial 
No. ....................
 


Received 
Form 13F of Shri/Smt./Kum 
.........................................................................
 



Date....................   
 



................................
 



Returning Officer
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 903 (E), dated 5th 
August, 2003 (w.e.f. 5-8-2003).
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 


 
 




Form 13G
 


[See
rule 27N (4)]
 


Serial 
No. ....................
 




Revocation of appointment of proxy or revocation of appointment of proxy and 
appointment of substitute proxy by classified service voter to give vote
 


I 
........................................ (name of the classified service voter) 
aged about.................... s/o, d/o, w/o .................... r/o 
.................... presently working as .................... and posted at 
.................... had appointed.................... (name of the proxy) aged 
about ......................... s/o, d/o, w/o ....................r/o 
.................... as my proxy to give vote on my behalf and in my name in 
.................... Assembly constituency and/or .................... 
Parliamentary constituency of the State/Union territory of ....................
 


2. I 
hereby revoke the appointment of my said proxy and do not wish to appoint any 
substitute proxy.
 


OR
 


Whereas 
such proxy has died I hereby revoke appointment of the said proxy and being 
entitled to appoint substitute proxy under sub‑rule (4) of rule 27N of the 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, hereby appoint 
........................................ (name of the substitute proxy) aged 
about ...................................................... s/o, d/o, w/o 
........................................ r/o 
........................................ as substitute proxy who shall hereafter 
give vote on my behalf and in my name in .................... Assembly 
constituency and/or .................... Parliamentary constituency of the 
State/Union territory of ..................................................... 
in which I am entitled to give vote under the Representation of the People Act, 
1951 (43 of 1951) and the rules made thereunder.
 



..............................................................      
...................................................................
 



(Signature of proxy)                                         (Signature of 
classified service voter)
 


 
 


Serial 
number of his name                               Serial number of his name in 
the last
 


and part 
no. of electoral roll of the                  part of electoral roll of the 
concerned
 



concerned constituency ....................              
constituency.............................................
 



                                                                        Service 
Identity Card No. .................... 
 



                                                                        Name of 
the Force to which he 
 



                                                                        belongs 
.....................................................
 


Note.—(1) 
The person to be appointed as proxy shall be an ordinary resident in the 
constituency concerned and of not less than eighteen years of age and shall not 
be a person disqualified for registration as an elector in an electoral roll 
under section 16 of the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950).
 


(2) The 
signature of the classified service voter and the proxy shall be made before a 
First Class Magistrate or Notary or the Commanding Officer of the Unit concerned 
who shall verify the signatures under his hand and seal. In case of First Class 
Magistrate or Notary verifying the signature, he shall personally check the 
service identity card of the classified service voter to authenticate veracity 
of the classified service voter.
 


(3) 
Score out the word (s) which are not applicable.
 



Receipt of Form 13G for revocation of appointment of proxy or revocation of 
appointment of proxy and appointment of substitute proxy by classified service 
voter to give vote.
 


(To be 
handed over to the person depositing the said form)
 


Serial 
No. ....................
 


Received 
Form 13G of Shri/Smt./Kum 
........................................r/o....................
 


Dated 
..................        (Signature and Seal)
 



                  Returning Officer.]
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




Form  17
 


[See 
rule 49 (3) (f)]
 




Tendered Ballot Paper
 


Election to 
the*..........................................from the 
.................................................constituency. Serial number of 
Ballot paper.......................................... Polling 
Station...................................
 


Name of 
elector.....................................................
 


Serial number of 
elector...........................................in Part 
number........................................ of the electoral roll.
 


Address of elector............................................................................................................................
 


Name of candidate in whose 
favour vote is tendered 
...............................................................
 



Date..............................
 


 
 


* Appropriate particulars 
of the election to be inserted here.
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




Form 18
 


[See
rule 52(2)]
 




Appointment of Counting Agents
 


Election to 
the...............................................from 
the........................................constituency.
 


To
 


The Returning Officer,
 


I, 
........................, * a candidate/the election agent 
of......................................who is a candidate at the above 
election, do hereby appoint the following persons as my counting agents to 
attend the counting of votes at 
....................................................
 


        Name of the 
counting agent        Address of the counting agent
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


etc.
 


 We agree to act as such 
counting agents Signature of *candidate/election agent.
 


1.
 


2.     
 


3.
 


etc.
 


 
 



Place....................................
 



Date.....................................                                                      
Signature of counting agents
 


 
 




Declaration of Counting Agents
 



(To be signed before the Returning Officer)
 


We hereby declare that at 
the above election we will not do anything forbidden by section 128† of the 
Representation of the People Act, 1951, which *we have read/has been read over 
to us.
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


etc.
 


 
 



Date...................................                                                        
Signature of counting agents
 


 
 


Signed before me.
 



Date..................................                                                                            
Returning Officer
 


* Strike off the 
inappropriate alternative.
 


†
Section 128 of the 
Representation of the People Act, 1951—
 


“128. Maintenance of 
secrecy of voting.—(1) Every officer, clerk, agent or other persons who 
performs any duty in connection with the recording or counting of votes at an 
election shall maintain and aid in maintaining, the secrecy of the voting and 
shall not (except for some purpose authorised by or under any law) communicate 
to any person information calculated to violate such secrecy.
 


(2) Any person who 
contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine or with 
both.”
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




Form 19
 


[See
rule 52 (4)]
 




Revocation of Appointment of Counting Agent
 



Election of the*.........................
 


 
 


To
 


The Returning Officer,
 


I, 
..........................., [the election agent of..........................] a 
candidate at the above election hereby revoke the appointment of 
...................... my/his counting agent.
 


 
 



Place..............................
 



Date...............................                                                           
Signature of person revoking.
 


 
 


* Here insert one of the 
following alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 


        (1)  House of the 
People from the ...............................constituency.
 


        (2)  Legislative 
Assembly from the ...........................constituency.
 


        (3)  Council of 
States by the elected members of the Legislative Assembly of 
....................... (State).
 


        (4)  Council of 
States by the members of the electoral colleges of ...................... (Union 
territory).
 


        (5)  Legislative 
Council by the members of the Legislative Assembly.
 


        (6)  Legislative 
Council from the ........................ constituency.
 


N.B.—Omit 
the words [ ] as necessary.
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




1[Form  
21
 


[See  rule 11 (1)]
 



(For use in General Election when seat is uncontested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under  

sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of  

the Representation of the People Act, 1951
 


Election to 
the†..........................
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of the 
Representation of the People Act, 1951, read with sub-rule (1) of rule 11 of the 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



................................(Name) .............................(Address) 
2[sponsored 
by......................... ..................... (name of the recognised/registered 
political party)] has been duly elected to fill the seat in that House from the 
above constituency.
 



Place...............................                                                          
Signature................................
 



Date................................                                                                             
Returning Officer]
 


* Score out, if 
inappropriate.
 


†Here insert one of the 
following alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 


        (1)  House of the 
People from the........................Parliamentary constituency in the 
State/Union territory of....................................................
 


        (2)  Legislative 
Assembly of the State/Union territory 
of............................................... from 
the......................................... Assembly constituency.
 


        (3)  Metropolitan 
Council of the Union territory of Delhi from the .......................... 
................................... Metropolitan Council constituency.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 4542, dated 20th 
December, 1968 (w.e.f. 1-1-1969).
 


   2.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




Form  21A
 


[See  rule 11 (1)]
 



(For use in Biennial Election when seat is uncontested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under  

sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of  

the Representation of the People Act, 1951
 


Election to 
the†..............................
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of the 
Representation of the People Act, 1951, read with sub-rule (1) of rule 11 of the 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



.................................(Name) 
............................................... (Address) 

1[Sponsored 
by.......... .......................... (name of the recognised/registered 
political party)]
 



..............................(Name) .......................... (Address) 

1[Sponsored by 
...................................... (name of the recognised/registered 
political party)] has been/have been duly elected to fill the seat(s) in that 
House of ................................ ** ...............................member(s) 
retiring on ....................... (date, month and year) on the expiration of 
their term of office.
 


 
 



Place.........................                                                                      
Signature.......................... 
 



Date.......................... 
                                                                                   
Returning Officer
 


 
 


* Score out, if 
inappropriate.
 


†Here insert one of the 
following alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 


        (1)  Council of 
States by the elected members of the Legislative Assembly of.......... 
............................ (State).
 


        (2)  Council of 
States by the members of the electoral college of............ 
........................................... (Union territory).
 


        (3)  Legislative 
Council of........................... (State) by the members of the Legislative 
Assembly.
 


        (4)  Legislative 
Council of............................... (State) from the 
................................ (Local Authorities’/Graduates’/Teachers’) 
constituency.
 


** Fill up the number of 
members retiring.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




Form  21B
 


[See  rule 11 (1)]
 



(For use in Election to fill a causal vacancy when seat is uncontested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under  

sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of  

the Representation of the People Act, 1951
 


Election to the 

†......................................
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in sub-section (2)*/sub-section (3)* of section 53 of the 
Representation of the People Act, 1951, read with sub-rule (1) of rule 11 of the 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



......................................(Name) 
...............................(Address) 

1[Sponsored 
by........................... (name of the recognised/registered political 
party)] has been/have been duly elected to fill the vacancy caused in that House 
by the—
 


* resignation 
of.................................................
 


* death 
of...........................................................
 


* election 
of....................................................... having been declared 
void
 


* seat 
of...................................................... *having become/*having 
been declared vacant.
 


 
 



Place........................                                                                        
Signature.........................
 



Date.........................                                                                                     
Returning Officer
 


 
 


*Score out, if 
inappropriate.
 


†Here insert one of the 
following alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 


        (1)  House of 
People from the ................................Parliamentary constituency in 
the State/Union territory of...................................
 


        (2)  Legislative 
Assembly of the State/Union territory of.................................. from 
the .........................Assembly constituency.
 


        (3)  Metropolitan 
Council of Delhi from the ..................Metropolitan Council constituency.
 


        (4)  Council of 
States by the elected members of the Legislative Assembly ................... 
(State).
 


        (5)  Council of 
States by the members of the electoral college 
of........................................... (Union territory).
 


        (6)  Legislative 
Council of ............................... (State) by the members of the 
Legislative Assembly.
 


        (7)  Legislative 
Council of ..................................... (State) from the 
................................. (Local Authorities’/Graduates’/Teachers’) 
constituency.
 





 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




Form  21C
 


(See  rule 64)
 



(For use in General Election when seat is contested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under section 66 of  

the Representation of the People Act, 1951
 


 


*Election to the House of 
  the People from the ......................................... Parliamentary 
  constituency in .................................. (State/Union territory).
 


*Election to the 
  Legislative Assembly of ................................ (State/Union 
  territory) from .........................Assembly constituency.
 


* Election to the 
Metropolitan Council of Delhi from ........................ Metropolitan Council 
constituency.
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in section 66 of the Representation of the People Act, 
1951, read with rule 64 of the Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



..............................(Name) ..............................(Address)


1[Sponsored 
by........................... (name of the recognised/registered political 
party)] has been duly elected to fill the seat in that House from the above 
constituency.
 



Place....................                                                                                 
Signature....................
 



Date....................                                                                                          
Returning Officer
 


* Score out, if 
inappropriate.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




Form  21D
 


(See  rule 64)
 



(For use in Election to fill a casual vacancy when seat is contested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under section 66 of  

the Representation of the People Act, 1951
 


 


*Election to the House of 
  the People from the ......................................... Parliamentary 
  constituency in .................................. (State/Union territory).
 


*Election to the 
  Legislative Assembly of ................................ (State/Union 
  territory) from .........................Assembly constituency.
 


*Election to the 
Metropolitan Council of Delhi from ........................ Metropolitan Council 
constituency.
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in section 66 of the Representation of the People Act, 
1951, read with rule 64 of the Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



........................(Name) .........................(Address) 

1[Sponsored 
by........................ (name of the recognised/registered political party)] 
has been duly elected to fill the vacancy caused in that House by the—
 


* resignation 
of..............................................
 


* death 
of.........................................................
 


* election 
of....................................................... having been declared 
void
 


* seat 
of...................................................... having become/having 
been declared vacant.
 



Place....................                                                                                 
Signature....................
 



Date....................                                                                                          
Returning Officer
 


*Score out, if 
inappropriate.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




1[Form  
21E]
 


(See  rule 64)
 




Return of Election
 


Election to the 
............................................from the 
..........................................constituency.
 


Return of Election
 


 


 
 



2[Serial No.      
Name of candidate       Party affiliation         Number of votes polled]
 


 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 



3[Total number of 
electors.............................................................................................]
 


Total number of valid votes 
polled...........................................................................................
 


Total number of rejected 
votes..................................................................................................
 


Total number of tendered 
votes................................................................................................
 


I declare that—
 



........................................................................................................................................ 
(Name) of 
.............................................................................................. 
(Address) has been duly elected to fill the seat.
 


 
 



Place..........................
 



Date..........................                                                                                    
Returning Officer
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Renumbered by S.O. 4542, dated 20th 
December, 1968 (w.e.f. 1-1-1969).
 


   2.  Subs. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


   3.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 


 
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 




 



1[Form 22A
 


[See rule 39AA(2)]
 


Appointment letter
 


Election of the.............................
 


I............................. 
*President/General Secretary of.............................Party do hereby 
appoint the following persons as the authorised agents of the Party to verify 
under rule *39AA/rule 42/rule 42A/rule 84 as to whom the electors who are the 
members of the said political party have cast their votes. Photographs of the 
aforesaid authorised agents are pasted hereunder and is attested under my hand 
and seal.
 


Name of the authorised agents     Address of 
the authorised agents
 


1.............................
 



2.............................                                                                      
Signature of* President
 


      General Secretary of the Party)
 


 
 



                                                                                          
Seal
 


We agree to act as such authorized 
agents          Signature of the authorized agents
 


1.............................
 


2.............................
 


 
 


Space for the photographs
 


 
 


 
 


*Strike off the inappropriate alternative.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 272 (E), dated 27th 
February, 2004 (w.e.f. 27-2-2004).
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 





 




1[Form 
23A
 


[See rule 84 (1) 
(a)]
 



(For use in Election to fill a casual vacancy when seat is contested)
 




Declaration of the result of Election under section 66 of  the Representation of 
the People Act, 1951
 


Election to the†............................
 


In pursuance of the 
provisions contained in section 66 of the Representation of the People Act, 
1951, read with clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 84 of the Conduct of 
Elections Rules, 1961, I declare that—
 



....................................(Name)...............................(Address)


1[sponsored by 
.......................... (name of the recognised/registered political party)] 
has been duly elected to fill the vacancy caused in that House by the 

 


* resignation 
of...................................................
 


* death 
of.............................................................
 


* election 
of......................................................... having been declared 
void
 


* seat 
of...................................................... *having become/*having 
been declared vacant.
 


 
 



Place.........................                                                                       
Signature.........................
 



Date.........................                                                                                     
Returning Officer
 



†Here insert one of 
the following alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 


        (1)  Council of 
States by the elected members of the Legislative Assembly of 
............................ (State).
 


        (2)  Council of 
States by the members of the electoral college of .............................. 
(Union territory).
 


        (3)  Legislative 
Council of ........................... (State) by the members of the Legislative 
Assembly.
 


        (4)  Legislative 
Council of ...................................... (State) from 
the.................... (Local Authorities’/Graduates’/Teachers’) constituency.
 


 
 


*Score out, if 
inappropriate.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th 
August, 1984.
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 




 



1[Form 24A
 


(See rule 85B)
 


[This Form should be filed with the Election 
Commission before the due date for furnishing a return of the political party’s 
income of the concerned financial year under section 139 of the Income-tax Act, 
1961 (43 of 1961) and a certificate to this effect should be attached with the 
income-tax return to claim exemption under the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 
1961).]
 


1. Name of political party:
 


2. Status of the political party: (Recognised/unrecognized)
 


3. Address of the headquarters of the 
political party:
 


4. Date of registration of political party 
with Election Commission:
 


5. Permanent Account Number (PAN) and 
Income-tax Ward/Circle where return of the political party is 
filed:.............................
 


6. Details of the 
contributions received, in excess of rupees twenty thousand, during the 
Financial Year 20....—20....
 


 


  Sl.      Name and 
  complete     PAN (if any)       Amount of             Mode of              
  Remarks
 


  No.         address of 
the         and Income-     contribution        contribution
 


                  
contributing             Tax Ward/            (Rs.)         *(cheque/demand
 


              
person/company             Circle                                      
draft/cash)
 


 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


* In case of payment by cheque/demand draft, 
indicate name of the bank and branch of the bank on which the cheque/demand 
draft has been drawn.
 


7. In case the contributor is a company, 
whether the conditions laid down under section 293A of the Companies Act, 1956 
(1 of 1956) have been complied with (A copy of the certificate to this effect 
obtained from the company should be attached).
 


Verification
 


I,.............................(full name in 
Block letters), son/daughter of............................. solemnly declare 
that to the best of my knowledge and belief, the information given in this Form 
is correct, complete and truly stated. I further declare that I am verifying 
this Form in my capacity as.............................on behalf of the 
political party above named and I am also competent to do so.
 


 
 


(Signature and name of the Treasurer/Authorised 
person)
 


Date.............................
 


Place...........................]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 1283 (E), dated 10th 
November, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-11-2003).
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




1[Form 
25
 


(See rule 94A)

 




Affidavit
 


I, 
............................, the petitioner in the accompanying election 
petition calling in question the election of 
Shri/Shrimati......................... (respondent No........................ in 
the said petition) make solemn affirmation/oath and say—
 


(a) that the statements 
made in paragraphs ................. of the accompanying election petition about 
the commission of the corrupt practice of*....................and the 
particulars of such corrupt practice mentioned in paragraphs 
......................... of the same petition and in paragraphs 
............................ of the Schedule annexed thereto are true to my 
knowledge;
 


(b) that the statements 
made in paragraphs ................ of the said petition about the commission of 
the corrupt practice of*................ and the particulars of such corrupt 
practice given in paragraphs ........................ of the said petition and 
in paragraphs ............... of the Schedule annexed thereto are true to my 
information;
 


(c)
 


(d)
 


etc.
 


Signature of deponent
 


Solemnly affirmed/sworn by 
Shri/Shrimati.................... at ..........this....................... day 
of................ 20............
 


Before me, Magistrate of 
the first class/ Notary/Commissioner of Oaths.]
 


* Here specify the name of 
the corrupt practice.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Added by S.O. 597 (E), dated 27th 
February, 1962.
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Conduct 
of Elections Rules, 1961
 


 
 




1[form 
26
 


(See 
rule 4A)
 




Affidavit to be furnished by the candidate before the returning officer for 
election to .................... (name of the House) from .................... 
constituency (name of the constituency)
 


I, ............, 
son/daughter/wife of.................. aged about ............. years, resident 
of ........... candidate at the above election, do hereby solemnly affirm/state 
on oath as under:—
 


1. I am/am not accused of 
any offence(s) punishable with imprisonment for two years or more in a pending 
case(s) in which a charge(s) has/have been framed by the court(s) of competent 
jurisdiction.
 


If the deponent is accused 
of any such offence(s) he shall furnish the following information:
 


   (i) Case/First 
information report No./Nos. ...............................
 


  (ii) Police station(s).................... 
District(s)........................ State(s)........................
 


(iii) Section(s) of the 
concerned Act(s) and short description of the offence(s) for which the candidate 
has been charged..............................................
 


(iv)  Court(s) which framed 
the charge(s).............................
 


  (v)  Date(s) on which the 
charge(s) was/were framed............................................
 


(vi)  Whether all or any of 
the proceeding(s) have been stayed by any court(s) of competent jurisdiction......................................................................................................
 


2. I have been/have not 
been convicted of an offence(s) [other than any offence(s) referred to in 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), or covered in sub-section (3), of section 8 
of the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951)] and sentenced to 
imprisonment for one year or more.
 


If the deponent is 
convicted and punished as aforesaid, he shall furnish the following information:
 


   (i) Case/First 
information report No./Nos. ...............................
 


  (ii)  Court(s) which 
punished......................................................
 


(iii) Police station(s).................... 
District(s)........................ State(s)........................
 


(iv) Section(s) of the 
concerned Act(s) and short description of the offence(s) for which the candidate 
has ever been charged..............................................
 


  (v)  Date(s) on which the 
sentence(s) was/were pronounced..........................................
 


(vi)  Whether the 
sentence(s) has/have been stayed by any court(s) of competent jurisdiction......................................................................................................
 



Place.............................
 



Date..............................           Signature of deponent
 




Verification
 


I, the above-named 
deponent, do hereby verify and declare that the contents of the affidavit are 
true and correct to the best of my knowledge and belief, no part of it is false 
and nothing material has been concealed therein.
 


Verified at 
.................... this................ day of............ 20....
 


Signature of deponent
 


Note.—The 
columns in this Form which are not applicable to the deponent may be struck 
off.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 935 (E), dated 3rd 
September, 2002 (w.e.f. 3-9-2002).
 

 
</form><form>
 

The 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961
 

 
 

Form 
5
 

[See 
rule 9 (1)]
 

Notice 
of withdrawal of Candidature
 

Election to 
the*........................
 

The Returning Officer,
 

I, 
...................................., a 1[candidate validly nominated] at 
the above election do hereby give notice that I withdraw my 
candidature.
 

Place..............................
 

Date..............................                                       
Signature of 2[validly nominated 
candidate]
 

This notice was delivered to me at 
my office at ................... (hour) on .................... (date) by 
....................... (name). the†.............................
 

Date............................                                                                              
Returning Officer
 

Receipt for 
Notice of Withdrawal
 

(To be handed 
over to the person delivering the notice)
 

The notice of withdrawal of 
candidature by ........................... a1[validly nominated candidate] at 
the election to the*...................... was delivered to me by 
the†......................... at my office at................. (hour) 
on............... (date).
 

Returning 
Officer
 

*Here insert one of the following 
alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 

        
(1)  House of the People from the .............................. 
constituency.
 

        
(2)  Legislative Assembly from the 
............................constituency.
 

        
(3)  Council of States by the elected members of the Legislative Assembly 
of ......................... (State).
 

        
(4)  Council of States by members of the electoral college of 
............................. (Union territory).
 

        
(5)  Legislative Council by the members of the Legislative 
Assembly.
 

        
(6)  Legislative Council from the ......................... 
constituency.
 

†Here insert one of the following 
alternatives as may be appropriate:—
 

        
(1)  Candidate.
 

        
(2)  Candidate’s proposer who has been authorised in writing by the 
candidate to deliver it.
 

        
(3)  Candidate’s election agent who has been authorised in writing by the 
candidate to deliver it.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th August, 1984.
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
Conduct of Elections Rules, 1961
 

 
 

Form 
6
 

[See 
rule 9 (2)]
 

Notice 
of Withdrawal of Candidatures
 

Election to 
the*.................
 

Notice is hereby given that 
following 1[validly nominated 
†candidate]/candidates at the above election withdraw †his candidature/their 
candidatures today.
 


 

 
 

    Name of 
1[validly nominated 
candidate]             
Address of 1[validly                  
Remarks
 


 

                                                                              
nominated candidate]
 

        
1.
 

        
2.
 

        
3.
 


 

        
etc.
 

Date..........................   
Returning Officer
 

* Appropriate particulars of the 
election to be inserted here.
 

†Strike off the inappropriate 
alternative.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
S.O. 565 (E), dated 4th August, 1984.
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>