<act><title>


the Performing Animals Rules, 19731</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Performing Animals Rules, 1973.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force in any State on such date as the State Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 
1960);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “performing animal” means any animal which is used at, or for the 
purpose of any entertainment to which the public are admitted through sale of 
tickets;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “prescribed authority” means the State Government or such other 
authority as the State Government may, by general or special order, specify in 
this behalf;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these rules.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for 
registration.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Every application by a person desirous of exhibiting or training any performing 
animal for registration under the Act shall be in the form and shall contain the 
particulars set out in the First Schedule;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Every such 
application shall be made to the prescribed authority within whose jurisdiction 
the applicant ordinarily resides and, if he has no fixed place of residence, the 
application shall be made to such authority as the Central Government may by 
order specify in this behalf.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Fee and 
registration.—Every 
application for registration shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees twenty-five 
which may be paid either in cash or in such other manner as may be specified by 
the prescribed authority.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Form or Certificate 
of Registration.—
<section><number>i</number> 
The certificate of registration to be issued by the prescribed authority shall 
be in the form set out in the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Every registration 
shall be given a serial number according to the order in which it is made, and 
the serial number shall be inserted in the certificate of registration issued to 
the applicant.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Register.—Every 
person to whom a certificate of registration is issued under these rules shall 
have his name entered in a register which shall be kept in the form set out in 
the Third Schedule.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Inspection of 
register.—The 
register kept under these rules shall be open to inspection during office hours 
on any working day on payment of a fee of two rupees and any person may take 
extract therefrom or may require the prescribed authority to issue to him a 
certified copy of any entry therein on payment of a fee of five rupees.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Application for 
variation of entries in register.—Every 
application under sub-section (5) of section 23 of the Act for the variation of 
any particulars entered in the register shall be in the form set out in the 
Fourth Schedule and when any particulars are varied the existing certificate of 
registration shall be cancelled and a new certificate issued to the applicant.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Issue of duplicate 
copies of certificates.—Any 
person whose name is registered under these rules may, on proof by him that the 
original certificate of registration has been lost or destroyed and on payment 
of a fee of rupees five, be given a duplicate copy of the certificate of 
registration which for the purposes of these rules shall have the same effects 
as the original certificate of registration.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Copies of 
certificates etc. to be sent to the Animal Welfare Board.—The 
prescribed authority shall cause a copy of every certificate of registration or 
duplicate thereof or a new certificate issued under these rules to be sent to 
the Animal Welfare Board established under the Act, as soon as may be after it 
is issued.
</article><form>
 




the Performing Animals Rules, 1973
 


 
 


FOURTH SCHEDULE
 


Form of Application for 
Variation of Particulars Entered in Register
 


Application to have the 
particulars entered in the register with respect to the applicant varied.
 


To
 


The Prescribed Authority,
 


Full name of applicant (in 
block letters).......................................................................
 


Number and date of 
certificate of 
registration.............................................................
 


I return herewith my 
certificate of registration under the Performing Animals Rules, 1973, and I 
hereby apply to have the particulars entered in the Register with respect to be 
varied, as follows’ and for the reasons given below :
 


I also request that my 
existing certificate may be cancelled and a new certificate of registration may 
be issued to me.
 



Signature......................................................
 



Address.........................................................
 


Note:
No fee is 
payable for the issue of a new certificate of registration.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>