<act><title>

THE 
    ARMS ACT, 1959</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Arms Act, 1959.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force 
    on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint.
 






 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions and interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    “acquisition” with its grammatical variations and 
    cognate expressions, includes hiring, borrowing, or accepting as a gift;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    “ammunition” means ammunition for any firearm, and 
    includes—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>   rockets, bombs, grenades, shells 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[and 
    other missiles],
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>   articles designed for torpedo service and submarine mining,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iii</number>  other articles containing, or designed or adapted to contain, 
    explosive, fulminating or fissionable material or noxious liquid, gas or 
    other such thing, whether capable of use with firearms or not,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iv</number> charges for firearms and accessories for such charges,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>v</number>  fuses and friction tubes,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>vi</number>  parts of, and machinery for manufacturing, ammunition, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>vii</number>  such ingredients of ammunition as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
     <number>c</number>    “arms” means articles of any description designed or 
    adapted as weapons for offences, or defence, and includes firearms, 
    sharp-edged and other deadly weapons, and parts of, and machinery for 
    manufacturing arms, but does not include articles designed solely for 
    domestic or agricultural uses such as a lathi or an ordinary walking stick 
    and weapons incapable of being used otherwise than as toys or of being 
    converted into serviceable weapons;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>    “district magistrate” in relation to any area 
    for which a Commissioner of Police has been appointed, means the 
    Commissioner of Police thereof and includes any such Deputy Commissioner of 
    Police, exercising jurisdiction over the whole or any part of such area, as 
    may be specified by the State Government in this behalf in relation to such 
    area or parts;]
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>e</number>    “firearms” means arms of any description designed or 
    adapted to discharge a projectile or projectiles of any kind by the action 
    of any explosive or other forms of energy, and includes,—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    artillery, hand-grenades, riot-pistols or 
    weapons of any kind designed or adapted for the discharge of any noxious 
    liquid, gas or other such things,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>    accessories for any such firearm designed or adapted 
    to diminish the noise or flash caused by the firing thereof,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iii</number>   parts of, and machinery for manufacturing, firearms, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iv</number>    carriages, platforms and appliances for mounting, 
    transporting and serving artillery;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>    “licensing authority” means an officer or authority 
    empowered to grant or renew licences under rules made under the Act, and 
    includes, the Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>ff</number>    “magistrate” means an Executive Magistrate 
    under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974);]
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>g</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this 
    Act;
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>h</number>    “prohibited ammunition” means any ammunition, containing, 
    or designed or adapted to contain, any noxious liquid, gas or other such 
    thing, and includes rockets, bombs, grenades, shells, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[missiles] 
    articles designed for torpedo service and submarine mining and such other 
    articles as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify to be prohibited ammunition;
 </subsection><subsection>
                 <number>i</number>    “prohibited arms” means—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    firearms so designed or adapted that, if 
    pressure is applied to the trigger, missiles continue to be discharged until 
    pressure is removed from the trigger or the magazine containing the missiles 
    is empty, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>    weapons of any description designed or adapted for 
    the discharge of any noxious liquid, gas or other such thing,
 
    and includes artillery, anti-aircraft and anti-tank firearms and such other 
    arms as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    specify to be prohibited arms;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
    <number>j</number>    “public servant” has the same meaning as in section 21 
    of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860);
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>k</number>    “transfer” with its grammatical variations and cognate 
    expressions, includes letting on hire, lending, giving and parting with 
    possession.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of this Act, the length 
    of the barrel of a firearm shall be measured from the muzzle to the point at 
    which the charge is exploded on firing.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any reference in the Act to any law which 
    is not in force in any area shall, in relation to that area, be construed as 
    a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any reference in this Act to any officer 
    or authority shall, in relation to any area in which there is no officer or 
    authority with the same designation, be construed as a reference to such 
    officer or authority as may be specified by the Central Government by 
    notification in the Official Gazette.
  
  









 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Licence for acquisition and 
    possession of firearms and ammunition.—<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    No person shall acquire, have in his possession, or carry any firearm or 
    ammunition unless he holds in this behalf a licence issued in accordance 
    with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder:
 
Provided that a person may, without himself 
    holding a licence, carry any firearms or ammunition in the presence, or 
    under the written authority, of the holder of the licence for repair or for 
    renewal of the licence or for use by such holder.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), no person, other than a person 
    referred to in sub-section (3), shall acquire, have in his possession or 
    carry, at any time, more than three firearms:
 
Provided that a person who has in his 
    possession more firearms than three at the commencement* of the Arms 
    (Amendment) Act, 1983, may retain with him any three of such firearms and 
    shall deposit, within ninety days from such commencement*, the remaining 
    firearms with the officer in charge of the nearest police station or, 
    subject to the conditions prescribed for the purposes of sub-section (1) of 
    section 21, with a licensed dealer or, where such person is a member of the 
    armed forces of the Union, in a unit armoury referred to in that 
    sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (2) 
    shall apply to any dealer in firearms or to any member of a rifle club or 
    rifle association licensed or recognised by the Central Government using a 
    point 22 bore rifle or an air rifle for target practice.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The provisions of sub-sections (2) to (6) 
    (both inclusive) of section 21 shall apply in relation to any deposit of 
    firearms under the proviso to sub-section (2) as they apply in relation to 
    the deposit of any arm or ammunition under sub-section (1) of that section.]
  











 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Licence for acquisition and possession of 
    arms of specified description in certain cases.—If 
    the Central Government is of opinion that having regard to the circumstances 
    prevailing in any area it is necessary or expedient in the public interest 
    that the acquisition, possession or carrying of arms other than firearms 
    should also be regulated, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    direct that this section shall apply to the area specified in the 
    notification and thereupon no person shall acquire, have in his possession 
    or carry in that area arms of such class or description as may be specified 
    in that notification unless he holds in this behalf a licence issued in 
    accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder.
  

 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Licence for manufacture, sale, etc., of arms and 
      ammunition.—<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] No person shall—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
      <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[use, manufacture], sell, transfer, convert, repair, test or 
      prove, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    expose or 
      offer for sale or transfer or have in his possession for sale, transfer, 
      conversion, repair, test or proof,
 any firearms or any other arms of 
      such class or description as may be prescribed or any ammunition unless he 
      holds in this behalf a licence issued in accordance with the provisions of 
      this Act and the rules made thereunder.
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section 
      (1), a person may, without holding a licence in this behalf, sell or 
      transfer any arms or ammunition which he lawfully possesses for his own 
      private use to another person who is entitled by virtue of this Act, or 
      any other law for the time being in force to have, or is not prohibited by 
      this Act or such other law from having in his possession such arms or 
      ammunition:
 Provided that no firearm or ammunition in 
      respect of which a licence is required under section 3 and no arms in 
      respect of which a licence is required under section 4 shall be sold or 
      transferred by any person unless—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    he has 
      informed in writing the district magistrate having jurisdiction or the 
      officer in charge of the nearest police station of his intention to sell 
      or transfer such firearms, ammunition or other arms and the name and 
      address of the person to whom he intends to sell or transfer such 
      firearms, ammunition or the other arms, and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    a period of 
      not less than forty-five days has expired after the giving of such 
      information.]
  
  








 </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Licence for the shortening of guns or 
    conversion of imitation firearms into firearms.—No 
    person shall shorten the barrel of a firearm or convert an imitation firearm 
    into a firearm unless he holds in this behalf a licence issued in accordance 
    with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder.
 
Explanation.—In 
    this section, the expression “imitation firearms” means anything which has 
    the appearance of being a firearm, whether it is capable of discharging any 
    shot, bullet or other missile or not.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Prohibition of acquisition or possession, 
    or of manufacture or sale, of prohibited arms or prohibited ammunition.—No 
    person shall—
 <section>
    <number>a</number>    acquire, have in his possession or carry; or
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number> 

<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[use, 
    manufacture], sell, transfer, convert, repair, test or prove; or
 </section><section>
    <number>c</number>  expose or offer for sale or transfer or have in his possession for 
    sale, transfer, conversion, repair, test or proof,
 any prohibited 
    arms or prohibited ammunition unless he has been specially authorised by the 
    Central Government in this behalf.
  






 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Prohibition of sale or transfer of 
    firearms not bearing identification marks—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall obliterate, remove, alter or forge any name, number or other 
    identification mark stamped or otherwise shown on a firearm.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall sell or transfer any 
    firearm which does not bear the name of the maker, manufacturer’s number or 
    other identification mark stamped or otherwise shown thereon in a manner 
    approved by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever any person has in his possession 
    any firearms without such name, number or other identification mark on which 
    such name, number or other identification mark has been obliterated, 
    removed, altered or forged, it shall be presumed unless the contrary is 
    proved, that he has obliterated, removed, altered or forged that name, 
    number or other identification mark:
 
Provided that in relation to a person who has 
    in his possession at the commencement of this Act any firearm without such 
    name, number or other identification mark stamped or otherwise shown 
    thereon, the provisions of this sub-section shall not take effect until 
    after the expiration of one year from such commencement.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Prohibition of acquisition or possession 
    by, or of sale or transfer to young persons and certain other persons of 
    firearms, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything in the foregoing provisions of this Act—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    no person,—
 <subsubsection>
     <number>i</number>    who has not completed the age of 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[twenty-one 
    years], or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>ii</number>    who has been sentenced on conviction of any 
    offence involving violence or moral turpitude to imprisonment for <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[any 
    term] at any time during a period of five years after the expiration of the 
    sentence, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>iii</number>    who has been ordered to execute under Chapter 
    VIII of the <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] a bond for keeping the peace or for 
    good behaviour, at any time during the term of the bond,
 
    shall acquire, have in his possession or carry any firearm or ammunition;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    no person shall sell or transfer any firearm or 
    ammunition to, or convert, repair, test or prove any firearm or ammunition 
    for, any other person whom he knows, or has reason to believe—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    to be prohibited under clause (a) from 
    acquiring, having in his possession or carrying any firearm or ammunition, 
    or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>    to be of unsound mind at the time of such sale or 
    transfer, or such conversion, repair, test or proof.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything in sub-clause (i) 
    of clause (a) of sub-section (1), a person who has attained the prescribed 
    age-limit may use under prescribed conditions such firearms as may be 
    prescribed in the course of his training in the use of such firearms:
 
Provided that different age-limits may be 
    prescribed in relation to different types of firearms.
  








 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Licence for import and export of arms, 
    etc.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall bring 
    into, or take out of, India by sea, land or air any arms or ammunition 
    unless he holds in this behalf a licence issued in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    a person who is entitled by virtue of this Act or any 
    other law for the time being in force to have, or is not prohibited by this 
    Act or such other law from having, in his possession any arms or ammunition, 
    may without a licence in this behalf bring into, or take out of, India such 
    arms or ammunition in reasonable quantities for his own private use;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    a person being a bona fide tourist belonging to 
    any such country as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, specify, who is not prohibited by the laws of that country 
    from having in his possession any arms or ammunition, may, without a licence 
    under this section but in accordance with such conditions as may be 
    prescribed, bring with him into India arms and ammunition in reasonable 
    quantities for use by him for purposes only of sport and for no other 
    purpose.
 
Explanation.—For 
    purposes of clause (b) of this proviso, the word “tourist” means a person 
    who not being a citizen of India visits India for a period not exceeding six 
    months with no other object than recreation, sight-seeing, or participation 
    in a representative capacity in meetings convened by the Central Government 
    or in international conferences, associations or other bodies.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the proviso to sub-section (1) where the <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[Commissioner of 
    Customs] or any other officer empowered by the Central Government in this 
    behalf has any doubt as to the applicability of clause (a) or clause (b) of 
    that proviso to any person who claims that such clause is applicable to him, 
    or as to the reasonableness of the quantities of arms or ammunition in the 
    possession of any person referred to in such clause, or as to the use to 
    which such arms or ammunition may be put by such person, may detain the arms 
    or ammunition in the possession of such person until he receives the orders 
    of the Central Government in relation thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Arms and ammunition taken from one part 
    of India to another by sea or air or across any intervening territory not 
    forming a part of India, are taken out of, and brought into, India within 
    the meaning of this section.
  
  





 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Power to prohibit import or export of 
    arms, etc.—The Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, prohibit the bringing into, or 
    the taking out of, India, arms or ammunition of such classes and 
    descriptions as may be specified in the notification.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to restrict or prohibit transport 
    of arms.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    direct that no person shall transport over India or any 
    part thereof arms or ammunition of such classes and descriptions as may be 
    specified in the notification unless he holds in this behalf a licence 
    issued in accordance with provisions of this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    prohibit such transport altogether.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Arms or ammunition trans-shipped at a 
    seaport or an airport in India are transported within the meaning of this 
    section.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Grant of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the grant of a licence under Chapter II shall be made to 
    the licensing authority and shall be in such form, contain such particulars 
    and be accompanied by such fee, if any, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> On receipt of an 
    application, the licensing authority shall call for the report of the 
    officer in charge of the nearest police station on that application, and 
    such officer shall send his report within the prescribed time.
 </section><section>
<number>2A</number> The licensing authority, after such 
    inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, and after considering the 
    report received under sub-section (2), shall, subject to the other 
    provisions of this Chapter, by order in writing either grant the licence or 
    refuse to grant the same:
 
Provided that where the officer in charge of 
    the nearest police station does not send his report on the application 
    within the prescribed time, the licensing authority may, if it deems fit, 
    make such order, after the expiry of the prescribed time, without further 
    waiting for that report.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensing authority shall grant—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>  a licence under section 3 where the licence is required—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    by a citizen of India in repsect of a smooth 
    bore gun having a barrel of not less than twenty inches in length to be used 
    for protection or sport or in respect of a muzzle loading gun to be used for
    bona fide crop protection:
 
     Provided that where having regard to the 
    circumstances of any case, the licensing authority is satisfied that a 
    muzzle loading gun will not be sufficient for crop protection, the licensing 
    authority may grant a licence in respect of any other smooth bore gun as 
    aforesaid for such protection; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>ii</number>    in respect of a point 22 bore rifle or an air 
    rifle to be used for target practice by a member of a rifle club or rifle 
    association licensed or recognised by the Central Government;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    a licence under section 3 in any other case or a licence 
    under section 4, section 5, section 6, section 10 or section 12, if the 
    licensing authority is satisfied that the person by whom the licence is 
    required has a good reason for obtaining the same.
  












 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Refusal of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything in section 13, licensing authority shall refuse to 
    grant—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    a licence under section 3, section 4 or section 5 where 
    such licence is required in respect of any prohibited arms or prohibited 
    ammunition;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    a licence in any other case under Chapter II,—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    where such licence is required by a person 
    whom the licensing authority has reason to believe—
 <subsubsubsection>
    <number>1</number>    to be prohibited by this Act or by any other law for 
    the time being in force from acquiring, having in his possession or carrying 
    any arms or ammunition, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
    <number>2</number>    to be of unsound mind, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
    <number>3</number>    to be for any reason unfit for a licence under this Act; or
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>    where the licensing authority deems it 
    necessary for the security of the public peace or for public safety to 
    refuse to grant such licence.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The licensing authority shall not refuse 
    to grant any licence to any person merely on the ground that such person 
    does not own or possess sufficient property.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the licensing authority refuses to 
    grant a licence to any person it shall record in writing the reasons for 
    such refusal and furnish to that person on demand a brief statement of the 
    same unless in any case the licensing authority is of the opinion that it 
    will not be in the public interest to furnish such statement.
  








 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Duration and renewal of licence—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A licence under section 3 shall, unless revoked earlier, continue in force 
    for a period of three years from the date on which it is granted:
 
Provided that such a licence may be granted 
    for a shorter period if the person by whom the licence is required so 
    desires or if the licensing authority for reasons to be recorded in writing 
    considers in any case that the licence should be granted for a shorter 
    period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A licence under any other provision of 
    Chaper II shall, unless revoked earlier, continue in force for such period 
    from the date on which it is granted as the licensing authority may in each 
    case determine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every licence shall, unless the licensing 
    authority for reasons to be recorded in writing otherwise decides in any 
    case, be renewable for the same period for which the licence was originally 
    granted and shall be so renewable from time to time, and the provisions of 
    sections 13 and 14 shall apply to the renewal of a licence as they apply to 
    the grant thereof.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Fees, etc., for licence.—The 
    fees on payment of which, the conditions subject to which and the form in 
    which a licence shall be granted or renewed shall be such as may be 
    prescribed:
 
Provided that different fees, different 
    conditions and different forms may be prescribed for different types of 
    licences:
 
Provided further that a licence may contain 
    in addition to prescribed conditions such other conditions as may be 
    considered necessary by the licensing authority in any particular case.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Variation, suspension and revocation of 
    licences.—
<section><number>1</number> The licensing 
    authority may vary the conditions subject to which a licence has been 
    granted except such of them as have been prescribed and may for that purpose 
    require the licence-holder by notice in writing to deliver-up the licence to 
    it within such time as may be specified in the notice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The licensing authority may, on the 
    application of the holder of a licence, also vary the conditions of the 
    licence except such of them as have been prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensing authority may by order in 
    writing suspend a licence for such period as it thinks fit or revoke a 
    licence—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    if the licensing authority is satisfied that the holder 
    of the licence is prohibited by this Act or by any other law for the time 
    being in force, from acquiring, having in his possession or carrying any 
    arms or ammunition, or is of unsound mind, or is for any reason unfit for a 
    licence under this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    if the licensing authority deems it necessary for the 
    security of the public peace or for public safety to suspend or revoke the licence; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    if the licence was obtained by the suppression of 
    material information or on the basis of wrong information provided by the 
    holder of the licence or any other person on his behalf at the time of 
    applying for it; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    if any of the conditions of the licence has been 
    contravened; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>e</number>    if the holder of the licence has failed to comply with a 
    notice under sub-section (1) requiring him to deliver-up the licence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The licensing authority may also revoke a 
    licence on the application of the holder thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the licensing authority makes an 
    order varying a licence under sub-section (1) or an order suspending or 
    revoking a licence under sub-section (3), it shall record in writing the 
    reasons therefor and furnish to the holder of the licence on demand a brief 
    statement of the same unless in any case the licensing authority is of the 
    opinion that it will not be in the public interest to furnish such 
    statement.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The authority to whom the licensing 
    authority is subordinate may by order in writing suspend or revoke a licence 
    on any ground on which it may be suspended or revoked by the licensing 
    authority; and the foregoing provisions of this section shall, as far as may 
    be, apply in relation to the suspension or revocation of a licence by such 
    authority.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A court convicting the holder of a 
    licence of any offence under this Act or the rules made thereunder may also 
    suspend or revoke the licence:
 
Provided that if the conviction is set aside 
    on appeal or otherwise, the suspension or revocation shall become void.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> An order of suspension or revocation 
    under sub-section (7) may also be made by an appellate court or by the High 
    Court when exercising its powers of revision.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Central Government may, by order in 
    the Official Gazette, suspend or revoke or direct any licensing authority to 
    suspend or revoke all or any licences granted under this Act throughout 
    India or any part thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> On the suspension or revocation of a 
    licence under this section the holder thereof shall without delay surrender 
    the licence to the authority by whom it has been suspended or revoked or to 
    such other authority as may be specified in this behalf in the order of 
    suspension or revocation.
  







 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the licensing authority refusing to 
    grant a licence or varying the conditions of a licence or by an order of the 
    licensing authority or the authority to whom the licensing authority is 
    subordinate, suspending or revoking a licence may prefer an appeal against 
    that order to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the appellate 
    authority) and within such period as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that no appeal shall lie against any 
    order made by, or under the direction of the Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal shall be admitted if it is 
    preferred after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor:
 
Provided that an appeal may be admitted after 
    the expiry of the period prescribed therefor if the appellant satisfies the 
    appellate authority that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the 
    appeal within that period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The period prescribed for an appeal shall 
    be computed in accordance with the provisions of the Indian Limitation Act, 
    1908 (9 of 1908), with respect to the computation of periods of limitation 
    thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every appeal under this section shall be 
    made by a petition in writing and shall be accompanied by a brief statement 
    of the reasons for the order appealed against where such statement has been 
    furnished to the appellant and by such fee as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In disposing of an appeal the appellate 
    authority shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that no appeal shall be disposed of 
    unless the appellant has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The order appealed against shall, unless 
    the appellate authority conditionally or unconditionally directs otherwise, 
    be in force pending the disposal of the appeal against such order.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every order of the appellate authority 
    confirming, modifying or reversing the order appealed against shall be 
    final.
  




 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Power to demand production of licence, 
    etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Any police officer or any 
    other officer specially empowered in this behalf by the Central Government 
    may demand the production of his licence from any person who is carrying any 
    arms or ammunition.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person upon whom a demand is made 
    refuses or fails to produce the licence or to show that he is entitled by 
    virtue of this Act or any other law for the time being in force to carry 
    such arms or ammunition without a licence, the officer concerned may require 
    him to give his name and address and if such officer considers it necessary, 
    seize from that person the arms or ammunition which he is carrying.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If that person refuses to give his name 
    and address or if the officer concerned suspects that person of giving a 
    false name or address or of intending to abscond, such officer may arrest 
    him without warrant.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Arrest of persons conveying arms, etc., 
    under suspicious circumstances.—Where 
    any person is found carrying or conveying any arms or ammunition whether 
    covered by a licence or not, in such manner or under such circumstances as 
    to afford just grounds of suspicion that the same are or is being carried by 
    him with intent to use them, or that the same may be used, for any unlawful 
    purpose, any magistrate, any police officer or any other public servant or 
    any person employed or working upon a railway, aircraft, vessel, vehicle or 
    any other means of conveyance, may arrest him without warrant and seize from 
    him such arms or ammunition.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Deposit of arms, etc., on possession 
    ceasing to be lawful.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    person having in his possession any arms or ammunition the possession 
    whereof has, in consequence of the expiration of the duration of a licence 
    or of the suspension or revocation of a licence or by the issue of a 
    notification under section 4 or by any reason whatever, ceased to be lawful, 
    shall without unnecessary delay deposit the same either with the officer 
    incharge of the nearest police station or subject to such conditions as may 
    be prescribed, with a licensed dealer or where such person is a member of 
    the armed forces of the Union, in a unit armoury.
 
Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section “unit armoury” includes an armoury in a ship or 
    establishment of the Indian Navy.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where arms or ammunition have or has been 
    deposited under sub-section (1) the depositor or in the case of his death, 
    his legal representative, shall, at any time before the expiry of such 
    period as may be prescribed, be entitled—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    to receive back anything so deposited on his becoming 
    entitled by virtue of this Act or any other law for the time being in force 
    to have the same in his possession, or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    to dispose, or authorise the disposal, of anything so 
    deposited by sale or otherwise to any person entitled by virtue of this Act 
    or any other law for the time being in force to have, or not prohibited by 
    this Act or such other law from having, the same in his possession and to 
    receive the proceeds of any such disposal:
 
Provided that nothing in this sub-section 
    shall be deemed to authorise the return or disposal of anything of which 
    confiscation has been directed under section 32.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All things deposited and not received 
    back or disposed of under sub-section (2) within the period therein referred 
    to shall be forfeited to Government by order of the district magistrate:
 
Provided that in the case of suspension of a 
    licence no such forfeiture shall be ordered in respect of a thing covered by 
    the licence during the period of suspension.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Before making an order under sub-section 
    (3) the district magistrate shall by notice in writing to be served upon the 
    depositor or in the case of his death, upon his legal representative, in the 
    prescribed manner, require him to show cause within thirty days from the 
    service of the notice why the things specified in the notice should not be 
    forfeited.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After considering the cause, if any, 
    shown by the depositor or as the case may be, his legal representative, the 
    district magistrate shall pass such order as he thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Government may at any time return to 
    the depositor or his legal representative things forfeited to it or the 
    proceeds of disposal thereof wholly or in part.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Search and seizure by magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever any magistrate has reason to believe—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    that any person residing within the local limits of 
    his jurisdiction has in his possession any arms or ammunition for any 
    unlawful purpose, or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    that such person cannot be left in the possession of 
    any arms or ammunition without danger to the public peace or safety, 
 the magistrate 
    may, after having recorded the reasons for his belief, cause a search to be 
    made of the house or premises occupied by such person or in which the 
    magistrate has reason to believe that such arms or ammunition are or is to 
    be found and may have such arms or ammunition, if any, seized and detain the 
    same in safe custody for such period as he thinks necessary, although that 
    person may be entitled by virtue of this Act or any other law for the time 
    being in force to have the same in his possession.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every search under this section shall be 
    conducted by or in the presence of a magistrate or by or in the presence of 
    some officer specially empowered in this behalf by the Central Government.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Search of vessels, vehicles for arms, 
    etc.—Any magistrate, any police 
    officer or any other officer specially empowered in this behalf by the 
    Central Government, may for the purpose of ascertaining whether any 
    contravention of this Act or the rules made thereunder is being or is likely 
    to be committed, stop and search any vessel, vehicle or other means of 
    conveyance and seize any arms or ammunition that may be found therein 
    alongwith such vessel, vehicle or other means of conveyance.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Seizure and detention under orders of the 
    Central Government.—The Central 
    Government may at any time order the seizure of any arms or ammunition in 
    the possession of any person, notwithstanding that such person is entitled 
    by virtue of this Act or any other law for the time being in force to have 
    the same in his possession, and may detain the same for such period as it 
    thinks necessary for the public peace and safety.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>24A</number> Prohibition 
    as to possession of notified arms in disturbed areas, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the 
    Central Government is satisfied that there is extensive disturbance of 
    public peace and tranquillity or imminent danger of such disturbance in any 
    area and that for the prevention of offences involving the use of arms in 
    such area, it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may by notification in 
    the Official Gazette—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    specify the limits of such area;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    direct that before the commencement of the period 
    specified in the notification (which period shall be a period commencing 
    from a date not earlier than the fourth day after the date of publication of 
    the notification in the Official Gazette), every person having in his 
    possession in such area any arms of such description as may be specified in 
    the notification (the arms so specified being hereafter in this section 
    referred to as notified arms), shall deposit the same before such 
    commencement in accordance with the provisions of section 21 and for this 
    purpose the possession by such person of any notified arms shall, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision of this Act 
    (except section 41) or in any other law for the time being in force, as from 
    the date of publication of such notification in the Official Gazette be 
    deemed to have ceased to be lawful;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    declare that as from the commencement of, and until 
    the expiry of, the period specified in the notification, it shall not be 
    lawful for any person to have in his possession in such area any notified 
    arms;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    authorise any such officer subordinate to the Central 
    Government or a State Government as may be specified in the notification,—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>    to search at any time during the period 
    specified in the notification any person in, or passing through, or any 
    premises in, or any animal or vessel or vehicle or other conveyance of 
    whatever nature in or passing through, or any receptacle or other container 
    of whatever nature in, such area if such officer has reason to believe that 
    any notified arms are secreted by such person or in such premises or on such 
    animal or in such vessel, vehicle or other conveyance or in such receptacle 
    or other container;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>    to seize at any time during the period 
    specified in the notification any notified arms in the possession of any 
    person in such area or discovered through a search under sub-clause (i), and 
    detain the same during the period specified in the notification.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The period specified in a notification 
    issued under sub-section (1) in respect of any area shall not, in the first 
    instance, exceed ninety days, but the Central Government may amend such 
    notification to extend such period from time to time by any period not 
    exceeding ninety days at any one time if, in the opinion of that Government, 
    there continues to be in such area such disturbance of public peace and 
    tranquillity as is referred to in sub-section (1) or imminent danger thereof 
    and that for the prevention of offences involving the use of arms in such 
    area it is necessary or expedient so to do.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), relating to searches and seizures shall, so far 
    as may be, apply to any search or seizure made under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    “arms” includes ammunition;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    where the period specified in a notification, as 
    originally issued under sub-section (1), is extended under sub-section (2), 
    then, in relation to such notification, references in sub-section (1) to 
    “the period specified in the notification” shall be construed as references 
    to the period as so extended.]





 


</subsection></section></article> 

   


   


 <article>1[<number>24B</number>
Prohibition as to carrying of notified arms in or through public places in
disturbed areas, etc.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where the Central Government is satisfied that there is extensive disturbance of
public peace and tranquillity or imminent danger of such disturbance in any area
and that for the prevention of offences involving the use of arms in such area
it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by notification in the Official
Gazette,— 
 <subsection> <number>a</number>
 specify the limits of such
area; tc "	(a) 	specify the limits of
such area;"

 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>b</number>
 direct that during the period
specified in the notification (which period shall be a period commencing from a
date not earlier than the second day after the date of publication of the
notification in the Official Gazette), no person shall carry or otherwise have
in his possession any arms of such description as may be specified in the
notification (the arms so specified being hereafter in this section referred to
as notified arms) through or in any public place in such area; tc "	(b) 	direct that during the
period specified in the notification (which period shall be a period commencing
from a date not earlier than the second day after the date of publication of
the notification in the Official Gazette), no person shall carry or otherwise
have in his possession any arms of such description as may be specified in the
notification (the arms so specified being hereafter in this section referred to
as notified arms) through or in any public place in such area;"

 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>c</number>
 authorise any such officer
subordinate to the Central Government or a State Government as may be specified
in the notification,— tc
"	(c) 	authorise any such officer subordinate to the Central Government or
a State Government as may be specified in the notification,—"

 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> to search at any time during the
period specified in the notification any person in or passing through, or any
premises in or forming part of, or any animal or vessel or vehicle or other
conveyance of whatever nature, in or passing through, or any receptacle or other
container of whatever nature in, any public place in such area if such officer
has reason to believe that any notified arms are secreted by such person or in
such premises or on such animal or in such vessel, vehicle or other conveyance
or in such receptacle or other container; tc
"	(i) 	to search at any time during the period specified in the
notification any person in or passing through, or any premises in or forming
part of, or any animal or vessel or vehicle or other conveyance of whatever
nature, in or passing through, or any receptacle or other container of whatever
nature in, any public place in such area if such officer has reason to believe
that any notified arms are secreted by such person or in such premises or on
such animal or in such vessel, vehicle or other conveyance or in such
receptacle or other container;"

 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> to seize at any time during the
period specified in the notification any notified arms being carried by or
otherwise in the possession of any person, through or in a public place in such
area or discovered through a search under such-clause (i), and detain the same
during the period specified in the notification. tc
"	(ii) 	to seize at any time during the period specified in the
notification any notified arms being carried by or otherwise in the possession
of any person, through or in a public place in such area or discovered through
a search under such-clause (i), and detain the same during the period specified
in the notification."

 


 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The period specified in a notification issued under sub-section (1) in respect
of any area shall not, in the first instance, exceed ninety days, but the
Central Government may amend such notification to extend such period from time
to time by any period not exceeding ninety days at any one time if, in the
opinion of that Government, there continues to be in such area such disturbance
of public peace and tranquillity as is referred to in sub-section (1) or
imminent danger thereof and that for the prevention of offences involving the
use of arms in such area it is necessary or expedient so to do. 
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, (2 of 1974), relating to
searches and seizures shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure
made under sub-section (1). 
 </section><section><number>4</number>
For the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection> <number>a</number>
“arms” includes ammunition; tc "	(a)	“arms” includes
ammunition;"

 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>b</number>
“public place” means any place intended for use by, or accessible to,
the public or any section of the public; and tc "	(b)	“public place” means any
place intended for use by, or accessible to, the public or any section of the
public; and"

 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
where the period specified in a notification, as originally issued under
sub-section (1), is extended under sub-section (2), then, in relation to such
notification, references in sub-section (l) to “the period specified in the
notification” shall be construed as references to the period as so extended.] tc "	(c)	where the period specified
in a notification, as originally issued under sub-section (1), is extended
under sub-section (2), then, in relation to such notification, references in
sub-section (l) to “the period specified in the notification” shall be
construed as references to the period as so extended.]"

 


   
















</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article> <number>25</number> Punishment for certain 
    offences—<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    manufactures, sells, transfers, converts, repairs, 
    tests or proves, or exposes or offers for sale or transfer, or has in his 
    possession for sale, transfer, conversion, repair, test or proof, any arms 
    or ammunition in contravention of section 5; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    shortens the barrel of a firearm or converts an immitation firearm into a firearm in contravention of section 6; or
 
<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    bring into, or takes out of, India, any arms or 
    ammunition of any class or description in contravention of section 11,
 shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three 
    years but which may extend to seven years and shall also be liable to fine.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> Whoever 
    acquires, has in his possession or carries any prohibited arms or prohibited 
    ammunition in contravention of section 7 shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years, but which 
    may extend to ten years and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>1AA</number> Whoever manufactures, sells, transfers, 
    converts, repairs, tests or proves, or exposes or offers for sale or 
    transfer or has in his possession for sale, transfer, conversion, repair, 
    test or proof, any prohibited arms or prohibited ammunition in contravention 
    of section 7 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall 
    not be less than seven years but which may extend to imprisonment for life 
    and shall also be liable to fine.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>1AAA</number>] Whoever has 
    in contravention of a notification issued under section 24A in his 
    possession or in contravention of a notification issued under section 24B 
    carries or otherwise has in his possession, any arms or ammunition shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[three years, but 
    which may extend to seven years] shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>1B</number> Whoever—
 <subsection>
     <number>a</number>    acquires, has in his possession or carries any 
    firearm or ammunition in contravention of section 3; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    acquires, has in his possession or carries in any 
    place specified by notification under section 4 any arms of such class or 
    description as has been specified in that notification in contravention of 
    that section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    sells or transfers any firearm which does not bear the 
    name of the maker, manufacturer’s number or other identification mark 
    stamped or otherwise shown thereon as required by sub-section (2) of section 
    8 or does any act in contravention of sub-section (1) of that section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    being a person to whom sub-clause (ii) or sub-clause 
    (iii) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 9 applies, acquires, has 
    in his possession or carries any firearm or ammunition in contravention of 
    that section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>e</number>    sells or transfers, or converts, repairs, tests or 
    proves any firearm or ammunition in contravention of clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 9; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>    brings into, or takes out of, India, any arms or 
    ammunition in contravention of section 10; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>g</number>    transports any arms or ammunition in contravention of 
    section 12; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>h</number>    fails to deposit arms or ammunition as required by 
    sub-section (2) of section 3, or sub-section (1) of section 21; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>i</number>    being a manufacturer of, or dealer in, arms or 
    ammunition, fails, on being required to do so by rules made under section 
    44, to maintain a record or account or to make therein all such entries as 
    are required by such rules or intentionally makes a false entry therein or 
    prevents or obstructs the inspection of such record or account or the making 
    of copies of entries therefrom or prevents or obstructs the entry into any 
    premises or other place where arms or ammunition are or is manufactured or 
    kept or intentionally fails to exhibit or conceals such arms or ammunition 
    or refuses to point out where the same are or is manufactured or kept,
 
shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[one 
    year] but which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine:
 
Provided that the Court may 
    for any adequate and special reasons to be recorded in the judgment impose a 
    sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than 

    6[one year].
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>1C</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1B), whoever commits an offence 
    punishable under that sub-section in any disturbed area shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three years but 
    which may extend to seven years and shall also be liable to fine.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, “disturbed area” means any area declared 
    to be a disturbed area under any enactment, for the time being in force, 
    making provision for the suppression of disorder and restoration and 
    maintenance of public order, and includes any areas specified by 
    notification under section 24A or section 24B.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever being a person to whom sub-clause 
    (i) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 9 applies, acquires, has in 
    his possession or carries any firearm or ammunition in contravention of that 
    section shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    one year, or with fine or with both.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Whoever sells or 
    transfers any firearm, ammunition or other arms—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>    without informing the district magistrate having 
    jurisdiction or the officer in charge of the nearest police station, of the 
    intended sale or transfer of that firearm, ammunition or other arms; or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>    before the expiration of the period of forty-five 
    days from the date of giving such information to such district magistrate or 
    the officer in charge of the police station,
 in contravention 
    of the provisions of clause (a) or clause (b) of the proviso to sub-section 
    (2) of section 5, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to six months, or with fine of an amount which may extend to five 
    hundred rupees, or with both.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Whoever fails to deliver-up a licence 
    when so required by the licensing authority under sub-section (1) of section 
    17 for the purpose of varying the conditions specified in the licence or 
    fails to surrender a licence to the appropriate authority under sub-section 
    (10) of that section on its suspension or revocation shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine of 
    an amount which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Whoever, when required under section 19 
    to give his name and address, refuses to give such name and address or gives 
    a name or address which subsequently transpires to be false shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or 
    with fine of an amount which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with both.
  















 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>26</number> Secret 
    contraventions.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever does any act in contravention of any of the 
    provisions of section 3, 4, 10 or 12 in such manner as to indicate an 
    intention that such act may not be known to any public servant or to any 
    person employed or working upon a railway, aircraft, vessel, vehicle or any 
    other means of conveyance, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to seven years 
    and also with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever does any act in contravention of 
    any of the provisions of section 5, 6, 7 or 11 in such manner as to indicate 
    an intention that such act may not be known to any public servant or to any 
    person employed or working upon a railway, aircraft, vessel, vehicle or any 
    other means of conveyance, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which shall not be less than five years but which may extend to ten years 
    and also with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever on any search being made under 
    section 22 conceals or attempts to conceal any arms or ammunition, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years and 
    also with fine.]





 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>27</number> Punishment for 
    using arms, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever uses any arms or ammunition in 
    contravention of section 5 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which shall not be less than three years but which may extend to seven years 
    and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever uses any prohibited arms or 
    prohibited ammunition in contravention of section 7 shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than seven years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever uses any prohibited arms or 
    prohibited ammunition or does any act in contravention of section 7 and such 
    use or act results in the death of any other person, shall be punishable 
    with death.]
  











 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Punishment for use and 
    possession of firearms or imitation firearms in certain cases.—Whoever 
    makes or attempts to make any use whatsoever of a firearm or an immitation 
    firearm with intent to resist or prevent the lawful arrest or detention of 
    himself or any other person shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to seven years <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[and with fine].
 
Explanation.—In 
    this section the expression “immitation firearm” has the same meaning as in 
    section 6.






 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Punishment for knowingly purchasing arms, 
    etc., from unlicensed person or for delivering arms, etc., to person not 
    entitled to possess the same.—Whoever—
 <section>
                <number>a</number>    purchases any firearms or any other arms of such class or 
    description as may be prescribed or any ammunition from any other person 
    knowing that such other person is not licensed or authorised under section 
    5; or
 </section><section>
                <number>b</number>    delivers any arms or ammunition into the possession of 
    another person without previously ascertaining that such other person is 
    entitled by virtue of this Act or any other law for the time being in force 
    to have, and is not prohibited by this Act or such other law from having, in 
    his possession the same,
 shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[three 
    years, or with fine, or with both].
  
  






 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Punishment for 
    contravention of licence or rule.—Whoever 
    contravenes any condition of a licence or any provision of this Act or any 
    rule made thereunder, for which no punishment is provided elsewhere in this 
    Act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to
    <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[six months], or with 
    fine which may extend to <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[two thousand] rupees, 
    or with both.
  











 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Punishment for subsequent offences.—Whoever 
    having been convicted of an offence under this Act is again convicted of an 
    offence under this Act shall be punishable with double the penalty provided 
    for the latter offence.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power to confiscate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When any person is convicted under this Act of any offence committed by him 
    in respect of any arms or ammunition, it shall be in the discretion of the 
    convicting court further to direct that the whole or any portion of such 
    arms or ammunition, and any vessel, vehicle or other means of conveyance and 
    any receptacle or thing containing, or used to conceal, the arms or 
    ammunition shall be confiscated:
 
Provided that if the conviction is set aside 
    on appeal or otherwise, the order of confiscation shall become void.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order of confiscation may also be made 
    by the appellate court or by the High Court when exercising its powers of 
    revision.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Offence by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, or was 
    responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing contained in this 
    sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment under this 
    Act if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge and 
    that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
    offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-section (1) where an offence under this Act has been committed by a 
    company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
    consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, 
    any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
    director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be 
    guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate, and includes a 
    firm or other association or individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
    the firm.
 


 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Sanction of the Central Government for Warehousing of Arms.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[Customs Act, 1962 (52 
    of 1962)] no arms or ammunition shall be deposited in any warehouse licensed 
    under <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[section 58] of that 
    Act without the sanction of the Central Government.
 

 







 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Criminal 
    responsibility of persons in occupation of premises in certain cases.—Where 
    any arms or ammunition in respect of which any offence under this Act has 
    been or is being committed are or is found in any premises, vehicle or other 
    place in the joint occupation or under the joint control of several persons, 
    each of such persons in respect of whom there is reason to believe that he 
    was aware of the existence of the arms or ammunition in the premises, 
    vehicle or other place shall, unless the contrary is proved, be liable for 
    that offence in the same manner as if it has been or is being committed by 
    him alone.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Information to be given regarding certain offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person aware of the commission of any offence under this Act shall, in 
    the absence of reasonable excuse the burden of proving which shall lie upon 
    such person, give information of the same to the officer in charge of the 
    nearest police station or the magistrate having jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person employed or working upon any railway, aircraft, vessel, vehicle or 
    other means of conveyance shall, in the absence of reasonable excuse the 
    burden of proving which shall lie upon such person, give information to the 
    officer in charge of the nearest police station regarding any box, package 
    or bale in transit which he may have reason to suspect contains arms or 
    ammunition in respect of which an offence under this Act has been or is 
    being committed.
  

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> Arrest 
    and searches.—Save as otherwise 
    provided in this Act,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all arrests and 
    searches made under this Act or under any rules made thereunder shall be 
    carried out in accordance with the provisions of the 
<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating respectively to arrests 
    and searches made under that Code;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any person arrested and 
    any arms or ammunition seized under this Act by a person not being a 
    magistrate or a police officer shall be delivered without delay to the 
    officer in charge of the nearest police station and that officer shall—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    either release 
    that person on his executing a bond with or without sureties to appear 
    before a magistrate and keep the things seized in his custody till the 
    appearance of that person before the magistrate, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    should that person fail 
    to execute the bond and to furnish, if so required, sufficient sureties, 
    produce that person and those things without delay before the magistrate.






 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable.—Every 
    offence under this Act shall be cognizable within the meaning of the [Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)].
 
 





 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> Previous sanction of the district 
    magistrate necessary in certain cases.—No 
    prosecution shall be instituted against any person in respect of any offence 
    under section 3 without the previous sanction of the district magistrate.

 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>40</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—No suit, prosecution or 
      other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is 
      in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
    Act.
 </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> Power to exempt.—Where 
    the Central Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient 
    in the public interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette and subject to such conditions, if any, as it may specify in the 
    notification,—
 <section>
    <number>a</number>    
<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[exempt 
    any person or class of persons (either generally or in relation to such 
    description of arms and ammunition as may be specified in the 
    notification)], or exclude any description of arms or ammunition, or 
    withdraw any part of India, from the operation of all or any of the 
    provisions of this Act; and
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number>    as often as may be, cancel any such notification and 
    again subject, by a like notification, the person or class of persons or the 
    description of arms and ammunition or the part of India to the operation of 
    such provisions.





 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> Power to take census of firearms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct 
    a census to be taken of all firearms in any area and empower any officer of 
    Government to take such census.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the issue of any such notification all 
    persons having in their possession any firearms in that area shall furnish 
    to the officer concerned such information as he may require in relation 
    thereto and shall produce before him such firearms if he so requires.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>43</number> Power to delegate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct 
    that any power or function which may be exercised or performed by it under 
    this Act other than the power under section 41 or the power under section 44 
    may, in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as 
    it may specify in the notification, be exercised or performed also by—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
    Government, or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    such State Government or such officer or authority 
    subordinate to the State Government,
 

    as may be specified in the notification.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any rules made by the Central Government 
    under this Act may confer powers or impose duties or authorise the 
    conferring of powers or imposition of duties upon any State Government or 
    any officer or authority subordinate thereto.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any 
    of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    the appointment, jurisdiction, control and functions of 
    licensing authorities 
<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[including 
    the areas and the categories of arms and ammunition for which they may grant 
    licences];
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    the form and particulars of application for the grant or 
    renewal of a licence and where the application is for the renewal of a 
    licence, the time within which it shall be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    the form in which and the conditions subject to which 
    any licence may be granted or refused, renewed, varied, suspended or 
    revoked;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    where no period has been specified in this Act, the 
    period for which any licence shall continue to be in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>e</number>    the fees payable in respect of any application for the 
    grant or renewal of a licence and in respect of any licence granted or 
    renewed and the manner of paying the same;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>    the manner in which the maker’s name, the 
    manufacturer’s number or other identification mark of a firearm shall be 
    stamped or otherwise shown thereon;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>g</number>    the procedure for the test or proof of any firearms;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>h</number>    the firearms that may be used in the course of 
    training, the age limits of persons who may use them and the conditions for 
    their use by such persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>i</number>    the authority to whom appeals may be preferred under 
    section 18, the procedure to be followed by such authority and the period 
    within which appeals shall be preferred, the fees to be paid in respect of 
    such appeals and the refund of such fees;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>j</number>    the maintenance of records or accounts of anything done 
    under a licence other than a licence under section 3 or section 4, the form 
    of, and the entries to be made in, such records or accounts and the 
    exhibition of such records or accounts to any police officer or to any 
    officer of Government empowered in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the entry and inspection 
    by any police officer or by any officer of Government empowered in this 
    behalf of any premises or other place in which arms or ammunition are or is 
    manufactured or in which arms or ammunition are or is kept by a manufacturer 
    of or dealer in such arms or ammunition and the exhibition of the same to 
    such officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>l</number>    the conditions subject to which arms or ammunition may 
    be deposited with a licensed dealer or in a unit armoury as required by 
    sub-section (1) of section 21 and the period on the expiry of which the 
    things so deposited may be forfeited;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>m</number>    any other matter is to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under this 
    section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House 
    of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which 
    may be comprised in one session or in 
<footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid]; both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.
  
  






 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> Act not to apply in certain cases.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall apply to—
 <section>
    <number>a</number>    arms or ammunition on board any sea-going vessel or 
    any aircraft and forming part of the ordinary armament or equipment of such 
    vessel or aircraft;
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number>    the acquisition, possession or carrying, the 
    manufacture, repair, conversion, test or proof, the sale or transfer or the 
    import, export or transport of arms or ammunition—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>    by or under orders of the Central Government, 
    or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>    by a public servant in the course of his duty as such 
    public servant, or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>iii</number>    by a member of the National Cadet Corps raised and 
    maintained under the National Cadet Corps Act, 1948 (31 of 1948), or by any 
    officer, enrolled person of the Territorial Army raised and maintained under 
    the Territorial Army Act, 1948 (56 of 1948) or by any member of any other 
    forces raised and maintained or that may hereafter be raised and maintained 
    under any Central Act, or by any member of such other forces as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, in the 
    course of his duty as such member, officer or enrolled person;
 </subsection></section><section>
    <number>c</number>    any weapon of an obsolete pattern or of antiquarian 
    value or in disrepair which is not capable of being used as a firearm either 
    with or without repair;
 </section><section>
    <number>d</number>    the acquisition, possession or carrying by a person of 
    minor parts of arms or ammunition which are not intended to be used along 
    with complementary parts acquired or possessed by that or any other person.

 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>46</number> Repeal of Act 11 of 1878.—
<section><number>1</number> The Indian Arms Act, 1878, is hereby 
      repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding the repeal of the Indian 
      Arms Act, 1878 (11 of 1878), and without prejudice to the provisions of 
      sections 6 and 24 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), every 
      licence granted or renewed under the first mentioned Act and in force 
      immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, unless sooner 
      revoked, continue in force after such commencement for the unexpired 
      portion of the period for which it has been granted or 
      renewed.
 </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   
    Came into force on 1-10-1962 vide G.S.R. 992, dated 13th July, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Subs. by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 2, for 
    “and other like missiles” (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Subs. by Act 55 of 1971, sec. 2, for 
    clause (d) (w.e.f. 13-12-1971).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 Ins. by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 
    27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   
    Section 3 re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   
    Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-19830).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Section 5 re-numbered 
      as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 
      22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 42 of 
      1988, sec. 3, for “manufacture” (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Proviso omitted by 
      Act 25 of 1983, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by Act 25 of 
      1983, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   
    Subs. by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 4, for “manufacture” (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 5, for “sixteen years” (w.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 5, for “a term of not less than six months” (w.r.e.f. 
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 5, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 
    1898)” (w.r.e.f.
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   
    Subs. by Act 22 of 1995, sec. 89, for “Collector of Customs” (w.e.f. 
    26-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 6, for sub-section (2) (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   
    Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 7 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 7 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).   tc "1.	Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec.
7 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983)." 
  
 tc " 1 [24B. Prohibition as to carrying of notified arms in or
through public places in disturbed areas, etc. —(1)
Where the Central Government is satisfied that there is extensive disturbance
of public peace and tranquillity or imminent danger of such disturbance in any
area and that for the prevention of offences "</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 8, for sub-section (1) (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   
    Clause (c) omitted by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 5 (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   
    Ins. by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 5 (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   
    Sub-section (1A) renumbered as sub-section (1AAA) by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 5
(w.r.e.f.
    27-5 1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   
    Subs. by Act 39 of 1985, sec. 2, for “one year, but which may extend to five 
    years” (w.e.f.
    28-5-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   
    Subs. by Act 39 of 1985, sec. 2, for “six months” (w.e.f. 28-5-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   
    Ins. by Act 39 of 1985, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-5-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 8, for sub-section (3) (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 9, for section 26  (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   
    Subs. by Act 42 of 1988, sec. 6, for section 27 (w.r.e.f. 27-5-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 10, for “, or within fine, or with both” (w.r.e.f. 
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 11, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   
    Subs. by Act  25 of 1983, sec. 12, for “three months” (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 12, for “five hundred” (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 13, for “Sea Customs Act, 1878 (8 of 1878)” (w.r.e.f. 
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 13, for “section 16” (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> 
 Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 14, for 
    “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 15, for “exempt any person or class of 
    persons” (w.r.e.f.
    22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   
    Ins. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 16 (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   
    Subs. by Act 25 of 1983, sec. 16, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>