<act> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>2</number> Numeration—how to be 
made.—
<section><number>1</number> Every numeration shall be 
made in accordance with the decimal system.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every number shall be 
represented on base ten.
 

1[(3) In representing any number in 
digits, the international form of Indian numerals, namely, 0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9, 
or a combination thereof shall be used]:
 

2[***]
 





</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>2</number> Numeration—how to be 
made.—
<section><number>1</number> Every numeration shall be 
made in accordance with the decimal system.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every number shall be 
represented on base ten.
 

1[(3) In representing any number in 
digits, the international form of Indian numerals, namely, 0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9, 
or a combination thereof shall be used]:
 

2[***]
 





</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>3</number> Manner in which numbers 
exceeding three digits (how to be expressed) shall be written in words.—Numbers 
expressed in digits exceedings three shall be written in words in the manner 
specified in the Schedule annexed to these rules.
 Provided that for a period of 
ten years from the commencement of these rules, such numbers may be expressed 
in words in the terminology used in any local or regional language.
</article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Numeration) Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>4</number> Manner in which numbers 
shall be written (how to be written).—
<section><number>1</number> 
In writing, according to any Indian terminology, any number in digits exceeding 
three, the decimal point shall be taken as the starting point and the first 
three digits, whether to the left or right of the decimal point, shall be 
grouped together and the subsequent digits shall be divided in groups of two 
and neither dots nor commas shall be inserted in the spaces intervening 
between such groups of digits.
 Example 
: 23 14 345, 732 23 50
 </section><section><number>2</number> in writing according to 
English terminology, any number in digit exceeding three, the decimal point 
shall be taken as the starting point and the digits, whether to the left or to 
the right of the decimal point, shall be divided into groups of three, starting 
from the decimal point and, neither dots nor commas shall be inserted in 
the spaces intervening between such groups of digits.
 Example: 
123 345, 732 456.
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>