<act><tid>1339328</tid>
<title>THE GENERAL INSURANCE BUSINESS (NATIONALISATION) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 57 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 20th September, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of shares of Indian 
insurance companies and undertakings of other existing insurers in 
order to serve better the needs of the economy by securing the 
development of general insurance business in the best interests of the 
community and to ensure that the operation of the economic system does 
not result in the concentration of wealth to the common detriment, for 
the regulation and control of such business and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>524637</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the General Insurance 
Business (Nationalisation) Act, <year>1972</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1676776</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to the Policy of the State. It is hereby 
declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State 
towards securing the principles specified in clause (c) of article 39 
of the Constitution.
Explanation.-- In this section," State" has the same meaning as in 
article 12 of the Constitution.



</article>



<article><tid>1479970</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>470968</tid>
<number>a</number>" acquiring company" means any Indian insurance company 
and, where a scheme has been framed involving the 
merger of one Indian insurance company in another or 
the amalgamation of two or more such companies, means 
the Indian insurance company in which any other company 
has been merged or the company which has been formed as 
a result of the amalgamation;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>206</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>161066</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means such day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, not being a day later 
than the 2nd day of January, <year>1973</year>, as the Central 
Government may, by notification, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>1088814</tid>
<number>c</number>" Companies Act" means the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1848152</tid>
<number>d</number>" Corporation" means the General Insurance Corporation of 
India formed under section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>1016977</tid>
<number>e</number>" existing insurer" means every insurer the management of 
whose undertaking has vested in the Central Government 
under section 3 of the General insurance (Emergency  
  Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year> (17 of <year>1971</year>), and includes the 
undertaking of the Life Insurance Corporation in so far 
as it relates to the general insurance business carried 
on by it;

</section>

<section><tid>1842458</tid>
<number>f</number>" foreign insurer" means an existing insurer incorporated 
under the law of any country outside India;

</section>

<section><tid>1271285</tid>
<number>g</number>" general insurance business" means fire, marine or 
miscellaneous insurance business, whether carried on 
singly or in combination with one or more of them, but 
does not include capital redemption business and 
annuity certain business;

</section>

<section><tid>1586167</tid>
<number>h</number>" Government company" means a Government company as 
defined in section 617 of the Companies Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1034874</tid>
<number>i</number>" Indian insurance company" means an existing insurer 
having a share capital who is a company within the 
meaning of the Companies Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1538935</tid>
<number>j</number>" Insurance Act" means the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1929186</tid>
<number>k</number>" Life Insurance Corporation" means the Life Insurance 
Corporation of India established under the Life 
Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1956</year> (31 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1641054</tid>
<number>l</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1355150</tid>
<number>m</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>319637</tid>
<number>n</number>" Schedule" means the Schedule to this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1581782</tid>
<number>o</number>" scheme" means the scheme framed under section 16 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and 
also includes a scheme framed under section 17A];

</section>

<section><tid>291853</tid>
<number>p</number>words and expressions used in this Act but not defined 
herein and defined in the Insurance Act, shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>207</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 1- <year>1973</year> vide Notification No. S. O. 724 (E), dated 24- 11- <year>1972</year>, 
Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II Sec. 3 (ii), p. <year>1979</year>. 
2 Ins. by Act 3 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1767769</tid>
<number>q</number>words and expressions used in this Act but not defined 
herein or in the Insurance Act and defined in the 
Companies Act, shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Companies Act.
CHAP

TRANSFER TO PUBLIC OWNERSHIP OF GENERAL INSURANCE BUSINESS

CHAPTER II

TRANSFER TO PUBLIC OWNERSHIP OF GENERAL INSURANCE BUSINESS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1931335</tid>
<number> 4</number> Transfer of shares of Indian insurance companies.
<section><tid>1183870</tid>
<number>1</number>On the  
appointed day all the shares in the capital of every Indian insurance 
company shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred to and vested 
in the Central Government free of all trusts, liabilities and 
encumbrances affecting them.

</section>

<section><tid>69815</tid>
<number>2</number>Out of the shares so transferred and vested, the Central 
Government shall, immediately thereafter, by notification, provide for 
the transfer of not less than ten shares of every such company to such 
persons as may be specified in the notification to enable the Indian 
insurance company to function as a Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>257152</tid>
<number>3</number>Every notification made under sub- section (2) shall specify 
the names and description of the persons to whom the shares are 
transferred and the particulars of the shares which are transferred to 
each such person.

</section>

<section><tid>83748</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of every notification made under sub- section (2) 
shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be sent by the Central 
Government to the concerned Indian insurance company, who shall, on 
receipt of such copy, and notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Companies Act or in its articles of association, forthwith rectify its 
register of members by including therein the persons mentioned in the 
notification as the holders of the shares specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>18708</tid>
<number>5</number>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that the 
transfer and vesting of shares effected under sub- section (1) shall 
not be deemed to affect any right of the Indian insurance company 
subsisting immediately before the appointed day against any 
shareholder to recover from him any sum of money on the ground that 
shareholder has not paid or credited to the insurer the whole or any 
part of the value of the shares held by him or on any other ground 
whatsoever.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>208</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1672843</tid>
<number> 5</number> Transfer of undertakings of other existing insurers.
<section><tid>149526</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
the appointed day, the undertaking of every existing insurer who is 
not an Indian insurance company shall stand transferred to and vested 
in the Central Government and the Central Government shall immediately 
thereafter provide, by notification, for the transfer to and vesting 
in such Indian insurance company, as it may specify in the 
notification, of that undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>1981023</tid>
<number>2</number>Any notification made under sub- section (1) may provide that 
any of the undertakings aforesaid may be transferred to and vested in 
more than one Indian insurance company in such manner and subject to 
such conditions as may be specified in the notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>937950</tid>
<number> 6</number> Effect of transfer of undertakings.
<section><tid>1524004</tid>
<number>1</number>The undertaking of  
every such existing insurer as is referred to in section 5 shall be 
deemed to include all assets, rights, powers, authorities and 
privileges and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances, 
reserve funds, investments and all other rights and interests in, or 
arising out of, such property as were immediately before the appointed 
day in the ownership, possession, power or control of such existing 
insurer in relation to the undertaking, whether within or without 
India, and all books of accounts, registers, records and all other 
documents of whatever nature relating thereto, and shall also be 
deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of 
whatever kind then subsisting of the existing insurer in relation to 
the undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>913075</tid>
<number>2</number>Unless otherwise expressly provided by this Act, all deeds, 
bonds, agreements, powers of attorney, grants of legal representation 
and other instruments of whatever nature subsisting or having effect 
immediately before the appointed day and to which any such insurer as 
is referred to in section 5 is a party or which are in favour of such 
existing insurer shall be of as full force and effect against or in 
favour of the Indian insurance company in which the undertaking or the 
part to which the instrument relates has vested and may be enforced or 
acted upon as fully and effectually as if, in the place of the 
existing insurer referred to in section 5, the Indian insurance 
company in which the undertaking or any part thereof has vested had 
been a party thereto, or as if they had been issued in its favour.

</section>

<section><tid>1722232</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other 
proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any business of the 
undertaking which has been transferred under section 5 is pending by 
or against any such existing insurer as is referred to in that 
section, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way 
prejudicially affected

<pagefootnote><pagenum>209</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by reason of the transfer of the undertaking or of anything contained 
in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Indian insurance 
company in which the undertaking or the part to which the proceeding 
relates has vested.


</section>

<section><tid>450369</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that in the 
case of a foreign insurer or, as the case may be, the Life Insurance 
Corporation, the provisions of section 5 and of the preceding sub- 
sections shall only apply to the extent to which any property 
appertains, in the former case, to the general insurance business 
carried on in India and, in the latter case, to the general insurance 
business carried on, whether within or without India, and to rights 
and powers acquired, and to debts, liabilities and obligations 
incurred and to contracts, agreements and other instruments made by 
the foreign insurer or the Life Insurance Corporation, as the case may 
be, for the purpose of such general insurance business and to legal 
proceedings relating to those purposes, and the said provisions shall 
be construed accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>142597</tid>
<number>5</number>If any question arises as to whether any property appertains 
to any such general insurance business as is referred to in this 
section or whether any rights, powers, liabilities or obligations were 
acquired or incurred or any contract, agreement or other instrument 
was made by the foreign insurer or the Life Insurance Corporation, as 
the case may be, for the purposes of any such business or whether any 
documents relate to those purposes, the question shall be referred to 
the Central Government which shall, after giving an opportunity of 
being heard to the persons interested in the matter, decide it in such 
manner as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287209</tid>
<number> 7</number> Transfer of service of existing employees in certain cases.

<section><tid>718050</tid>
<number>1</number>Every whole- time officer or other employee of an existing insurer  
other than an Indian insurance company who was employed by that 
insurer wholly or mainly in connection with his general insurance 
business immediately before the appointed day shall, on the appointed 
day, become an officer or other employee, as the case may be, of the 
Indian insurance company in which the undertaking of that insurer or 
that part of the undertaking to which the service of the officer or 
other employee relates has vested, and shall hold his office or 
service under the Indian insurance company on the same terms and 
conditions and with the same rights to pension, gratuity and other 
matters as would have been admissible to him if there

<pagefootnote><pagenum>210</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

had been no such vesting, and shall continue to do so unless and until 
his employment in the Indian insurance company in which the 
undertaking or part has vested is terminated or until his 
remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by that Indian 
insurance company:

Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any such 
officer or other employee who has given, in writing, notice to the 
Central Government or to any person nominated in this behalf by that 
Government before the appointed day intimating his intention of not 
becoming an officer or employee of the Indian insurance company in 
whom the undertaking or part thereof to which his service relates has 
vested.


</section>

<section><tid>397465</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any person was a whole- 
time officer or employee, or as to whether any officer or employee, 
was employed wholly or mainly in connection with the general insurance 
business of the existing insurer referred to in sub- section (1), 
immediately before the appointed day, the question shall be referred 
within a period of two years from the appointed day and not 
thereafter, to the Central Government which shall, after giving an 
opportunity of being heard to the person concerned in the matter, 
decide it in such manner as it thinks fit and such decision shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>196230</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other employee 
under sub- section (1) shall not entitle any such officer or other 
employee to any compensation under that Act or such other law, and no 
such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1114954</tid>
<number> 8</number> Provident, superannuation, welfare and other funds.
<section><tid>1713628</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
an existing insurer has established a provident, superannuation, 
welfare or any other fund for the benefit of his employees and 
constituted a trust in respect thereof (hereafter in this section  
  referred to as an existing trust), the moneys standing to the credit 
of such fund on the appointed day, together with any other assets 
belonging to such fund, shall stand transferred to and vested in the 
Indian insurance company on the appointed day free from any such 
trust.

</section>

<section><tid>1616155</tid>
<number>2</number>Where all the employees of the Life Insurance Corporation or 
any other existing insurer do not become employees of an Indian 
insurance company, the monies and other assets belonging to any such 
fund as is referred to in sub- section (1), shall be apportioned

<pagefootnote><pagenum>211</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

between the trustees of the fund and the Indian insurance company in 
the prescribed manner; and in case of any dispute about such 
apportionment the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be 
final.


</section>

<section><tid>490989</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the undertaking of an existing insurer has vested in 
more than one Indian insurance company, the Central Government may, by 
order, provide for the apportionment among such Indian insurance 
companies of monies and other assets belonging to any existing trust 
relating to that undertaking in such manner as in its opinion may be 
appropriate.

</section>

<section><tid>683336</tid>
<number>4</number>The Indian insurance company shall as soon as may be after 
the appointed day constitute in respect of the moneys and other assets 
which are transferred to and vested in it under this section one or 
more trusts having objects as similar to the objects of the existing 
trusts as in the circumstances may be practicable.

</section>

<section><tid>1387527</tid>
<number>5</number>Where all the moneys and other assets belonging to an 
existing trust are transferred to and vested in an Indian insurance 
company under this section, the trustees of such trust shall, as from 
the appointed day, stand discharged from the trust, except as respects 
things done or omitted to be done before the appointed day.
CHAP

GENERAL INSURANCE CORPORATION OF INDIA

CHAPTER III

GENERAL INSURANCE CORPORATION OF INDIA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1542000</tid>
<number> 9</number> Formation of General Insurance Corporation of India.
<section><tid>1596948</tid>
<number>1</number>As  
soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the Central 
Government shall form a Government company in accordance with the 
provisions of the Companies Act, to be known as the General Insurance 
Corporation of India for the purpose of superintending, controlling 
and carrying on the business of general insurance.

</section>

<section><tid>1333602</tid>
<number>2</number>The authorised capital of the Corporation shall be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> rupees 
two hundred and fifty crores, divided into two hundred and fifty lakhs 
fully paid- up shares] of one hundred rupees each, out of which rupees 
five crores shall be the initial subscribed capital of the 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>125393</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), it shall not be necessary to add the word" Limited" 
as the last word of the name of the Corporation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>212</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>872226</tid>
<number>10</number>Transfer to Corporation of shares vested in Central 
Government. All the shares in the capital of every Indian insurance 
company which stand transferred to and vested in the Central 
Government by virtue of section <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> with the exception of the shares 
transferred to any person under sub- section (2) of that section] 
shall, immediately after such vesting, stand transferred to and vested 
in the Corporation and every Indian insurance company shall forthwith 
give effect to such transfer of shares and rectify its register of 
members by including therein the Corporation as the holder of such 
shares.
CHAP

AMOUNTS TO BE PAID FOR ACQUISITIONS

CHAPTER IV

AMOUNTS TO BE PAID FOR ACQUISITIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1417902</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amounts to be paid for transfer and vesting of shares or 
undertakings.
<section><tid>918941</tid>
<number>1</number>For the transfer of the shares of each Indian  
insurance company to, and vesting in, the Central Government, under 
section 4, there shall be paid by the Central Government to the 
Corporation, for distribution to the shareholders of each such 
company, the amount specified against such company in the 
corresponding entry under column (3) of Part A of the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>417439</tid>
<number>2</number>For the transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government, 
under section 5, of the undertaking of each existing insurer, who is 
not an Indian insurance company, there shall be paid by the Central 
Government to the Corporation, for payment to each such existing 
insurer, the amount specified against such insurer in the 
corresponding entry under column (3) of Part B of the Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1266062</tid>
<number> 12</number> Disbursement of amounts by Corporation.
<section><tid>85321</tid>
<number>1</number>The total amount  
paid by the Central Government under section 11 shall be treated as 
additional contribution to the subscribed capital of the Corporation 
and such additional subscribed capital shall stand allotted to, and 
vested in, the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>561271</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall distribute the amount paid to it under 
section 11, to the shareholders of each Indian insurance company and 
to each existing insurer, who is not an Indian insurance company, in 
accordance with their rights and interests, and, if there is any doubt 
or dispute as to the right, or extent of the right, of any person to 
receive the whole or any part of such amount, refer such doubt or 
dispute to the Central Government for determination and thereafter act 
in accordance with the determination made by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1533138</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (2), the amount 
referred to in section 11 shall be given in accordance with the 
provisions of section 13, section 14 or section 15, as the case may 
be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1819444</tid>
<number> 13</number> Mode of payment.
<section><tid>158057</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the amount referred to in section  
 11 is to be given--

<subsection><tid>482989</tid>
<number>a</number>to the members of an Indian insurance company, the 
amount due to each such member shall be paid in full, 
where it does not exceed twenty- five thousand rupees, 
and where it exceeds twenty- five thousand rupees, each 
such member shall be paid twenty- five thousand rupees 
and the balance of the amount due to such member shall 
be paid to him in three equal annual instalments, the 
first of which shall fall due on the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1696421</tid>
<number>b</number>to a foreign insurer, it shall be given to him in cash 
within three months from the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>675101</tid>
<number>c</number>to the Life Insurance Corporation, it shall be given to 
it in three equal annual instalments, the first of 
which shall fall due on the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1141428</tid>
<number>d</number>to an existing insurer who is a co- operative society, it 
shall be distributed as soon as may be after the 
appointed day in accordance with the rules of the 
society which will apply in case of dissolution of the 
society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>997878</tid>
<number>e</number>to an existing insurer not falling within any of the 
foregoing provisions, it shall be apportioned by the 
acquiring company among the individual policy- holders 
of the insurer whose policies with that insurer were in 
force on the appointed day and were comprised in the 
undertaking of such insurer in proportion to the 
premiums paid by the policy- holders under such policies 
and every such payment shall be made either--

<subsubsection><tid>393032</tid>
<number>i</number>in cash, to be sent by postal money 
order, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1335709</tid>
<number>ii</number>at the option of the policy- holder, as a 
deduction in the premium due at the time of the 
renewal of the policy and such option shall be 
exercised by the policyholder before the expiry of 
three months from the appointed day (or within  
such further time not exceeding three months as 
the Central Government may, on the application of 
  the policy- holder, allow); and the option so 
exercised shall be final and shall not be altered 
or rescinded after it has been exercised:
Provided that if any policy- holder fails to 
exercise his option within the time allowed, he 
shall be deemed


<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to have exercised his option in favour of payment 
in cash by postal money order.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1259180</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any amount is payable whether in instalments or 
otherwise under the provisions of this section, the unpaid amount, 
where its payment has become due, shall carry interest at the rate of 
four per cent. per annum from the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1009103</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amount payable to shareholders may be paid to named persons 
instead in certain cases.
<section><tid>1964141</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained  
elsewhere in this Act, if a majority in number of the persons, who, 
immediately before the appointed day, were registered in the books of 
an Indian insurance company as the members thereof, and representing 
two- thirds in value of the amount payable to the Indian insurance 
company, agree either in person or by proxy at a meeting specially 
convened for the purpose that the amount so payable instead of being 
distributed among the members, shall be given to any such person or 
body of persons as the members may nominate either at that meeting or 
subsequently for the purpose of carrying on any business, and the 
Central Government is satisfied that due provision has been or will be 
made for the payment of the value of their respective shares to 
persons who have dissented from the reasolution, the amount may be 
given to the person or body of persons so nominated in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as the Central Government may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1529688</tid>
<number>2</number>No resolution passed at any such meeting as is referred to in 
sub- section (1) held after the appointed day shall have any effect 
unless the meeting has been convened after obtaining the approval of 
the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1927394</tid>
<number>15</number>Payment into court in case of rival claims. Where a claim to 
the amount payable under section 11 is made by two or more persons 
adversely to one another, the corporation may cause the amount to be 
deposited in any civil court having jurisdiction in that behalf and 
the court shall decide as to whom the payment shall be made.

</article>



 </act>