<act><title>

 The Cine-Workers 
    and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Rules, 19841</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation 
    of Employment) Rules, 1984.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on 1st day of October, 1984.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
 <number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires:—
 <section>
<number>1</number> ‘Act’ 
    means the Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) 
    Act, 1981 (50 of 1981);
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> ‘tribunal’ 
    means a cine-workers tribunal constituted under section 7 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> ‘Forms’ 
    means a Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> ‘section’ 
    means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> ‘leave’ 
    means earned leave, medical leave, casual leave, maternity leave;
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> ‘leave not 
    due’ means leave which is not due to the cine-worker but which may be 
    granted to him in anticipation of it being earned subsequently;
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    ‘quarantine leave’ means leave of absence from duty by reason of the 
    presence of an infectious disease in the family or household of a 
    cine-worker;
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> ‘study 
    leave’ means leave granted to a cine-worker to enable him to undergo any 
    special course of training which may be of use to him in his career.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Form of 
    agreement under section 3.—Agreement 
    as envisaged in section 3 of the Act shall be as in Form ‘A’.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Applications.—An 
    application under section 4 or section 7 for the reference of a dispute to a 
    conciliation officer or a tribunal shall be made in Form ‘B’ and shall be 
    delivered personally or forwarded by registered post to the Secretary to the 
    Government of India in the
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Ministry 
    of Labour] in triplicate. The application shall be accompanied by a 
    statement setting forth the following information:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   Name of the parties to the dispute;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the specific matters in dispute;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the total number of cine-workers 
      employed in the establishment affected;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   an estimate of the number of 
      cine-workers affected or likely to be affected by the dispute; and
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   the efforts made by the parties 
      themselves to adjust the dispute.
</section>





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Attestation of application.—The 
    application and the statement accompanying it shall be signed:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in the case of a producer, by the 
      producer himself;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in the case of cine-workers, either by 
      the president and secretary of a trade union of the cine-workers or by 
      five representatives of the cine-workers duly authorised in this behalf at 
      a meeting of the cine-workers held for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   in the case of an individual 
      cine-worker, by the cine-worker himself or by any officer of the trade 
      union of which he is a member or by another cine-worker in the same 
      establishment duly authorised by him in this behalf provided that such 
      cine-worker is not a member of a different trade union.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Conciliation Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    conciliation officer on receipt of notice of the strike or lockout, shall 
    forthwith arrange to interview both the producer and the cine-workers 
    concerned with the dispute at such place and time as he may deem fit and 
    shall endeavour to bring about a settlement of the dispute in question.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    Conciliation Officer receives any information about an existing or 
    apprehended disputes and he considers it necessary to intervene in the 
    dispute, he shall give formal intimation in writing to the parties concerned 
    declaring his intention to commence conciliation proceedings with effect 
    from such date as may be specified therein.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Parties 
    to submit statement.—The 
    producers or the party representing cine-workers or in the case of the 
    individual cine-worker, the cine-worker himself involved in a dispute, shall 
    forward a statement setting forthwith the specific matter in the dispute to 
    the conciliation officer concerned, whenever his intervention in the dispute 
    is required.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    The conciliation officer for resolving the dispute may hold a meeting of the 
    representatives of both parties jointly or of each party separately.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> 
      The conciliation officer shall conduct proceeding expeditiously and in 
      such manner as he may deem fit.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Proceeding before the tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Central Government refers any dispute for adjudication to a 
    tribunal within two weeks of the date of receipt of the order of reference, 
    the party representing workmen or in the case of individual workman, the 
    workman himself and the producer involved in the dispute shall file with the 
    tribunal a statement of demands relating to the issues as are included in 
    the order of reference and shall also forward a copy of such statement to 
    each one of the opposite parties involved in the said dispute.
 
Provided that 
    where the tribunal considers it necessary, it may,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   extend the time limit for filing of 
      such statement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   reduce the time limit for filing of 
      such statement to one week in emergent cases for reasons to be recorded in 
      writing.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   where both the parties agree, reduce 
      the time limit for filing of each statement as per agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   where both the parties agree, dispense 
      with the requirement of filing such statement altogether;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   allow at any stage of the proceeding; 
      amendments to such statement to the extent as may be necessary for the 
      purpose of determining the real issues included in the order of reference.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Within two 
    weeks of the receipt of the statement under sub-rule (1), the opposite party 
    shall file its rejoinder with the tribunal and simultaneously forward a copy 
    thereof to the other party;
 
Provided that 
    such rejoinder shall relate only to such of the issues as are included in 
    the order of reference:
 
Provided 
    further that where the tribunal considers it necessary it may,
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   extend the time limit for filing of 
      such rejoinder;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   reduce the time limit for filing of 
      such rejoinder to one week in emergent cases for reasons to be recorded in 
      writing;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   where both the parties agree, reduce 
      the time limit for filing of such rejoinder as per agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   where both the parties agree; dispense 
      with the requirement of filing such rejoinder altogether;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   allow at any stage of the proceedings 
      amendments to such rejoinder to the extent as may be necessary for the 
      purpose of determining the real issues included in the order of reference.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    tribunal shall ordinarily fix the date for the first hearing of the dispute 
    within 6 weeks of the date on which it was referred for adjudication:
 
Provided that 
    the tribunal may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, fix a later date 
    for the first hearing of the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    hearing shall ordinarily be continued from day-to-day and arguments shall 
    follow immediately after the closing of evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    tribunal shall ordinarily not grant any adjournment for a period exceeding a 
    week at a time, not more than three adjournments in all at the instance of 
    any one of the parties to the dispute:
 
Provided that 
    the tribunal for reasons to be recorded in writing grant an adjournment 
    exceeding a week or more than 3 adjournments at the instance of any one of 
    the parties to the dispute;
 
Provided 
    further that the producer should deposit the disputed amount with the 
    Tribunal pending finalisation of the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    tribunal shall make a memorandum of the substance of evidence of each 
    witness:
 
Provided that 
    the tribunal may follow the procedure laid down in rule 5 of order XVIII of 
    the first Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) if it 
    considers necessary so to do in view of the nature of the particular dispute 
    pending before it.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
 <number>11</number> Place 
    and time of hearing.—Subject to 
    the provisions contained in rules 6 and 7, the sittings of the Conciliation 
    Officer and the tribunal shall be held at such times and places as the 
    presiding officer may fix and Conciliation Officer or the presiding officer 
    as the case may be, shall inform the parties of the same in such manner as 
    he thinks fit.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Evidence.—The tribunal may 
    accept, admit or call for evidence at any stage of the proceedings before it 
    and in such manner as it may think fit.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number> A 
      tribunal may grant to any party to any proceedings before it, such interim 
      or other reliefs (whether subject to any conditions or not), including 
      stay of any order, issue of any injunction or direction in regard to 
      payment of wages or other amounts payable under the agreement referred to 
      in section 3, setting aside any unilateral termination of contract or the 
      dismissal of a worker or reinstating a worker, as it deems just and proper 
      in the circumstances of the case.
 Provided that the Tribunal shall not grant any 
      such interim relief unless all the parties to the proceeding have been 
      served with a notice on the application for such interim relief and have 
      been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard:
 Provided further that the Tribunal may, having 
      regard to the nature of the interim relief sought and the circumstances of 
      the case, pass appropriate orders granting such interim relief as it deems 
      just and proper in the circumstances of the case before the notice 
      referred to in the proceeding proviso is served on the parties to the 
      proceeding:
 Provided also that where the Tribunal makes any 
      order under the proviso immediately proceeding, it shall record the 
      reasons for making the order before complying with the requirements 
      specified in the first proviso.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> The 
    summons.—The summons issued by a 
    tribunal shall be in Form ‘C’ and may require any person to produce before 
    it any books, papers or other documents and things in the possession of or 
    under the control of such person in any way relating to the matter under 
    investigation or adjudication by the tribunal which the tribunal thinks 
    necessary for the purpose of such investigation or adjudication.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Service 
    of summons or notice.—Subject to 
    the provision contained in rule 18, any notice, summons, process or order 
    issued by a tribunal shall be served either personally or by post. In the 
    event of refusal by the party concerned to accept the said notice, summons, 
    process or order, the same shall be sent by registered post.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Description of parties in certain cases.—Where 
    in any proceeding before a tribunal, there are numerous persons arrayed on 
    any side, such persons shall be described as follows:—
 <section>
<number>1</number> all such 
    persons as are members of any trade union or association shall be described 
    by the name of such trade union or association; and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> all such 
    persons as are not member of any trade union or association shall be 
    described in such manner as the tribunal may determine.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Manner 
    of service in the case of numerous persons as parties to dispute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where there are numerous persons as parties to any proceedings before a 
    tribunal and such persons are members of any trade union or association, the 
    service of notice on the secretary or where there is no secretary, on the 
    principal officer of the trade union or association shall be done deemed to 
    be service on such persons.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    there are numerous persons as parties to any proceedings before a tribunal 
    and such persons are not members of any trade union or association, the 
    tribunal shall where personal service is not practicable, cause the service 
    of any notice to be made by affixing the same at or near the main entrance 
    of the establishment concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A notice 
    served in the manner specified in sub-rule 2 shall also be considered as 
    sufficient service in the case of such workman who cannot be ascertained and 
    found.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Procedure at the first sitting.—At 
    the first sitting of a tribunal, the presiding officer shall call upon the 
    parties in such order as he may think fit to state their case.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Tribunal may proceed ex-parte.—If 
    without sufficient cause being shown, any party to proceedings before a 
    tribunal fails to attend or to be represented, the tribunal may proceed as 
    if the party had duly attended or had been represented.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>20</number> A 
      Conciliation Officer or a Tribunal may enter in any premises in occupation 
      of the party to the dispute after giving a reasonable notice to the party 
      concerned for the purpose of making enquiries under this 
      Act.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Power 
    of Tribunals.—Every tribunal 
    shall have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) when trying a suit, in respect of the 
    following matters, namely:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   enforcing the attendance of any person 
      and examining him on oath;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   compelling the production of documents 
      and material objects;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   issuing commissions for the 
      examination of witnesses;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   discovery and inspection;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   power of order—any point to be proved 
      by affidavit.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Appointment of Assessors.—For any 
    proceedings before the Tribunal, the Assessors may be appointed under 
    sub-section (4) of section 7 of the Act, to advise the Tribunal.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>23</number> 
      The tribunal shall have power to award damages in and the cost of an 
      incidental to any proceeding before it.
 
  </article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



 The Cine-Workers 
    and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Rules, 1984
 



 

FORM ‘A’ 

    (See rule 3)
 


An agreement between Film Producer 
    and Cine Worker
 


This agreement is made on 
    this................of....................20..... between Messres........................having 
    office at.................................... (a sole proprietory concern/a 
    firm registered under the Partnership Act, 1932/a Company incorporated and 
    registered under the Companies Act, 1956) (hereinafter referred to as the 
    “Producer” on the first part and Shri/Smt./Kum. 
    ...........................................................son/daughter/wife 
    of Shri............................. residing 
    at................................(hereinafter referred to as the “Cine 
    Worker”) on the second part. The terms ‘Producer’ and ‘Cine-Worker’ shall 
    include their heirs, successors, administrators and legal representatives:
 


WHEREAS the Producer is engaged in the 
    production of a talkie film, his production 
    No..........................tentatively titled, as...................... 
    in.......................... language in 35 mm/16mm/70 mm gauge/Cinemascope, 
    in colour/black and white:
 


WHEREAS the said producer is desirous to 
    engage the Cine Worker in the capacity of a 
    .................................in the aforesaid film and the Cine Worker 
    accepts the same:
 


Now, therefore this agreement is made as 
    follows:
 


1. That both the parties agree that the 
    duration of this agreement shall be from the date hereof till the completion 
    of the film and this period shall not exceed consecutive months.
 


2. That the Cine-Worker agrees to attend 
    studio, location or work place as the case may be subject to the requirement 
    of his previous engagement and on his confirmation, to his respective job 
    punctually as and when he shall be required by a written intimation by the 
    Producer or the person duly authorised by him in writing.
 


3. That in consideration of the Cine-Worker’s 
    services, as aforesaid, the Producer agrees to pay and the Cine-Worker 
    agrees to receive a sum of Rs................ 
    ........................(Rupees.....................) payable as advance on 
    signing of this agreement and the balance of Rs.................payable 
    in...............equal instalments.
 


4. That in the event of the film being not 
    complete within the stipulated period and the Producer still needing the 
    services of the Cine-Worker to complete the film, the producer agrees to pay 
    and the Cine-Worker agrees to receive additional remuneration on pro-rata 
    basis, payable in the same manner as stated in clause 3 above, till the 
    completion of the film.
 


5. That in case the assignment of the 
    Cine-Worker is completed earlier than the period stipulated in clause 1 and 
    4 above, the Producer shall settle the account of the Cine-Worker and pay 
    the remaining balance of the agreement amount in full before the 
    commencement of the re-recording work/censor of the film, whichever is 
    earlier.
 


6. It is agreed by the Producer that for the 
    purposes of this agreement,
 
 


(a)  a working day shall mean a period not 
      exceeding eight consecutive hours (to include one hour’s break for rest 
      and refreshments);
 


(b)  a working week shall mean a six-day 
      week from Monday to Saturday, both inclusive, and the Cine-Worker is not 
      liable to work on Sundays and Public Holidays;
 


(c)  the Cine-Worker shall not be required 
      to work for more than five consecutive hours without a break; and
 


(d)  a period of not less than twelve hours 
      shall elapse between the Cine-Workers’ release from the 
      studio/location/work-place and the next succeeding call.

 


7. That the Cine-Worker shall if so required,
 
 


(a)  attend the studio, location or 
      work-place as the case may be earlier than the scheduled time of the 
      shift, for preparatory work, and in that case, he/she shall be paid by the 
      Producer extra wages at the rate of Rs...................per hour or part 
      thereof for such early attendance.
 


(b)  continue to work beyond the working 
      day, with one hour break and in that case he/she shall be paid by the 
      Producer extra wages at the rate of Rs........................ for the 
      work during the extended hours and refreshments, and transport facilities.

 


8. That the Producer shall provide transport 
    and food or pay travelling allowances to and fro to report to duty and food 
    allowance while on duty as are customary or fixed by bilateral arrangements 
    between the Producers and Cine-Workers’ representative organisations.
 


9. That the Producer shall also pay for all 
    travelling and accommodation expenses, fares, cost of food and such other 
    allowances as are customary when the Cine-Worker is required to work on 
    location outdoors.
 


10. That the Producer shall get the 
    Cine-Worker insured for any injury or damage to his/her person including 
    death caused by accident arising out of or in the course of his/her 
    employment and/or during the period of his/her assignment under this 
    agreement.
 


11. That where the Producer is prevented from 
    proceeding with the production of the film by reason of fire, riot, natural 
    calamity, order of the public authority or any other reason beyond his 
    control:—
 
 


(a)  he shall be entitled to suspend the 
      operation of this agreement during the period of suspension of production 
      in case the production is suspended. The producer shall serve notice in 
      writing of such suspension on the Cine Worker and shall pay all his/her 
      dues up to the date of service of such notice. Upon resumption of work on 
      the film, this agreement shall revive and shall remain valid for the 
      period stipulated in clause 1, excluding the period of suspension 
      therefrom; or
 


(b)  he shall be entitled to terminate this 
      agreement as from the cessation of production, in case the production 
      ceases completely. The producer shall serve a notice in writing of such 
      cessation on the Cine-Worker and make payment of all the amount due to the 
      Cine-Worker at the time of termination.

 


12. That in case if the Producer desires to 
    terminate this agreement before the expiry of its term for reasons other 
    than misconduct in relation to performance of the Cine-Worker's duties or of 
    his/her unwillingness to perform the services required under this agreement 
    the Producer shall be entitled to do so only upon payment of the balance of 
    the stipulated amount of the agreement. Only after such payment to the 
    Cine-Worker, the Producer shall be entitled to employ another Cine-Worker in 
    his/her place.
 


13. That the Producer shall have the right to 
    terminate this agreement on ground of misconduct on the part of the 
    Cine-Worker in relation to performance of his/her duties or his/her 
    unwillingness to perform the services required under the agreement, upon 
    payment to the Cine-Worker of the amount due at the time of termination, 
    calculated taking into consideration the Cine-Worker’s total work in the 
    film and the work he/she has completed till the date of termination of this 
    agreement. Termination under this clause shall not be made unless the 
    charges of the Producer against the Cine-Worker are proved before a forum 
    comprising equal number of representatives of the Producers’ Organisation 
    and the Cine-Workers’ Organisation to which the Producer and the Cine-Worker 
    respectively may belong. The decision of the forum shall be binding on both 
    the parties. The Producer can engage another Cine-Worker for the job towards 
    this agreement only after the forum has given a decision in favour of such 
    termination and the Cine-Worker has been paid all his dues.
 


14. That in case of premature termination of 
    this agreement, it shall be the option of the Producer whether or not to 
    retain the work of the Cine-Worker in the film and at the same time, it 
    shall be option of the Cine-Worker whether or not to allow his/her name to 
    go on the credit titles of the film.
 


15. That the Producer shall have the right to 
    decide the manner of representing the Cine-Worker’s personality on the 
    screen, his/her clothes, make-up and hair-style and the Cine-Worker shall 
    fully and willingly comply with the direction of the Producer in this 
    regard, provided that the requirements of the Producer in this respect have 
    been notified to the Cine-Worker and accepted by him/her.
 


16. That the Cine-Worker agrees that he/she 
    shall render his/her services to the best of his/her ability in such manner 
    as the Producer or, at his instance, the Director of the film may direct and 
    shall comply with all reasonable instructions that he may give for the 
    production of the film.
 


17. That the Cine-Worker, shall comply with 
    all the regulations of the studio location or work-place as the case may be.
 


18. That the Producer shall not without the 
    consent in writing of the Cine-Worker, assign or transfer the benefit of 
    this agreement to any other person.  
 


19. That the provisions of the Employees’ 
    Provident Funds and Misc. Provisions Act, 1952 shall be applicable to this 
    agreement.
 


20. That the Producer shall not utilise the 
    work of the Cine-Worker in any film other than the film under this 
    agreement, without prior permission of the Cine-Worker.
 


The parties have put their hands to this 
    agreement on the date, month and year said above in the presence of each 
    other and in the presence of the witnesses.
 

 
 
 
 
 

1. Witness
 
 

Producer

 
 
 

    Name
 
 

 

 
 
 

    Address
 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 

 
 
 

2. Witness
 
 

Cine - Worker

 
 
 

    Name
 
 

 

 
 
 

    Address
 
 

 


 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



 The Cine-Workers 
    and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Rules, 1984
 



 

FORM ‘B’ 

    (See rule 4)
 


Form of application for reference of 
    a dispute  

    to a Conciliation Officer or a tribunal under  

    section 4 or section 7 of the 1981 Act
 


 The Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers 
    (Regulation and Employment) Act, 1981.
 


Whereas a dispute *is apprehended/exists 
    between........................................... 
    and......................... and it is expedient that the *matters specified 
    in the enclosed statement which are connected/the dispute investigation and 
    settlement relevant to the dispute....................should be referred for 
    adjudication by a Conciliation/Tribunal Officer 
    Tribunal....................................an application is hereby made 
    under section 4 or 7 of the Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers 
    (Regulation of Employment) Act 1981 that the said matters/said dispute 
    should be referred to a Conciliation Officer/Tribunal.
 


This application is made by the undersigned 
    who has/have been duly authorised to do so by virtue of a resolution (copy 
    enclosed) adopted by a majority of the members present at a meeting of 
    the.............................held on the.....................20....
 


A statement giving the particulars required 
    under rule 4 of the Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers, 1984 is 
    enclosed.
 


Signature of 
    employer*..........................
 


or 
    agent..............................................
 



    or.......................................................
 


*Delete whichever is not applicable.
 


Signature of the President of the Trade 
    Union                       

                                                    Secretary to the Trade 
    Union             

                                                    or
 


Signature of five representatives duly 
    authorised                 

                                                    (vide resolution 
    enclosed)............................      

                                                    *or
 


Signature of the Cine-Worker(s)
 


                                        or
 


Signature of the Cine-Worker in the
 


same establishment duly authorised
 


(vide authorisation 
    enclosed)...........................
 

 
 


To,
 


The Secretary to the Government of India,
    
 


1[Ministry of Labour],
 


New Delhi.
 


Statement required under rule 4 of the 
    Cinema-Workers and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Rules, 
    1984;
 
 


(a)  Parties to the dispute including the 
      name and address of the establishment involved.
 


(b)  Specific matters in dispute.
 


(c)  Total number of Cine-Workers employed 
      in the establishment affected.
 


(d)  Estimated number of Cine-Workers 
      affected or likely to be affected by the dispute.
 


(e)  Efforts made by the parties themselves 
      to adjust the dispute.

 

 *Delete whichever is not 
    applicable.
 



    ------------------------
 



        1.    Subs. by G.S.R. 284 dated 1st April, 1986.
 



    -----------------------

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

 The Cine-Workers 
      and Cinema Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Rules, 
      1984
 

 
 

FORM ‘C’ 
(See rule 
      14)
 

Whereas a dispute 
      between...........................and.....................for 
      investigation and settlement has been referred to this Tribunal for 
      adjudication under section (7) of the Cine-Workers and Cinema Theatre 
      Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act,1981, you are hereby summoned to 
      appear before the Tribunal in person on the.........................day 
      of....................at...........o’clock in 
      the.........................noon to answer all material questions relating 
      to the said dispute and you are directed to produce on that day all the 
      books, papers and other documents and things in your possession or under 
      your control in any way to the matter under investigation by this 
      Tribunal.
 

 
 

Dated..........................  
 

Presiding Officer, 
      Tribunal.
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 284, 
    dated 1st April, 1986.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>