<act><title>


THE MUSSALMAN WAKF VALIDATING ACT, 1913</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>1</number> Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Mussalman Wakf Validating  Act, 1913. 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India 
    except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[the territories which, immediately before the 1st 
    November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States]. 
 
 





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, 
    unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>   
    “Wakf” means the permanent dedication by a person professing the Mussalman 
    faith of any property for any purpose recognized by the Mussalman law as 
    religious, pious or charitable.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   
    “Hanafi Mussalman” means a follower of the Mussalman faith who conforms to 
    the tenets and doctrines of the Hanafi school 
    of Mussalman 
    law.  
 
  
 
  


 
 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Power of Mussalmans to create 
    certain wakfs.—It shall be lawful for any person 
    professing the Mussalman faith to create a wakf which in all other respects 
    is in accordance with the provisions of Mussalman law for the following 
    among other purposes:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    for the maintenance and support wholly or partially of his family, children 
    or descendants, and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    where the person creating a wakf is a Hanafi Mussalman, also for his own 
    maintenance and support during his lifetime or for the payment of his debts 
    out of the rents and profits of the property dedicated: 
 
Provided that the ultimate benefit is in 
    such cases expressly or impliedly reserved for the poor or for any other 
    purpose recognised by the Mussalman law as a religious, pious or charitable 
    purpose of a permanent character.
 

 
  


 
 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Wakfs not to be invalid by reason 
    of remoteness of benefit to poor, etc.—No such 
    wakf shall be deemed to be invalid merely because the benefit reserved 
    therein for the poor or other religious, pious or charitable purpose of a 
    permanent nature is postponed until after the extinction of the family, 
    children or descendents of the person creating the wakf.  
  
 
  


 
 

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Saving of local and sectarian 
    custom.—Nothing in this Act shall affect any 
    custom or usage whether local or prevalent among Mussalmans of any 
    particular class or sect.
 
  


 
 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the A.O. (No. 
    3), 1956, for “Part B States”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>