<act><tid>1645922</tid>
<title>THE GOA, DAMAN AND DIU (EXTENSION OF THE CODE OF CIVIL PROCEDURE  
  ANDTHE ARBITRATION ACT) ACT, <year>1965</year></title>

ACT NO. 30 OF <year>1965</year>
An Act to provide for t

[ 25th September, <year>1965</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>372086</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1302202</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Goa,  
Daman and Diu (Extension of the Code of Civil Procedure and the  
  Arbitration Act) Act, <year>1965</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1995554</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594339</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>126293</tid>
<number>a</number>" Goa, Daman and Diu" means the Union territory of Goa, Daman and 
Diu;

</section>

<section><tid>1830293</tid>
<number>b</number>" Lieutenant- Governor" means the administrator of Goa, Daman and 
Diu appointed by the President under article 239 of the Constitution.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1850826</tid>
<number>3</number>Extension of Code of Civil Procedure and Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10  
  of <year>1940</year>), to Goa, Daman and Diu.- The Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5  
  of <year>1908</year>), and the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), as in force in 
the territories to which they generally exte d, are hereby extended 
to, and shall be in force in, Goa, Daman and Diu.


</article>



<article><tid>348983</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1450947</tid>
<number>1</number>So much of any law in force in Goa, Daman  
and Diu as corresponds to the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), or the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), or any part of the 
said Code or Act, as the case may be, shall stand r pealed as from the 
coming into force of this Act in Goa, Daman and Diu:
Provided that the repeal shall not affect-


<subsection><tid>1988981</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any law so repealed or anything duly 
done or suffered thereunder, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>908547</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or 
incurred under any law so repealed, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>141422</tid>
<number>c</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any 
such right, privilege, obligation or liability as aforesaid,
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, notifications 
published, declarations and rules made, places appointed, aggreements 
filed, awards made or filed, scales prescribed, forms framed, 
appointments made and powers conferred under any la w so repealed 
shall, so far as they are consistent with the said Code or, as the 
case may be, 1. 15- 6- <year>1966</year>: vide Notification No. S. O. 1597, dated 
24- 5- <year>1966</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 1471.

the said Act have the same force and effect as if they had been 
respectively published, made, appointed, filed, prescribed, framed and 
conferred under the said Code or the said Act and by the authority 
empowered thereby in such behalf.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1597535</tid>
<number>2</number>In every law or notification passed or issued before the 
commencement of this Act in which reference is made to or to any 
Chapter or section or provision of any law hereby repealed, such 
reference shall, so far as may be practicable, be taken to be m de to 
the said Code or, as the case may be, to the said Act or its 
corresponding Part, Order, section or rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>181122</tid>
<number> 5</number> Rules of construction.-
<section><tid>1706626</tid>
<number>1</number>In the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5   
  of <year>1908</year>), and in the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>),-

<subsection><tid>1617218</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference to any provision of law not in force, or to any 
functionary not in existence, in Goa, Daman and Diu shall be construed 
as a reference to the corresponding law in force, or to the 
corresponding functionary in existence, in that Union ter itory:
Provided that-


<subsubsection><tid>141325</tid>
<number>i</number>if any question arises as to who that corresponding functionary 
is, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1174162</tid>
<number>ii</number>if there is no such corresponding functionary, the 
Lieutenant- Governor shall decide as to who such functionary will be 
and his decision shall be final;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1680954</tid>
<number>b</number>any reference to the State Government shall be construed as a 
reference to the Central Government and also as including a reference 
to the Lieutenant- Governor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1415239</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of facilitating the application in relation to 
Goa, Daman and Diu of the said Code or the said Act, any court or 
other authority may construe it in such manner not affecting the 
substance as may be necessary or proper to adaptt it to he matter 
before the court or other authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>465658</tid>
<number>6</number>Power to remove Difficulties.- If any difficulty arises in giving 
effect in Goa, Daman and Diu to the provisions of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), or the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of  
  <year>1940</year>), extended by this Act to that Union territory, he Central 
Government may, by order in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
or give such directions as appear to it to be necessary for the 
removal of the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>1407364</tid>
<number> 7</number> Consequential provisions.- As from the commencement of this Act, in 
the Goa, Daman and Diu (Judicial Commissioner' s Court) Regulation, 
 <year>1963</year> (Reg. 10 of <year>1963</year>),-
<section><tid>138594</tid>
<number>i</number>in section 8, in sub- section (1), the words" Subject to the 
provisions of any law for the time being in force" shall be inserted 
at the commencement;

</section>

<section><tid>1732199</tid>
<number>ii</number>in section 16, after the words" subject to the provisions of this 
Regulation", the words" and until other provision is made by law" 
shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1732572</tid>
<number>iii</number>in section 17, in sub- section (1), after the word" shall", the 
words", until other provision is made by law," shall be inserted.


</section>

</article>



 </act>