<act><title>


The Central Electricity 
    Authority (Terms and Conditions of Service
    of Chairperson and 
    other members) Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Central Electricity Authority (Terms and Conditions 
    of Service of Chairperson and other Members) Rules, 2005. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Authority” means the Central 
    Electricity Authority established under section 70 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of 
    the Authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Member” means a full‑time member of 
    the Authority, including Chairperson, where the context so requires;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “other Member” means a Member other 
    than a full‑time Member;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expressions used herein but not defined shall have the same 
    meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions contained under sub‑section (5) of sections 70 and 
    73 of the Act, the Authority shall consist of the following:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    Chairperson  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    Member (Economic &amp; Commercial)  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    Member (Grid Operations &amp; Distribution)  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    Member (Hydro)  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    Member (Planning)  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    Member (Power Systems)  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    Member (Thermal).  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson and the Members of the Authority shall be appointed by an order 
    either on deputation basis or on short‑term contract basis, subject to the 
    fulfilling of the eligibility conditions laid down in these Rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Eligibility and term of office of the Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall be eligible for appointment to the office of a Member, 
    including the Chairperson, of the Authority unless he has held—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the post of Chief Engineer or 
    equivalent in the scale of pay of Rs. 18400‑500‑22400 or higher post or 
    scale of pay on a regular basis for at least five years under the Central 
    Government or a State Government;   
 
or  
 
a post equivalent to that of a post mentioned 
    above, under a State Electricity Board or a semi‑Government organisation or 
    a public sector undertaking or an autonomous body or a statutory body or a 
    university or an Indian Institute of Technology or an Indian Institute of 
    Management on a regular basis for at least five years; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    possesses a minimum of three years’ 
    field experience in the relevant field;  
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of the sub‑rule, the expression “relevant field” means relevant 
    field as defined in sub‑section (5) of section 70 of the Act:   
 
Provided that 
    whenever a post of Member or any vacancy thereof is required to be filled 
    up, area of specialisation or discipline shall be decided from amongst the 
    categories listed under sub‑section (5) of section 70 of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub‑section (6) of section 70 of the Act, a Member shall 
    normally hold office for a period not exceeding five years or till he 
    attains the age of superannuation:  
 
Provided that 
    where the prescribed term of office of a Member as provided in sub‑rule (2) 
    expires before he attains the age of superannuation, the Central Government 
    may extend the term of office of such a Member for a further period not 
    exceeding the date of his superannuation in the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    shall cease to be Member of the Authority if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    remains absent, without the prior 
    permission of the Authority, from three consecutive meetings of the 
    Authority; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    having been appointed on deputation, 
    ceases to be in service of the respective State Government, Central 
    Government or any other lending authority; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has been convicted and sentenced to 
    imprisonment for an offence which is in the opinion of the Central 
    Government, involves moral turpitude; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is an un‑discharged insolvent.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number>
Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson of the Authority may resign from his 
    office by giving notice of at least three months to the Central Government, 
    in writing, and on such resignation being accepted by the Government, he 
    shall be deemed to have vacated his office.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member of 
    the Authority may resign from his office after giving notice of at least 
    three months, in writing, to the Chairperson of the Authority who shall 
    forward the same to the Central Government and on such resignation being 
    accepted by the Government, he shall be deemed to have vacated his office.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Pay and 
    Allowances and other terms of the Members including the Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Chairperson of the Authority shall enjoy the status of 
    ex-officio, Secretary to the Government of India and shall carry the 
    same pay and allowances as available to the Secretary to the Government of 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member of 
    the Authority shall enjoy the status of ex-officio, Additional 
    Secretary to the Government of India and shall carry the same pay and 
    allowances as available to the Additional Secretary to the Government of 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The other 
    terms and conditions of service of Chairperson and Members, including 
    entitlement of leave, leave salary, leave travel concession, travelling 
    allowance, medical benefits etc. shall be as are applicable to the Central 
    Government officers of corresponding status.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The pension 
    and leave salary contribution in respect of the Chairperson and Member(s), 
    if they are on deputation to the Authority, shall be paid by the Authority 
    to the respective lending authority in accordance with their rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Allowances and fees payable to other Members.—The 
    other Members shall receive such allowances and fees for attending the 
    meetings of the Authority as may be determined by the Central Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    relax.—Where the Central 
    Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it 
    may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax any of the 
    provisions of these Rules with respect to any class or category of persons.
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>