<act> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Rules, 1938.
  
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>2</number> 

<section><number>1</number> In these rules, “the Act” means the Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925 
(IV of 1925).
 </section><section><number>2</number> All words used herein and 
defined in the Act shall be deemed to have the meanings respectively attributed 
to them by the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>3</number> 
The prescribed authority for the purpose of sub-clause (iv) of clause (b) of 
section 3 and sections 6, 7, and 8 of the Act shall be the officer Commanding 
the unit or the Depot of the unit to which the soldier belongs.
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>4</number> 
The certificate given by a Collector under section 5 of the Act shall be in Form 
A of the Schedule.
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>5</number> 
The notice given by the Court under section 6 of the Act shall be in Form B of 
the Schedule and shall be sent to the prescribed authority care of the General 
Officer Commanding-in-Chief of the Command in which the Court is situated, and 
the certificate of the prescribed authority under section 7 of the Act, shall be 
in Form C of the Schedule.
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>6</number> 
If at any time it appears to the prescribed authority that the circumstances in 
which he certified to the Court under Section 7 of the Act that a postponement 
of the proceedings was necessary in the interests of justice, no longer exist, 
he shall forthwith certify to the Court to that effect in Form D of the 
Schedule.
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>7</number> 
On receipt of a certificate from the prescribed authority under Section of the 
Act that postponement of the proceedings is necessary in the interests of 
justice, the Court shall postpone the proceedings until the receipt of a 
certificate in Form D from the prescribed authority, or until the soldier is 
represented in the proceedings by some person duly authorised to appear, plead 
or act in his behalf.
</article> 
 The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  
Rules, 1938
  
 <article><number>8</number> 
The prescribed authority for the purposes of Section 12 of the Act shall be the 
General Officer Commanding-in-Chief of the Command in which the Court is 
situated.
</article><form>
 

The Indian Soldiers (Litigation)  

Rules, 1938
 

 
 

Schedule 

 

Form A
 

(See rule 4)
 

Collector’s 
certificate under section 5 of the  

Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925
 

From
 

The Collector,
 

District.........................
 

......................................
 

To
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

In re........................           No......................... 
                  of 20........................
 

........................
 

versus
 

........................
 

      No........................., 
dated........................
 

Sir,
 

I have the honour to certify under section 5 of the Indian 
Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925 (IV of 1925), that I have reason to believe 
that……………………son of……………………… who is an Indian soldier ordinarily residing / 
having property in my district and who is a party in the above-mentioned (enter 
suit, appeal, application or other proceedings), now pending in (enter name of 
court), is unable to appear therein.
 

Yours faithfully,
 

 
 

Collector
 

Notes.—(1) This certificate should be sent by post in a 
registered cover or by hand and an acknowledgement should be obtained for it.
 

(2) It should be addressed, in the case of a High Court, to 
the Registrar of the Court, or in the case of a Board of Revenue to the 
Secretary of such Board, or in the case of a Financial Commissioner, to the 
Clerk of the Court, or in other cases to the Presiding Officer of the Court.
 

 
 

Form B
 

(See rule 5)
 

Notice under section 
6 of the Indian Soldiers  

(Litigation) Act, 1925
 

      In the…………………………No………………………… of……………………
 

........................
 

versus
 

........................
 

To
 

The Officer Commanding (enter name of unit / depot of unit.).
 

Care of the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief.
 

………………………………Command.
 

Please take notice that [upon the certificate of the Collector 
of.................. under section 5 of the Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 
1925 (IV of 1925)] [having had reason to believe]1 that........................, 
son of........................ an Indian soldier, who is a party in the 
above-mentioned proceeding now pending in this Court and is not represented by 
any person duly authorized to appear, plead or act on his behalf, is unable to 
appear therein, this Court has, under Section 6 of the said Act, suspended the 
proceedings. If, within the period prescribed in Section 8 of the said Act, no 
certificate is received from you under Section 7 thereof, the Court will, if it 
thinks fit, continue the proceedings.
 

Given under my hand and the seal of the Court, this the 
……………day of …………………… 20................
 

Presiding officer of 
the Court
 

…………………………….....
 

Registrar.
 

Note.—This notice should be sent by post in a 
registered cover, or by hand, and an acknowledgement should be obtained for it.
 

 
 

Form C
 

(See rule 5)
 

Certificate under 
Section 7 of the Indian Soldiers  

(Litigation) Act, 1925
 

From
 

The Officer Commanding,     
 

(enter name of unit/depot of unit)
 

To
 

...................................
 

..................................
 

..................................
 

..........No..............of 20…
 

……………………
 

versus
 

……………………
 

No. , dated
 

Sir,
 

I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your notice, dated 
...................................., under Section 6 of the Indian Soldiers 
(Litigation) Act, 1925, in the abovementioned proceedings, and to certify under 
section 7 of the said Act that…………………… son of 
..................................., in respect of whom the above-mentioned 
notice has been given, is serving under special conditions and that a 
postponement of the proceeding in respect of that soldier is necessary in the 
interests of justice.
 

Yours faithfully,
 

 
 

Officer Commanding
 

Note.—(1) This certificate should be sent by post in a 
registered cover or by hand, and an acknowledgement should be obtained for it.
 

(2) It should be addressed in the case of a High Court, to the 
Registrar of the Court, or in the case of a Board of Revenue to the Secretary of 
such Board, or in the case of a Financial Commissioner, to the Clerk of the 
Court, or in other cases to the Presiding Officer of the Court.
 

 
 

Form D
 

(See rule 6)
 

Certificate under 
Rule 6 of the Indian Soldiers 

Litigation Rules, 1938
 

From
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

To
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

In re……………………No……………………of 20…….
 

……………………
 

versus
 

……………………
 

No. dated
 

Sir,
 

I have the honour to invite a reference to my letter 
No..............., dated ....................................., and to certify 
under Rule 6 of the Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Rules, 1938, that circumstances 
no longer exist for the postponement of the above-mentioned (enter suit, appeal, 
application or other proceeding), now pending in (enter name of Court), wherein 
......................., son of ......................., an Indian soldier, is a 
party.
 

Yours faithfully,
 

 
 

Officer Commanding.
 

Notes.—(1) This certificate should be sent by post in a 
registered cover, or by hand, and acknowledgement should be obtained for it.
 

(2) It should be addressed, in the case of a High Court, to 
the Registrar of the Court, or in the case of a Board of Revenue to the 
Secretary of such Board, or in the case of a Financial Commissioner, to the 
Clerk of the Court, or in other cases to the Presiding Officer of the Court.
 

 
 

————————
 

   1.  One of the two portions within the square brackets 
should, according to the circumstances of each case, be penned through.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>