<act><title>


THE RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENt CESS RULES, 19961</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Research and Development Cess Rules, 1996.
 </section></article><article>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Research 
    and Development Cess Act, 1986 (32 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “authorised dealer” 
    means any person authorised by the Reserve Bank of India to deal in foreign 
    exchange under section 6 of the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 
    1973);
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Board” means the 
    Technology Development Board constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3 
    of the Technology Development Board Act, 1995 (44 of 1995);
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Form” means the form 
    annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    all other words and 
    expression used in these rules, but defined in the Act or the Technology 
    Development Board Act, 1995 (44 of 1995), shall have the meaning 
    respectively assigned to them in those Acts.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Levy of 
    cess.—For the purpose of levy of 
    cess under section 3 of the Act, ‘payment’ shall include—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    payment made towards 
    import of technology as approved by the Central Government in terms of any 
    foreign collaboration agreement, or approved in accordance with the 
    Industrial Policy of the Government of India, in force, from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    payment made towards the 
    cost of drawings and designs in terms of any foreign collaboration agreement 
    as approved by the Central Government or approved in accordance with the 
    Industrial Policy of the Government of India in force from time to time;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    payment made to foreign 
    collaborators or to any other person for or in connection with deputation of 
    technical personnel to India in terms of any foreign collaboration 
    agreement, in accordance with the approval granted by the Central Government 
    or approved in accordance with the Industrial Policy of the Government of 
    India, in force, from time to time;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    any other payment made 
    towards the import of technology approved by the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Manner 
    of payment of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> The cess 
    payable under section 3 of the Act by an industrial concern shall be paid to 
    any office of a specified agency referred to in clause (g) of section 2 of 
    the Act, alongwith the form of challan prescribed under the Central 
    Government Account (Receipts and Payments) Rules, 1983.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    industrial concern shall on or before making any payment towards the import 
    of technology, furnish to the authorised dealer through whom such payment 
    was made the counter-foil of the form referred to in sub-rule (1) evidencing 
    the payment of cess payable under the Act:  
 
Provided that 
    where such payment is not accompanied by the said counter-foil the 
    authorised dealer shall not refuse to accept such payment but report the 
    fact within a period of thirty days to the Board.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Furnishing of statistical and other information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every industrial concern shall, within sixty days from the date of 
    commencement of these rules, furnish the information referred to in section 
    8 of the Act to the Board in Form A containing the particulars of the 
    technology imported or to be imported under any subsisting foreign 
    collaboration agreement.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    industrial concern enters into a foreign collaboration agreement for the 
    import of technology after the commencement of these rules, it shall furnish 
    the information referred to in section 8 of the Act to the Board in Form A 
    within thirty days from the date of entering into the agreement.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any change 
    or modification in the particulars furnished under sub-rules (1) and (2) 
    above, shall be communicated by the industrial concern to the Board 
    immediately but in no case later than thirty days form the date of effecting 
    the modification or change.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Manner 
    of recovery of arrears of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If on a scrutiny of the statistical and other information furnished by an 
    industrial concern under rule 5 or on the basis of a report furnished by any 
    authorized dealer under rule 4 or otherwise, it appears to the Board that an 
    industrial concern has not paid the cess or paid an amount lesser than what 
    is payable under section 3 of the Act, it shall issue a notice to such 
    industrial concern calling upon it to pay the cess or, as the case may be, 
    the difference of cess due, to a specified agency within thirty days of the 
    date of receipt of such notice or within such extended time as the Board may 
    permit in writing.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where on 
    the expiry of the time-limit specified in the notice under sub-rule (1), any 
    industrial concern fails to pay the amount specified in the notice and the 
    Board is satisfied that the amount of cess is due to the Central Government, 
    the officer authorised by the Board in this behalf shall proceed to recover 
    the amount from such industrial concern as sums due to the Central 
    Government as if it were an arrears of land revenue.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purpose of recovery of sums due to Central Government, an officer of the 
    Board authorised in this behalf by the Board, may prepare a certificate 
    signed by him specifying the amount due and send it to the Collector of the 
    district in which the industrial concern has its registered office or 
    principal place of business and the said Collector on receipt of such 
    certificate, shall proceed to recover from the said industrial concern the 
    amount specified thereunder as if it were an arrear of land revenue.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Manner 
    of holding inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> Before 
    imposing any penalty under sub-section (2) of section 9 of the Act the Board 
    shall authorise in writing one or more of its officers to make inquiry into 
    the affairs of the industrial concern.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officer authorised under sub-rule (1) shall issue to the industrial concern 
    a notice addressed to the registered office or principal place of business 
    directing it to show cause as to why the penalty specified in the notice 
    should not be imposed.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    industrial concern may, within thirty days from the date of receipt of the 
    said notice, send to the officer concerned a reply together with copies of 
    documentary or other evidence relied on in such reply.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    officer authorised under sub-rule (1) may, if so requested by the industrial 
    concern, give a personal hearing to enable the industrial concern to explain 
    its stand in regard to the arrears of cess.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If at any 
    stage of inquiry, the officer authorised under sub-rule (1) is satisfied 
    that the default was on account of good or sufficient reason, he shall not 
    proceed further with the inquiry and report the fact to the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If the 
    officer authorised under sub-rule (1) is satisfied after inquiry that there 
    was no good or sufficient reason for the default committed by the industrial 
    concern, he shall send his report to the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> On receipt 
    of the report of the officer authorsed under sub-rule (1), the Board shall 
    impose on the industrial concern, such penalty as it deems fit not exceeding 
    ten times the amount of arrears.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    penalty imposed under sub-rule (7) shall be recoverable in accordance with 
    the procedure laid down in sub-rule (3) of rule 6.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Manner 
    of refund of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
    industrial concern desiring refund of cess paid in excess on account of 
    wrong calculation or revision of payable amounts for the purposes of cess 
    shall apply to the Secretary of the Board in writing with all the supporting 
    documents.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After 
    scrutiny of the application in accordance with the procedure laid down by 
    the Board the dues as found eligible shall be refunded.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    decision on the application for refund shall be communicated within six 
    months of the receipt of the application and the refund, if any, shall be 
    made within sixty days thereafter.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    interest, processing or any other charges shall be payable on such refund by 
    the Board.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Interpretation of the rules.—Where 
    any doubt arises as to the interpretation of these rules, it shall be 
    referred to the Central Government for its decision.  
 
  


</article> 
 THE RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENt CESS RULES 1996
  
 <article><number>10</number> Repeal and saving.—The
Research and Development Cess Rules, 1987 are hereby repealed:
 Provided that such repeal shall 
not effect— 
 <section>        <number>a</number>  the previous operation of the said rules or 
anything duly done or suffered thereunder; or
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  any right, privilege, obligation or liability 
acquired, accrued or incurred under the said rules; or
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>  any penalty incurred in respect of non-payment 
of cess under the said rules; or
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>  any investigation are remedy in respect of such 
right, privilege, obligation of such right, privilege, obligation, liability or 
penalty as aforesaid, and any such investigation or remedy may be instituted, 
continued or enforced and any such penalty may be imposed as if the said rule 
has not been repealed.
  
</section></article><form>
 

THE RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENt CESS RULES 1996
 

 
 

FORM A 
 

[See rule 5 (1) and (2)]
 

DECLARATION
 

      1.   Name and address of the industrial concern 
importing technology.
 

      2.   Name and address of the party outside India 
providing technology (collaborator).
 

      3.   Number and date of Government of India’s 
approval for the foreign collaboration.
 

      4.   Number and date of Reserve Bank of India’a 
approval for the foreign collaboration.
 

      5.   Date of foreign collaboration agreement.
 

      6.   State the nature of the foreign collaboration 
agreement whether—
 

      (a)  technical or 
financial, or technical and financial;
 

      (b)  design/drawings.
 

      7.   State the period for engagement of foreign 
technical personnel, if any.
 

      8.   Number and date of Reserve Bank of India 
approval for engagement of foreign technical personnel.
 

      9.   Period during which technology is likely to be 
transferred.
 

    10.   amount payable towards the import of technology 
under foreign collaboration agreement, for engagement of foreign technical 
personnel and any other payment approved by the Government (State the period, 
currency and amounts to be paid including local payments made in rupees in 
connection with import of technology).
 

    11.   Mode of payment in respect of amounts payable 
under item 10 above.
 

    12.   Amount already remitted (including dates) to 
collaborator (as on date of filling this form).
 

    13.   Period (if any) for which the amount has been 
remitted.
 

    14.   Name and address of the authorised dealer, if 
any, through whom the amount is remitted or is to be remitted.
 

 
 

Date: 
.........................                                          Authorised 
signatory
 

Place: 
........................                               (on behalf of the 
industrial concern)
 

 
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>