<act><title>

The 
    Prevention of Terrorism Act, 2002</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, application, commencement, duration and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Prevention of Terrorism Act, 2002. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person shall be liable to punishment under this Act for every act or 
    omission contrary to the provisions thereof, of which he is held guilty in 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person 
    who commits an offence beyond India which is punishable under this Act shall 
    be dealt with according to the provisions of this Act in the same manner as 
    if such act had been committed in India.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    provisions of this Act apply also to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    citizens of India outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    persons in the service of the 
    Government, wherever they may be; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    persons on ships and aircrafts, 
    registered in India, wherever they may be.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in respect of entries at serial numbers 24 and 25 of the 
    Schedule to this Act, it shall be deemed to have come into force on the 24th 
    day of October, 2001 and shall remain in force for a period of three years 
    from the date of its commencement, but its expiry under the operation of 
    this sub-section shall not affect—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the previous operation of, or anything 
    duly done or suffered under this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any right, privilege, obligation or 
    liability acquired, accrued or incurred under this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any penalty, forfeiture or punishment 
    incurred in respect of any offence under this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any investigation, legal proceeding or 
    remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
    penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid,  
 
and, any such investigation, legal proceeding 
    or remedy may be instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, 
    forfeiture or punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not expired.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Code” means the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Designated Authority” shall mean such 
    officer of the Central Government not below the rank of Joint Secretary to 
    the Government, or such officer of the State Government not below the rank 
    of Secretary to the Government, as the case may be, as may be specified by 
    the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, by a 
    notification published in the Official Gazette;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “proceeds of terrorism” shall mean all 
    kinds of properties which have been derived or obtained from commission of 
    any terrorist act or have been acquired through funds traceable to a 
    terrorist act, and shall include cash irrespective of person in whose name 
    such proceeds are standing or in whose possession they are found;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “property” means property and assets of 
    every description, whether corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, 
    tangible or intangible and deeds and instruments evidencing title to, or 
    interest in, such property or assets and includes bank account;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Public Prosecutor” means a Public 
    Prosecutor or an Additional Public Prosecutor or a Special Public Prosecutor 
    appointed under section 28 and includes any person acting under the 
    directions of the Public Prosecutor;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “Special Court” means a Special Court 
    constituted under section 23;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “terrorist act” has the meaning 
    assigned to it in sub-section (1) of section 3, and the expression 
    “terrorist” shall be construed accordingly;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “State Government”, in relation to a 
    Union territory, means the Administrator thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    words and expressions used but not 
    defined in this Act and defined in the Code shall have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in the Code.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to any enactment or any provision thereof shall, in 
    relation to an area in which such enactment or such provision is not in 
    force, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law or the relevant 
    provision of the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Punishment for terrorist acts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    with intent to threaten the unity, 
    integrity, security or sovereignty of India or to strike terror in the 
    people or any section of the people does any act or thing by using bombs, 
    dynamite or other explosive substances or inflammable substances or firearms 
    or other lethal weapons or poisons or noxious gases or other chemicals or by 
    any other substances (whether biological or otherwise) of a hazardous nature 
    or by any other means whatsoever, in such a manner as to cause, or likely to 
    cause, death of, or injuries to any person or persons or loss of, or damage 
    to, or destruction of, property or disruption of any supplies or services 
    essential to the life of the community or causes damage or destruction of 
    any property or equipment used or intended to be used for the defence of 
    India or in connection with any other purposes of the Government of India, 
    any State Government or any of their agencies, or detains any person and 
    threatens to kill or injure such person in order to compel the Government or 
    any other person to do or abstain from doing any act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    is or continues to be a member of an 
    association declared unlawful under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) 
    Act, 1967 (37 of 1967), or voluntarily does an act aiding or promoting in 
    any manner the objects of such association and in either case is in 
    possession of any unlicensed firearms, ammunition, explosive or other 
    instrument or substance capable of causing mass destruction and commits any 
    act resulting in loss of human life or grievous injury to any person or 
    causes significant damage to any property, 
 

    commits a terrorist act.
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “a terrorist act” shall include the act of raising funds 
    intended for the purpose of terrorism.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    commits a terrorist act, shall,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if such act has resulted in the death 
    of any person, be punishable with death or imprisonment for life and shall 
    also be liable to fine;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in any other case, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life and shall also be liable to fine.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever 
    conspires or attempts to commit, or advocates, abets, advises or incites or 
    knowingly facilitates the commission of, a terrorist act or any act 
    preparatory to a terrorist act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which shall not be less than five years but which may extend to 
    imprisonment for life and shall also be liable to fine.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Whoever 
    voluntarily harbours or conceals, or attempts to harbour or conceal, any 
    person knowing that such person is a terrorist shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life and shall also be liable to fine:  
 
Provided that 
    this sub-section shall not apply to any case in which the harbour or 
    concealment is by the husband or wife of the offender.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person 
    who is a member of a terrorist gang or a terrorist organisation, which is 
    involved in terrorist acts, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to imprisonment for life, or with fine which may extend to 
    rupees ten lakh, or with both.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “terrorist organisation” means an organisation which is 
    concerned with or involved in terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Whoever 
    knowingly holds any property derived or obtained from commission of any 
    terrorist act or has been acquired through the terrorist funds shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to imprisonment for 
    life, or with fine which may extend to rupees ten lakh, or with both.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Whoever 
    threatens any person who is a witness or any other person in whom such 
    witness may be interested, with violence, or wrongfully restrains or 
    confines the witness, or any other person in whom the witness may be 
    interested, or does any other unlawful act with the said intent, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three years and fine.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number>
Possession of certain unauthorised arms, etc.—Where any person is in 
    unauthorised possession of any—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    arms or ammunition specified in columns 
    (2) and (3) of Category I or Category III (a) of Schedule 1 to the Arms 
    Rules, 1962, in a notified area,  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    bombs, dynamite or hazardous explosive 
    substances or other lethal weapons capable of mass destruction or biological 
    or chemical substances of warfare in any area, whether notified or not,  
 
he shall be guilty of terrorist act 
    notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, and be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    imprisonment for life, or with fine which may extend to rupees ten lakh, or 
    with both.
 

    Explanation.—In this section, 
    “notified area” means such area as the State Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, specify.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Enhanced 
    penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any person with 
    intent to aid any terrorist contravenes any provision of, or any rule made 
    under the Explosives Act, 1884 (4 of 1884), the Explosive Substances Act, 
    1908 (6 of 1908), the Inflammable Substances Act, 1952 (20 of 1952), or the 
    Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959), he shall, notwithstanding anything contained in 
    any of the aforesaid Acts or the rules made thereunder, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to imprisonment for life and shall 
    also be liable to fine.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of this section, any person who attempts to contravene or abets, or 
    does any act preparatory to the contravention of any provision of any law, 
    rule or order, shall be deemed to have contravened that provision, and the 
    provisions of sub-section (1) shall, in relation to such person, have effect 
    subject to the modification that the reference to “imprisonment for life” 
    shall be construed as a reference to “imprisonment for ten years”.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Holding 
    of proceeds of terrorism illegal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall hold or be in possession of any proceeds of terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Proceeds 
    of terrorism, whether held by a terrorist or by any other person and whether 
    or not such person is prosecuted or convicted under this Act, shall be 
    liable to be forfeited to the Central Government or the State Government, as 
    the case may be, in the manner provided under this Chapter.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number>
Powers of investigating officers and appeal against order of Designated 
    Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> If an officer (not below the rank of Superintendent of 
    Police) investigating an offence committed under this Act, has reason to 
    believe that any property in relation to which an investigation is being 
    conducted, represents proceeds of terrorism, he shall, with the prior 
    approval in writing of the Director General of the Police of the State in 
    which such property is situated, make an order seizing such property and 
    where it is not practicable to seize such property, make an order of 
    attachment directing that such property shall not be transferred or 
    otherwise dealt with except with the prior permission of the officer making 
    such order, or of the Designated Authority before whom the properties seized 
    or attached are produced and a copy of such order shall be served on the 
    person concerned.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    removal of doubts, it is hereby provided that where an organisation is 
    declared as a terrorist organisation under this Act and the investigating 
    officer has reason to believe that any person has custody of any property 
    which is being used or is intended to be used for the purpose of such 
    terrorist organisation, he may, by an order in writing, seize or attach such 
    property.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    investigating officer shall duly inform the Designated Authority within 
    forty-eight hours of the seizure or attachment of such property.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall 
    be open to the Designated Authority before whom the seized or attached 
    properties are produced either to confirm or revoke the order of attachment 
    so issued:  
 
Provided that 
    an opportunity of making a representation by the person whose property is 
    being attached shall be given.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the 
    case of immovable property attached by the investigating officer, it shall 
    be deemed to have been produced before the Designated Authority, when the 
    investigating officer notifies his report and places it at the disposal of 
    the Designated Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    investigating officer may seize and detain any cash to which this Chapter 
    applies if he has reasonable grounds for suspecting that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    it is intended to be used for the 
    purposes of terrorism;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    it forms the whole or part of the 
    resources of an organisation declared as terrorist organisation under this 
    Act:
 
Provided that 
    the cash seized under this sub-section by the investigating officer shall be 
    released not later than the period of forty-eight hours beginning with the 
    time when it is seized unless the matter involving the cash is before the 
    Designated Authority and such Authority passes an order allowing its 
    retention beyond forty-eight hours.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “cash” means—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    coins and notes in any currency;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    postal orders;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    traveller’s cheques;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    banker’s drafts; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    such other monetary instruments as the 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government may specify 
    by an order made in writing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by an order made by the Designated Authority may prefer an appeal 
    to the Special Court and the Special Court may either confirm the order of 
    attachment of property or seizure so made or revoke such order and release 
    the property.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Forfeiture of proceeds of terrorism.—Where 
    any property is seized or attached on the ground that it constitutes 
    proceeds of terrorism and the Special Court is satisfied in this regard 
    under sub-section (7) of section 7, it may order forfeiture of such 
    property, whether or not the person from whose possession it is seized or 
    attached, is prosecuted in a Special Court for an offence under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Issue of 
    show cause notice before forfeiture of proceeds of terrorism.—
<section><number>1</number>
    no order forfeiting any 
    proceeds of terrorism shall be made under section 8 unless the person 
    holding or in possession of such proceeds is given a notice in writing 
    informing him of the grounds on which it is proposed to forfeit the proceeds 
    of terrorism and such person is given an opportunity of making a 
    representation in writing within such reasonable time as may be specified in 
    the notice against the grounds of forfeiture and is also given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard in the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No order 
    of forfeiture shall be made under sub-section (1), if such person 
    establishes that he is a bona fide transferee of such proceeds for 
    value without knowing that they represent proceeds of terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    be competent for the Special Court to make an order in respect of property 
    seized or attached,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    directing it to be sold if it is a 
    perishable property and the provisions of section 459 of the Code shall, as 
    nearly as may be practicable, apply to the net proceeds of such sale;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    nominating any officer of the Central 
    or State Government, in the case of any other property, to perform the 
    function of the Administrator of such property subject to such conditions as 
    may be specified by the Special Court.
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number>  
    Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved 
    by an order of forfeiture under section 8 may, within one month from the 
    date of the receipt of such order, appeal to the High Court within whose 
    jurisdiction, the Special Court, who passed the order appealed against, is 
    situated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    order under section 8 is modified or annulled by the High Court or where in 
    a prosecution instituted for the contravention of the provisions of this 
    Act, the person against whom an order of forfeiture has been made under
    section 8 is acquitted, such property shall be returned to him and in either 
    case if it is not possible for any reason to return the forfeited property, 
    such person shall be paid the price therefor as if the property had been 
    sold to the Central Government with reasonable interest calculated from the 
    day of seizure of the property and such price shall be determined in the 
    manner prescribed.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number>
Order of forfeiture not to interfere with other punishments.—The 
    order of forfeiture made under this Act by the Special Court, shall not 
    prevent the infliction of any other punishment to which the person affected 
    thereby is liable under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Claims 
    by third party.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any 
    claim is preferred, or any objection is made to the seizure of any property 
    under section 7 on the ground that such property is not liable to seizure, 
    the Designated Authority, before whom such property is produced, shall 
    proceed to investigate the claim or objection:  
 
Provided that 
    no such investigation shall be made where the Designated Authority considers 
    that the claim or objection is designed to cause unnecessary delay.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case 
    claimant or objector establishes that the property specified in the notice 
    issued under section 9 is not liable to be forfeited under the Act, the said 
    notice shall be withdrawn or modified accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number>
Powers of Designated Authority.—The Designated Authority, acting 
    under the provisions of this Act, shall have all the powers of a civil court 
    required for making a full and fair enquiry into the matter before it.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number>
Obligation to furnish information.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in any other law, the officer investigating any offence under this 
    Act, with prior approval in writing of an officer not below the rank of a 
    Superintendent of Police, may require any officer or authority of the 
    Central Government or a State Government or a local authority or a bank, or 
    a company, or a firm or any other institution, establishment, organisation 
    or any individual to furnish information in their possession in relation to 
    such offence, on points or matters, where the investigating officer has 
    reason to believe that such information will be useful for, or relevant to, 
    the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Failure to 
    furnish the information called for under sub-section (1), or deliberately 
    furnishing false information shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, the offence under 
    sub-section (1) shall be tried as a summary case and the procedure 
    prescribed in Chapter XXI of the said Code [except sub-section (2) of 
    section 262] shall be applicable thereto.
  






































 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number>
Certain transfers to be null and void.—Where, after the issue of an 
    order under section 7 or issue of a notice under section 9, any property 
    referred to in the said order or notice is transferred by any mode 
    whatsoever, such transfer shall, for the purpose of the proceedings under 
    this Act, be ignored and if such property is subsequently forfeited, the 
    transfer of such property shall be deemed to be null and void.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number>
Forfeiture of property of certain persons.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any person is 
    accused of any offence under this Act, it shall be open to the Special Court 
    trying him to pass an order that all or any of the properties, movable or 
    immovable or both belonging to him, shall, during the period of such trial, 
    be attached, if not already attached under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    person has been convicted of any offence punishable under this Act, the 
    Special Court may, in addition to awarding any punishment, by order in 
    writing, declare that any property, movable or immovable or both, belonging 
    to the accused and specified in the order, shall stand forfeited to the 
    Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, free from 
    all encumbrances.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Company 
    to transfer shares to Government.—Where 
    any shares in a company stand forfeited to the Central Government or the 
    State Government, as the case may be, under this Act, then, the company 
    shall, on receipt of the order of the Special Court, notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or the articles 
    of association of the company, forthwith register the Central Government or 
    the State Government, as the case may be, as the transferee of such shares.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number>
Declaration of an organisation as a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the purposes of this Act, an organisation is a terrorist organisation if—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    it is listed in the Schedule, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    it operates under the same name as an 
    organisation listed in that Schedule.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may by order, in the Official Gazette,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    add an organisation to the Schedule;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    remove an organisation from that 
    Schedule;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    amend that Schedule in some other way.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may exercise its power under clause (a) of sub- 
    section (2) in respect of an organisation only if it believes that it is 
    involved in terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the 
    purposes of sub-section (3), an organisation shall be deemed to be involved 
    in terrorism if it—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    commits or participates in acts of 
    terrorism,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    prepares for terrorism,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    promotes or encourages terrorism, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is otherwise involved in terrorism.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number>
Denotification of a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> An application may be 
    made to the Central Government for the exercise of its power under clause 
    (b) of sub-section (2) of section 18 to remove an organisation from the 
    Schedule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application may be made by—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the organisation, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any person affected by inclusion of the 
    organisation in the Schedule as a terrorist organisation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may make rules to prescribe the procedure for admission 
    and disposal of an application made under this section.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an 
    application under sub-section (1) has been refused, the applicant may apply 
    for a review to the Review Committee constituted by the Central Government 
    under sub-section (1) of section 60 within one month from the date of 
    receipt of the order by the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Review 
    Committee may allow an application for review against refusal to remove an 
    organisation from the Schedule, if it considers that the decision to refuse 
    was flawed when considered in the light of the principles applicable on an 
    application for judicial review.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    Review Committee allows review under sub-section (5) by or in respect of an 
    organisation, it may make an order under this sub-section.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where an 
    order is made under sub-section (6), the Central Government shall, as soon 
    as the certified copy of the order is received by it, make an order removing 
    the organisation from the list in the Schedule.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number>
Offence relating to membership of a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
    person commits an offence if he belongs or professes to belong to a 
    terrorist organisation:  
 
Provided that 
    this sub-section shall not apply where the person charged is able to prove—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the organisation was not declared 
    as a terrorist organisation at the time when he became a member or began to 
    profess to be a member; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that he has not taken part in the 
    activities of the organisation at any time during its inclusion in the 
    Schedule as a terrorist organisation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable, on conviction, to 
    imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years, or with fine, or with both.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Offence 
    relating to support given to a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person commits an offence if—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    he invites support for a terrorist 
    organisation, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the support is not, or is not 
    restricted to, the provision of money or other property within the meaning 
    of section 22.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    commits an offence if he arranges, manages or assists in arranging or 
    managing a meeting which he knows is—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to support a terrorist organisation, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to further the activities of a 
    terrorist organisation, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to be addressed by a person who belongs 
    or professes to belong to a terrorist organisation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    commits an offence if he addresses a meeting for the purpose of encouraging 
    support for a terrorist organisation or to further its activities.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A person 
    guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on conviction, to 
    imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years, or with fine, or with both.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, the expression “meeting” means a meeting of three or more 
    persons whether or not the public are admitted.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Fund 
    raising for a terrorist organisation to be an offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person commits an offence if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    invites another to 
    provide money or other property, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    intends that it should be 
    used, or has reasonable cause to suspect that it may be used, for the 
    purposes of terrorism.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    commits an offence if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    receives money or other 
    property, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    intends that it should be 
    used, or has reasonable cause to suspect that it may be used, for the 
    purposes of terrorism.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    commits an offence if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    provides money or other 
    property, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    knows or has reasonable 
    cause to suspect that it will or may be used for the purposes of terrorism.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> In this 
    section, a reference to the provision of money or other property is a 
    reference to its being given, lent or otherwise made available, whether or 
    not for consideration.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A person 
    guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on conviction, to 
    imprisonment for a term not exceeding fourteen years, or with fine, or with 
    both.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Special 
    Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government or a State Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, constitute one or more Special Courts for such area or areas, or 
    for such case or class or group of cases, as may be specified in the 
    notification.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    notification constituting a Special Court for any area or areas or for any 
    case or class or group of cases is issued by the Central Government under 
    sub-section (1), and a notification constituting a Special Court for the 
    same area or areas or for the same case or class or group of cases has also 
    been issued by the State Government under that sub-section, the Special 
    Court constituted by the Central Government, whether the notification 
    constituting such Court is issued before or after the issue of the 
    notification constituting the Special Court by the State Government, shall 
    have, and the Special Court constituted by the State Government shall not 
    have, jurisdiction to try any offence committed in that area or areas or, as 
    the case may be, the case or class or group of cases and all cases pending 
    before any Special Court constituted by the State Government shall stand 
    transferred to the Special Court constituted by the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    question arises as to the jurisdiction of any Special Court, it shall be 
    referred to the Central Government whose decision in the matter shall be 
    final.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Special 
    Court shall be presided over by a judge to be appointed by the Central 
    Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, with the 
    concurrence of the Chief Justice of the High Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government may also 
    appoint, with the concurrence of the Chief Justice of the High Court, 
    additional judges to exercise jurisdiction of a Special Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A person 
    shall not be qualified for appointment as a judge or an additional judge of 
    a Special Court unless he is, immediately before such appointment, a 
    sessions judge or an additional sessions judge in any State.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> For the 
    removal of doubts, it is hereby provided that the attainment, by a person 
    appointed as a judge or an additional judge of a Special Court, of the age 
    of superannuation under the rules applicable to him in the service to which 
    he belongs, shall not affect his continuance as such judge or additional 
    judge.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where any 
    additional judge or additional judges is or are appointed in a Special 
    Court, the judge of the Special Court may, from time to time, by general or 
    special order, in writing, provide for the distribution of business of the 
    Special Court among all judges including himself and the additional judge or 
    additional judges and also for the disposal of urgent business in the event 
    of his absence or the absence of any additional judge.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number>
Place of sitting.—A Special Court may, on its own motion, or on an 
    application made by the Public Prosecutor and if it considers it expedient 
    or desirable so to do, sit for any of its proceedings at any place other 
    than its ordinary place of sitting:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall be construed to change the place of sitting of 
    a Special Court constituted by a State Government to any place outside that 
    State.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number>
Jurisdiction of Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Code, every offence punishable under any provision of this 
    Act shall be triable only by the Special Court within whose local 
    jurisdiction it was committed or, as the case may be, by the Special Court 
    constituted for trying such offence under section 23.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, having 
    regard to the exigencies of the situation prevailing in a State,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    it is not possible to 
    have a fair, impartial or speedy trial; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    it is not feasible to 
    have the trial without occasioning the breach of peace or grave risk to the 
    safety of the accused, the witnesses, the Public Prosecutor and a judge of 
    the Special Court or any of them; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    it is not otherwise in 
    the interests of justice,  
 
the Supreme Court may transfer any case 
    pending before a Special Court to any other Special Court within that State 
    or in any other State and the High Court may transfer any case pending 
    before a Special Court situated in that State to any other Special Court 
    within the State.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Supreme Court or the High Court, as the case may be, may act under this 
    section either on the application of the Central Government or a party 
    interested and any such application shall be made by motion, which shall, 
    except when the applicant is the Attorney-General of India, be supported by 
    an affidavit or affirmation.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number>
Power of Special Courts with respect to other offences.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
    trying any offence, a Special Court may also try any other offence with 
    which the accused may, under the Code, be charged at the same trial if the 
    offence is connected with such other offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, in the 
    course of any trial under this Act of any offence, it is found that the 
    accused person has committed any other offence under this Act or under any 
    other law, the Special Court may convict such person of such other offence 
    and pass any sentence or award punishment authorised by this Act or such 
    rule or, as the case may be, under such other law.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Power 
    to direct for samples, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a police officer investigating a case requests the Court of a Chief 
    Judicial Magistrate or the Court of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate in 
    writing for obtaining samples of hand writing, finger-prints, foot-prints, 
    photographs, blood, saliva, semen, hair, voice of any accused person, 
    reasonably suspected to be involved in the commission of an offence under 
    this Act, it shall be lawful for the Court of a Chief Judicial Magistrate or 
    the Court of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate to direct that such samples be 
    given by the accused person to the police officer either through a medical 
    practitioner or otherwise, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    accused person refuses to give samples as provided in sub-section (1), the 
    Court shall draw adverse inference against the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number>
Public Prosecutors.—
<section><number>1</number> For every Special Court, the Central 
    Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, shall appoint a 
    person to be the Public Prosecutor and may appoint one or more persons to be 
    the Additional Public Prosecutor or Additional Public Prosecutors:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, may 
    also appoint for any case or class or group of cases, a Special Public 
    Prosecutor.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    shall not be qualified to be appointed as a Public Prosecutor or an 
    Additional Public Prosecutor or a Special Public Prosecutor under this 
    section unless he has been in practice as an Advocate for not less than 
    seven years or has held any post, for a period of not less than seven years, 
    under the Union or a State, requiring special knowledge of law.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person appointed as a Public Prosecutor or an Additional Public Prosecutor 
    or a Special Public Prosecutor under this section shall be deemed to be a 
    Public Prosecutor within the meaning of clause (u) of section 2 of the Code, 
    and the provisions of the Code shall have effect accordingly.  
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number>
Procedure and powers of Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions 
    of section 50, a Special Court may take cognizance of any offence, without 
    the accused being committed to it for trial, upon receiving a complaint of 
    facts that constitute such offence or upon a police report of such facts.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    offence triable by a Special Court is punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term not exceeding three years, or with fine, or with both, the Special 
    Court may, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) of section 
    260 or section 262 of the Code, try the offence in a summary way in 
    accordance with the procedure prescribed in the Code and the provisions of 
    sections 263 to 265 of the Code, shall so far as may be, apply to such 
    trial:  
 
Provided that 
    when, in the course of a summary trial under this sub-section, it appears to 
    the Special Court that the nature of the case is such that it is undesirable 
    to try it in a summary way, the Special Court shall recall any witnesses who 
    may have been examined and proceed to re-hear the case in the manner 
    provided by the provisions of the Code for the trial of such offence and the 
    said provisions shall apply to and in relation to a Special Court as they 
    apply to and in relation to a Magistrate:  
 
Provided 
    further that in the case of any conviction in a summary trial under this 
    section, it shall be lawful for a Special Court to pass a sentence of 
    imprisonment for a term not exceeding one year and with fine which may 
    extend to rupees five lakh.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the other provisions of this Act, a Special Court shall, for the purpose of 
    trial of any offence, have all the powers of a Court of Session and shall 
    try such offence as if it were a Court of Session so far as may be in 
    accordance with the procedure prescribed in the Code for the trial before a 
    Court of Session.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to 
    the other provisions of this Act, every case transferred to a Special Court 
    under section 25 shall be dealt with as if such case had been transferred 
    under section 406 of the Code to such Special Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, but subject to the 
    provisions of section 299 of the Code, a Special Court may, if it thinks fit 
    and for reasons to be recorded by it, proceed with the trial in the absence 
    of the accused or his pleader and record the evidence of any witness, 
    subject to the right of the accused to recall the witness for cross-examination.  
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number>
Protection of witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    the Code, the proceedings under this Act may, for reason to be recorded in 
    writing, be held in camera if the Special Court so desires.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Special 
    Court, if on an application made by a witness in any proceeding before it or 
    by the Public Prosecutor in relation to such witness or on its own motion, 
    is satisfied that the life of such witness is in danger, it may, for reasons 
    to be recorded in writing, take such measures as it deems fit for keeping 
    the identity and address of such witness secret.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of 
    sub-section (2), the measures which a Special Court may take under that 
    sub-section may include—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the holding of the 
    proceedings at a place to be decided by the Special Court;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the avoiding of the 
    mention of the names and addresses of the witnesses in its orders or 
    judgments or in any records of the case accessible to public;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the issuing of any 
    directions for securing that the identity and address of the witnesses are 
    not disclosed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a decision that it is in 
    the public interest to order that all or any of the proceedings pending 
    before such a Court shall not be published in any manner.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person 
    who contravenes any decision or direction issued under sub-section (3) shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and 
    with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number>
Trial by Special Courts to have precedence.—The trial under this Act 
    of any offence by a Special Court shall have precedence over the trial of 
    any other case against the accused in any other court (not being a Special 
    Court) and shall be concluded in preference to the trial of such other case 
    and accordingly the trial of such other case shall remain in abeyance.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number>
Certain confessions made to police officers to be taken into 
    consideration.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything in the Code or in the Indian 
    Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), but subject to the provisions of this 
    section, a confession made by a person before a police officer not lower in 
    rank than a Superintendent of Police and recorded by such police officer 
    either in writing or on any mechanical or electronic device like cassettes, 
    tapes or sound tracks from out of which sound or images can be reproduced, 
    shall be admissible in the trial of such person for an offence under this 
    Act or the rules made thereunder.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A police 
    officer shall, before recording any confession made by a person under 
    sub-section (1), explain to such person in writing that he is not bound to 
    make a confession and that if he does so, it may be used against him:  
 
Provided that 
    where such person prefers to remain silent, the police officer shall not 
    compel or induce him to make any confession.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    confession shall be recorded in an atmosphere free from threat or inducement 
    and shall be in the same language in which the person makes it.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person 
    from whom a confession has been recorded under sub-section (1), shall be 
    produced before the Court of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the Court of 
    a Chief Judicial Magistrate along with the original statement of confession, 
    written or recorded on mechanical or electronic device within forty-eight 
    hours.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chief 
    Metropolitan Magistrate or the Chief Judicial Magistrate, shall, record the 
    statement, if any, made by the person so produced and get his signature or 
    thumb impression and if there is any complaint of torture, such person shall 
    be directed to be produced for medical examination before a Medical Officer 
    not lower in rank than an Assistant Civil Surgeon and thereafter, he shall 
    be sent to judicial custody.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number>
Power to transfer cases to regular courts.—Where, after taking 
    cognizance of any offence, a Special Court is of the opinion that the 
    offence is not triable by it, it shall, notwithstanding that it has no 
    jurisdiction to try such offence, transfer the case for the trial of such 
    offence to any court having jurisdiction under the Code and the court to 
    which the case is transferred may proceed with the trial of the offence as 
    if it had taken cognizance of the offence.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number>
Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, an appeal 
    shall lie from any judgment, sentence or order, not being an interlocutory 
    order, of a Special Court to the High Court both on facts and on law.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, “High Court” means a High Court within whose jurisdiction, a 
    Special Court which passed the judgment, sentence or order, is situated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    appeal under sub-section (1) shall be heard by a bench of two
    judges of the High Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Except as 
    aforesaid, no appeal or revision shall lie to any court from any judgment, 
    sentence or order including an interlocutory order of a Special Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (3) of section 378 of the 
    Code, an appeal shall lie to the High Court against an order of the Special 
    Court granting or refusing bail.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every 
    appeal under this section shall be preferred within a period of thirty days 
    from the date of the judgment, sentence or order appealed from:  
 
Provided that 
    the High Court may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period 
    of thirty days if it is satisfied that the appellant had sufficient cause 
    for not preferring the appeal within the period of thirty days.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Transitional provisions and transfer of pending proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The jurisdiction conferred by this Act on a Special Court, shall, until a 
    Special Court is constituted under section 23, in the case of any offence 
    punishable under this Act, notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, 
    be exercised by the Court of Session of the division in which such offence 
    has been committed and it shall have all the powers and follow the procedure 
    provided under this Chapter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On and 
    from the date when the Special Court is constituted under section 23, every 
    trial under the provisions of this Act, which would have been required to be 
    held before the Special Court, shall stand transferred to that Court on the 
    date on which it is constituted.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number>  
    Definitions.—In this Chapter, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “electronic 
    communication” means any transmission of signs, signals, writings, images, 
    sounds, data or intelligence of any nature transmitted in whole or in part 
    by a wire, radio, electromagnetic, photo electronic or photo optical system 
    that affects inland or foreign commerce but does not include— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the radio 
    portion of a cordless telephone communication that is transmitted between 
    the wireless telephone hand-set and the base unit; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any wire or oral 
    communication; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any communication 
    made through a tone only paging device; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    any communication 
    from a tracking device;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    “intercept” means the 
    aural or other acquisition of the contents by wire, electronic or oral 
    communication through the use of any electronic, mechanical or other device;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “oral communication” 
    means any oral communication uttered by a person exhibiting an expectation 
    that such communication is not subject to interception under circumstances 
    justifying such expectation but such term does not include any electronic communication;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “wire communication” means 
    any aural transmission made in whole or part through the use of facilities 
    for the transmission of communications by the aid of wire, cable or other 
    like connection between the point of origin and the point of connection, 
    between the point of origin and the point of reception (including the use of 
    such connection in switching station) and such term includes any electronic 
    storage of such communication.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number>
Appointment of Competent Authority.—The Central Government or the 
    State Government, as the case may be, may appoint an officer not below the 
    rank of Secretary to the Government in the case of State Government and not 
    below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government in the case of Central 
    Government, to be the Competent Authority for the purposes of this Chapter.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number>  
    Application for authorisation of interception of wire, electronic or oral 
    communication.—
<section><number>1</number> A police 
    officer not below the rank of Superintendent of Police supervising the 
    investigation of any terrorist act under this Act may submit an application 
    in writing to the Competent Authority for an order authorising or approving 
    the interception of wire, electronic or oral communication by the 
    investigating officer when he believes that such interception may provide, 
    or has provided evidence of any offence involving a terrorist act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    application shall include the following information:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the identity of the 
    investigating officer making the application, and the head of the department authorising the application;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a statement of the facts 
    and circumstances relied upon by the applicant to justify his belief that an 
    order should be issued, including—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    details as to the 
    offence of terrorist act that has been, is being, or is about to be, 
    committed;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    a particular 
    description of the nature and location of the facilities from which or the 
    place where the communication is to be intercepted;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    a particular 
    description of the type of communications sought to be intercepted; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    the identity of the 
    person, if known, committing the terrorist act whose communications are to 
    be intercepted;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a statement of the period 
    of time for which the interception is required to be maintained, if the 
    nature of the enquiry is such that the authorisation of interception should 
    not automatically terminate after the described type of communication has 
    been first obtained;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a particular description 
    of facts establishing probable cause to believe that additional 
    communications of the same type will occur thereafter; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    where the application is 
    for the extension of an order, a statement setting forth the results thus 
    far obtained from the interception, or a reasonable explanation of the 
    failure to obtain such results.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Competent Authority may require the applicant to furnish additional oral or 
    documentary evidence in support of the application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number>  
    Decision by Competent Authority on application for interception.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Upon such application, the Competent Authority may reject the application, 
    or issue an order, as requested or as modified, authorising or approving 
    interception of wire, electronic or oral communications, if the Competent 
    Authority determines on the basis of the facts submitted by the applicant 
    that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    there is a probable cause 
    for belief that an individual is committing, has committed, or is about to 
    commit a particular offence described and made punishable under sections 3 
    and 4 of this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    there is a probable cause 
    of belief that particular communications concerning that offence may be 
    obtained through such interception;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    there is probable cause 
    of belief that the facilities from which, or the place where, the wire, 
    electronic or oral communications are to be intercepted are being used or 
    are about to be used, in connection with the commission of such offence, 
    leased to, or are listed, in the name of or commonly used by such person.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>   Each 
    order by the Competent Authority authorising or approving the interception 
    of any wire, electronic or oral communication under this section shall 
    specify—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the identity of the 
    person, if known, whose communications are to be intercepted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the nature and location 
    of the communication facilities as to which, or the place where, authority 
    to intercept is granted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a particular description 
    of the type of communication sought to be intercepted, and a statement of 
    the particular offence to which it relates;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the identity of the agency authorised to intercept the communications, and the person authorising the 
    application; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the period of time during 
    which such interception is authorised, including a statement as to whether 
    or not the interception shall automatically terminate after the described 
    communication has been first obtained.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number>
Submission of order of interception to Review Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Competent Authority shall, immediately after passing the order under 
    sub-section (1) of section 39, but in any case not later than seven days 
    from the passing of the order, submit a copy of the same to the Review 
    Committee constituted under section 60 along with all the relevant 
    underlying papers, record and his own findings, in respect of the said 
    order, for consideration and approval of the order by the Review Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    authorising the interception of a wire, electronic or oral communication 
    under this section shall, upon request of the applicant, direct that a 
    provider of wire or electronic communication service, landlord, custodian or 
    other person shall furnish to the applicant forthwith all information, 
    facilities, and technical assistance necessary to accomplish the 
    interception unobtrusively and with a minimum of interference with the 
    services that such service provider, landlord, custodian, or person is 
    providing to the person whose communications are to be intercepted.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Duration of an order of interception, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No order issued under this section may authorise or approve the interception 
    of any wire, electronic or oral communication for any period longer than is 
    necessary to achieve the objective of the authorisation, nor in any event 
    longer than sixty days and such sixty days period shall begin on the day 
    immediately preceding the day on which the investigating officer first 
    begins to conduct an interception under the order or ten days after order is 
    issued whichever is earlier.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    extension of an order may be granted, but only upon an application for an 
    extension made in accordance with sub-section (1) of section 38 and the 
    Competent Authority making the findings required by sub-section (1) of 
    section 39, and the period of such extension shall be no longer than the 
    Competent Authority deems necessary to achieve the purposes for which it was 
    granted and in no event for longer than sixty days at a time.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    order and extension thereof shall contain a provision that the authorisation 
    to intercept shall be executed as soon as practicable and shall be conducted 
    in such manner as to minimise the interception of communications not 
    otherwise subject to interception under this section and shall terminate 
    upon attainment of the authorised objective, or in any event on the expiry 
    of the period of said order or extension thereof.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number>
Authority competent to carry out interception.—
<section><number>1</number> An interception 
    under this Chapter may be conducted in whole or in part by a public servant, 
    acting under the supervision of the investigating officer authorised to 
    conduct the interception.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever 
    an order authorising an interception is issued pursuant to this section, the 
    order may require reports to be made to the Competent Authority who issued 
    the order showing that progress has been made towards achievement of the 
    authorised objective and the need for continued interception and such report 
    shall be made at such intervals as the Competent Authority may require.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>43</number>
Interception of communication in emergency.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other provision of this Chapter, an officer not 
    below the rank of Additional Director General of Police or a police officer 
    of equivalent rank who reasonably determines that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an emergency situation 
    exists that involves—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    immediate danger 
    of death or serious physical injury to any person; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    conspiratorial 
    activities threatening the security or interest of the State; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    conspiratorial 
    activities, characteristic of a terrorist act, that requires a wire, 
    electronic or oral communication to be intercepted before an order from the 
    Competent Authority authorising such interception can, with due diligence, 
    be obtained; and  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    there are grounds on 
    which an order should be issued under this section to authorise such 
    interception,  
 
may authorise, in writing, the investigating 
    officer to intercept such wire, electronic or oral communication, if an 
    application for an order approving the interception is made in accordance 
    with the provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 38 within 
    forty-eight hours after the interception has occurred, or begins to occur.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In the 
    absence of an order approving the interception made under sub-section (1), 
    such interception shall immediately terminate when the communication sought 
    is obtained or when the application for the order is rejected, whichever is 
    earlier, and in the event of an application for permitting interception 
    being rejected under sub-section (1) of section 39 or an application under 
    sub-section (1) of this section for approval being rejected, or in any other 
    case where the interception is terminated without an order having been 
    issued, the contents of any wire, electronic or oral communication 
    intercepted shall be treated as having been obtained in violation of this 
    section.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number>
Protection of information collected.—
<section><number>1</number> The contents of any wire, 
    electronic or oral communication intercepted by any means authorised by this 
    Chapter shall, as far as possible, be recorded on tape or wire or other 
    comparable device and shall be done in such manner as to protect the 
    recording from editing or other alterations.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Immediately upon the expiration of the period of order, or extension 
    thereof, such recording shall be made available to the Competent Authority 
    issuing such order and shall be sealed under his directions and kept in the 
    custody of such person or authority as the Competent Authority orders, and 
    such recordings shall not be destroyed except upon an order of the Competent 
    Authority and in any event shall be kept for ten years.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Applications made and orders issued under this Chapter shall be sealed by 
    the Competent Authority and custody of the applications and orders shall be 
    kept in such manner as the Competent Authority directs, and shall not be 
    destroyed except on an order of the Competent Authority, and in any event 
    shall be kept for ten years.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number>
Admissibility of evidence collected through the interception of 
    communications.—Notwithstanding anything in the Code or in any other law 
    for the time being in force, the evidence collected through the interception 
    of wire, electronic or oral communication under this Chapter shall be 
    admissible as evidence against the accused in the Court during the trial of 
    a case:  
 
Provided that, 
    the contents of any wire, electronic or oral communication intercepted 
    pursuant to this Chapter or evidence derived therefrom shall not be received 
    in evidence or otherwise disclosed in any trial, hearing or other proceeding 
    in any court unless each accused has been furnished with a copy of the order 
    of the Competent Authority, and accompanying application, under which the 
    interception was authorised or approved not less than ten days before trial, 
    hearing or proceeding:  
 
Provided 
    further that, the period of ten days may be waived by the judge trying the 
    matter, if he comes to the conclusion that it was not possible to furnish 
    the accused with the above information ten days before the trial, hearing or 
    proceeding and that the accused will not be prejudiced by the delay in 
    receiving such information.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number>
Review of authorisation order.—
<section><number>1</number> The Review Committee constituted 
    by the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall 
    review every order passed by the Competent Authority under section 39.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order passed by the Competent Authority under section 39, or disapproved by 
    the officer under section 43, shall be placed before the Review Committee, 
    which shall be considered by the Review Committee within ten days after its 
    receipt, to decide whether the order was necessary, reasonable and 
    justified.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   The 
    Review Committee, after examining the entire record and holding such 
    enquiry, if any, deemed necessary may, by order in writing, either approve 
    the order passed by the Competent Authority or may issue order disapproving 
    the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   On issue 
    of an order of disapproval by the Review Committee, the interception, if 
    any, already commenced shall be forthwith discontinued and the intercepted 
    communication, if any, in the form of tape, wire or other device shall, 
    thereupon, not be admissible as evidence in any case and shall be directed 
    to be destroyed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number>
Interception and disclosure of wire, electronic or oral communications 
    prohibited.—Except as otherwise specifically provided in section 39, any 
    police officer who—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    intentionally intercepts, endeavours to intercept, or procures any other person to intercept or 
    endeavours to intercept any wire, electronic or oral communication;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    intentionally uses, endeavours to use, or procures any other person to use or endeavours to use 
    any electronic, mechanical or other device to intercept any oral 
    communication when—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    such device is 
    affixed to, or otherwise transmits a signal through a wire, cable, or other 
    like connection used in wire communication; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    such device 
    transmits communications by radio, or interferes with the transmission of 
    such communication;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>    intentionally discloses, 
    or endeavours to disclose, to any other person the contents of any wire, 
    electronic or oral communication, knowing or having reason to know that the 
    information was obtained through the interception of a wire, electronic or 
    oral communication in violation of this Chapter;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    intentionally uses, or endeavours to use, the contents of any wire, electronic or oral 
    communication, knowing or having reason to know that the information was 
    obtained through the interception of a wire, electronic or oral 
    communication in violation of this Chapter;  
     
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    intentionally discloses, 
    or endeavours to disclose, to any other unauthorised person the contents of 
    any wire, electronic or oral communication, intercepted by means authorised 
    by section 39;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    intentionally continues 
    the interception of wire, electronic or oral communication after the issue 
    of an order of rejection by the Competent Authority under this Chapter;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    intentionally continues 
    the interception of wire, electronic or oral communication after the issue 
    of an order of disapproval by the Review Committee under sub-section (3) of 
    section 46,  
 
shall for such violation be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and with fine upto 
    rupees fifty thousand.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>48</number>
Annual Report of interceptions.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government and the 
    State Government, as the case may be, shall cause an annual report to be 
    prepared giving a full account of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the number of 
    applications for authorisation of interceptions received by the Competent 
    Authority from the Police Department in which prosecutions have been 
    launched;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the number of such 
    applications permitted or rejected;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the number of 
    interceptions carried out in emergency situations and the number of 
    approvals granted or rejected in such matters;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the number of prosecutions 
    launched based on such interceptions and convictions resulting from such 
    interceptions, along with an explanatory memorandum giving general 
    assessment of the utility and importance of the interceptions authorised.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An annual 
    report shall be laid by the State Government before the State Legislature 
    within three months of the completion of every calendar year:  
 
Provided that, 
    if the State Government is of the opinion that the inclusion of any matter 
    in the annual report would be prejudicial to the security of the State or to 
    the prevention or detection of any terrorist act, the State Government may 
    exclude such matter from being included in such annual report.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An annual 
    report shall be laid by the Central Government before each House of 
    Parliament within three months of the completion of every calendar year:  
 
Provided that, 
    if the Central Government is of the opinion that the inclusion of any matter 
    in the annual report would be prejudicial to the security of the country or 
    to the prevention or detection of any terrorist act, the Central Government 
    may exclude such matter from being included in such annual report.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Modified application of certain provisions of the Code.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code or any other law, every 
    offence punishable under this Act shall be deemed to be a cognizable offence 
    within the meaning of clause (c) of section 2 of the Code , and “cognizable 
    case” as defined in that clause shall be construed accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Section 
    167 of the Code shall apply in relation to a case involving an offence 
    punishable under this Act subject to the modification that in sub-section (2),—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the references to 
    “fifteen days”, “ninety days” and “sixty days”, wherever they occur, shall 
    be construed as references to “thirty days”, “ninety days” and “ninety 
    days”, respectively; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    after the proviso, the 
    following provisos shall be inserted, namely:—  
 
“Provided further 
    that if it is not possible to complete the investigation within the said 
    period of ninety days, the Special Court shall extend the said period up to 
    one hundred and eighty days, on the report of the Public Prosecutor 
    indicating the progress of the investigation and the specific reasons for 
    the detention of the accused beyond the said period of ninety days:
 
Provided also that 
    if the police officer making the investigation under this Act, requests, for 
    the purposes of investigation, for police custody from judicial custody of 
    any person from judicial custody, he shall file an affidavit stating the 
    reasons for doing so and shall also explain the delay, if any, for 
    requesting such police custody.”.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number>   Section 
    268 of the Code shall apply in relation to a case involving an offence 
    punishable under this Act subject to the modification that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the reference in 
    sub-section (1) thereof—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    to “the State 
    Government” shall be construed as a reference to “the Central Government or 
    the State Government”,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    to “order of the 
    State Government” shall be construed as a reference to “order of the Central 
    Government or the State Government, as the case may be”; and  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the reference in 
    sub-section (2) thereof, to the “State Government” shall be construed as a 
    reference to “the Central Government or the State Government, as the case 
    may be”.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number>   Sections 
    366, 367 and 371 of the Code shall apply in relation to a case involving an 
    offence triable by a Special Court subject to the modification that the 
    reference to “Court of Session”, wherever occurring therein, shall be 
    construed as the reference to “Special Court”.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   Nothing 
    in section 438 of the Code shall apply in relation to any case involving the 
    arrest of any person accused of having committed an offence punishable under 
    this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, no person accused of an 
    offence punishable under this Act shall, if in custody, be released on bail 
    or on his own bond unless the Court gives the Public Prosecutor an 
    opportunity of being heard.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where the 
    Public Prosecutor opposes the application of the accused to release on bail, 
    no person accused of an offence punishable under this Act or any rule made 
    thereunder shall be released on bail until the Court is satisfied that there 
    are grounds for believing that he is not guilty of committing such offence:  
 
Provided that 
    after the expiry of a period of one year from the date of detention of the 
    accused for an offence under this Act, the provisions of sub-section (6) of 
    this section shall apply.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>   The 
    restrictions on granting of bail specified in sub-sections (6) and (7) are 
    in addition to the restrictions under the Code or any other law for the time 
    being in force on granting of bail.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>   
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (6), (7) and (8), no bail 
    shall be granted to a person accused of an offence punishable under this 
    Act, if he is not an Indian citizen and has entered the country 
    unauthorisedly or illegally except in very exceptional circumstances and for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—No court 
    shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act without the previous 
    sanction of the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
    Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Officers competent to investigate offences under this Act.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code, no police officer,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of the Delhi 
    Special Police Establishment, below the rank of a Deputy Superintendent of 
    Police or a police officer of equivalent rank;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in the metropolitan 
    areas of Mumbai, Kolkata, Chennai and Ahmedabad and any other metropolitan 
    area notified as such under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Code, below 
    the rank of an Assistant Commissioner of Police;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    in any other case not 
    relatable to clause (a) or clause (b), below the rank of a Deputy 
    Superintendent of Police or a police officer of an equivalent rank,  
 
shall investigate any offence punishable under 
    this Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>52</number> Arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a police officer arrests a person, he shall prepare a custody memo of 
    the person arrested.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The person 
    arrested shall be informed of his right to consult a legal practitioner as 
    soon as he is brought to the police station.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever 
    any person is arrested, information of his arrest shall be immediately 
    communicated by the police officer to a family member or in his absence to a 
    relative of such person by telegram, telephone or by any other means and 
    this fact shall be recorded by the police officer under the signature of the 
    person arrested.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person 
    arrested shall be permitted to meet the legal practitioner representing him 
    during the course of interrogation of the accused person:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this sub-section shall entitle the legal practitioner to remain 
    present throughout the period of interrogation.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Presumption as to offences under section 3.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In a prosecution for an offence under sub-section (1) of section 3, if it is 
    proved—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the arms or 
    explosives or any other substances specified in section 4 were recovered 
    from the possession of the accused and there is reason to believe that such 
    arms or explosives or other substances of a similar nature, were used in the 
    commission of such offence; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the finger-prints 
    of the accused were found at the site of the offence or on anything 
    including arms and vehicles used in connection with the commission of such 
    offence,  
 
the Special Court shall draw adverse inference 
    against the accused.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In a 
    prosecution for an offence under sub-section (3) of section 3, if it is 
    proved that the accused rendered any financial assistance to a person, 
    having knowledge that such person is accused of, or reasonably suspected of, 
    an offence under that section, the Special Court shall draw adverse 
    inference against the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>54</number>
Bar of jurisdiction of courts, etc.—No civil court or other authority 
    shall have or, be entitled to, exercise any jurisdiction, powers or 
    authority in relation to the matters referred to in sections 19 and 40 of 
    the Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>55</number> Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in this Act shall affect the jurisdiction exercisable by, or the 
    procedure applicable to, any court or other authority under any law relating 
    to the naval, military or air force or other armed forces of the Union.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that for the purposes of any such 
    law as is referred to in sub-section (1), a Special Court shall be deemed to 
    be a court of ordinary criminal justice.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Overriding effect.—The provisions 
    of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent 
    therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or in any 
    instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government or a State Government or any officer or authority of the Central 
    Government or State Government or any other authority on whom powers have 
    been conferred under this Act, for anything which is in good faith done or 
    purported to be done in pursuance of this Act:  
 
Provided that 
    no suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any 
    serving member or retired member of the armed forces or other para-military 
    forces in respect of any action taken or purported to be taken by him in 
    good faith, in the course of any operation directed towards combating 
    terrorism.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Punishment and compensation for malicious action.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any police officer who exercises powers corruptly or maliciously, knowing 
    that there are no reasonable grounds for proceeding under this Act, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or with fine, or 
    with both.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    Special Court is of the opinion that any person has been corruptly or 
    maliciously proceeded against under this Act, the Court may award such 
    compensation as it deems fit to the person, so proceeded against and it 
    shall be paid by the officer, person, authority or Government, as may be 
    specified in the order.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Impounding of passport and arms licence of person charge-sheeted under the 
    Act.—Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in any other law for the time being in force, the passport and the 
    arms licence of a person, who is charge-sheeted for having committed any 
    offence under this Act, shall be deemed to have been impounded for such 
    period as the Special Court may deem fit.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>60</number> Review 
    Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government and each State Government shall, whenever necessary, constitute 
    one or more Review Committees for the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    Committee shall consist of a Chairperson and such other members not 
    exceeding three and possessing such qualifications as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    Chairperson of the Committee shall be a person who is, or has been, a Judge 
    of a High Court, who shall be appointed by the Central Government, or as the 
    case may be, the State Government, so however, that the concurrence of the 
    Chief Justice of the High Court shall be obtained in the case of a sitting 
    Judge:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of a Union territory, the appointment of a person who is a Judge 
    of the High Court of a State shall be made as a Chairperson with the 
    concurrence of the Chief Justice of the concerned High Court.  
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> 
    Without prejudice to the other provisions of this Act, any Review Committee 
    constituted under sub-section (1) shall, on an application by any aggrieved 
    person, review whether there is a prima facie case for proceeding 
    against the accused under this Act and issue directions accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    direction issued under sub-section (4),—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    by the Review Committee 
    constituted by the Central Government, shall be binding on the Central 
    Government, the State Government and the police officer investigating the 
    offence; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    by the Review Committee 
    constituted by the State Government, shall be binding on the State 
    Government and the police officer investigating the offence.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    reviews under sub-section (4) relating to the same offence under this Act, 
    have been made by a Review Committee constituted by the Central Government 
    and a Review Committee constituted by the State Government, under 
    sub-section (1), any direction issued by the Review Committee constituted by 
    the Central Government shall prevail.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where any 
    Review Committee constituted under sub-section (1) is of opinion that there 
    is no prima facie case for proceeding against the accused and issues 
    directions under sub-section (4), then, the proceedings pending against the 
    accused shall be deemed to have been withdrawn from the date of such 
    direction.]  
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>61</number>  
    Power of High Courts to make rules.—The 
    High Courts may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such rules, 
    if any, as they may deem necessary for carrying out the provisions of this 
    Act relating to Special Courts within their territories.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>62</number>  
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> Without 
    prejudice to the powers of the High Courts to make rules under section 61, 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    regulating the conduct 
    of persons in respect of areas the control of which is considered necessary 
    or expedient and the removal of such persons from such areas;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the entry into, and 
    search of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    any vehicle, vessel or 
    aircraft; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    any place, whatsoever,  
 
reasonably suspected of being used for 
    committing the offences referred to in section 3 or section 4 or for 
    manufacturing or storing anything for the commission of any such offence;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    conferring powers upon,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Central Government;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    a State Government;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    an Administrator of a 
    Union territory under article 239 of the Constitution;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    an officer of the 
    Central Government not lower in rank than that of a Joint Secretary; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    an officer of a State 
    Government not lower in rank than that of a District Magistrate,  
 
to make general or special orders to prevent 
    or deal with terrorist acts;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the arrest and trial of 
    persons contravening any of the rules or any order made thereunder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the punishment of any 
    person who contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets or attempts to 
    abet the contravention of any rule or order made thereunder with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or fine or both;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    providing for the 
    seizure and detention of any property in respect of which such 
    contravention, attempt or abetment as is referred to in clause (e) has been 
    committed and for the adjudication of such seizure and detention, whether by 
    any court or by any other authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    determination of the 
    price of the forfeited property under sub-section (2) of section 10;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the procedure of making 
    application under sub-section (3) of section 19; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the qualifications of 
    the members of the Review Committee under sub-section (2) of section 60.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>63</number> Orders 
    and rules to be laid before Houses of Parliament.—Every 
    order and every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be 
    laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
    while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
    comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
    before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
    successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification 
    in the order or rule or both Houses agree that the order or rule should not 
    be made, the order or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that order or rule.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>64</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Prevention of 
    Terrorism (Second) Ordinance, 2001 (Ord. 12 of 2001) is hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance, anything done or any 
    action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
    taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

the Schedule
 
(See section 18)
 

    Terrorist Organisations
 
 
 
BABBAR KHALSA INTERNATIONAL.

 
 
KHALISTAN COMMANDO FORCE.

 
 
KHALISTAN ZINDABAD FORCE.

 
 
INTERNATIONAL SIKH YOUTH FEDERATION.

 
 
LASHKAR-E-TAIBA/PASBAN-E-AHLE HADIS.

 
 
JAISH-E-MOHAMMED/TAHRIK-E-FURQAN.

 
 
HARKAT-UL-MUJAHIDEEN/HARKAt-UL-ANSAR/HARKAT-UL-JEHAD-E-ISLAMI.

 
 
HIZB-UL-MUJAHIDEEN/HIZB-UL-MUJAHIDEEN PIR 
    PANJAL REGIMENT.

 
 
AL-UMAR-MUJAHIDEEN.

 
 
JAMMU AND KASHMIR ISLAMIC FRONT.

 
 
UNITED LIBERATION FRONT OF ASSAM (ULFA).

 
 
NATIONAL DEMOCRATIC FRONT OF BODOLAND (NDFB).

 
 
PEOPLE’S LIBERATION ARMY (PLA).

 
 
UNITED NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (UNLF).

 
 
PEOPLE’S REVOLUTIONARY PARTY OF KANGLEIPAK (PREPAK).

 
 
KANGLEIPAK COMMUNIST PARTY (KCP).

 
 
KANGLEIYAOL KANBALUP (KYKL).

 
 
MANIPUR PEOPLE’S LIBERATION FRONT (MPLF).

 
 
ALL TRIPURA TIGER FORCE.

 
 
NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT OF TRIPURA.

 
 
LIBERATION TIGERS OF TAMIL EELAM (LTTE).

 
 
STUDENTS ISLAMIC MOVEMENT OF INDIA.

 
 
DEENDAR ANJUMAN.

 
 

Communist Party of India 
    (Marxist-Leninist)—People’s War, All Its Formations and Front Organisations.

 
 
Maoist 
    Communist Centre (MCC), All Its Formations and Front Organisations.

 
 
AL BADR

 
 
JAMIAT-UL-MUJAHIDDEN]

 
 
AL-QAIDA.]

 
 
DUKHTARAN-E-MILLAT (DEM)]

 
 
TAMIL NADU LIBERATION ARMY (TNLA)

 
 
TAMIL NATIONAL RETRIEVAL TROOPS (TNRT)

 
 
AKHIL BHARAT NEPAL EKTA SAMAJ (ABNES)]


 
Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    Schedule, serial numbers 24 and 25 shall be deemed to have been included 
    with effect from the date of publication of S.O. No. 1194 (E), dated the 5th 
    December, 2001.
 
 







 




<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   
    Ins. by Act 4 of 2004, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 27-10-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   
    Added by S.O. 382(E), dated 1st April, 2002 (w.e.f. 3-4-2002).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>