<act><tid>1469183</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL EXCISE TARIFF ACT, <year>1985</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1986</year>
[ 19th January, <year>1986</year>.]

An Act to provide for tariff for Central duties of excise.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1546068</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1025978</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1568766</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>992626</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1519534</tid>
<number>2</number>Duties specified in the Schedule to be levied. The rates at 
which duties of excise shall be levied under the Central Excises and 
Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>.) are specified in the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1048359</tid>
<number> 3</number> Emergency power of Central Government to increase duty of 
excise.
<section><tid>1513307</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in respect of any goods, the Central Government is  
satisfied that the duty leviable thereon under section 3 of the 
Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>.) should be increased 
and that circumstances exist which render it necessary to take 
immediate action, the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct an amendment of the Schedule to be made so as 
to substitute for the rate of duty specified in the Schedule in 
respect of such goods,--

<subsection><tid>1899361</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where the rate of duty as specified in the 
Schedule as in force immediately before the issue of such 
notification is nil, a rate of duty not exceeding fifty per cent. 
ad valorem expressed in any form or method;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>762925</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, a rate of duty which shall not be 
more than twice the rate of duty specified in respect of such 
goods in the Schedule as in force immediately before the issue of 
the said notification:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>90</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 28th February, <year>1986</year>: Vide Notification No. G. S. R. 89 (E), dated 
5.  2. <year>1986</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1986</year>, Extraordinary, Part II Section 3 
 (i). 89


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the Central Government shall not issue any 
notification under this sub- section for substituting the rate of duty 
in respect of any goods as specified by an earlier notification issued 
under this sub- section by that Government before such earlier 
notification has been approved with or without modifications under 
sub- section (2).

Explanation.--" Form or method", in relation to a rate of duty of 
excise, means the basis, namely, valuation, weight, number, length, 
area, volume or other measure with reference to which the duty may be 
levied.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>350159</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under sub- section (1) shall be laid before 
each House of Parliament, if it is sitting, as soon as may be after 
the issue of the notification, and, if it is not sitting, within seven 
days of its reassembly, and the Central Government shall seek the 
approval of Parliament to the notification by a resolution moved 
within a period of fifteen days beginning with the day on which the 
notification is so laid before the House of the People and if 
Parliament makes any modification in the notification or directs that 
the notification should cease to have effect, the notification shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, but without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>567788</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any 
notification issued under sub- section (1), including any such 
notification approved or modified under sub- section (2), may be 
rescinded by the Central Government at any time by notification in the 
Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>233653</tid>
<number> 4</number> Consequential amendments of, and construction of references 
to, the First Schedule to, Act 1 of <year>1944</year>.
<section><tid>438810</tid>
<number>1</number>In the Central Excises  
and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>--

<subsection><tid>564264</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" First Schedule", wherever they occur, the 
words and figures" Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act, 
<year>1985</year>" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550249</tid>
<number>b</number>in section 2, for clause (f), the following clause shall 
be substituted, namely:--

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932771</tid>
<number>f</number>" manufacture" includes any process,--

<subsubsection><tid>1018076</tid>
<number>i</number>incidental or ancillary to the completion of a 
manufactured product;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1896832</tid>
<number>ii</number>which is specified in relation to any goods 
in the Section or Chapter Notes of the Schedule to the 
Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year> as amounting to 
manufacture, and the word" manufacturer" shall be 
construed accordingly and shall include not only a 
person who employs hired labour in the production or 
manufacture of excisable goods, but also any person who 
engages in their production or manufacture on his own 
account;';

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>460316</tid>
<number>c</number>the First Schedule shall be omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>906945</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference to the expression" First Schedule to the 
Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>" (1 of <year>1944</year>.) in any Central Act 
shall, on and after the commencement of this Act, be construed as a 
reference to the Schedule to this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>91</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>