<act> 
 
The MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Mines Rules, 1955.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Except as otherwise 
expressly provided, the rules shall apply to every mine of whatever description 
to which the Act applies.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  “the Act” means the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 
1952);
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  “court of inquiry” means a court of inquiry 
apppointed under section 24 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> “Form” means a Form as given in the First 
Schedule;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number> “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>e</number> “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these 
rules;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number> “Manager” includes Mine Superintendent who is 
appointed by the owner or agent of mine under section 17 of the Act and as such, 
responsible for the control, management,
1[supervision] 
and direction of a mine;
 </section><section>         <number>g</number> “certifying surgeon” means a qualified medical 
practitioner appointed to be a certifying surgeon under section 11;
 
        2[(h)]  
“calendar year” means a year from the first day of January to the thirty-first 
day of December;
 
3[(i)  
"Officer in-charge canteen" means the person (other than the manager) whom the 
owner or agent may appoint for security compliance with the provisions in 
respect of canteens;]
 
          4[(j)]  
“ordinarily employed” with reference to any mine or part thereof, means the 
average number of persons employed per day in the mine or part of mine during 
the preceding 5[calendar 
year] (obtained by dividing the number of mandays worked by the number of 
working days excluding rest days and other non-working days);]
 

        6[***]
  








</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> Term of office.—The 
term of office of the members referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 of the Act, shall be three years from the date on 
which their appointment is notified in the Official Gazette:
 Provided that a member shall 
notwithstanding the expiry of a period of three years, continue to hold office 
until the appointment of his successor is notified in the Official Gazette;
 Provided further that a member 
appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the remaining period of 
the term of office of the member in whose place he is appointed and shall 
continue to hold office on the expiry of the term of office until the 
appointment of his successor is notified in the Official Gazette.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> Term of office.—The 
term of office of the members referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 of the Act, shall be three years from the date on 
which their appointment is notified in the Official Gazette:
 Provided that a member shall 
notwithstanding the expiry of a period of three years, continue to hold office 
until the appointment of his successor is notified in the Official Gazette;
 Provided further that a member 
appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the remaining period of 
the term of office of the member in whose place he is appointed and shall 
continue to hold office on the expiry of the term of office until the 
appointment of his successor is notified in the Official Gazette.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>4</number> Secretary of the Committee.—An 
Inspector of Mines nominated in this  behalf by the Chief Inspector shall act 
the Secretary of the Committee.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>4</number> Secretary of the Committee.—An 
Inspector of Mines nominated in this  behalf by the Chief Inspector shall act 
the Secretary of the Committee.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>5</number> Remuneration.—Members 
of the Committee shall receive such honorarium as the Central Government may 
fix.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]
  



 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>7</number> Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member other than the Chairman may resign his office by writing under his hand 
addressed to the Chairman.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairman may resign his 
office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The resignation referred to 
in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) above shall take effect from the date of its 
acceptance 

1[or on the expiry of thirty days from 
the date of receipt of such resignation whichever is earlier, by the Chairman of 
the Central Government as the case may be].
  



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Absence from India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before a member leaves India—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  he shall intimate to the 
Chairman the date of his departure from and the date of his expected return to 
India; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  if he intends to be absent from 
India for a period longer than six months, he shall tender his resignation.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any member leaves 
India without taking the action required by sub-rule (1), he shall be deemed to 
have resigned with effect from the date of his departure from India.
 


</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>9</number> Notification of vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall inform the Central Government as soon as a vacancy occurs in 
the membership of the 

1[Committee] by the resignation or death 
of a member.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case such a vacancy 
occurs by the death of the Chairman, information shall be furnished to the 
Central Government by the Chief Inspector or the Inspector 

2[appointed] to the Board by the Central 
Government, as the case may be.
  




</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>10</number> Disposal of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All questions which the 

1[Committee] is required to consider 
shall be considered either at its meeting or by circulation of papers as the 
Chairman may direct:
 Provided that papers need not be 
circulated to any member who is absent from India at the time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a question is referred 
by circulation of papers, any member may request that the question be considered 
at a meeting of the 

1[Committee], and thereupon the Chairman 
may direct that it be so considered:
 Provided that if three or more 
members make such a request, the Chairman shall direct that it be so considered.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>11</number> Time and place of 
meetings.—The 

1[Committee] shall meet at such places 
and times as may be appointed by the Chairman.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>12</number> Notice of meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Secretary to the 

1[Committee] shall give at least fourteen 
days’ notice to every member of the 

1[Committee] present in India of the time 
and place fixed for each meeting and shall send to every such member agenda of 
business to be disposed of at that meeting, not less than seven days before the 
meeting:
 Provided that when an emergent 
meeting is called, at least two days’ clear notice shall be given.
 

2[***]
 

3[(2) Notices referred to in sub-rule (1) 
shall be delivered at or posted to, the usual place of residence of the member.]
 

4[(3)] No business which is not on the 
agenda shall be considered at a meeting without the permission of the Chairman.
  






</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Presiding at meetings.—The 
Chairman shall preside at every meeting of the Board at which he is present. If 
the Chairman is absent from any meeting, the members present shall elect one of 
them to preside over the meeting and the member so elected shall at that meeting 
exercise all the powers of the Chairman.
 


</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>14</number> Quorum.—No 
business shall be transacted at a meeting of the 

1[Committee] unless atleast four members 
are present:
 Provided that at any meeting in 
which less than four members present, the Chairman may adjourn the meeting to a 
date not less than fourteen days later and inform the members present and notify 
other members that he proposes to dispose of the business at the adjourned 
meeting irrespective of the quorum, and it shall thereupon be lawful to dispose 
of the business at such adjourned meeting irrespective of the number of members 
attending.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>15</number> Decision by majority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every question referred to the 

1[Committee] by circulation of papers 
shall, unless the Chairman, in pursuance of sub-rule (2) of rule 10 reserves it 
for consideration at a meeting, be decided in accordance with the opinions of 
the majority sending their opinions within the time allowed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All questions referred to a 
meeting of the 

1[Committee] shall be decided by a 
majority of votes of the members present and voting on that question.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of an equal 
division of votes or opinions the Chairman shall exercise an additional vote or 
opinion.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any member disagreeing with 
a decision of the 

1[Committee] may enter a note of dissent 
which shall form part of the record of the proceedings.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>16</number> Minutes of the meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Secretary of the 

1[Committee] shall circulate the 
proceedings of each meeting to all members of the 

1[Committee] present in India, and 
thereafter record the proceedings in a minute book which shall be kept for 
permanent record.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The record of the 
proceedings of each meeting shall be signed by the Chairman.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>17</number> Allowances to 
non-official members.—Travelling and 
daily allowance to non-official members of the 

1[Committee] shall be regulated in 
accordance with the orders regarding allowances to non-official members of 
Committees, Commissions and 

1[Committee] of Enquiry issued by the 
Central Government from time to time.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>18</number> Correspondence and 
accounts.—The Secretary of the 

1[Committee] shall conduct all the 
correspondence of the committee and keep its accounts.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>19</number> Appearance at hearings.—Any 
appearance required to be made by a party before the 

1[Committee], except for purposes of 
being examined as a witness, may be made either in person or by his agent duly 
authorised in writing, or by a legal practitioner on his behalf.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>20</number> Proceedings to be in 
camera.—Unless the Chairman otherwise 
directs, the proceedings of the 

1[Committee] shall be conducted in camera 
and shall be regarded as confidential in nature.
  



</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Court of inquiry to 
the public.—The 
person appointed to hold inquiry under section 24 of the Act shall hold the 
inquiry in public in such manner and under such conditions as the Court thinks 
most effectual for ascertaining the causes and circumstances of the accident or 
other occurrences and for enabling the Court to make the report.
 
 
</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>22</number> Recovery of expenses.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
If a court of inquiry finds that the accident was due to any carelessness or 
negligence on the part of the management, the court may direct the recovery of 
the expenses of such court, including any other expenses connected with the 
inquiry, from the owner 

2[***] of the mine concerned, in such 
manner and within such time as the court may specify.]
 

3[(2) The amount directed to be recovered 
under sub-rule (1) may, on application by the Chief Inspector or an Inspector to 
the concerned authority, be recovered from the owner in the same manner as an 
arrears of land revenue.]
  





</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 


 <article>
<number>23</number> Powers of Certifying 
Surgeons.—A 
Certifying Surgeon may within the local limits of his jurisdiction or in respect 
of mines or class or description of mines assigned to him make such inspection, 
examination or inquiry as he thinks fit for the purpose of the Act, and it shall 
be the duty of owner, agent or manager of the mine concerned to afford the 
Certifying Surgeon all reasonable facilities for carrying out such inspection, 
examination or inquiry as the case may be.
 


</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>24</number> Duties of Certifying 
Surgeon.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of a reference under sub-section (1) of section 43 of the Act, the 
certifying surgeon shall, giving prior notice regarding date, time and place for 
medical examination and upon examining the person sent for such examination, 
prepare the age and fitness certificate and deliver the same to the manager of 
the mine concerned after retaining a copy thereof.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The certifying surgeon 
shall, upon a request being made to him by the Chief Inspector, or Inspector, 
carry out such examination and furnish him with such report as he may indicate 
in respect of any mine or class or description of mines in which operations 
involve any risk of injury to the health of any person or class of persons 
employed therein.]



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]



 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]



 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]
  



 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Fresh examination.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person sent up for medical examination in pursuance of section 40 or 
section 43 

1[***] is not 
certified to be fit by the Certifying Surgeon, he shall not without the 
permission in writing of an Inspector, be sent for another medical examination 
unless a period of six months has elapsed from the time when he was last sent up 
for medical examination.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any certificate 
obtained in contravention of sub-rule (1) shall be void.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]
  



 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29A</number> Applicability of this 
Chapter.—Nothing in this Chapter 
shall apply to persons who are employed purely on temporary or casual basis for 
a continuous period not exceeding six months.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29B</number> Initial and periodical 
medical examinations.—After such date 
or dates as the Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette 
appoint in this behalf, the owner, agent or manager of every mine shall make 
arrangements—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  (i) for the initial medical examination of 
every person employed in the mine, within a period of five years of the date so 
notified and the said examination shall be so arranged over a period of five 
years that one-fifth of the persons employed at the mine undergo the examination 
every year:
                       Provided that in the case of a mine 
where a system of carrying out of such medical examination (of a comparable 
standard as determined by the Chief Inspector) is already in existence before 
the date aforesaid, a person who has undergone a medical examination under such 
a system on a date not earlier than five years before the date aforesaid, shall 
be deemed to have undergone an initial medical examination under this sub-clause 
and the last date of his medical examination under the said system shall be 
taken to be the date of his initial medical examination under these rules;
 <subsection>              <number>ii</number> for the initial medical examination of 
every person seeking employment in a mine, unless such person has already 
undergone within the preceding five years, a medical examination under these 
rules while in employment at another mine; and
 </subsection></section><section>         <number>b</number> for the periodical medical examination 
thereafter of every person employed in the mine at intervals of not more than 
five years:
 

1[Provided that, for the persons who are 
engaged in the process of mining or milling of asbestos ore, periodic medical 
examination shall be done at least once in every twelve months and every such 
examination shall include all the tests specified in Form “P” of the First 
Schedule except the X-ray examination, which shall be carried out once in every 
three years:
 Provided further that the 
periodic medical examination or the X-ray examination or both, shall be 
conducted at more frequent intervals if the examining authority deems it 
necessary to confirm a suspected case of dust-related disease.]
  




</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29C</number> Examining authorities.—The 
medical examination aforesaid shall be carried out by a Medical Officer 
appointed for the mine or a Medical Officer in the employment of the owner of 
the mine, if any, or by any medical officer employed in the Coal Mines Welfare 
Fund Organisation or any other mines welfare organisation, failing which by any 
State or Central Government medical officer not below the rank of the Assistant 
Civil Surgeon.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29D</number> Notice of medical 
examination.—
<section><number>1</number> In respect of every 
medical examination under rule 29B, the manager of the mine concerned shall give
 
at least twenty days’ prior notice in writing to the person to be examined, in 
Form ‘M’, provided that in case of the initial medical examination of a person 
seeking employment at a mine, the period of notice may be shorter.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A copy of every such notice 
issued shall be sent by the manager to the examining authority and in the case 
of periodical medical examination of a person, the copies of the previous 
medical certificate issued in Form O, pertaining to the persons concerned shall 
also be sent to the examining authority by the manager.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A person, who for any 
reasonable cause, fails to submit himself for a medical examination in 
accordance with the notice issued to him under sub-rule (1), shall be given a 
second notice of a minimum period of ten days in Form N, by the manager and a 
copy of every such notice shall be sent by the manager to the examining 
authority.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The examining authority 
shall inform the manager whether the person concerned has submitted himself for 
medical examination or not.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29E</number> Failure to undergo 
medical examination.—A person who, 
without reasonable cause, fails to submit himself for medical examination in 
accordance with a notice issued to him under sub-rule (3) of rule 29D, shall be 
liable to be discharged from service:
 Provided that a person who 
renders himself so liable to be discharged for failure to submit himself for 
medical examination shall be required to show cause why he could not comply with 
the notice within the time specified therein. If his explanation is found 
satisfactory by the management, he shall be given another chance to appear for 
medical examination. In case his explanation is not found satisfactory by the 
management, his service shall be terminated by the management:
 Provided further that in case of 
any dispute, the same shall be referred to the Chief Inspector for his decision 
within 60 days of the order communicated by the owner, agent or manager of the 
mine to the said person.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29F</number> Standard and report of 
medical examination.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
examining authority holding initial medical examination under sub-clause (i) of 
clause 
<subsection><number>a</number>, or periodical medical examination under clause (b) of rule 29B shall 
examine a person according to the standard laid down in Form P and the initial 
medical examination under sub-clause (ii) of clause (a) of rule 29B of all 
persons seeking employment in a mine shall be according to the standard laid 
down in Form PI.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> As soon as may be, after 
examination, a copy of the medical certificate in Form O, shall be issued by the 
examining authority to the person concerned by Registered post or delivered 
under receipt and another copy sent to the manager of the mine concerned by 
Registered post, or delivered under receipt.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The examining authority 
shall retain the third copy of the medical certificate.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the case of periodical 
medical examination of a person, the examining authority shall also sent the 
copy of the previous medical certificates of the person concerned received in 
pursuance of sub-rule (1) of rule 29D, to the manager of the mine concerned.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29G</number> Retention and transfer 
of medical certificates.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
medical certificates 

1[including all medical examination 
records with medical history and job details to depict the occupational dust 
exposure profiles] of persons employed or to be employed in a mine shall be 
retained in the possession of the manager of the mine so long as the person is 
employed in the mine and for a period of 

2[ten years] thereafter:
 Provided that the manager of a 
mine where such person is or was employed shall, if so requested by the manager 
of any other mine where the person is to be employed, send to him all medical 
certificates with respect to such person.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the examining authority 
who conducts medical examination of persons employed or to be employed in any 
mine, is relieved of his duties regarding medical examination, the medical 
practitioner shall transfer all records on medical examination in his possession 
to the manager of the mine concerned.
  





</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29H</number> Identity of candidates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every candidate for medical examination under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of rule 29B shall, at 
the time of examination handover three unmounted photographs (passport size) of 
himself to the examining authority. The examining authority, after satisfying 
itself that each photograph is a likeness of the candidate, shall endorse each 
of them with the name and father’s name or husband’s name of the candidate.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The examining authority, 
shall also record the left hand thumb impression or the signature of every 
candidate appearing before it for medical examination on the copies of the 
medical certificate in Form O.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29-I</number> Medical examination of 
women.—No woman shall, without her 
consent, be medically examined by a male medical practitioner except in the 
presence of another woman.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29J</number> Appeal for 
re-examination.—
<section><number>1</number> Where as a result 
of an initial medical examination under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number>, or of a periodical medical 
examination under clause (b) of rule 29B, a person has been declared unfit for 
employment in mines or in a particular category of mine or in any specified 
operations in mine, he may, within thirty days of the receipt by him of a copy 
of the Certificate referred to in sub-rule (2) of rule 29F, file an appeal with 
the manager of the mine against declaration aforesaid, and request for a medical 
re-examination by an Appellate Medical Board constituted under rule 29K.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> (a) The manager shall 
arrange to have the appellant medically re-examined by the Appellate Medical 
Board within thirty days of the receipt of the appeal, and shall give to the 
Appellant fifteen days’ prior notice of the medical re-examination by the 
Appellate Medical Board in Form Q.
 <subsection><number>b</number> A person, who for any 
reasonable cause, fails to submit himself for a medical re-examination in 
accordance with the notice given to him under clause (a), shall be given another 
notice in Form R in similar manner.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> A person who without 
reasonable cause, fails to submit himself for a medical re-examination in 
accordance with a notice given to him under clause (b) shall cease to be in 
employment at the time or in a particular category of mines or in any specified 
operations in mine, as the case may be, after the expiry of thirty days from the 
last date notified for his medical re-examination.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> In respect of every medical 
re-examination by the Appellate Medical Board, the appellant shall pay such fees 
and the medical examination shall be conducted in such manner as may be 
determined by the Appellate Medical Board. In case the Appellate Medical Board 
finds him fit for employment in mines, the fees shall be reimbursed in full to 
the appellant by the owner of the mine where he is employed.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29K</number> Constitution of 
Appellate Medical Board.—For the 
purpose of medical re-examination on appeal the Appellate Medical Board shall 
consist of the following officers, namely:—
 <section>         <number>a</number> One duly qualified Medical Officer in the 
employment of the Directorate-General of Mines Safety who shall also act as the 
Convenor of the Board.
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> One Medical Officer duly qualified in 
allopathic system of medicine to be nominated by the Chief Inspector in 
consultation with the Welfare Organisation set up by the Central Government for 
the persons employed in the mine.
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> One Medical Officer duly qualified in 
allopathic system of medicine employed in the State or Central Government or a 
Government Undertaking and not below the rank of Assistant Civil Surgeon:
 Provided that if a Medical 
Officer under clause (b) or clause (c) is not available, the Appellate Medical 
Board shall be constituted with two persons only.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29L</number> Standard and report of 
medical re-examination by the Appellate Medical Board.—The 
Appellate Medical Board shall medically examine the appellant in accordance with 
the standard laid down in Form P for initial medical examination of workers 
already in employment as well as periodical medical examination and in 
accordance with the standard laid down in Form P1 for initial medical 
examination of the persons to be employed and shall issue to the manager of the 
mine concerned and to the appellant a medical certificate in Form S.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29M</number> Unfit persons not to be 
employed.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, as a result of 
an initial medical examination made under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number>, or of a periodical medical 
examination under clause (b) of rule 29B a person has been declared unfit for 
employment in mines or in a particular category of mines or in any specified 
operations in mines, he shall not be employed or continue to be employed in mine 
or in the category of mine or on the operations specified, after the expiry of 
thirty days from the date of his medical examination unless he has filed an 
appeal under sub-rule (1) of rule 29J against the declaration.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where the person concerned 
has filed an appeal under sub-rule (1) of rule 29J, but has been declared by the 
Appellate Medical Board, after a medical re-examination, to be unfit for 
employment in mines or in a particular category of mines or on any specified 
operations in mines, he shall not be employed or continue to be employed in mine 
or in the category of mines or on the operations specified, after the expiry of 
thirty days from the date of his medical re-examination by the Appellate Medical 
Board:
 Provided that, if the Medical 
Officer carrying out the initial medical examination under clause (a), or the 
periodical examination under clause (b) of rule 29B, or the Appellate Medical 
Board carrying out the medical re-examination of persons already in employment 
is of the opinion that the disability of the person examined is of such a nature 
and degree that it will not seriously affect or interfere with the normal 
discharge of his duties, it may recommend his continuation in employment in the 
mine for a period not exceeding six months during which such person may get his 
disability cured or controlled and submit himself for another medical 
examination and be declared fit.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29N</number> Compensation for 
industrial disease.—If as a result of 
any medical examination under these rules or under the regulations, a person is 
found to have contracted any disease specified in Part C of Schedule III to the 
Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, the provision of section 3 of the Act shall 
become applicable in respect of that person.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29-O</number> Cost of medical 
examination.—Subject to the 
provisions of sub-rule (3) of rule 29J full cost of every medical examination 
under these rules, shall be borne by the owner of the mine concerned.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29P</number> Annual returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On or before the 20th day of February every year, the manager of every mine 
shall submit to the Chief Inspector annual returns in respect of the preceding 
calendar year in Form T.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If a mine is abandoned or 
working thereof is discontinued over a period exceeding sixty days or if a 
change occurs in the ownership of a mine, the returns required under sub-rule 
(1) shall be submitted within thirty days of abandonment or change of ownership 
or within ninety days of discontinuance, as the case may be.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29Q</number> Workmen’s Inspector.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
For every mine wherein 500 or more persons are ordinarily employed, the owner, 
agent or manger shall designate three suitably qualified employees of the mine 
in consultation with the registered trade union in the mine and where there are 
more than one registered trade unions, the union recognised as per procedure in 
practice or the most representative union as per the membership records 
available at that point of time, and if there are no registered trade unions, in 
consultation with the elected representative of the workmen, as technical 
experts, to carry out inspection of the mine on behalf of the workers employed 
therein, one each for mining operations, electrical installations and mechanical 
installations. When the number of persons employed in a mine exceeds 1500, the 
Workmen’s Inspector shall be assisted by one additional Workmen’s Inspector in 
mining discipline for every additional 1000 persons or part thereof.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> In every mine, the owner, 
agent or manager shall constitute in the manner laid down in clause (a), a panel 
of Workmen's Inspector who may serve as substitute during absence of regular 
Workmen's Inspector.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> In the panel there shall be 
at least one Workmen's Inspector each for mining, electrical and mechanical 
installations and operations.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> No person shall act as a 
Workmen's Inspector of a mine unless—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number>  he possesses an Overman's or Foreman's 
Certificate granted under the Act:
               Provided that—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  in relation to electrical machinery 
installed in mines, a person holding a valid Electrical Supervisor's Certificate 
of Competency covering mining installations, issued under sub-rule (1) of rule 
45 read with clause (ii) of sub-rule (1) of rule 131 of the Indian Electricity 
Rules, 1956 framed under the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 shall be so 
designated; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  In relation to other machinery and 
mechanical appliances installed in mines a person appointed to secure the 
installation, running and maintenance in safe working order of machinery in the 
mine, being not less in status than that of an Overman, Mine Foreman or 
Electrical Supervisor shall be so designated.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  he has at least five years of experience in 
mines including at least two years in workings of the mines for which he is 
nominated, and
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  he has undergone an orientation training 
course for Workmen’s Inspector consisting of not less than thirty lectures and 
demonstrations, of not less than two hours’ duration each, in accordance with 
the syllabus specified by and at a centre approved by the Chief Inspector by a 
general or special order.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall perform the duties mentioned in clause (a) of sub rule (1) of rule 29R for 
two days in every week; on remaining days of the week, he shall perform his 
normal duties unless called upon to perform the duties mentioned in clauses (b) 
and (c) of sub-rule (1) of rule 29R.
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) The owner, agent or 
manager shall afford the Workmen’s Inspector all reasonable facilities for 
making any entry, inspection, measurement, examination or inquiry in connection 
with his duties.
 <subsection><number>b</number> An official of the mine 
shall accompany the Workmen’s Inspector during his inspection.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The Workmen’s Inspector may 
carry out his inspection at any time.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> When there occurs an 
accident or dangerous occurrence in or about a mine, the owner, agent or manager 
shall forthwith inform the concerned Workmen’s Inspector about the accident or 
the occurrence.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall not exercise his powers to impede or obstruct the working of the mine.
 </section><section><number>7</number> A Workmen’s Inspector 
nominated under sub-rule (1) shall, unless he resigns from his office, hold 
office for a period of three years from the date of his nomination and shall be 
eligible for one re-nomination.
 </section><section><number>8</number> No owner, agent or 
manager shall take any action against a Workmen’s Inspector for any of his 
actions in the discharge of his duties and functions laid down in these rules.



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29Q</number> Workmen’s Inspector.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
For every mine wherein 500 or more persons are ordinarily employed, the owner, 
agent or manger shall designate three suitably qualified employees of the mine 
in consultation with the registered trade union in the mine and where there are 
more than one registered trade unions, the union recognised as per procedure in 
practice or the most representative union as per the membership records 
available at that point of time, and if there are no registered trade unions, in 
consultation with the elected representative of the workmen, as technical 
experts, to carry out inspection of the mine on behalf of the workers employed 
therein, one each for mining operations, electrical installations and mechanical 
installations. When the number of persons employed in a mine exceeds 1500, the 
Workmen’s Inspector shall be assisted by one additional Workmen’s Inspector in 
mining discipline for every additional 1000 persons or part thereof.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> In every mine, the owner, 
agent or manager shall constitute in the manner laid down in clause (a), a panel 
of Workmen's Inspector who may serve as substitute during absence of regular 
Workmen's Inspector.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> In the panel there shall be 
at least one Workmen's Inspector each for mining, electrical and mechanical 
installations and operations.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> No person shall act as a 
Workmen's Inspector of a mine unless—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number>  he possesses an Overman's or Foreman's 
Certificate granted under the Act:
               Provided that—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  in relation to electrical machinery 
installed in mines, a person holding a valid Electrical Supervisor's Certificate 
of Competency covering mining installations, issued under sub-rule (1) of rule 
45 read with clause (ii) of sub-rule (1) of rule 131 of the Indian Electricity 
Rules, 1956 framed under the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 shall be so 
designated; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  In relation to other machinery and 
mechanical appliances installed in mines a person appointed to secure the 
installation, running and maintenance in safe working order of machinery in the 
mine, being not less in status than that of an Overman, Mine Foreman or 
Electrical Supervisor shall be so designated.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  he has at least five years of experience in 
mines including at least two years in workings of the mines for which he is 
nominated, and
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  he has undergone an orientation training 
course for Workmen’s Inspector consisting of not less than thirty lectures and 
demonstrations, of not less than two hours’ duration each, in accordance with 
the syllabus specified by and at a centre approved by the Chief Inspector by a 
general or special order.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall perform the duties mentioned in clause (a) of sub rule (1) of rule 29R for 
two days in every week; on remaining days of the week, he shall perform his 
normal duties unless called upon to perform the duties mentioned in clauses (b) 
and (c) of sub-rule (1) of rule 29R.
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) The owner, agent or 
manager shall afford the Workmen’s Inspector all reasonable facilities for 
making any entry, inspection, measurement, examination or inquiry in connection 
with his duties.
 <subsection><number>b</number> An official of the mine 
shall accompany the Workmen’s Inspector during his inspection.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The Workmen’s Inspector may 
carry out his inspection at any time.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> When there occurs an 
accident or dangerous occurrence in or about a mine, the owner, agent or manager 
shall forthwith inform the concerned Workmen’s Inspector about the accident or 
the occurrence.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall not exercise his powers to impede or obstruct the working of the mine.
 </section><section><number>7</number> A Workmen’s Inspector 
nominated under sub-rule (1) shall, unless he resigns from his office, hold 
office for a period of three years from the date of his nomination and shall be 
eligible for one re-nomination.
 </section><section><number>8</number> No owner, agent or 
manager shall take any action against a Workmen’s Inspector for any of his 
actions in the discharge of his duties and functions laid down in these rules.



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29R</number> Duties of Workmen’s 
Inspector.—
<section><number>1</number> The duties of the 
Workmen’s Inspector shall be—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number>  to inspect all shafts, inclines, roads, 
workplaces and the equipment thereat including the equipment for conveyance and 
transport of workers;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  in case of any urgent and immediate danger 
that comes to his notice;
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  to inform the manager and the Inspector 
about the same; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  to suggest remedial measures necessary 
to avoid the danger; and 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  to accompany the Inspector in the course of 
complete inspection of the mine and also during such other inspections as may be 
considered necessary by the Inspector.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall record a full report of the matters ascertained as a result of his 
Inspection in an interleaved paged and bound register kept for the purpose in 
the mine in Form U. The Workmen’s Inspector making the entry in the register 
aforesaid shall duly sign such entries with dale and take a copy of the entries 
for his record.



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29R</number> Duties of Workmen’s 
Inspector.—
<section><number>1</number> The duties of the 
Workmen’s Inspector shall be—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number>  to inspect all shafts, inclines, roads, 
workplaces and the equipment thereat including the equipment for conveyance and 
transport of workers;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  in case of any urgent and immediate danger 
that comes to his notice;
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  to inform the manager and the Inspector 
about the same; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  to suggest remedial measures necessary 
to avoid the danger; and 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  to accompany the Inspector in the course of 
complete inspection of the mine and also during such other inspections as may be 
considered necessary by the Inspector.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Workmen’s Inspector 
shall record a full report of the matters ascertained as a result of his 
Inspection in an interleaved paged and bound register kept for the purpose in 
the mine in Form U. The Workmen’s Inspector making the entry in the register 
aforesaid shall duly sign such entries with dale and take a copy of the entries 
for his record.



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29S</number> Action on the report of 
Workmen’s Inspector .—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, 
agent or manager of the mine shall enter in the register mentioned in sub-rule 
(2) of rule 29R, within a period of 15 days from the date of entry in the 
register, remarks thereon showing the remedial measures taken and the date on 
which such action was taken.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of any difference of 
opinion between the Workmen’s Inspector and the owner, agent or manager, a copy 
of the report with remarks thereon regarding such difference of opinion shall be 
sent by the owner, agent or manager to the Chief Inspector or an Inspector for 
decision.
  


</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29S</number> Action on the report of 
Workmen’s Inspector .—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, 
agent or manager of the mine shall enter in the register mentioned in sub-rule 
(2) of rule 29R, within a period of 15 days from the date of entry in the 
register, remarks thereon showing the remedial measures taken and the date on 
which such action was taken.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of any difference of 
opinion between the Workmen’s Inspector and the owner, agent or manager, a copy 
of the report with remarks thereon regarding such difference of opinion shall be 
sent by the owner, agent or manager to the Chief Inspector or an Inspector for 
decision.
  


</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29T</number> Safety Committee.—For 
every mine wherein more than 100 persons are ordinarily employed, the owner, 
agent or manager shall constitute a Safety Committee for promoting Safety in the 
mine:
 Provided that the Chief 
Inspector or an Inspector may by a general or special order in writing require 
the owner, agent or manager of any group of specified mines or of all mines in a 
specified area to constitute a group Safety Committee in such manner and subject 
to such conditions as he may specify in the order.
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29U</number> Composition of Safety 
Committee.—The Safety Committee shall 
consist of:—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  the manager who shall be the Chairman ;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  five officials or competent persons of the 
mine nominated by the Chairman ;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  five workmen nominated by the workmen of the 
mine in accordance with the procedure prescribed in clause (a) of sub-rule (1) 
of rule 29Q for nomination of Workmen’s Inspector; 
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  Workmen’s Inspector where so designated; and
 </section><section>         <number>e</number>  the Safety Officer, or where there is no 
Safety Officer, the senior most mine official next to the manager, who shall act 
as Secretary to the Committee:
 Provided that any other 
official, competent person or work person may be co-opted by the Chairman as a 
member of the Committee on any day or days of the meeting, if considered 
necessary.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29V</number> Functions of Safety 
Committee.—The functions of the 
Committee shall be—
 <section>         <number>1</number> to discuss remedial measures against the unsafe 
conditions and practices in the mine as pointed out in the reports of Workmen’s 
Inspector or otherwise brought to the notice of the Committee and make 
appropriate recommendations;
 </section><section>         <number>2</number> to consider, before commencement of operations 
in any new district of mine or commissioning of new electrical or mechanical 
installation or introduction of new mining technique, the proposed Safety and 
health measures including related codes of practice and to make appropriate 
recommendations;
 </section><section>         <number>3</number> to discuss the report of inquiry into accident 
and make appropriate recommendations;
 </section><section>         <number>4</number> to formulate and implement appropriate Safety 
campaign based on analysis of accidents;
 </section><section>         <number>5</number> to meet at least once in 30 days to consider 
the matter placed before it and any other matter that may be raised by the 
members and make such recommendations as it may deem fit; and
 </section><section>         <number>6</number> to serve as a forum for communication on Safety 
and occupational health matters.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>*<number>29W</number> Implementation of 
recommendations of the Safety Committee.—The 
owner, agent or manager shall, within a period of 15 days from the date of 
receipt of the recommendations of the Safety Committee, shall indicate to the 
Secretary to the Safety Committee, the action taken to implement the 
recommendations.]
  



</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 


 <article>
<number>30</number> Quantity of drinking 
water.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
quantity of drinking water to be provided in a mine or any part thereof shall be 
on a scale of at least 

1[two litres] for 
every person employed at any one time and such drinking water shall be readily 
available at conveniently accessible points during the whole of the working 
shift.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 100 persons or 
more are employed, either above ground or in open cast working, at any one time, 
an Inspector may by order in writing require the drinking water to be 
effectively cooled by mechanical or other means available.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No charge shall be 
made for the drinking water so supplied.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Storage of drinking 
water.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
If drinking water is not provided from taps connected with constant water supply 
system, it shall be kept cool in suitable vessels sheltered from weather and 
such vessels shall be emptied, cleaned and refilled every day. Steps shall be 
taken to preserve the water, the storage vessels and the vessels used for 
drinking water in a clean and hygienic condition.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the source of 
drinking water is not from a public water supply system, an Inspector may by 
order in writing require the owner, agent or manager of the mine to submit with 
the least possible delay a certificate from a competent health authority or 
analyst as to the fitness of the water for human consumption.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Decision of Chief 
Inspector final.—If 
any question arises as to whether water supply arrangements are satisfactory and 
in accordance with the requirements of section 19 and rules 30 and 31, the 
decision of the Chief Inspector shall be final.
 


</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Surface laterines and 
urinals.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
the surface at every mine, adequate latrine and urinal accommodation shall be 
provided at conveniently accessible places separately for the use of males and 
females employed in the mine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The scale of latrine 
accommodation shall be at least one seat for every 50 males and at least one 
seat for every 50 females employed at only one time:
 
Provided that where 
sanitary latrines are maintained in bathing places, the number of latrines to be 
provided under this rule may include such sanitary latrines.
 
Note.—In 
calculating latrine accommodation, any fraction less than 50 shall be reckoned 
as 50.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Standards of 
construction.—Every 
latrine on the surface provided for the use of persons employed in a mine shall 
conform to the following standards of construction:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> it shall be on a site approved 
of in writing by an Inspector;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> it shall be built of brick or 
other suitable building material;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> it shall be adequately drained 
and properly ventilated and afforded effective protection from the weather;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> it shall be of a type approved 
of in writing by an Inspector;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number> the floor and any interior 
surface of walls up to a height of 

1[1.25 metres] shall be cement punned 
or otherwise so finished as to provide a smooth impressive surface;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number> it shall be partitioned off so 
as to secure privacy and shall have a proper door and fastenings; and where a 
latrine intended for the use of one sex adjoins a latrine intended for the use 
of other sex, the approaches shall be separate;
 </section><section>
         <number>g</number> where a latrine is of the 
service type, the service chamber shall be provided with an efficient trap door 
and the receptacles for night-soil shall be of galvanised iron;
 </section><section>
         <number>h</number> the interior walls, ceilings and 
partitions shall be white-washed once at least in every four months, and the 
date of such white-washing shall be recorded in a book kept at the mine for the 
purpose:
 
                 Provided that this 
requirement regarding white-washing shall not apply to those parts of walls, 
ceilings or partitions which are laid in glazed tiles or otherwise finished so 
as to provide a smooth polished and impervious surface but all these parts shall 
be washed with suitable detergents and disinfectants at least once in every 
seven days.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Sign-boards to be 
displayed.—Where 
persons of both sexes are employed, there shall be displayed outside each 
latrine a signboard in the language understood by the majority of workpersons 
“For Males” or “For Females” as the case may be. Each signboard shall also have 
the figure of a man or a woman as the case may be.
 


</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Provision of water for 
washing, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a piped water supply is available, a sufficient number of water taps, 
conveniently accessible, shall be provided in or near such latrines.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If piped water supply 
is not available, a sufficient quantity of water shall be kept stored in 
suitable receptacles near such latrines.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Underground latrines.—If 
in any mine more than fifty persons are employed underground at any one time, 
latrines shall be provided underground on a scale approved by an Inspector at 
convenient points near the working shafts and at entrances to the districts or 
sections of the mine. The latrines shall be of a type approved of in writing by 
an Inspector.
 


</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Sanitation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At every mine all underground working places and travelling roadways shall be 
kept clean from excreta.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All latrines and 
urinals in or about a mine shall be kept in a clean and sanitary condition.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Receptacles for 
night-soil shall be cleaned and disinfected at least once in every day.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Proper arrangements 
shall be made on the surface for the disposal of night-soil and urine. Such 
arrangements shall comply with the requirements of any health authority or Mines 
Board within whose jurisdiction the mine is situated.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Obligation of 
workpersons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall want only misuse or damage the latrines provided either on the 
surface or underground.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall 
pollute the underground working of a mine with excreta. All persons employed 
underground shall acquaint themselves with the sanitary arrangements provided 
from time to time in the section of the mine in which they have to work or pass.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>40</number> 
Arrangements for training persons in first-aid etc.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be the duty 
of the owner, agent or manager of a mine to see that adequate and suitable 
arrangements are made for the training of persons in first-aid and the provision 
of such equipments as is prescribed in these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) It shall be the 
duty of the owner, agent or manager to see that adequate and suitable 
arrangements are made for the speedy removal from the mine to a dispensary or 
hospital, of persons employed in the mine who while on duty suffers from serious 
bodily injury or illness of a serious nature.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Unless otherwise 
approved by an order in writing of the Chief Inspector or an Inspector and 
subject to such conditions as may be specified therein, the arrangements for the 
purposes of clause (a) shall be by means of a proper ambulance van, and in case 
such ambulance van is not readily available in spite of proper and timely 
requisition, it may be by other suitable motor vehicle in which the person can 
be taken in a supine condition on a stretcher.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> First-aid 
qualifications.—No 
person other than a qualified nurse, dresser, compounder-cum-dresser or medical 
practitioner shall be appointed to render first-aid 

1[or to be in 
charge of a first-aid station referred to in rule 44] unless he is the holder of 
a valid first aid certificate of the standard of St. John’s Ambulance 
Association (India).
 
 



</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>42</number> First-aid 
personnel.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent or manager of a mine shall see that every 
first-aid station provided under rule 44 is placed, during every working shift, 
in charge of a person holding qualifications specified in rule 41. The person in 
charge of a first-aid station in any shift should be readily available 
throughout the shift.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The name and 
designation of every person appointed to be in charge of a first-aid station 
shall be prominently displayed at every first-aid station.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An up-to-date list of 
persons appointed to be in charge of first-aid stations in the mine shall be 
kept in the office of the mine and also displayed prominently at the first-aid 
room.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>43</number> 

1[First-aid] rooms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At every mine employing 

1[more than 150 persons] on any one day 
of the preceding calendar year, there shall be provided and maintained in good 
order a suitable 

1[first-aid] room.
 

1[(2) The first-aid room shall be 
situated at a convenient place on the surface of the mine and shall be used only 
for first-aid work.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The 

1[first-aid] room shall have a floor 
space of not less than 

1[10 square metres] and shall contain at 
least the equipment specified in the Second Schedule.
 

2[(4) (a) The first-aid room shall be in 
charge of a qualified medical practitioner, where the number of persons 
ordinarily employed in a mine is more than 1000, such medical practitioner shall 
be a whole time employee at the mine.
 <subsection><number>b</number> The medical practitioner 
referred to in clause (a) shall be assisted by a nurse and a dresser or a 
compounder and a dresser who are qualified in the Allopathic system of medicine. 
Whenever the Chief Inspector feels it necessary, he may require by an order in 
writing that such number of additional nurses or compounders or dressers shall 
be appointed to assist the medical practitioner as may be specified by him.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The nurse, compounder or 
dresser referred to in clause (b) shall be whole time employee of the mine and 
shall be readily available at the first-aid room throughout the period when 
persons work at the mine:
 Provided that where in 
conformity with any other law in force, or otherwise an adequately equipped 
hospital or dispensary belonging to the owner of the mine or to any Mines 
Welfare Organisation is provided and maintained at or in the immediate vicinity 
of the mine, the Chief Inspector or an Inspector authorised by him in this 
behalf may grant exemption from the provision of this sub-rule subject to such 
conditions as he may specify in writing.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Every person who suffers an 
injury during the course of work shall report for examination or treatment at


3[the first-aid] room, hospital or 
dispensary, as the case may be, before leaving the mine, irrespective of 
first-aid having been rendered at or near the place of work.
  





</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>44</number> First-aid stations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At every mine there shall be provided and maintained first-aid equipment as 
prescribed in the Third Schedule, at conveniently accessible stations where 
injured persons may receive first-aid treatment, as follows:
 <subsection>         <number>a</number> above ground, a first-aid station—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number> at the top of every shaft or incline 
where men or material are normally wound or hauled;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number> in every workshop;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>iii</number> at every screening plant and loading 
place; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>iv</number> at every other place where more than 50 
persons are employed at any one time.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  in every opencast working, one first-aid 
station for every 50 persons or part thereof, employed at any one time; and
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number> below ground, one first-aid station—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number> at the bottom of every shaft where men or 
material are normally wound, and at or near every plant;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number> near the drive and of every haulage;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>iii</number> in or at the entrance to every district 
or section of the mine:
 Provided that nothing in this 
sub-rule shall be construed to require the provision of a first-aid station 
within 300 metres of another first-aid station.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> It shall be the duty of the 
person appointed to be in charge of first-aid station under rule 42, to see that 
the equipment provided at the station is kept in good order and that it is 
replenished whenever necessary.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An up-to-date list of all 
first-aid stations provided in the mine shall be kept in the office of the mine 
and also displayed prominently at the first-aid room.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>45</number> Carrying of first-aid outfit by 
officials.—Notwithstanding anything 
contained in rule 42, every overman, foreman, sirdar, mate, shot-firer, blaster, 
electrician and mechanic in a mine shall hold the first-aid qualifications 
specified in rule 41 and shall carry, while on duty, a first-aid outfit 
consisting of one large sterilized dressing, one small sterilized dressing and 
an ampule of tincture of iodine or other suitable antiseptic, and such outift 
shall be securely packed to protect it against dirt and water.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>45A</number> Medical attention in case of 
injury.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person receiving an 
injury in the course of his duty shall, as soon as possible, report the same to 
an official. Where the person receiving an injury is not in a position to report 
the same to an official, it shall be the duty of the person who first comes to 
know of it, to report the same to an official. The official shall make such 
arrangements for rendering first aid to the injured as may be required. If in 
the opinion of the official the injury is of such a nature as to require 
immediate attention by the medical practitioner he shall arrange for the medical 
practitioner to be called.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If an official who is 
required to carry a first-aid outfit under rule 45 receives information about 
injury to a workperson, he shall himself attend to the injured person.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be the duty of the 
person in charge of the nearest first-aid station provided under rule 44 to 
render such first-aid to the injured person as may be necessary.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>46</number> Persons holding positions 
of supervision or management etc.—For 
the purpose of section 37, the following shall be deemed to be persons holding 
position of supervision or management or employed in a confidential capacity:—
 
          1[
<section><number>a</number>  
manager, undermanager, underground manager, assistant manager, ventilation 
officer and safety officer;]
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> mining, electrical and mechanical engineer;
 
          1[(c)  
overman, foreman, sirdar, and mate;]
 
          1[(d)  
mechanical and electrical foreman and electrical supervisor;]
 </section><section>         <number>e</number> surveyor and assistant surveyor;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number> medical officer, chemist, assayer, metallurgist 
and welfare or personnel officer;
 
          2[(g)  
any other person who in the opinion of the Chief Inspector holds a position of 
supervision or management.]
  




</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Weekly day of rest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of sections 28 and 29, a day of rest for any person shall mean a 
period of rest of at least 24 consecutive hours.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall be posted 
up in a conspicuous place outside the office of every mine a notice showing the 
weekly day of rest. Where the weekly day of rest is not the same day for all 
persons employed in the mine, the notice shall show the day of rest allowed to 
each relay, or set of persons, or individual.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Notice regarding hours 
of work.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The notice of hours of work referred to in sub-section (1) of section 36 shall 
be maintained in Form A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In addition to the 
particulars specified in sub-sections (1) and (3) of section 36, the notice 
shall also show the particulars of the system in which periodical changes of 
shifts are made for all or each set of persons employed in the mine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the notice 
shall be affixed on the first page in the registers maintained in Forms B, C, D 
and E.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Compensatory days of 
rest.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
compensatory days of rest to be allowed under sub-section (1) of section 29 
shall be so spaced that in any one week not more than two such days shall be 
allowed to any one person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On or before the last 
day of every month, there shall be displayed on a notice board outside the 
office of the mine a list of all persons who have not been allowed compensatory 
days of rest during that month, and the dates on which compensatory days of rest 
will be allowed to them in the following two months.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event of a 
person being discharged or dismissed, such number of compen-satory days as are 
due to him shall not be reckoned as part of any period of notice to which he is 
entitled under any rule, award, agreement or contract of service, and he shall 
be allowed all such compensatory days of rest before the date of his discharge 
or dismissal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> There shall be 
maintained at every mine a register of compensatory days of rest in Form F.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Exemption from hours 
and limitation of employment.—For 
the purpose of section 39 of the Act, male adults employed in a mine on any work 
specified in column 1 of the Fourth Schedule shall be exempted from the 
provisions of the sections of the Act specified in column 2, subject to such 
conditions as are specified in column 3.
 


</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>51</number> Termination of employment.—When 
the employment of a person in a mine is terminated, whether by way of dismissal, 
discharge or otherwise,  
or where such person leaves the employment, the date of such termination  
or leaving shall be entered against his name in the register maintained in  
Form B.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>52</number> Employment of apprentices and 
trainees.—No apprentice or trainee of 
the age of sixteen to eighteen years shall be employed in a mine except under 
immediate supervision of a competent person and no such apprentice or trainee 
shall be employed in a mine—
 <section>         <number>a</number> in any work which is unduly arduous; or
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> in close proximity to any machinery involving 
risk of injury from any moving part of the machines; or   
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> at any place where the dust produced in mining 
operations is known to constitutes a hazard to health.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>53</number> Register of leave with 
wages.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent or manager of every mine shall maintain in respect of every 
employee thereof a record of leave with wages in Forms G and H:
 Provided that if the Chief 
Inspector or an Inspector is of opinion that any muster roll or register 
maintained in accordance with any other rules for the time being in force 
contains all the particulars required for the observance of the provisions 
contained in Chapter VII of the Act, he may, by order in writing, permit the 
maintenance of such muster roll or register in place of the register in Forms G 
and H:
 Provided further that in the 
case of a mine exempted under section 56, the Chief Inspector or an Inspector 
may permit the maintenance of records of leave with wages in such manner as he 
may approve by order in writing.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The registers mentioned in 
sub-rule (1) shall be preserved for a period of two years after the last entry 
in them has been made and shall not be destroyed even after the expiry of that 
period unless it has been certified by an Inspector that the leave account 
therein has been properly transferred to the new registers.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>54</number> Information regarding leave with 
wages.—On or before the 20th day of February every year the owner, agent or 
manager of a mine shall exhibit on the notice board at the office of the mine 
information regarding leave with wages due to each person employed in the mine 
calculated upto the Ist of January of that year giving the particulars specified 
in Form L.]
  



</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 

1[***]



 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>56</number> Payment of leave wages 
due if a person dies.—In the event of 
any person entitled to leave with wages, shall accrue to his legal heirs or 
nominee as the case may be.
  
  
</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>56</number> Payment of leave wages 
due if a person dies.—In the event of 
any person entitled to leave with wages, shall accrue to his legal heirs or 
nominee as the case may be.
  
  
</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
 

1[***]
  




 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
 

1[***]
  



 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Overtime register.—The 
register required by sub-section (4) of section 33 shall be maintained in Form 
I. 
 
 
</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>60</number> Extra wages for overtime.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of section 33, overtime shall be paid at the end of each 
wage-period] 

2[***].
 

3[(2)] In calculating overtime on any 
day, a fraction of an hour less than 30 minutes shall be ignored and a fraction 
of 30 minutes or more shall be counted as one hour.
 

4[(3)] In calculating the ordinary rate 
of wages or earnings in the case of a person paid by the month, the daily wages 
shall be 1/26th of his monthly rate of wages, and in the case of any other 
person it shall be the ordinary rate of his daily wages or earnings as the case 
may be.
  






</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Cases of exemption 
under section 56.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an exemption is granted under section 56, the manager shall display at the 
main entrance of the mine, a notice giving full details of the system 
established in the mine for leave with wages and shall send a copy of it to the 
Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No alteration shall be 
made in the scheme approved by the Central Government at the time of granting 
exemption under section 56 without its previous sanction.
 


</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

2[<number>62</number> Provision of shelters.—At 
every mine where more than 50 persons are  
ordinarily employed, there shall be provided adequate and suitable shelter at or 
near loading wharves, opencast workings, workshops and mine entrances where 25 
or more persons are ordinarily employed, for taking food and rest:
 Provided that any canteen 
maintained in accordance with these rules may be  
regarded as part of the requirements of this rule.]
  



</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Standards of shelters.—Every 
shelter shall—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> have a floor area of not less 
than 

1[14 square metres]; and 
 

                    1[(i)  in the case 
of a flat roof, a height of not less than 2.5 metres to the lowest part of the 
roof; and
 <subsection>
              <number>ii</number>  where the roof is a 
sloping one, a height of not less than 1.8 metres to the lowest part of the roof 
and not less than 2.5 metres to the heighest part of the roof;]
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>b</number> be so constructed as to afford 
effective protection from the weather;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> be constantly provided with 
adequate supply of cool and wholesome drinking water during the working hours of 
the mine;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> be kept in a clean and tidy 
condition.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>64</number> Provision 
of Canteens.—
<section><number>1</number> At every mine wherein more than 250 persons are ordinarily 
employed, if the Chief Inspector or an Inspector so requires, there shall be 
provided and maintained in or adjacent to the precincts of the mine a canteen 
for the use of all persons employed:
 
Provided that where the 
conditions at any mine so require the Chief Inspector or an Inspector may direct 
that other suitable arrangements approved by him for serving food, drink and 
other items to the persons employed be provided and maintained in addition to 
the canteen required under this sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If in any case, the 
Chief Inspector or Inspector is satisfied that no inconvenience will be caused 
to the employees concerned if a single canteen is provided to serve neighbouring 
mines, he may, by an order in writing and subject to such conditions as he may 
specify therein, authorise the owners, agents or managers of such mines to 
provide jointly a single canteen.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>65</number> Standards of canteen.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
Every canteen shall—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number> be constructed in accordance with plans and 
specifications approved by the Chief Inspector or an Inspector;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number> be situated not less than
2[15 
metres] from any latrine, urinal, boiler house, engine room, coal heap, ash heap 
or heap of other material and any other source of dust or smoke;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number> be sufficiently lighted during all hours when 
open for use;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>d</number> be provided with a washing place for females, 
suitably separated or screened to secure privacy;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>e</number> be white-washed or colour-washed inside the 
rooms and passages at least once a year, and woodwork and structural iron or 
steel work shall be varnished or painted at least once every three years;
                   Provided that the inside walls of the 
kitchen shall be white-washed or colour- washed once every four months.
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>f</number> be provided with receptacles for garbage and 
have drains to carry away waste water.
 

3[(2) The canteen or any part thereof 
shall not be used or allowed to be used for any other purpose which tends to 
interfere with the normal or efficient functioning of the canteen.]
  





</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Furniture and 
equipment.—In 
every canteen there shall be provided and maintained—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> sufficient furniture, utensils 
and other equipment necessary for its efficient operation;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> an adequate supply of cool and 
wholesome drinking water;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> suitable clean clothes for 
persons cooking and serving food, drink, etc.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Cleanliness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The canteen and its precincts shall be kept in a sanitary condition.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An adequate supply of 
hot water shall be provided for cleansing utensils and equipment; and all 
furniture, utensils and other equipment shall be kept clean and in a hygienic 
condition.
 


</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>68</number> Maintenance of canteens and 
provision of staff.—
<section><number>1</number> Every canteen provided under these rules shall be 
run by the owner, agent or 

2[officer in-charge canteen] thereof who 
shall appoint supervisory and other staff sufficient for the proper working of 
the canteen.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (1), where the workers offer to run the canteen themselves 
and for this purpose organise a Co-operative Society, they shall be permitted to 
do so with financial assistance from the management.]
 

3[(3) In every such canteen, such food, 
drink or other articles shall be made available as may be recommended by the 
Canteen Managing Committee appointed under rule 69.]
  





</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>69</number> Canteen Managing 
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent or


1[officer in-charge canteen] shall 
appoint a Canteen Managing Committee which shall be consulted from time to time, 
but not less than once a month, as to the management and working of the canteen.
 </section><section><number>2</number>  (a) The Committee shall 
consist of an equal number of members nominated by the owner, agent or 

1[officer in-charge canteen] and elected 
by the persons employed in the mine. The number of elected members shall be on a 
scale of one for every 1,000 persons employed, provided that the number shall 
not be more than 5 or less than 2.
 <subsection><number>b</number> The term of office of the 
elected members shall be two years commencing from the date of the last 
election, no account being taken of a bye-election.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The owner, agent or 

1[officer in-charge canteen] shall 
determine the procedure for and supervise the elections to the Committee.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>          The owner, agent or


1[officer in-charge canteen] shall 
appoint either himself or his nominee as ex-officio Chairman of the Committee, 
and the Chairman shall preside at every meeting of the Committee.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The proceedings of every 
meeting of the Committee shall be recorded in a minute book and shall be signed 
by the Chairman.
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>70</number> Prices to be charged.—Food, 
drink and other items served in a canteen shall be sold on a non-profit basis 
and the prices charged shall be subject to the approval of the Canteen 
Management Committee. A list of approved prices shall be conspicuously displayed 
in the canteen in English, Hindi and in the language of the district in which 
the mine is situated.
 

1[Explanation.—In calculating the 
cost of food, drink and other items served in a canteen, expenditure on the 
following items shall not be taken into account:—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  the cost of utensils, including cooking 
vessels and utensils necessary to serve food to the workmen;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  the cost of furniture;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  the cost of coal, fuel and electricity; and
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  the salaries of supervisory and other staff.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>71</number> Accounts.—Proper 
accounts pertaining to the canteen shall be maintained. Such accounts shall be 
audited once every twelve months by a 

1[chartered accountant] or auditor, and a 
balance-sheet shall be submitted to the Canteen Management Committee not later 
than two months after the date of closing of the accounts:
 

2[Provided that the accounts pertaining 
to the canteen in a mine owned and worked by Government having its own Accounts 
Department, may be audited by such Department.]
  




</article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>72</number> Welfare Officers.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
For every mine wherein 500 or more persons are 

2[ordinarily employed], the owner, agent 
or manager shall appoint a suitably qualified person as Welfare Officer, and 
where the number of persons so employed in a mine exceeds 2,500, such Welfare 
Officer shall be assisted by one suitably qualified additional Welfare Officer 
for every additional 2,000 persons or part thereof employed.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall act as a 
Welfare Officer of a mine unless he possesses—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number> a university degree;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  a degree or diploma in social science,
3[or 
social work] or labour welfare
2[recognised 
by the Government for the purpose of this rule], and preferably practical 
experience of handling labour problems in any industrial undertaking for at 
least three years; and
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number> a knowledge of the language of the district in 
which the mine is situated or the language understood by the majority of persons 
employed in the mine:
 Provided that in case of a 
person already in service as a Welfare Officer in a mine the above 
qualifications may, with the approval of the Chief Inspector, be relaxed.
 

4[(2A) Notwithstanding anything contained 
in sub-rule (2), the Labour Officers included in the Central Pool under the 
provisions of the Labour Officers (Central Pool) Recruitment and Conditions of 
Service Rules, 1951, shall be eligible for appointment as a Welfare Officer in a 
mine.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Where by reason of temporary 
absence, illness or any other similar cause, the Welfare Officer is unable to 
perform his duties, the owner, agent or manager shall authorise in writing a 
person whom he considers competent, to act in his place:
 Provided that no such authority 
shall have effect for a period in excess of 30 days except with the previous 
consent of the Chief Inspector or Inspector.
 

2[(4) A written notice of every 
appointment, authorisation, discharge, dismissal, resignation or termination of 
service of every Welfare Officer and of the date thereof shall be sent by the 
owner, agent or manager to the Chief Inspector within seven days from the date 
of such appointment, authorisation, discharge, dismissal, resignation or 
termination of service.]
 

5[(5) The post of Welfare Officer shall 
be advertised in a newspaper having a wide circulation in the State.]
  







</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>73</number> Duties of Welfare 
Officer.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The duties of Welfare Officer shall be—
 <subsection>          <number>i</number> to establish contacts and hold consultations 
with a view to maintain harmonious relations between the management and persons 
employed in the mine;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>ii</number> to bring to the notice of the management the 
grievances of employees, individual as well as collective, with a view to 
securing their expeditious redressal;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>iii</number> to promote relations between management and 
employees, which will ensure productivity efficiency as well as amelioration in 
the working conditions, and to help workers to adjust and adapt themselves to 
their working environments;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>iv</number> to assist in the formation of Works and Joint 
Production Committees, Co-operative Societies and Safety-First and Welfare 
Committees and to supervise their work;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>v</number> to help the management in regulating the grant 
of leave with wages and explain to the workers the provisions relating to leave 
with wages and other leave privileges and to guide the workers in the matter of 
submission of applications for grant of leave for regulating authorised absence;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>vi</number> to advise on welfare provisions such as housing 
facilities, food-stuffs, social and recreational facilities, sanitation, 
individual personnel problems and education of children;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>vii</number> to supervise welfare activities, statutory or 
otherwise, including education and training of employees;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>viii</number>  to suggest measures which will tend to raise 
the standard of living of workers and in general promote their well-being; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ix</number> to perform any other duty connected with the 
welfare of the persons employed in the mine.
 

2[(2) Notwithstanding anything contained 
in sub-rule (1), no Welfare Officer shall deal with any disciplinary case 
against a person employed in a mine, or appear before a Conciliation Officer, 
Court or Tribunal on behalf of the management of a mine against a person or 
persons employed in the mine, except when he is required by the Conciliation 
Officer, Court or Tribunal to appear as an independent witness:
 Provided that nothing in this 
sub-rule shall be deemed to prohibit a person  
employed in a mine from approaching the Welfare Officer in respect of a 
grievance arising out of any case of disciplinary action against him.]
 

3[(3)] Every Welfare Officer shall keep 
the record of his day-to-day work and shall at the end of every year forward to 
the Chief Inspector through the manager of the mine concerned, a summary of the 
report of his work during the year.]
  





</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Conditions of service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Welfare Officer shall be given appropriate status corresponding to the status 
of the other executive heads of the mine.
 

1[(2) The 
conditions of service of a Welfare Officer shall be the same as of other members 
of the staff or corresponding status in the mine:
 
Provided that before the 
owner, agent or manager discharges or dismisses a Welfare Officer who has 
satisfactorily completed a probationary period of six months, he shall consult 
the Chief Inspector or an Inspector authorised in this behalf by the Chief 
Inspector.]
 

2[(3) A Welfare 
Officer shall not be given less than two hundred rupees as his basic pay per 
mensem.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Maintenance and 
production of reports, registers and other records.—All 
reports, registers and other records maintained in pursuance of the regulations, 
rules or bye-laws, unless otherwise provided for, shall—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> be kept at an office or the 
nearest convenient building within the precincts of the mine;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> be legibly entered in ink in 
English, Hindi or either the language of the district in which the mine is 
situated or the language understood by a majority of the persons employed in the 
mine;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> be preserved in original for a 
period of one calendar year after the date of the last report or entry:
 
                  Provided that when the 
original record is lost or destroyed before the expiry of one year’s period, 
true copies thereof, if available, shall be preserved for the prescribed period;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> be produced on demand before the 
Chief Inspector or Inspector or any person authorised in that behalf by the 
Central Government.
 
 
</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>76</number> Registers of reportable and minor 
accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> The registers required 
by sub-section (1A) of section 23 of the Act shall be maintained in Form J and a 
copy thereof shall be sent to the concerned Inspector of Mines.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The register, required by 
sub-section (3) of section 23 of the Act shall be maintained in Form K.]
  



</section></article> 
 The MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>77</number> Register of employees.—The 
register required by sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 48 shall be maintained in Form 
B, 

1[keeping separate page for each person 
employed in the mine.
  
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>77A</number> Identity 
tokens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The owner, agent or manager of a mine shall issue, free of 
cost, to every person employed in the mine, a metal token (hereinafter referred 
to as token), bearing a number and other particulars by which such person may be 
identified:
 
Provided that if any other 
equally effective system of identification is in force in any mine and Chief 
Inspector is satisfied of the same he may exempt such mine from the operation of 
this rule, subject to such conditions as he may deem fit to impose.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> No person employed in 
a mine shall enter or be permitted to enter for work in any part of a mine 
unless he carries on his person the token issued to him.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The token shall be of 
such durable and strong material as cannot be easily damaged or defaced.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The token shall be 
carried by an employee on his person during the time he is on duty.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> Where a token is 
damaged, defaced or lost, due to reasons other than the fault or negligence of 
the employee concerned a duplicate token shall be issued forthwith to such 
employee free of charge and such duplicate token shall be stamped “DUPLICATE”.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> Where a token is 
damaged, defaced or lost due to the fault or negligence of the employee 
concerned, a duplicate token stamped “DUPLICATE”, shall be issued forthwith and 
such employee shall be liable to pay fifty per cent of the cost of the duplicate 
token issued to him.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The token number and 
other particulars by which the employee may be identified, together with a 
passport size photograph, shall be entered in the register in Form B prescribed 
under rule 77.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Register of daily 
attendance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The registers required by sub-section (4) of section 48 of persons employed in 
the mine 
<subsection><number>a</number> below ground, (b) in open-cast workings and (c) above ground shall 
be maintained if Forms C, D, and E respectively.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The entries in the 
register maintained in Form C shall be made at the entrance or entrances to the 
mine, at the time when a person against whose name the entry is made enters or 
leave the mine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The entries in the 
registers maintained in Forms D and E shall be made at suitable points on the 
premises of the mine with reasonable despatch, at the commencement and end of 
the period of work.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>79</number> Postings of abstracts, 
bye-laws and notices.—
<section><number>1</number> The abstracts of the Act as 
given in the Fifth Schedule shall be posted up outside the office of every mine 
in English, Hindi and either the language of the district in which the mine is 
situated or the language understood by a majority of the persons employed in the 
mine.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The bye-laws shall be posted 
up in the manner required by sub-section (5) of section 61, in English, Hindi 
and either the language of the district in which the mine is situated or the 
language understood by a majority of the persons employed in the 
mine:
 Provided that the Chief 
Inspector may require the abstracts and the bye-laws to be posted up in any 
Indian language other than the language of the district in which the mine is 
situated or the language understood by a majority of the persons employed in the 
mine.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every notice required to be 
posted up under these rules shall be in English, Hindi and either the language 
of the district in which the mine is situated or the language understood by a 
majority of the persons employed in the mine.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The abstracts, bye-laws and 
notices required to be posted up by the Act, regulations and rules shall be 
maintained in a clear and legible condition.
  </section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Observance of local 
time.—For the 
purpose of section 4, the local mean time that shall ordinarily be observed in 
any class or group of mines situated in any local area, specified in column 1 of 
the Sixth Schedule shall be as specified in column 2 thereof.
 


</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Intoxicating drugs and 
drinks.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
intoxicating drink or drug shall be carried or permitted to be carried below 
ground into the workings of a mine or part.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall, 
during the course of his employment in or about a mine, possess, carry or 
consume any intoxicating drink or drug or remain in a state of intoxication or 
drunkenness.
 


</section></article> 
 THE MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>82</number> Occupational 
diseases—Fees of medical 
practitioner.—A medical practitioner making an examination in accordance 
with sub-section (2) of section 25, shall be paid as follows:
 <section>         
<number>a</number>  a fee not exceeding rupees sixteen for each clinical 
examination.
 </section><section>         
<number>b</number>  a fee not exceeding rupees sixteen for each x-ray 
examination.
  </section></article> 
 THE MINES RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>82</number> Occupational 
diseases—Fees of medical 
practitioner.—A medical practitioner making an examination in accordance 
with sub-section (2) of section 25, shall be paid as follows:
 <section>         
<number>a</number>  a fee not exceeding rupees sixteen for each clinical 
examination.
 </section><section>         
<number>b</number>  a fee not exceeding rupees sixteen for each x-ray 
examination.
  </section></article> 
 THE MINES RULES, 1955
  
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>82A</number> Disability allowance and compensation for occupational diseases.</title>—
<section><number>1</number> The disability allowance payable under first provision to sub-section (5) of section 9A of the Act shall be at the rate of fifty per cent of the monthly wages that he was in receipt of immediately before presenting himself for the medical examination under sub-section (2) of section 9A of the Act. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> If, a person decides to leave his employment in the mine, he shall be entitled to compensation as may be admissible under the provisions of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923) as contacting of such disease is deemed to be an injury by accident under that Act. In case the disease is not covered under Schedule III of that Act, he shall be paid by way of disability compensation at the same rates as provided under that Act as if it is an injury. The lump sum compensation payable under this rule shall not be in addition to the compensation payable under that Act.
 Explanation.—For the purpose of this rule, "wages" shall have the same meaning as defined in clause (m) of section (1) of section 2 of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923). 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) shall not operate to the prejudice to any right to which a person employed in a mine be entitled to under any other law or under the terms of any award, agreement or contract of service and when such award, agreement or contract or service provides for more favourable benefits than the disability compensation provided in sub-rules (1) and (2), such person shall be entitled to such benefit only.]


</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Mode of payment of 
fees etc.—The 
fees or other expenses payable by the owner, agent or manager under these rules 
shall be paid directly into the treasury or a branch of the State Bank of India, 
and the reciept of the treasury or bank shall be sent to the Chief Inspector 
along with the particulars to which the fees or other expenses relate.
 


</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>83A</number> Appeals 
to the Chief Inspector.—Against an order made by the Inspector under any of 
these rules, an appeal shall lie to the Chief Inspector who may confirm or 
modify or cancel the order. Every such appeal shall be preferred within 30 days 
of the receipt of the order by the appellant.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE MINES RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Rescission and 
Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All rules framed by State Government under section 30 of Indian Mines Act, 1923, 
those contained in Chapter II, III and VI of the Mysore Gold Mines Rules, 1953, 
and those issued vide the Government of India notification No. S.R.O. 
2403, dated the 12th July, 1954, are hereby rescinded, but all acts done, orders 
issued and certificates granted or renewed under any rule so rescinded shall, so 
far as they are not inconsistent with these rules, be deemed to have been 
respectively done, issued, granted or renewed under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rules contained in 
Chapter IV amd V of the Mysore Gold Mines Rules, 1953, shall continue to apply 
to gold mines in the State of Mysore in addition to these rules.
 
 
  
</section></article><form>
 


The MINES RULES, 1955
 




 


SECOND SCHEDULE
 


[See rule 43(3)]
 


Equipment of


1[a 
first-aid room]
 


      (a) A stretcher and a table of 
convenient height 

3[0.75 metres] large enough to place 
the stretcher on;
 


      (b) a bench or chairs, and one screen;
 


      (c) a glazed sink; with water readily 
available;
 


      (d) soap, towel and nail brush;
 


      (e) a supply of suitable sterilized 
dressings, cotton wool, bandages and adhesive plaster;
 


       (f) a supply of tincture of iodine (2 
per cent alcoholic solution) or other antiseptic solution;
 


      (g) blankets and hot-water bottles;
 


      (h) sets of splints 

2[1.40 metres, 0.90 metre and 0.3 
metre], with necessary triangular bandages for applying them;
 


       (i) a supply of drinking water and a 
drinking vessel;
 


       (j) a tourniquet, scissors and safety 
pins;
 


      (k) a pair of artery forceps;
 


       (l) one eyebath;
 


     (m) two clinical thermometers;
 


      (n) one record syringe (5 c.c.)
 


      (o) an adequate supply of anti-tetanus 
serum and morphine ampules;
 


      (p) first-aid boxes or cupboards not 
less than one for every 150 persons employed in the mine marked with requisites 
specified in Third Schedule; and
 


      (q) stove or other apparatus for 
boiling water.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Subs. by G.S.R. 239, dated 3rd 
February, 1965.
 


   2. Subs. by G.S.R. 31, dated 29th 
December, 1960.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The MINES RULES, 1955
 


 
 


THIRD SCHEDULE
 


[See rule 44(1)]
 


Requisites of a 
first-aid station
 


      (a) a stretcher with two blankets;
 


      (b) sets of splints 

1[1.40 metres, 0.90 metre and 0.3 
metre], with necessary triangular bandages for applying them;
 


      (c) first-aid boxes or cupboards not 
less than one for every 150 persons employed containing at least—
 


             (i) a sufficient supply of large 
and small sterilized dressings and burn dressings;
 


            (ii) a sufficient supply of 
sterilized cotton-wool and of adhesive plaster;
 


           (iii) a supply of roller bandages;
 


           (iv) a supply of tincture of 
iodine or other antiseptic solution;
 


            (v) a tourniquet, scissors and 
safety pins; and
 


           (vi) a piece of carbolic soap.
 


Note.—Each 
first-aid box or cupboard shall be distinctly marked with the sign of Red Cross 
and with the words “FIRST-AID”, and nothing except appliances or requisites for 
first-aid shall be kept in it.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Subs. by G.S.R. 239, dated 3rd 
February, 1965.
 

 
</form><form>
 

The MINES RULES, 1955
 

 
 

FIFTH SCHEDULE
 

[See rule 79(1)]
 

ABSTRACTS OF THE ACT
 

Inspectors
 

1. Any Inspector may enter and inspect any mine (by day and 
night) and make such examination and enquiry as may be necessary to determine 
the condition of the mine and to ascertain whether the provisions of this Act 
and of the Regulations, Rules and Bye-laws are being observed. If he has reason 
to believe that these provisions have been or are being contravened, he may 
search any place and take possession 1[ of any 
material, plan, section, register or other record] concerning the mine. (Section 
7)
 

2. Any Government servant, duly authorised by the Chief 
Inspector or an Inspector may enter any mine for the purpose of surveying, 
levelling and measuring after giving at least 3 days, notice to the manager. 
(Section 8)
 

3. Every owner, agent and manager of a mine shall afford every 
Inspector and every person authorised under section 8 all reasonable facilities 
for making an entry, inspection, survey, measurement, examination or enquiry 
under this Act. (Section 9)
 

Management of Mines
 

4. Every mine shall be under the control, management 2[supervision] 
and direction of one manager having the prescribed qualifications. (Section 
17)
 

5. The owner, agent and manager of every mine shall be 
responsible that all operations carried on in connection with the mine are 
conducted in accordance with the provisions of this Act and of the Regulations, 
Rules and Bye-laws and any order made thereunder. (Section 18)
 

Provision of drinking water, ambulance appliances and 
latrines
 

6. In every mine, both above and below ground—
 

      (a) A sufficient supply of 
cool and wholesome drinking water shall be provided and maintained at suitable 
points conveniently situated for all persons employed in the mine. (Section 
19)
 

      (b) A sufficient number of 
first-aid boxes shall be provided and maintained. (Section 21)
 

      (c) A sufficient number of 
latrines and urinals, separately for males and females, shall be provided in 
every mine at suitable places accessible at all times to all persons employed in 
the mine. All latrines and urinals shall be maintained in a clean and sanitary 
condition. (Section 20)
 

Accidents
 

7. Where there occurs in or about a mine an accident causing 
loss of life or serious bodily injury on any dangerous occurrence, a notice in 
the prescribed form shall be sent to the prescribed authorities and 
simultaneously a copy of such notice shall be posted at the mine on a special 
notice board and kept posted for 3[not less than 
fourteen days] from the date of such posting. (Section 23)
 

8. Where any person employed in a mine contacts any disease 
connected with mining operations, the owner, agent or manager shall send notice 
thereof to the Chief Inspector and to such other authorities as may be 
prescribed. (Section 25)
 

Hours of Limitation of Employment
 

9. No person shall work in a mine on more than six days in any 
one week. (Section 28)
 

10. If any person works, as provided under this Act, on any day 
of rest fixed for him, he should be given a compensatory day of rest within that 
or the following two months. (Section 29)
 

11. No adult shall work above ground in a mine for more than 
forty-eight hours in any week or 4[normally] for 
more than nine hours in any day and he shall have at least half an hour’s rest 
after working for not more than five hours. The spread-over of the period of 
work including rest interval shall not normally be more than 12 hours. 5[Consecutive 
shifts for the same type of workers employed above ground shall not overlap]. 
(Section 30)
 

12. No adult shall work below ground in a mine for more than 
forty-eight hours in any week 4[normally] or 
for more than eight hours in any day 5[***]. (Section 
31)
 

3[13. Where in a 
mine a person works above ground for more than nine hours or works below ground 
for more than eight hours on any day, or works for more than forty-eight hours 
in any week, whether above ground or below ground, he shall get, for such 
overtime work, wages at the rate of twice his ordinary rate of wages.
 

“Ordinary rate of wages”, means the basic wages plus any 
dearness allowance and compensation in cash, including such compensation, if 
any, accruing through free issue of foodgrains etc., but not including bonus. 
(Section 33)
 

14. No person shall be allowed to work in a mine who has already 
been working in any other mine within the preceding 12 hours. (Section 34)
 

3[15. Except as 
may be permitted under clauses (a) and (e) of section 39, no person employed in 
a mine shall be required or allowed to work for more than ten hours in any day, 
inclusive of overtime. (Section 35)]
 

16. The manager of every mine shall post outside the office a 
notice of working hours, and no person shall be allowed to work otherwise than 
in accordance with the notice. (Section 36)
 

17. The provisions regarding weekly day of rest, hours of work 
above and below ground and of section 36 shall not apply to supervising staff. 
(Section 37)
 

18. In case of an emergency, the manager may permit in 
accordance with the rules made under section 39, persons to be employed in 
contravention of the provisions regarding hours of work. (Section 38)
 

Employment of adolescents
 

19. 6[No person below 
16 years of age shall work underground in a mine. No person aged between 16 and 
18 years shall work underground in mine] unless he has been certified as fit for 
work as an adult by a Certifying Surgeon and carries, while at work, token 
giving a reference to such certificate and he shall have rest for at least half 
an hour after not more than four and a half hours of continuous work. He shall 
not be employed between 6 P.M. and 6 A.M. (Section 40).
 

20. A certificate of fitness granted or renewed for the purpose 
of section 10 shall be valid for only 12 months and may be conditional regarding 
employment in general or regarding the nature of work, and may be revoked by a 
Certifying Surgeon if the holder of a certificate is no longer fit for the work 
specified in the certificate. Where a certificate or the renewal of a 
certificate is refused, a Certifying Surgeon shall state his reason for refusal 
if the person concerned so requires. The adolescent or his parents shall not be 
liable to pay any fees for medical examination under section 40 in all cases 
where he is sent by the manager of the mine in which he will be employed if 
found fit. (Section 41)
 

21. An adolescent granted a certificate of fitness and working 
in a mine shall be considered to be an adult for the purposes of this Act. 
(Section 42)
 

6[22. Where an 
Inspector is of opinion that any person working in a mine is a child, or is an 
adolescent without a certificate of fitness, or is an adolescent with a 
certificate of fitness but no longer fit to work in the capacity stated in the 
certificate,  he may ask the manager not to employ such person till such 
person has been examined or re-examined as the case may be, by a Certifying 
Surgeon and declared by him to be an adult or if an adolescent, declared fit.] 
(Section 43)
 

6[23.  (1) 
No adolescent who has not been granted a medical certificate certifying that he 
is fit for work as an adult, shall be employed or permitted to be employed above 
ground or in a mine—
 

      (a) for more than four and a 
half hours in any day, and
 

      (b) between the hours of 6 
P.M. and 6 A.M.
 

(2) The period of work of all such adolescents employed in a 
mine shall be limited to two shifts which shall not be spread over more than 
five hours each and there shall be no change of shifts except once in a period 
of thirty days and with the previous permission in writing of the Chief 
Inspector.] (Section 44)
 

Employment of women and 
children
 

24. No person below the age of fifteen years shall be employed 
in any mine or allowed to be present in any part of a mine which is below ground 
or in any 6[opencast 
working] in which any mining work is being done. (Section 45)
 

6[25. (1) No 
woman shall be employed in any part of a mine which is below ground.
 

(2) No woman shall be employed in any mine above ground except 
between the hours of 6 A.M. and 7 P.M.
 

(3) Every woman employed in a mine above ground shall be allowed 
an interval of not less than eleven hours between the termination of employment 
on any one day and the commencement of the next period of employment.] (Section 
46)
 

Registration of workers
 

7[26. (1) For 
every mine there shall be kept a register of employees showing in respect of 
each person his or her name with the name of his father or of her husband as the 
case may be, age, sex, nature of employment, date of commencement of employment, 
and in case of an adolescent, reference to the certificate of fitness. The 
entries in the register shall be authenticated by the signature or thumb 
impression of the person concerned.
 

(2) There shall also be kept separate attendance register for 
employes working—
 

      (a)  below ground;
 

      (b)  above ground in 
opencast working; and
 

      (c)  above ground in 
other cases;
 

showing in respect of each person the name, class or kind of his 
employment and the hours of shift and the shift to which he belongs. The 
register of persons employed below ground shall show at any moment the name of 
every person who is then present below ground in the mine.
 

(3) No unauthorised person shall enter any opencast working or 
any working below ground.] (Section 48)
 

Leave with wages
 

7[27. (1) Every 
person employed in a mine who has completed a calendar year’s service therein 
shall be allowed, during the subsequent calendar year, leave with wages 
calculated—
 

      (a) in the case of a person 
employed below ground, at the rate of one day for every sixteen days of work 
performed by him; and
 

      (b) in any other case, at the 
rate of one day for every twenty days of work performed by him.
 

(2) A calendar year’s service referred to in sub-clause (1) 
shall be deemed to have been completed—
 

      (a)  in the case of a 
person employed below ground in a mine, if he has during the calendar year put 
in not less than one hundred and ninety attendances at the mine; and
 

      (b) in the case of any other 
person, if he has during the calendar year put in not less than two hundred and 
forty attendances at the mine.
 

Explanation.—For the purpose of this sub-clause—
 

      (a) any days of lay-off by 
agreement or contract or as permissible under the standing order;
 

      (b) in the case of a female 
employee, maternity leave for any number of days not exceeding twelve weeks; and 

 

      (c) the leave earned in the 
year prior to that in which the leave is enjoyed,
 

shall be deemed to be days on which the 
employee has worked in a mine for the purpose of computation of the attendance, 
but he shall not earn leave for these days.
 

(3) A person whose service commences otherwise than on the first 
day of January shall be entitled to leave with wages in the subsequent calendar 
year at the rates specified in clause (1), if—
 

      (a) in the case of a person 
employed below ground in a mine, he has put in attendances for not less than 
one-half of the total number of days during the remainder of the calendar year; 
and
 

      (b) in any other case, he has 
put in attendances for not less than two-thirds of the total number of days 
during the remainder of the calendar year.
 

(4) Any leave not taken by a person to which he is entitled in 
any one calendar year under sub-clause (1) or sub-clause (3) shall be added to 
the leave to be allowed to him under sub-clause (1) during the succeeding 
calendar year:
 

Provided that the total number of days of leave which may be 
accumulated by any such person shall not at any one time exceed thirty days in 
all:
 

Provided further that any such person who has applied for leave 
with wages but has not been given such leave in accordance with sub-clause (6), 
shall be entitled to carry forward the unavailed leave without any limit.
 

(5) Any such person may apply in writing to the manger of the 
mine not less than fifteen days before the day on which he wishes his leave to 
begin, for all leave or any portion thereof then allowable to him under 
sub-clauses (1), (3) and (4):
 

Provided that the number of times in which leave may be taken 
during any one calendar year shall not exceed three.
 

(6) An application for such leave made in accordance with 
sub-clause (5) shall not be refused unless the authority empowered to grant the 
leave is of opinion that owing to the exigencies of the situation the leave 
shall be refused.
 

(7) If a person employed in a mine wants to avail himself of the 
leave with wages due to him to cover a period of illness, he shall be granted 
such leave even if the application is not made within the time specified in 
sub-clause (5).
 

(8) If the employement of a person employed in a mine is 
terminated by the owner, agent or manager of the mine before he has taken the 
entire leave to which he is entitled upto the day of termination of his 
employment, or if such person having applied for and having not been granted 
such leave, quits his employment before he has taken the leave, the owner, agent 
or manager of the mine shall pay him the amount payable under clause 28, in 
respect of the leave not taken, and such payment shall be made, where the 
employment of the person is terminated by the owner, agent or manager, before 
the expiry of the second working day after such termination and where a person 
himself quits his employment, on or before the next pay-day.
 

(9) The unavailed leave of a person employed in a mine shall not 
be taken into consideration in computing the period of any notice required to be 
given before the termination of his employment.
 

Explanation.—For the purposes of sub-clauses (1) and (3), 
any fraction of leave of half a day or more shall be treated as one full day and 
fraction of less than half a day shall be omitted.] (Section 52)
 

8[28. For the 
leave allowed to a person, he shall be paid at a rate equal to the daily average 
of his total full-time earnings during the month immediately preceeding his 
leave, exclusive of overtime wages and bonus, but inclusive of any dearness 
allowance and compensation in cash including such compensation. If any, accruing 
through the free issue of foodgrains, and other articles as persons employed in 
the mine may, for the time being, be entitled to. If figures for his average 
earnings are not available, the average shall be computed on the basis of the 
daily average of the total full-time earnings of all persons similarly employed 
for that month.] (Section 53)
 

8[29. Any person 
who has been allowed leave for not less than four days shall be paid wages due 
for the period of leave allowed before his leave begins.] (Section 54)
 

Penalties
 

30. Any person obstructing an inspector in the execution of his 
duties may be punis-hed with imprisonment up to three months or fine up to Rs. 
500 or both. (Section 63)
 

31. Whoever makes, gives or delivers any plan, return, notice, 
record or report containing a statement, entry or detail which is not to the 
best of his knowledge or belief true, may be punished with imprisonment  up 
to three months or a fine up to 9[Rs. 
1,000]  or both. (Section 64)
 

32. Whoever knowingly uses for himself a certificate of fitness 
granted (under section 40) to some other person or allows a certificate of 
fitness granted to him to be used by any other person, may be punished with 
imprisonment up to one month or a fine up to 10[Rs. 200] or 
both. (Section 65)
 

33. If any person below 18 years of age is employed in more than 
one mine on any day, his parents, guardian or custodian may be punished with a 
fine upto Rs. 50.  (Section 68)
 

34. If any mine is run without a manager, the owner or agent may 
be punished with imprisonment upto three months or with a fine up to 9[Rs. 2500] or 
both. (Section 69)
 

35. Whoever fails to give notice of any accidental occurrence or 
to post a copy of the notice on a special notice board, may be punished with 
imprisonment upto three months or a fine upto Rs. 500 or both. (Section 70)
 

36. No person shall interfere with, misuse or wilfully neglect 
to make use of any appliance provided for the purpose of health, safety or 
welfare of the workers, or wilfully do anything likely to endanger himself or 
others. (Section 2)
 

37. Whoever contravenes any provision of any regulation or 
bye-law or of any order made thereunder relating to matters specified in clauses 
(d), (i), (m), (n), (o), (p), (r), (s) and (u) of section 57 shall be punished 
with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend 
to Rs. 2,000 or with both. (Section 72A)
 

38. Whoever contravenes any order issued under sub-section (1A), 
or sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 22 shall be punished with 
imprisonment upto two years and fine up to Rs. 5,000. (Section 72B)
 

39. Whoever contravenes any provision of the Act or of any 
regulation, rule or bye-law or of any order made thereunder (other than an order 
made under sub-section (1A) or sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 22) 
shall be punishable—
 

      (a) if such contravention 
results in loss of life, with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or 
with fine which may extend  to Rs. 5,000 or with both; or
 

      (b) if such contravention 
results in serious bodily injury, with imprisonment which may extend to one 
year, or with fine which may extend to Rs. 3,000 or with both; or
 

      (c) if such contravention 
otherwise causes injury or danger to persons employed in the mine or other 
persons in or about the mine, with imprisonment which may extend to three months 
or with fine which may extend to Rs. 1,000 or with both. (Section 72C)
 

40. Whoever contravenes any provision of this Act or of any 
regulation, rule or bye-law, or of any order made thereunder, for which no 
penalty is expressly provided may be punished with imprisonment upto three 
months, or a fine up to Rs. 1,000 or both. (Section 73)
 

11[41. If any 
person who has been convicted for any offence other than an offence mentioned in 
clause 38 or 39 is again convicted for the same offence within two years of the 
previous conviction, he shall be punished, for each subsequent conviction, with 
double the punishment to which he would have been liable for the first 
contravention of such provisions.] (Section 74).
 

 
 

—————
 

   1. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   2. Ins. by G.S.R. 
1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   3. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   4.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   5. Omitted by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   6. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   7. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   8. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

   9. Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965, for "Rs. 500".
 

  10.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965, for "Rs. 50".
 

  11.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 1886, dated 25th December, 1965.
 

 
 

 </form><form>
 




The MINES RULES, 1955
 


 
 



SIXTH SCHEDULE
 


(See 
rule 80)
 


 


                     
  1                                           2
 



1[All mines situated 
in the                          An hour in advance of Indian
 


District of Lakhimpur in 
the                        Standard Time.
 


State of Assam.
 


 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Subs. by G.S.R. 1786, 
dated 30th September, 1970.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 316, dated 26th April, 1986.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 18, dated 24th December, 
1973.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>