<act><tid>1495031</tid>
<title>THE WORKING JOURNALISTS AND OTHER NEWSPAPER EMPLOYEES (CONDITIONS  
  OFSERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS ACT, <year>1955</year></title>

ACT NO. 45 OF <year>1955</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 20th December, <year>1955</year>.]

An Act to regulate certain conditions of service of working 
journalists and other persons employed in newspaper establishments.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>396948</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1077351</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Working Journalists and other Newspaper Employees] (Conditions of  
  Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1955</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1877657</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>62863</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1162956</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Board" means--

<subsection><tid>295568</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to working journalists, the 
Wage Board constituted under section 9; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>710343</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to non- journalist newspaper 
employees, the Wage Board constituted under 
section 13C;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>950786</tid>
<number>b</number>" newspaper" means any printed periodical work containing 
public news or comments on public news and includes 
such other class of printed periodical work as may, 
from time to time, be notified in this behalf by the 
Central Government in the Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1916936</tid>
<number>c</number>" newspaper employee" means any working journalist, and 
includes any other person employed to do any work in, 
or in relation to, any newspaper establishment;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>324</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 11 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. and Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. 
2. Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2 for" Working Journalists". 
3. The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
51 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1971</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3, for cl. (a).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>109077</tid>
<number>d</number>" newspaper establishment" means an establishment under 
the control of any person or body or persons, whether 
incorporated or not, for the production or publication 
of one or more newspapers or for conducting any news 
agency or syndicate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and includes newspaper 
establishments specified as one establishment under the 
Schedule.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause,--


</section>

<section><tid>1162956</tid>
<number>a</number>different departments, branches and 
centres of newspaper establishments shall be 
treated as parts thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>950786</tid>
<number>b</number>a printing press shall be deemed to be a 
newspaper establishment if the principal business 
thereof is to print newspaper;]

</section>

<section><tid>1580303</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" non- journalist newspaper employee" means a person 
employed to do any work in, or in relation to, any 
newspaper establishment, but does not include any such 
person who--

<subsection><tid>399908</tid>
<number>i</number>is a working journalist, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>680270</tid>
<number>ii</number>is employed mainly in a managerial or 
administrative capacity, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>474230</tid>
<number>iii</number>being employed in a supervisory capacity, 
performs, either by the nature of the duties attached 
to his office or by reason of the powers vested in him, 
functions mainly of a managerial nature;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>896374</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>24410</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Tribunal" means,--

<subsection><tid>439247</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to working journalists, the 
Tribunal constituted under section 13AA; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>863673</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to non- journalist newspaper 
employees, the Tribunal constituted under section 
13DD;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1081116</tid>
<number>eee</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" wages" means all remuneration capable of being 
expressed in terms of money, which would, if the terms 
of employment, expressed or implied, were fulfilled, 
be payable to a newspaper employee in respect of his 
employment or of work done in such employment, and 
includes--

<subsection><tid>1031564</tid>
<number>i</number>such allowances (including dearness allowance) as the 
newspaper employee is for the time being entitled to;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735146</tid>
<number>ii</number>the value of any house accommodation, or of supply of 
light, water, medical attendance or other amenity or of any 
service or of any concessional supply of food- grains or other 
articles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314582</tid>
<number>iii</number>any travelling concession,
but does not include--


<subsubsection><tid>1156534</tid>
<number>a</number>any bonus;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>179379</tid>
<number>b</number>any contribution paid or payable by the employer to 
any pension fund or provident fund or for the benefit of the 
newspaper employee under any law for the time being in 
force;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1325307</tid>
<number>c</number>any gratuity payable on the termination of his 
service.
Explanation.-- In this clause, the term" wages" shall also include 
new allowances, if any, of any description fixed from time to time.]


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>956123</tid>
<number>f</number>" working journalist" means a person whose principal 
avocation is that of a journalist and <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> who is 
employed as such, either whole- time or part- time, in, 
or in relation to, one or more newspaper 
establishments], and includes an editor, a leader- 
writer, news editor, sub- editor, feature- writer, copy- 
tester, reporter, correspondent, cartoonist, 
newsphotographer and proof- reader, but does not include 
any such person who--

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1031564</tid>
<number>i</number>is employed mainly in a managerial or 
administrative capacity, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735146</tid>
<number>ii</number>being employed in a supervisory capacity, 
performs, either by the nature of the duties attached 
to his office or by reason of the powers vested in him, 
functions mainly of a managerial nature;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>886354</tid>
<number>g</number>all words and expressions used but not defined in this 
Act and defined in the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> 
 (14 of <year>1947</year>) shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in that Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>325</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2, retrospectively. 
2. Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3. 
3. Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1979</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 31- 1- <year>1979</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 13- 8-  
  <year>1980</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

WORKING JOURNALISTS

CHAPTER II

WORKING JOURNALISTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>860975</tid>
<number> 3</number> Act 14 of <year>1947</year> to apply to working journalists.-
<section><tid>531129</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year>, as in force for the 
time being, shall, subject to the modification specified in sub- 
section (2), apply to, or in relation to, working journalists as they 
apply to, or in relation to, workmen within the meaning of that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>538987</tid>
<number>2</number>Section 25F of the aforesaid Act, in its application to 
working journalists, shall be construed as if in clause (a) thereof, 
for the period of notice referred to therein in relation to the 
retrenchment of a workman, the following periods of notice in relation 
to the retrenchment of a working journalist had been substituted, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1005767</tid>
<number>a</number>six months, in the case of an editor, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>814039</tid>
<number>b</number>three months, in the case of any other working 
journalist.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>110931</tid>
<number> 4</number> Special provisions in respect of certain cases of 
retrenchment.- Where at any time between the 14th day of July, <year>1954</year>, 
and the 12th day of March, <year>1955</year>, any working journalist had been 
retrenched, he shall be entitled to receive from the employer--
<section><tid>1482849</tid>
<number>a</number>wages for one month at the rate to which he was entitled 
immediately before his retrenchment, unless he had been 
given one month' s notice in writing before such 
retrenchment; and

</section>

<section><tid>1344438</tid>
<number>b</number>compensation which shall be equivalent to fifteen days' 
average pay for every completed year of service under 
that employer or any part thereof in excess of six 
months.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>74771</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Payment of gratuity.-
<section><tid>1361803</tid>
<number>1</number>Where-- 

<subsection><tid>1265778</tid>
<number>a</number>any working journalist has been in continuous service, 
whether before or after the commencement of this Act, 
for not less than three years in any newspaper 
establishment, and--

<subsubsection><tid>194639</tid>
<number>i</number>his services are terminated by the employer in 
relation to that newspaper establishment for any reason 
whatsoever, otherwise than as a punishment inflicted by 
way of disciplinary action; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1042287</tid>
<number>ii</number>he retires from service on reaching the age 
of superannuation; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>757558</tid>
<number>b</number>any working journalist has been in continuous service, 
whether before or after the commencement of this Act, 
for not less than ten years in any newspaper 
establishment, and he volun-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>326</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3, for s. 5 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


tarily resigns on or after the 1st day of July, <year>1961</year>, 
from service in that newspaper establishment on any 
ground whatsoever other than on the ground of 
conscience; or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001605</tid>
<number>c</number>any working journalist has been in continuous service, 
whether before or after the commencement of this Act 
for not less than three years in any newspaper 
establishment, and he voluntarily resigns on or after 
the 1st day of July, <year>1961</year>, from service in that 
establishment on the ground of conscience; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1417832</tid>
<number>d</number>any working journalist dies while he is in service in 
any newspaper establishment,
the working journalist or, in the case of his death, his nominee or 
nominees or if there is no nomination in force at the time of the 
death of the working journalist, his family, as the case may be, 
shall, without prejudice to any benefits or rights accruing under the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), be paid, on such 
termination, retirement, resignation or death, by the employer in 
relation to that establishment gratuity which shall be equivalent to 
fifteen days' average pay for every completed year of service or any 
part thereof in excess of six months:

Provided that in the case of a working journalist referred to in 
clause (b), the total amount of gratuity that shall be payable to him 
shall not exceed twelve and half months' average pay:

Provided further that where a working journalist is employed in any 
newspaper establishment wherein not more than six working journalists 
were employed on any day of the twelve months immediately preceding 
the commencement of this Act, the gratuity payable to a working 
journalist employed in any such newspaper establishment for any period 
of service before such commencement shall not be equivalent to fifteen 
days' average pay for every completed year of service or any part 
thereof in excess of six months but shall be equivalent to--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1265778</tid>
<number>a</number>three days' average pay for every completed year of 
service or any part thereof in excess of six months, if 
the period of such past service does not exceed five 
years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>757558</tid>
<number>b</number>five days' average pay for every completed year of 
service or any part thereof in excess of six months, if 
the period of such past service exceeds five years but 
does not exceed ten years; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001605</tid>
<number>c</number>seven days' average pay for every completed year of 
service or any part thereof in excess of six months, if 
the period of such past service exceeds ten years.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>327</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section and sub- 
section (1) of section 17," family" means--


<subsubsection><tid>816493</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a male working journalist, his widow, 
children, whether married or unmarried, and his 
dependent parents and the widow and children of his 
deceased son:
Provided that a widow shall not be deemed to be a member of 
the family of the working journalist if at the time of 
his death she was not legally entitled to be maintained 
by him;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>5061</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a female working journalist, her 
husband, children, whether married or unmarried, and 
the dependent parents of the working journalist or of 
her husband, and the widow and children of her deceased 
son:
Provided that if the working journalist has expressed her 
desire to exclude her husband from the family, the 
husband and his dependent parents shall not be deemed 
to be a part of the working journalist' s family,

and in either of the above two cases, if the child of a working 
journalist or of a deceased son of a working journalist has been 
adopted by another person and if under the personal law of the 
adopter, adoption is legally recognised, such a child shall not be 
considered as a member of the family of the working journalist.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>407754</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute whether a working journalist has voluntarily 
resigned from service in any newspaper establishment on the ground of 
conscience shall be deemed to be an industrial dispute within the 
meaning of the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or any 
corresponding law relating to investigation and settlement of 
industrial disputes in force in any State.

</section>

<section><tid>731545</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a nominee is a minor and the gratuity under sub- section 
 (1) has become payable during his minority, it shall be paid to a 
person appointed under sub- section (3) of section 5A:
Provided that where there is no such person, payment shall be 
made to any guardian of the property of the minor appointed by a 
competent court or where no such guardian has been appointed, to 
either parent of the minor, or where neither parent is alive, to any 
other guardian of the minor:

Provided further that where the gratuity is payable to two or 
more nominees, and either or any of them dies, the gratuity shall be 
paid to the surviving nominee or nominees.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>328</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1066312</tid>
<number> 5A</number> Nomination by working journalist.-
<section><tid>845126</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in any law for the time being in force, or in any 
disposition, testamentary or otherwise in respect of any gratuity 
payable to a working journalist, where a nomination made in the 
prescribed manner purports to confer on any person the right to 
receive payment of the gratuity for the time being due to the working 
journalist, the nominee shall, on the death of the working journalist, 
become entitled to the gratuity and to be paid the sum due in respect 
thereof to the exclusion of all other persons, unless the nomination 
is varied or cancelled in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1818065</tid>
<number>2</number>Any nomination referred to in sub- section (1) shall become 
void if the nominee predeceases, or where there are two or more 
nominees, all the nominees predecease, the working journalist making 
the nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>385658</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the nominee is a minor, it shall be lawful for the 
working journalist making the nomination to appoint any person in the 
prescribed manner to receive the gratuity in the event of his death 
during the minority of the nominee.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1389868</tid>
<number> 6</number> Hours of work.-
<section><tid>1614574</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules that may be made under  
this Act, no working journalist shall be required or allowed to work 
in any newspaper establishment for more than one hundred and forty- 
four hours during any period of four consecutive weeks, exclusive of 
the time for meals.

</section>

<section><tid>833804</tid>
<number>2</number>Every working journalist shall be allowed during any period 
of seven consecutive days rest for a period of not less than twenty- 
four consecutive hours, the period between 10 P. M. and 6 A. M. being 
included therein.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," week" means a 
period of seven days beginning at mid- night on Saturday.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1437135</tid>
<number> 7</number> Leave.- Without prejudice to such holidays, casual leave or 
other kinds of leave as may be prescribed, every working journalist 
shall be entitled to--
<section><tid>536837</tid>
<number>a</number>earned leave on full wages for not less than one- 
eleventh of the period spent on duty;

</section>

<section><tid>1490109</tid>
<number>b</number>leave on medical certificate on one- half of the wages 
for not less than one- eighteenth of the period of 
service.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975845</tid>
<number> 8</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Fixation or revision of rates of wages.-
<section><tid>997305</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, in the manner hereinafter provided,--

<subsection><tid>622943</tid>
<number>a</number>fix rates of wages in respect of working journalists;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>329</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, ss. 4, for s. 8 to 13 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8152</tid>
<number>b</number>revise, from time to time, at such intervals as it may 
think fit, the rates of wages fixed under this section 
or specified in the order made under section 6 of the 
Working Journalists (Fixation of Rates of Wages) Act, 
 <year>1958</year> (29 of <year>1958</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>89397</tid>
<number>2</number>The rates of wages may be fixed or revised by the Central 
Government in respect of working journalists for time work and for 
piece work.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>988022</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure for fixing and revising rates of wages.- For the 
purpose of fixing or revising rates of wages in respect of working 
journalists under this Act, the Central Government shall, as and when 
necessary, constitute a Wage Board which shall consist of--
<section><tid>815215</tid>
<number>a</number>two persons representing employers in relation to 
newspaper establishments;

</section>

<section><tid>548425</tid>
<number>b</number>two persons representing working journalists;

</section>

<section><tid>1482774</tid>
<number>c</number>three independent persons, one of whom shall be a person 
who is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court or the 
Supreme Court and who shall be appointed by that 
Government as the Chairman thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>637136</tid>
<number> 10</number> Recommendation by Board.-
<section><tid>1136137</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall, by notice  
published in such manner as it thinks fit, call upon newspaper 
establishments and working journalists and other persons interested in 
the fixation or revision of rates of wages of working journalists to 
make such representations as they may think fit as respects the rates 
of wages which may be fixed or revised under this Act in respect of 
working journalists.

</section>

<section><tid>300137</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such representation shall be in writing and shall be 
made within such period as the Board may specify in the notice and 
shall state the rates of wages which, in the opinion of the person 
making the representation, would be reasonable, having regard to the 
capacity of the employer to pay the same or to any other circumstance, 
whichever may seem relevant to the person making the representation in 
relation to his representation.

</section>

<section><tid>586812</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall take into account the representations 
aforesaid, if any, and after examining the materials placed before it 
make such recommendations as it thinks fit to the Central Government 
for the fixation or revision of rates of wages in respect of working 
journalists; and any such recommendation may specify, whether 
prospectively or retrospectively, the date from which the rates of 
wages should take effect.

</section>

<section><tid>1216126</tid>
<number>4</number>In making any recommendations to the Central Government, the 
Board shall have regard to the cost of living, the prevalent rates of 
wages

<pagefootnote><pagenum>330</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

for comparable employment, the circumstances relating to the newspaper 
industry in different regions of the country and to any other 
circumstances which to the Board may seem relevant.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent the Board from making 
recommendations for fixation or revision of rates of wages on all 
India basis.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>228407</tid>
<number> 11</number> Powers and procedure of the Board.-
<section><tid>1472563</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions contained in sub- section (2), the Board may exercise all or 
any of the powers which an Industrial Tribunal constituted under the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), exercises for the 
adjudication of an industrial dispute referred to it and shall, 
subject to the provisions contained in this Act, and the rules, if 
any, made thereunder, have power to regulate its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>378941</tid>
<number>2</number>Any representations made to the Board and any documents 
furnished to it by way of evidence shall be open to inspection on 
payment of such fee as may be prescribed, by any person interested in 
the matter.

</section>

<section><tid>757401</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for any reason, a vacancy occurs in the office of 
Chairman or any other member of the Board, the Central Government 
shall fill the vacancy by appointing another person thereto in 
accordance with the provisions of section 9 and any proceeding may be 
continued before the Board so reconstituted from the stage at which 
the vacancy occurred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>279838</tid>
<number> 12</number> Powers of Central Government to enforce recommendations of 
the Wage Board.-
<section><tid>1482521</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be, after the receipt of the  
recommendations of the Board, the Central Government shall make an 
order in terms of the recommendations or subject to such 
modifications, if any, as it thinks fit, being modifications which, in 
the opinion of the Central Government, do not effect important 
alterations in the character of the recommendations.

</section>

<section><tid>1008566</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
Central Government may, if it thinks fit,--

<subsection><tid>56647</tid>
<number>a</number>make such modifications in the recommendations, not 
being modifications of the nature referred to in sub- 
section (1), as it thinks fit:
Provided that before making any such modifications, the 
Central Government shall cause notice to be given to 
all persons likely to be affected thereby in such 
manner as may be prescribed, and shall take into 
account any representations which they may make in this 
behalf in writing; or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>896926</tid>
<number>b</number>refer the recommendations or any part thereof to the 
Board, in which case, the Central Government shall 
consider its further recommendations and make an order 
either in terms of the recommendations or with such 
modifications of the nature referred to in sub- section 
 (1) as it thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>330A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 31 of <year>1989</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1711272</tid>
<number>3</number>Every order made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be published in the Official Gazette together with the 
recommendations of the Board relating to the order and the order shall 
come into operation on the date of publication or on such date, 
whether prospectively or retrospectively, as may be specified in the 
order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>549397</tid>
<number>13</number>Working journalists entitled to wages at rates not less than 
those specified in the order.- On the coming into operation of an order 
of the Central Government under section 12, every working journalist 
shall be entitled to be paid by his employer wages at the rate which 
shall in no case be less than the rate of wages specified in the 
order.


</article>



<article><tid>884672</tid>
<number> 13A</number> Power of Government to fix interim rates of wages.-
<section><tid>1759159</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, where the Central 
Government is of opinion that it is necessary so to do, it may, after 
consultation with the Board, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
fix interim rates of wages in respect of working journalists.

</section>

<section><tid>1167264</tid>
<number>2</number>Any interim rates of wages so fixed shall be binding on all 
employers in relation to newspaper establishments and every working 
journalist shall be entitled to be paid wages at a rate which shall, 
in no case, be less than the interim rates of wages fixed under sub- 
section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1252396</tid>
<number>3</number>Any interim rates of wages fixed under sub- section (1) shall 
remain in force until the order of the Central Government under 
section 12 comes into operation.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13AA</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Constitution of Tribunal for fixing or revising rates of wages inrespect 
of working journalists.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>228453</tid>
<number> 13AA</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Constitution of Tribunal for fixing or revising rates of 
wages in respect of working journalists.-
<section><tid>651452</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in this Act, where the Central Government is of opinion that 
the Board constituted under section 9 for the purpose of fixing or 
revising rates of wages in respect of working journalists under this 
Act has not been able to function (for any reason whatsoever) 
effectively, and in the circumstances, it is necessary so to do, it 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Tribunal, 
which shall consist of a person who is, or has been, a Judge of a High 
Court or the Supreme Court, for the purpose of fixing or revising 
rates of wages in respect of working journalists under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1015864</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 10 to 13A shall apply to, and in 
relation to, the Tribunal constituted under sub- section (1) of this 
section, the Central Government and working journalists, subject to 
the modifications that--

<subsection><tid>846509</tid>
<number>a</number>the references to the Board therein, wherever they 
occur, shall be construed as references to the 
Tribunal;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1979</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 31- 1- <year>1979</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930584</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3) of section 11,--

<subsubsection><tid>105059</tid>
<number>i</number>the reference to the office of Chairman or any 
other member of the Board shall be construed as a reference 
to the office of the person constituting the Tribunal; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1304207</tid>
<number>ii</number>the reference to section 9 shall be construed as a 
reference to sub- section (1) of this section; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1050850</tid>
<number>c</number>the references in section 13 and section 13A to section 
 12 shall be construed as references to section 12 read 
with this section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>415122</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal, in discharging its functions under this Act, 
may act on, the evidence recorded by the Wage Board or partly recorded 
by the Wage Board and partly recorded by itself:
Provided that if the Tribunal is of opinion that further 
examination of any of the witnesses whose evidence has already been 
recorded is necessary in the interests of justice, it may re- summon 
any such witness, and after such further examination, cross- 
examination and re- examination, if any, as it may permit, the witness 
shall be discharged.


</section>

<section><tid>134255</tid>
<number>4</number>On the constitution of a Tribunal under sub- section (1), the 
Board constituted under section 9 and functioning immediately before 
such constitution shall cease to exist and the members constituting 
that Board shall be deemed to have vacated their offices:
Provided that any interim rates of wages fixed by the Central 
Government under section 13A in respect of working journalists and in 
force immediately before the constitution of the Tribunal shall remain 
in force until the order of the Central Government under section 12 
read with this section comes into operation.]

CHAP

NON- JOURNALIST NEWSPAPER EMPLOYEES

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> CHAPTER II- A

NON- JOURNALIST NEWSPAPER EMPLOYEES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1314848</tid>
<number> 13B</number> Fixation or revision of rates of wages of non- journalists 
newspaper employees.-
<section><tid>95322</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in the manner  
hereinafter provided,--

<subsection><tid>600414</tid>
<number>a</number>fix rates of wages in respect of non- journalist 
newspaper employees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>499437</tid>
<number>b</number>revise, from time to time, at such intervals as it may 
think fit, the rates of wages fixed under this section.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1846377</tid>
<number>2</number>The rates of wages may be fixed or revised by the Central 
Government in respect of non- journalist newspaper employees for time 
work and for piece work.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1786059</tid>
<number> 13C</number> Wage Board for fixing or revising rates of wages in respect 
of non- journalist newspaper employees.- For the purpose of fixing or 
revising rates of wages in respect of non- journalist newspaper 
employees under this Act, the Central Government shall, as and when 
necessary, constitute a Wage Board which shall consist of--
<section><tid>1371935</tid>
<number>a</number>two persons representing employers in relation to 
newspaper establishments;

</section>

<section><tid>248231</tid>
<number>b</number>two persons representing non- journalist newspaper 
employees, and

</section>

<section><tid>1412288</tid>
<number>c</number>three independent persons, one of whom shall be a person 
who is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court or the 
Supreme Court and who shall be appointed by that 
Government as the Chairman thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1043909</tid>
<number> 13D</number> Application of certain provisions.- The provisions of 
sections 10 to 13A shall apply to, and in relation to, the Board 
constituted under section 13C, the Central Government and non- 
journalist newspaper employees, subject to the modifications that--
<section><tid>1288935</tid>
<number>a</number>the references to the Board and working journalists 
therein, wherever they occur, shall be construed 
respectively as references to the Board constituted 
under section 13C and to non- journalist newspaper 
employees;

</section>

<section><tid>1951837</tid>
<number>b</number>the references in sub- section (3) of section 11 to 
section 9 shall be construed as a reference to section 
13C; and

</section>

<section><tid>1815291</tid>
<number>c</number>the references in section 13 and section 13A to section 
 12 shall be construed as references to section 12 read 
with this section.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13DD</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Constitution of Tribunal for fixing or revising rates of wages inrespect 
of non- journalist newspaper employees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>626951</tid>
<number> 13DD</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Constitution of Tribunal for fixing or revising rates of 
wages in respect of non- journalist newspaper employees.-
<section><tid>773115</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, where the Central 
Government is of opinion that the Board constituted under section 13C 
for the purpose of fixing or revising rates of wages in respect of 
non- journalist newspaper employees under this Act has not been able to 
function (for any reason whatsoever) effectively, and in the 
circumstances, it is necessary so to do, it may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, constitute a Tribunal, which shall consist of a 
person who is, or has been,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1979</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 31- 1- <year>1979</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


a Judge of a High Court or the Supreme Court, for the purpose of 
fixing or revising rates of wages in respect of non- journalist 
newspaper employees under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1659871</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 10 to 13A shall apply to, and in 
relation to, the Tribunal constituted under sub- section (1) of this 
section, the Central Government and non- journalist newspaper 
employees, subject to the modifications that--

<subsection><tid>1350863</tid>
<number>a</number>the references to the Board and working journalists 
therein, wherever they occur, shall be construed 
respectively as references to the Tribunal and to non- 
journalist newspaper employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>774674</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3) of section 11,--

<subsubsection><tid>987830</tid>
<number>i</number>the reference to the office of Chairman or any 
other member of the Board shall be construed as a reference 
to the office of the person constituting the Tribunal; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1892913</tid>
<number>ii</number>the reference to section 9 shall be construed as a 
reference to sub- section (1) of this section; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30988</tid>
<number>c</number>the references in section 13 and section 13A to section 
 12 shall be construed as references to section 12 read 
with this section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1764238</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal, in discharging its functions under this Act, 
may act on the evidence recorded by the Wage Board or partly recorded 
by the Wage Board and partly recorded by itself:
Provided that if the Tribunal is of opinion that further 
examination of any of the witnesses whose evidence has already been 
recorded is necessary in the interests of justice, it may re- summon 
any such witness, and after such further examination, cross- 
examination and re- examination, if any, as it may permit, the witness 
shall be discharged.


</section>

<section><tid>1203253</tid>
<number>4</number>On the constitution of a Tribunal under sub- section (1), the 
Board constituted under section 13C and functioning immediately before 
such constitution shall cease to exist and the members constituting 
that Board shall be deemed to have vacated their offices:
Provided that any interim rates of wages fixed by the Central 
Government under section 13A read with section 13D in respect of 
nonjournalist newspaper employees and in force immediately before the 
constitution of the Tribunal shall remain in force until the order of 
the Central Government under section 12 read with this section comes 
into operation.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>330E</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO NEWSPAPER EMPLOYEES

CHAPTER III

APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO NEWSPAPER EMPLOYEES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1304249</tid>
<number>14</number>Act 20 of <year>1946</year> to apply to newspaper establishments.- The 
provisions of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, <year>1946</year>, 
as in force for the time being, shall apply to every newspaper 
establishment wherein twenty or more newspaper employees are employed 
or were employed on any day of the preceding twelve months as if such 
newspaper establishment were an industrial establishment to which the 
aforesaid Act has been applied by a notification under sub- section (3) 
of section 1 thereof, and as if a newspaper employee were a workman 
within the meaning of that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>975238</tid>
<number>15</number>Act 19 of <year>1952</year> to apply to newspaper establishments.- The 
Employees' Provident Funds Act, <year>1952</year>, as in force for the time being, 
shall apply to every newspaper establishment in which twenty or more 
persons are employed on any day, as if such newspaper establishment 
were a factory to which the aforesaid Act had been applied by a 
notification of the Central Government under sub- section (3) of 
section 1 thereof, and as if a newspaper employee were an employee 
within the meaning of that Act.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1201874</tid>
<number> 16</number> Effect of laws and agreements inconsistent with this Act.-
<section><tid>1791552</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law or in the terms of 
any award, agreement or contract of service, whether made before or 
after the commencement of this Act:
Provided that where under any such award, agreement, contract of 
service or otherwise, a newspaper employee is entitled to benefits in 
respect of any matter which are more favourable to him than those to 
which he would be entitled under this Act, the newspaper employee 
shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable benefits in 
respect of that matter, notwithstanding that he receives benefits in 
respect of other matters under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1011905</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in this Act shall be construed to preclude 
any newspaper employee from entering into an agreement with an 
employer for granting him rights or privileges in respect of any 
matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would 
be entitled under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>330F</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1742717</tid>
<number>16A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Employer not to dismiss, discharge, etc., newspaper 
employees.- No employer in relation to a newspaper establishment shall, 
by reason of his liability for payment of wages to newspaper employees 
at the rates specified in an order of the Central Government under 
section 12, or under section 12 read with section 13AA or section 
13DD, dismiss, discharge or retrench any newspaper employee.]


</article>



<article><tid>1005162</tid>
<number> 17</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Recovery of money due from an employer.-
<section><tid>183887</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
amount is due under this Act to a newspaper employee from an employer, 
the newspaper employee himself, or any person authorised by him in 
writing in this behalf, or in the case of the death of the employee, 
any member of his family may, without prejudice to any other mode of 
recovery, make an application to the State Government for the recovery 
of the amount due to him, and if the State Government, or such 
authority, as the State Government may specify in this behalf, is 
satisfied that any amount is so due, it shall issue a certificate for 
that amount to the Collector, and the Collector shall proceed to 
recover that amount in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>569251</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to the amount due under this Act to 
a newspaper employee from his employer, the State Government may, on 
its own motion or upon application made to it, refer the question to 
any Labour Court constituted by it under the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or under any corresponding law relating to 
investigation and settlement of industrial disputes in force in the 
State and the said Act or law shall have effect in relation to the 
Labour Court as if the question so referred were a matter referred to 
the Labour Court for adjudication under that Act or law.

</section>

<section><tid>205999</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Labour Court shall be forwarded by it to 
the State Government which made the reference and any amount found due 
by the Labour Court may be recovered in the manner provided in sub- 
section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>484426</tid>
<number>17A</number>Maintenance of registers, records, and muster- rolls.- Every 
employer in relation to a newspaper establishment shall prepare and 
maintain such registers, records and muster- rolls and in such manner 
as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>78830</tid>
<number> 17B</number> Inspectors.-
<section><tid>891203</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by notification in  
the Official Gazette, appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be 
Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and may define the local 
limits within which they shall exercise their functions.

</section>

<section><tid>639459</tid>
<number>2</number>Any Inspector appointed under sub- section (1) may for the 
purpose of ascertaining whether any of the provisions of this Act or 
of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330G</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 13- 8- <year>1980</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 5, for s. 17 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Working Journalists (Fixation of Rates of Wages) Act, <year>1958</year> (29 of  
  <year>1958</year>) have been complied with in respect of a newspaper 
establishment--


<subsection><tid>1942386</tid>
<number>a</number>require an employer to furnish such information as he 
may consider necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461150</tid>
<number>b</number>at any reasonable time enter any newspaper establishment 
or any premises connected therewith and require any one 
found in charge thereof to produce before him for 
examination any accounts, books, registers and other 
documents relating to the employment of persons or the 
payment of wages in the establishment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>192928</tid>
<number>c</number>examine with respect to any matter relevant to any of 
the purposes aforesaid, the employer, his agent or 
servant or any other person found in charge of the 
newspaper establishment or any premises connected 
therewith or any person whom the Inspector has 
reasonable cause to believe to be or to have been an 
employee in the establishment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479816</tid>
<number>d</number>make copies of or take extracts from any book, register 
or other documents maintained in relation to the 
newspaper establishment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656264</tid>
<number>e</number>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>382127</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within 
the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>77616</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person required to produce any document or thing or to 
give information by an Inspector under sub- section (2) shall be 
legally bound to do so.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294207</tid>
<number> 18</number> Penalty.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1892881</tid>
<number>1</number>If any employer contravenes any of the  
provisions of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder, he shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1756011</tid>
<number>1A</number>Whoever, having been convicted of any offence under this 
Act, is again convicted of an offence involving the contravention of 
the same provision, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>571321</tid>
<number>1B</number>Where an offence has been committed by a company, every 
person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, 
and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of 
the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of 
the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330H</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 6, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 15- 1-  
  <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this section if 
he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that 
he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.


</section>

<section><tid>550118</tid>
<number>1C</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1B), 
where an offence under this section has been committed by a company 
and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent 
or connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is 
attributable to, any gross negligence on the part of any director, 
manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty 
of such offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>205898</tid>
<number>1D</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>1019610</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979743</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>861928</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a 
Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under 
this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1032216</tid>
<number>3</number>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence under this 
section, unless the complaint thereof is made within six months of the 
date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>136782</tid>
<number>19</number>Indemnity.- No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding 
shall lie against the Chairman or any other member of the Board <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or 
the person constituting the Tribunal] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or an Inspector appointed 
under this Act] for anything which is in good faith done or intended 
to be done.


</article>



<article><tid>1768334</tid>
<number>19A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts.- No act or 
proceeding of the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of 
the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of the 
Board.


</article>



<article><tid>1752427</tid>
<number>19B</number>Saving.- Nothing in this Act or the Working Journalists 
 (Fixation of Rates of Wages) Act, <year>1958</year> (29 of <year>1958</year>) shall apply to 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any newspaper employee] who is an employee of the Government to 
whom the Fundamental and Supplementary Rules, Civil Services 
 (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, Civil Services (Temporary  
  Service) Rules, Revised Leave Rules, Civil Service Regulations, 
Civilians in Defence Services (Classification, Control and 
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330I</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1979</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 31- 1- <year>1979</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1963</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1963</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 5, for" any working journalist".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  Appeal) Rules or the Indian Railway Establishment Code or any other 
rules or regulations that may be notified in this behalf by the 
Central Government in the Official Gazette, apply.]



</article>



<article><tid>780154</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>704271</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1128634</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1453740</tid>
<number>a</number>payment of gratuity to working journalists;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630358</tid>
<number>b</number>hours of work of working journalists;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>508279</tid>
<number>c</number>holidays, earned leave, leave on medical certificate, 
casual leave or any other kind of leave admissible to 
working journalists;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>354194</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the procedure to be followed by the Board <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or, as 
the case may be, the Tribunal,] in the discharge of its 
functions under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1673831</tid>
<number>e</number>the form of nominations, and the manner in which 
nominations may be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1511849</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the 
purposes of sub- section (3) of section 5A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1715269</tid>
<number>g</number>the variation or cancellation of nominations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>793962</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner of giving notice under clause (a) of sub- 
section (2) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1782628</tid>
<number>i</number>the registers, records and muster- rolls to be prepared 
and maintained by newspaper establishments, the forms 
in which they should be prepared and maintained and the 
particulars to be entered therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>154864</tid>
<number>j</number>the powers that may be exercised by an Inspector;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1504514</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1428353</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon 
as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>330J</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 9, for cls. (d), (e) and (f)  (w. e. f.  
  15- 1- <year>1963</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1979</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 31- 1- <year>1979</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1962</year>, s. 9, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 15- 1-  
  <year>1963</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1974</year>, s. 6, for" or in two successive 
sessions".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in two or more successive sessions], and if before the expiry of the 
session <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> immediately following the session or the successive 
sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the 
rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification 
or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1960652</tid>
<number>21</number>[ Repeal of Act 1 of <year>1955</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

</article>



 </act>