<act><tid>734720</tid>
<title>THE CANTONMENTS (HOUSE- ACCOMMODATION) ACT, <year>1923</year></title>

ACT NO. 6 OF <year>1923</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 5th March, <year>1923</year>.] WH

An Act further to amend and to consolidate the law relating to the 
provision of house- accommodation for military officers in cantonments.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>714099</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>1937664</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, <year>1923</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1803835</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>9491</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the first day of April, <year>1923</year>, but 
it shall not become operative in any cantonment or part of a 
cantonment until the issue, or otherwise than in pursuance, of a 
notification as hereinafter provided by section 3:
Provided that any notification made under section 3 of the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 
Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, <year>1902</year> (2 of <year>1902</year>), which is in 
force at the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to be a 
notification made under section 3 of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>985716</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.-
<section><tid>1732279</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless there is anything  
repugnant in the subject or context,--

<subsection><tid>546579</tid>
<number>a</number>" Brigade area" means one of the Brigade areas, whether 
occupied by a brigade or not, into which India is for 
military purposes for the time being divided, and 
includes any area which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
Brigade area for all or any or the purposes of this 
Act;
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>). 
2. The words" except Part B States" were omitted by Act 53 of <year>1950</year>, 
s. 2. 
3. The brackets and words" (inclusive of British Baluchistan)" were 
rep. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>. 
4. The words" except Aden" were rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. Rep. by s. 39 and Sch. of this Act. 
6. The original cl. (b) was rep. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>239686</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Cantonment Board" means a Cantonment Board 
constituted under the Cantonments Act, <year>1924</year> (2 of  
  <year>1924</year>);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>251183</tid>
<number>c</number>" Command" means one of the Commands into which India is 
for military purposes for the time being divided, and 
includes any area which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
Command for all or any of the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>770155</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] means the officer 
for the time being in command of the forces in a 
cantonment <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or, if that Officer is the Officer 
Commanding the District, the military officer who would 
be in command of those forces in the absence of the 
Officer Commanding the District];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1880692</tid>
<number>e</number>" District" means one of the Districts into which India 
is for military purposes for the time being divided; it 
includes a Brigade area which does not form part of any 
such District and any area which the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare 
to be a District for all or any of the purposes of this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1508020</tid>
<number>f</number>" house" means a house suitable for occupation by a 
military officer or a military mess, and includes the 
land and buildings appurtenant to a house;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>217347</tid>
<number>g</number>" military officer" means a commissioned or warrant 
officer of the Indian military or air forces on 
military or air force duty in a cantonment, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> an 
officer of the Cantonments Department] and any person 
in Army departmental employment whom the Officer 
Commanding the District may at any time, by an order in 
writing, place on the same footing as a military 
officer for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>374769</tid>
<number>h</number>" owner" includes the person who is receiving, or is 
entitled to receive, the rent of a house, whether on 
his own account or on behalf of himself and others or 
as an agent or trustee, or who would so receive the 
rent, or be entitled to receive it, if the house were 
let to a tenant; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (bb), ins. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2, was relettered (b) by Act 
9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
3. Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2. 
4. The words" and includes a Chaplain on duty with troops in a 
cantonment" were omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
5. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2, for" a Cantonment Magistrate".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>22703</tid>
<number>i</number>a house is said to be in a state of reasonable repair 
when--

<subsubsection><tid>1798116</tid>
<number>i</number>all floors, walls, pillars and arches are 
sound and all roofs sound and watertight,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1052006</tid>
<number>ii</number>all doors and windows are intact, properly 
painted or oiled, and provided with proper locks or 
bolts or other secure fastenings, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>253987</tid>
<number>iii</number>all rooms, out- houses and other appurtenant 
buildings are properly colour- washed or white- washed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1696650</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether any land or building is 
appurtenant to a house, it shall be decided by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer 
Commanding the station], whose decision thereon shall, subject to 
revision by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Collector], be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1344755</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> In the application of this Act to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
any Part B State], any reference to an enactment not in force in 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> those territories] shall be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law in force in <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> those territories].]
CHAP

APPLICATION OF ACT

CHAPTER II

APPLICATION OF ACT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>538127</tid>
<number> 3</number> Cantonments or parts of cantonments in which Act to be 
operative.-
<section><tid>1181758</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> may, by notification in  
the Official Gazette, declare this Act to be operative in any 
cantonment or part of a cantonment <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>, other than a cantonment 
situate within the limits of a presidency- town.

</section>

<section><tid>813757</tid>
<number>2</number>Before issuing a notification under sub- section (1) in 
respect of any cantonment or part of a cantonment, the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Central 
Government] shall cause local inquiry to be made with a view to 
determining whether it is expedient to issue such notification, and 
what portion (if any) of the area proposed to be included therein 
should be excluded therefrom.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
2. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2, for" District Magistrate". 
3. Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1950</year>, s. 3. 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" any 
Part B State". 
5. Subs., ibid., for" that State". 
6. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
7. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." rep. by 
the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
8. The words" situate in the Province" rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1936062</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Saving of written instruments.- Nothing in this Act shall 
affect the provisions of any written <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> contract with the Government] 
unless all the parties to that contract consent in writing to be bound 
by the terms of this Act.]
CHAP

APPROPRIATION OF HOUSES

CHAPTER III

APPROPRIATION OF HOUSES



</article>



<article><tid>1813814</tid>
<number> 5</number> Liability of houses to appropriation.- Every house situate in a 
cantonment or part of a cantonment in respect of which a notification 
under sub- section
<section><tid>1370682</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 is for the time being in force  
shall be liable to appropriation by <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government] on a 
lease in the manner and subject to the conditions hereinafter 
provided.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1428106</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Conditions on which houses may be appropriated.-
<section><tid>1268469</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where--

<subsection><tid>1065090</tid>
<number>a</number>a military officer who is stationed in or has 
been posted to the cantonment, or a President of a 
military mess in the cantonment, applies in writing to 
the Officer Commanding the station stating that he is 
unable to secure suitable accommodation in the 
cantonment for himself or the mess on reasonable terms 
by the private agreement, and that no suitable house or 
quarter <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> belonging to the Government] is available 
for his occupation or for the occupation of the mess, 
and the Officer Commanding the station is satisfied on 
inquiry of the truth of the facts so stated; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>742771</tid>
<number>b</number>the Officer Commanding the station is 
satisfied on inquiry that there is not in the 
cantonment a sufficient and assured supply of houses 
available at reasonable rates of rent by private 
agreement to meet the requirements of the military 
officers and military messes whose accommodation in the 
cantonment is in his opinion necessary or expedient,
the Officer Commanding the station may, with a view to enforcing the 
liability under section 5, serve a notice on the owner of any house 
which appears to him to be suitable for occupation by a military 
officer or a military mess, as the case may be, within the cantonment,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original section. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Crown Contract". 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt,". 
4. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s, 3, for the original section. 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" belonging to Govt.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or, of this Act is in force in part only of the cantonment, within 
that part, requiring the owner to permit the house to be inspected, 
measured and surveyed by such person and on such date, not being less 
than three clear days from the service of the notice, and at such time 
between sunrise and sunset, as may be specified in the notice.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>973180</tid>
<number>2</number>On the date and at the time so specified the owner shall be 
bound to afford all reasonable facilities to the person specified in 
the notice for the purpose of the inspection, measurement and survey 
of the house and, if he refuses or neglects to do so, such person may,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

subject to any rules made under this Act, enter on the premises and do 
all such things as may be reasonably necessary for the said purpose.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1408055</tid>
<number> 7</number> Procedure for taking house on lease.-
<section><tid>882798</tid>
<number>1</number>If, on the report of  
such person as aforesaid, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] is 
satisfied that the house is suitable for occupation by a military 
officer or a military mess, he may <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by notice--

<subsection><tid>118861</tid>
<number>a</number>require the owner to execute a lease of the house to 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government] for a specified period which 
shall not be less than five years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>954696</tid>
<number>b</number>require the existing occupier, if any, to vacate the 
house; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>574387</tid>
<number>c</number>require the owner to execute within such time as may be 
specified in the notice such repairs as may, in the 
opinion of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> officer Commanding the station], be 
necessary for the purpose of putting the house into a 
state of reasonable repair.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>573405</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notice issued under sub- section (1) shall state the 
amount of the annual rent proposed as reasonable for the house, 
calculated on the assumption that the owner will carry out the 
required repairs, if any. It shall also contain an estimate of the 
cost of such repairs.

</section>

<section><tid>507080</tid>
<number>3</number>The following shall be deemed to be conditions of every lease 
executed under sub- section (1), namely:--

<subsection><tid>800381</tid>
<number>a</number>that the house shall, on the expiration of the lease, be 
redelivered to the owner in a state of reasonable 
repair, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1629107</tid>
<number>b</number>that the ground and the garden, if any, appertaining to 
the house shall be maintained in the condition in which 
they are at the time at which the lease is executed:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to 
affect the right of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government] to avoid the lease in 
any such event as is specified in clause (e) of section 108 of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>).]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>619509</tid>
<number>8</number>[ Procedure to be observed before taking a house on lease.]- 
Rep. by the Cantonments (House- Accommodation Amendment) Act, <year>1930</year> (9  
  of <year>1930</year>), s. 5.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
2. The words" with the previous sanction of the Officer Commanding 
the District" were rep. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 4. 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt.". 
4. Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>42796</tid>
<number>9</number>Sanction to be obtained before a house is occupied as a 
hospital, etc. No house in any cantonment or part of a cantonment in 
which this Act is operative shall, unless it was so occupied at the 
date of the issue of the notification declaring this Act or the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, <year>1902</year> (2 of <year>1902</year>), as the 
case may be, to be operative, be occupied for the purposes of a 
hospital, school, school hostel, bank, hotel, or shop, or by a 
railway administration, a company or firm engaged in trade or business 
or a club, without the previous sanction of the Officer Commanding the 
District given with the concurrence of the Commissioner or, in a State 
where there are no Commissioners, of the Collector.


</article>



<article><tid>1195114</tid>
<number> 10</number> Houses not to be appropriated in certain cases.- No notice 
shall be issued under section 7 if the house--
<section><tid>736721</tid>
<number>a</number>was, at the date of the issue of the notification 
declaring this Act or the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Cantonments (House-  
  Accommodation) Act, <year>1902</year> (2 of <year>1902</year>), as the case may 
be, to be operative in the cantonment or part of the 
cantonment, or is, with such sanction as is required by 
section 9, occupied as a hospital, school, school 
hostel, bank, hotel or shop, and has been so occupied 
continuously during the three years immediately 
preceding the time when the occasion for issuing the 
notice arises, or

</section>

<section><tid>1432841</tid>
<number>b</number>was, at the date of such a notification as is referred 
to in clause (a), or is, with such sanction as 
aforesaid, occupied by a railway administration or by a 
company or firm engaged in trade or business or by a 
club, or

</section>

<section><tid>1465599</tid>
<number>c</number>is occupied by the owner, or

</section>

<section><tid>1250388</tid>
<number>d</number>has been appropriated by the State Government with the 
concurrence of the Officer Commanding the District, or 
by the Central Government, for use a public office or 
for any other purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1600166</tid>
<number> 11</number> Time to be allowed for giving possession of house.-
<section><tid>1978827</tid>
<number>1</number>If a  
house is unoccupied, a notice issued under section 7 may require the 
owner to give possession of the same to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> officer Commanding the 
station] within twenty- one days from the service of the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>674697</tid>
<number>2</number>If a house is occupied, a notice issued under section 7 shall 
not require its vacation in less than thirty days from the service of 
the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>727554</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a notice has been issued under section 7 and the house 
has been vacated in pursuance thereof, the lease shall be deemed to 
have commenced on the date on which the house was so vacated.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep. by s. 39 and Sch. of this Act. 
2. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment".




</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>12</number>Surrender of house when to be enforced.- If the owner fails to 
give possession of a house to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] 
in pursuance of a notice issued under section 7, or if the existing 
occupier fails to vacate a house in pursuance of such a notice, the 
District Magistrate, by himself or by another person generally or 
specially authorised by him in this behalf, shall enter on the 
premises and enforce the surrender of the house.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>13</number>Option in certain cases for owner on whom notice is issued 
under section 7 to call upon the Government to purchase.- (1) If a 
house, in respect of which a notice is issued under section 7, is 
shown to the satisfaction of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government], or is proved 
by a decree or order of a Court of competent jurisdiction, to have 
been erected--

(a) under any conditions, rules, regulations or orders which 
were in force in Bengal prior to the eighth day of 
December, <year>1864</year>, and conferred on the owner the option 
of offering the house for sale to the military officer 
applying for its appropriation for his occupation or to 
the East India Company or the Government, or

(b) under any conditions, rules, regulations or orders which 
were in force in Bombay prior to the first day of June, 
<year>1875</year>, and conferred such an option as is described in 
clause (a),

then the owner shall have the option of either complying with the 
notice or offering the house <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> for sale to the Central Government].

(2) If the owner elects to sell the house, and <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Central 
Government] is willing to purchase it, the question of the amount of 
the purchase- money to be paid shall, in the event of disagreement, be 
referred to <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> a civil court, in accordance with the previsions of 
Chapter IV].


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>14</number>Provision where house is held on long lease by a tenant.- (1) 
If a house, in respect of which a notice is issued under section 7, is 
occupied by a tenant holding in good faith and for valuable 
consideration under a registered lease for any term exceeding one 
year, the Central Government shall, for the term of one year from the 
date on which the house is vacated in pursuance of the notice, or for 
the unexpired term of the lease whichever is the shorter, be liable to 
the owner for the rent fixed by the registered lease instead of for 
the rent payable under this Act if the rent so fixed exceeds the rent 
so payable.

(2) If a house, in respect of which a notice is issued under 
section 7, is occupied by a tenant holding in good faith and for 
valuable 
1. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" for sale to the Govt." 
4. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt". 
5. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 6, for" a Committee of Arbitration".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


consideration under a registered lease from year to year, the Central 
Government shall be liable as aforesaid for the term of six months 
from the date on which the house is vacated in pursuance of the 
notice.


</section>

<section><tid>727554</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed--

<subsection><tid>1054549</tid>
<number>a</number>to render the Central Government so liable unless an 
application in writing in this behalf is made by the 
owner to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] within 
fifteen days from the service of the notice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>906356</tid>
<number>b</number>to limit or otherwise affect any agreement between the 
Government and the owner.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>756863</tid>
<number> 15</number> Power for owner to refer to civil court on question of rent.-

<section><tid>156299</tid>
<number>1</number>If the owner considers that the rent stated in a notice issued  
under section 7 is not reasonable, he may, within a period of 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> thirty] days from the service of such notice, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> refer the matter 
to a civil court, in accordance with the provisions of Chapter IV]:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that where an appeal has been made to the Officer 
Commanding the District under section 30, the period of thirty days 
shall be reckoned from the date on which the owner received notice of 
the result of the appeal under sub- section (2) of section 32.]


</section>

<section><tid>15903</tid>
<number>2</number>If the owner does not make such a <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> reference] within the 
said period, he shall be deemed to have accepted the rent so offered.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>177393</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power for owner to refer to civil court on question of 
repairs.-
<section><tid>1075039</tid>
<number>1</number>If the owner fails to execute any repairs to a house as  
required by a notice issued to him under section 7, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer 
commanding the station] may by notice require the owner to execute the 
repairs within such period, not being less than <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> thirty] days, as 
may be specified in the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>969554</tid>
<number>2</number>If the owner objects to any requisition contained in a notice 
issued under sub- section (1), he may within <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> thirty] days from the 
service of the notice <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> refer the matter to a civil court in 
accordance with the provisions of Chapter IV]:
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Provided that where an appeal has been made to the Officer 
Commanding the District under section 30, the period of thirty days 
shall be reckoned from the date on which the owner received notice of 
the result of the appeal under sub- section (2) of section 32.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
2. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 7, for" fifteen". 
3. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" require that the matter be referred by 
the Officer Commanding the station to a Committee of Arbitration". 
4. Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1933</year>, s. 2. 
5. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 7, for" requisition". 
6. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for" fifteen". 
7. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for" require that the matter be referred by 
the Officer Commanding the station to a Committee of Arbitration". 
8. Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1933</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 3 Every reference under sub- section (2) shall be accompanied 
by an estimate of the repairs, if any, which the owner considers 
necessary in order to put the house into a state of reasonable 
repair.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1653426</tid>
<number> 17</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to have repairs executed and recover cost.- If the 
owner fails to comply with a notice issued under sub- section
<section><tid>1951607</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 16, the Military Engineer Services or the Public Works 
Department may, with the previous sanction of the Officer Commanding 
the station and notwithstanding any right of reference conferred by 
that section, cause the repairs specified in the notice to be executed 
at the expense of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government], and the cost thereof, 
or, where a reference has been made, the amount finally determined by 
the civil court, may be deducted from the rent payable to the owner.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1326884</tid>
<number> 18</number> Notice to be given of devolution of interest in house in 
cantonment.- Every person on whom devolves, by transfer, by succession 
or by operation of law, the interest of an owner in any house, or in 
any part of any house, situate in a coantonment or part of a 
cantonment in respect of which a notification under sub- section
<section><tid>1784739</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 3 is for the time being in force, shall be bound to give 
notice of the fact to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] within 
one month from the date of such devolution, and, if he, without 
reasonable cause, fails to do so, he shall be punishable with fine 
which may extend to fifty rupees.
CHAP

PROCEDURE IN REFERENCES

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> CHAPTER IV

PROCEDURE IN REFERENCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13809</tid>
<number>19</number>Jurisdiction in references.- All references under this Act 
shall be made by application to, and tried by, the Court of the 
District Judge.


</article>



<article><tid>1891841</tid>
<number>20</number>Procedure and powers of the Court.- References under this Act 
shall be deemed to be proceedings within the meaning of section 141 of 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), and in the trial 
thereof the Court may exercise any of its powers under that Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1031680</tid>
<number>21</number>Restriction of scope of inquiry.- The scope of the inquiry in 
a reference under this Act shall be restricted to a consideration of 
the matters referred to the Court in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 8. 
2. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for the original section. 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt.". 
4. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
5. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 10, for the original Chapter IV 
entitled" Committees of Arbitration" and consisting of ss. 19 to 
28.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

APPEALS

CHAPTER V

APPEALS



</article>



<article><tid>1597002</tid>
<number> 29</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Appeal to High Court.-
<section><tid>1545600</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the High  
Court against the decision of the Court of the District Judge upon a 
reference tried by it.

</section>

<section><tid>295729</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal under this section shall be admitted unless it is 
made within thirty days from the date of the decision against which it 
is preferred.

</section>

<section><tid>329777</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal preferred under this section shall be deemed to be 
an appeal from an order within the meaning of section 108 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1920542</tid>
<number>30</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appeal to Officer Commanding the District.- The owner or 
any tenant of a house in respect of which a notice has been issued 
under section 7 may, within a period of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> ten days] from the date of 
the service thereof, appeal to the Officer Commanding the District 
against the decision of the Officer Commanding the station to 
appropriate the house.]


</article>



<article><tid>1616308</tid>
<number> 31</number> Petition of appeal.-
<section><tid>68796</tid>
<number>1</number>Every petition of appeal under  
section 30 shall be in writing and accompanied by a copy of the notice 
appealed against.

</section>

<section><tid>1549515</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such petition may be presented to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Officer 
Commanding the station], and that officer shall be bound to forward it 
to the authority empowered by section 30 to hear the appeal, and may 
attach thereto any report which he may desire to make in explanation 
of the notice appealed against.

</section>

<section><tid>510762</tid>
<number>3</number>If any such petition is presented direct to the Officer 
Commanding the District and an immediate order on the petition is not 
necessary, the Officer Commanding the District may refer the petition 
to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Officer Commanding the station] for report.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>999768</tid>
<number> 32</number> Order in appeal final.- <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1571728</tid>
<number>1</number>] The decision on any such  
appeal of the Officer Commanding the District <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> shall be final, and 
shall not be questioned in any court otherwise than on the ground that 
the house is situate in a cantonment, or part of a cantonment, in 
which this Act is not operative:
Provided that no appeal shall be decided until the appellant has 
been heard or has had a reasonable opportunity of being heard in 
person or through a legal practitioner <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> and in giving a decision the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 11, for the original section. 
2. Subs. by s. 12, ibid., for the original section. 
3. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1933</year>, s. 4, for" twenty- one days". 
4. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
5. The original s. 32 was re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that 
section by Act 22 of <year>1933</year>, s. 5. 
6. The words" or of the General Officer Commanding- in- chief, the 
Command, as the case may be" were rep. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 13. 
7. Ins. by s. 13, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Officer Commanding the District shall record briefly the grounds 
therefor].


</section>

<section><tid>802339</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notice of the result of the appeal shall be given to the 
appellant as soon as may be, and, where the appellant is a tenant of 
the house, to the owner of the house also.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414214</tid>
<number>33</number>Suspension of action pending appeal.- Where an appeal has been 
presented under section 30 within the period prescribed <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> therein], 
all action on the notice shall, on the application of the appellant, 
be held in abeyance pending the decision of the appeal.
CHAP

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS

CHAPTER VI

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1675382</tid>
<number>34</number>Service of notice and requisitions.- Every notice or 
requisition prescribed by this Act shall be in writing, signed by the 
person by whom it is given or made or by his duly appointed agent, and 
may be served by post on the person to whom it is addressed, or, in 
the case of an owner who does not reside in or near the cantonment, on 
his agent appointed <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in accordance with a bye- law made under clause 
 (29) of section 282 of the Cantonments Act, <year>1924</year> (2 of <year>1924</year>)].


</article>



<article><tid>590470</tid>
<number>34A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Computation of periods of limitation.- The period 
prescribed for making any reference or preferring any appeal under 
this Act shall be computed in accordance with the provisions of the 
Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>).]


</article>



<article><tid>11169</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power for Central Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>556058</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may make rules <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> to carry out the purposes and objects of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1513712</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may--
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>


<subsection><tid>518938</tid>
<number>b</number>define the powers of entry, inspection, measurement or 
survey which may be exercised in carrying out the 
purposes and objects of this act or of any rule made 
hereunder.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>561285</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1831765</tid>
<number> 36</number> Further provisions respecting rules.-
<section><tid>581875</tid>
<number>1</number>The power to make  
rules under section 35 shall be subject to the condition of the rules 
being made after previous publication and of their not taking effect 
until they have been published in the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1933</year>, s. 5. 
2. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 14, for" by sub- section (2) of that 
section". 
3. Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1925</year>, s. 4, for" under the Cantonments Act, 
<year>1910</year>, or any rule made thereunder". 
4. Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 15. 
5. For such rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1923</year>, Pt. I, p. 1242. 
6. Cl. (a) was rep. by Act 9 of <year>1930</year>, s. 16. 
7. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Official Gazette and in such other manner (if any) as the Central 
Government may direct.


</section>

<section><tid>97467</tid>
<number>2</number>Any rule under section 35 may be general for all cantonments 
or parts of cantonments <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in which this Act is for the time being 
operative, or may be special for any of such cantonments or parts as 
the Central Government may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1400548</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the rules under section 35 for the time being in 
force in a cantonment shall be kept open to inspection free of charge 
at all reasonable times in the office of the Cantonment <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board].

</section>

<section><tid>1892354</tid>
<number>4</number>In making any rule under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of 
section 35, the Central Government may direct that whoever obstructs 
any person, not being a public servant within the meaning of section 
 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), in making any entry, 
inspection, measurement or survey, shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to fifty rupees, and, in the case of a continuing offence, 
with fine which, in addition to such fine as aforesaid, may extend to 
five rupees for every day after the first during which such offence 
continues.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1886460</tid>
<number>37</number>Inapplicability of section 556 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year>, to trials of offences.- No Judge or Magistrate shall 
be deemed, within the meaning of section 556 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), to be a party to, or personally 
interested in, any prosecution for an offence constituted by or under 
this Act merely because he is a member of the Cantonment <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board or 
has ordered or approved the prosecution.


</article>



<article><tid>65112</tid>
<number>38</number>Protection to persons acting under Act.- No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything in good 
faith done, or intended to be done, under this Act or in pursuance of 
any lawful notice or order issued under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>88747</tid>
<number>39</number>[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1927</year> (12 of <year>1927</year>), s. 2 
and Sch.

</article>



 </act>