<act><title>THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (PROCEDURE 
AND SAFEGUARDS FOR BLOCKING FOR ACCESS OF INFORMATION BY PUBLIC) RULES, 
20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Information Technology (Procedure and Safeguards for Blocking for 
Access of Information by Public) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> computer resource means computer resource as defined in clause (k) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Designated Officer means an officer designated as Designated Officer 
  under rule 3; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Form means a form appended to these rules; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> intermediary means an intermediary as defined in clause (w) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> nodal officer means the nodal officer designated as such under 
   rule 4; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> organisation means 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Ministries or Departments of the Government of India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> State Governments and Union territories; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> any agency of the Central Government, as may be notified in the 
    Official Gazette, by the Central Government; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>h</number> request means the request for blocking of access by the public any 
  information generated, transmitted, received, stored or hosted in any computer 
  resource; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> Review Committee means the Review Committee constituted under rule 
  419A of Indian Telegraph Rules, 1951.</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Designated Officer. </title>The Central Government shall 
designate by notification in Official Gazette, an officer of the Central 
Government not below the rank of a Joint Secretary, as the Designated Officer, 
for the purpose of issuing direction for blocking for access by the public any 
information generated, transmitted, received, stored or hosted in any computer 
resource under sub-section (2) of section 69A of the Act. <title></title>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Direction by Designated Officer. </title>The Designated Officer 
may, on receipt of any request from the Nodal Officer of an organisation or a 
competent court, by order direct any Agency of the Government or intermediary to 
block for access by the public any information or part thereof generated, 
transmitted, received, stored or hosted in any computer resource for any of the 
reasons specified in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 69A of the Act. 
<title></title>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Forwarding of request by organisation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person 
may send their complaint to the Nodal Officer of the concerned organisation for 
blocking of access by the public any information generated, transmitted, 
received, stored or hosted in any computer resource: 
 Provided that any request, other than the one from the Nodal Officer of the 
organisation, shall be sent with the approval of the Chief Secretary of the 
concerned State or Union territory to the Designated Officer: 
 Provided further that in case a Union territory has no Chief Secretary, then, 
such request may be approved by the Adviser to the Administrator of that Union 
territory. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The organisation shall examine the complaint received under sub-rule (1) 
to satisfy themselves about the need for taking of action in relation to the 
reasons enumerated in sub-section (1) of section 69A of the Act and after being 
satisfied, it shall send the request through its Nodal Officer to the Designated 
Officer in the format specified in the Form appended to these rules. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Designated Officer shall not entertain any complaint or request for 
blocking of information directly from any person. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The request shall be in writing on the letter head of the respective 
organisation, complete in all respects and may be sent either by mail or by fax 
or by e-mail signed with electronic signature of the Nodal Officer: 
 Provided that in case the request is sent by fax or by e-mail which is not 
signed with electronic signature, the Nodal Officer shall provide a signed copy 
of the request so as to reach the Designated Officer within a period of three 
days of receipt of the request by such fax or e-mail. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> On receipt, each request shall be assigned a number alongwith the date 
and time of its receipt by the Designated Officer and he shall acknowledge the 
receipt thereof to the Nodal Officer within a period of twenty-four hours of its 
receipt. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Committee for examination of request. </title>The request 
alongwith the printed sample content of the alleged offending information or 
part thereof shall be examined by a committee consisting of the Designated 
Officer as its Chairperson and representatives, not below the rank of Joint 
Secretary in Ministries of Law and Justice, Home Affairs, Information and 
Broadcasting and the Indian Computer Emergency Response Team appointed under 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 70B of the Act. <title></title>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Examination of request. </title>
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of request under 
rule 6, the Designated Officer shall make all reasonable efforts to identify the 
person or intermediary who has hosted the information or part thereof as well as 
the computer resource on which such information or part thereof is being hosted 
and where he is able to identify such person or intermediary and the computer 
resource hosting the information or part thereof which have been requested to be 
blocked for public access, he shall issue a notice by way of letters or fax or 
e-mail signed with electronic signatures to such person or intermediary in 
control of such computer resource to appear and submit their reply and 
clarifications, if any, before the committee referred to in rule 7, at a 
specified date and time, which shall not be less than forty-eight hours from the 
time of receipt of such notice by such person or intermediary. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of non-appearance of such person or intermediary, who has been 
served with the notice under sub-rule (1), before the committee on such 
specified date and time, the committee shall give specific recommendation in 
writing with respect to the request received from the Nodal Officer, based on 
the information available with the committee. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case, such a person or intermediary, who has been served with the 
notice under sub-rule (1), is a foreign entity or body corporate as identified 
by the Designated Officer, notice shall be sent by way of letters or fax or 
e-mail signed with electronic signatures to such foreign entity or body 
corporate and any such foreign entity or body corporate shall respond to such a 
notice within the time specified therein, failing which the committee shall give 
specific recommendation in writing with respect to the request received from the 
Nodal Officer, based on the information available with the committee. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The committee referred to in rule 7 shall examine the request and printed 
sample information and consider whether the request is covered within the scope 
of sub-section (1) of section 69A of the Act and that it is justifiable to block 
such information or part thereof and shall give specific recommendation in 
writing with respect to the request received from the Nodal Officer. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Designated Officer shall submit the recommendation of the Committee, 
in respect of the request for blocking of information alongwith the details sent 
by the Nodal Officer, to the Secretary in the department of Information 
Technology under the Ministry of Communications and Information Technology, 
Government of India (hereinafter referred to as the Secretary, Department of 
Information Technology). 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Designated Officer, on approval of the request by the Secretary, 
Department of Information Technology, shall direct any agency of the Government 
or the intermediary to block the offending information generated, transmitted, 
received, stored or hosted in their computer resource for public access within 
the time limit specified in the direction: 
 Provided that in case the request of the Nodal Officer is not approved by the 
Secretary, Department of Information Technology, the Designated Officer shall 
convey the same to such Nodal Officer. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Blocking of information in cases of emergency. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in rules 7 and 8, the Designated Officer, in 
any case of emergency nature, for which no delay is acceptable, shall examine 
the request and printed sample information and consider whether the request is 
within the scope of sub-section (1) of section 69A of the Act and it is 
necessary or expedient and justifiable to block such information or part thereof 
and submit the request with specific recommendations in writing to Secretary, 
Department of Information Technology. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In a case of emergency nature, the Secretary, Department of Information 
Technology may, if he is satisfied that it is necessary or expedient and 
justifiable for blocking for public access of any information or part thereof 
through any computer resource and after recording reasons in writing, as an 
interim measure issue such directions as he may consider necessary to such 
identified or identifiable persons or intermediary in control of such computer 
resource hosting such information or part thereof without giving him an 
opportunity of hearing. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Designated Officer, at the earliest but not later than forty-eight 
hours of issue of direction under sub-rule (2), shall bring the request before 
the committee referred to in rule 7 for its consideration and recommendation. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of recommendations of committee, Secretary, Department of 
Information Technology, shall pass the final order as regard to approval of such 
request and in case the request for blocking is not approved by the Secretary, 
Department of Information Technology in his final order, the interim direction 
issued under sub-rule (2) shall be revoked and the person or intermediary in 
control of such information shall be accordingly directed to unblock the 
information for public access. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Process of order of court for blocking of information. 
</title>In case of an order from a competent court in India for blocking of 
any information or part thereof generated, transmitted, received, stored or 
hosted in a computer resource, the Designated Officer shall, immediately on 
receipt of certified copy of the court order, submit it to the Secretary, 
Department of Information Technology and initiate action as directed by the 
court. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Expeditious disposal of request. </title>The request received 
from the Nodal Officer shall be decided expeditiously which in no case shall be 
more than seven working days from the date of receipt of the request. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Action for non-compliance of direction by intermediary. 
</title>In case the intermediary fails to comply with the direction issued to 
him under rule 9, the Designated Officer shall, with the prior approval of the 
Secretary, Department of Information Technology, initiate appropriate action as 
may be required to comply with the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 69A 
of the Act. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Intermediary to designate one person to receive and handle 
directions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every intermediary shall designate at least one person 
to receive and handle the directions for blocking of access by the public any 
information generated, transmitted, received, stored or hosted in any computer 
resource under these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The designated person of the Intermediary shall acknowledge receipt of 
the directions to the Designated Officer within two hours on receipt of the 
direction through acknowledgement letter or fax or e-mail signed with electronic 
signature. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Meeting of Review Committee. </title>The Review Committee shall 
meet at least once in two months and record its findings whether the directions 
issued under these rules are in accordance with the provisions of sub-section 

<section><number>1</number> of section 69A of the Act and if is of the opinion that the directions are 
not in accordance with the provisions referred to above, it may set aside the 
directions and issue order for unblocking of said information generated, 
transmitted, received, stored or hosted in a computer resource for public 
access. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Maintenance of records by Designated Officer. </title>The 
Designated Officer shall maintain complete record of the request received and 
action taken thereof, in electronic database and also in register of the cases 
of blocking for public access of the information generated, transmitted, 
received, stored or hosted in a computer resource. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Requests and complaints to be confidential. </title>Strict 
confidentiality shall be maintained regarding all the requests and complaints 
received and actions taken thereof. 

</article><form>
 

THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (PROCEDURE 
AND SAFEGUARDS FOR BLOCKING FOR ACCESS OF INFORMATION BY PUBLIC) RULES, 
20091
 

 
 

 
 

FORM 
 

[ See rule 6(2)] 
 

A. Complaint 
 

1. Name of the complainant 
.................................................................................................. 

 

(Person who has sent the complaint to the Ministry/Department/State 
Govt./Nodal Officer) 
 

2. Address 
.................................................................................................................................. 

 

.................................................................................................................................. 

 

City ................................................. Pin Code 
............................................ 
 

3. Telephone ............................................... (prefix STD 
code) 
 

4. Fax (if any) ............................................. 
 

5. Mobile (if any) ....................................... 
 

6. Email (if any) ......................................... 
 

B. Details of website/computer resource/intermediary/ offending 
Information hosted on the website 
 

(Please give details wherever known) 
 

7. URL/web address 
................................................................................................................ 

 

8. IP Address 
............................................................................................................................. 

 

9. Hyperlink 
............................................................................................................................... 

 

10. Server/Proxy Server address 
............................................................................................ 

 

11. Name of the Intermediary 
................................................................................................ 

 

12. URL of the Intermediary 
................................................................................................... 

 

(Please attach screenshot/printout of the offending information) 
 

13. Address or location of intermediary in case the intermediary is telecom 
service provider, network service provider, internet service provider, 
web-hosting service provider and cyber cafe or other form of intermediary for 
which information under points (7), (8), (9), (10), (11) and (12) are not 
available. 
 

............................................................................................ 

 

............................................................................................ 

 

............................................................................................ 

 

C. Details of Request for blocking 
 

14. Recommendation/Comments of the Ministry/State 
Govt............................................ 
 

.................................................................................................................................................... 

 

.................................................................................................................................................... 

 

15. The level at which the comments/recommendation have been 
approved  
(Please specify designation) 
................................................................................................ 

 

16. Have the complaint been examined in Ministry/State Government: Y/N 
 

17. If yes, under which of the following reasons it falls (please tick): 

 
 

(i) Interest of sovereignty or integrity of India 
 

(ii) Defence of India 
 

(iii) Security of the State 
 

(iv) Friendly relations with foreign States 
 

(v) Public order 
 

(vi) For preventing incitement to the commission of any cognisable offence 
  relating to above 
 

D. Details of the Nodal Officer forwarding the complaint alongwith 
recommendation of the Ministry/State Govt. and related enclosures 

 

18. Name of the Nodal Officer 
................................................................................................ 

 

19. Designation 
............................................................................................................................. 

 

20. Organisation 
........................................................................................................................... 

 

21. Address 
.................................................................................................................................. 

 

.................................................................................................................................. 

 

City ................................................ Pin Code 
.............................................. 
 

22. Telephone ............................................... (prefix STD 
code) 
 

23. Fax (if any) ............................................ 
 

24. Mobile (if any) ...................................... 
 

25. E-mail (if any) ...................................... 
 

E. Any other information 
 

F. Enclosures: 1. 
 

2. 
 

3. 
 
 
 

Date.......................... 
    Place...............................Signature 
 

---------
 

1. Vide G.S.R 781(E), dated 27th October, 2009, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), No. 618, dated 
27th October, 2009. </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-10-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>