<act><title>


    The debts recovery appellate tribunal 
    (financial and Administrative power) 
    rules, 19971</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may 
    be called the Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal (Financial and 
    Administrative Power) Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come 
    into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    
    "Act" means the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial Institutions 
    Act, 1993 (51 of 1993);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    "Appellate Tribunal" means the Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal established 
    under sub-section (1) of section 9 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    
    "Presiding Officer" means a person appointed as Presiding Officer of an 
    Appellate Tribunal under section 9 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    
    all other words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but 
    defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in 
    the Act.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Powers of the 
    Presiding Officer of the Appellate Tribunal.—The 
    Presiding Officer shall have the same powers as are conferred on a Head of 
    Department in respect of the General Financial Rules, 1963, the Delegation 
    of the Financial Powers Rules, 1978, the Fundamental Rules, the 
    Supplementary Rules, the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, the 
    Central Civil Services (Joining Time) Rules, 1979, the Civil Services 
    (Pension) Rules, 1972, the Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, the 
    Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965 and 
    the General Provident Fund 9 (Central Services) Rules, 1960 as amended from 
    time to time
 
Provided that the 
    exercise of powers by the Presiding Officer under these rules shall be 
    subject to such instructions as may be issued from time to time by the 
    Central Government.
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>