<act><tid>397596</tid>
<title>THE INSTITUTES OF TECHNOLOGY (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 28th March, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Institutes of Technology Act, <year>1961</year>

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- Second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1545580</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>43273</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Institutes of Technology (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>318265</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 21st day of 
September, <year>2001</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1259589</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of Section 2.- In section of the Institutes of 
Technology Act, <year>1961</year> (59 of <year>1961</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), for the words" Kanpur and the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Madras", the words" Kanpur, the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Madras and the Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1301836</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1655657</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (c),-

<subsection><tid>1653228</tid>
<number>i</number>the word" and" appearing at the end of sub clause (ii) shall be 
omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1092684</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- clause (iii), after the words" the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Madras;", the word" and" shall be inserted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>684588</tid>
<number>iii</number>after sub- clause (iii), the following sub- clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (iv) in relation to the University of Roorkee, Roorkee, the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Roorkee;";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1984308</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (k), the following clause shall be inserted, namely 
:-
' (l)" University of Roorkee" means the University of Roorkee 
established under the Roorkee University Act, <year>1947</year> (U. P. Act IX of  
  <year>1948</year>).'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>799269</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (1B), the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (IC) The University of Roorkee, Roorkee shall, on such 
incorporation, be called the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Roorkee.".



</article>



<article><tid>370814</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 5A.- After section 5 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 5A. Effect of incorporation of Institute of Technology, Roorkee.- On 
and from the commencement of the Institutes of Technology (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2001</year>,-

<section><tid>1423276</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference to the University of Roorkee in any law (other than  
  this Act) or in any contract or other instrument shall be deemed as a 
reference to the Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee;

</section>

<section><tid>1593861</tid>
<number>b</number>all property, movable and immovable, of or belonging to the 
University of Roorkee, shall vest in the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Roorkee;

</section>

<section><tid>129519</tid>
<number>c</number>all rights and liabilities of the University of Roorkee shall be 
transferred to, and be the rights and liabilities of, the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Roorkee;

</section>

<section><tid>715743</tid>
<number>d</number>every person employed by the University of Roorkee immediately 
before such commencement shall hold his office or service in the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee by the same tenure, at the 
same remuneration and upon the same terms and conditi ns and with the 
same rights and privileges as to pension, leave, gratuity, provident 
fund and other matters as he would have held the same if this Act had 
not been passed, and shall continue to do so unless and until his 
employment is terminated or unti such tenure, remuneration and terms 
and conditions are duly altered by the Statutes:
Provided that if the alteration so made is not acceptable to such 
employee, his employment may be terminated by the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Roorkee in accordance with the terms of the contract with 
the employee or, if no provision is mad therein in this behalf, on 
payment to him by the Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee of 
compensation equivalent to three months' remuneration in the case of 
permanent employees and one month' s remuneration in the case of other 
employees:

Provided further that any reference, by whatever form of words, to the 
Vice- Chancellor and Pro- Vice- Chancellor of the University of Roorkee 
in any law for the time being in force, or in any instrument or other 
document, shall be construed as a r ference to the Director and the 
Deputy Director, respectively, of the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Roorkee; and


</section>

<section><tid>549232</tid>
<number>e</number>on the commencement of the Institutes of Technology (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2002</year>, the Vice- Chancellor of the University of Roorkee, appointed 
under the provisions of the Roorkee University Act, <year>1947</year> (U. P. Act IX  
  of <year>1948</year>) shall be deemed to have been ppointed as Director under the 
Act, and shall hold office for a period of three months or till such 
time the Director is appointed, whichever is earlier.
Explanation.- The reference in this section to the commencement of 
this Act shall be construed in relation to the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Roorkee as the reference to the date on which the 
provisions of the Institutes of Technology (Amendm nt) Act, <year>2002</year> come 
into force.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>376800</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 38.- In section 38 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1663437</tid>
<number>a</number>after clause (d), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (e) the Syndicate of the University of Roorkee functioning as such 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall continue to so 
function until a new Board is constituted for the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Roorkee under this Act, but on the onstitution of a new 
Board under this Act, the members of the Syndicate holding office 
before such constitution shall cease to hold office;


</section>

<section><tid>746620</tid>
<number>f</number>the academic Council of the University of Roorkee functioning as 
such immediately before the commencement of this Act shall continue to 
so function until a new Senate is constituted for the Indian Institute 
of Technology, Roorkee under this Act, but n the constitution of a new 
Senate under this Act, the members of the Academic Council holding 
office before such constitution shall cease to hold office;

</section>

<section><tid>1940804</tid>
<number>g</number>until the first Statutes and the Ordinances in relation to the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee are made under this Act, the 
Statutes and Ordinances of the Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay 
as in force immediately before the commencement of the Institutes of 
Technology (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> shall apply to the Indian Institute 
of Technology, Roorkee with the necessary modifications and 
adaptations in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions 
of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>218075</tid>
<number>h</number>notwithstanding anything contained in the Institutes of Technology 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, any student who joined classes of the 
University of Roorkee on or after the commencement of <year>1994</year>- 95 academic 
session shall, for the purpose of clause (b) of su- section (1) of 
section 6, be deemed to have pursued a course of study in the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Roorkee provided that such student has not 
already been awarded degree or diploma for the same course of study;

</section>

<section><tid>861931</tid>
<number>i</number>if any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of the 
Institutes of Technology (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the provisions of t is Act as may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order shall be made under this clause after the 
expiry of two years from the commencement of the Institutes of 
Technology (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>:

Provided further that every order made under this clause shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament.".


</section>

<section><tid>508509</tid>
<number>b</number>Explanation shall be numbered as Explanation 1 thereof and after 
Explanation 1 as so numbered, the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Explanation 2.- The reference in clauses (e) and (f) of this section 
to the commencement of this Act shall be construed in relation to the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee as the reference to the date 
on which the provisions of the Institutes of Technology (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2002</year> come into force.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1052042</tid>
<number> 7</number> Repeal and savings.-
<section><tid>1037427</tid>
<number>1</number>The Roorkee University Act, <year>1947</year> (U. P.   
  Act IX of <year>1948</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1573531</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>) shall 
apply to the repeal of the said Act as if the said Act were a Central 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1420321</tid>
<number>3</number>The Institutes of Technology (Amendment) Second Ordinance, <year>2001</year> 
 (Ord. 10 of <year>2001</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1883137</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the repealed Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of the principal Act, as 
amended by this Act.
K. N. CHATURVEDI, 
Addl. Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>