<act><title>


The Public Records Rules, 19971</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Public Records Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Public Records Act, 1993 (69 of 1993);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “appraisals” 
means the evaluation of public records in association with the National Archives 
of India or Archives of Union territory as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “classified 
records” means the files relating to the public records classified as topsecret, 
secret, confidential and restricted in accordance with procedure laid down in 
the Manual of Departmental Security Instructions circulated by the Ministry of 
Home Affairs from time to time.
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “custody” 
means the possession of public records;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “defunct body” 
means a corporate or non-corporate body which has been wound up with no 
successor to carry on its functions;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  “file” means 
a collection of papers relating downgrade the security classifications after 
their evaluation;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  “file” means a 
collection of papers relating to the public records on a specific subject-matter 
consisting of correspondence, notes and appendix thereto and assigned with a 
file number;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  “Form” means 
the form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  “private 
records” means records lying in the possession of a private individual or with 
any non-governmental organisation;
 </section><section>
        <number>j</number>  “recording” 
means the process of closing a file after action on all issues considered 
thereon has been completed;
 </section><section>
       <number>k</number>  “records of 
permanent nature” means the public records being maintained after recording for 
a period specified, under sub-rule (1) of rule 5 by the records creating agency 
in accordance with the procedure laid in its Manual of Office Procedure or 
Institutions on the subject;
 </section><section>
        <number>l</number>  “retention 
Schedule of records” means a Schedule which provides the period of retention;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  “review” means 
period evaluation of recorded files on the expiry of the period of retention for 
determining their further retention or destruction, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>n</number>  “section” 
means the section of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>o</number>  “standing 
guard file” means a compilation of papers on a particular subject- matter 
consisting of copies of policy decisions, orders, instructions or any another 
matter incidental thereto arranged in a chronological order;
 </section><section>
<number>p</number> words and expressions 
used herein and not defined but defined in the Act, shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Nomination of 
records officer.—The 
records creating agency shall by an office order issued in pursuance of the 
provisions of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5 of the Act nominate one of its 
officers, not below the rank or grade of a Section Officer, as the Records 
Officer. A copy of such office order shall be forwarded to the Director General 
or Head of the Archives, as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Maintenance of 
standing guard file.—The 
Records Officer shall be responsible for maintaining and keeping a standing 
guard file and proper record of the directions issued by the Director General or 
Head of the Archives, as the case may be, in pursuance of the provisions of 
sub-section (2) of section 6 and shall produce the same for inspection as and 
when required by the Director General or Head of the Archives, as the case may 
be.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Acceptance of public 
records of permanent nature.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director General or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, shall accept 
for deposit and preservation the public records of permanent nature which have 
been retained after recording by the records creating agency in its records room 
for the last twenty-five years or more.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Records Officer shall 
intimate to the Director General or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, 
each year before 31st day of January, in Form 1, the particulars of all public 
records of permanent nature which are due for appraisal during the year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of an 
intimation under sub-rule (2), the Director General or Head of the Archives, as 
the case may be, through his officers, shall assist the Records Officer in 
conducting the appraisal of public records. When the appraisal is over, the 
Records Officer shall prepare in triplicate, a transfer list in Form 2 of all 
public records and deposit the same for preservation with the Director General 
or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, who shall after his satisfaction, 
return one copy of the transfer list to the Records Officer as a receipt of the 
public records.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the Records Officer 
after appraisal deems it necessary to retain any record or file of permanent 
nature beyond the period of twenty-five years, he may do so for reasons to be 
recorded in writing and under intimation to the Director General or Head of the 
Archives as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Withdrawal of public 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
public records deposited and preserved with the Director General or Head of the 
Archives, as the case may be, is required by the records creating agency for any 
official purpose, then the Records Officer shall send a duly signed and stampted 
requisition slip in Form 3 to the Director General or Head of the Archives, as 
the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The public records 
requisitioned under sub-rule (1) may be returned as soon as the purpose is 
achieved but shall not be retained beyond the period of six months by the 
Records Officer of the record creating agency.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Down-grading of 
classified records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The records creating agency shall by an office order authorise an officer not 
below the rank of the Under Secretary to the Government of India to evaluate and 
downgrade the classified records being maintained by it. A copy of such office 
order shall be forwarded to the Director General or Head of the Archives, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The officer so 
authorised under sub-rule (1) shall evaluate the classified records every fifth 
year for the purpose of down-grading.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After down-grading if 
the officer declares any records as of permanent nature, the same shall be 
deposited and preserved with the Director General or Head of the Archives, as 
the case may be, after its appraisal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The records deposited 
under this rule can be requisitioned for any official purpose and returned to 
the Director General or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, in the manner 
provided under rule 6.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every year in the last 
week of June and December, a half-yearly statement in Form 4 shall be furnished 
by the officer authorised under sub-rule (1) to the Director General or Head of 
the Archives, as the case may be, on the action taken for evaluation and 
downgrading the classified records.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Submission of Annual 
Report.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Records Officer nominated under rule 3 furnish to the Director General or Head 
of the Archives, as the case may be, an Annual Report in Form 5 every year in 
the month of March of the following year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director General 
or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, shall, thereafter, submit a report 
to the Government in the Ministry of Human Resource Development every year on 
the action taken by the Records Officer in pursuance to the provisions of 
clauses (a) to (1) of sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Destruction of 
Public Records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No public record shall be destroyed without being recorded and revised. In the 
month of January every year, each records creating agency shall record after 
consulting the records retention Schedule all those files on which action has 
been completed. This work shall be accomplished in consultation with the Records 
Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No public record which 
is more than twenty-five years old shall be destroyed by any records creating 
agency unless it is appraised.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A list of all such 
public records which are proposed to be destroyed shall be prepared by the 
record creating agency in Form 6 and retained permanently for future reference.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Record Officer 
shall furnish a half yearly report in Form 7 on recording, indexing, reviewing 
and weeding of records to the Director General or Head of the Archives, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Records shall be 
destroyed either by burning or shredding in the presence of Record Officer.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Access to private 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Records acquired from private sources by way of gift or purchase or otherwise 
shall be made available for bona fide research subject to the conditions 
laid down by the donor.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Research scholar shall 
submit an application in Form 8 to the Director General or Head of the Archives, 
as the case may be, for permission to consult records. The Director General or 
Head of the Archives, as the case may be, may refuse such permission in public 
interest and for reasons to be recorded on the said application.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where microfilm rolls 
may be available, the original records shall not be supplied for consultation to 
research scholars. No copy of any record shall be made by any one without the 
prior permission of the Director General or Head of the Archives as the case may 
be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Access to public 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The public records accepted for deposit and preservation under sub-rule (1) of 
rule 5 shall be made available for bona fide consultation and research 
purposes subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 12 and the 
following conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  a person who 
intends to consult the public records shall apply to the Director General or 
Head of the Archives, as the case may be, in Form 8. The Director General or 
Head of the Archives, as the case may be, may refuse such permission in public 
interest and for reasons to be recorded on the said application;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  foreign 
national intending to consult the public records may be permitted only on the 
production of letters of introduction for their sponsoring institution and 
diplomatic Mission;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  records, 
maps and cartographic records relating to the Ministry of External Affairs and 
Ministry of Defence, in respect of Arunachal Pradesh (including Eastern section 
of the Sino-Indian border), Sikim, Bhutan, Nepal, Tibet, China and Myanmar and 
areas comprising Pakistan and Bangladesh may be made available for consultation 
keeping in view the security and the defence of India or of any part of the 
territory thereof. Records relating to the Ministry of External Affairs, Home 
Affairs and Human Resource Development in respect of Jammu and Kashmir 
(including Gilgit and Chitral)may also be made available for consultation 
keeping in view the security and defence of Indian or of any part of the 
territory thereof:
 
                 Provided 
that the director General or Head of the Archives, as the case may be, may 
refuse such consultation;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  wherever 
microfilm rolls may be made available, the original records shall not be 
supplied for consultation to research scholar;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  reprographic 
and transcription facilities may made available on submission of an application 
in Form 9 and for such services the applicant shall have to make the payment of 
such service charges as may be fixed by the Director General or Head of the 
Archives, as the case may be, from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  a person 
consulting public records for the purpose of research when he publishes the work 
which is based upon the material taken from the said records may acknowledge the 
same.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person intending to 
consult the public records shall not,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  write and put 
any marks or indications or on public records;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  fold, tear, 
cut, crease, or otherwise damage or mutilate public records;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  remove any 
public records without obtaining the permission from the Director General or 
Head of the Archives, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  be allowed to 
take any eatable or drinking products or smoking while consulting public 
records;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  place any 
thing or object on any public records with a view to make out any copy of the 
said records;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  disturb or 
interrupt any other person while consulting the public records; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  behave in a 
manner which, in the opinion of the Director General or Head of the Archives, as 
the case may be, is detrimental to the maintenance and preservation of public 
records.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Allowances to the 
members of the Archival Advisory Board.—The 
members of the Archival Advisory Board nominated by the Central Government under 
clause (d) of sub-section (2) of section 13 shall draw travelling allowance and 
daily allowance for attending the meetings of the Archival Advisory Board at the 
rates admissible to Group ‘A’ officers of the Central Government.
  
</article><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 1
 


[See sub-rule (2) of rule 5]
 


Particulars of 
records of permanent nature due for appraisal during the year..................
 


 


Total number of           
  Total number of files of        Total No. of           Total No. of         
  Remarks,
 


files of ‘A’ &amp; ‘B’ 
             `A' &amp; `B’ categories         files referred         files due 
for            if any
 


categories lying in        
transferred to records           to under               appraisal
 


the records rooms         
rooms by the section           columns 1
 


of the 
records                  during the period                 and 2
 


creating 
agencies                under report
 


 


   
      1                                         2                               
  3                         4                      5
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 2
 


[See sub-rule (3) of rule 5]
 


Transfer List
 


Name of the records creating agency i.e. 
Ministry/ 
 


Department/office/Public Undertaking etc. 
:           ......................................................
 


Name and Particulars of the Records Officer 
:        ......................................................
 


Name of the 
Branch/Section                                  
......................................................
 


year                                   
                                    
......................................................
 


 


Sl. No.        File No.             Subject 
  matter of the file     Remarks, if any
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
 



........................................................................
 


Signature and seal of the Records Officer
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 3
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 6)]
 


Requisition slip
 


Name of the records creating agency (i.e. 
Ministry/
 


Department/office) 
:                                                       
.............................................
 


Name and Particulars of the Records Officer 
:                 ..............................................
 


Particulars of records or file No. 
requisitioned                ..............................................
 


Purpose for which required 
                                            
..............................................
 


Undertaking by the Records Officer.— I 
....................................................hereby declare that the 
Records/file requisitioned shall be returned to the Director General/the Head of 
the Archives before the expiry of six months as required under sub-rule (2) of 
rule 6.
 


 
 



.........................................................................
 


Signature and seal of the Records Officer
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 4
 


[See sub-rule (5) of rule 7]
 


Half yearly 
statement on periodical review of  

classified records
 


 


    Total No. of                No. of 
  classified records          No. of files reviewed          Remarks
 


classified records               due for 
reviewing                  and downgraded
 


lying at 
present                                                              during the 
period
 


 


in the organisation                                                             
  under report
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 5
 


[(See sub-rule (1) of rule 8)]
 


Form for the 
submission of Annual Report to Director General of Archives/Head of the Archives
 


1. A Setting up organised Departmental 
Records Room: Whether your organisation has set up an organised Records 
Room, and if so, is the space sufficient?
 


B. Nomination of Records Officers:—Whether 
your organisation has nominated an officer as Departmental Records Office and if 
not; give reasons?
 


C. Training of Records Officer and Staff:
 


         (i)  Whether Departmental Records 
Officer has received training in Records management?
 


        (ii)  Whether the junior staff 
working in the Departmental Records Room are trained in various aspects of 
Records Management?
 


        (iii)  If not, are you willing to 
avail training facilities existing at National Archives of India?
 


D. I. Sharing of space for housing 
semi-current records at National Archives/Archives of the Union 
Territory:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation is 
willing to share space at National Archives, 
New Delhi 
and its Records Centres at Jaipur, 
Pondicherry and Bhubaneshwar and Regional Office at Bhopal?
 


        (ii)  If yes, please state bulk of 
records proposed to be transferred.
 


II. (i) Whether your organisation is willing 
to share space at the Archives of the Union 
Territory?
 


2. Periodical recording, reviewing and 
weeding out of semi-current records:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
taken steps for recording, reviewing and weeding out of ephemeral records?
 


        (ii)  Indicate the total number of 
records recorded, reviewed and weeded out during the period under report.
 


3. Appraisal of Non-Current records:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
initiated action to get non-current records appraised in consultation with 
National Archives?
 


        (ii)  State the total bulk of records 
awaiting appraisal.
 


4. Compilation/Revision of Retention Schedule 
of Records:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
compiled Record Retention Schedule of substantive functions in consultation with 
National Archives and if not what action do you propose to take?
 


        (ii)  Has your organisation taken 
steps to revise the above schedule after five years?
 


5. Periodical review of classified records:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
de-classified the classified records during the period under report?
 


        (ii)  If not, state reasons?
 


6. Compilation of Annual Indices to records:
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
compiled annual indices?
 


        (ii)  State inclusive years with the 
name of the series.
 


7. Compilation of Organisational history: 
Has your organisation compiled organisational history reflecting various 
functions alongwith the date of their creation? and if so furnish a copy to the 
National Archives.
 


8. Records of Defunit Bodies :
 


         (i)  Whether your organisation has 
got records of defunct bodies? give details.
 


        (ii)  If yes, what action have you 
initiated for their transfer to National Archives.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 6
 


[See sub-rule (3) of rule 9]
 


Particulars of 
record destroyed during the year .................
 


 


File 
  Nos.                                      Subject of the 
  files                                       Remarks
 


 
 


 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 7
 


[See sub-rule (4) of rule 9]
 


Quarterly report 
on recording indexing, reviewing and weeding of records during the quarter 
ending........
 


 


Sl.       Total number 
  of       Total number        Total No. of         Total No. of           
  Remarks
 


No.        files 
recorded              of files           files reviewed      files weeded
 



                                                
indexed                                        out, if any
 


 


  1                   
  2                            3                         
  4                         5                         6
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


Form 8
 


[See sub-rule (2) of rule 10 and 
clause (i) of sub-rule (1) of rule 11] 
 


Application form 
for permission to consult records
 


To,
 


The Director General of Archives,
 


Government of India,
 


New Delhi-110001.
 


Sir,
 


I hereby apply for enrolment as a research 
scholar for consulting record in the research room of the National Archives of 
India. I agree to comply with the rules and conditions inforce and promise to 
deposit a copy of each of my work based on the materials consulted at the 
National Archives of India immediately after the publication.
 


1.   Name, including Surname 
:                     Shri/Smt/Km/Dr........................................
 


2.   Father’s/Husband’s Name 
:                    
...............................................................
 


3.   Date of Birth 
:                                         
……..........................................................
 


4.   Qualifications 
:                                        
..............................................................
 


5.   Nationality 
:                                            
............................................................... 
 


6.   Profession 
:                                            
............................................................... 
 


7.   Subject of Research 
:                              
...............................................................  
 


8.   University/institution* registered with 
: ............................................................... 
 


9.   Period for which admission is sought :   
............................................................... 
 


10. Signature and date 
:                              
............................................................... 
 


11. Address (i) Local 
:                                   
.............................................................. 
 


                   (ii) Permanent 
:                          
.............................................................. 
 


Particulars of records to be consulted :
 


 


Sl. No.                    Department 
                  Period                          Remarks
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


4.
 


 


 
 


*Scholars are requested to attach a letter of 
recommendation from their University Institution/Department. However, the 
foreign scholars are requested to bring a letter of accredition from the 
diplomatic representatives of their country in India as well.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Public Records Rules, 1997
 


 
 


From 9
 


[See clause (v) of sub-rule (1) of 
rule 11]
 


Application for 
Reprographic/Transcription facilities
 


To
 


The Director General of Archives,
 


National Archives of India
 


New Delhi
 



Sir,                                                                                                       
Dated:
 


Kindly supply me Microfilm (NFG/POS) Photo 
Copies/Xerox Transcripts of the material(s) indicated in the enclosed list for 
my research/publication/University. The material is from the Ministry(s) 
Department(s) of ........................ consists of ........................ 
items and covers the period from ..................to ................
 


1. I declare that the above material is for 
my research/publication/university.
 


2. I undertake to pay the charges as per 
schedule of rates prevailing at the time of completion of work. I understand and 
accept that the estimated cost, when supplied is only tentative and the rates 
are also liable to revision without notice.
 


3. The photocopies/transcripts supplied will 
not be sold/transferred to any other person without prior permission of the 
Director General of Archives.
 


4. The material, if published, will be 
suitably acknowledged and provisions of copyright, where applicable, will be 
complied with.
 


5. I hereby deposit a sum of Rs. 
.................................................................. as advance
 


 
 



                                                                                          
Yours faithfully
 


Permanent 
Address                                                           Signature
 


(in block 
letters)                                                     Name (in block 
letters)
 



                                                                              
Local Address
 


 
 


For Office use
 


Advance received vide Receipt No. 
........................... dated .................. for Rs. 
..............Service charge have come to Rs. 
.......................................................................
 


Balance receipt vide Receipt No. 
....................... dated ........................... Rs. 
....................
 


Cleared for photo copying/transcription 
subject to following :—
 


(1) 
.........................................................................................................................
 


 
 



                                                                              
Signature of Archivist 
 



                                                                              
Date
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>