<act><tid>735211</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES AND THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL 
CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2006</year></title>

NO. 5 OF <year>2006</year>
[ 2nd March, <year>2006</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year> 
and the Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year>.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAPTER I

Preliminary





<article><tid>1163037</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>154775</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Government of Union Territories and the Government of National 
Capital Territory of Delhi (Amendment) Act, <year>2006</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>779238</tid>
<number>2</number>Section 2 shall be deemed to have come into force on the 31st day 
of March, <year>2005</year>.
CHAPTER II

AMENDMENT OF THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES ACT, <year>1963</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1813857</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new section 43F.- After section 43E of the Government 
of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>) the following section 
shall be inserted, namely:- 
" 43F. Special provision as to readjustment of territorial 
constituencies on the basis of <year>2001</year> census.- Notwithstanding the 
publication of orders under sub- section
<section><tid>502773</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 10 of the  
Delimitation Act, <year>2002</year> (33 of <year>2002</year>) or anything contained in sub- 
section (2) or sub- section (4) of the said section, any readjustment 
in the division of Union territory into territorial constituencies by 
the Delimitation Commission under the said Act, on the basis of <year>2001</year> 
census shall take effect from such date as the Central Government 
may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, specify and until 
such readjustment takes effect, any election to the Legislative 
Assembly may be held on the basis of the territorial constituencies 
existing before such readjustment.".
CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT OF THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI 
ACT, <year>1991</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1394580</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the Government of National 
Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year> (1 of <year>1992</year>), in sub- section (3), 
after the proviso, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided further that any readjustment in the division of the 
Capital into territorial constituencies by the Delimitation 
Commission under the Delimitation Act, <year>2002</year> (33 of <year>2002</year>) on the basis 
of <year>2001</year> census shall take effect from such date as the Central 
Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, specify 
and until such readjustment takes effect, any election to the 
Legislative Assembly may be held on the basis of the territorial 
constituencies existing before such readjustment.".

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.

----

CORRIGENDUM

In the Criminal Law (Amendment) Act, <year>2005</year> (No. 2 of <year>2006</year>) as 
published in the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part II, Section 1, 
dated the 12th January <year>2006</year> (issue No. 2), at page 2, for the 
marginal heading of section 195A, read" Threatening any person to 
give false evidence.".




</article>



 </act>