<act><title>

The
religious endowments act, 1863</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Repeal of parts of Bengal Regulation XIX of 1810 and Madras Regulation VII of
1817.—[Rep. by the Repealing Act,
1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch.]
  

 
  


</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>2</number> Interpretation clause.—In 
this Act—
 
1[***]

 
2[***]

           “Civil Court” and “Court”.—The words “Civil 
Court” and “Court” shall
3[save as 
provided in section 10] mean the principal Court of original civil jurisdiction 
in the District in which
3[or any 
other Court empowered in that behalf by the
4[State 
Government] within the local limits of the jurisdiction of which] the mosque, 
temple or religious establishment is situate, relating to which, or to the 
endowment whereof, any suit shall be instituted or application made under the 
provisions of this Act.
  






</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>2</number> Interpretation clause.—In 
this Act—
 
1[***]

 
2[***]

           “Civil Court” and “Court”.—The words “Civil 
Court” and “Court” shall
3[save as 
provided in section 10] mean the principal Court of original civil jurisdiction 
in the District in which
3[or any 
other Court empowered in that behalf by the
4[State 
Government] within the local limits of the jurisdiction of which] the mosque, 
temple or religious establishment is situate, relating to which, or to the 
endowment whereof, any suit shall be instituted or application made under the 
provisions of this Act.
  






</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>3</number> Government to make special 
provision respecting mosques, etc.—In 
the case of every mosque, temple or other religious establishment to which the 
provisions of either of the Regulations specified in 

1[the Preamble to this Act] are 
applicable, and nomination of the trustee, manager or superintendent thereof, at 
the time of the passing of this Act, is vested in, or may be exercised by, the 
Government, or any public officer, or in which the nomination of such trustee, 
manager or superintendent shall be subject to the confirmation of the Government 
or any public officer, the 

2[State Government] shall, as soon as 
possible after the passing of this Act, make special provision as hereinafter 
provided.







</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>4</number> Transfer to trustees, etc., 
of trust-property in charge of Revenue Board.—In 
the case of every such mosque, temple or other religious establishment which, at 
the time of the passing of this Act, shall be under the management of any 
trustee, manager or superintendent, whose nomination shall not vest in, nor be 
exercised by, nor be subject to the confirmation of, the Government, or any 
public officer, the 

1[State Government] shall, as soon as 
possible after the passing of this Act, transfer to such trustee, manager or 
superintendent, all the landed or other property which, at the time of the 
passing of this Act, shall be under the superintendence or in the possession of 
the Board of Revenue, or any local agent, and belonging to such mosque, temple 
or other religious establishment, except such property as is hereinafter 
provided:
 Cessation of Board’s powers 
as to such property.—And the powers 
and responsibilities of the Board of Revenue, and the local agents, in respect 
to such mosque, temple or other religious establishment, and to all land and 
other property so transferred, except as regards acts done and liabilities 
incurred by the said Board of Revenue or any local agent, previous to such 
transfer, shall cease and determine.






</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article>*<number>5</number> Procedure in case of 
dispute as to right of succession to vacated trusteeship.—Whenever from any 
cause a vacancy shall occur in the office of any trustee, manager, or 
superintendent, to whom any property shall have been transferred under the last 
preceding section, and any dispute shall arise respecting the right of 
succession to such office, it  shall be lawful for any person interested in the 
mosque, temple or religious establishment, to which such property shall belong, 
or in the performance of the worship or of the service thereof, or the trusts 
relating thereto, to apply to the Civil Court to appoint a manager of such 
mosque, temple or other religious establishment, and thereupon such Court may 
appoint such manager, to act until some other person  shall by suit have 
established his right of succession to such office.
 Powers of managers appointed 
by Court.—The manager so appointed by 
the Civil Court shall have, and shall exercise, all the powers which, under this 
or any other Act, the former trustee, manager, or superintendent, in whose place 
such manager is appointed, by the Court, had or could exercise, in relation to 
such mosque, temple or religious establishment, or the property belonging 
thereto.
  



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Rights, etc., of trustees to whom property is transferred under section
4.—The rights, powers, and
responsibilities of every trustee, manager or superintendent, to whom the land
and other property of any mosque, temple or other religious establishment is
transferred in the manner prescribed in section 4 of this Act, as well as the
conditions of their appointment, election and removal, shall be the same as if
this Act had not been passed, except in respect of the liability to be sued
under this Act, and except in respect of the authority of the Board of Revenue,
and local agents, given by the Regulations hereby repealed, over such mosque,
temple or religious establishment, and over such trustee, manager, or
superintendent, which authority is hereby determined and repealed.
 All
the powers which might be exercised by any Board or local agent, for the
recovery of the rent of land or other property transferred under the said
section 4 of this Act, may, from the date of such transfer, be exercised by any
trustee, manager or superintendent to whom such transfer is made.

 
  


</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article> <number>7</number> Appointment of 
committees.—In all cases described in 
section 3 of this Act, the 

1[State Government] shall once for all 
appoint one or more committees in every division or district, to take the place, 
and to exercise the powers, of the Board of Revenue and the local agents under 
the Regulations hereby repealed.
 Constitution and duties of 
committees.—Such committee shall 
consist of three or more persons, and shall perform all the duties imposed on 
such Board and local agents, except in respect of any property which is 
specially provided for under section 21 of this Act.






</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>8</number> Qualifications of member 
of committee.—The members of the said 
committee shall be appointed from among persons professing the religion for the 
purposes of which the mosque, temple or other religious establishment was 
founded or is now maintained, and in accordance, so far as can be ascertained, 
with the general wishes of those who are interested in the maintenance of such 
mosque, temple or other religious establishment.
 The appointment of the committee 
shall be notified in the Official 
Gazette.
 Ascertaining wishes of 
persons interested.—In order to 
ascertain the general wishes of such persons in respect of such appointment, the


1[State Government] may cause an election 
to be held, under such rules 

2[, by notification in the Official 
Gazette] not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as shall be framed by 
such 

1[State Government].
 

2[Every rule framed under this section 
shall be laid, as soon as it is framed, before the State Legislature.]
 
 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Tenure of office.—Every member of a
committee appointed as above shall hold his office for life, unless removed for
misconduct or unfitness;
 <section><number>Removal</number>—and
no such member shall be removed except by an order of the Civil Court as
hereinafter provided.

 
  


</section></article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>10</number> Vacancies to be filled.—Whenever 
any vacancy shall occur among the members of a committee appointed as above, a 
new member shall be elected to fill the vacancy by the persons interested as 
above provided.
 <section><number>Procedure</number>—The 
remaining members of the committee shall, as soon as possible, give public 
notice of such vacancy, and shall fix a day, which shall not be later than three 
months from the date of such vacancy, for an election of a new member by the 
persons interested as above provided, under rules for elections which shall be 
framed by the 

1[State Government];
 and whoever shall be then 
elected, under the said rules, shall be a member of the committee to fill such 
vacancy.
 When Court may fill vacancy.—If 
any vacancy as aforesaid shall not be filled up by such election as aforesaid 
within three months after it has occurred, the Civil Court, on the application 
of any person whatever, may appoint a person to fill the vacancy or may order 
that the vacancy be forthwith filled up by the remaining members of the 
committee, with which order it shall then be the duty of such remaining members 
to comply; and if this order be not complied with, the Civil Court may appoint a 
member to fill the said vacancy.
 

2[Explanation.—In this section 
“Civil Court” means the principal Court of original civil jurisdiction in the 
district in which the mosques, temples or religious establishments for which the 
committee has been appointed or any of them are situate].
  




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
No member of committee to be also trustee, etc. of mosque, etc.—No
member of a committee appointed under this Act shall be capable of being, or
shall act, also as a trustee, manager or superintendent of the mosque, temple or
other religious establishment for the management of which such committee shall
have been appointed.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
On appointment of committee, Board and local agents to transfer
property.—Immediately on the
appointment of a committee as above provided for the superintendence of any such
mosque, temple or religious establishment, and for the management of its
affairs, the Board of Revenue, or the local agents acting under the authority of
the said Board, shall transfer to such committee all landed or other property
which at the time of appointment shall be under the superintendence, or in the
possession of the said Board or local agents, and belonging to the said
religious establishment, except as is hereinafter provided for,
 Termination
of powers and responsibilities of Board and Agents.—and
thereupon the powers and responsibilities of the Board and the local agents, in
respect to such mosque, temple or religious establishment, and to all land and
other property so transferred except as above, and except as regards acts done
and liabilities incurred by the said Board or agents previous to such transfer,
shall cease and determine.
 Commencement
of powers of Committee.—All the
powers which might be exercised by any Board or local agent for the recovery of
the rent of land or other property transferred under this section may from the
date of such transfer be exercised by such committee to whom such transfer is
made.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Duty of trustee, etc., as to accounts.—It
shall be the duty of every trustee, manager and superintendent of a mosque,
temple or religious establishment ot which the provisions of this Act shall
apply to keep regular accounts of his receipts and disbursements in respect of
the endowments and expenses of such mosque, temple or other religious
establishment;
 and
of committee.—and it shall be the
duty of every committee of management, appointed or acting under the authority
of this Act, to require from every trustee, manager and superintendent of such
mosque, temple or other religious establishment, the production of such regular
accounts of such receipts and disbursements at least once in every year; and
every such committee of management shall themselves keep such accounts thereof.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Persons interested may singly sue in case of breach of trust, etc.—Any
person or persons interested in any mosque, temple or religious establishment,
or in the performance of the worship or of the service thereof, or the trusts
relating thereto, may, without joining as plaintiff any of the other persons
interested therein, sue before the Civil Court the trustee, manager or
superintendent of such mosque, temple or religious establishment or the member
of any committee appointed under this Act, for any misfeasance, breach of trust
or neglect of duty, committed by such trustee, manager, superintendent or member
of such committee, in respect of the trusts vested in, or confided to, them
respectively;
 Powers
of Civil Court.—and the Civil Court
may direct the specific performance of any act by such trustee, manager,
superintendent or member of a committee,
 and
may decree damages and costs against such trustee, manager, superintendent or
member of a committee,
 and
may also direct the removal of such trustee, manager, superintendent or member
of a committee.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Nature of interest entitling person to sue.—The
interest required in order to entitle a person to sue under the last preceding
section need not be a pecuniary, or a direct or immediate, interest or such an
interest as would entitle the person suing to take any part in the management or
superintendence of the trusts.
 Any
person having a right of attendance, or having been in the habit of attending,
at the performance of the worship or service of any mosque, temple or religious
establishment, or of partaking in the benefit of any distribution of alms, shall
be deemed to be a person interested within the meaning of the last preceding
section.

 
  


</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>16</number> Reference to 
arbitrators.—In any suit or 
proceeding instituted under this Act it shall be lawful for the Court before 
which such suit or proceeding is pending to order any matter in difference in 
such suit to be referred for decision to one or more arbitrators.
 Act 10 of 1940 
applied.—Whenever any such order 
shall be made, the provisions of 1[Chapter IV of the Arbitration Act, 1940 (10 of 1940)] 
shall in all respects apply to such order and arbitration, in the same manner as 
if such order had been made on the application of the parties under 2[section 21 of the said Act].
  



</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>17</number> Reference under Act 10 of 
1940.—Nothing in the last preceding 
section shall prevent the parties from applying to the Court, or the Court from 
making the order of reference, under the said 1[section 21 of the Arbitration Act, 1940].
  


</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>18</number> Application for leave to 
institute suits.—No suit shall be 
entertained under this Act without a preliminary application being first made to 
the Court for leave to institute such suit, 

1[***]
 The Court, on the perusal of the 
application, shall determine whether there are sufficient prima facie 
grounds for the institution of a suit, and, if in the judgment of the Court 
there are such grounds, leave shall be given for its institution.
 <section><number>Costs</number>—2[***] 
If the Court shall be of opinion that the suit has been for the benefit of the 
trust, and that no party to the suit is in fault, the Court may order the costs 
or such portion as it may consider just to be paid out of the estate.
  




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
Court may require accounts of trust to be filed.—Before
giving leave for institution of a suit, or, after leave has been given, before
any proceeding is taken, or at any time when the suit is pending, the Court may
order the trustee, manager or superintendent, or any member of a committee, as
the case may be, to file in Court the accounts of the trust, or such part
thereof as to the Court may seem necessary.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Proceedings for criminal breach of trust.—No
suit or proceeding before any Civil Court under the preceding sections shall in
any way affect or interfere with any proceeding in a Criminal Court for criminal
breach of trust.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Cases in which endowments are partly for religious and partly for secular
purposes.—In any case in which any
land or other property has been granted for the support of an establishment
partly of a religious and partly of a secular character,
 or
in which the endowment made for the support of an establishment is appropriated
partly to religious and partly to secular uses,
 the
Board of Revenue, before transferring to any trustee, manager or superintendent,
or to any committee of management appointed under this Act, shall determine what
portion, if any, of the said land or other property shall remain under the
superintendence of the said Board for application to secular uses,
 and
what portion shall be transferred to the superintendence of the trustee, manager
or superintendent, or of the committee,
 and
also what annual amount, if any, shall be charged on the land or other property
which may be so transferred to the superintendence of the said trustee, manager
or superintendent, or of the committee, and made payable to the said Board or to
the local agents, for secular uses as aforesaid.
 In
every such case the provisions of this Act shall take effect only in respect to
such land and other property as may be so transferred.

 
  


</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>22</number> Government not to hold 
charge henceforth of property for support of any mosque, temple, etc.—Except 
as provided in this Act, it shall not be lawful 

1[***] for 

2[the Central Government or any State 
Government], or for any officer of any Government in his official character,
 to undertake or resume the 
superintendence of any land or other property granted for the support of, or 
otherwise belonging to, any mosque, temple or other religious establishment, or
 to take any part in the 
management or appropriation of any endowment made for the maintenance of any 
such mosque, temple or other establishment, or 
 to nominate or appoint any 
trustee, manager or superintendent thereof, or to be in any way concerned 
therewith.*








</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>23</number> Effect of Act in respect of 
Regulations therein mentioned, and of buildings of antiquity, 
etc.—Nothing in this Act shall 
be held to affect the provisions of the *Regulations mentioned in this Act, 
except in so far as they relate to mosques, Hindu temples and other religious 
establishments; or to prevent the Government from taking such steps as it may 
deem necessary, under the provisions of the said Regulations, to prevent injury 
to and preserve buildings **remarkable for their antiquity, or for their 
historical or architectural value, or required for the convenience of the 
public.***
  




</article> 
 the religious endowments act, 1863
  
 <article><number>23</number> Effect of Act in respect of 
Regulations therein mentioned, and of buildings of antiquity, 
etc.—Nothing in this Act shall 
be held to affect the provisions of the *Regulations mentioned in this Act, 
except in so far as they relate to mosques, Hindu temples and other religious 
establishments; or to prevent the Government from taking such steps as it may 
deem necessary, under the provisions of the said Regulations, to prevent injury 
to and preserve buildings **remarkable for their antiquity, or for their 
historical or architectural value, or required for the convenience of the 
public.***
  




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>24</number>
“India”.—[Rep. by the A.O.
1948.]
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>