<act><title>


The Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Appeal 
    to Securities Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 20001</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Appeal to 
    Securities Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the 
    Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>    
    “appeal” means an appeal filed under section 21A or section 22A or section 
    23L of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 or under sub-rule (5) 
    of rule 19 or sub-rule (5) of rule 20 of the Securities Contracts 
    (Regulation) Rules, 1957;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Appellate Tribunal” 
    means the Securities Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 15K of the 
    Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “bye-laws” means 
    bye-laws made by a stock exchange under the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “form” means the form 
    appended to these rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>ea</number>    
    ‘Member’ means the member of the Securities Appellate Tribunal appointed 
    under section 15L of the Securities Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 
    1992);]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “party” means a person 
    who prefers an appeal before the Appellate Tribunal and includes respondent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “Presiding Officer” 
    means the Presiding Officer of the Securities Appellate Tribunal appointed 
    under section 15L of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 
    (15 of 1992);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>h</number>    
    “Registrar” means the Registrar of the Appellate Tribunal and includes an 
    Officer of such Appellate Tribunal who is authorised by the Presiding 
    Officer to function as Registrar;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “registry” means the 
    registry of the Appellate Tribunals;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    “rules” means the rules 
    made under the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    “recognised stock 
    exchange” means a stock exchange defined under clause (f) of section 2 of 
    the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    “stock exchange” means a 
    stock exchange defined under clause (j) of section 2 of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and 
    expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 
    Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 shall have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in that Act.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Limitation for filing appeal.—<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Where a recognised stock exchange acting in pursuance of any power given to 
    it by its bye-laws, refuses to list the securities of any company, the 
    company shall be entitled to be furnished with reasons for such refusal and 
    may,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    within 15 days from the 
    date on which the reasons for such refusal are furnished to it, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the stock exchange 
    had omitted or failed to dispose of, within the time specified in 
    sub-section (1A) of section 73 of the Companies Act, 1956 (hereinafter in 
    this rule referred to as the “specified time”), the application for 
    permission for the shares or debentures to be dealt with on the stock 
    exchange, within 15 days from the date of expiry of the specified time or 
    within such further period, not exceeding one month, as the Appellate 
    Tribunal may, on sufficient cause being shown, allow appeal to the 
    Securities Appellate Tribunal having jurisdiction in the matter against such 
    refusal, omission or failure, as the case may be.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Every appeal shall be filed within a period of forty-five days from the date 
    on which a copy of the order, against which the appeal is filed, of a 
    recognised stock exchange withdrawing admission to dealings or suspending 
    admission to dealings which continues for a period exceeding three months in 
    any security/units or other instruments of a “collective instrument scheme”, 
    as defined under the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 
    1992), is received by the appellant:  
 
Provided that 
    the Appellate Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the 
    period of forty-five days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause 
    for not filing it within that period.]
 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Form and 
    procedure of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
    memorandum of appeal shall be presented in the Form by any aggrieved person 
    in the registry of the Appellate Tribunal within whose jurisdiction his case 
    falls or shall be sent by registered post addressed to the Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    memorandum of appeal sent by post shall be deemed to have been presented in 
    the registry on the day it was received in the registry.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Sittings of Appellate Tribunal.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The Appellate Tribunal shall hold its sitting either at a place where its 
    office is situated or at such other place falling within its jurisdiction, 
    as it may deem fit by the Appellate Tribunal.
 


    2[(2) In the temporary 
    absence of the Presiding Officer, Government may authorise one of the two 
    other Members to preside over the sitting of the Tribunal either at a place 
    where its office is situated or at such other place falling within  its 
    jurisdiction as it may deem fit by the Appellate Tribunal.]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Language 
    of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    proceedings of the Appellate Tribunal shall be conducted in English or 
    Hindi.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal, 
    application, representation, document or other matters contained in any 
    language other than English or Hindi, shall be accepted by Appellate 
    Tribunal, unless the same is accompanied by a true copy of translation 
    thereof in English or Hindi.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appeal 
    to be in writing.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    appeal, application, reply, representation or any document filed before the 
    Appellate Tribunal shall be typewritten, cyclostyled or printed neatly and 
    legibly on one side of the good quality paper of foolscap size in double 
    space and separate sheets shall be stitched together and every page shall be 
    consecutively numbered and filed in the manner provided in sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    appeal under sub-rule (1) shall be presented in 

    1[five] sets in a 
    paper book along with an empty file size envelope bearing full address of 
    the respondent and in case the respondents are more than one, then 
    sufficient number of extra paper books together with empty file size 
    envelope bearing full addresses of each respondent shall be furnished by the 
    appellant.
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Presentation and scrutiny of memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar shall endorse on every appeal the date on which it is 
    presented under Rule 4 or deemed to have been presented under that rule and 
    shall sign endorsement.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on 
    scrutiny, the appeal is found to be in order, it shall be duly registered 
    and given a serial number.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If an 
    appeal on scrutiny is found to be defective and the defect noticed is formal 
    in nature, the Registrar may allow the appellant to rectify the same in his 
    presence and if the said defect is not formal in nature, the Registrar may 
    allow the appellant such time to rectify the defect as he may deem fit. If 
    the appeal has been sent by post and found to be defective, the Registrar 
    may communicate the defects to the appellant and allow the appellant such 
    time to rectify the defect as he may deem fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the 
    appellant fails to rectify the defect within the time allowed in sub-rule 
    (3), the Registrar may by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
    decline to register such memorandum of appeal and communicate the order to 
    the appellant within seven days thereof.  
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> 
    An appeal against the order of the Registrar under sub-rule (4) shall be 
    made within 15 days of receiving of such order to the Presiding Officer or 
    in his temporary absence, to the Member authorised under sub-rule (2) of 
    rule 5,  whose decision thereon shall be final.] 
 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Payment of Fees.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied with a fee as provided in 
    sub-rule (2) and such fee may be remitted in the form of crossed demand 
    draft drawn on any nationalized bank in favour of “the Registrar, Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal” payable at the station where the registry is located.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount 
    of fee  payable in respect of appeal against adjudication orders made 
    under the Act shall be as follows:  
  
 

Table
 
 
 Serial 
        Number
 Amount 
        of Penalty Imposed
 Amount 
        of Fees Payable

 
 (1)
 (2)
 (3)

 
  
  
  

 
 i.
 Less than rupees ten 
        thousand
 Rs. 500

 
 ii.
 Rupees Ten Thousand or 
        more but less that One Lakh
 Rs. 1200

 
 iii.
 Rupees One Lakh or more
 Rs. 1200 plus Rs. 500 for 
        every additional one lakh of Penalty or fraction thereof subject to 
        maximum of Rs. 150000.


  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Contents of memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every memorandum of appeal filed under Rule 4 shall set forth concisely 
    under distinct heads, the grounds of such appeal without any argument or 
    narrative, and such ground shall be numbered consecutively and shall be in 
    the manner provided in sub-rule (1) of Rule 7.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall 
    not be necessary to present separate memorandum of appeal to seek interim 
    order or direction if in the memorandum of appeal, the same is prayed for.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Documents to accompany memorandum of appeal.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every memorandum of appeal shall be in five copies and shall be accompanied 
    with copies of the order, at least one of which shall be certified copy, 
    against which the appeal is filed.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    party is represented by authorised representative, a copy of the 
    authorisation to act as the authorised representative and the written 
    consent thereto by such authorised representative, shall be appended to the 
    appeal.
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Plural 
    remedies.—A memorandum of appeal 
    shall not seek relief or reliefs therein against more than one order unless 
    the reliefs prayed for are consequential.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Notice 
    of appeal to the respondent.—A 
    copy of the memorandum of appeal and paper book shall be served by the 
    Registrar on the respondent as soon as they are registered in the registry, 
    by hand delivery, or by Registered Post or Speed Post.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Filing of reply to the appeal and other documents by the respondent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The respondent may file 

    1[five] complete sets 
    containing the reply to the appeal along with documents in a paper book form 
    with the registry within one month of the service of the notice on him of 
    the filing of the memorandum of appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    reply, application or written representation filed before the Appellate 
    Tribunal shall be verified in the manner provided for, in the Form.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of 
    every application, reply, document or written material filed by the 
    respondent before the Appellate Tribunal shall be forthwith served on the 
    appellant, by the respondent.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal may, in its discretion, on application by the respondent 
    allow the filing of reply referred to in sub-rule (1) after the expiry of 
    the period referred to therein.  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Date of 
    hearing to be notified.—The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall notify the parties the date of hearing of the 
    appeal in such manner as the Presiding Officer may by general or special 
    order direct.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Hearing 
    of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> On the day fixed 
    or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the appellant 
    shall be heard in support of the appeal. The Securities Appellate Tribunal 
    shall, then, if necessary, hear the Board or its authorised representative 
    against the appeal, and in such case the appellant shall be entitled to 
    reply. During the course of the hearing of appeal the written arguments 
    could be supplemented by time-bound oral arguments:
 


    1[Provided that in 
    case of temporary absence of the Presiding Officer or of the Member 
    authorised by the Government under sub-rule (2) of rule 5, the Presiding 
    Officer can authorise the other Member present on the day to hear the Board 
    or authorised representative against the appeal.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case 
    the appellant does not appear in person or through an authorised 
    representative when the appeal is called for hearing, the Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal may dispose of the appeal on merits:  
 
Provided that 
    where an appeal has been disposed of as provided above and the appellant 
    appears afterwards and satisfies the Securities Appellate Tribunal that 
    there was sufficient cause for his non appearance, when the appeal was 
    called for hearing, the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall make an order 
    setting aside the ex parte order and restore the appeal.
 
 


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>17</number> 
    Dress regulations for the Presiding Officer, Members and for the 
    representatives of the parties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The dress for the Presiding Officer shall be white or striped or black pant 
    with black coat over white shirt and band or buttoned-up black coat and 
    band. The dress for the two other Members shall be white or striped or black 
    pant with black coat over white shirt and black tie or buttoned-up black 
    coat. In the case of female Presiding Officer or a Member, the dress shall 
    be black coat over a white saree.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    authorised representative, other than a relative or regular employee of the 
    party shall appear before the Appellate Tribunal in his professional dress 
    if any, and if there is no such dress, a male, in a suit or buttoned-up coat 
    over a pant or national dress, that is a long buttoned-up coat on dhoti or 
    churidar pyjama, and a female, in a coat over white or any other sober 
    coloured saree or in any other sober dress.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All other 
    persons appearing before the Appellate Tribunal shall be properly dressed.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>18</number> 
    Order to be signed and dated.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every order of the Appellate Tribunal shall be signed and dated by the 
    Presiding Officer and two other Members. The Presiding Officer will have 
    powers to pass such interim orders or injunctions, subject to reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, which it considers necessary in the interest of 
    justice. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Orders 
    shall be pronounced in the sitting of the Appellate Tribunal by the 
    Presiding Officer or in case of the temporary absence of the Presiding 
    Officer, by the Member authorized under sub-rule (2) of rule 5.]  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Publication of orders.—The orders 
    of the Appellate Tribunal, as are deemed fit for publication in any 
    authoritative report or the press may be released for such publication on 
    such terms and conditions as the Presiding Officer may lay down.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Communication of orders.—A 
    certified copy of every order passed by the Appellate Tribunal shall be 
    communicated to the Board, the Adjudicating Officer and to the parties, as 
    the case may be.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Orders 
    and directions in certain cases.—The 
    Appellate Tribunal may make such orders or give such directions as may be 
    necessary or expedient to give effect to its orders or prevent abuse of its 
    process or to secure the ends of justice.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Fee for 
    inspection of records and obtaining copies thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A fee of rupees twenty, for every hour or part thereof of inspection subject 
    to a minimum of rupees one hundred shall be charged for inspecting the 
    records of a pending appeal by a party thereto.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A fee of 
    rupees five for a folio or part thereof not involving typing and a fee of 
    rupees ten for a folio or part thereof involving typing of statement and 
    figures shall be charged for providing copies of the records of an appeal, 
    to a party thereto.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Working 
    hours of the Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The office of the Appellate Tribunal shall observe such public and other 
    holidays as observed by the offices of the Central Government in the 
    locality where the office of the Appellate Tribunal is situated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall, subject to any other order made by the Presiding 
    Officer, remain open on the working days from 10 a.m. to 6.00 p.m. But no 
    work, unless of an urgent nature, shall be admitted after 4.30 p.m. on any 
    working day.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    sitting hours of the Appellate Tribunal shall ordinarily be from 10.30 a.m. 
    to 1.00 p.m. and 2.00 p.m. to 5.00 p.m., subject to any order made by the 
    Presiding Officer.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Holiday.—Where the last day for 
    doing any act falls on a day on which the office of the Appellate Tribunal 
    is closed and by reason thereof the act cannot be done on that day, it may 
    be done on the next day on which that office opens.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Functions of the Registrar.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar shall discharge his functions under general superintendence of 
    the Presiding Officer or in the temporary absence of the Presiding Officer, 
    the Member authorized under sub-rule (2) of rule 5. He shall discharge such 
    other functions as are assigned to him under these rules or by the Presiding 
    Officer or in the temporary absence of the Presiding Officer, by the Member 
    authorized under sub-rule (2) of rule 5, by a separate order in writing.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall 
    have the custody of the records of the Appellate Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    official seal of the Appellate Tribunal shall be kept in the custody of the 
    Registrar.  
 


    2[(4) Subject to any 
    general or special direction by the Presiding Officer, or in the temporary 
    absence of the Presiding Officer, the Member authorized under sub-rule (2) 
    of rule 5, the official seal of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be affixed 
    to any order, summons or other process save under the authority in writing 
    from the Registrar.]  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    official seal of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be affixed to any 
    certified copy issued by the Appellate Tribunal, save under the authority in 
    writing of the Registrar.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>26</number> Additional 
    functions and duties of Registrar.—In 
    addition to the functions and duties assigned in the rules, the Registrar 
    shall have the following functions and duties subject to any general or 
    special orders of the Presiding Officer or in his temporary absence, the 
    Member authorized under sub-rule (2) of rule 5, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    to receive all appeals, 
    replies and other documents;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    to decide all questions 
    arising out of the scrutiny of the appeal before they are registered;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    to require any appeal 
    presented to the Appellate Tribunal to be amended in accordance with the 
    rule;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    subject to the 
    directions of the Presiding Officer, or in his temporary absence, the Member 
    authorized under sub-rule (2) of rule 5,  to fix date of hearing of the 
    appeals or other proceedings and issue notices thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    to direct any formal 
    amendment of records;
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    to order grant of 
    copies of documents to parties to proceedings;
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    to grant leave to 
    inspect the record of the Appellate Tribunal;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>    to dispose of all 
    matters relating to the service of notices or other processes, application 
    for the issue of fresh notice or for extending the time for or ordering a 
    particular method of service on a respondent including a substituted service 
    by publication of the notice by way of advertisement in the newspapers; and
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>    for requisition of 
    records from the custody of any court or other authority.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Seal 
    and emblem.—The official seal and 
    emblem of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as Central Government may 
    specify.
  
 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Appeal 
    to Securities Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 2000
 

 
 

 
 



    Form
 


(See rule 4)
 



    Memorandum of Appeal
 


For use in Appellate Tribunal’s Office
 

 
 


Date of presentation in the Registry  
 


Date of receipt by post  
 


Registration Number  
 


Signature  
 


Registrar  
 


Before the Securities Appellate Tribunal  
 


In the matter of the Securities Contracts 
    (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956)
 


and
 


In the matter of appeal against the order made 
    on ................................. by ......................
 


A.B. 
    ................................................ Appellant
 


C.D. and other 
    ................................................ Respondent(s)
 


Details of appeal:
 


1.  Particulars of the appellant:
 


(i) Name of the appellant:  
 


(ii) Address of registered office of the 
    appellant:  
 


(iii) Address of service of all notices:  
 


(iv) Telephone/Fax Number and e-mail address, 
    if any:  
 


2.  Particulars of the respondent(s):  
 


(i) Name of the respondent(s):  
 


(ii) Office address(es) of the respondent(s):  
 


(iii) Address(es) of respondent(s) for service 
    of all notices:  
 


(iv) Telephone/Fax Number and e-mail address, 
    if any:  
 


3.  Jurisdiction of the Appellate 
    Tribunal.—The appellant declares that the matter of appeal falls within 
    the jurisdiction of the Appellate Tribunal.  
 


4.  Limitation.—The appellant 
    further declares that the appeal is within the limitation as prescribed in 
    section 22D of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956).  
 


5.  Facts of the case and the details 
    of the order against which appeal is filed:  
 


The facts of the case are given below:
 


      (Give here a 
    concise statement of facts and grounds of appeal against the specified order 
    in a chronological order, each paragraph containing as neatly as possible as 
    separate issue, fact or otherwise.)  
 


6.  Relief(s) sought.—In view of 
    the facts mentioned in Paragraph 5 above, the appellant prays for the 
    following relief(s) [Specify below the relief(s) sought explained the 
    grounds for relief(s) and the legal provisions, if any, relied upon].  
 


7.  Interim order, if prayed for.—Pending 
    final decision of the appeal the appellant seeks issue of the following 
    interim order:  
 


       (Give 
    here the nature of the interim order prayed for with reasons.)  
 


8.  Matter not pending with any other 
    court etc.—The appellant further declares that the matter regarding with 
    this appeal has been made is not pending before any court of law or any 
    other authority or any other Tribunal.  
 


9.  Particulars in respect of the fee 
    paid in terms of Rule 9 of these rules.—  
 


(1)  Amount of fees  
 


(2)  Name of the Bank on which Demand 
    Draft is drawn  
 


(3)  Demand Draft number  
 


10.  Details of Index.—An index 
    containing of details of the documents to be relied upon is enclosed.  
 


11.  List of enclosures.—
 


(Signature of the appellant/ 

    Authorised Representative)
 

 
 



Verification
 


I, 
    ................................................ (Name in block letters) 
    son/daughter/wife of ................................................ Shri 
    ................................................ being the appellant/Authorised 
    Representative of ................................................ (Name of 
    the appellant) do hereby verify that the contents of Paras 1 to 11 are true 
    to my personal knowledge and belief and that I have not suppressed any 
    material facts.
 

 
 


Signature of the appellant/ 

    Authorised Representative
 


Place ..............................
 


Date .............................
 

 
 


To
 


The Registrar
 



    ................................................
 



    ................................................
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    229(E), dated 11th April, 2005, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 11-4-2005). Clause 
    (b), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    559(E), dated 27th July, 2001, for clause (h), (w.e.f. 27-7-2001), clause 
    (h), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   
    Rule 3 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 655(E), dated 8th 
    August, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-8-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 655(E), dated 8th August, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-8-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   
    Rule 5 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st 
    January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   
    Subs. for “3” by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for sub-rule 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for sub-rule (1) &amp; 
    (2).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for sub-rule (1).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   
    Subs. for “three” by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   
    Ins. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   
    Subs. for rule 17 by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   
    Subs. for rule 18 by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for sub-rule (1).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for sub-rule (4).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   
    Subs. by  G.S.R. 54(E), dated 31st January, 2005 for rule 26.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>