<act><tid>204842</tid>
<title>THE BENGAL BONDED WAREHOUSE ASSOCIATION ACT, <year>1838</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1838</year>
[ 14th March, <year>1838</year>.]





<article><tid>916812</tid>
<number>1</number>Incorporation.-- It is hereby enacted, that the persons whose 
names appear in the Schedule No. 1, hereunto annexed, shall, from the 
 14th day of March, <year>1838</year>, form a corporate body for the Warehousing of 
Goods, either in bond or otherwise, by the name of the Bengal Bonded 
Warehouse Association.


</article>



<article><tid>554162</tid>
<number>2</number>Power to sue and be sued, and to acquire, hold and transfer 
property.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The said Association shall sue and be sued by its 
corporate name, and shall use such common seal as the Directors of the 
said Association shall from time to time appoint, and may acquire may 
hold absolutely, may hold by way of pledge, and may transfer, any 
description of property whatever.


</article>



<article><tid>684021</tid>
<number>3</number>Capital Stock and shares.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The sum of Rs. 10, 00, 000 
subscribed for the purpose of the said Association by the Persons 
hereby incorporated, shall be the Capital Stock of the said 
Association, and shall be divided into 2, 000 shares of 500 Rupees 
each, and every one of the persons hereby incorporated shall have one 
share of such Capital Stock for every 500 Rupees which such person 
shall have subscribed.


</article>



<article><tid>50220</tid>
<number>4</number>Registering of names of proprietors. Register to be open to 
inspection.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Directors of the said Association shall cause 
the names, additions, and places of residence of the proprietors of 
shares in the said Capital Stock, and the number of shares held by 
each proprietor, to be registered in a book, and the said shares shall 
in such book be numbered, beginning from No. 1, and such book shall 
be kept at the office of the said Association, and shall there be open 
to the inspection of all persons during the usual hours of business.


</article>



<article><tid>1441993</tid>
<number>5</number>Share- certificates.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> A certificate signed by three 
Directors of the said Association shall be delivered to every 
proprietor of the said Capital Stock, and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> it shall be at the 
option of every proprietor of several shares to receive one 
certificate for all the shares of such proprietor, or one certificate 
for each of those shares or several certificates, each of which may be 
for any number of those shares.


</article>



<article><tid>1973917</tid>
<number>6</number>Transfer of shares.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any share or shares of the said 
Capital Stock may be transferred by endorsement made on the 
certificate for such share or shares by the proprietor of such share 
or shares, or by the Attorney of such proprietor duly authorized 
thereunto; provided always, that such endorsement shall specify the 
name of the party to whom the transfer is made; and provided also that 
no such endorsement shall be effectual to transfer any such share or 
shares until such endorsement shall have been registered in a Register 
to be kept for that purpose at the office of the said Association, and 
until a note of such registration, and of the date thereof, shall have 
been made on the back of the indorsed certificate under the hand of an 
officer appointed for that purpose by the Directors of the said 
Association.


</article>



<article><tid>1761630</tid>
<number>7</number>Proprietors of shares to be members of Association.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
Every proprietor of a share of the said Capital Stock, who shall cease 
to be a proprietor of such Stock, shall cease to be a member of the 
corporation created by this Act; and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> every person who shall 
become a proprietor of the said Capital Stock, shall become a member 
of the corporation created by this Act; and shall, in respect of his 
share or shares of the said Capital Stock, be under the same 
liabilities under which an original proprietor of the said Capital 
Stock would be.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" omitted by Act 12 of 
<year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
2. The word" that" omitted by s. 2 and Sch. 1, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1449896</tid>
<number>8</number>First Directors of Association.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The business of the 
said Association shall be managed by six Directors, and Francis 
Macnaghten, Joseph Walker, Jasper Ouseley, Richard Howe Cockerell, 
Alexander Colvin, Joseph Willis, and James Church, Esquires, shall be 
the first Directors of the said Association.


</article>



<article><tid>1263536</tid>
<number>9</number>Removal and election of Directors.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every Director of 
the said Association may be removed by a general meeting of the 
proprietors, and every future Director of the said Association shall 
be elected by such a general meeting.


</article>



<article><tid>1835855</tid>
<number>10</number>Directors to go out by rotation.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> A rotation among the 
Directors of the said Association shall be settled by lot, so that two 
of the said Directors may go out of office on the Monday following the 
 15th day of May in every year, and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> on the Monday following the 
 15th day of May, in every year, a general meeting of proprietors shall 
be held, at which two Directors shall be chosen, and that no Director 
going out by such rotation shall be capable of being re- elected, till 
the Monday after the 15th of May in the year next following.


</article>



<article><tid>1904089</tid>
<number>11</number>Election of successor, when Director ceases to be so, 
otherwise than by rotation.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If any Director of the said 
Association shall cease to be a Director, otherwise than by the 
operation of the rule of rotation aforesaid, the Directors of the said 
Association shall, with all convenient speed after such public notice 
as is hereinafter directed, call an extraordinary general meeting of 
the proprietors for the purpose of choosing a successor and such 
successor shall come into the same place in the rotation aforesaid in 
which the Director whom he has succeeded was.




</article>



<article><tid>448053</tid>
<number>13</number>Directors to be residents of Bengal Presidency.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> No 
person shall be capable of being a Director of the said Association, 
unless he be resident within the Territories subject to the Presidency 
of Fort William in Bengal.




</article>



<article><tid>1660458</tid>
<number>15</number>Adjournment of ordinary meeting.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any ordinary general 
meetings of the said Association may adjourn itself to a future day, 
and may, on the day to which it shall have so adjourned itself, resume 
its proceedings, and transact any business which it would have been 
competent to transact on the day when it originally assembled.


</article>



<article><tid>653077</tid>
<number>16</number>Extraordinary general meetings.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Extraordinary general 
meetings of the said Association shall be held according to such rules 
as may be made for that purpose, in the Bye- laws of the said 
Association; provided always, that no such extraordinary general 
meeting shall be held without a previous notice of not less than 
fourteen days, which notice shall be published in not less than two 
newspapers printed at Calcutta.


</article>



<article><tid>1426942</tid>
<number>17</number>Voting at general meetings. Qualification for voting.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
At General Meetings of the Proprietors, every election and question 
shall be decided by a majority of votes; and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> no proprietor shall 
be allowed to vote unless he be possessed of two or more shares of the 
Capital Stock of the said Association, which shares shall have been 
registered in his name not less than three calendar months before.


</article>



<article><tid>610829</tid>
<number>18</number>Number of votes to which proprietors are entitled.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> At 
such general meetings, no proprietor shall have more than eight votes, 
and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the proprietors shall vote according to the following scale 
:- 
 2 Shares shall entitle to 1 vote. 
 4"""" 2 votes. 
 6"""" 3" 
 10"""" 4"
<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" omitted by Act 12 of 
<year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
2. The word" that" omitted by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 20 Shares shall entitle to 6 votes. 
 35,,,,,,,, 7" 
 50,,,,,,,, 8"



</article>



<article><tid>426661</tid>
<number>19</number>Votes of joint proprietors of shares.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If more persons 
than one, being partners in trade, shall be joint proprietors of two 
or more shares of the said Capital Stock, and shall agree to give a 
joint vote or joint votes, such joint vote or joint votes, shall be 
received in all respects as the vote or votes of a single proprietor 
would be received.


</article>



<article><tid>213639</tid>
<number>20</number>Voting by proxy.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every proprietor entitled to vote at 
any general meeting may give a proxy in writing, general or special, 
limited or unlimited, and singed by himself or by his attorney duly 
authorized thereunto, to any other proprietor; and 2 the proprietor to 
whom the proxy is given, may vote on behalf of the proprietor who had 
given the proxy, according to the terms of such proxy.


</article>



<article><tid>1168971</tid>
<number>21</number>Authority of Directors.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Directors of the said 
Association shall have authority to expend the money of the said 
Association for the purpose of purchasing and erecting warehouses, and 
of warehousing and bonding goods therein, and to make and fulfil 
contracts for the said purpose, and to appoint and remove such 
servants as may be necessary for the said purpose and generally to 
manage all the concerns of the said Association, subject to such rules 
as may be laid down in the Bye- laws of the said Association, and to 
keep the seal of the said Association, and to use the said seal in the 
affairs of the said Association, provided always, that the said seal 
shall never be affixed to any instrument except in the presence and by 
the consent of three Directors, who shall sign their names on every 
such instrument in token of their presence and consent.


</article>



<article><tid>1992244</tid>
<number>22</number>Calls for share money.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Directors of the said 
Association shall have authority to call on the proprietors to pay 
such instalment or instalments as shall, together with the instalments 
already paid, amount to a sum not exceeding 50 per cent. on each 
share; and 2 no further call shall be made, except in consequence of a 
vote of a general meeting of the proprietors, authorising such further 
call; provided always that no proprietor shall be called upon to pay 
more in proportion to his share in the Capital Stock than any other 
proprietor.


</article>



<article><tid>807105</tid>
<number>23</number>Interest to run on each call. Application of dividend in 
satisfaction of unpaid calls.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If any proprietor shall not pay 
any instalment which he is lawfully called upon to pay, in the manner 
described in the last section, on the day appointed for such payment, 
the said Association shall have a claim against such proprietor for 
interest on the deficient sum, after the rate of 10 per cent. per 
annum; and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> it shall be lawful for the Directors of the said 
Association to apply, in satisfaction of such instalment and of such 
interest, any dividend due to such proprietor, placing every dividend 
so applied to the credit of such proprietor with the said Association.


</article>



<article><tid>1781767</tid>
<number>24</number>Power to refuse to register transfer by defaulting 
proprietor. Power to sell shares to satisfy calls, and issue fresh 
certificates.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It shall be lawful for the Directors of the said 
Association to refuse to register the transfer of any share belonging 
to any proprietor who shall not have paid such instalment and interest 
as aforesaid; and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in case such instalment and interest shall not 
be paid within two months after notice to pay the same has been given 
by lawful for the said Directors to such proprietor, or to his 
attorney or attorneys duly authorised, it shall be lawful for the said 
Directors to sell by public sale the share or shares of such 
proprietor, to such an extent as may be sufficient to satisfy such 
instalment and interest, and to grant, upon such sale, a new 
certificate or new certificates to the purchaser of such share or 
shares whereupon the former certificate or certificates for such share 
or shares shall become void, and if there by any surplus after such 
instalment and interest have been satisfied, such surplus shall be 
paid on demand to the proprietor of such share or shares, and shall, 
till demand, be credited in the books of the said Association to such 
proprietor, but no interest shall run thereon.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" omitted by Act 12 of 
<year>1891</year> s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" that" omitted by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1380441</tid>
<number>25</number>Extension of Act No. 25 of <year>1836</year> to warehouse of Association.- 
- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All the provisions of 2 Act No. XXV of <year>1836</year>, of the Governor 
General of India in Council, relating to private licensed Warehouses, 
shall be applicable to all Warehouses wherein the said Association 
shall receive bonded Goods.


</article>



<article><tid>119047</tid>
<number>26</number>Power to give general security for payment of import and 
export duties.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It shall be lawful for the said Association to 
give general security, by bond, under the seal of the said 
Association, for payment of the full duties of importation on Goods, 
lodged in any Warehouse of the said Association, or for the due 
exportation of such Goods; and if the said Association shall give such 
bond, no security shall be required from any other party to the same 
effect.


</article>



<article><tid>860647</tid>
<number>27</number>Rates for warehousing.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Directors of the said 
Association shall, from time to time, fix the rates at which the said 
Association will warehouse Goods and receive Goods at its Wharfs, and 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a table of such rates shall be placed at every Warehouse and 
Wharf of the said Association.


</article>



<article><tid>1873646</tid>
<number>28</number>Certificates of deposit, transferable by endorsement.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
As often as any Goods are lodged in any Warehouse of the said 
Association, the Secretary of the said Association shall deliver a 
warrant signed by him as such Secretary, to the person lodging such 
Goods, which warrant shall be, as nearly as possible, in the form set 
forth in Schedule II annexed to this Act, and such warrant shall be 
transferable by endorsement, and shall entitle any person to whom it 
may have been so transferred by endorsement, to receive the Goods 
specified in such warrant on the same terms on which the person who 
originally lodged those Goods would have been entitled to receive the 
same.


</article>



<article><tid>1029520</tid>
<number>29</number>Suits against Association.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All suits brought against 
the said Association shall be brought in the Supreme Court of 
Judicature at Fort William in Bengal and not elsewhere.


</article>



<article><tid>5254</tid>
<number>30</number>Joint Stock of Association.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All the Joint Stock of the 
said Association of what kind or description soever, and all the Land, 
Warehouses, Messuages, Tenements, Hereditaments, Premises and Property 
acquired therewith, of which the said Association shall become in any 
manner possessed, entitled to, or interested in, shall be held and 
enjoyed by the Proprietors thereof, and their successors respectively, 
as Personal Estate, or as in the nature of Chattel Interests, and not 
as, or in the nature of, Real Estate.


</article>



<article><tid>1275525</tid>
<number>31</number>Individual members not to be liable.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In order to 
define the liability of Proprietors or shares, and to save harmless 
themselves and their respective Heirs, Executors, Administrators, 
Representatives and Assigns, no Proprietor, his Heirs, Executors, 
Administrators, Representatives or Assigns, shall be personally liable 
to any person or persons whatsoever by reason of being a Proprietor in 
any event, or for or on account of any acts, deeds, contracts or 
liabilities of the said Association, or of the Directors or Secretary 
thereof respectively, or under or by virtue of any judgment or decree 
in any action or suit, but <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the party or parties having any legal 
or equitable demand or claim for or on the account last aforesaid, or 
having obtained such judgment or decree as last aforesaid, shall and 
may only recover the amount of such demand, claim, judgment or decree 
from and out of or to the whole extent of the paid up Capital, 
accumulated Funds, Lands, Messuages, Tenements, Hereditaments and 
Premises whatsoever and wheresoever, which may at the time belong to 
the said Association, or to which they may at the time be entitled.




</article>



<article><tid>757705</tid>
<number>33</number>Increase of Capital Stock.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It shall be lawful for the 
said Association to increase its Capital Stock; provided always that 
no such increase shall take place unless it be authorized by a vote of 
two extraordinary general meetings of Proprietors specially convened 
for that purpose, of which meetings the second shall be held not less 
than three calendar months after the first.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" omitted by Act 12 of 
<year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I,

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1873</year> (12 of <year>1873</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The word" that" omitted by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>510768</tid>
<number>34</number>Option to original proprietors to subscribe in first 
instance.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In the event of such increase, the Proprietors of 
the original Stock shall not be bound to subscribe, but shall in the 
first instance have the option of subscribing for the increased 
Capital Stock in proportion to the share which each has of the 
original Capital Stock; and so much of the additional Capital Stock as 
shall not be subscribed for by the said Proprietors of the original 
stock, within one year after the passing of the final resolution for 
the increase, shall be open to the public, and be sold, for the 
benefit of the said Association, by public sale.


</article>



<article><tid>998430</tid>
<number>35</number>Provisions of Act to apply to additional Stock.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All 
the rules laid down in this Act respecting the original Capital Stock 
of the said Association, shall be applicable to any additional Stock 
which may be subscribed in the manner hereinbefore described.


</article>



<article><tid>893561</tid>
<number>36</number>East India Company to have right of pre- emption.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If 
the said Association shall be desirous to dispose of any premises 
purchased by the said Association from the East India Company, the 
said East India Company shall have the right of pre- emption, and the 
price shall be fixed by two appraisers, the one named on the part of 
the said East India Company, and the other by the Directors of the 
said Association; and if the said appraisers shall not agree on a 
price, the price shall be fixed by an umpire named by the said 
appraisers.




</article>



<article><tid>1898082</tid>
<number>38</number>Dissolution of Association by resolution of proprietors.-- 1 
The said Association may at any time be dissolved by a resolution 
to that effect of two- thirds in number and value of the proprietors 
qualified to vote at two successive extraordinary meetings specially 
called for the purpose of taking into consideration the expediency of 
such dissolution; provided that not less than three months shall have 
elapsed between the first and second of such two extraordinary 
meetings.


</article>



<article><tid>1949021</tid>
<number>39</number>Division of property on dissolution.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Whenever the 
dissolution of the said Association shall be ordered either by the 2 
[ Central Government], or by a vote of the said Association, the 
Directors of the said Association shall cause all the property of the 
said Association to be converted into money, and shall divide whatever 
surplus may remain after satisfying the debts of the said Association 
among the proprietors in proportion to the shares which the 
proprietors have in the Capital Stock of the said Association; and 
after such distribution the said Association shall forthwith be 
dissolved.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" omitted by Act 12 of 
<year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I,

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Governor General of India in 
Council".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>