<act><tid>166920</tid>
<title>THE MANIPUR PANCHAYATI RAJ (As Passed by the Houses of Parliament)</title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1994</year>.
[ 23th April, <year>1994</year>]

An Act to provide for the constitution and organisation of Panchayats 
as units oflocal self- Government in the rural areas of Manipur and for 
matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.

WHEREAS it is expedient to reorganise Panchayats in rural areas 
of Manipur by comprehensive enactment to establish a two- tier 
Panchayati Raj system in the State with elected bodies at the Gram and 
District levels, in keeping with the Constitutional provisions 
relating to Panchayats for greater participation of the people and 
more effective implementation of rural development programmes.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1324962</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>161972</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Manipur Panchayati Raj Act, <year>1994</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>948983</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the State of Manipur excepting any 
area to which the Manipur (Hill Areas) District Council Act, <year>1971</year> 
 (Manipur Act 76 of <year>1971</year>.) or the Manipur (Village Authorities in Hill  
  Areas) Act <year>1956</year> (Manipur Act 80 of <year>1956</year>) extends, or which has been or 
may hereafter be declared as, or included in, a municipality under any 
law for the time being in force, or which has been or may hereafter be 
declared as, or included in a cantonment under the Cantonment Act, 
<year>1924</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1458126</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, 
by Notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates 
may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 23. 4. <year>1994</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 328 (E), dt. 23. 4. <year>1994</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98474</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1563593</tid>
<number>a</number>" Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha" means an Adhyaksha and a 
Up- Adhyakhsa of a Zilla Parishad elected under section 54 of 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1364836</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairperson" means Chairperson of a Standing Committee 
of a Zilla Parishad or a Gram Panchayat, as the case may be, 
constituted under the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>801864</tid>
<number>c</number>" Chief Executive Officer" means the Chief Executive 
Officer of a Zilla Parishad appointed under section 75 of 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>783321</tid>
<number>d</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of the Government 
in the Development and Panchayati Raj or such other person as 
may be appointed by the State Government to exercise the 
powers of a Commissioner under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>328483</tid>
<number>e</number>" district" means the revenue district;

</section>

<section><tid>1348068</tid>
<number>f</number>" Deputy Commissioner" means the Deputy Commissioner of 
District;

</section>

<section><tid>323221</tid>
<number>g</number>" Government" means the State Government of Manipur;

</section>

<section><tid>586981</tid>
<number>h</number>" Gram Sabha" means a body consisting of persons 
registered in the electoral rolls relating to a village 
comprised within the area of the Panchayat at the village 
level;

</section>

<section><tid>1292380</tid>
<number>i</number>" Gram Panchayat" means the Gram Panchayat Constituted 
under the Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1176415</tid>
<number>j</number>" Official Gazette" means the Manipur Gazette,

</section>

<section><tid>553191</tid>
<number>k</number>" Panchayat" means a Gram Panchayat and a Zilla Paris ad 
constituted under the provision of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>148322</tid>
<number>l</number>" Panchayat area" means the territorial area of a 
Panchayat;

</section>

<section><tid>1315514</tid>
<number>m</number>" population" means the population is ascertained at the 
last preceding census of which the relevant figures have beep 
published,

</section>

<section><tid>23719</tid>
<number>n</number>" Pradhan" means a Pradhan of a Gram Panchayat elected 
under section 21 of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1586369</tid>
<number>o</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under the 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1878766</tid>
<number>p</number>" Secretary" means the Secretary of a Gram Panchayat 
appointed under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1575142</tid>
<number>q</number>" Standing Committee" means a Standing Committee 
constituted by a Zilla Parishad or a Gram Panchayat under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1379669</tid>
<number>r</number>" Up- Pradhan" means a Up- Pradhan of a Gram Panchayat 
elected under section 24 of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>61535</tid>
<number>s</number>" village" means a village, specified by the Governor 
by, public notification to be a village for the purpose of 
this Act and includes a group of villages so specified and

</section>

<section><tid>606495</tid>
<number>t</number>" Zilla Parishad" means a Zilla Parishad of a district 
constituted under section 48 of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

GRAM SABHA

CHAPTER II

GRAM SABHA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>599261</tid>
<number> 3</number> Membership of Gram Sabha and disqualification.-
<section><tid>170792</tid>
<number>1</number>A Gram  
Sabha shall, subject to sub- section (2), consist of persons whose 
names are included in electoral rolls referred to in section 15 within 
the area of the Gram Sabha:
Provided that no person shall be a member of more than one Gram 
Sabha.


</section>

<section><tid>1644126</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall be disqualified for being a member of the 
Gram Sabha, if-

<subsection><tid>695155</tid>
<number>a</number>he is not a citizen of India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>271009</tid>
<number>b</number>he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a 
competent court' or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>331440</tid>
<number>c</number>he is for the time being disqualified from voting 
under the provision of any law relating to corrupt practices 
and other offence in connection with election to State 
Legislature.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>25795</tid>
<number> 4</number> Cessation of membership.-
<section><tid>1004087</tid>
<number>1</number>A member of Gram Sabha shall  
cease to be a member, if he has ceased to be ordinarily resident 
within the Gram Sabha area.

</section>

<section><tid>440677</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person ceases to be a member of Gram Sabha under 
sub- section (1) he shall also cease to hold any office to which he may 
have been elected, or appointed by virtue of being a member thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414279</tid>
<number>5</number>Periodicity of meetings.- The Gram Sabha shall meet from time 
to time but six month shall not intervene between any two meetings.


</article>



<article><tid>76707</tid>
<number>6</number>Periodicity of meetings. The meeting of the Gram Sabha shall 
be held in accordance with such procedure as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>935185</tid>
<number> 7</number> Quorum.-
<section><tid>327164</tid>
<number>1</number>The quorum for a meeting of the Gram Sabha shall  
be one- tenth of its total membership.

</section>

<section><tid>1334947</tid>
<number>2</number>If at the time appointed for the meeting, a quorum is not 
present, the person presiding shall wait for thirty minutes, and if 
within such period, there is no quorum, the person presiding shall 
adjourn the meeting to the same time on the same day in the following 
week. He shall similarly, after waiting for thirty minutes, adjourn 
the meeting if at any time after it has begun, attention is drawn to 
the want of a quorum. A notice of the meeting so fixed shall be 
posted in the office of the Gram Panchayat. The business which could 
not be considered at the meeting so postponed for want of quorum, 
shall be brought before and disposed of at the meeting so fixed or at 
any subsequent adjourned meeting at which there is a quorum.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>564135</tid>
<number>8</number>Gram Sabha meetings.- Every meeting of the Gram Sabha shall be 
presided over by the Pradhan of the concerned Gram Panchayat and in 
his absence, by the Up- Pradhan, and in the absence of both by member 
of the Gram Panchayat to be chosen from amongst the members of the 
Panchayat.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1622892</tid>
<number> 9</number> Agenda. The Gram Panchayat shall prepare the agenda for 
discussion of the Gram Sabha, such matters shall relate to the 
following, namely:-
<section><tid>1097755</tid>
<number>a</number>the annual statement of accounts of the Gram Panchayat, 
the report of administration of the preceding financial year 
and the last audit note and replies if any, made thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1875095</tid>
<number>b</number>the budget of the Gram Panchayat for the next financial 
year; and

</section>

<section><tid>1200413</tid>
<number>c</number>the report in respect of development programmes of the 
Gram Panchayat relating to the preceding year and development 
programmes proposed to be undertaken during the current year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1212305</tid>
<number>10</number>Resolution.- Any resolution relating to the functions 
entrusted to the Gram Sabha under section 11, shall have to be passed 
by a majority of votes of the members present and voting in the 
meeting of the Gram Sabha.


</article>



<article><tid>803258</tid>
<number> 11</number> Functions of Gram Sabha.- A Gram Sabha shall exercise the 
following functions, namely:-
<section><tid>1698414</tid>
<number>a</number>rendering assistance in the implementation of development 
schemes pertaining to the village;

</section>

<section><tid>1790912</tid>
<number>b</number>identification of beneficiaries for the implementation 
of development schemes pertaining to the village:
Provided that in case the Gram Sabha fails to identify the 
beneficiaries within a reasonable time the Gram Panchayat can 
identify the beneficiaries;


</section>

<section><tid>1763523</tid>
<number>c</number>mobilising voluntary labour and contributions in kind 
or cash or both for the community welfare programmes;

</section>

<section><tid>681506</tid>
<number>d</number>to promote adult education and family welfare within 
the village;

</section>

<section><tid>848866</tid>
<number>e</number>promotion of unity and harmony among all sections of 
society in the village;

</section>

<section><tid>883242</tid>
<number>f</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1658146</tid>
<number>12</number>Vigilance Committee.- The Gram Sabha may also form one or more 
Vigilance Committees consisting of persons, who are not members of the 
Gram Panchayat to supervise the Gram Panchayat works, schemes and 
other activities and to put up reports concerning them in its meeting.
CHAP

GRAM PANCHAYATS

CHAPTER III

GRAM PANCHAYATS



</article>



<article><tid>124172</tid>
<number> 13</number> Constitution of Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1883404</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
constituted a Gram Panchayat for every Gram Sabha.

</section>

<section><tid>1133486</tid>
<number>2</number>The Gram Panchayat constituted under sub- section (1) shall 
be notified in the Official Gazette and shall be deemed to have 
been constituted from the date of its first meeting.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>148039</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person shall be entitled to be included in the list Of 
electors of Gram Panchayat if he is not less than eighteen years of 
age on the date of its publication under sub- section (1) and is 
ordinarily resident within the area of the Gram Panchayat:
Provided that no person shall be entitled to be included in the 
list of the electors of any Gram Panchayat for more than one Gram Pan- 
chayat and no person shall be entitled to be included in the electoral 
roll of any Gram Panchayat for more than once:

Provided further that if the applicant is included in the 
electoral roll of any other Gram Panchayat, the officer who includes 
his name shall inform the officer publishing the electoral roll of 
that other Gram Panchayat and that the other officer shall, on receipt 
of the information, strike off the applicant' s name from that list.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub- section, the expression 
" ordinarily resident" shall have the same meaning as has been given in 
section 20 of the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (47 of  
  <year>1950</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>367615</tid>
<number>4</number>The name of any person included in the list of electors who 
becomes disqualified at any time after his name was entered in the 
list, shall forthwith be struck- off from the list in which it is 
included:.
Provided that the name of any person struck- off from the 
electoral roll by reason of disqualification under clause (c) of sub- 
section (2) of section 3 shall forthwith be reinstated if such person 
ceases to' become disqualified.


</section>

<section><tid>673054</tid>
<number>5</number>An appeal shall be made within such time and in such manner 
and to such authority as may be prescribed against any order Passed 
under sub- sections (2) and (4).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975168</tid>
<number>14</number>Incorporation of Gram roll of Panchayat.- Every Gram Panchayat 
shall, by the name notified in the Official Gazette under section 13, 
be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a, common seal 
with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to enter into 
contracts, and shall. by the said name sue and be sued.


</article>



<article><tid>1044223</tid>
<number>15</number>Electoral roll of Gram Panchayat.- The electoral roll of the 
Manipur Assembly prepared under the provision of the Representation of 
the Peopel Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>) and as in force on such date as 
the State Government may, by general or special order, notify in this 
behalf for such part of the constituency of the Assembly as is 
included in the Gram Sabha. shall be' the list of electors for such 
Gram Panchayat.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>834448</tid>
<number> 16</number> Publication of Electoral roll of Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1684758</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
list of electors referred to in section 15 shall be published in such 
manner and by such authority as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1095674</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person whose name is not included in the list of 
electors published under sub- section (1) may apply within ten days 
from its publication to the officer publishing the same for inclusion 
of his name therein and officer concerned shall, if he is satisfied 
that the applicant fulfils the condition mentioned in sub- section (3) 
and is not disqualified from being included in the list of electors 
under section 151 after making such inquiry as may be prescribed, 
direct his name to be included in the list of electors.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1461258</tid>
<number>17</number>Composition of Gram Panchayat.- A Gram Panchayat shall consist 
of the Pradhan and such number of directly elected members as may be 
notified from time to time by the State Government and one member for 
every 350 population or part thereof of the Panchayat area shall be 
elected as a member of such Panchayat.


</article>



<article><tid>757861</tid>
<number> 18</number> Division of Gram Sabha into territorial constituencies.-
<section><tid>841335</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Deputy Commissioner shall, for the conduct of the election,

<subsection><tid>1192492</tid>
<number>i</number>divide the area of the Gram Sabha into territorial 
constituencies in such manner that the ratio between the 
population of each constituency and the number of seats 
allotted to it shall, as far as practicable, be the same 
throughout the Gram Sabha area;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1939785</tid>
<number>ii</number>determine the number of seats allotted to each 
constituency.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>105967</tid>
<number>2</number>One member from each territorial constituency shall be 
elected by direct election to the Gram Panchayat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1548597</tid>
<number> 19</number> Reservation of seats.-
<section><tid>740885</tid>
<number>1</number>Seats shall be reserved for  
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in every Gram Panchayat, and the 
number of seats so reserved shall bear, as nearly as may be, the same 
proportion to the total number of seats to be filled by direct 
election in that Panchayat as the population of Scheduled Castes or of 
the Scheduled Tribes in that Panchayat area bears to the total 
population of that area and such seats shall be allotted by rotation 
to different constituencies in such Gram Panchayat, in such manner as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1359871</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than one- third of the total number of seats 
reserved under sub- section (1) shall be reserved for women belonging 
to Scheduled Castes, or as the case may be, the Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

<section><tid>65398</tid>
<number>3</number>Not less than one- third (including the number of seats  
reserved for women belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
  Tribes) of the total number of seats to be filled by direct election 
in every Gram Panchayat shall be reserved for women and such seats may 
be allotted by rotation to different constituencies in a Gram 
Panchayat in such manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1850886</tid>
<number> 20</number> Term of the Gram Panchayats.-
<section><tid>167910</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Gram Panchayat, shall  
continue for a term of five years from the date appointed for its 
first meeting and no longer:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that a Gram Panchayat which is functioning 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall continue 
till the expiration of its duration.


</section>

<section><tid>707497</tid>
<number>2</number>The election to constitute a Gram, Panchayat shall be 
completed-

<subsection><tid>1097083</tid>
<number>a</number>before the expiration of its duration specified in sub- 
section (1); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1710936</tid>
<number>b</number>in case of dissolution, before the expiration of a 
period of six months from the date of dissolution:
Provided that where the remainder of the period for which the dis- 
solved Gram Panchayat would have continued is less than six months, it 
shall not be necessary to hold any election under this clause for con- 
stituting the Gram Panchayat for such period.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>183010</tid>
<number>3</number>A Gram Panchayat constituted upon the dissolution of a Gram 
Panchayat before the expiration of its duration, shall continue only 
for the remainder of the period for which the dissolved Gram Panchayat 
would have continued under subsection (1) had it not been so 
dissolved.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1954546</tid>
<number>21</number>Election of the Pradhan and members of Gram Panchayat.- The 
Pradhan and members of the Gram Panchayat shall be elected by direct 
election under secret ballot by the members of the Gram Sabha from 
amongst themselves in such manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>562972</tid>
<number> 22</number> Appointment of an Administrative Committee or Administrator on 
failure to elect members of Gram Panchayat and in other cases.-
<section><tid>1400365</tid>
<number>1</number>

<subsection><tid>1213911</tid>
<number>a</number>If the Deputy Commissioner is satisfied that a Gram Panchayat for 
a village or group of villages immediately after the establishment 
of such Gram Panchayat cannot be constituted by reason of-

<subsubsection><tid>74471</tid>
<number>i</number>any difficulty in holding an election of the members of 
the Gram Panchayat; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>349407</tid>
<number>ii</number>failure to elect such members at two successive 
elections held under section 17; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1447683</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other sufficient reason whatsoever.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>940139</tid>
<number>b</number>If at any general election to a Gram Panchayat, no member is 
elected or less than two- third of the total number of members are 
elected. the Deputy Commissioner shall, by notification either,-

<subsubsection><tid>2157</tid>
<number>i</number>appoint an Administrative Committee consisting of 
persons qualified to be elected, the number of such persons 
being equal to the number of members determined under section 
17; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>899402</tid>
<number>ii</number>appoint an Administrator.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1659244</tid>
<number>2</number>The members of the Administrative Committee or the 
Administrator shall hold office for such period not exceeding six 
months as the Deputy Commissioner may specify in the notification 
under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>484052</tid>
<number>3</number>On the appointment of an Administrative Committee or an 
Administrator under sub- section (1), the persons, if any, chosen as 
members of the' Gram Panchayat before such appointment shall cease to 
be members of the Gram Panchayat and all the powers and duties of the 
Gram Panchayat shall be exercised and performed by such Administrative 
Committee or Administrator, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1418740</tid>
<number>4</number>The Administrative Committee or Administrator shall be 
deemed to be a duly constituted Gram Panchayat for the purpose of this 
Act, notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions:
Provided that if at any time after the appointment of the 
Administrative Committee or the Administrator under sub- section (1), 
the Deputy Commissioner is satisfied that there is no difficulty in 
duly constituting the Gram Panchayat by election of members, the 
Deputy Commissioner, may, notwithstanding that the term of office for 
which the members of the Administrative Committee or the Administrator 
had been appointed has not expired, direct by notification that the 
members of the Administrative Committee or the Administrator, as the 
case may be, shall cease to hold office with effect from such date as 
may be specified in such notification.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>244059</tid>
<number> 23</number> Filling of casual vacancy in the office of Pradhan and of the 
member.-
<section><tid>487152</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of occurrence of any vacancy by reason of  
death, resignation, removal or otherwise in the office of Pradhan or 
of a member of a Gram Panchayat, the vacancy shall be filled by 
election in the manner prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>454383</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Pradhan and every Member elected to fill a casual 
vacancy, shall hold office for the remaining term of office of the 
person in whose place he is so elected.
Provided that no election for filling, the casual vacancy shall 
be held if the. vacancy is for a period of less- than six months.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1035092</tid>
<number> 24</number> Election of Up- Pradhan.-
<section><tid>363868</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Gram Panchayat shall, as  
soon as may be, elect one of its members to be Up- Pradhan.

</section>

<section><tid>521971</tid>
<number>2</number>In the event of occurrence of any vacancy by reason of 
death, resignation, removal or otherwise in the office of Up- Pradhan, 
the Gram Panchayat shall elect another member to be the Up- Pradhan:
Provided that no election shall be held if the vacancy is for a. 
period of less than six months.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1609547</tid>
<number> 25</number> Reservation of seats for Pradhan and Up- Pradhan.- Subject to 
the general or special order of the Government, the Deputy 
Commissioner shall, reserve-
<section><tid>1321138</tid>
<number>i</number>such number of offices of Pradhan and Up- Pradhan of 
Grain Panchayat in the district for the Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes as nearly as may be, in the same proportion 
as the total number of offices in the district bears to the 
population of the Scheduled Castes or, of the Scheduled 
Tribes in the district bears to the total population of that 
district;

</section>

<section><tid>354255</tid>
<number>ii</number>not less than one- third of the total number of offices 
of Pradhan and Up- Pradhan, as the case may be, of the Gram 
Panchayat in the district shall be reserved for women:
Provided that the offices reserved under this section shall be 
allotted by rotation to different Gram Panchayats in such manner as 
may be prescribed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1342739</tid>
<number>26</number>Procedure for election of Up- Pradhan on the establishment of 
Gram Panchayat.- On the establishment of Gram Panchayat for the first 
time under this Act, or on its reconstitution or establishment under 
section 20, a meeting of the Gram Panchayat shall be called 
immediately by the prescribed officer who shall himself preside over 
the meeting, but shall have no right to vote, and in such meeting, the 
Up- Pradhan shall be elected.


</article>



<article><tid>1171307</tid>
<number> 27</number> Term of the office of the Pradhan and Up- Pradhan.-
<section><tid>1379544</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
term of office of every Pradhan and Up- Pradhan of the Gram 
Panchayat shall, save as otherwise provided in this Act, cease on the 
expiry of the term of the Gram Panchayat.

</section>

<section><tid>1633154</tid>
<number>2</number>Pradhan and Up- Pradhan shall be entitled to such honoraria 
and other allowances, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1194355</tid>
<number>3</number>Every member of the Gram Panchayat shall be entitled to 
receive such honoraria and allowances as may be fixed by the 
Government from time to time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>467625</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power functions and duties of Pradhan and up- Pradhan.-
<section><tid>1611232</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Pradhan shall-

<subsection><tid>630399</tid>
<number>a</number>be responsible for convening the meeting of Gram Sabha 
and preside over its meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1975112</tid>
<number>b</number>be responsible for convening the meeting of Gram 
Panchayat and shall preside over its meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169311</tid>
<number>c</number>be responsible for the maintenance of the records of 
the Gram Panchayat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>583453</tid>
<number>d</number>have the general responsibility for the financial and 
executive administration of the Gram Panchayat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>723264</tid>
<number>e</number>exercise administrative supervision and control over 
the work of the staff of the Gram Panchayat and the officers 
and employees whose services may be plated at the disposal of 
the Gram Panchayat by any other authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30023</tid>
<number>f</number>for the transaction of business connected with this Act, 
or for the purpose of making any order authorised thereby, 
exercise such powers, perform such functions and discharge 
such duties as may be exercised, performed or discharged by 
the Gram Panchayat under this Act or the rules made 
thereunder:
Provided that the Pradhan shall not exercise such powers, 
perform such functions or discharge such duties as may be 
required by the rules made under this Act to be exercised, 
performed or discharged by the Gram Panchayat at a meeting; 
and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>677954</tid>
<number>g</number>exercise such other powers, perform such other 
functions and discharge such other duties as the Gram 
Panchayat may, by general or special resolution direct or as 
the Government may by rules made in this behalf, prescribe.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1722768</tid>
<number>2</number>The Up- Pradhan shall-

<subsection><tid>1913998</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise such of the powers, perform such of the 
functions and discharge such of the duties of Pradhan as the 
Pradhan may from time to time, subject to rules made in this 
behalf by the Government, delegate to him by order in 
writing:
Provided that the Pradhan may at any time withdraw all or 
any of the powers, functions and duties so delegated to the 
Up- Pradhan;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>762575</tid>
<number>b</number>during the absence of the Pradhan, exercise all the 
powers, perform all the functions and discharge all the 
duties of the Pradhan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>907150</tid>
<number>c</number>exercise such other powers, perform such other 
functions and discharge such other duties as the Gram 
Panchayat may, by general or special resolution, direct or as 
the Government may, by rules made in this behalf, prescribe.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>188474</tid>
<number> 29</number> Resignation of Pradhan and Up- Pradhan.-
<section><tid>1409217</tid>
<number>1</number>The Pradhan and  
the Up- Pradhan, as the case may be, may resign his office by writing 
under his hand addressed to the prescribed authority.

</section>

<section><tid>375137</tid>
<number>2</number>Every resignation under sub- section (1) shall take effect on 
the expiry of fifteen days from the date of its receipt by the 
prescribed authority, unless within this period of fifteen days he 
withdraws such resignation by writing under his hand addressed to the 
prescribed authority.

</section>

<section><tid>901229</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Up- Pradhan shall vacate the office if he ceases to be 
a member of a Gram Panchayat.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1333412</tid>
<number> 30</number> No confidence motion against the Pradhan and Up- Pradhan.- (i) 
Every, Pradhan and every Up- Pradhan shall be deemed to have vacated 
his office forthwith if a resolution expressing want of confidence in 
him is passed by a majority of not less than two- third of the members 
of the Gram Panchayat present and voting, at a meeting specially 
convened for the purpose. The requisition for such a special meeting 
shall be signed by not less than half of the total number of members 
of the Gram Panchayat and shall be delivered to the prescribed 
authority. The prescribed authority shall within seven days from the 
date of the receipt of the requisition, convene a special meeting of 
the Gram Panchayat. The meeting shall be held on a day not later than 
fifteen days from the date of issue of the notice of the meeting. The, 
meeting shall be presided over by the prescribed authority. In the 
initial two years of their term as Pradhan and Up- Pradhan of a Gram 
Panchayat on such motion of no confidence shall be moved against 
them. If the motion of no confidence is once rejected, no fresh motion 
of no confidence shall be brought before the Gram Panchayat within a 
period of one year from the date of such rejection of the motion.
<section><tid>1221907</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions under this Act, a 
Pradhan and Up- Pradhan may be removed from office by the Government 
for misconduct in the discharge of his duties or neglect or, 
incapacity to perform his duties or for being persistently remiss in 
the discharge thereof, or guilty of any disgraceful conduct:
Provided that, no such Pradhan, or Up- Pradhan be removed from 
office unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity to defend 
himself.


</section>

<section><tid>1492173</tid>
<number>3</number>The Pradhan or Up- Pradhan removed under sub- section (2) 
shall not be eligible for re- election as Pradhan or Up- Pradhan during 
the remaining term of office.

</section>

<section><tid>1886859</tid>
<number>4</number>A Pradhan or Up- Pradhan removed from his office under sub- 
section (2) shall cease to be a member of the Gram Panchayat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>507762</tid>
<number>31</number>Resignation of members.- A member of a Gram Panchayat may 
resign his membership in writing under his hand addressed to the 
Pradhan of the Gram Panchayat and his seat shall become vacant on the 
expiry of fifteen clear days from the date of such resignation unless 
within the said period of fifteen days, he withdraws such resignation 
by writing under his hand addressed to the Pradhan.


</article>



<article><tid>1516359</tid>
<number> 32</number> Meeting of Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1118199</tid>
<number>1</number>A Gram Panchayat shall meet  
for the transaction of business at least once in two months at the 
office of the Gram Panchayat and at such time as the Pradhan may 
determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1333505</tid>
<number>2</number>The Pradhan may, whenever he thinks fit, and shall, upon the 
written request of not less than one- third of the total number of 
members and on a date within fifteen days from the receipt of such 
request, call a special meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>358465</tid>
<number>3</number>Seven clear days' notice of an ordinary meeting and three 
clear days' notice of a special meeting specifying the place, date and 
time of such meeting and business to be transacted thereat, shall be 
given by the Secretary to the members and such officers as the 
Government may prescribe, and affixed on the notice. board of the Gram 
Panchayat.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>856066</tid>
<number>4</number>The officers to whom notice is given under sub- section (3) 
and other Government officers having jurisdiction over the Gram 
Panchayat area or any part thereof shall be entitled to attend every 
meeting of Gram Panchayat and take part in the proceedings but shall 
not be entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>221176</tid>
<number>5</number>If the Pradhan fails to call a special meeting as provided 
in sub- section (2), the Up- Pradhan or, in his absence, one- third of 
the total number of members may call such a meeting for a day not more 
than fifteen days thereafter and require the Secretary to give notice 
to the members and to take such action as may be necessary to convene 
the meeting.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1634876</tid>
<number> 33</number> Minutes.-
<section><tid>1661372</tid>
<number>1</number>Minutes shall be kept of the names of the  
members and of the officers, if any, present, and of the proceedings 
at each meeting of the Gram Panchayat and if any member present at the 
meeting so desires, of the names of the member voting respectively for 
or against any resolution, in a book to be provided for the purpose 
and after they are read over and agreed to, shall be signed by the 
Pradhan and Up- Pradhan or person presiding at such meeting, and shall 
at ail reasonable times be open to inspection by any member of the, 
Gram Panchayat. Any person may inspect the copy of minutes of the 
meeting. The minutes books shall always be kept in the office of the 
Gram Panchayat, and shall be in the custody of the Secretary of the 
Gram Panchayat.

</section>

<section><tid>1405353</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of every resolution passed by the Gram Panchayat 
shall within ten days from the date of meeting, be forwarded by the 
Secretary to the Chief Executive Officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>314976</tid>
<number> 34</number> Quorum and procedure.-
<section><tid>954497</tid>
<number>1</number>The quorum for a meeting of the  
Gram Panchayat shall be one- half of the total number of members. If, 
at the time appointed for the meeting, a quorum is not present, the 
presiding authority shall wait for thirty minutes, and if within such 
period there is no quorum, the presiding authority shall adjourn the 
meeting to such time on the following day or such future day as he may 
fix. He shall, similarly, after waiting for thirty minutes adjourn 
the meeting if, at any time, after it has begun, attention is drawn to 
the want of a quorum. A notice of the meeting so fixed shall be 
pasted in the office of the Gram Panchayat. The business which could 
not be considered at the meeting so postponed for want of quorum, 
shall be brought before and disposed of at the meeting so fixed or at 
any subsequent adjourned meeting at which there is a quorum.

</section>

<section><tid>1264530</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided by or under this Act, at every 
meeting of Gram Panchayat, the Pradhan or in his absence the Up- 
Pradhan shall preside, and in the absence of both, the members 
present, shall elect one from amongst themselves to preside for the 
occasion.

</section>

<section><tid>335456</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions shall, unless otherwise specifically provided, 
be decided by a majority of votes of the members present and voting. 
The Pradhan or Up- Pradhan or person presiding, as the, case may be, 
unless he refrains from voting shall give his vote before declaring 
the number of votes for and against a question and in the case of 
equality of votes, be may give his casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>432800</tid>
<number>4</number>No member of a Gram Panchayat shall vote on, or take part in 
the discussion of, any question coming up for consideration at a 
meeting of a Gram Panchayat, if the question is one in which, apart 
from its general application to the public, he has any pecuniary 
interest, and if the person presiding has such an interest, he shall 
not preside over the meeting when such question comes up for 
consideration.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>839490</tid>
<number>5</number>If the person presiding is believed by any member present at 
the meeting to have any such pecuniary interest in any matter under 
discussion, and if a motion to that effect be carried, he shall not 
preside at the meeting during such discussion or vote on or take part 
in it. Any member of the Gram Panchayat may be chosen to preside at 
the meeting during the continuance of such discussion.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1997556</tid>
<number> 35</number> Functions of Gram Panchayat.- Subject to such conditions as 
may be specified by the Governments from time to time, the Gram 
Panchayat shall perform the functions specified below:-
<section><tid>1821848</tid>
<number>1</number>General Functions:-

<subsection><tid>1349084</tid>
<number>a</number>preparation of annual plans for the development of the 
Panchayat area;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>623323</tid>
<number>b</number>preparation of annual budget;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5780</tid>
<number>c</number>power for mobilising reliefs in natural calamities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>674839</tid>
<number>d</number>removal of encroachments on public properties;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1631334</tid>
<number>e</number>organising voluntary labour and contribution for 
community works; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>641533</tid>
<number>f</number>maintenance of essential statistics of village (s).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1360826</tid>
<number>2</number>Agriculture, including Agriculture Extension:-

<subsection><tid>474027</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion and development of agriculture and 
horticulture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607658</tid>
<number>b</number>development of waste lands;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1128417</tid>
<number>c</number>development and maintenance of grazing lands and 
preventing their unauthorised alienation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53004</tid>
<number>d</number>promote land improvement and soil conservation mea- 
sures; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>639878</tid>
<number>e</number>promote measures for implementation of land reforms and 
land consolidation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1742261</tid>
<number>3</number>Animal husbandry, Dairying and Poultry:-

<subsection><tid>710342</tid>
<number>a</number>improvement of breed of cattle, poultry and other live- 
stock;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1506929</tid>
<number>b</number>promotion of dairy farming, poultry and piggery; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1511477</tid>
<number>c</number>grassland development.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>427841</tid>
<number>4</number>Fisheries:--
development fisheries in the village (s)


</section>

<section><tid>771901</tid>
<number>5</number>Social and Farm, Forestry, Minor Forest produce Fuel and 
Fodder:-

<subsection><tid>1245738</tid>
<number>a</number>Planting and preservation of trees on the sides of 
roads and public lands under its control;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1613773</tid>
<number>b</number>fuel plantations and fodder development;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>191285</tid>
<number>c</number>promotion of farm forestry; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1655830</tid>
<number>d</number>development of social forestry.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>11250</tid>
<number>6</number>Khadi, Village and Cottage Industries:

<subsection><tid>35826</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of rural and cottage industries

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662256</tid>
<number>b</number>organisation of awareness camps, seminars and training 
programmes, agricultural and industrial exhibitions for the 
benefit of the rural' areas; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>760925</tid>
<number>c</number>identification of traditional skills in the area to 
develop small scale industries and popularising food 
processing units.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1353007</tid>
<number>7</number>Rural Housing:-

<subsection><tid>1492583</tid>
<number>a</number>implementation of house building programme; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>345410</tid>
<number>b</number>maintenance of records relating to the houses, sites 
and other private and public properties.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>302861</tid>
<number>8</number>Drinking water:-

<subsection><tid>483729</tid>
<number>a</number>construction, repair and maintenance of drinking water 
wells, tanks and ponds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1279824</tid>
<number>b</number>prevention and control of water pollution; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>209822</tid>
<number>c</number>maintenance of rural water supply schemes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>238035</tid>
<number>9</number>Roads, buildings, culverts, bridges, ferries, waterways and 
other means of communication:-

<subsection><tid>28241</tid>
<number>a</number>construction and maintenance of village roads, drains 
and culverts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1063651</tid>
<number>b</number>maintenance of buildings under its control or 
transferred to it by the Government or any public authority; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1622234</tid>
<number>c</number>maintenance of boats, ferries and waterways.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>111692</tid>
<number>10</number>Non- Conventional Energy Source:-

<subsection><tid>659301</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion and development of non- conventional, energy 
schemes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>702902</tid>
<number>b</number>maintenance of community, non- conventional, energy 
devices, including, bio- gas plants; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>849871</tid>
<number>c</number>propagation of improved chulhas and other, efficient energy 
devices.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1642801</tid>
<number>11</number>Poverty Alleviation Programme:-

<subsection><tid>786742</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of public awareness and participation in 
poverty alleviation programmes for fuller employment and 
creation of productive assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1445357</tid>
<number>b</number>selection of beneficiaries under various programmes 
through Gram Sabha; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>592115</tid>
<number>c</number>participation in effective implementation and 
monitoring.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>853016</tid>
<number>12</number>Education including primary schools and secondary schools:-

<subsection><tid>243688</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of public awareness and participation in pri- 
mary and secondary education with special emphasis on, 
technical training and vocational education; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1389607</tid>
<number>b</number>ensuring full enrolment, and attendance in primary and 
secondary schools and its management.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1544408</tid>
<number>13</number>Adult and non- formal Education: promotion of Adult literacy..

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1884608</tid>
<number>14</number>Libraries:-
village libraries and reading rooms.


</section>

<section><tid>1675457</tid>
<number>15</number>Cultural activities:--
promotion of social and cultural activities.


</section>

<section><tid>698874</tid>
<number>16</number>Markets and fairs:--
regulation of fairs (including cattle fairs) and festivals.


</section>

<section><tid>897125</tid>
<number>17</number>Rural sanitation:-

<subsection><tid>280941</tid>
<number>a</number>maintenance of general sanitation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824008</tid>
<number>b</number>cleaning of public roads, drains, tanks, wells and 
other public places;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>688018</tid>
<number>c</number>maintenance and regulation of burning and burial 
grounds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1933281</tid>
<number>d</number>construction and maintenance of public latrines; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1331677</tid>
<number>e</number>management and control of washing and bathing ghats.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1820303</tid>
<number>18</number>Public health and family welfare:-

<subsection><tid>1005745</tid>
<number>a</number>implementation of family welfare programmes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1863826</tid>
<number>b</number>prevention and remedial measures against epidemics;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1589886</tid>
<number>c</number>regulation of sale of meat, fish and other perishable 
food articles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1726044</tid>
<number>d</number>participation in programmes of human and animal 
vaccination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1036888</tid>
<number>e</number>regulation of eating and entertainment establishments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1843059</tid>
<number>f</number>destruction of stray dogs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1526913</tid>
<number>g</number>regulation of curing, tanning and hides; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>55660</tid>
<number>h</number>regulation of offensive and dangerous trades.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1528179</tid>
<number>19</number>Woman and child development:-

<subsection><tid>668223</tid>
<number>a</number>participation in the implementation of woman and child 
welfare programmes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1799771</tid>
<number>b</number>promotion of school health and nutrition programmes,

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>704088</tid>
<number>20</number>Social welfare including welfare of the handicapped and men- 
tally retarded:-

<subsection><tid>1680013</tid>
<number>a</number>participation in the implementation of the social 
programmes, including welfare of the handicapped, mentally 
retarded and destitute; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>430481</tid>
<number>b</number>monitoring of the, old- age and widows pension schemes;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>409208</tid>
<number>21</number>Welfare of the weaker section and in particular the 
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribe:--

<subsection><tid>1131544</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of public awareness with regard to welfare of 
Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and other Weaker Sections; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>592044</tid>
<number>b</number>participation in the implementation of the specific 
programmes for the welfare of the weaker sections.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>416946</tid>
<number>22</number>Public distribution system:-

<subsection><tid>1706231</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of the public awareness with regard to the 
distribution of essential commodities: and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1511539</tid>
<number>b</number>monitoring the public distribution system.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>115911</tid>
<number>23</number>Maintenance of community assets:-

<subsection><tid>821702</tid>
<number>a</number>maintenance of community assets; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1380417</tid>
<number>b</number>preservation and maintenance of other community assets.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>107353</tid>
<number>24</number>Construction and maintenance of Dharmashalas, Chatras and 
similar institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>1198289</tid>
<number>25</number>Construction and maintenance of cattle sheds, pounds and 
cart stands.

</section>

<section><tid>51379</tid>
<number>26</number>Construction and maintenance of slaughter houses.

</section>

<section><tid>102750</tid>
<number>27</number>Maintenance of public parks, playgrounds.

</section>

<section><tid>1265336</tid>
<number>28</number>Regulation of manure pits in public places.

</section>

<section><tid>419504</tid>
<number>29</number>Establishment and control of shandies.

</section>

<section><tid>742015</tid>
<number>30</number>Irrigation, water management and watershed development:-

<subsection><tid>1348349</tid>
<number>a</number>promote measures for construction and maintenance of 
minor irrigation works and watershed development programmes.;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>244235</tid>
<number>b</number>develop ground water resources;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>325841</tid>
<number>c</number>providing for timely and equitable distribution of 
irrigation water.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>653561</tid>
<number>31</number>Rural electrification including distribution of 
electricity:-

<subsection><tid>1252564</tid>
<number>a</number>promote extension of electricity to unelectrified 
areas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1094313</tid>
<number>b</number>help in prevention of illegal tapping of electricity; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607902</tid>
<number>c</number>help in the recovery and collection of electricity due.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1081991</tid>
<number>32</number>Such other functions as may be entrusted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>31787</tid>
<number> 36</number> Assignment of functions.- The Government may, by notification 
and subject to such conditions as may be specified therein-
<section><tid>1058542</tid>
<number>a</number>transfer to any Gram Panchayat the management and main- 
tenance of a forest situated in the panchayat area;

</section>

<section><tid>323810</tid>
<number>b</number>make over to the Gram Panchayat the management of waste 
lands, pastures lands or vacant lands belonging to the 
Government situated within the panchayat area;

</section>

<section><tid>507301</tid>
<number>c</number>entrust the Gram Panchayat with the collection of land 
revenue on behalf of the Government and the maintenance of 
such records as are connected therewith; and

</section>

<section><tid>1163681</tid>
<number>d</number>entrust such other functions as may be prescribed:
Provided that no entrustment under clause (c) shall be made 
without the concurrence of the Gram PanchaYat concerned:

Provided further that when any transfer of the management and 
maintenance of a forest is made under clause (a) the Government shall 
direct that any amount required for such management and maintenance 
or an adequate portion of the income from such forest be placed at 
the disposal of the Gram Panchayat.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1161453</tid>
<number>37</number>General powers of the Gram Panchayat.- A Gram Panchayat shall 
have powers to do all acts necessary for or incidental to the carrying 
out the functions entrusted, assigned or delegated to it and, in 
particular, anti without prejudice to the foregoing powers, to 
exercise all powers specified under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1201879</tid>
<number> 38</number> Standing Committees.-
<section><tid>227769</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Gram Panchayat shall  
constitute, the following committees by election-

<subsection><tid>551020</tid>
<number>i</number>Production Committee for performing functions relating 
to agricultural productions, animal husbandry and rural 
industries and poverty alleviation programmes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180170</tid>
<number>ii</number>Social Justice Committee for performing functions 
relating to-

<subsubsection><tid>1579735</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of education, economic, social, cultural 
and other interests of the Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes and Backward Classes;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>945586</tid>
<number>b</number>protection of such Castes wad classes from social 
injustice and any form of exploitation; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1650484</tid>
<number>c</number>welfare of women and children.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>572151</tid>
<number>iii</number>Amenities Committee to perform functions in respect of 
education, public health, public works and other functions of 
the Gram Panchayat.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>635605</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) Each Committee shall consist of not less than three and 
not more than five members including the Pradhan and Up- Pradhan as the 
case may be. The Pradhan shall be the ex officio member and Chairman 
of Production Committee and Amenities Committee. The Pradhan shall be 
the ex officio member and Chairman of the Social Justice Committee:
Provided that the Social Justice Committee shall consist of at 
least one member who is a woman and one member belonging to the 
Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes.


<subsection><tid>1876912</tid>
<number>b</number>Each Committee shall be competent to co- opt in such manner as may 
be prescribed, members of farmers club, mahila mandals, yuvak mandals 
and other similar bodies recognised by the Government. A re- 
presentative of Co- operative societies in the panchayat areas shall 
be, co- opted to the Production Committee. The rights and liabilities 
of the co- opted members shall be such, as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>367964</tid>
<number>3</number>The Standing Committee shall perform the functions referred 
to above, to the extent the powers are delegated to them by the Gram 
Panchayat



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1526027</tid>
<number> 39</number> Property and funds.-
<section><tid>27994</tid>
<number>1</number>For every Gram Panchayat there shall  
be constituted a Gram Panchayat Fund bearing the name of the Gram 
Panchayat and there shall be placed to the credit thereof-

<subsection><tid>487150</tid>
<number>a</number>contributions and, grants, if any, made by the Central or 
State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1164409</tid>
<number>b</number>contributions and grants, if any, made by the Zilla 
Parishad or any other local authority;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1860932</tid>
<number>c</number>loans, if any, granted by the Central or the State 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1302350</tid>
<number>d</number>all receipts on accounts of taxes, rates and fees 
levied by it; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>847599</tid>
<number>e</number>all other sums received by or on behalf of other Gram 
Panchayat.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1594553</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Gram Panchayat shall set apart and apply annually such 
sum as may be required to meet-

<subsection><tid>1629453</tid>
<number>a</number>The cost of its own administration including the 
payment of salary, allowances, provided fund and gratuity to 
the officers and employees and to the Secretary:
Provided that the total expenditure on establishment shall 
not exceed one- third of the total expenditure, of the Gram 
Panchayat in any year.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>318776</tid>
<number>b</number>Every Gram Panchayat shall have the power to spend such 
sums as it thinks fit for carrying out the purpose of this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>99051</tid>
<number>c</number>The Gram Panchayat Fund shall be vested in the Gram 
Panchayat and the balance to the credit of the Fund shall be 
kept in such custody as may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804874</tid>
<number> 40</number> Taxation.-
<section><tid>591769</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such rules as may be made in this  
behalf, a Gram Panchayat shall impose yearly tax on lands and 
buildings within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Gram 
Panchayat.

</section>

<section><tid>886403</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such maximum rates as the Government may 
prescribe, a Gram Panchayat may levy the following fees and rates, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1162884</tid>
<number>a</number>a fee for providing sanitary arrangements at such 
places of worship or pilgrimage, fairs and melas within its 
jurisdiction; as may be specified by the Government by 
notification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1660033</tid>
<number>b</number>a lighting rate, where arrangement for lighting of 
public streets and places is made by the Gram Panchayat 
within its jurisdiction; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>681184</tid>
<number>c</number>a conservancy rate, where arrangement for clearing 
private latrines, urinals and, cesspools is made by the Gram 
Panchayat within its jurisdiction.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>608272</tid>
<number>41</number>Financial assistance to Gram Panchayats.- Subject to the 
provisions of this section, every Gram Panchayat shall, after a 
reappropriation made by law in this behalf, be entitled to receive 
grants- in- aid from the Consolidated Fund of the State as recommended 
by the State Finance Commission, constituted under section 97 of Act.


</article>



<article><tid>989627</tid>
<number> 42</number> Budget of the Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1889445</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Gram Panchayat shall,  
at such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, prepare during 
each year a budget of its estimated receipts and disbursements for the 
following year and shall submit the budget to the Zilla Parishad 
having jurisdiction over the area of the Gram Panchayat.

</section>

<section><tid>1886710</tid>
<number>2</number>The Zilla Parishad may, within such time as may be 
prescribed, either approve the budget or return it to the Gram 
Panchayat for such modifications as it may direct. On such 
modifications being, made the budget shall be resubmitted within such 
time as may be prescribed for approval of the Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>1907833</tid>
<number>3</number>No expenditure shall be incurred unless the budget is 
approved by the Zilla Parishad. If the Zilla Parishad does not convey 
its approval within the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

time prescribed for the purpose, the budget will be deemed to have 
been approved by the Zilla Parishad.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>964343</tid>
<number>43</number>Accounts.- Accounts of the income and expenditure of every 
Gram Panchayat shall be kept in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1265184</tid>
<number> 44</number> Audit.-
<section><tid>17644</tid>
<number>1</number>The accounts of a Gram Panchayat shall be audited  
by the Director, Local Fund Audit and Accounts of the Government of 
Manipur in such manner as may be prescribed and a copy of the audit 
report shall be forwarded to the Gram Panchayat within one month of 
the completion Of the audit.:

</section>

<section><tid>447494</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of the audit report referred to in sub- section 
 (1), the Gram Panchayat shall either remedy the defects or 
irregularities which have been pointed out in the audit report and 
send to the Zilla Parishad within three months an intimation of its 
having done so, or shall, within the said period, supply any further 
explanation to the prescribed authority in regard to such defects or 
irregularities as, it is required to furnish.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>337775</tid>
<number> 45</number> Staff of Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1176409</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Secretary for  
every Gram Panchayat who shall be appointed in such manner as may be 
prescribed and shall draw his salary and allowances from the Gram 
Panchayat Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1395249</tid>
<number>2</number>The Secretary shall be in charge of the office of the Gram 
Panchayat and shall perform all the duties and exercise all the powers 
imposed or conferred upon him by or under this Act or any rules or 
bye- law made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>393318</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government shall make rules relating to the method, of 
recruitment and the terms and conditions of service including the pay 
and allowances, superannuation, provident fund and gratuity of the 
Secretary.

</section>

<section><tid>1658403</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to rules as may be prescribed by Government 
regarding discipline and control, the Secretary shall act in all 
matters under the control of Gram Panchayat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1843772</tid>
<number> 46</number> Staffing pattern and category of employees.-
<section><tid>1299980</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Government may, by order, specify the staffing pattern, the scales of 
pay and mode of recruitment of staff of Gram Panchayats.

</section>

<section><tid>1330276</tid>
<number>2</number>The Gram Panchayat shall, subject to sub- section (1), 
determine and submit for approval of the Chief Executive Officer a 
category of, employ specifying the designation and grades and the, 
salaries and allowances payable to its officers other than the 
Secretary required for carrying out the duties imposed upon the Gram 
Panchayat by or under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1586076</tid>
<number>47</number>Appointment and control of employees.- Subject to the 
provisions of sections 45 and 46 the Gram Panchayat may, with the 
prior approval of the Chief Executive Officer appoint other employees 
of the Gram Panchayat and pay their salaries from the Gram Panchayat 
fund:
Provided that in making appointments, posts for the Scheduled 
Castes, the Scheduled Tribes and other socially and educationally 
backward classes of citizens shall be reserved in the same manner and 
to the same extent as is applicable for the recruitment to posts in 
the State Civil Services.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ZILLA PARISHAD

CHAPTER IV

ZILLA PARISHAD



</article>



<article><tid>1746163</tid>
<number> 48</number> Establishment of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>1398062</tid>
<number>1</number>The Governor shall, by  
notification in the Official Gazette establish a Zilla Parishad for a 
district and having jurisdiction over it, with effect from such date 
as may be specified.

</section>

<section><tid>1954536</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall be a corporate body by the name of 
its district, having perpetual succession and common seal and subject 
to such restrictions as are imposed by or under this or any, other 
enactment shall be vested with the capacity of seeing or being sued in 
its corporate name, of acquiring, holding and transferring property 
movable or unmovable, whether without or within the limits of the area 
over which it has authority, of entering into contracts and of doing 
all things, necessary, proper or expedient for which it is 
constituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>840354</tid>
<number> 49</number> Composition of Zilla Parishad.- The Zilla Parishad shall 
consist of-
<section><tid>844189</tid>
<number>a</number>the members directly elected from the territorial 
constituencies in the district under section 50;

</section>

<section><tid>1398462</tid>
<number>b</number>the members of the House of the People and the members 
of the State Legislative Assembly representing a part or 
whole of, the district whose constituencies lie within the 
district; and

</section>

<section><tid>193871</tid>
<number>c</number>ten per cent. of the Pradhans of the Gram Panchayats in 
the district:
Provided that when the total number of members under clauses (b) 
and (c) exceed the total number of members under clause (a), only one- 
third of the members under clause (c) shall be selected on rotation 
for a period of one year by lot as the Government may decide from time 
to time and district to district, subject to the condition that a 
Pradhan who was a member under this clause for one year shall not be 
eligible to become member for a second term during the remainder of 
his term of office as Pradhan:

Provided further that all members of the Zilla Parishad whether 
elected or not from territorial constituencies in the Zilla Parishad 
area shall have the right to vote in the meeting of the Zilla Parishad 
except in the election of Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1665756</tid>
<number> 50</number> Elected Members.-
<section><tid>1504384</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government may, by notification in  
the Official Gazette, determine the number of directly elected members 
from territorial constituencies keeping in view the overall population 
of the district at a rate of the one member for every 15, 000 
population or part thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1398719</tid>
<number>2</number>For the conduct of the election, the prescribed authority 
shall, in accordance with such rules as may be prescribed in this 
behalf by the Government,-

<subsection><tid>1871761</tid>
<number>a</number>divide the arm of Zilla Parishad into territorial 
constituencies in such manner so that the ratio between the 
population of each constituency and the numbers of seats 
allotted to it shall, so far as may be practicable, be the 
same throughout the panchayat area and determine the number 
of seats allotted to each constituency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130212</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to each territorial constituency shall 
elect one or more members through direct election in the 
manner prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>276688</tid>
<number>51</number>Filling of casual vacancy.- If vacancy of a member in Zilla 
Parishad occurs because of resignation, death, removal or otherwise, 
it shall be filled by election in the prescribed manner:
Provided that no election for filling the casual vacancy shall be 
held if the vacancy is for a period of less than six months.



</article>



<article><tid>1058121</tid>
<number> 52</number> Reservation.-
<section><tid>1785965</tid>
<number>1</number>Seats shall be reserved for- 

<subsection><tid>1854471</tid>
<number>a</number>the Scheduled Castes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802234</tid>
<number>b</number>the Scheduled Tribes;
in every Zilla Parishad and the number of seats shall bear, as nearly 
as may be, the same proportion to the total number of seats to be 
filled by direct election in that Zilla Parishad as the population 
of the Scheduled Castes in that Zilla Parishad area or of the 
Scheduled Tribes in that Zilla Parishad area bears to the total 
population of that area and such, seats may be allotted by rotation 
to different constituencies in a Zilla Parishad in such manner as may 
be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>100247</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than one- third of the total number of seats 
reserved under sub- section (1) shall be reserved for women belonging 
to the Scheduled Castes or, as the case may be, the Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

<section><tid>112217</tid>
<number>3</number>Not less than one- third (including the number of seats  
  reserved for women belonging to Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes) 
of the total number of seats filled by direct election in every Zilla 
Parishad shall be reserved for women and such seats may be allotted by 
rotation to different constituencies in a Zilla Parishad, in such 
manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1011071</tid>
<number> 53</number> Term of a Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>661004</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall  
continue for five years from the date of its first meeting:
Provided that, a Zilla Parishad which is functioning immediately 
before the commencement of this Act shall continue till the expiration 
of its duration.


</section>

<section><tid>362993</tid>
<number>2</number>An election to constitute a Zilla Parishad shall be 
completed:-

<subsection><tid>1897880</tid>
<number>a</number>before the expiry of its duration specified in sub- 
section (1); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1534640</tid>
<number>b</number>in case off its dissolution, before the expiration of a 
period of six months from the date of such dissolution:
Provided that where the remainder of the period for which the 
dissolved Zilla Parishad would have continued, is less than six 
months, it shall not, be necessary to hold any election under this 
clause for such period.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1599389</tid>
<number>3</number>A Zilla, Parishad constituted upon the dissolution of a 
Zilla Parishad before the expiration of its duration shall continue 
only for the remainder of the period for which the dissolved Zilla 
Parishad would have continued under sub- section (1) had it not been so 
dissolved.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>577351</tid>
<number> 54</number> Election of Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha.-
<section><tid>1920565</tid>
<number>1</number>The elected  
members of the Zilla Parishad referred to in section 50, shall, as 
soon as may be, elect two members from amongst them- selves to be 
respectively Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha thereof and so often

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as there is a casual vacancy in the Office of the Adhyaksha and Up- 
Adhyaksha, they shall elect another member from amongst themselves to 
be Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha, as the case may be:

Provided that no election shall be held if the vacancy is for 
period of less than one month.


</section>

<section><tid>1647702</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government, shall in the prescribed manner 
reserve-

<subsection><tid>1575737</tid>
<number>a</number>such number of offices of the Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha 
of Zilla Parishad in the State for persons belonging to the 
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes shall as nearly as may 
be, the same proportion to the total number of offices in the 
Zilla Parishad as the population of the Scheduled Castes or 
of the Scheduled Tribes in the State bear to the total 
population of the State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1322433</tid>
<number>b</number>not less than one- third of the total number of offices 
of Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha in the State from each category 
Which are reserved for persons belonging to the Scheduled 
Castes, the Scheduled Tribes and those which are unreserved, 
for women;
Provided that the offices reserved under this section shall be 
allotted by rotation to different Zilla Parishads.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1487035</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the Adhyaksha or Up- 
Adhyaksha shall hold office for the term of office of the members of 
the Zilla Parishad.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1992968</tid>
<number> 55</number> Salary and allowances to the Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha and 
other members.-
<section><tid>817008</tid>
<number>1</number>The salary and allowances of the Adhyaksha and Up-  
Adhyaksha shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>595932</tid>
<number>2</number>Every member of the Zilla Parishad other than the Adhyaksha 
and Up- Adhyaksha shall be entitled to receive, such sitting fee and 
allowances as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1435560</tid>
<number> 56</number> Powers, functions and duties of the Adhyaksha and Up- 
Adhayaksha.-
<section><tid>9197</tid>
<number>1</number>The Adhyaksha shall-

<subsection><tid>807052</tid>
<number>a</number>perform all the duties imposed and exercise all the 
powers conferred on the Adhyaksha under this Act and rules 
made thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>241294</tid>
<number>b</number>convene, preside over, and conduct meetings of the 
Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92466</tid>
<number>c</number>exercise Administrative supervision and control over 
the Chief Executive Officer and through him. all officers 
and, other employees of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Zilla Parishad and the officers and employees whose 
services may be, placed at the disposal of the Zilla Parishad 
by, the State Government;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517828</tid>
<number>d</number>exercise such other powers,' perform such other, 
functions and discharge such other duties as the Zilla 
Parishad may by general resolution direct or as the 
Government may, by rules made in this behalf, prescribe:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>681960</tid>
<number>e</number>exercise overall supervision over the financial and 
executive administration of the Zilla Parishad and place 
before the Zilla Parishad all questions connected therewith 
which shall appear to him to require its orders and for this 
purpose may call for records of the Zilla Parishad; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1740222</tid>
<number>f</number>have power to accord sanction up to a total sum of 
rupees one lakh in a year for the. purpose of providing 
immediate relief to those who are affected by natural 
calamities in the district:
Provided that the Adhyaksha shall place at the next meeting of 
the Zilla Parishad for its ratification, the de- tails of such 
sanctions.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1520524</tid>
<number>2</number>The Up- Adhyaksha shall-

<subsection><tid>99610</tid>
<number>a</number>in the absence of the Adhyaksha, preside over the meet- 
ings of the Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1274948</tid>
<number>b</number>exercise such powers and perform such duties of the 
Adhyaksha as the Adhyaksha from time to time may, subject to 
the rules as may be prescribed delegate to him by order in 
writing-, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>756952</tid>
<number>c</number>pending the election of the Adhyaksha or during the 
absence of the Adhyaksha fro the district, or by reason of 
leave for a period exceeding thirty days, exercise the powers 
and perform the duties of the Adhyaksha.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1755815</tid>
<number> 57</number> Resignation or removal of the Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha.-
<section><tid>1717214</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Adhyaksha may resign his office' by writing under his hand 
addressed to the, Commissioner, and the Up- Adhyaksha may resign his 
office by writing under his hand addressed to the Adhyaksha.

</section>

<section><tid>487528</tid>
<number>2</number>Every resignation under sub- section (1) shall take effect on 
the expiry of fifteen days from the date of its receipt by the 
prescribed authority, unless within this period of fifteen days he 
withdraws such resignation by writing under his hand addressed to the 
prescribed authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1942442</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha shall vacate the office if, 
he ceases to be a member of the Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>794171</tid>
<number>4</number>Every Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha shall be deemed to have 
vacated his office forthwith if a resolution expressing want of 
confidence in him is Passed by a majority of the total number of 
elected members of the territorial constituencies of the Zilla 
Parishad at a meeting specially convened for the purpose. The 
requisition for such a special meeting shall be signed by not less 
than one- fifth of the total membership of the Zilla Parishad and shall 
be delivered to the Adhyaksha. The Adhyaksha shall, within seven days 
from the date' of receipt of the requisition, convene a special 
meeting of the Zilla Parishad The meeting shall be held on a day not 
later than fifteen days from the date of issue of the notice of the 
meeting. The meeting shall be presided over by the Adhyaksha, if the 
motion is against the Up- Adhyaksha and in the case of Adhyaksha, the 
Up- Adhyaksha shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

preside over the meeting, if it is against both, a member nominated 
from amongst themselves by the members present in such meeting shall 
preside over such meeting. In the initial two years of their term as 
Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha, as the case may be, of zilla Parishad, no 
motion of no- confidence shall be brought against them.


</section>

<section><tid>1552629</tid>
<number>5</number>If the motion of no- confidence against the Adhyaksha or Up- 
or Up- Adhyaksha or both is once rejected, no fresh motion of no- 
confidence against the Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha or both, as the case 
may be, shall be brought before the Zilla Parishad within a period of 
one year from the date of such rejection of the motion.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1420745</tid>
<number>58</number>Resignation of Member.- A member of a Zilla Parishad may 
resign his membership in writing under his hand addressed to the 
Adhyaksha of the Zilla Parishad and his seat shall become vacant on 
the expiry of fifteen clear days from the date of such resignation, 
unless within the said period of fifteen days, he withdraws such 
resignation by writing under his hand addressed to the Adhyaksha.


</article>



<article><tid>1567629</tid>
<number> 59</number> Meeting of the Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>1954463</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall  
hold meetings, at least once in every three months, at such time and 
at such place within the local limits of the district concerned as the 
Zilla Parishad may fix at the immediately preceding meeting:
Provided that the first meeting of a newly constituted Zilla 
Parishad shall be held at such time and at such place within the local 
limits of the district concerned, as the prescribed authority may fix:

Provided further that the Adhyaksha when required in writing by 
one fifth of the members of the Zilla Parishad to call a meeting he 
shall do so within ten days, failing which the aforesaid members may 
call a meeting after giving intimation to the prescribed authority and 
seven clear days notice to the Adhyaksha and the other members of the 
Zilla Parishad.


</section>

<section><tid>1958287</tid>
<number>2</number>One- third of the total number of members of the Zilla 
Parishad shall form a quorum for transacting the business at the 
meeting of the Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>451389</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions coming before the Zilla Parishad shall be 
decided, by a majority of votes and in case of equality of votes, the 
Adhyaksha or the member presiding shall have a casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>768107</tid>
<number>4</number>Every meeting shall be presided over by the Adhyaksha or if 
he is absent by the Up- Adhyaksha and if both the Adhyaksha and the Up- 
Adhyaksha are absent or if the Adhyaksha is absent and there is no Up- 
Adhyaksha the members present shall elect one from among themselves to 
preside over the meeting.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1546563</tid>
<number> 60</number> Minutes.-
<section><tid>1430710</tid>
<number>1</number>Minutes shall be kept of the names of the  
members and of the officers, if any, present, and of the proceedings 
at each meeting of the Zilla Parishad and if any member present at the 
meeting so desires, of the names of the members voting respectively 
for Or against any resolution, in a book to be provided for purpose 
and after, they are read over and agreed to, shall be signed by the 
Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha or person presiding at such meeting, and 
shall at all reasonable times be open to inspection by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any member of the Zilla Parishad Any person may inspect the copy of 
the minutes of the meeting. The minutes books shall always be kept in 
the office of the Zilla Parishad and shall be in the custody of the 
Chief Executive Officer of the Zilla Parishad.


</section>

<section><tid>1460919</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy, of every resolution passed by the Zilla Parishad 
shall within ten days from the date of its passing in, the meeting, be 
forwarded by the Chief Executive Officer to the Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966159</tid>
<number> 61</number> Functions and powers of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>60474</tid>
<number>1</number>Any transfer of a  
subject to the Zilla Parishad shall- be with the approval of the 
Government from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>461382</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the condition and exceptions as the Government 
may, from time to time, impose, it shall be the function of the Zilla 
Parishad to prepare plans for economic development and social justice 
of the District, and to ensure the coordinated implementation of such 
plans in respect of matters including those mentioned below, namely:-

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1324962</tid>
<number> 1</number> AGRICULTURE AND AGRICULTURAL EXTENSION:
<section><tid>1746899</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of measures to increase agricultural 
production and to popularise the use of improved 
agricultural implements and the adoption of improved 
agricultural practices;

</section>

<section><tid>1959136</tid>
<number>ii</number>establishment and maintenance of godowns;

</section>

<section><tid>1313045</tid>
<number>iii</number>conducting agricultural fairs and exhibitions;

</section>

<section><tid>1103560</tid>
<number>iv</number>training of farmers;

</section>

<section><tid>748693</tid>
<number>v</number>land improvement and soil conservation; and

</section>

<section><tid>902637</tid>
<number>vi</number>promotion of agricultural extension works.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98474</tid>
<number> 2</number> IRRIGATION GROUND WATER RESOURCES, AND WATERSHED 
DEVELOPMENT:
<section><tid>1292380</tid>
<number>i</number>construction, renovation and maintenance of minor 
irrigation works and lift irrigation;

</section>

<section><tid>634927</tid>
<number>ii</number>providing for the timely and equitable 
distribution, and full use of water under irrigation 
schemes under the control of the Zilla Parishad;

</section>

<section><tid>152736</tid>
<number>iii</number>development of ground water resources;

</section>

<section><tid>1018446</tid>
<number>iv</number>installation of community pump sets; and

</section>

<section><tid>619201</tid>
<number>v</number>watershed development programme.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>599261</tid>
<number> 3</number> HORTICULTURE:
<section><tid>591266</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of rural parks and gardens;

</section>

<section><tid>1819964</tid>
<number>ii</number>promotion of cultivation of fruits and vegetables; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1279202</tid>
<number>iii</number>promotion of farms.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>25795</tid>
<number> 4</number> STATISTICS:
<section><tid>1652301</tid>
<number>i</number>publication of statistical and other information 
relating to activities of Gram Panchayats and Zilla 
Parishads;

</section>

<section><tid>1874498</tid>
<number>ii</number>co- ordination and use of statistics and other 
information required for the activities of' the Gram 
Panchayats and Zilla Parishads; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1732585</tid>
<number>iii</number>periodical supervision and evaluation of project 
and programmes entrusted to the Gram Panchayats and 
Zilla Parishads.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414279</tid>
<number>5</number>DISTRIBUTION OF ESSENTIAL COMMODITIES.
</article>



<article><tid>76707</tid>
<number> 6</number> SOIL CONSERVATION AND LAND REFORMS:
<section><tid>917926</tid>
<number>i</number>soil conservation measures;

</section>

<section><tid>402832</tid>
<number>ii</number>land reclamation and kind development works; and

</section>

<section><tid>845189</tid>
<number>iii</number>promote implementation of land reforms and land 
consolidation.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>935185</tid>
<number> 7</number> MARKETING:
<section><tid>948418</tid>
<number>i</number>development of regulated markets and marketing 
yards; and

</section>

<section><tid>1525942</tid>
<number>ii</number>grading and quality control of agriculture 
products.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>564135</tid>
<number> 8</number> SOCIAL FORESTRY:
<section><tid>1851002</tid>
<number>i</number>organise campaign for tree planting; and

</section>

<section><tid>56031</tid>
<number>ii</number>planting and maintenance of trees.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1622892</tid>
<number> 9</number> ANIMAL HUSBANDRY AND DAIRYING:
<section><tid>1683608</tid>
<number>i</number>improvement of breed of cows and pigs;

</section>

<section><tid>1892860</tid>
<number>ii</number>promotion of poultry farms, duck farms and goat 
farms;

</section>

<section><tid>1734296</tid>
<number>iii</number>promotion of fodder development programmes;

</section>

<section><tid>1922485</tid>
<number>iv</number>promotion of dairy farming, poultry and 
piggery; and

</section>

<section><tid>1116109</tid>
<number>v</number>prevention of epidemics and contagious diseases.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1212305</tid>
<number> 10</number> MINOR FOREST PRODUCE, FUEL AND FODDER:
<section><tid>1998128</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of social and farm forestry, fuel 
plantation and fodder development;

</section>

<section><tid>978845</tid>
<number>ii</number>management of minor forest produce of the in 
community lands; and

</section>

<section><tid>875950</tid>
<number>iii</number>development of wasteland.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>803258</tid>
<number> 11</number> FISHERIES:
<section><tid>208655</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of fish seed production and 
distribution;

</section>

<section><tid>1471182</tid>
<number>ii</number>development of pisiculture in private and 
community tanks'

</section>

<section><tid>373175</tid>
<number>iii</number>development of inland fisheries;

</section>

<section><tid>361460</tid>
<number>iv</number>promotion of fish curing and drying;

</section>

<section><tid>668290</tid>
<number>v</number>assistance to traditional fishing;

</section>

<section><tid>863811</tid>
<number>vi</number>organising fish marketing co- operatives; and

</section>

<section><tid>924987</tid>
<number>vii</number>welfare schemes for the uplift and development of 
fisherman.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1658146</tid>
<number> 12</number> HOUSEHOLD, INDUSTRIES: 
 (including food processing):
<section><tid>471044</tid>
<number>i</number>identification of traditional skills in the 
locality and Promotion of household industries;

</section>

<section><tid>689370</tid>
<number>ii</number>organisation of training programme for craftsmen 
and artisan;

</section>

<section><tid>1224964</tid>
<number>iii</number>liaison to tap bank credit for household 
industries;

</section>

<section><tid>148469</tid>
<number>iv</number>popularising and marketing of finished products; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1728045</tid>
<number>v</number>organising khadi, handloom, handicraft and 
village and cottage industries.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>124172</tid>
<number> 13</number> RURAL ROADS AND INLAND WATERWAYS:
<section><tid>1445614</tid>
<number>i</number>construction and maintenance of roads other than 
National, State Highways and other District road;

</section>

<section><tid>1179130</tid>
<number>ii</number>bridges and culverts coming under roads falling in 
item (i);

</section>

<section><tid>1479558</tid>
<number>iii</number>construction and maintenance of office buildings 
of the Zilla Parishad;

</section>

<section><tid>424995</tid>
<number>iv</number>identification of major. link roads connecting 
markets, educational institutions, health centres; and

</section>

<section><tid>234399</tid>
<number>v</number>organising voluntary surrender of lands for new 
roads and for widening of existing roads.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975168</tid>
<number> 14</number> HEALTH AND HYGIENE:
<section><tid>107698</tid>
<number>i</number>implementation of immunization and vaccination 
programme;

</section>

<section><tid>318459</tid>
<number>ii</number>health education, activities in hospitals, primary 
health centres and dispensaries;

</section>

<section><tid>1332961</tid>
<number>iii</number>maternity and child health service activities;

</section>

<section><tid>937816</tid>
<number>iv</number>family welfare activities;

</section>

<section><tid>540318</tid>
<number>v</number>organising health camps with Gram Panchayats; and

</section>

<section><tid>295892</tid>
<number>vi</number>measures against environment pollution.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1044223</tid>
<number> 15</number> RURAL HOUSING:
<section><tid>1125857</tid>
<number>i</number>identification of houseless families;

</section>

<section><tid>884605</tid>
<number>ii</number>implementation of house building programmes in the 
district; and

</section>

<section><tid>796992</tid>
<number>iii</number>popularising low cost housing.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>834448</tid>
<number> 16</number> EDUCATION:
<section><tid>1458682</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of educational activities including the 
establishment and maintenance of primary and secondary 
schools;

</section>

<section><tid>171078</tid>
<number>ii</number>planning of programmes for Adult Education and 
Library, facilities;

</section>

<section><tid>1357482</tid>
<number>iii</number>propagation of technical training and vocational 
education-, and

</section>

<section><tid>984439</tid>
<number>iv</number>extension work for propagation of Science and 
Technology to rural areas.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1461258</tid>
<number> 17</number> SOCIAL WELFARE AND WELFARE OF WEAKER SECTIONS AND 
HANDICAPPED PERSONS:
<section><tid>1087063</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of social welfare programme and social 
welfare activities with emphasis on handicapped and 
mentally retarded persons;

</section>

<section><tid>851262</tid>
<number>ii</number>organising nursery schools, balwadies, night 
schools and libraries to eradicate illiteracy and 
impart general education; and

</section>

<section><tid>151113</tid>
<number>iii</number>organising co- operative societies of Scheduled 
Castes and Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>757861</tid>
<number>18</number>POVERTY ALLEVIATION PROGRAMMES:
planning, supervision monitoring and implementation Of 
poverty alleviation programmes.

</article>



<article><tid>1548597</tid>
<number> 19</number> DRINKING WATER:
<section><tid>534654</tid>
<number>i</number>construction, repair and maintenance of drinking 
water wells, tanks and ponds;

</section>

<section><tid>24909</tid>
<number>ii</number>prevention and control of water pollution.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1850886</tid>
<number> 20</number> RURAL ELECTRIFICATION:
<section><tid>1414445</tid>
<number>i</number>promote extension of electricity to unelectrified 
areas;

</section>

<section><tid>1954926</tid>
<number>ii</number>help in the prevention of illegal tapping of 
electricity; and

</section>

<section><tid>69850</tid>
<number>iii</number>help in the recovery and collection of electricity 
dues.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1954546</tid>
<number> 21</number> NON CONVENTIONAL ENERGY SOURCES:
<section><tid>1626534</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion and development of non- conventional 
energy scheme; and

</section>

<section><tid>1214997</tid>
<number>ii</number>propagation of efficient energy devices.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>562972</tid>
<number> 22</number> SOCIAL REFORM ACTIVITIES:
<section><tid>1781368</tid>
<number>i</number>promotion of women' s organisation and welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>1468252</tid>
<number>ii</number>promotion Of children' s organization and welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>577533</tid>
<number>iii</number>organise cultural and recreation activities;

</section>

<section><tid>1200587</tid>
<number>iv</number>encouragement of sports and games and construction 
of rural stadia;

</section>

<section><tid>655866</tid>
<number>v</number>promotion of thrift and savings through:-

<subsection><tid>1753671</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of saving habits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1992812</tid>
<number>b</number>small savings campaign;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>433958</tid>
<number>c</number>fight against spurious money lending 
practices and rural indebtedness.

<subsubsection><tid>1767917</tid>
<number>4</number>In addition, the Zilla Parishad may-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<subsubsubsection><tid>142021</tid>
<number>a</number>manage or maintain any work of public utility or any 
institution vested in it or under its control and management;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1858975</tid>
<number>b</number>acquire and maintain village hats and markets;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1204783</tid>
<number>c</number>make grants to Gram Panchayats;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>588310</tid>
<number>d</number>adopt measures for the relief of people in distress;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>694809</tid>
<number>e</number>co- ordinate and integrate the development plans and 
schemes prepared by Gram Panchayats in the district;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>192978</tid>
<number>f</number>examine and sanction the budget estimates of Gram 
Panchayat in the district;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1946005</tid>
<number>g</number>undertake or execute any scheme extending to the whole 
or part of the district; and

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>779268</tid>
<number>h</number>take over the maintenance and control of any rural 
bridge, tank, ghat, well, channel or drain, belonging to a 
private owner or any other authority on such terms as may be 
agreed upon.

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>932635</tid>
<number>5</number>The Zilla Parishads two or more adjacent districts may 
jointly undertake and execute any development scheme on such terms and 
conditions as may be mutually agreed upon:
Provided that the A Government may by notification and subject 
to such conditions as it may impose, transfer additional functions 
to the Zilla Parishad.




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1723031</tid>
<number> 62</number> General powers of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>1454122</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the general  
or special orders of the Government, he Zilla Parishad may-

<subsection><tid>1934410</tid>
<number>a</number>incur expenditure on education or medical relief 
outside its jurisdiction;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>769308</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for carrying out any work or measure likely to 
promote health, safety, education, comfort, convenience or 
social or economic or cultural well- being of the inhabitants 
of the district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8769</tid>
<number>c</number>contribute to association of All India, State or 
Inter- State level concerned with the promotion of local 
government and for holding exhibition, seminar and 
conferences within the district related to the activities of 
Gram Panchayat and Zilla Parishad; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1383206</tid>
<number>d</number>render financial or other assistance to any person, for 
carrying in the district any activity which is related to any 
of its functions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1988646</tid>
<number>2</number>The Zilla Parishad shall have powers to do all acts 
necessary for or incidental to the carrying out of the functions 
entrusted or delegated to it and, in particular, and without prejudice 
to the foregoing powers to exercise all powers specified under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>118304</tid>
<number> 63</number> Assignment of functions.-
<section><tid>1929366</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government may assign to  
Zilla Parishad, functions in relation, to, any matters to which the 
executive authority of the Government extends or in respect of 
functions which have been assigned to the State Government by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>533512</tid>
<number>2</number>The Government may, by notification, withdraw or modify the 
functions assigned under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191154</tid>
<number>64</number>Delegation of powers.- The Zilla Parishad may, by 
notification., delegate to the Chief Executive Officer or other 
Officer any of the powers conferred by or under this Act on the Zilla 
Parishad.


</article>



<article><tid>1067344</tid>
<number> 65</number> Standing Committees.-
<section><tid>1794205</tid>
<number>1</number>The Zilla Parishad shall have the  
Mowing Standing Committees, namely:

<subsection><tid>283881</tid>
<number>a</number>General Standing Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1712566</tid>
<number>b</number>Finance, Audit and Planning Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>579791</tid>
<number>c</number>Social Justice Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1927914</tid>
<number>d</number>Education and Health Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>938779</tid>
<number>e</number>Agriculture and Industries Committee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>616717</tid>
<number>f</number>Works Committee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>354030</tid>
<number>2</number>Each Standing Committee shall consist of such number of 
members not exceeding five including the Chairman elected by the 
members of Zilla Parishad from amongst the elected members.

</section>

<section><tid>199986</tid>
<number>3</number>The Adhyaksha shall be the ex officio member and Chairman of 
the General Standing Committee and the Finance, Audit and Planning 
Committee. The Up- Adhyaksha shall be the ex officio member and Chair- 
man of the Social Justice Committee. The other Standing Committee 
shall elect the Chairman from among their members.

</section>

<section><tid>1044800</tid>
<number>4</number>No member of the Zilla Parishad shall be eligible to serve 
not more than two Standing Committees.

</section>

<section><tid>1206086</tid>
<number>5</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall be the ex officio 
Secretary of the General Standing Committee and the Finance, Audit and 
Planning Committee and he shall nominate one of the Deputy Secretaries 
as ex officio Secretary for each of the remaining Standing Committees. 
The Chief Executive Officer shall be entitled to attend the meetings 
of all the Standing Committees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>884700</tid>
<number> 66</number> Functions of the Standing Committee.-
<section><tid>1826180</tid>
<number>1</number>The General Standing  
Committee shall perform functions relating to the establishment 
matters and- functions relating to communication, buildings, rural 
housing, village extensions, relief against the natural calamities 
and: allied matters and all other matters.

</section>

<section><tid>1160363</tid>
<number>2</number>The Finance Audit and Planning Committee shall perform the 
functions relating to:

<subsection><tid>943269</tid>
<number>a</number>the finances of the Zilla Parishad, framing of budgets, 
scrutinising proposals for increase of revenue, examination 
of receipts and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

expenditure statements, consideration, of all. proposals 
affecting the finances of the Zilla Parishad and general 
supervision, of the revenue and expenditure of the Zilla 
Parishad;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131295</tid>
<number>b</number>the plan priorities, allocation of outlays to 
developments, horizontal and vertical linkages, 
implementation of guidelines issued by the Government, 
regular review of planning programmes, evaluation of 
important programmes and small savings schemes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1478763</tid>
<number>3</number>The Social Justice Committee shall perform functions 
relating to:

<subsection><tid>1656379</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion of education, economic, social, cultural and 
other interests of the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and 
Backward Classes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1004329</tid>
<number>b</number>protecting them from social injustice and all other 
forms of exploitation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425842</tid>
<number>c</number>amelioration, of the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled 
Tribes and Backward Classes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>197728</tid>
<number>d</number>securing social justice to the Scheduled Castes, the 
Scheduled Tribes, women and other weaker sections of the 
society.,

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>874669</tid>
<number>4</number>The Education and Health Committee shall:-

<subsection><tid>797868</tid>
<number>a</number>be incharge of all educational activities of the Zilla. 
Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1218623</tid>
<number>b</number>undertake the planning of education in the district 
within the framework of the national policy and the national 
and state plans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>303232</tid>
<number>c</number>survey and evaluate the educational activities of the 
Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378851</tid>
<number>d</number>perform such other duties pertaining to education, 
adult literacy and cultural activities as the Zilla Parishad 
may assign to it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1328754</tid>
<number>e</number>health services, hospitals, water supply, family welfare 
and other related matters.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1624701</tid>
<number>5</number>The Agriculture and industry Committee shall perform 
functions relating to:

<subsection><tid>340003</tid>
<number>a</number>agricultural production, animal husbandry, co- operation, 
contour bunding and, reclamation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1407723</tid>
<number>b</number>village and cottage industries: and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1612799</tid>
<number>c</number>promotion of industrial development of the district.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1362743</tid>
<number>6</number>The Works Committee shall perform functions relating to 
maintenance of:-

<subsection><tid>486070</tid>
<number>a</number>roads including district roads, bridges, culverts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>133530</tid>
<number>b</number>maintenance of buildings under its control or 
transferred by the Government or any public authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>429697</tid>
<number>c</number>maintenance of boats, ferries, waterways.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1118578</tid>
<number>7</number>The Standing Committee referred to in sub- sections (1) to 
 (6) shall perform the functions referred to above to the extent the 
powers are delegated to them by the Zilla Parishad.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>821862</tid>
<number>8</number>The Standing Committees shall perform in respect of matters 
assigned to them such additional duties as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1407110</tid>
<number> 67</number> Procedure of Committees.-
<section><tid>1297107</tid>
<number>1</number>The Zilla Parishad may frame  
regulations relating to election of members of committees, conduct of 
business therein, and all other matters relating to the committees.

</section>

<section><tid>1954529</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of every Standing Committee shall in respect of 
the work of that committee be entitled to call for any information, 
return statement or report from the officer of the Zilla Paris W. and 
to enter on and inspect any immovable property of the Zilla Parishad 
or any work in progress concerning the committee.

</section>

<section><tid>788230</tid>
<number>3</number>Each Standing Committee shall be entitled to require 
attendance at its meetings of any officer of the Zilla Parishad who is 
connected with the work of the Committee. The Chief Executive Officer 
shall under instruction of the committee, issue notices and secure the 
attendance of the officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>278501</tid>
<number> 68</number> Power to acquire hold and dispose of property.-
<section><tid>1179140</tid>
<number>1</number>A Zilla  
Parishad shall have the power to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
and to enter into contracts:-
Provided that in all cases of acquisition or disposal of 
immovable property the Zilla Parishad shall obtain the previous 
approval of the Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1454328</tid>
<number>2</number>All roads buildings or other works constructed by a Zilla 
Parishad with its own funds shall vest in it.

</section>

<section><tid>711108</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government may allocate to a Zilla Parishad any public 
property situated within its jurisdiction, and threupon such property 
shall vest in the Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>334062</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a Zilla Parishad requires land to carry out any of the 
purposes of this Act, it may negotiate with the, person or persons 
having in the said land, and if it fails to reach an agreement, it may 
make an application to the Deputy Commissioner for the acquisition of 
the land and the Deputy Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the 
land is required for a public purpose, take steps to acquire the land 
under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> and such land 
shall on acquisition, vest in the Zilla Parishad. (1 of <year>1894</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1092487</tid>
<number> 69</number> Zilla Parishad Fund.-
<section><tid>958135</tid>
<number>1</number>For every Zilla Parishad there shall  
be constituted a Zilla Parishad Fund bearing the name of the Zilla 
Parishad and there shall be placed to the credit thereof:-

<subsection><tid>34740</tid>
<number>a</number>contributions and grants, if any, made by the Central or 
the State Government including such part of land revenue 
collected in the State as may be determined by the 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>347276</tid>
<number>b</number>contributions and grants, if any, made by a Gram 
Panchayat or any other local authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1787573</tid>
<number>c</number>loans, if any, granted by the Central or State 
Government or raised by the Zilla Parishad oh security of its 
assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254883</tid>
<number>d</number>the proceeds of road- cess and public works- cess levied 
in the district;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>534951</tid>
<number>e</number>all receipts on account of tolls, rates and fees levied 
by the Zilla parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1845496</tid>
<number>f</number>all receipts in respect of any schools, hospitals, 
dispensaries, buildings, institutions or works, vested in, 
constructed by or Placid under the control and management of 
the Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1412926</tid>
<number>g</number>all sums received as gift or contribution and all 
income from any, trust or endowment made in favour of Zilla 
Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169326</tid>
<number>h</number>such fines or penalties imposed and realised under the 
provisions of this Act or of the bye- laws made thereunder, as 
may be, prescribed and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>586362</tid>
<number>i</number>all other sums received by or on behalf of the Zilla 
Parishad

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>980693</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall set apart and apply annually such 
sum as may be required to meet the cost of its own administration 
including' the' payment of salary, allowances, provident fund and 
gratuity of the officers and employees. The overall expenditure on 
establishment shall not exceed one- third of the total

</section>

<section><tid>1655379</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall have the power to spend such sums 
as it thinks fit for carrying, out the purpose; of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>174536</tid>
<number>4</number>The Zilla Parishad Fund shall be vested in the Zilla 
Parishad and the amount standing to the credit of the fund shall be 
kept in such custody or invested in Such manner as the Government may, 
from time to time, direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>245752</tid>
<number> 70</number> Taxation.-
<section><tid>763659</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such maximum rates as the Government  
prescribe, a Zilla Parishad may-

<subsection><tid>129373</tid>
<number>a</number>levy tolls on persons, vehicles or animals or any class 
Of then at any toll- bar established by it on any road other 
than kutcha road or any bridge vested in it or under its 
management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1624780</tid>
<number>b</number>levy tools in respect for any ferry established by it 
or under its management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884187</tid>
<number>c</number>levy road- cess and public works- cess;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1994705</tid>
<number>d</number>levy the following fees and rates, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1797510</tid>
<number>i</number>fees on the registration of boats or vehicles;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>957994</tid>
<number>ii</number>a fee for licence for fair or mela; pilgrimage, 
fairs and melas within its jurisdiction as may be 
specified by the Government by notification;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1653878</tid>
<number>iii</number>a fee for licence for fair or mela;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>515569</tid>
<number>iv</number>a lighting rate where arrangement for lighting 
of public streets and places is made by the Zilla 
Parishad within its jurisdiction; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1102372</tid>
<number>v</number>water rate, where arrangement for the supply of 
water for drinking, irrigation or any other purpose is 
made by the Zilla Parishad within its jurisdiction.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>567902</tid>
<number>2</number>The Zilla Parishad shaH not undertake registration of any 
vehicle or levy fee thereof and shall not provide sanitary 
arrangements at places of worship

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or pilgrimage, fairs and melas within its jurisdiction or levy fee 
thereof if such vehicle has already been registered by any other 
authority under any law for the, time being in force or if such 
provision for sanitary arrangement has already been made by any other 
local authority.


</section>

<section><tid>586556</tid>
<number>3</number>The scales of to- Us, fees or rates and the terms and 
conditions for the imposition thereof shall be such as may be provided 
by regulation. Such regulation may provide for exemption from all or 
any of the tolls, fees or roles in any class of cases.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>528628</tid>
<number> 71</number> Financial arrangements of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>1370169</tid>
<number>1</number>A Zilla  
Parishad may, subject to the provisions of any law relating to the 
raising of loans by local authorities for the time being in force, 
raise from time to time, with the approval of the Government, loans 
for the purpose of the Act and create a sinking fund for the repayment 
of such loans.

</section>

<section><tid>1257188</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) a 
Zilla Parishad may borrow money from the Government or, with the 
previous sanction, of the Government, from banks or other financial 
institutions, for furtherance of its, objective on the basis of 
specific scheme as may be drawn up by the Zilla Parishad for the 
purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>724539</tid>
<number> 72</number> Budget.-
<section><tid>312719</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall, at such time and in  
such manner as may be prescribed, prepare in each year a budget of its 
estimated receipts and disbursements for the following year and submit 
it to the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1536655</tid>
<number>2</number>The Government may, within such time as may, be prescribed 
either approve the budget or return it to the Zilla Parishad for such 
modifications as it may direct. On such modifications being made the 
budget shall be resubmitted within such time as may be prescribed 
for' approval of the Government if the approval of the Government is 
not received by the Zilla Parishad by the last date of the financial 
year, the budget shall be deemed to be approved by the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1692458</tid>
<number>3</number>No expenditure shall be incurred unless the budget is 
approved by the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1248263</tid>
<number>4</number>The Zilla Parishad may prepare in each year a supplementary 
estimate providing for any modification of its budget and may submit 
it to the Government for approval within such time and in such manner 
as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>548578</tid>
<number>73</number>Accounts.- A Zilla Parishad shall keep accounts in such 
manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1843522</tid>
<number> 74</number> Audit.-
<section><tid>10696</tid>
<number>1</number>The audit of the accounts of the Zilla Parishad  
shall be carried out by the authority as may be prescribed by the 
Government and a copy of the audit note shall be, forwarded to the 
Zilla Parishad within one month of the completion of the audit.

</section>

<section><tid>1531736</tid>
<number>2</number>on receipt of the audit report referred to in sub- section 
 (1), the Zilla Parishad shall either remedy any defects or 
irregularities which have been pointed out in the audit and send to 
the Government within three" months an intimation of its having done 
so or shall, within the said period. supply any further explanation 
to, the prescribed authority in regard to such defects or 
irregularities as it is required to furnish.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>192710</tid>
<number> 75</number> Staff of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>90387</tid>
<number>1</number>An officer of the rank of the  
Deputy Commissioner shall be the Chief Executive Officer of the Zilla 
Parishad who shall be appointed by the Government. The Government 
may, also appoint an Additional Chief Executive officer for a Zilla 
Parishad on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>73161</tid>
<number>2</number>The Government shall also appoint a Chief Accounts Officers 
and a Chief planning Officer for each Zilla Parishad on such, terms 
and conditions as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1556158</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government shall post from time to time in every Zilla 
Parishad such number of officers of Group A, B and C services of the 
State (including any officers appointed to such service from amongst  
  person employed by the existing local authority) and officers of an 
All India Service allocated to serve under the Government, as the 
Government considers necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>75253</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other 
law for the time being in force the Government or any other officer or 
other authority authorised by it in this behalf shall have the power 
to effect transfer of the officers and officials so posted from one 
district to another district.

</section>

<section><tid>622355</tid>
<number>5</number>The Government may constitute, from such date as is 
specified, such services for each Zilla Parishad as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1988133</tid>
<number> 76</number> Functions of the Chief Executive officer and other officers.-

<section><tid>576798</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided by or under this Act, the  
Chief Executive Officer shall-

<subsection><tid>814028</tid>
<number>a</number>carry out the policies and directions of the Zilla 
Parishad and take necessary measures for the speedy execution 
of all works and developmental schemes of Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140624</tid>
<number>b</number>discharge the duties imposed upon him, by or under this 
Act or the rules and regulations made thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1822779</tid>
<number>c</number>control the officers and servants of the Zilla Parishad 
subject to the general superintendence and control of the 
Zilla Adhyaksha and under such rules as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1310822</tid>
<number>d</number>have custody of all papers and documents relating to 
Zilla Parishad; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1060745</tid>
<number>e</number>draw and disburse money out of the Zilla Parishad Funds 
and exercise such other powers and perform such other 
functions as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1809976</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall attend every meeting of 
the Zilla Parishad and may take part in the discussion but shall not 
have the right to move any resolution or to vote. If in the opinion 
of the Chief Executive Officer any proposal before the Zilla Parishad 
is violative of or is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or 
any other law or the rules made thereunder, it shall be his duty to 
bring the same to the notice of the Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>1727108</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Accounts Officer shall advise the Zilla Parishad 
in matters of financial policy and shall be responsible for all 
matters relating to the accounts of the Zilla Parishad including 
preparation of accounts and the budget.

</section>

<section><tid>390666</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chief Accounts Officer shall ensure that no expenditure 
is incurred except under proper sanction and in accordance with this 
Act and the rules and regulations made thereunder and shall disallow 
any expenditure not warranted by the Act or rules and regulations or 
for which no provision is made in the budget.

</section>

<section><tid>838433</tid>
<number>5</number>The Additional Chief Executive Officer shall assist the 
Chief Executive Officer in the performance of his duties.

</section>

<section><tid>951617</tid>
<number>6</number>The Chief Planning Officer shall advise the Zilla Parishad 
in matters of plan formulation and shall be responsible for all 
matters relating to planning of the Zilla Parishad including the 
preparation of plans of economic development and social justice and 
annual plan of the district.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1364964</tid>
<number> 77</number> Right to requsition records, recover money, etc.-
<section><tid>117371</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
person in possession of money, accounts, records or other property 
pertaining to a Gram Panchayat or a Zilla Parishad shall on the 
requisition in writing of the Chief Executive Officer for this 
purpose, forthwith hand

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

over such money or deliver up such accounts, records or other property 
to the Executive Officer or the person authorised in the requisition 
to receive e same.


</section>

<section><tid>861357</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive Officer may also take steps to recover 
any money due by such person in the same manner and subject to the 
same provisions as in the relevent Land Revenue Act, for the recovery 
of the arrears of land revenue from defaulters and for the purpose of 
requisitioning the accounts, records or for covering any other 
property apertaining to tile Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad may 
issue a search warrant and exercise all such powers with respect 
thereto as may lawfully be exercised by a Magistrate under the 
provisions of Chapter VII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>. (2  
  of <year>1974</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>563898</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person knowing where any money, accounts, records or 
other property apertaining to a Gram Panchayat or a Zilla Parishad are 
concealed shall be bound to give information of the same to the Chief 
Executive Officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1748355</tid>
<number>4</number>An appeal shall lie from an order of the Chief Executive 
Officer under this section to the Government.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485572</tid>
<number>78</number>Powers to revise or modify revise or modify decisions of 
committees.- Every Gram Panchayat and every Zilla Parishad shall have 
power to revise or modify any decision taken by any of its committees.


</article>



<article><tid>1160717</tid>
<number> 79</number> Powers of Gram Panchayats to make bye- laws.-
<section><tid>1719184</tid>
<number>1</number>A Gram  
Panchayat may, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules 
made thereunder and with the previous sanction of the Zilla Parishad 
make bye- laws to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1235634</tid>
<number>2</number>In making any bye- laws under sub- section (1) the Gram Pan- 
chayat may provide that a contravention thereof shall be punishable 
with such fine as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>226404</tid>
<number>3</number>Any such bye- law may also provide that a person contravening 
the same shall be required to remedy so far as it lies in his power, 
the mischief, if any, caused by such contravention.

</section>

<section><tid>289568</tid>
<number>4</number>All bye- laws made under this section shall be subject to the 
condition of previous publication and such publication shall be in 
such manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>741196</tid>
<number> 80</number> Powers of Zilla parishad to make Regulation.-
<section><tid>1694516</tid>
<number>1</number>A Zilla  
Parishad may subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder and with the previous sanction of the Government, by noti- 
fication, make regulations to carry out the purposes of this Act in so 
far as it relates to its powers and duties.

</section>

<section><tid>1367448</tid>
<number>2</number>The regulations made under sub- section (1) shall be subject 
to the condition of previous publication and such publication shall be 
in such manner as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1785285</tid>
<number> 81</number> Powers of Government to make model regulations and bye- 
laws.-
<section><tid>1504201</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government may, subject to the provisions of this Act  
and the rules made thereunder and after previous publication of the 
draft for not less than one month, make model regulations and bye- laws 
for Zilla Parishads and Grain Panchayats respectively.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>298551</tid>
<number>2</number>A Gram Panchayat or a Zilla Parishad may by resolution adopt 
the model bye- laws or regulations, as the case may be, made under sub- 
section (1), and such bye- laws and regulations shall come into force 
withinq the jurisdiction of the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad from 
such date as the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad as the case may be, 
may specify in a notice published in the prescribed manner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1045904</tid>
<number> 82</number> Power of Government to dissolve and reconstitute Gram 
Panchyat and Zilla Parishad in case of alteration of area.-
<section><tid>1100385</tid>
<number>1</number>When  
on account of the reason that the limits of an area of Gram Panchayat 
or Zilla Parishad, are altered, the Government may by order published 
in the Official Gazette dissolve such Panchayat or Parishad, from a 
date, specified in the order and direct that Gram Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad concerned:-

<subsection><tid>1856572</tid>
<number>i</number>be reconstituted for the Panchayat area of which the 
Gram Panchayat or the district of which Zilla Parishad has 
been dissolved; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1893892</tid>
<number>ii</number>be established for a panchayat area, or district which 
has been newly constituted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1710471</tid>
<number>2</number>The members of the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad which 
has been dissolved under sub- section (1) shall vacate their office 
from the date specified in the order of the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1796943</tid>
<number>3</number>The Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad reconstituted or 
established under the provisions of sub- section (1) shall consist of 
members nominated by the, Government and such members shall as far as 
practicable be persons who are members of the Gram Panchayat or Lila 
Parishad which has been dissolved under sub section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>938042</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairpersons of Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad shall 
be elected in the manner provided in this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1733507</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad so 
reconstituted or established shall be for such period not exceeding 
six months as the Government shall by order specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1920335</tid>
<number>6</number>Before the expiry of the term of the Gram Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad constituted in accordance with the provisions of sub- 
section (5), a Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad shall be constituted 
in the manner provided under this Act
Provided that where the remainder of the period for which the 
dissolved Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad would have continued is 
less than six months it; shall not be necessary to hold an election 
under this section for constituting a Gram Panchayat or a Zilla 
Parishad for such period.


</section>

<section><tid>1773524</tid>
<number>7</number>A Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad constituted under sub- 
section (1) shall continue only for the remainder of the period for 
which the dissolved Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad would have 
continued had it not been so dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>1331953</tid>
<number>8</number>When a Gram Panchayat or a Zilla Parishad has been dissolved 
and reconstituted or established under this section so much of the 
Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad fund and other property vesting in 
the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad which has been. dissolved shall 
vest in and such portion of the debts, and obligations shall be 
transferred to, the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad reconstituted or 
established tinder this section as the Government may direct by an 
Order made in writing.

</section>

<section><tid>1542095</tid>
<number>9</number>The rights and liabilities of the dissolved Gram Panchayat 
or Zilla Parishad in respect of civil and criminal proceedings, 
contracts, agreements and other matters or things arising in and 
relating to any part of the area subject to the authority of the 
Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad reconstituted or established shall 
vest in such Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>1545772</tid>
<number>10</number>Any appointment, notification, notice, tax, order, scheme, 
licence, permission, rule, regulation or form made, issued, imposed or 
granted by the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad which has beer, 
dissolved in respect of any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

part of the area subject to the authority of the Gram Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad which has been reconstituted or established, shall be 
deemed to have been made, issued, imposed or granted by such Gram 
Panchayat or Zilla Parishad unless and until it is suspended by any 
appointment. notification, notice, form, order, scheme, licence, 
permission, rule and regulation made, issued, imposed or granted by 
such Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>186501</tid>
<number> 83</number> Dissolution of Gram Panchayats and Zila Parishad in certain 
other cases.-
<section><tid>69563</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in the opinion of the Zilla Parishad, a Gram  
Panchayat exce or abuses its powers or is not competent to perform or 
makes persistent defaw in the performance of the duties imposed on it 
under this Act or any other la for the time being in force, the Zilla 
Parishad may by order published in the Official Gazette, dissolve such 
Gram Panchayat.

</section>

<section><tid>1887098</tid>
<number>2</number>If in the opinion of the Government, a Zilla Parishad 
exceeds or abuses its powers or is not competent to perform or makes 
persistent default in the performance of the duties imposed on it 
under this Act or any other law for the time being in force, the 
Government may, by an order published in the Official Gazette, 
dissolve such Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>341330</tid>
<number>3</number>Before publishing an order under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2) the Zilla Parishad or the Government shall communicate to 
the Gram Panchayat or to the Zilla Parishad, as the case may be, the 
grounds on which it proposes to do so, and fix a reasonable period for 
the Panchayat concerned to show cause against the proposal and 
consider its explanation and objections, if any.

</section>

<section><tid>1480747</tid>
<number>4</number>When a Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad is dissolved all the 
members of Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad shall, from the date 
specified in the order, vacate their office as such members.

</section>

<section><tid>198565</tid>
<number>5</number>If a Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad is dissolved:-

<subsection><tid>753505</tid>
<number>a</number>all the powers and duties of the Gram Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad shall, during the period of its dissolution be 
exercised and performed by such person or persons as the 
Zilla Parishad or the Government, as the case may be, may 
from time to time, appoint in his behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>196423</tid>
<number>b</number>all property vested in the Gram Panchayat or Zilla 
Parishad shall during the period of dissolution vest in the 
Zilla Parishad or the Government, as the case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>681731</tid>
<number>c</number>the person is vacating office on dissolution shall be 
eligible for reelection.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1277528</tid>
<number> 84</number> Inquiry into the affairs of the panchayats by the 
Government.-
<section><tid>534384</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government may, at any time for reasons to be  
recorded in writing, cause any inquiry to be made by any of its 
officers in regard to any Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad on matters 
concerning it, or any matters with respect to which the sanction, 
approval, consent or orders of the Government is required under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1644563</tid>
<number>2</number>The Officer holding such inquiry shall have the powers of 
the Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>) 
to take evidence and to compel attendance of witnesses and production 
of documents for the purposes of the inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>1051476</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government may make orders as to costs of inquiries made 
under sub- section (1) and as to the parties by whom and the funds out 
of which they shall be paid and such order may, on the application of 
the Commissioner or of any person named therein be executed as if it 
were a decree of a Civil Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>372944</tid>
<number> 85</number> Inspection of Development Schemes.-
<section><tid>721157</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of  
efficient and economical execution of any works development schemes 
undertaken by a Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad an order or person 
authorised by general or special order of the Government officer 
considers it necessary to give technical guidance or assistance, to 
any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officer of or under the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad who is 
charged with the execution or maintenance of any such work or 
development scheme, th the officer or person so authorised may 
periodically inspect such works or development schemes to give such 
guidance, assistance or advise as he thinks necessary in relation to 
such works or development schemes and shall forward to the Gram 
Panchayat or Zilla Parishad a report on the inspection made pointing 
out therein any irregularities noticed, and suggestions for 
improvement.


</section>

<section><tid>1033809</tid>
<number>2</number>In implementation of the plans' or schemes all the rules 
applicable to Government Departments such as for purchase, tender, 
quality control, chnical sanctions, accounts and audit and supervision 
shall mutatis- mutandis te applicable in case of a Panchayat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>61288</tid>
<number> 86</number> Directions from the Government
<section><tid>582601</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in this Act it shall be lawful for the Government to issue 
directions to any Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad in matters relating 
to State and National Policies and such directions shall be binding on 
the Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad.

</section>

<section><tid>1273053</tid>
<number>2</number>The Government may:-

<subsection><tid>1601199</tid>
<number>a</number>call for any record', register or, any other document in 
possession under the control of any Gram Panchayat or Zilla 
Parish.,. O.;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>355625</tid>
<number>b</number>require any Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad to furnish 
in return, plan, estimate, statement, account or statistics; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1772779</tid>
<number>c</number>require any Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad to furnish 
any information or report on any matter connected with such 
Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635314</tid>
<number> 87</number> Commissioner and Chief Executive Officer' s powers in respect 
of Gram Panchayat and Zilla Parishad.
<section><tid>1104201</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Executive Officer  
may in respect of Gram Panchayat exercise the following powers, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1553923</tid>
<number>a</number>call for proceedings of any Gram Panchayat or any 
extract of any book or document in the possession of or under 
the control of the Gram Panchayat or any return or statement 
of account or report;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1305926</tid>
<number>b</number>require a Gram Panchayat, to take into consideration any 
objection which appears to him to exist to the doing of 
anything which is about to be done or is being done by such 
Gram Panchayat or any information which appears to him to 
necessitate the doing of anything by such Gram Panchayat or 
within such period as he may fix;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>507098</tid>
<number>c</number>order a duty to be performed within a specified period 
if a Gram Panchayat has made default in the performance of 
any duty and if such duty is not performed within the 
specified period, to appoint a person to perform such duty 
and direct that the expenses thereof shall be paid by the de- 
faulting Gram Panchayat within such period as he may fix;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>923929</tid>
<number>d</number>direct a Gram Panchayat to levy any tax if it has 
failed to do so in accordance with the provision of this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662901</tid>
<number>e</number>call for meetings of the Gram Panchayat, or any of its 
committees if no meeting of the Gram Panchayat or its 
committees has been held in accordance with the provisions 
of this Act or rules made thereunder.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1784163</tid>
<number>2</number>The Gram Panchayat may appeal to the Commissioner, against 
any order made under clause (c) of sub- section (1) by the Chief 
Executive Officer within thirty days from the date of such order.

</section>

<section><tid>374324</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commissioner may in respect of Zilla Parishad exercise 
the following Powers, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1060311</tid>
<number>a</number>call for proceedings of any Zilla Parishad or any 
extract of any book or document in the possession of or under 
the control of the Zilla Parishad or any return or statement 
of account or report;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929016</tid>
<number>b</number>require a Zilla Parishad, to take into consideration 
any objection which appears to him to exist to the doing of 
anything which is about to be done or is being done by such 
Zilla Parishad or any information which appears to him to 
necessitate the doing of anything by such Zilla Parishad or 
within such period as he may fix;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>778377</tid>
<number>c</number>order a duty to be performed within a specified period 
if a Zilla Parishad has made default in the performance of 
any duty and if such duty is not performed within the 
specified period, to appoint a person to perform such duty 
and direct that the expenses thereof shall be paid by the 
defaulting Zilla Parishad within such period as he may 
fix;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1792603</tid>
<number>d</number>call for meetings of the Zilla Parishad or any of its 
committees if no meeting of the Zilla Parishad or its 
committees has been held in accordance with the provisions of 
this Actor rules made thereunder.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>79407</tid>
<number>4</number>The Zilla Parishad may appeal to the Government, against any 
order made under clause (c) of sub- section (3) by the Commissioner, 
within thirty days from the date of such order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>545312</tid>
<number>88</number>Power of Government and Chief Executive Officer to 
provide for performance of duties in default of Gram Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad.- When the Government in case of a Zilla Parishad and 
the Chief Executive Officer in case of a Gram Panchayat is informed on 
complaint made or otherwise, that any Zilla Parishad or Gram Panchayat 
has made default in performing any duty imposed on it, by or under 
this Act. or by or under any law for the time being in force and if 
the Government or Chief Executive Officer, as the case may be, is 
satisfied after due enquiry that any Lila Parishad or Gram Panchayat, 
has failed in the performance of such duty, the Government or the 
Chief Executive Officer, as the case may be, may fix a period for the 
performance of that duty.
Provided that no such period shall be fixed unless the Zilla 
Parishad or Gram Panchayat concerned has been given an opportunity to 
show cause why such an order shall not be made.



</article>



<article><tid>186258</tid>
<number> 89</number> Zilla Parishad' s power of suspending the executions order 
etc. of Gram Panchayat.-
<section><tid>1865814</tid>
<number>1</number>If in the opinion of the Zilla Parishad  
the execution of any order or resolution of a Gram Panchayat or any 
order of any authority or Officer of a Gram Panchayat or the doing 
anything which is about to be done, or is being done, by or on behalf 
of a Gram Panchayat is unjust, unlawful, improper or is causing or is 
likely to cause injury or annoyance to the public or to lead to a 
breach of the peace, it may by order suspend the execution of or 
prohibit, the doing thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1791785</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Zilla Parishad makes an order under sub- section (1) 
it shall forthwith forward to the Government and to the Gram Panchayat 
affected thereby a copy of the order with a statement of the reasons 
for making it and it shall be in the discretion of the Government to 
confirm or resind the order or to direct that it shall continue to be 
in force with or without modification permanently or for such period 
as it thinks fit:
Provided that no order of the Zilla Parishad made under this 
section shall be confirmed, revised or modified by the Government 
without giving the Gram Panchayat reasonable opportunity of showing 
cause against the said order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>715855</tid>
<number> 90</number> Governments power of suspending execution of unlawfull 
order or resolution.-
<section><tid>670096</tid>
<number>1</number>If on the receipt of a report from the Chief  
Executive Officer in this behalf or otherwise the Government is of the 
opinion that execution of any order or resolution of Zilla Parishad or 
the doing of anything which is about to be done or is being done by on 
behalf of a Zilla Parishad is unjust, unlawful, or improper or is 
causing or is likely to cause injury or annoyance to tile public or to 
lead to a breach of the peace, it may, by an order suspend the 
execution or prohibit the doing thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>339828</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Government makes an order under sub- section (1)- it 
Shall forthwith forward to the Zilla Parishad affected thereby a copy 
of the order with a statement of reasons for making it and the 
Government may confirm or rescind the order or direct that it shall 
continue to be in force with or without modification permanently or 
for such period as it thinks fit:
Provided that no order under this sub- section shall be made by 
the Government without giving the Zilla Parishad concerned a 
reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the said order.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1605123</tid>
<number> 91</number> Purchase of Stores and equipment.-
<section><tid>610016</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government may by  
general or special order provide for all any of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>79794</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which Purchase of stores, equipments, 
machineries and other articles required by the Zilla Parishad 
or Gram Panchayat shall be made by them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>791845</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which tender for works, contracts and 
supplies shall be invited and examined and accepted by the 
Gram Panchayat or Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>378108</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which works, and development schemes may 
be e ecuted and inspected and payment may be made in respect 
of such works an schemes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>678495</tid>
<number>d</number>constitution of committee for the purposes of this sub- 
section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>597978</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided in sub- section (1), in 
respect of all other matters relating to withdrawal of funds, form of 
bins, incurring of expenditure, maintenance of accounts, rendering of 
accounts and such other matters, the rules, of implementation as 
applicable to Departments of the Government shall mutatis mutandis 
apply in case of a Gram Panchayat and Zilla Parishad.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1245265</tid>
<number> 92</number> Power to appoint administrator in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1437831</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Whenever,-

<subsection><tid>734063</tid>
<number>a</number>any general election to a Zilla Parishad under this Act 
or any proceedings consequent thereon has been stayed by an 
order of a competent court, or authority; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>6361</tid>
<number>b</number>all the members or more than two- thirds of the members 
of a Zilla Parishad have resigned,
the Government shall by notification in the Official Gazette appoint 
an Administrator for such period as may be specified in the 
notification and may, by like notification, curtail or extend the 
period of such appointment, so however, that the total period of such 
appointment shall not exceed six months.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>719781</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, on the 
appointment of an Administrator under sub- section (1) the Zilla 
Parishad and the Committees thereof and the Adhyaksha, or Up- 
Adhyaksha of such Zilla Parishad charged with carrying out the 
provisions of this Act, or any other law, shall cease to exercise any 
powers and perform and discharge any duties or functions conferred or 
imposed on them by or under this Act or any other law and all such 
powers shall be exercised and all such duties and functions shall be 
performed and discharged by the Administrator during the period of 
such appointment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1848697</tid>
<number>93</number>Removal of members for misconduct, etc.- The Government if it 
thinks fit on the recommendation of the Gram Panchayat or Zilla 
Parishad or otherwise, may remove any member after giving him an 
opportunity of being heard and after such enquiry as it deems 
necessary if such members has been guilty of misconduct in the 
discharge of his duties or of any disgraceful conduct or has become 
incapable of performing his duties as a member.


</article>



<article><tid>110134</tid>
<number> 94</number> Restrictions on withdrawal of powers and functions from the 
Panchayats.-
<section><tid>641004</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding the transfer of any power, functions  
and duties in respect of any matter to a Panchayat under this Act the 
Government on a proposal from Panchayat in that behalf or where it 
is satisfied that by reason of a change in the nature of the matter 
such as, the conversion of a primary health centre into a secondary 
health centre or hospital or the conversion of a seed multiplication 
farm into an agricultural research farm or a road becoming a part of a 
highway, the matter would cease to be a matter in relevant Panchayat 
functions list and it is necessary to withdraw from the Panchayat 
powers, functions or duties in respect of such matter, may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, withdraw such powers, functions 
and duties with effect from the date specified in the notification and 
make such incidental and consequential orders as may be necessary to 
provide for matters including the taking over of the property, right 
and liabilities, if any vesting in the Panchayat and of the staff, if 
any, which may have been transferred to the Panchayat as the case may 
be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645048</tid>
<number> 95</number> Preparation of development plans.-
<section><tid>1599361</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Grain Panchayat  
shall prepare every year a development plan and submit it to the Zilla 
Parishad before such date and in such form as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>667862</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Zilla Parishad shall prepare every year a development 
plan of the District after including the development plans of the 
Gram Panchayat and submit it to the District Planning Committee 
constituted under section 96 of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>553034</tid>
<number> 96</number> District Planning Committee.-
<section><tid>1639743</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government shall  
constitute in every district a District Planning Committee to 
consolidate the plans prepared by the Zilla Parishad, Gram Panchayats, 
Nagar Panchayat, Municipal Council and Municipal Corporation in the 
district and to prepare a draft development plan for the district as a 
whole.

</section>

<section><tid>1506952</tid>
<number>2</number>The District Planning Committee shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>595966</tid>
<number>a</number>members of the House of the People who represent the 
whole or part of the district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>35907</tid>
<number>b</number>all the members or the State Legislative Assembly whose 
constituencies lie within the district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>178172</tid>
<number>c</number>Adhyaksha of the Zilla Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520120</tid>
<number>d</number>Mayor or the President of the Municipal Corporation or 
the Municipal Council respectively, having jurisdiction over 
the headquarters of the District; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1072051</tid>
<number>e</number>such number of persons not less than four- fifth of the 
total number of members of the Committee as may be specified 
by the Government elected in the prescribed manner from 
amongst the members of the Zilla Parishad, Nagar Panchayat 
and Councillors of the Municipal Corporation and the 
Municipal Councils in the district, in proportion to the 
ratio between the population of the rural areas and of the 
urban areas in the district.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>962299</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman of the District Co- operative Banks and of the 
Land Development Bank shall be permanent invitees of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>733310</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall be the Secretary of the 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>482082</tid>
<number>5</number>The Deputy Commissioner of the districts shall be the 
Chairman of the District Planning Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>256782</tid>
<number>6</number>The District Planning Committee shall consolidate the plans 
prepared by the Zilla Parishad, Gram Panchayat, Nagar Panchayat, Muni- 
cipal Council and the- Municipal Corporations in the district and 
prepare a draft development plan for the district as a whole.

</section>

<section><tid>1777017</tid>
<number>7</number>Every District Planning Committee shall in preparing the 
draft development plan:-

<subsection><tid>1458198</tid>
<number>a</number>have regard to-

<subsubsection><tid>1408723</tid>
<number>i</number>the matters of common interest between the Zilla 
Parishad, Gram Panchayats, Nagar Panchayats, Municipal 
Corporation and Municipal Councils in the district 
including spatial planning sharing of water and other 
physical and natural resource, the integrated 
development of infrastructure and environmental 
conservation,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>798319</tid>
<number>ii</number>the extent and type of available resources whether 
financial or otherwise;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422146</tid>
<number>b</number>consult such institutions and organisations as the 
Government may by order specify.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1298094</tid>
<number>8</number>The Chairman of every District Planning Committee shall 
forward the development plan, as recommended by such Committee lo the 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1553647</tid>
<number> 97</number> Finance Commission for panchayats.-
<section><tid>1041391</tid>
<number>1</number>The Governor shall  
constitute every five years a Finance Commission to review the 
financial position of the Zilla Parishads and Gram Panchayats and to 
make recommendations to the Government as to

<subsection><tid>1430106</tid>
<number>a</number>the principles Which should govern

<subsubsection><tid>1419461</tid>
<number>i</number>the distribution between the State and the Zilla 
Parishads and the Gram Panchayats and the net proceeds 
of the taxes, duties, tolls and fees leviable by the 
Government which may be divided between them and 
allocation between the Zilla Parishad and Gram Panchayat 
 0f their respective shares of such proceeds;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>881586</tid>
<number>ii</number>the determination of the taxes, duties, tolls and 
fees which may be assigned to or appropriated by the 
Zilla Parishad and Gram Panchayat;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>406129</tid>
<number>iii</number>the grants- in- aid to the Zilla Parishads and Gram 
Panchayats from the Consolidated fund of the State.;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1652349</tid>
<number>b</number>the measures needed to improve the financial position 
of the Zilla Parisheds and Gram Panchayats; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>118729</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter referred to the Finance Commission by 
the Governor in the interest of sound finance of the Zilla 
Parishads and Gram Panchayats.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>158053</tid>
<number>2</number>The Finance Commission shall consist of a member.

</section>

<section><tid>959422</tid>
<number>3</number>The member of Finance Commission shall be appointed in such 
manner as may be prescribed from among persons who-

<subsection><tid>1983821</tid>
<number>a</number>have experience in public affairs; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>51682</tid>
<number>b</number>are or have been, or are qualified to be appointed as a 
Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>255962</tid>
<number>c</number>have special knowledge of the finances and accounts of 
Governments; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>307364</tid>
<number>d</number>have had wide experience in inancial matters and in 
administration; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1374980</tid>
<number>e</number>have special knowledge of economics.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>189894</tid>
<number>4</number>The Finance Commission shall determine is procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>176142</tid>
<number>5</number>The member of the Finance Commission may resign his office 
by writing under his hand and addressed to the Governor but he shall 
continue in office until his resignation is accepted by the 
Governor.

</section>

<section><tid>1222056</tid>
<number>6</number>The casual vacancy occurring due to the resignation of the 
member under sub- section (5) or for any other reason may be filled by 
appointment and a member so appointed shall hold office for the 
remaining period for which the member in whose place as he was 
appointed would have held office.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1497352</tid>
<number>7</number>in the performance of its functions, the Commission shall 
have the following powers, namely

<subsection><tid>1444485</tid>
<number>a</number>to call for any record from any officer or authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>250121</tid>
<number>b</number>to summon any person to give evidence or produce 
records; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1816755</tid>
<number>c</number>such other powers as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1549852</tid>
<number>8</number>The Governor shall cause every recommendation made by the 
Finance, Commission under this section together with an explanatory 
memorandum as to the action taken thereon to be laid before the State 
Legislature.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1234764</tid>
<number> 98</number> State Election Commission.-
<section><tid>1140238</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a State  
Election Commission constutied by the Government for superintendence, 
direction and control of the preparation or electoral rolls for, and 
the conduct of all elections to the Panchayat bodies in the State 
under this Act and tile rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>859638</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission shall consist of a State Election 
Commissioner to be appointed by the Governor.

</section>

<section><tid>1668459</tid>
<number>3</number>The conditions of services and tenure of office of the State 
Election Commissioner shall be such as the Governor maybe rule 
determine:
Provided that the State Election Commissioner shall not be 
removed from his office except in like manner and on the like grounds 
as a Judge of the High Court and the conditions of service of the 
State Election Commissioner shall not be varied to his disadvantage 
after his appointment:


</section>

<section><tid>115337</tid>
<number>4</number>The Government shall. when so requested by the State 
Election Commission, make available to the State Election Commission 
such staff as may be necessary for the discharge of the functions 
conferred on the State Election Commission under this Act,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1592096</tid>
<number>99</number>Determination of elected members after Census.- Upon the 
publication of the figures of each Census, the, nuder of elected 
members of a Panchayat shall be determined by the State Government on 
the basis of tile population of the Panchayat area as ascertained at 
that Census
Provided that the determination of the number as aforesaid shall 
no affect the then composition of the Panchayats existing at the time 
of the publication of Census under this section until the expiry of 
its term.



</article>



<article><tid>1219056</tid>
<number>100</number>Qualification of membership for election to Panchayat or 
Zilla Parishad.- Every person whose name is in the list of voters 
within the Grain Panchayat or Zilla Parishad constituency and is 
ordinarily resident within the Grain Panchayat or Zilla Parishad area 
shall, unless disqualified under this Act, or under any other law for 
the time being in force, be qualified to be elected a; a member of the 
Gram Panchayat:
Provided that In the case of seats reserved for the Scheduled 
Castes or Scheduled Tribes or Back- ward Classes and women, no person 
who is not a member of any of the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes 
or Backward Classes or is not a women, as the case may be, shall be 
qualified to be elected to such seat.



</article>



<article><tid>1023368</tid>
<number> 101</number> Disqualification for memberships.-
<section><tid>124325</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be  
disqualified for being chosen and for being a member of a Gram 
Panchayat or Zilla Parishad,-

<subsection><tid>1071790</tid>
<number>a</number>if he has not attained the age of twenty- one years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1814567</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is so disqualified by or under any law for the 
time being in force for the purposes of elections to the 
State Legislatures;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1904693</tid>
<number>c</number>if an order has been passed against him under section 
 117 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>, (2 of <year>1974</year>.) in 
proceedings instituted under section 110 of the Code, such 
order not having been subsequently revised or quashed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1053932</tid>
<number>d</number>if be has been dismissed from the service under any 
local authority; or-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275527</tid>
<number>e</number>if having been a legal or medical practitioner or a 
chartered accountant, his name has been removed from the 
rolls or he is suspended by order of a competent authority, 
the disqualification in the latter case being operative 
during the period of such suspension; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1110551</tid>
<number>f</number>if he has been removed from membership of any local 
authority or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000004</tid>
<number>g</number>if he holds any office of profit under any local or 
other authority subject to the control of the Central 
Government, the State Government or th, Government of any 
other State, other than such offices as are declared by rules 
made under this Act not to disqualify the holder.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this clause, a person shall 
not be deemed to hold any office of profit under the Gram 
Panchayat or Zilla Parishad by reason only that he is a 
Pradhan or Up- Pradhan of the Gram Panchayat or an Adhyaksha 
or Up- Adhyaksha of Zilla Parishad;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446531</tid>
<number>h</number>if save as hereinafter provided he has directly or 
indirectly any share or interest in any work done by order 
of the Gram Panachayat or the Zilla Parishad or in any 
contract or employment with, or under, or by, or on behalf of 
the Gram Panachayat or the Zilla Parishad; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1998649</tid>
<number>i</number>if he is employed as a paid legal practitioner on 
behalf of the Gram Panchayat or the Zilla Parishad or accepts 
employments as legal practitioner against the Gram Panchayat 
or Zilla Parishad; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1857775</tid>
<number>j</number>if arrears of any kind are due by him to the Gram 
Panchayat or the Zilla Parishad under this Act:
Provided that,-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1071790</tid>
<number>a</number>the disqualification in clause (b) shall cease to 
operate after the expiry of the period during which a person 
is ordered to furnish security;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1814567</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualification in clause (d) or clause (e) shall 
cease to operate after the expiry of five years from the date 
of such sentence or dismissal, or disenrolment or earlier by 
an order of the Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1904693</tid>
<number>c</number>the disqualification in clause (f) shall cease to 
operate after the expiry of five years from the date of 
such removal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1053932</tid>
<number>d</number>a person shall not be deemed to have incurred 
disqualification on under clause (h) by reason of his,-

<subsubsection><tid>904906</tid>
<number>i</number>having a share in any join' stock company or a 
share or interest in any association registered under 
the Manipur Societies Registration Act, <year>1989</year> (1 of  
  <year>1990</year>.) in any co- operative society, which shall contract 
with or be employed by or on behalf of the Gram 
Panchayat or the Zilla Parishad; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1962178</tid>
<number>ii</number>having a share or interest in any newspaper in 
which any advertisement relating to the affairs of the 
Gram Panchayat or the Zilla Parishad is inserted; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>499083</tid>
<number>iii</number>holding a debenture or, being otherwise concerned 
in any loan raised by or on behalf of the Gram Panchayat 
or the Zilla Parishad.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1470034</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether a member of a Panchayat 
at any level has become subject to any of disqualification mentioned 
in sub- section (1), the question------------- referred for the 
decision of Election Tribunal.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1583950</tid>
<number>3</number>If a person who is chosen as a member of a Panchayat is or 
become Member of the House of the People, the Council of States, the 
State Legislative Assembly or the State Legislative Council, or is or 
becomes a Municipal Councillor a Councillor of Municipal Corporation 
or a Member of a Sanitary Board, and other Panchayat, then within 
fifteen days from the date of commencement of the term of office of a 
Member of the House of the People, the Council of States, the State 
Legislative Assembly or State Legislative Council or of a Municipal 
Councillor or a Councillor of a Municipal Corporation or a Member of 
such other Panchayat his seat in the Panchayat shall become vacant 
unless he has previously resigned his seat in the House of the People, 
the Council of States, the State Legislative Assembly or the State 
Legislative Council or the Municipal Corporation of the Board or such 
other Panchayat as, the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>778488</tid>
<number> 102</number> Power of State Government to rescind or suspend resolution 
of a Gram Panchayat of Zilla Parishad.-
<section><tid>244004</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may,  
within a Period of six months, by order in writing, rescind any- 
resolution passed by a Gram Panchayat or a Zilla Parishad, if in its 
opinion such resolution,-

<subsection><tid>1314000</tid>
<number>a</number>has not been legally passed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>989633</tid>
<number>b</number>is in excess, or abuse of the powers conferred by, or 
under this Act or in rules made thereunder.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1449594</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government shall, before taking any such action 
under sub- section (1) give the Gram Panchayat or the Zilla Parishad 
concerned an opportunity for making representation against the 
proposed order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>440761</tid>
<number> 103</number> Constitution of Election Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1991373</tid>
<number>1</number>The Government shall  
constitute Election Tribunal consisting of one member to be 
appointed by that Government to dispose of:

<subsection><tid>714089</tid>
<number>i</number>all election petitions challenging elections to a 
Panchayat; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>136845</tid>
<number>ii</number>matters relating to disqualification of a member of the 
Panchayat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1129984</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other election matter,
in such manner as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1172321</tid>
<number>2</number>The Headquarter of the Tribunal shall be at such place as may 
be notified.

</section>

<section><tid>431719</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Election Tribunal made under sub- section 
 (1) shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>246314</tid>
<number> 104</number> Annual Administration Report.-
<section><tid>1657430</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon is may be after  
the first day of April in every year and not later than such date as 
may be fixed by the Government, the Chief Executive Officer of the 
Zilla Parishad shall prepare a report on the administration of the 
Zilla Parishad during the preceding year in such form and with such 
details as the Government may direct and submit the report to the 
Zilla Parishad. After approval, by the Zilla Parishad the report 
shall be submitted to the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1235447</tid>
<number>2</number>The report submitted to the Government under sub- section (1) 
shall together with a memorandum by the Government reviewing the 
working of the, Zilla Parishad be laid before the House of the State 
Legislature.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>699866</tid>
<number> 105</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1998177</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by  
notification In the Official Gazette;, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>720912</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1333416</tid>
<number>a</number>the procedure for convening and holding the meetings of 
Gram Sabha under section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064239</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner for publication of Electoral Rolls of Gram 
Panchayat and the authority competent to publish the same as 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 16;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290814</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner for filing an appeal against the order of 
the authority publishing the Electoral Rolls as referred to 
in sub- section (5) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1318496</tid>
<number>d</number>the rotation of the reserved seats in constituencies of 
a Gram Panchayat under sub- sections (1) and (3) of section 
19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1717083</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure for election of Pradhan and members of 
Gram Panchayat under section 21;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>474440</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner for filling up the casual vacancies in Gram 
Panchayat referred to in sub- section (1) of section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>595973</tid>
<number>g</number>the payment of honorarium and other allowances to 
Pradhan and Up- Pradhan under sub- section (2) of section 27;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53421</tid>
<number>h</number>powers, functions and duties of Pradhan and Up- Pradhan 
as referred to in clause (g) of sub- section (1) and clause 
 (c) of sub- section (2) of section 28;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1494989</tid>
<number>i</number>the authority competant to receive and accept the 
resignation of Pradhan and Up- Pradhan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>526982</tid>
<number>j</number>the officers to whom the notice of meeting of the 
Gram Panchayat is to be forwarded by the Secretary 
under sub- section (3) of section 32;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>542836</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner for co- opting the members by Standing 
Committee under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 38;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>983907</tid>
<number>l</number>the custody in which Gram Panchayat fund shall be kept- 
as referred to in clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 
39;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1613548</tid>
<number>m</number>the procedure for preparation and approval of the 
budget of Gram Panchayat under section 42 and maintenance of 
accounts and its audit under sections 43 and 44;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1564266</tid>
<number>n</number>appointment, terms and conditions of service, pay and 
allowances and other service conditions of the Secretary as 
referred to in section 45;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1952257</tid>
<number>o</number>the manner of election of members to Zilla Parishad 
under section 50;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1906607</tid>
<number>p</number>the manner for filling up the casual vacancy in Zilla 
Parishad referred to in section 51;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>379629</tid>
<number>q</number>the rotation of reserved seats in constituencies of 
Zilla Parishad under sub- sections (1) and (3) of section 52;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>13514</tid>
<number>r</number>the. manner for reservation of seats of Adhyaksha and 
Up- Adhyaksha of Zilla Parishad referred to in sub- section (2) 
of section 54;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1414458</tid>
<number>s</number>salary and allowances of Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha and 
sitting fee and other allowances to the members of Zilla 
Parishad under section 55;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754863</tid>
<number>t</number>powers, functions and duties of Adhyaksha and Up- 
Adhyaksha referred to in section 56;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292879</tid>
<number>u</number>the authority competent to receive and accept the 
resignation of Adhyaksha and Up- Adhyaksha under sub- section 
 (2) of section 57;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>48</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1628288</tid>
<number>v</number>the additional duties to be performed by the Committees 
under sub- section (8) of section 66;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911579</tid>
<number>w</number>the maximum rate of taxes to be levied by a Zilla 
Parishad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>648904</tid>
<number>x</number>preparation and approval of budget for Zilla Parishad 
under section 72;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>175623</tid>
<number>y</number>maintenance of accounts of Zilla Parishad and their 
audit referred to in sections 73 and 74;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1632490</tid>
<number>z</number>the terms and conditions for appointment of Additional 
Chief Executive Officer, Chief Accounts Officer, Chief 
Planning Officer and other staff members under section 75;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1959686</tid>
<number>aa</number>the superintendence and control of the affairs of Zilla 
Parishad by the Chief Executive Officer referred to in 
clauses (c) and (e) of sub- section (1) of section 76;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>714351</tid>
<number>ab</number>the limits of fine to be imposed by Gram Panchayat under 
sub- section (2) of section 79 and the manner of publication 
of bye- laws of Gram Panchayat under sub- section (4) of the 
said section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>222108</tid>
<number>ac</number>the manner for appointment of member of Finance 
Commission referred to in sub- section (3) of section 97.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1357954</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be, after it is made, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in 
session, for a total period of twenty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the successive sessions 
aforesaid. the House agrees in making modification in the rule or that 
the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect 
only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220916</tid>
<number> 106</number> Bar to interference by Courts in electoral matters.- 
Notwithstanding anything in this Act-
<section><tid>1652431</tid>
<number>a</number>the validity of any law relating to the delimitation of 
constituencies or the allotment of seat to such 
constituencies, made or purporting to be made under the 
relevant provision of the Constitution of India shall not be 
called in question in any Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1681544</tid>
<number>b</number>no election to any Panchayat shall be called in 
question in any Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1773778</tid>
<number>107</number>Taking of oath.- Every member, Adhyaksha or Up- Adhyaksha of 
the Zilla Parishad and every Member, Pradhan of Up- Pradhan of a Gram 
Panchayat shall before taking his seat, make at a meeting of the Zilla 
Parishad or Gram Panchayat at, the case may be, an oath or 
affirmation of his allegiance to the Constitution of India in the 
following form, namely:-
I,............................................................... 
being a Member- Adhyaksha Up- Adhyaksha Pradhan Up- Pradhan of 
the.................................... do swear in the name of God 
 (or solemnly affirm) that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the 
Constitution of India as by law established and that I will faithfully 
discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>49</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>911988</tid>
<number> 108</number> Repeal and savings.-
<section><tid>584084</tid>
<number>1</number>The Manipur Panchayati Raj Act,  
 <year>1975</year> (Manipur Act 12 of <year>1975</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1606124</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Manipur Panchayati Raj 
Act, <year>1975</year> (hereinafter referred to as th erepealed Act) the repeal 
shall not affect,-

<subsection><tid>1211581</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operations of the repealed Act or anything 
duly done or suffered thereunder; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>898450</tid>
<number>b</number>any righ, privilege, obligation or liability acuiqured, 
accrued or incurred under the repealed Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1672614</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed under the repealed Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>716600</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceedings or remedy in 
respect of such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid, and any such 
investigation, legal proceedings or remedy may be instituted, 
continued or enforced, and any such penalty, foreiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1892380</tid>
<number>109</number>Removal of difficulties.- If any difficulty arises in giving 
effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government, may by order, 
published in the Official Gazette as the occasion may require, do 
anything which appears to it to be necessary to remove the difficulty.
K. L. MOHANPURIA,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>