<act><tid>538826</tid>
<title>THE BIHAR AND UTTAR PRADESH (ALTERATION OF BOUNDARIES) ACT, <year>1968</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>1968</year>
[ 22nd May, <year>1968</year>]

An Act to provide for the alteration of boundaries of the States of 
Bihar and Uttar Pradesh and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1642237</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Bihar and Uttar 
Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1968</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1592755</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>595028</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the day which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>1746268</tid>
<number>b</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1453305</tid>
<number>c</number>" deep stream", in relation to the river Ganga or the 
river Ghaghra, means the deep stream thereof as 
verified and agreed upon by the State Governments of 
Bihar and Uttar Pradesh after the 30th day of September 
of the year preceding the year in which the appointed 
day falls and before the 1st day of January of the year 
in which the appointed day falls and in default of 
agreement between the State Governments, as determined 
by such authority as may be specified by the Central 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>680430</tid>
<number>d</number>" fixed boundary" means the boundary line demarcated 
under the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 3 in 
relation to the river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as 
the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>717865</tid>
<number>e</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument
<pagefootnote><pagenum>862</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 10- 6- <year>1970</year>: vide Notifn No. G. S. R. 901, dated 9- 6- <year>1970</year>, Gaz of 
India, Extn, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p- 543.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


having the force of law in the whole or in any part of 
the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh;


</section>

<section><tid>1501664</tid>
<number>f</number>" notified order" means an order published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1820455</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>159095</tid>
<number>h</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a 
person who immediately before the appointed day is a 
member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>954137</tid>
<number>i</number>" transferred territories" means,--

<subsection><tid>418441</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the State of Bihar, the 
territories transferred by this Act from that State to 
the State of Uttar Pradesh, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1144736</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the State of Uttar Pradesh, 
the territories transferred by this Act from that State 
to the State of Bihar;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1218947</tid>
<number>j</number>any reference to a district of a State shall be 
construed as a reference to the area physically 
comprised within that district immediately before the 
appointed day.
PART

TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES

PART II

TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98794</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of territories.
<section><tid>1792482</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day,-- 

<subsection><tid>395501</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be added to the State of Bihar--

<subsubsection><tid>605875</tid>
<number>i</number>all the territories of Ballia district of the State 
of Uttar Pradesh lying between the fixed boundary and the 
deep stream of the river Ghaghra, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1783344</tid>
<number>ii</number>all the territories of that district lying between 
the fixed boundary and the deep stream of the river Ganga,
and the said territories shall thereupon cease to form part of the 
State of Uttar Pradesh; and


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1597753</tid>
<number>b</number>there shall be added to the State of Uttar Pradesh--

<subsubsection><tid>1309051</tid>
<number>i</number>all the territories of Saran district of the 
State of Bihar lying between the fixed boundary and the 
deep stream of the river Ghaghra, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>863</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1209569</tid>
<number>ii</number>all the territories of Shahabad district of 
the State of Bihar lying between the fixed boundary and 
the deep stream of the river Ganga,
and the said territories shall thereupon cease to form part 
of the State of Bihar.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>986877</tid>
<number>2</number>The fixed boundary in relation to each of the rivers 
Ganga and Ghaghra shall be demarcated by an authority 
appointed in this behalf by the Central Government so 
as to be generally in conformity with the boundary line 
described in the Schedule in relation to that river:
Provided that in the process of such demarcation, the said 
authority shall have power to rationalise to the extent considered 
necessary by him, the boundary alignment between the high banks of the 
river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as the case may be, and in 
particular shall try--


<subsection><tid>196163</tid>
<number>a</number>to ensure, as far as possible, the stability of the 
boundary pillars and the recognition of the boundary 
alignment both during the dry and flood seasons; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>35418</tid>
<number>b</number>to avoid, as far as possible, the splitting up of the 
existing abadis.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>909263</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of such demarcation,--

<subsection><tid>871644</tid>
<number>a</number>the decision of the said authority on any matter 
relating to the interpretation of any part of the 
description of the boundary given in the Schedule 
 (including the determination of the relevant record  
  referred to in the Explanatory Note to the Schedule) 
shall be final;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1853532</tid>
<number>b</number>the said authority shall have power to determine the 
location of the points at which the boundary pillars 
shall be constructed and to specify the State 
Government which shall be responsible for the 
construction and maintenance of the boundary pillars at 
such points according to such specifications as that 
authority may indicate (the pillars of the same  
specifications being apportioned, as far as practicable 
  equally between the two State Governments), the 
decision of the said authority in regard to these 
matters being final;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1189313</tid>
<number>c</number>it shall be lawful for the said authority and for any 
person specified by such authority to enter upon and 
survey any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>864</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

area in the vicinity of the boundary line and to do all 
other acts as may be necessary.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1336523</tid>
<number>4</number>The authority referred to in sub- section (2) shall also 
prepare a map of the transferred territories showing--

<subsection><tid>383061</tid>
<number>a</number>the deep stream of the river Ghaghra or the river Ganga, 
as the case may be, and the fixed boundary in relation 
to that river;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1704116</tid>
<number>b</number>the names and boundaries of the villages in the 
transferred territories, as indicated by the State 
Government having jurisdiction over the territories 
before their transfer, with reference to the revenue 
record of that Government in force immediately before 
the preparation of such map,
and forward such map to the Central Government who shall cause it to 
be published in the transferred territories in such manner as it 
thinks fit.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1741239</tid>
<number>5</number>As from the appointed day, the State Government of Bihar or 
Uttar Pradesh shall, by order in the Official Gazette, provide for the 
administration of the territories transferred to that State under sub- 
section (1) by including them or any part of them in such district, 
sub- division, police- station or other administrative unit as may be 
specified in the order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1836220</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the 
heading" I. THE STATES"--
<section><tid>1229100</tid>
<number>a</number>for the entry against" 3. Bihar", the following shall be 
substituted, namely:--
" The territories which immediately before the 
commencement of this Constitution were either comprised 
in the Province of Bihar or were being administered as 
if they formed part of that Province and the 
territories specified in clause (a) of sub- section (1) 
of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration  
  of Boundaries) Act, <year>1968</year>, but excluding the territories 
specified in sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar 
and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories) Act, <year>1956</year>, 
and the territories specified in clause (b) of sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the first mentioned Act";


<pagefootnote><pagenum>865</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1493077</tid>
<number>b</number>for the entry against" 13. Uttar Pradesh", the following 
shall be substituted, namely:--
" The territories which immediately before the 
commencement of this Constitution were either comprised 
in the Province known as the United Provinces or were 
being administered as if they formed part of that 
Province and the territories specified in clause (b) of 
sub- section 91 of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar 
Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1968</year>, but 
excluding the territories specified in clause (a) of 
sub- section (1) of section 3 of that Act.".

PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1927182</tid>
<number> 5</number> Construction of Delimitation Orders. As from the appointed 
day, any reference in any order relating to delimitation of 
parliamentary constituencies, assembly constituencies or council 
constituencies--
<section><tid>1342221</tid>
<number>a</number> (i) to the State of Bihar, shall be construed as 
including the territories transferred to that State 
from the State of Uttar Pradesh under clause (a) of 
sub- section (1) of section 3, but excluding the 
territories transferred from the State of Bihar to the 
State of Uttar Pradesh under clause (b) of that sub- 
section;

<subsection><tid>981423</tid>
<number>ii</number>to any district, sub- division, police- station or other 
administrative unit in the State of Bihar, shall be 
construed as including that part of the territories, if 
any, transferred to that State, which is included in 
that district, sub- division, police- station or other 
administrative unit by order made under sub- section (5) 
of section 3;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1117253</tid>
<number>b</number> (i) to the State of Uttar Pradesh, shall be construed as 
including the territories transferred to that State 
from the State of Bihar under clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 3, but excluding the territories 
transferred from the State of Uttar Pradesh to the 
State of Bihar under clause (a) of that sub- section;

<subsection><tid>1536170</tid>
<number>ii</number>to any district, sub- division, police- station or other 
administrative unit in the State of Uttar Pradesh, 
shall be construed as including that part of the 
territories, if any,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>866</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

transferred to that State, which is included in that 
district, sub- division, police- station or other 
administrative unit by order made under sub- section (5) 
of section 3.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>489108</tid>
<number> 6</number> Provision as to sitting members.
<section><tid>377858</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sitting member of  
the House of the People representing any parliamentary constituency 
the extent of which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of 
this Act shall, notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from 
the appointed day, to have been elected to that House by that 
constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>948958</tid>
<number>2</number>Every sitting member of the Legislative Assembly of the State 
of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh representing any assembly constituency the 
extent of which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of this 
Act shall, notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from the 
appointed day, to have been elected to the said Legislative Assembly 
by that constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1047053</tid>
<number>3</number>Every sitting member of the Legislative Council of Bihar or 
Uttar Pradesh representing any council constituency the extent of 
which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of this Act, shall, 
notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from the appointed day, 
to have been elected to the said Legislative Council by that 
constituency as so altered.
PART

HIGH COURTS

PART IV

HIGH COURTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1342294</tid>
<number> 7</number> Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to, 
High Court at Patna.
<section><tid>305638</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided-- 

<subsection><tid>686678</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court at Patna shall, as 
from the appointed day, extend to the territories 
transferred by this Act from the State of Uttar Pradesh 
to the State of Bihar; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>308773</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad shall, as from 
that day, have no jurisdiction in respect of the said 
territories.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1261276</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the 
Chief Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of 
accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances, to be 
proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High Court at 
Patna shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the High Court at Patna.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>867</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>722855</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad shall have, and the High Court at Patna shall not have, 
jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications 
for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and 
other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in 
respect of any order passed by the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad before the appointed day:
Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by 
the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad, it appears to the Chief 
Justice of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the 
High Court at Patna, he shall order that they shall be so transferred 
and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>943593</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad--

<subsection><tid>1721858</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court at Patna by virtue of sub- section 
 (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1528905</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
of Judicature at Allahabad retains jurisdiction by 
virtue of sub- section (3),
shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of the High 
Court of Judicature at Allahabad, but also as an order made by the 
High Court at Patna.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1626775</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court 
at Patna, any such person who immediately before the appointed day is 
an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of 
the High Court at Patna having regard to the transfer of territories 
from the State of Uttar Pradesh to the State of Bihar, shall be 
recognised as an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at 
Patna.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>784780</tid>
<number> 8</number> Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to, 
High Court at Allahabad.
<section><tid>1318563</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided-- 

<subsection><tid>450638</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad shall, as from the appointed day, extend to 
the territories transferred by this Act from the State 
of Bihar to the State of Uttar Pradesh; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>868</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>339615</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court at Patna shall, as from that day, have no 
jurisdiction in respect of the said territories.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1522171</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court at Patna 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the Chief 
Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of accrual of 
the cause of action and other circumstances, to be proceedings which 
ought to be heard and decided by the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad.

</section>

<section><tid>443218</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court at Patna shall 
have, and the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad shall not have, 
jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications 
for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and 
other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in 
respect of any order passed by the High Court at Patna before the 
appointed day:
Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by 
the High Court at Patna, it appears to the Chief Justice of that High 
Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court of 
Judicature at Allahabad, he shall order that they shall be so 
transferred and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred 
accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>345176</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court at Patna--

<subsection><tid>1679086</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad by virtue 
of sub- section (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>817770</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
at Patna retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section 
 (3),
shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of the High 
Court at Patna, but also as an order made by the High Court of 
Judicature at Allahabad.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>621395</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court 
of Judicature at Allahabad, any such person who immediately before the 
appointed day is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at 
Patna as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of the 
High Court of Judicature at Allahabad having regard to the transfer of 
territories from the State of Bihar to the State of Uttar Pradesh, 
shall be recognised as an advocate entitled to practise in the High 
Court of Judicature at Allahabad.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>869</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>311531</tid>
<number>9</number>Right to appear in any proceedings transferred under section 7 
or section 8. Any person who immediately before the appointed day is 
an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at Patna or the 
High Court of Judicature at Allahabad and was authorised to appear in 
any proceedings transferred under section 7 or section 8 shall have 
the right to appear in the High Court to which the proceedings have 
been transferred, in relation to those proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>1730062</tid>
<number> 10</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 7 and 8,--
<section><tid>1195819</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High 
Court at Patna or the High Court of Judicature at 
Allahabad until that Court has disposed of all issues 
between the parties, including any issue with respect 
to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings and 
shall include appeals, applications for leave to appeal 
to the Supreme Court, applications for review, 
petitions for revision and petitions for writs;

</section>

<section><tid>118737</tid>
<number>b</number>references to the High Court at Patna or the High Court 
of Judicature at Allahabad shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>67274</tid>
<number> 11</number> Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred 
territories under existing appropriation Acts.
<section><tid>668770</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the  
appointed day, any Act passed by the Legislature of the State of Bihar 
or Uttar Pradesh before that day for the appropriation of any moneys 
out of the Counsolidated Fund of the State of meet any expenditure in 
respect of any part of the financial year in which the appointed day 
falls shall have effect also in relation to the territories 
transferred to that State by the provisions of Part II and it shall be 
lawful for the State Government to spend any amount in those 
territories out of the amount authorised by such Act to be expended 
for any service in that State.

</section>

<section><tid>1172865</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governor of Bihar or of Uttar Pradesh may, after the 
appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund 
of the State as he deems necessary for any purpose or service in the 
territories transferred to that State for a period of not more than 
six months beginning with the appointed day pending the sanction of 
such expenditure by the Legislature of the State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>870</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1800471</tid>
<number>12</number>Reports relating to accounts of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh. The 
reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India referred to in 
clause (2) of article 151 of the Constitution relation to the accounts 
of the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in respect of any period prior 
to the appointed day shall be submitted to the Governor of each of the 
States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh who shall cause them to be laid 
before the Legislature of the State.
PART

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>60513</tid>
<number> 13</number> Land and goods.
<section><tid>764547</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this  
Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods belonging to 
the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in the transferred territories 
shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State to which the 
territories are transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>1472635</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable 
property of every kind and any rights in or over such property.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>645776</tid>
<number>14</number>Arrears of taxes. The right of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to 
recover arrears of any tax or duty on property situate in the 
transferred territories, including land revenue. or to recover arrears 
of any other tax or duty in any case where the place of assessment of 
that tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall belong to the 
State to which the territories are transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>1622099</tid>
<number>15</number>Right to recover loans and advances. The right to recover any 
loans or advances made before the appointed day by Bihar or Uttar 
Pradesh to any local body, society agriculturist, or other person in 
the transferred territories shall belong to the State to which the 
territories are transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>1843477</tid>
<number>16</number>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of Bihar 
or Uttar Pradesh to refund any tax or duty on property situate in the 
transferred territories, including land revenue, collected in excess 
shall be the liability of the State to which the territories are 
transferred, and the liability of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to refund any 
other tax or duty collected in excess in any case where the place of 
assessment of the tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall 
also be the liability of the State to which the territories are 
transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>1518282</tid>
<number>17</number>Deposits. The liability of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in respect 
of any civil deposit or local fund deposit made in the transferred 
territories shall,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>871</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as from the appointed day, be the liability of the State to which the 
territories are transferred.



</article>



<article><tid>148600</tid>
<number> 18</number> Contracts.
<section><tid>1308265</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, before the appointed day, the State of  
Bihar or Uttar Pradesh has made any contract in the exercise of its 
executive power for any purposes of the State, that contract shall be 
deemed to have been made in the exercise of the executive power--

<subsection><tid>1982314</tid>
<number>a</number>if such purposes are, as from that day, purposes 
relatable exclusively to the transferred territories, 
of the State to which the territories are transferred; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1671483</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, of the State which made the contract,
and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue, 
under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they are rights 
or liabilities of the State which made the contract, be rights or 
liabilities of the State specified in clause (a) or clause (b) above.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1544547</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be 
included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any 
contract--

<subsection><tid>578392</tid>
<number>a</number>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any 
court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the 
contract; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>721085</tid>
<number>b</number>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in 
connection with any such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>903695</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall have effect subject to the other 
provisions of this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities 
in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1324512</tid>
<number> 19</number> Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately 
before the appointed day, the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh is 
subject to any liability in respect of an actionable wrong, other than 
breach of contract, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>1614017</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cause of action arose wholly within the 
transferred territories, be a liability of the State to 
which the territories are transferred; and

</section>

<section><tid>120608</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the 
State which, immediately before that day, was subject 
to such liability.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>872</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1401466</tid>
<number> 20</number> Liability as guarantor of co- operative societies. Where, 
immediately before the appointed day, the State of Bihar or Uttar 
Pradesh is liable as guarantor in respect of any liability of a 
registered co- operative society, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>1781526</tid>
<number>a</number>if the area of the society' s operations is limited to 
the transferred territories, be a liability of the 
State to which the territories are transferred; and

</section>

<section><tid>1706602</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the 
State which, immediately before that day, was subject 
to such liability.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1800405</tid>
<number>21</number>Items in suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately 
found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any 
of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in 
accordance with that provision.


</article>



<article><tid>642092</tid>
<number>22</number>Apportionment of assets or liabilities by agreement. Where 
the States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh agree that the benefit or burden 
of any particular asset or liability should be apportioned between 
them in a manner other than that provided for in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part, then, notwithstanding anything contained 
therein, the benefit or burden of that asset or liability shall be 
apportioned in the manner agreed upon.


</article>



<article><tid>1105509</tid>
<number>23</number>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment 
in certain cases. Where, by virtue of any of the provisions of this 
Part, either of the States of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh becomes subject 
to any liability, and the Central Government, on a reference made 
within a period of three years from the appointed day by either of the 
States, is of opinion that it is just and equitable that property or 
those benefits should be transferred to, or shared with, the other 
State or that a contribution towards that liability should be made by 
the other State, the said property or benefits shall be allocated in 
such manner between the two States, or the other State shall make to 
the State subject to the liability such contribution in respect 
thereof, as the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
two State Governments, by order determine.


</article>



<article><tid>474431</tid>
<number>24</number>Expenditure to be charged on the Consolidated Fund. All sums 
payable by either Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to the other State by virtue 
of the provisions of this Part shall be charged on the Consolidated 
Fund of the State by which such sums are payable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>873</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART VII

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1608228</tid>
<number> 25</number> State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As 
from the appointed day--
<section><tid>927078</tid>
<number>a</number>the Financial Corporation constituted under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>.), for the 
States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh, and

</section>

<section><tid>465805</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the 
Electricity (Supply) Act, <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>.), for the 
said States,
shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their 
areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>452593</tid>
<number>26</number>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of section 3 shall 
not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which 
any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or 
applies, and territorial references in any such law to the State of 
Bihar or Uttar Pradesh shall, until otherwise provided by a competent 
Legislature or other competent authority, be construed as meaning the 
territories within that State immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>1733950</tid>
<number>27</number>Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application of any law in relation to the State of Bihar or Uttar 
Pradesh, the appropriate Government may, before the expiration of one 
year from the appointed day, by order make such adaptations and 
modifications of the law, whether by way of repeal or amendment as may 
be necessary or expedient, and thereupon every such law shall have 
effect subject to the adaptations or modifications so made until 
altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or other 
competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated 
in the Union List, the Central Government, and as respects any other 
law, the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1062391</tid>
<number>28</number>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made for the adaptation of a law made 
before the appointed day, any court, tribunal or authority, required 
or empowered to enforce such law may, for the purpose of facilitating 
its application in relation to the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh, 
construe the law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as 
may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court, 
tribunal or authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>874</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>555909</tid>
<number>29</number>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh is a party to any legal 
proceedings with respect to any property, rights or liabilities 
transferred to the other State under this Act, the other State shall 
be deemed to be substituted for the State from which such property 
rights or liabilities are transferred as a party to those proceedings, 
or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the proceedings 
may continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>755159</tid>
<number> 30</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>711825</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh shall, if it is a 
proceeding relatable exclusively to any part of the territories which 
as from that day are the territories of the other State, stand 
transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in the other State.

</section>

<section><tid>893006</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
High Court having jurisdiction in respect of the area in which the 
court, tribunal, authority or officer before which, or before whom, 
such proceeding is pending on the appointed day, is functioning, and 
the decision of that High Court shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1572870</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section,--

<subsection><tid>441213</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>427174</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
a State means--

<subsubsection><tid>1829282</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in 
which, or before whom, the proceeding would have lain 
if the proceeding had been instituted after the 
appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1773931</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State as may be determined 
after the appointed day by the Government of that 
State, or before the appointed day by the Government of 
the other State, to be the corresponding court, 
tribunal, authority or officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1784325</tid>
<number>31</number>Right of pleaders to practise in certain courts. Any person 
who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the transferred 
territories shall, for a period of six months from

<pagefootnote><pagenum>875</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

that day, continue to be entitled to practise in those courts, 
notwithstanding that the whole or any part of the territories within 
the jurisdiction of those courts has been transferred to another 
State.



</article>



<article><tid>883803</tid>
<number> 32</number> Construction of boundary pillars, etc.
<section><tid>1930726</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be lawful  
for the State Government which is responsible for the construction of 
any boundary pillar under sub- section (3) of section 3 to cause such 
pillar to be constructed and maintained and no suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government or any 
of its officers for anything in good faith done or intended to be done 
under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1020374</tid>
<number>2</number>The boundary pillars shall be inspected jointly by the 
officers of the State Governments of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh in 
accordance with such rules as the Central Government may make in this 
behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>760209</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever wilfully removes or injures any boundary pillar shall 
be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which 
may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1296804</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>.), an offence under sub- section (3) may be 
inquired into and tried by a court in either of the States of Bihar 
and Uttar Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>717381</tid>
<number>33</number>Validity of demarcation done before commencement of Act. All 
things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement of this Act 
in connection with the demarcation of the fixed boundary in relation 
to the river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as the case may be, shall, in 
so far as they are in conformity with the provisions of sub- sections 
 (2) and (3) of section 3, be deemed to have been done in accordance 
with law.


</article>



<article><tid>1093234</tid>
<number>34</number>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding any law, 
custom or usage which is inconsistent therewith.


</article>



<article><tid>74151</tid>
<number>35</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
notified order, do anything, not inconsistent with such provisions 
which appears to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>1035959</tid>
<number> 36</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1105705</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>876</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1229407</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>