<act><title>THE ARMED FORCES TRIBUNAL (FINANCIAL AND 
ADMINISTRATIVE POWERS) RULES, 20081 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number>Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Armed Forces Tribunal (Financial and Administrative Powers) Rules, 
2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication 
in Official Gazette. 
 ___________
 </section></article><article><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 25(E), dated 12th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra, Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 12th September, 
2008. 
 </article><article><number>2</number> Came into force on 12-9-2008 . 
  
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act' means the Armed Forces Tribunals Act, 2007 (55 of 2007); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Tribunal; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Tribunal means the Armed Forces Tribunal. </section>
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 25(E), dated 12th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra, Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 12th September, 
2008. 
  
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Sitting of an additional Bench at place other than the place where 
it shall ordinarily sit. </title>If at any time the Vice-Chairperson/Member of 
any additional Bench is satisfied that circumstances exist which render it 
necessary to have sitting of the said Bench at any place falling within its 
territorial jurisdiction, other than the place or places at which it ordinarily 
sits, he may with the previous consent of the Chairperson direct that the 
additional Bench shall hold its sittings at any such appropriate place. .
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 25(E), dated 12th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra, Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 12th September, 
2008. 
  
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number>Powers of Chairperson. </title>The Chairperson shall have the 
same powers as are conferred on a Department of the Central Government in 
respect of the delegation of Financial Powers Rules, 1978, the General Financial 
Rules, 1963, the Fundamental and Supplementary Rules, the Central Civil Services 
(Leave) Rules, 1972, the Central Civil Services (Joining Time) Rules, 1979, the 
Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, the Central Civil Services 
(Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965 and the General Provident Fund 
(Central Services) Rules, 1960: 
 Provided that the exercise of the financial powers shall be subject to any 
procedural or other instructions issued from time to time by the Government and 
after obtaining the advice of the Financial Adivser and Chief Accounts Officer 
of the Tribunal: 
 Provided further that in respect of matters not within the competence of the 
Chairperson, concurrence of the Ministry of Finance or any other authority shall 
be obtained by the Chairperson through the Ministry of Defence. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 25(E), dated 12th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra, Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 12th September, 
2008. 
  
  
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>