<act><title>

    THE ENEMY PROPERTY ACT, 1968</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, Application and Commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Enemy Property Act, 1968.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir and it applies 
    also to all citizens of India outside India and to branches and agencies 
    outside India of companies or bodies corporate registered or incorporated in 
    India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    be deemed to have come into force on the 10th day of July, 1968.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Custodian” means the Custodian of 
    Enemy Property for India appointed or deemed to have been appointed under 
    section 3 and includes a Deputy Custodian and an Assistant Custodian of 
    Enemy Property appointed or deemed to have been appointed under that 
    section; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “enemy” or “enemy subject” or 
    “enemy firm” means a person or country who or which was an enemy, an enemy 
    subject or an enemy firm, as the case may be, under the Defence of India 
    Act, 1962, and the Defence of India Rules, 1962, 
1[or 
    the Defence of India Act, 1971 and the Defence of India Rules, 1971] but 
    does not include a citizen of India;
2[or 
    the Defence of India Act, 1971 and the Defence of India Rules, 1971] but 
    does not include a citizen of India;" 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “enemy property” means any property for 
    the time being belonging to or held or managed on behalf of an enemy, an 
    enemy subject or an enemy firm:  
 
Provided that where an individual enemy 
    subject dies in the territories to which this Act extends, any property 
    which immediately before his death, belonged to or was held by him or was 
    managed on his behalf, may, notwithstanding his death, continue to be 
    regarded as enemy property for the purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Appointment of custodian of enemy property for india and deputy Custodian, 
    etc.—The Central Government may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a Custodian of Enemy 
    Property for India and one or more Deputy Custodians and Assistant 
    Custodians of Enemy Property for such local areas as may be specified in the 
    notification: 
 
Provided 
    that the Custodian of Enemy Property for India and any Deputy Custodian or 
    Assistant Custodian of Enemy Property appointed under the Defence of India 
    Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971] shall be deemed to have been appointed under this 
    section. 
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Appointment of inspectors of enemy property.—The 
    Central Government may, either generally or for any particular area, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint one or more Inspectors of 
    Enemy Property for securing compliance with the provisions of this Act and 
    may, by general or special order, provide for the distribution and 
    allocation of the work to be performed by them for securing such compliance: 
 
Provided 
    that every Inspector of Enemy Firms appointed under the Defence of India 
    Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971, as the case may be] shall be deemed to be an Inspector of 
    Enemy Property appointed under this section. 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Property vested in the Custodian of enemy property for India under the 
    defence of India Rules, 1962 to continue to vest in Custodian.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Notwithstanding the expiration of the Defence of India Act, 1962 and the 
    Defence of India Rules, 1962, all enemy property vested before such 
    expiration in the Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed under the 
    said Rules and continuing to vest in him immediately before the commencement 
    of this Act, shall, as from such commencement, vest in the Custodian.—3[(1)] 
    Notwithstanding the expiration of the Defence of India Act, 1962 and the 
    Defence of India Rules, 1962, all enemy property vested before such 
    expiration in the Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed under the 
    said Rules and continuing to vest in him immediately before the commencement 
    of this Act, shall, as from such commencement, vest in the Custodian." 
 


    2[(2) Notwithstanding 
    the expiration of the Defence of India Act, 1971 and the Defence of India 
    Rules, 1971, all enemy property vested before such expiration of the 
    Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed under the said Rules and 
    continuing to vest in him immediately before the commencement of the Enemy 
    Property (Amendment) Act, 1977 shall, as from such commencement, vest in the 
    custodian.] 
 
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Transfer 
    of property vested in Custodian by enemy or enemy subject or enemy firm.—Where 
    any property vested in the Custodian under this Act has been transferred, 
    whether before or after the commencement of this Act, by an enemy or an 
    enemy subject or an enemy firm and where it appears to the Central 
    Government that such transfer is injurious to the public interest or was 
    made with a view to evading or defeating the vesting of the property in the 
    Custodian, then, the Central Government may, after giving a reasonable 
    opportunity to the transferee to be heard in the matter, by order, declare 
    such transfer to be void and on the making of such order, the property shall 
    continue to vest or be deemed to vest in the Custodian. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Payment to Custodian of money otherwise payable to an enemy, enemy subject 
    or enemy firm.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any sum payable by way of dividend, interest, share profits or otherwise to 
    or for the benefit of an enemy or an enemy subject or an enemy firm shall, 
    unless otherwise ordered by the Central Government, be paid by the person by 
    whom such sum would have been payable but for the prohibition under the 
    Defence of India is Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971], to the Custodian or such person as may be authorised by 
    him in this behalf and shall be held by the Custodian or such person subject 
    to the provisions of this Act.—(1) 
    Any sum payable by way of dividend, interest, share profits or otherwise to 
    or for the benefit of an enemy or an enemy subject or an enemy firm shall, 
    unless otherwise ordered by the Central Government, be paid by the person by 
    whom such sum would have been payable but for the prohibition under the 
    Defence of India is Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971], to the Custodian or such person as may be authorised by 
    him in this behalf and shall be held by the Custodian or such person subject 
    to the provisions of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    cases in which money would, but for the prohibition under the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971], be payable in a foreign currency to or for the benefit 
    of an enemy or an enemy subject or an enemy firm (other than cases in which 
    money is payable under a contract in which provision is made for a specified 
    rate of exchange), the payment shall be made to the Custodian in rupee 
    currency at the middle official rate of exchange fixed by the Reserve Bank 
    of India on the date on which the payment became due to that enemy, enemy 
    subject or enemy firm. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Custodian shall, subject to the provisions of section 8, deal with any money 
    paid to him under the Defence of India Rules, 1962, 

    1[or the Defence of 
    India Rules, 1971] or under this Act and any property vested in him under 
    this Act in such manner as the Central Government may direct. 
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Powers 
    of Custodian in respect of enemy property vested in him.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With respect to the property vested in the Custodian under this Act, the 
    Custodian may take or authorise the taking of such measures as he considers 
    necessary or expedient for preserving such property and where such property 
    belongs to an individual enemy subject, may incur such expenditure out of 
    the property as he considers necessary or expedient for the maintenance of 
    that individual or of his family in India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, the Custodian or 
    such person as may be specifically authorised by him in this behalf, may for 
    the said purpose,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    carry on the business of the enemy; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    take action for recovering any money 
    due to the enemy; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    make any contract and execute any 
    document in the name and on behalf of the enemy; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    institute, defend or continue any suit 
    or other legal proceeding, refer any dispute to arbitration and compromise 
    any debts, claims or liabilities; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    raise on the security of the property 
    such loans as may be necessary; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    incur out of the property any 
    expenditure including the payment of any taxes, duties, cesses and rates to 
    Government or to any local authority and of any wages, salaries, pensions, 
    provident fund contributions to, or in respect of, any employee of the enemy 
    and the repayment of any debts due by the enemy to persons other than 
    enemies; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    transfer by way of sale, mortgage or 
    lease or otherwise dispose of any of the properties; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    invest any moneys held by him on 
    behalf of enemies for the purchase of Treasury Bills or such other 
    Government securities as may be approved by the Central Government for the 
    purpose; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>    make payments to the enemy and his 
    dependants; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    make payments on behalf of the 
    enemy to persons other than those who are enemies, of dues outstanding on 
    the 25th October, 1962 
1[or 
    on the 3rd December, 1971]; and
1[or 
    on the 3rd December, 1971]; and" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>    make such other payments out of the 
    funds of the enemy as may be directed by the Central Government. 
 
Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section and in sections 10 and 17, “enemy” includes an enemy 
    subject and an enemy firm. 
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Exemption from attachment, etc.—All 
    enemy property vested in the Custodian under this Act shall be exempt from 
    attachment, seizure or sale in execution of decree of a civil court or 
    orders of any other authority. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Transfer of Securities belonging to an enemy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, in exercise of the powers conferred by section 8, the Custodian 
    proposes to sell any security issued by a company and belonging to an enemy, 
    the company may, with the consent of the Custodian, purchase the securities, 
    notwithstanding anything to the contrary in any law or in any regulations of 
    the company and any securities so purchased may be re-issued by the company 
    as and when it thinks fit so to do.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    Custodian executes and transfers any securities issued by a company, the 
    company shall, on receipt of the transfer and an order in this behalf from 
    the Custodian, register the securities in the name of the transferee 
    notwithstanding that the regulations of the company do not permit such 
    registration in the absence of the certificate, script or other evidence of 
    title relating to the securities transferred:  
 
Provided that 
    any such registration shall be without prejudice to any lien or charge in 
    favour of the company and to any other lien or charge of which the Custodian 
    gives express notice to the company.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this section, “securities” includes shares, stock, bonds, debentures and 
    debenture stock but does not include bills of exchange. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Power 
    of custodian to summon persons and call for documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Custodian may, by notice in writing, require any person whom he believes 
    to be capable of giving information concerning any enemy property to attend 
    before him at such time and place as may be specified in the notice and 
    examine any such person concerning the same reduce his statement to writing 
    and require him to sign it. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Custodian may, by notice in writing, require any person whom he believes to 
    have in his possession or control any account book, letter book, invoice, 
    receipt or other document of whatever nature relating to any enemy property, 
    to produce the same or cause the same to be produced before the Custodian at 
    such time and place as may be specified in the notice and to submit the same 
    to his examination and to allow copies of any entry therein or any part 
    thereof to be taken by him. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Protecton for complying with orders of Custodian.—Where 
    any order with respect to any money or property is addressed to any person 
    by the Custodian and accompanied by a certificate of the Custodian that the 
    money or property is money or property vested in him under this Act, the 
    certificate shall be evidence of the facts stated therein and if that person 
    complies with the orders of the Custodian, he shall not be liable to any 
    suit or other legal proceeding by reason only of such compliance. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Validity of action taken in pursuance of 
      orders of Custodian.—Where 
      under this Act,— 
 <section><number>a</number>    any money is paid 
      to the Custodian; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    any property is 
      vested in the Custodian or an order is given to any person by the 
      Custodian in relation to any property which appears to the Custodian to be 
      enemy property vested in him under this Act, neither the payment, vesting 
      nor order of the Custodian nor any proceedings in consequence thereof 
      shall be invalidated or affected by reason only that at a material time,— 
 <subsection><number>i</number>    some person who 
      was or might have been interested in the money or property, and who was an 
      enemy or an enemy firm, has died or had ceased to be an enemy or an enemy 
      firm; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    some person who 
      was so interested and who was believed by the Custodian to be an enemy or 
      an enemy firm, was not an enemy or an enemy firm. 
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Proceedings against companies whose assets vest in Custodian.—Where 
    the enemy property vested in the Custodian under this Act consists of assets 
    of a company, no proceeding, civil or criminal, shall be instituted under 
    the Companies Act, 1956, against the company or any director, manager or 
    other officer thereof except with the consent in writing of the Custodian. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Returns 
    as to enemy property.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Custodian may call for from persons who, in his opinion, have any interest 
    in, or control over, any enemy property vested in him under this Act, such 
    returns as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person from whom a return is called for under sub-section (1) shall be bound 
    to submit such return within the prescribed period. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Registers of returns.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
    returns relating to enemy property submitted to the Custodian under this Act 
    shall be recorded in such registers as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All such 
    registers shall be open to inspection subject to the payment of such fees as 
    may be prescribed and to such reasonable restrictions as the Custodian may 
    impose, to any person who, in the opinion of the Custodian, is interested in 
    any particular enemy property as a creditor or otherwise and any such person 
    may also obtain a copy of the relevant portion form the registers on payment 
    of the prescribed fees. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Levy of 
    fees.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be levied 
    by the Custodian fees equal to two per centum of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the amount of moneys paid to him; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the proceeds of the sale or transfer of 
    any property which has been vested in him under this Act; and  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the value of the residual property, if 
    any, at the time of its transfer to the original owner or other person 
    specified by the Central Government under section 18: 
 
Provided that 
    in the case of an enemy whose property is allowed by the Custodian to be 
    managed by some person specially authorised in that behalf, there shall be 
    levied a fee of two per centum of the gross income of the enemy or such less 
    fee as may be specifically fixed by the Central Government after taking into 
    consideration the cost of direct management incurred by that Government, the 
    cost of superior supervision and any risks that may be incurred by that 
    Government in respect of the management: 
 
Provided 
    further that the Central Government may, for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing, reduce or remit the fees leviable under this sub-section in any 
    special case or class of cases.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section “gross income of the enemy” means income derived out of the 
    properties of the enemy vested in the Custodian under this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The value 
    of any property for the purpose of assessing the fees shall be the price 
    which, in the opinion of the Central Government or of an authority empowered 
    in this behalf by the Central Government, such property would fetch if sold 
    in the open market.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fees 
    in respect of property may be levied out of any proceeds of the sale or 
    transfer thereof or out of any income accrued therefrom or out of any other 
    property belonging to the same enemy and vested in the Custodian under this 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The fees 
    levied under this section shall be credited to the Central Government. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Divesting of enemy property vested in the custodian.—The 
    Central Government may, by general or special order, direct that any enemy 
    property vested in the Custodian under this Act and remaining with him shall 
    be divested from him and be returned, in such manner as may be prescribed, 
    to the owner thereof or to such other person as may be specified in the 
    direction and thereupon such property shall cease to vest in the Custodian 
    and shall revest in such owner or other person. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number> Protection of action taken under the 
      act.—No suit, prosecution or 
      other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the 
      Custodian or an Inspector of Enemy Property for anything which is in good 
      faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> If any person makes 
    any payment in contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 
    7, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    six months, or with fine, or with both and the payment or dealing shall be 
    void. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person contravenes the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 10, he shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, 
    or with fine, or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    person fails to comply with a requisition made by the Custodian under 
    sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 11, he shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any 
    person fails to submit the return under sub-section (2) of section 15, or 
    furnishes such return containing any particular which is false and which he 
    knows to be false or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, 
    at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible 
    to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as 
    the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission 
    of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm.
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number> Effect of laws in consistent with the 
      act.—The provisions of this Act 
      shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
      contained in any other law for the time being in force. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide 
    for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the returns that may be called for by 
    the Custodian under sub-section (1) of section 15 and the period within 
    which such returns shall be submitted under sub-section (2) of that section; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the registers in which the returns 
    relating to enemy property shall be recorded under section 16; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the fees for the inspection of 
    registers and for obtaining copies of the relevant portions from the 
    registers under sub-section (2) of section 16; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the manner in which enemy property 
    vested in the Custodian may be returned under section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any other matter which has to be or may 
    be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government under this section shall be laid, 
    as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it 
    is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
    one session 

    1[or in two or more 
    successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Certain orders made under the Defence of India Rules, 1962, to continue in 
    force.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Every order which was made under the Defence of India Rules, 1962, by the 
    Central Government or by the Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed 
    under those Rules, relating to enemy property and which was in force 
    immediately before the expiration thereof shall, in so far as such order is 
    not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to continue in 
    force and to have been made under this Act.—2[(1)] 
    Every order which was made under the Defence of India Rules, 1962, by the 
    Central Government or by the Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed 
    under those Rules, relating to enemy property and which was in force 
    immediately before the expiration thereof shall, in so far as such order is 
    not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to continue in 
    force and to have been made under this Act." 
 


    2[(2) Every order 
    which was made under the Defence of India Rules, 1971 by the Central 
    Government or by the Custodian of Enemy Property for India appointed under 
    those rules relating to enemy property and which was in force immediately 
    before the expiration thereof shall, in so far as such order is not 
    inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to continue in force 
    and to have been made under this Act.] 
 
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Enemy 
    Property Ordinance, 1968, is hereby repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of this Act. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>