<act><tid>1568486</tid>
<title>THE COLONIAL COURTS OF ADMIRALTY (INDIA) ACT, <year>1891</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1891</year>
[ 14th May, <year>1891</year>.]

An Act t declare certain courts in India to be Colonial Courts of 
Admiralty.

WHEREAS it is provided by the Colonial Courts of Admiralty Act, 
 <year>1890</year> (53 and 54 Vict., c. 27), that the legislature of a British posses- 
sion may by any colonial law declare any court of unlimited civil jur- 
isdiction in that possession to be a Colonial Court of Admiralty;

And whereas it is expedient, in pursuance of that provision, to 
declare certain Courts in India to be Colonial Courts of Admiralty;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>918855</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and commencement.
<section><tid>1444763</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Colonial 
Courts of Admiralty (India) Act, <year>1891</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>1866260</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into effect-

<subsection><tid>1290788</tid>
<number>a</number>If Her Majesty' s pleasure thereon has been signified, 
by 1 notification in the Official Gazette, on or before the 
first day of July, <year>1891</year>, then on that day, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1837574</tid>
<number>b</number>If Her Majesty' s pleasure thereon has not been so 
signified on or before that day, then on the day on which Her 
Majesty' s pleasure shall be signified by such a notification 
as aforesaid.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297323</tid>
<number> 2</number> Appointment of Colonial Courts of Admiralty. The following 
Courts of unlimited civil jurisdiction are hereby declared to be 
Colonial Courts of Admiralty, namely:-
<section><tid>1202111</tid>
<number>1</number>the High Court of Judicature at Fort William in Bengal,

</section>

<section><tid>1633917</tid>
<number>2</number>the High Court of Judicature at Madras, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and]

</section>

<section><tid>126329</tid>
<number>3</number>the High Court of Judicature at Bombay, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>34016</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of Indian Acts referring to Admiralty and Vice- 
Admiralty Courts. The expressions" Court having Admiralty 
jurisdiction" and Admiralty Court" and the expression" Admiralty or 
Vice- Admiralty cause," and other expressions referring to Admiralty or 
Vice- Admiralty Courts or causes, shall, wherever any such expression 
occurs in any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For notification publishing Her Britannic Majesty' s Assent to 
this Act, see Gazette of India, <year>1891</year>, Pt. I, p. 371.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The word" and" was rep. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words and figures" (4) the High Court of Judicature at 
Rangoon, (5) the Court of the Resident at Aden, and" were rep. by the 
A. O. <year>1937</year> and" (6) the District Court of Karachi" rep. by the A. O. 
<year>1948</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Indian law], be deemed to include a Colonial Court of Admiralty and 
a Colonial Court of Admiralty cause, and to refer to a Colonial Court 
of Admiralty or a Colonial Court of Admiralty cause, respectively.



</article>



<article><tid>746740</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Court- fees in suits in the Colonial Court of Admiralty at 
Karachi]. Rep. by the A. O. <year>1947</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1584713</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Repeal.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1914</year> (10 of  
  <year>1914</year>).
THE SCHEDULE.[ ENACTMENTS REPEALED.][ Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1914</year> (10 of <year>1914</year>).]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" enactment of the G. G. in C. or 
or Lieutenant- Governor in Council".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>