<act><title>THE DELHI SPECIAL POLICE ESTABLISHMENT ACT, 1946</title> 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to 

1[the whole of 
India], 

2[***].



</section></article> 



 <article>

1[<number>1A</number> 
Interpretation section.—Words 
and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Central 
Vigilance Commission Act, 2003, shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned 
to them in that Act.]
 
 



</article> 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Constitution and 
powers of special police establishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything in the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), the Central 
Government may constitute a special police force to be called the Delhi Special 
Police Establishment 

1[***] for the 
investigation 

2[in any 

3[Union 
territory]] of offences notified under section 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to any orders 
which the Central Government may make in this behalf, members of the said 
police establishment shall have throughout 

4[any 

5[Union 
territory]] in relation to the investigation of such offences and arrest of 
persons concerned in such offences, all the powers, duties, privileges and 
liabilities which police officers of 

6[that Union 
territory] have in connection with the investigation of offences committed 
therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any member of the 
said police establishment of or above the rank of Sub-Inspector may, subject to 
any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, exercise in


7[any 

5[Union 
territory]] any of the powers of the officer in charge of a police station in 
the area in which he is for the time being and when so exercising such powers 
shall, subject to any such orders as aforesaid, be deemed to be an officer in 
charge of a police station discharging the functions of such an officer within 
the limits of his station.
 
 
 
­—————
 </section><section>
   <number>1</number>  The words “for the 
State of Delhi” omitted by  Act 26 of 1952, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).
 </section></article><article>
   <number>2</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1952, sec. 3, for  “any Part C States” (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).
 </article><article>
   <number>3</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
(No. 3), 1956, for “Part C States”.
 </article><article>
   <number>4</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1952, sec. 3, for “the State of Delhi” (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).
 </article><article>
   <number>5</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
(No. 3), 1956, for “Part C States”. 
 </article><article>
   <number>6</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
1956, for “that State”.
 </article><article>
   <number>7</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1952, sec. 3, for  “any Part C States” (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).
 
 
</article> 



 <article>
<number>3</number> Offences to be 
investigated by special police establishment.—The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify the 
offences or classes of offences 

1[***] which are 
to be investigated by the Delhi Special Police Establishment.






</article> 



 <article>

1[<number>4</number> 
Superintendence and administration of Special Police Establishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The superintendence of the Delhi Special Police Establishment insofar as it 
relates to investigation of offences alleged to have been committed under the 
Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), shall vest in the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in sub-section (1), the superintendence of the said police 
establishment in all other matters shall vest in the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The administration of 
the said police establishment shall vest in an officer appointed in this behalf 
by the Central Government (hereinafter referred to as the Director) who shall 
exercise in respect of that police establishment such of the powers exercisable 
by an Inspector-General of Police in respect of the police force in a State as 
the Central Government may specify in this behalf.]





</section></article> 



 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Committee for 
appointment of Director.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall appoint the Director on the recommendation of the 
Committee consisting of:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the Central 
Vigilance Commissioner                Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Vigilance 
Commissioners                               Members;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  Secretary to 
the Government of India  
in-charge of the Ministry of Home   
Affairs in the Central Government                  Member;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>  the 
Secretary to the Government of India 
 
in-charge of the 
Ministry or Department  
of the Central Government having  
administrative control of the Delhi  
Special Police Establishment]                        Member.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> While making any 
recommendation under sub-section (1), the Committee shall take into 
consideration the views of the outgoing Director.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Committee shall 
recommend a panel of officers—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  on the basis 
of seniority, integrity and experience in the investigation of anti-corruption 
cases; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  chosen from 
amongst officers belonging to the Indian Police Service constituted under the 
All-India Services Act, 1951 (61 of 1951), 
 
for being considered for 
appointment as the Director.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 



 <article>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>4B</number> Terms and 
conditions of service of Director.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
rules relating to his conditions of service, continue to hold office for a 
period of not less than two years from the date on which he assumes office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director shall 
not be transferred except with the previous consent of the Committee referred 
to in sub-section (1) of section 4A.]
 




</section></article> 



 <article>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>4C</number> Appointment for 
posts of Superintendent of Police and above, extension and   curtailment of 
their tenure, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Committee referred to in section 4A shall, after consulting the Director, 
recommend officers for appointment to the posts of the level of Superintendent 
of Police and above and also recommend the extension or curtailment of the 
tenure of such officers in the Delhi Special Police Establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the 
recommendation under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall pass such 
orders as it thinks fit to give effect to the said recommendation.]
 




</section></article> 



 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>4C</number> Appointment for 
posts of Superintendent of Police and above, extension and   curtailment of 
their tenure, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Committee referred to in section 4A shall, after consulting the Director, 
recommend officers for appointment to the posts of the level of Superintendent 
of Police and above and also recommend the extension or curtailment of the 
tenure of such officers in the Delhi Special Police Establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the 
recommendation under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall pass such 
orders as it thinks fit to give effect to the said recommendation.]
 




</section></article> 



 <article>
<number>5</number> Extension of powers 
and jurisdiction of special police establishment to other areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may by order extend to any area (including Railway 
areas), 

1[in 

2[a State, not 
being a Union territory]] the powers and jurisdiction of members of the Delhi 
Special Police Establishment for the investigation of any offences or classes 
of offences specified in a notification under section 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When by an order 
under sub-section (1) the powers and jurisdiction of members of the said police 
establishment are extended to any such area, a member thereof may, subject of 
any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, discharge the 
functions of a police officer in that area and shall, while so discharging such 
functions, be deemed to be a member of a police force of that area and be 
vested with the powers, functions and privileges and be subject to the 
liabilities of a police officer belonging to that police force.
 

3[(3) where any 
such order under sub-section (1) is made in relation to any area, then, without 
prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (2) any member of the Delhi Special 
Police Establishment of or above the rank of Sub-Inspector may subject to any 
orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, exercise the 
powers of the officer in charge of a police station in that area and when so 
exercising such powers, shall be deemed to be an officer in charge of a police 
station discharging the functions of such an officer within the limits of his 
station.]







</section></article> 



 <article>


1[<number>6</number> Consent of 
State Government to exercise of powers and jurisdiction.—Nothing 
contained in section 5 shall be deemed to enable any member of the Delhi 
Special Police Establishment to exercise powers and jurisdiction in any area in


2[a State, not 
being a Union territory or railway area], without the consent of the Government 
of that State.]
 
 



</article> 



 <article>

1[<number>6A</number> Approval 
of Central Government to conduct inquiry or investigation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Delhi Special Police Establishment shall not conduct any inquiry or 
investigation into any offence alleged to have been committed under the 
Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988)  except with the previous 
approval of the Central Government where such allegation relates to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the employees 
of the Central Government of the Level of Joint Secretary and above; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  such officers 
as are appointed by the Central Government in corporations established by or 
under any Central Act, Government companies, societies and local authorities 
owned or controlled by that Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), no such approval shall be necessary for 
cases involving arrest of a person on the spot on the charge of accepting or 
attempting to accept any gratification other than legal remuneration referred 
to in clause (c) of the Explanation to section 7 of the Prevention of 
Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988).]





</section></article> 



 <article>
<number>7</number> Repeal of Ordinance 
22 of 1946.—[Repealed 
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1950 (35 of 1950), Sec. 2 and Sch. I.]
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by Act 45 of 
2003, sec. 26  for sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by Act 20 of 
2006, sec. 2, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 6-4-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Subs. by Act 45 of 
2003, sec. 26  for sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by Act 45 of 
2003, sec. 26  for sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by Act 45 of 
2003, sec. 26  for sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1952, sec. 5, for “in India outside the State of Delhi”  (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
(No. 3) 1956, for “a Part A State or a Part B State”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1952, sec. 6, for section 6 (w.e.f. 6-3-1952).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
(No. 3), 1956, for “a Part A State or a Part B State not being a railway area”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Ins. by Act 45 of 
2003, sec. 26 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>