<act><title>

The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 19731</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force in a State on 
    the date on which the Act comes  into force in that State.
  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>a</number> “Act” means the 
    Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Form” 
    means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> “licensee” 
    means a holder of a licence granted under the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “section” 
    means a section of the Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> 
    Reference to committee of experts for report as to artistic and aesthetic 
    value of any human work of art.—Where 
    having regard to the nature and other matters pertaining to any human work 
    of art which the Central Government proposed to declared to be an art 
    treasure under clause (b) of section 2 of the Act, the Central Government 
    considered it necessary so to do, it may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, constitute a committee consisting of not less than three persons 
    having expert knowledge as to like works of art to consider and submit a 
    report on the artistic and aesthetic value of the work of art so proposed to 
    be declared.]
  
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2B</number> 
    Notice for ascertaining whether the author of a work of art is alive.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With a view to determining whether the author of any human work of art which 
    the Central Government proposes to declare to be an art treasure under 
    clause (b) of section 2 of the Act is alive the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, give notice of its intention to make 
    such declaration and require—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    that in case the author thereof is alive, he shall, 
    within two months from the date of publication of the notification in the 
    Official Gazette, communicate the fact and his address to the Central 
    Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    that any other person knowing such author to have been 
    alive within thirty years, to make known to the Central Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[within 
    two months from the date of publication of the notification in Official 
    Gazette] the name of the author and the fact of the author being alive and 
    his address or, as the case may be, the date on which the author was last 
    seen alive, and the last known address of the author.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of a notice published under 
    sub-rule (1) may also be published in any Indian or Foreign newspaper or 
    journal.]
 

 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Authority competent to issue permits 
    under sub-section (2) of section 3.—The 
    Director-General shall be authority competent to issue permit under section 
    3 for the export of any antiquity or art treasure.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of rules, the expression “Director-General” means the 
    Director-General, Archaeological Survey of India and includes an officer not 
    below the rank of the Director, Archaeological Survey of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[duly authorized in 
    this behalf by the Director‑General].
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Form of application for 
    licence to carry on business or selling antiquities.—Every 
    application for a licence to carry on the business of selling or offering to 
    sell antiquities, shall be made in Form I and shall be accompanied with a 
    challan of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[rupees two thousand] 
    in token of having paid the fee for the licence applied for.
 

 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Grant of licence under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 8.—(1) On receipt of an 
    application for licence to carry on the business of selling or offering to 
    sell the antiquities, the licensing officer shall, in addition to 
    considering the factors mentioned in a clause (a), (b) and (c) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 8 consider the bona fide intention of the 
    applicant and if satisfied about such intention, may grant a licence to the 
    applicant in Form II.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Every licence 
    granted under sub‑rule (1), shall be valid for two years from the date of 
    issue. This period of two years may be extended by one year by the licensing 
    officer, if application for such extension is received by him at least two 
    months before the date of expiry and <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[the licensee (i) has 
    been submitting all the prescribed returns; (ii) has satisfactorily 
    maintained all the prescribed records; and (iii) continues to comply with 
    all the conditions laid down for the grant of licence]:
 
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Provided that an 
    application for extension under this sub‑rule may be entertained by the 
    licensing officer even up to one month before the date of expiry if he is 
    satisfied that the delay in applying for extension was due to circumstances 
    beyond the control of the applicant.]
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Conditions of licence under rule 
      5.—Every licence granted under 
      rule 5 shall be subject to the following conditions, 
      namely:—
 <section><number>a</number>    The licence 
      shall not be transferable:
 Provided that where a 
      licensee transfers his business to another person the transferee may, on 
      an application made in 1[Form I A] be granted a fresh licence, without payment of a 
      licence‑fee, for the unexpired period of the licence of the transferor, by 
      the licensing officer, having regard to the factors mentioned in rule 
      5:
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided further that in 
      the case of the death of licensee when the licensee is an individual, a 
      fresh licence for the unexpired period of the licence can be granted in 
      Form II A without payment of any fee, to the legal heir of the late 
      licensee subject to the condition that an application in Form IA is made 
      by that heir to the licensing officer <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[within three months of 
      the date of death of the licensee], and the licensing officer is satisfied 
      with the factors mentioned in rule 5, in regard to the 
      applicant.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>    
      No licensee shall enter into partnership, or if the licensee is already a 
      partnership firm, into further partnership, in regard to the business 
      covered by the licence:
 Provided that if the licensee 
      wants to enter into partnership or further partnership, as the case may 
      be, in regard to the business covered by the licence, all the proposed 
      partners including the existing one(s) may apply in Form IA to the 
      licensing officer and if the licensing officer is satisfied with all the 
      facts mentioned in rule 5 in regard to all the proposed partner(s), he may 
      issue a fresh licence in Form II A for the unexpired period of the licence 
      without payment of any fee.]
 </section><section><number>c</number>    Where a firm in respect of which 
      a licence is granted is dissolved every person who was a partner of that 
      firm immediately before the dissolution shall, within ten days of such 
      dissolution, send a report thereof to the licensing officer.
 </section><section><number>d</number>    Where a licensee carries on his 
      business at more than one place he shall obtain a separate licence for 
      each place.
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>e</number>    No licensee shall 
      shift his business covered by the licence to new premises during the 
      currency of the licence. However, if he wants to do so, he may apply in 
      Form IA to the licensing officer and if the licensing officer is satisfied 
      with the fact mentioned in section 8 (b) of the said Act, in regard to the 
      proposed premises, he may modify the licence accordingly. The modified 
      licence shall be valid in regard to the new premises only from the date of 
      such modification.]
 </section><section><number>f</number>    The licensee shall if so 
      required by the licensing officer permit the licensing officer’s 
      photographer to take photographs of antiquities in the possession of the 
      licensee.
 </section><section><number>g</number>    the licensee shall cause his 
      licence to be prominently displayed at his licensed premises
 </section><section><number>h</number>    the licensee shall submit to the 
      licensing officer in Form III, a monthly return of sales and acquisition 
      of antiquities, within fifteen days of the expiry of the month to which 
      the return relates and shall also, on demand, within such time as the 
      licensing ,officer may specify, produce such records;
 </section><section><number>i</number>    Where a licence is revoked or 
      suspended under the Act, the licensee shall not be entitled to any 
      compensation for such revocation or suspension, nor shall he be entitled 
      to claim refund of any sum paid in respect of his licence.
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>j</number>    In case of termination of a licence through 
      expiry/dissolution of partnership, the ex-holders of the licence shall be 
      allowed to antiquities in his/her/their possession on the date of 
      termination to a licensee or recognized museum in India within six months 
      of the date of termination of the licence provided the ex‑holder of the 
      licence has/have properly declared his/her/their stock in Form V as laid 
      down in conditions (k) and (m).]
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>k</number>    Two months before 
      the date of expiry of a licence, every licensee shall send to the 
      licensing officer a declaration of stock in Form V and another declaration 
      of stock in Form VI immediately after six months from the date of 
      expiry.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>l</number> In the case 
      of revocation of a licence for now compliance with any condition for the 
      grant of a licence, an ex‑licensee shall submit a declaration of stock in 
      Form V to the licensing officer within fifteen days of 
      revocation.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>m</number>    In the case of 
      dissolution of a partnership firm, which holds a licence, every partner in 
      the firm shall immediately on dissolution jointly, or severally, send to 
      the licensing officer a declaration of stock in Form V and another 
      declaration of stock, in Form VI immediately after six months from the 
      date of dissolution.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>n</number>    A licensee who 
      wants to surrender his licence shall apply in Form X to the licensing 
      officer. The application shall be accompanied by a declaration of stock in 
      Form V. If the licensing officer is satisfied that there has been 
      compliance with all the conditions of the licence by the licensee, he may 
      accept the surrender and the licence shall be deemed to have terminated 
      from the date of such acceptance. This shall not entitle the licensee to 
      any compensation by way of refund of licence fee in any form.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>o</number>    The licensee who 
      has surrendered his licence shall be allowed to  sell the antiquities 
      declared to another licensee or recognized museum in India up to six 
      months from the date of acceptance of the surrender of his licence 
      provided that on the expiry of such six months, he shall send to the 
      licensing officer a declaration of stock in Form VI.]
  
  






 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Renewal of licence under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 9.—On 
    an application made by the licensee for the renewal of the licence and on 
    payment of a fee of <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[rupees one thousand] 
    the licence may be renewed <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[for a further period 
    of two years at one time]:
 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Provided that such 
    application is received by the licensing officer at least two months before 
    the date of expiry of the licence and is accompanied by a declaration of 
    stock in Form V.]
  
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Maintenance of records, photographs 
    and register by licensee.—Every 
    licensee shall maintain the following records, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a register of antiquities 
<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[***] 
    in Form IV separately for each category of antiquity for which he has been 
    authorized to carry on business of selling or offering to sell; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    photo albums 
    separately for each category of antiquities having clear photographs in at 
    least post‑card size, pasted in the album together with a loose photograph 
    bearing the serial number of his register.
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article> <number>9</number> Form of 
      <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[declaration under section 12 and rule 7] and period within which it 
      shall be made.—Every person whose licence has been revoked under 
      section 11 shall make before the licensing 
      officer:—
 <section><number>a</number>    a declaration in Form V, within 
      fifteen days from the revocation of his licence; and
 </section><section><number>b</number>    a declaration in Form VI, 
      immediately after a period of six months from the date of revocation of 
      his licence.
  
  





 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Amendment of licence.—A 
    licence may be waived or amended by the licensing officer suo motu or 
    on an application made in that behalf by the  
    licensee:
 
Provided that no amendment or variation 
    shall be made suo motu by the licensing officer unless the licensee 
    has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Application for certificate of registration under section 16. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for a certificate of registration under section 16 shall be made in Form VII to the registering officer having jurisdiction over the area in which the applicant resides. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every such application shall be accompanied by <footcitenum>18</footcitenum> [three copies of photographs in post or quarter size] in sharp focus, of each antiquity in the applicants' possession, and if so required by the registering officer by an equal number of photographs of different sides, 
 or facets of such antiquity. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Form of certificate of registration 
    under section 16.—The certificate 
    of registration under section 16 shall be granted in Form VIII.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Transfer of ownership.—When 
    any person transfers the ownership control or possession of a registered 
    antiquity to any other person, the transfer shall be intimated in Form IX by 
    the transferor within fifteen days of the date of transfer to the 
    registering officer having jurisdiction over the area where the transferor 
    resides and also to the registering officer having jurisdiction over the 
    areas where the transferor resides.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Appeal against a decision of the 
    licensing officer or registering officer.—Any 
    person aggrieved by a decision of a licensing officer under section 8 or 
    section 9 or section 11 or by a decision of a registering officer under 
    section 16 may, within thirty days from the date on which the decision is 
    communicated prefer an appeal to the Director‑General, Archaeological Survey 
    of India.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>15</number> 
    Director‑General to sanction prosecution.—The 
    Director‑General shall be the officer competent in terms of sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> 
    of section 26 of the Act, to institute,­ or to sanction institution of 
    prosecution for offences under sub‑section (1) of section 25 of the Act.]
 
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[Note.—The 
    declaration in Forms V and VI referred to in conditions (j) to (o) of rule 6 
    and sub‑rule (b) of rule 9, shall be made either by registered post or in 
    person.]
  
  





 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


FORM I
 


Application for Licence to carry 
    Business of  

    Selling or offering to sell Antiquities
 


(See rule 4)
 



 


*1.  Name and address of applicant/s.
 


**2.  Name and address of firm 
    including its branches or collaterals and other names (aliases) and 
    addresses during the last 10 years.
 


3.  Names and addresses of partners, if 
    any, including adult members of the family having an interest in, or share 
    in, the business.
 


4.  Addresses of showroom/sale premises.
 


5.  Addresses of all godowns and 
    repositories including residential premises of the constituents.
 


6.  The period for which the applicant 
    has been in business giving the details of his experience.
 


7.  Whether the applicant/firm (including 
    all constituents individually and jointly) was convicted of any offence 
    punishable under the Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947, or, in any 
    other case involving theft or smuggling of antiquities. If so, details 
    thereof may be stated.
 


8.  Whether the applicant/firm (including 
    all constituents individually or jointly) is a subject of 
    prosecution/investigation/inquiry regarding the infringement of the 
    Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947 or the theft of antiquities or art 
    treasures.
 


9.  Whether all stock up to the date of 
    application has been entered in the applicant’s register.
 


10.  The village, town or city, including 
    District and State, where the applicant intends to carry on the business.
 


11.  Nature, i.e. details of 
    the varieties of antiquities in which the applicant wishes to deal in, such 
    as, stone sculptures, metal works, wood works, coins, paintings, jewellery 
    and the like.
 


12.  Categorywise list of all 
    objects on hand claimed by the applicants to be antiquities including those 
    which have been registered with registering officer.
 


13.  Proof of deposition of licence 
    fee, i.e. treasury challan of Rs. 100 payable into the Account 
    No............ bearing No.................dated ..........to be attached.
 


14.  I declare that the above 
    information is correct and complete to the best of my knowledge and belief. 
    I/We also undertake to observe the provisions of the Antiquities and Art 
    Treasures Act, 1972, and the rules made thereunder.
 

I also enclose an attested* 
    copy of the Income‑tax Certificate for the preceding year 
    (20......20.......) and the Registration No. of the business establishment. 
    I also undertake to intimate any change of address or acquisition of new 
    godown within a week.** I also undertake to maintain such records, 
    photographs and registers and furnish at my expense periodical returns with 
    such particulars and photographs as may be required under the rules. I also 
    undertake to make available every record, photograph and register maintained 
    in this connection for the inspection of the licensing officer, or any other 
    gazetted officer of Government authorized in writing by the licensing 
    officer in this behalf.
 

 
 

Seal of the organization
 

Place.................                                                        Name and 
    signature of the applicant
 

Date...................
 

 
 

*Any change of address has 
    to be promptly (within a week of shifting) intimated to the licensing 
    officer.
 

**To be attested by a 
    gazetted officer with seal of office.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


1[Form 
    X]
 


Application for surrender of a 
    licence for carrying on the business of selling or offering to sell 
    antiquities
 


[See
    rule 6 (n)]
 

1. 
    Name of the 
    applicant.....................................................................
 

2. 
    Present address of the 
    applicant.......................................................
 

3. 
    Particulars of the licence to be surrendered:
 


    (a)  Number...............................................................................
 


    (b)  Date...................................................................................
 


    (c)  Name of the 
    holder...............................................................
 


    (d)  Period with dates of 
    validity...................................................
 

4. 
    Reason for surrendering the 
    licence..................................................
 


    I/We hereby declare my/our intention or surrendering the licence aforesaid, 
    of which I/we/am/are/holder (s) and am/are aware that on the acceptance of 
    this surrender, I/we will not be entitled to any compensation by way of 
    refund of licence fee or in any other form.
 


    I/We hereby attach a declaration of Form V of the stock of antiquities held 
    by me/us on the date of this declaration and hereby undertake to submit 
    another declaration of Form VI immediately six months after the date of 
    acceptance of this surrender.
 

 
 


    Place................                                                     
    Signature and name of the applicant
 


    Date................                                                      No. of licence
 


                                                                                Seal of the firm]
 

 
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 

     
    1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 



    ------------------------------------------------ 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


1[Form 
    IA
 


 (See rule 6)
 



 



Application for grant of a fresh licence for 
    carrying business of selling or offering  

    to sell antiquities in lieu of one, 
    the holder which has died, or the holder(s) of  

    which has/have transferred 
    his/their business to other(s) or the holder(s) of  

    which propose(s) to enter into partnership/further partnership
 


1. Name and address of applicant(s).
 


2. Name and address of firm including its 
    branches or collaterals and other name (aliases) and addresses during 
    the last 10 years.
 


3. Name and addresses of partners, if any, 
    including adult members of the family having an interest in or share in, the 
    business.
 


Note.—In case this application is in 
    consequence of proposed entry into, or proposed enlargement of the existing 
    partnership, the required details should be applied separately for the 
    existing holders and the proposed partners.
 


4. Address of showroom/sale premises.
 


5. Address of all godowns and repositories 
    including residential premises of the constituents.
 


6. The period for which the applicant has been 
    in business giving the details of his experience.
 


7. Whether the applicant/firm (including all 
    constituents individually and jointly) was convicted of any offence 
    punishable under the Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947, or in any other 
    case involving theft or smuggling of antiquities. If so, details thereof may 
    be stated.
 


8. Whether the applicant/firm (including all 
    constituents individually or jointly) is a subject of 
    prosecution/investigation/inquiry regarding the infringement of the 
    Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947 or the theft of antiquities or art 
    treasures.
 


9. Whether all stock up to the date of 
    application has been entered in the applicant’s register.
 


10. The village, town or city, including 
    District and State, where the applicant intends to carry on the business.
 

11. Nature, i.e. 
    details of the varieties of the business which applicant wishes to deal in, 
    such as stone sculptures, metal works, wood works, coins, paintings, 
    manuscripts, jewellery and the like.
 

12. Categorywise list of all 
    objects on hand claimed by the applicants to be antiquities including those 
    which have been registered with registering officer.
 

13. Particulars of the 
    licence in lieu of which a fresh licence is needed.
 

(a) No.
 

(b) Date.
 

(c) Name(s) of the licensee.
 

(d) Period with dates for 
    which issued/renewed.
 

14. The circumstance in 
    consequence of which this application has been made.
 

(Death of the 
    licensee/transfer of business/entry into partnership enlargement of the 
    existing partnership). Proof must be furnished.
 

15. I/We declare that the 
    above information is correct and complete to the best of my/our knowledge 
    and belief. I/We also undertake to observe the provisions of the Antiquities 
    and Art Treasures Act, 1972, and the rules made thereunder. I/We also 
    enclose an attested copy of the Income‑tax Certificate for the preceding 
    year (20........20............) and the Registration Number of the business 
    establishment. I/We also undertake to intimate any change of address of 
    acquisition of new godown within a week. I/We also undertake to maintain 
    such records. Photographs and registers and furnish at my/our expense 
    periodical returns with such particulars and photographs as may be required 
    under the rules. I/We also undertake to make available every record 
    photograph and register maintained in this connection for the inspection of 
    the licensing officer, or any other gazetted officer of Government 
    authorized in writing by the licensing officer in this behalf.
 

 
 

Seal of the Organization.
 

Place................                                                        Name and 
    signature of the applicant.
 

Date................
 

 
 

To be attested by a gazetted 
    officer with seal of officer. Any change of address has to be promptly 
    intimated to the licensing office.]
 

 
 



    ---------------------------------------------------
 


     1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 



    ---------------------------------------------------
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

FORM II
 


Licence No..............
 


Date of 
    issue...............
 


Licence for carrying on the Business 
    of Selling or  

    Offering to sell Antiquities
 

[See rule 5 (1)]
 


Not Transferable
 

 
 

Whereas.............(son 
    of)..................of (address) has applied for a licence for carrying on 
    the business of selling or offering to sell antiquities and has undertaken 
    to observe the provisions of the Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972, 
    and the rules made thereunder and has further deposited the sum of Rs. 100 
    (Rupees one hundred) only as required by the rules.
 

I 
    ........................licensing officer, do hereby grant this licence 
    under sub‑rule (1) of rule 5 of the Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 
    1973...............for the period of ................years with effect from 
    ...................
 

The licence is granted 
    subject to the provisions of the said Act, and rules and is further subject 
    to the following conditions:
 


(1) Accordingly licensee will deal only in the 
    following categories of antiquities. The area where the business will be 
    carried on will be—
 


         
    (1)                                                   (5)
 


         
    (2)                                                   (6)
 


         
    (3)                                                   (7)
 


         
    (4)                                                   (8)
 

Seal of 
    office                                             Signature
 


    Place..........                                              Name
 


    Date..........                                               Licensing 
    Officer (Designation)
 


 
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


1[FORM IIA
 


(See rule 6)
 

Licence 
    No.................
 

Date of 
    Issue...............
 

 
 


    Licence for carrying on the business of selling or offering to sell 
    antiquities, in lieu of one the holder of which had died or the holder(s) of 
    which has/have transferred his/their business to other (s) or the holder(s) 
    which propose(s) to enter into partnership/further partnership
 

Whereas the holder(s) of 
    licence No...............dated ..............valid from ..........to 
    ............... has/have died/transferred his/her/their business to other/propose(s) 
    to enter into partnership/further partnership.
 

And whereas the 
    heir/transferee/proposed/partners whose particulars are given below, 
    has/have applied for the issue of a fresh licence in lieu of the licence 
    aforesaid for the unexpired period or the licence aforesaid.
 


    Name:.........................
 

Father’s Name:..........
 

Address:....................
 

And whereas the applicants 
    aforesaid have undertaken to observe the provisions of the Antiquities and 
    Art Treasures Act, 1972 and the rules made thereunder, as amended from time 
    to time.
 

I, 
    ...................licensing officer do hereby grant this licence under 
    sub‑rule (1) of rule 5 of the Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973 for 
    the period with effect from...................
 

The licence is granted 
    subject to the provisions of the said Act, and rules and is further subject 
    to the following conditions:
 

(1) The licensee will deal 
    only in the following categories of antiquities. The area where the business 
    will be carried on will be—
 


(1)
 


(2)
 


(3)
 


(4)
 


(5)
 


(6)
 


(7)
 


    (8)
 

Seal of Office
 

Place..................                                                                                          Signature
 

Date...................                                                                                               Name
 


Licensing Officer]
 


 
 



    ----------------------------------------------
 


     1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 



    ----------------------------------------------
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


FORM III
 


Name of the firm 
    (Licensee).....................
 



Monthly Return of Sales or 
    Acquisition of Antiquities
 


[See rule 6 (h)]
 


For the 
    month of................. 


 
 
 
 

1. Serial 
        Number............................. 

    (in the register)
 
 

1. Serial 
        Number............................. 

    (in the register)

 
 
 

2. Description of 
        object.................... 

    (with a photograph)
 
 

2. Description of 
        object.................... 

    (with photograph)

 
 
 

*3. Address of person to 

      whom sold............................. 

 
 

3. Address of person from 

      whom acquired.............................

 
 
 

 
 
 

 

 
 
 

Seal of 
        Organisation
 
 


†Signature 
        of Licensee


 


    Place...............
 


    Date................
 

 
 


      *.   The nationality of foreigners to 
    whom an antiquity is sold together with their address in India and at home 
    and passport number should be recorded.
 


     †.   In the case of a firm, the signature 
    of the head of the organization.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 


Form IV
 



    Register of Antiquities 

[See rule 8 (a)]
 


Antiquities such as stone 
    sculpture / terracottas / metal / objects / objects of bone and ivory / 
    jewellery / woodwork / seals / medals / coins / paintings/manuscripts and 
    textiles.
 

 
 
 
 Serial No.
 
        Identification of objects and description
 Material
 Size
 Approximate 
        Age
 Date of 
        Acquisition 

 
 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  


 

 
 
 
 Source of 
        Acquisition including the name of the person/firm from whom acquired 
        with address
 Mode of 
        Acquisition
 Price paid 
        for Acquisition
 
        Registration No.
 Date of 
        Registration
 Date of 
        Sale, if any

 
 7
 8
 9
 10
 11
 12

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  


 

 
 
 
 Name and 
        address of person or firm to whom sold**
 Place where 
        object is kept
 Reference 
        No. of Photo Album No.
 Photo No. 
        and Page
 Photographs 
        in 6x6 cm. size

 
 13
 14
 15
 16
 17

 
   

 
  
  
  
  


 

-------------------------------------
 


                    **.           In the case of a foreigner his addrevses in 
    India and at home and passport number should also be recorded.
 

-------------------------------------
 

 
 

 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 


1[Form V
 


Declaration of Stock 

[See 
    conditions under rule 6 (j), (k), (l), (m), (n), rule 7 and rule 9 (a)] 

    Particulars of objects (category‑wise)
 

 
 
 
 Serial No. 
        in the Register
 
        Identification and description of the object registered of unregistered
 Material 
        Size
 Approximate
 Date of 
        registration if registered
 
        Registration No.

 
 1
 2
 3
 4
 6
 6

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  


 




    I/We declare our stock of antiquities as hereabove on the date of 
    declaration.
 




    Seal of Organization
 

 
 




    Place...................
 




    Date....................                                                        
    Signature of the Licensee
 




                                                                                      
    Name of the firm
 


                                                                              
             Licence No...............]
 



    -------------------------------------------
 


1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 
    (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 


    ----------------------------------------------
 

 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

1[Form 
    VI
 


Declaration of Stock 

[See conditions under rules 6 (k), (m), (o) and 9 (b)]
 

 

Particulars of objects sold out of the stock declared 
    on..................
 
 
 Serial No. 
        in the Register
 Description 
        of the object with photographs
 Name and 
        address of the licensee / license firm to whom sold
 Date of 
        Sale
 Price at 
        which sold
 Approximate 
        Age
 Balance 
        with details (registration No. etc.) of the object in hand

 
 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  
  


 


I/We hereby declare the stock of antiquities 
    as hereabove held by me/us on the date of making this declaration.
 

 
 




    Seal of Organization
 




    Place...................
 




    Date....................                                                       
 




    Signature of the Licensee
 




    Name of the firm
 


     Licence 
    No...............]
 

 
 

 
 



    -------------------------------------------
 


1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 
    (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 


    ----------------------------------------------
  


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


    FORM VII
 



    Licence No.................
 


Application for Registration of 
    Antiquities
 


(See
    rule 11)
 

 
 

1. 
    Name of applicant (person or firm)
 

2. 
    Address of applicant (person or firm).
 


3. Identification and description of 
    object with 
1[three 
    copies of photographs in postcard or quarter size.]
 

4. 
    Material.
 

5. 
    Size.
 

6. 
    Approximate date.
 

7. 
    Source of acquisition.
 

8. 
    Where the applicant has come into ownership, control or possession of any 
    antiquity which is already registered under the Act, registration number of 
    such antiquity and the name of registering officer, who had registered it.
 

9. 
    Date of acquisition
 

10. 
    Mode of acquisition
 

11. 
    Price paid, if any.
 

12. 
    (a) Present location, and 
 

   
    (b) Condition of preservation and security.
 

13. 
    If the antiquity is already registered under the Act, whether its 
    registration certificate has been attached.
 

I 
    declare that the above information is correct and complete to the best of my 
    knowledge and belief. I also undertake to observe the provisions of the 
    Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972, and the rules made thereunder.
 

 
 


    Seal of the Organization
 


    Place..................                                                                Signature
 


    Date...................                                                                Name of the applicant
 

1. 
    If the application is on behalf of an organization, the name thereof should 
    be given.
 

2. 
    If the application is on behalf of an organization, the signature should be 
    that of the head of that organization.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 


     
    1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


    Form VIII
 


Certificate of Registration of 
    Antiquities
 


(See
    rule 12)
 

 
 


    Whereas .............. resident of..............has applied for registration 
    of the antiquity/antiquities mentioned below, and has undertaken to observe 
    the provision of the Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972, and the rules 
    made thereunder
 


    Place..........................
 

I 
    ,...............registering officer................do hereby grant this 
    certificate under section 16 of the said......... for the object described 
    below together with ...........authenticated photographs.
 

1. 
    Name of object
 

2. 
    Material
 

3. 
    Size (height and width)
 

4. 
    Approximate date
 

5. 
    Location.
 

The 
    certificate is granted subject to the provision of the said Act and the 
    rules made thereunder and is further subject to the condition that in the 
    event of change of location of the antiquity from area of registration to 
    another or its sale, the fact must be communicated by the owner to the 
    registering officer, with the name and address of the person/firm to 
    whom/which it was sold or gifted.
 


    Seal of 
    office                                                                   Signature
 


    Place...................                                                           Name of registering officer
 


        
    Date...................                                                            Designation
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The Antiquities and Art Treasures Rules, 1973
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


1[Form 
    IX
 


Transfer of Ownership 

 


(See
    rule 13)
 

 
 


    N.B. 1.—This Form must be completed (in triplicate) 
    simultaneously with the transfer of ownership.
 

2. 
    One copy shall be sent to the registering officer concerned and the other 
    two copies to the Director‑General, Archaeological Survey of India, New 
    Delhi by registered post so as to reach them within ten days of transfer.
 

3. 
    In case the object is an unregistered antiquity each copy of this Form shall 
    be accompanied by a photograph (in sharp focus) of the object in postcard or 
    quarter size. If the sides of the object are decorated differently than the 
    front, the photographs, as stated above, shall be sent in respect of each 
    such side also in .addition to the front side.
 

4. 
    The responsibility for completion of the above formalities rests with the 
    seller/giver if the object has been sold, gifted or donated; otherwise with 
    the new owner of the object.
 

 
 


Section A (to be Completed by the 
    seller/giver)
 

1. 
    Name of Owner..................................................................................
 

2 
    Address of Owner................................................................................
 

3. 
    *Licence No......................................................................................
 

4. 
    Serial No. in Register...........................................................................
 

5. 
    Serial No. in Album..............................................................................
 

6. 
    Name/Subject of object 
    ......................................................................
 

7. 
    Nature (e.g. sculpture, painting, manuscript, coins, etc.) 
    ..........................
 

8. 
    Whether it is registered ? 
 


    If so—­
 


    (i) Name and Station of registering officer 
     
    ................................................
 


    (ii)       Registration No..........................................................................
 

9.Material.............................................................................................
 

10. 
    Size................................................................................................
 

11. 
    Price offered 
    ...................................................................................
 


    Place ............                                          Signature of 
    Owner
 


    Date.............                                           Name (In Block 
    Letters) as signed and Seal.
 

 
 



          *.   Applicable in the case of dealers only.
 

 
 


Section B (to be completed by the new 
    owner)
 

1. 
    Name 
    ............................................................................................
 

2. 
    Complete address
 


                (i) Present..............................................................................
 


               (ii) Permanent..........................................................................
 

3. 
    Mode of 
    acquisition...........................................................................
 

   
    (e.g. purchase, gift, inheritance, donation, etc.)
 

4. 
    Present location of object 
    ..................................................................
 

5. 
    Safeguards for preservation and security of the object 
     
    ............................
 


6. 
†Nationality......................................................................................
 


7. 
†Passport 
    No....................................................................................
 


8. 
†Duration 
    of stay in India....................................................................
 

9. 
    Purpose of visit.................................................................................
 

 
 

I 
    hereby declare that the information given above by me is correct and 
    complete to the best of my knowledge and belief. I undertake to observe the 
    provisions of the Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972 and the rules made 
    thereunder as in force from time to time.
 

I 
    am aware that the object now acquired by me is an antiquity that it cannot 
    be taken or sent out of the territorial limits of India except on the 
    authority of a permit issued by Director-General of Archaeological Survey of 
    India and that any attempt to take or send out of India without such a valid 
    permit is punishable under the law.
 

 
 


    Place........................                                             
    Signature
 


    Date.........................                                             
    Name (in Capital letters assigned]
 

 
 



         †.   Applicable in the case of foreigners only.
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 


     
    1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 683 (E), dated the 6th December, 1979 (w.e.f. 6-12-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 683 (E), dated the 6th December, 1979 (w.e.f. 6-12-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 815 (E), dated 2nd November, 1983 (w.e.f. 2-11-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   
    Added by G.S.R. 546 (E) dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   
    Subs. by G.S.R. 746 (E), dated 28th August, 1992 (w.e.f. 28-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   
    Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   
    Subs. by G.S.R. 56 (E), dated 10th February, 1981 (w.e.f. 10-2-1981).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   
    Ins. by G.S.R. 56 (E), dated 10th February, 1981 (w.e.f. 10-2-1981).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
 Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), 
      dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>    Subs. by G.S.R. 
      564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>    Ins. by G.S.R. 56 
      (E), dated, 10th February, 1981 (w.e.f. 10-2-1981).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>    Ins. by G.S.R. 
      564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    746 (E), dated 28th August, 1992 (w.e.f. 28-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Omitted by G.S.R. 
    654 (E), dated, 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 
      30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    564 (E), dated 30th November, 1978 (w.e.f. 30-11-1978).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>