<act><title>

[The] 
    Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888 </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Title 
    and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888; and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such day as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in this behalf.
 
The Act has 
    now been extended* to the Union Territories of—
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>    Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Regn. 6 of 
    1963 (1-7-1965);
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Pondicherry by Regn. 7 of 1963 
    (1-10-1963);
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands 
    by Regn. 8 of 1965 (1-10-1967).
 
       These Islands are now known as 
    Lakshadweep—see Act 34 of 1973, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-11-1973).
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Division of Reserve Forces into Regular and Supplementary Reserves.—The 
    Indian Reserve Forces shall consist of the Regular Reserve and the 
    Supplementary Reserve.]
 
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Locality of service of Reserves.—<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] 
    A person belonging to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Indian Reserve Forces] shall be 
    liable to serve beyond the limits of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[India} as well as within 
    those limits.
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***]
 
 
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Power to make rules for regulation of Reserve Forces.—<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The Central Government may make rules and orders for the Government, 
    discipline and regulation of the Indian Reserve Forces.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>] 
    Every rule and every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon 
    as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or order 
    or both Houses agree that the rule or order should not be made, the rule or 
    order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
    effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that rule or order.]
 
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Liability of Reserve Forces to military law.—Subject 
    to <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***] such rules and orders as may be made under section 4, a 
    person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces shall, as an office, or 
    soldier, as the case may be, be subject to military law in the same manner 
    and to the same extent as a person belonging to the 

    2[the Regular Army].
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Punishment of certain offences by persons belonging to Reserve Forces.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    when required by or in pursuance of any 
    rule or order under this Act to attend at any place, fails without 
    reasonable excuse to attend in accordance with such requirement, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    fails without reasonable excuse to 
    comply with any such rule or order, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    fraudulently obtains any pay or other 
    sum contrary to any such rule or order,  
 
he shall be liable—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    on conviction by a Court-martial, 
    to such punishment other than death, transportation or imprisonment for a 
    term exceeding one year as such Court is by the 
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Army 
    Act, 1950] empowered to award, or
3[Army 
    Act, 1950] empowered to award, or" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    on conviction by <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[a 
    Presidency Magistrate or] a Magistrate of the first class, to imprisonment 
    for a term which may extend, in the case of a first offence under this 
    section, to six months, and, in the case of any subsequent offence 
    thereunder, to one year.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces is required by or in pursuance 
    of any rule or order under this Act to attend to any place, a certificate 
    purporting to be signed by an officer appointed by such rule or order in 
    this behalf, and stating that the person so required to attend failed to do 
    so in accordance with such requirement, shall, without proof of the 
    signature or appointment of such officer, be evidence of the matters stated 
    therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person 
    charged with an offence under this section may be taken into and kept in 
    either military or civil custody, or partly into and in one description of 
    custody and partly into and in the other, or be transferred from one 
    description of custody to the other.
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> 
    Reinstatement in civil employ of persons belonging to Reserve Forces on 
    termination of period of training, muster or army service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces is, during the period of 
    his employment under an employer, called up for training, muster or army 
    service in pursuance of his liability under any rule or order under this 
    Act, it shall be the duty of every such employer to reinstate the person in 
    his employment on the termination of the period of his training, muster or 
    army service in an occupation and under conditions not less favourable to 
    him than those which would have been applicable to him had his employment 
    not been so interrupted:
 
Provided that 
    if the employer refuses to reinstate such person or denies his liability to 
    reinstate such person, or if for any reason reinstatement of such person is 
    represented by the employer to be impracticable, either party may refer the 
    matter to the authority prescribed in this behalf by rules made under this 
    Act, and that authority shall, after considering all matters which may be 
    put before it and after making such further inquiry into the matter as may 
    be prescribed in the said rules, pass an order— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    exempting the employer from the 
    provisions of this section, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the employer to re-employ 
    such person on such terms as the authority thinks suitable, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    requiring the employer to pay to such 
    person by way of compensation for failure or inability to re-employ, a sum 
    not exceeding an amount equal to six months’ remuneration at the rate at 
    which his last remuneration was payable to him by the employer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    employer fails to obey the order of any such authority as is referred to in 
    the proviso to sub-section (1); he shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to one thousand rupees, and the Court by which an employer is 
    convicted under this section shall order him (if he has not already been so 
    required by the said authority) to pay to the person whom he has failed to 
    re-employ a sum equal to six months’ remuneration at the rate at which his 
    last remuneration was payable to him by the employer, and any amount so 
    required to be paid either by the said authority or by the Court shall be 
    recoverable as if it were a fine imposed by such Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In any 
    proceeding under this section it shall be a defence for an employer to prove 
    that the person formerly employed did not apply to the employer for 
    reinstatement within a period of two months from the termination of the 
    period of his training, muster or army service.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The duty 
    imposed by sub-section (1) upon an employer to reinstate in his employment a 
    person such as is described in that sub-section shall attach to an employer 
    who, before such person is actually called up for training, muster or army 
    service, terminates his employment in circumstances such as to indicate an 
    intention to evade the duty imposed by that sub-section, and such intention 
    shall be presumed until the contrary is proved, if the termination takes 
    place after the issue of orders calling him up for training, muster or army 
    service under this Act.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
    Preservation of certain rights of persons belonging to Reserve Forces when 
    called up for training, muster or army service.—When 
    any person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces and called up for 
    training, muster or army service in pursuance of his liability under any 
    rule or order under this Act has any rights under any provident fund or 
    superannuation fund or other scheme for the benefit of employees maintained 
    in connection with the employment he relinquishes, he shall continue, so 
    long as he is engaged in training, muster or army services and if he is 
    reinstated, until such reinstatement under the provisions of this Act, to 
    have in respect of such fund or scheme such rights as may be prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act.]
  



 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   The Act came into 
    force on the 26th May, 1888—see Gazette of India, 1888, Pt. I, p. 
    239.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Indian 
    Reserve Forces (Amendment) Act, 1931 (12 of 1931), sec. 2 for the original 
    section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   The figure and brackets 
    “(1)” were repealed by the Indian Reserve Forces (Amendment) Act, 1931 (12 
    of 1931), sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. for the words “Active 
    Reserve,” ibid.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by 2 A.L.O., 1956 for 
    the words and letters “the territories comprised within Part A States and 
    Part C States” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Sub-section (2) was 
    repealed by Act 12 of 1931, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Section 
    4 renumbered as sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) ins. by the Delegated 
    Legislation Provisions (Amendment) Act, 1983 (20 of 1983), sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   The words “the provision of 
    section 3 with respect to persons belonging to the Garrison Reserve, and to” 
    were repealed by the Indian Reserve Forces (Amendment) Act, 1931 (12 of 
    1931), sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by A.L.O., 1950 for 
    the words, “Her Majesty’s Indian Forces” (w.e.f. 26-1-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by the Repealing and 
    Amending Act, 1953 (42 of 1953), sec. 4 and Sch. III for the words and 
    figures “Indian Army Act, 1911” (w.e.f. 23-12-1953).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by the Indian Reserve 
    Forces (Amendment) Act, 1931 (12 of 1931), sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Ins. by the Indian 
    Reserve Forces (Amendment) Act, 1958 (3 of 1958), sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-3-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Ins. by the Indian 
    Reserve Forces (Amendment) Act, 1958 (3 of 1958), sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-3-1958).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>