<act><tid>450651</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL EXCISES AND SALT ACT, <year>1944</year></title>

ACT No. 1 OF <year>1944</year>
[ 24th February, <year>1944</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Central duties 
of 
excise and to salt.

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law 
relating 
to Central duties of excise on goods manufactured or produced 
in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> certain parts] of India] and to salt;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-

CHAP

CHAPTER I





<article><tid>867336</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1453498</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>213778</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>;

</section>

<section><tid>701907</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date 5 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>762181</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in 
the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1850794</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" adjudicating authority" means any authority competent 
to pass any order or decision under this Act, but does not 
include the Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted 
under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>, (54 of <year>1963</year>) 
Collector of Central Excise (Appeals) or Appellate Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1075253</tid>
<number>aa</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Customs, Excise and Gold 
 (Control) Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 129 of 
the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>;] (52 of <year>1962</year>)
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For Statement of Objects and Reasons, see Gazette of India, 
<year>1943</year>, Pt. V, p. 243 and for Report of the Select Committee, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1944</year>, Pt. V, p. 12.

This Act has been applied to--


(1) all the partially excluded areas in the State of Orissa 
by Orissa Government notification No. 1226-II- C- 13 44-Com., 
dated the 21st March, <year>1944</year>;

(2) Darjeeling District with effect from 28th[ February, 
<year>1944</year>, see Bengal Government notification No. 342-R, dated the 
22nd March, <year>1944</year>;

(3) excluded areas in the State of Madras (with  
  modifications), see Madras Government notification No. 37, 
Fort St. George Gazette, Pt. I, p. 281, dated 11th April, 
<year>1944</year>;

(4) partially excluded areas in the State of Madras with 
effect from 28th February, <year>1944</year>, see Madras Government 
notification No. 745-Public- Political, dated 4th March, <year>1944</year>.

This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch; to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 
and Sch. I and to the whole of the Union territory of Lakshadweep by 
Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. 0. <year>1948</year>, for" British India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. 0. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir, omitted by 
Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number> 28th February, <year>1944</year>, see notification No. III- D, dated the 26th 
February, <year>1944</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1944</year>, p. 293.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 50 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 11- 10- <year>1982</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>954052</tid>
<number>aaa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>]" broker" or" commission agent" means a person who in 
the ordinary course of business makes contracts for the sale 
or purchase of excisable goods for others;

</section>

<section><tid>328429</tid>
<number>b</number>" Central Excise Officer" means any officer of the 
Central Excise Department, or any person (including an  
  officer of the State Government) invested by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central 
Board of Excise and Customs constituted under the Central 
Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>) with any of the 
powers of a Central Excise Officer under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1886269</tid>
<number>c</number>" curing" includes wilting, drying, fermenting and any 
process for rendering an unmanufactured product fit for 
marketing or manufacture;

</section>

<section><tid>37099</tid>
<number>d</number>" excisable goods" means goods specified in the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year>] as being 
subject to a duty of excise and includes salt; (5 of <year>1986</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>555760</tid>
<number>e</number>" factory" means any premises, including the precincts 
thereof, wherein or in any part of which excisable goods 
other than salt are manufactured, or wherein or in any part 
of which any manufacturing process connected with the 
production of these goods is being carried on or is 
ordinarily carried on;

</section>

<section><tid>550313</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" Fund" means the Consumer Welfare Fund established 
under section 12C;]
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1432477</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" manufacture" includes any process,- 
 (i) incidental or ancillary to the completion of a 
manufactured product;

<subsection><tid>750482</tid>
<number>ii</number>which is specified in relation to any goods in the 
Section or Chapter notes of the Schedule to the Central 
Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year> as amounting to manufacture, (5  
  of <year>1986</year>).
and the word" manufacturer" shall be construed accordingly 
and shall include not only a person who employs hired labour 
in the production or manufacture of excisable, goods, but 
also any person who engages in their production or 
manufacture on his own account;]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1324230</tid>
<number>g</number>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1731174</tid>
<number>h</number>" sale" and" purchase", with their grammatical 
variations and cognate expressions, mean any transfer of the 
possession of goods by one person to another in the ordinary 
course of trade or business for cash or deferred payment or 
other valuable consideration;

</section>

<section><tid>655563</tid>
<number>i</number>" saltpeter" includes rasi, sajji, and all other 
substances manufactured from saline earth, and kharinun and 
every form of sulphate or carbonate of soda;

</section>

<section><tid>249509</tid>
<number>j</number>" salt factory" includes-

<subsection><tid>1259332</tid>
<number>i</number>a place used or intended to be used in the 
manufacture of salt and all embankments, reservoirs, 
condensing and evaporating pans, buildings and waste 
places situated within the limits of such place as 
defined from time to time by the Collector of Central 
Excise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275720</tid>
<number>ii</number>all drying grounds and storage platforms and 
storehouses appertaining to any such place;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>598466</tid>
<number>iii</number>land on which salt is spontaneously produced.;
and a" private salt factory" is one not solely owned or not 
solely worked by the Central Government;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (a) relettered as cl. (aaa) by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 50 and 
Sch. V (w. e. f. 11- 10- <year>1982</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for" Central Board of Revenue" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4, for" First Schedule" (w. e. f.  
  28- 2- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Cl. (ee) ins. by Act 25 of <year>1950</year>, s. 11 and Sch. IV, omitted by 
Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4, for cl. (f)  (w. e. f. 28- 2- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1991</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1307554</tid>
<number>k</number>' wholesale dealer" means a person who buys or sells 
excisable goods wholesale for the purpose of trade or 
manufacture, and includes a broker or commission agent who, 
in addition to making contracts for the sale or purchase of 
excisable goods for others, stocks such goods belonging to 
others as an agent for the purpose of sale.
CHAP

LEVY AND COLLECTION OF DUTY

CHAPTER II

LEVY AND COLLECTION OF DUTY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>233474</tid>
<number> 3</number> Duties specified in the Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff 
Act, <year>1985</year> to be levied.
<section><tid>1098567</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected in  
such manner as may be prescribed duties of excise on all excisable 
goods other than salt which are produced or manufactured in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] 
and a duty on salt manufactured in, or imported by land into, any part 
of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] as, and at the rates, set forth in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Schedule to the 
Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year>:] (5 of <year>1986</year>)
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that the duties of excise which shall be levied and 
collected on any <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> excisable goods which are produced or 
manufactured,-


<subsection><tid>1765584</tid>
<number>i</number>in a free trade zone and brought to any other place in 
India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1133232</tid>
<number>ii</number>by a hundred per cent., export- oriented undertaking and 
allowed to be sold in India,
shall be an amount equal to the aggregate of the duties of customs 
which would be leviable under section 12 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52  
  of <year>1962</year>) on like goods produced or manufactured outside India if 
imported into India, and where the said duties of customs are 
chargeable by reference to their value, the value of such excisable 
goods shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision 
of this Act, be determined in accordance with the provisions of the 
Customs Act, <year>1962</year> and the Customs Tariff Act, <year>1975</year>. (51 of <year>1975</year>)

Explanation 1.- Where in respect of any such like goods, any duty 
of customs leviable under the said section 12 is leviable at different 
rates, then, such duty shall, for the purposes of this proviso, be 
deemed to be leviable under the said section 12 at the highest of 
those rates.

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Explanation 2.- In this proviso,-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1765584</tid>
<number>i</number>" free trade zone" means the Kandla Free Trade Zone and 
the Santa Cruz Electronics Export Processing Zone and 
includes any other free trade zone which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1133232</tid>
<number>ii</number>" hundred per cent. export- oriented undertaking" means 
an undertaking which has been approved as a hundred per cent. 
export- oriented undertaking by the Board appointed in this 
behalf by the Central Government in exercise of the powers 
conferred by section 14 of the Industries (Development and  
  Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year>, (65 of <year>1951</year>) and the rules made under 
that Act.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1398413</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> The provisions of sub- section (1) shall apply in respect 
of all excisable goods other than salt which are produced or 
manufactured in India by, or on behalf of, Government, as they apply 
in respect of goods which are not produced or manufactured by 
Government.]

</section>

<section><tid>163356</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, fix, for the purpose of levying the said duties, tariff 
values of any articles enumerated, either specifically or under 
general headings, in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act, 
<year>1985</year>] (5 of <year>1986</year>) as chargeable with duty ad valorem and may alter any 
tariff values for the time being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (jj) ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, omitted by Act 25 of <year>1950</year>, 
s. 11 and Sch. IV.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 11 and Sch. IV, ibid., for" the States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4, for" First Schedule" (w. e. f.  
  28- 2- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1982</year>, s. 46.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 45, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by s. 45, ibid., for Explanation 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 30 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3, for sub- section (1A)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1963</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>992941</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Different tariff values may be fixed-

<subsection><tid>1985478</tid>
<number>a</number>for different classes or descriptions of the same 
excisable goods; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1785969</tid>
<number>b</number>for excisable goods of the same class or description-

<subsubsection><tid>1802662</tid>
<number>i</number>produced or manufactured by different classes of 
producers or manufacturers; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1642044</tid>
<number>ii</number>sold to different classes of buyers:
Provided that in fixing different tariff values in respect of 
excisable goods falling under sub- clause (i) or sub- clause (ii), 
regard shall be had to the sale prices charged by the different 
classes of producers or manufacturers or, as the case may be, the 
normal practice of the wholesale trade in such goods.]

 2 3A.[ Emergency. power of Central Government to increase duties of 
excise.][ Emergency. power of Central Government to increase duties of 
excise.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 
 2 and Sch. I.




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1373248</tid>
<number> 4</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Valuation of excisable goods for purposes of charging of 
duty of excise.
<section><tid>496009</tid>
<number>1</number>Where under this Act, the duty of excise is  
chargeable on any excisable goods with reference to value, such value 
shall, subject to the other provisions of this section, be deemed to 
be-

<subsection><tid>61709</tid>
<number>a</number>the normal price thereof, that is to say, the price at 
which such goods are ordinarily sold by the assessee to a 
buyer in the course of wholesale trade for delivery at the 
time and place of removal, where the buyer is not a related 
person and the price is the sole consideration for the sale:
Provided that-


<subsubsection><tid>1689531</tid>
<number>i</number>where, in accordance with the normal practice of 
the wholesale trade in such goods, such goods are 
sold by the assessee at different prices to different 
classes of buyers (not being related persons) each such 
price shall, subject to the existence of the other 
circumstances specified in clause (a), be deemed to be 
the normal price of such goods in relation to each such 
class of buyers;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1807553</tid>
<number>ii</number>where such goods are sold by the assessee in the 
course of wholesale trade for delivery at the time and 
place of removal at a price fixed under any law foe the 
time being in force or at a price, being the maximum, 
fixed under any such law, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in clause (ill) of this proviso, the price or 
the maximum price, as the case may be, so fixed, shall, 
in relation to the goods so sold, be deemed to be the 
normal price thereof;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>764079</tid>
<number>iii</number>where the assessee so arranges that the goods are 
generally not sold by him in the course of wholesale 
trade except to or through a related person, the normal 
price of the goods sold by the assessee to or through 
such related person shall be deemed to be the price at 
which they are ordinarily sold by the related person in 
the course of wholesale trade at the time of removal, to 
dealers (not being related persons) or where such goods 
are not sold to such dealers, to dealers (being related  
  persons) who sell such goods in retail;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1445830</tid>
<number>b</number>where the normal price of such goods is not 
ascertainable for the reason that such goods are not sold or 
for any other reason, the nearest ascertainable equivalent 
thereof determined in such manner as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1519336</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, in relation to any excisable goods the price thereof 
for delivery at the Place of removal is not known and the value 
thereof is determined with reference to the price for delivery at a 
place other than the place of removal, the cost of transportation from 
the place of removal to the place of delivery shall be excluded from 
such price.

</section>

<section><tid>49415</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this section shall not apply in respect of 
any excisable goods for which a tariff value has been fixed under sub- 
section (2) of section 3.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, s. 19, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 81 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2, for s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1975</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>160894</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section,-

<subsection><tid>481213</tid>
<number>a</number>" assessee" means the person who is liable to pay the 
duty of excise under this Act and includes his agent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1942004</tid>
<number>b</number>" place of removal" means-

<subsubsection><tid>712074</tid>
<number>i</number>a factory or any other place or premises of 
production or manufacture of the excisable goods; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1060359</tid>
<number>ii</number>a warehouse or any other place or premises wherein 
the excisable goods have been permitted to be deposited 
without payment of duty, from where such goods are 
removed;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348862</tid>
<number>c</number>" related person" means a person who is so associated with 
the assessee that they have interest, directly or indirectly, in the 
business of each other and includes a holding company, a subsidiary 
company, a relative and a distributor of the assessee, and any 
sub- distributor of such distributor.
Explanation.- In this clause" holding company"," subsidiary 
company and" relative" have the same meanings as in the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>; (1 of <year>1956</year>)


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1617872</tid>
<number>d</number>" value", in relation to any excisable goods,-

<subsubsection><tid>130083</tid>
<number>i</number>where the goods are delivered at the time of removal in 
a packed condition, includes the cost of such packing except 
the cost of the packing which is of a durable nature and is 
returnable by the buyer to the assessee.
Explanation.- In this sub- clause," packing" means the 
wrapper, container, bobbin, pirn, spool, reel or warp beam or 
any other thing in which or on which the excisable goods are 
wrapped, contained or wound;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1251015</tid>
<number>ii</number>does not include the amount of the duty of excise, 
sales tax and other taxes, if any, payable on such goods and, 
subject to such rules as may be made, the trade discount 
 (such discount not being refundable on any account  
  whatsoever) allowed in accordance with the normal practice of 
the wholesale trade at the time of removal in respect of such 
goods sold or contracted for sale.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- clause, the 
amount of the duty of excise payable on any excisable goods 
shall be the sum total of-


<subsubsubsection><tid>769693</tid>
<number>a</number>the effective duty of excise payable on such goods 
under this Act; and

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>123404</tid>
<number>b</number>the aggregate of the effective duties of excise 
payable under other Central Acts, if any, providing for 
the levy of duties of excise on such goods,
and the effective duty of excise on such goods under each Act 
referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) shall be,-


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>130083</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where a notification or order providing for 
any exemption (not being an exemption for giving credit with  
respect to, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or reduction of duty of excise under such Act 
on such goods equal to, any duty of excise under such Act, or 
the additional duty under section 3 of the Customs Tariff 
Act, <year>1975</year>, (51 of <year>1975</year>) already paid] on the raw material or 
component parts used in the production or manufacture of 
  such, goods) from the duty of excise under such Act is for 
the time being in force, the duty of excise computed with 
reference to the rate specified in such Act in respect of 
such goods as reduced so as to give full and complete effect 
to such exemption; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1982</year>, s. 47 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4 6, for certain words.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1251015</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, the duty of excise computed 
with reference to the rate specified in such Act in 
respect of such goods;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>389377</tid>
<number>e</number>" wholesale trade" means sales to dealers, industrial 
consumers Government, local authorities and other buyers, who 
or which purchase their requirements otherwise than in 
retail.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1579739</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Remission of duty on goods found deficient in quantity.
<section><tid>241480</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by rules made under this section, provide 
for remission of duty of excise leviable on any excisable goods which 
due to any natural cause are found to be deficient in quantity.

</section>

<section><tid>1522341</tid>
<number>2</number>Any rules made under sub- section (1) may, having regard to 
the nature of the excisable goods or of processing or of curing 
thereof, the period of their storage or transit and other relevant 
considerations, fix the limit or limits of percentage beyond which no 
such remission shall be allowed:
Provided that different limit or limits of percentage may be 
fixed for different varieties of the same excisable goods or for 
different areas or for different seasons.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>996541</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Power to grant exemption from duty of excise.
<section><tid>918849</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary in the public 
interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
exempt generally either absolutely or subject to such conditions (to  
  be fulfilled before or after removal) as may be specified in the 
notification, excisable goods of any specified description from the 
whole or any part of the duty of excise leviable thereon:
Provided that, unless specifically provided in such notification, 
no exemption. therein shall apply to excisable goods which are pro- 
duced or manufactured-


<subsection><tid>720869</tid>
<number>i</number>in a free trade zone and brought to any other place in 
India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1692947</tid>
<number>ii</number>by a hundred per cent. export- oriented undertaking and 
allowed to be sold in India.
Explanation.- In this proviso," free trade zone" and" hundred per 
cent. export- oriented undertaking" shall have the same meanings as in 
Explanation 2 to sub- section (1) of section 3.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1081702</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary 
in the public interest so to do, it may, by special order in each 
case, exempt from the payment of duty of' excise, under circumstances 
of an exceptional nature to be stated in such order, any excisable. 
goods on which duty of excise is leviable.

</section>

<section><tid>775541</tid>
<number>3</number>An exemption under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) in 
respect of any excisable goods from any part of the duty of excise 
leviable thereon (the duty of excise leviable thereon being herein-  
  after referred to as the statutory duty) may be granted by providing 
for the levy of a duty on such goods at a rate expressed in a form or 
method' different from the form or method in which the statutory duty 
is leviable and any exemption granted in relation to any excisable 
goods in th manner provided in this sub- section shall have effect 
subject to the condition that the duty of excise chargeable on such 
goods shall in no case exceed the statutory duty.
Explanation.--" Form or method", in relation to a rate of duty of 
excise means. the basis, namely, valuation, weight, number, length, 
area, volume or other measure with reference to which the duty is 
leviable.


</section>

<section><tid>1222353</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notification issued under sub- rule (1), and every 
order made under sub- rule (2), of rule 8 of the Central Excise Rules, 
<year>1944</year>, and in force immediately before the commencement of the Customs 
and Central Excises Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>1987</year> shall be deemed to have 
been issued or made under the provisions of this section and shall 
continue to have the same force and effect after such commencement 
until it is amended, varied rescinded or superseded under the 
provisions of this section.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1947138</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Registration of certain persons. Any prescribed person who 
is engaged in-
<section><tid>670028</tid>
<number>a</number>the production or manufacture or any process of pro- 
duction or manufacture of any specified goods included in the 
Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year>, or

</section>

<section><tid>1667137</tid>
<number>b</number>the wholesale purchase or sale (whether on his own  
  account or as a broker or commission agent) or the storage of 
any specified goods included in the Schedule to the Central 
Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year>,
shall get himself registered with the proper officer in such manner 
as may be prescribed.]

 9 xxx.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>432452</tid>
<number>8</number>Restriction on possession of goods specified in the Second 
Schedule. From such date as may be specified in this behalf by the 
Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, no person 
shall, except as provided by rules made under this Act, have in his 
possession <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> any goods specified in the Second Schedule] in excess of 
such quantity as may be prescribed for the purposes of this section as 
the maximum amount of such goods or of any variety of such goods which 
may be possessed at any one time by such a person.


</article>



<article><tid>1503706</tid>
<number> 9</number> Offences and penalties. <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1901340</tid>
<number>1</number>] Whoever commits any of the  
following offences, namely.-

<subsection><tid>1650751</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>9</footcitenum> contravenes any of the provisions of section 8 or of 
a rule made under clause (iii) or clause (xxvii) of sub- 
section (2) of section 37;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1979031</tid>
<number>b</number>evades the payment of any duty payable under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>530626</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> removes any excisable goods in contravention of any of 
the provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder or in 
any way concerns himself with such removal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1347003</tid>
<number>bbb</number>acquires possession of, or in any way concerns himself 
in transporting, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or 
purchasing, or in any other manner deals with, any excisable 
goods which he knows or has reason to believe are liable to 
confiscation under this Act or any rule made thereunder;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1978</year>). The original 
s. 5 was omitted by Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1956</year>, s. 33, for" any specified excisable 
goods".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4 for" First Schedule" (w. e. f. 28- 2-  
  <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1956</year>, s. 33, for" any excisable goods 
specified in this behalf in Part A of the second Schedule".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by s. 34, ibid., for" any excisable goods specified in 
this behalf in Part B of the Second Schedule".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>S. 9 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 36 of 
<year>1973</year>, s. 20.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by s. 20, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1988</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. and omitted by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, s. 113



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>79024</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to supply any information which he is required by 
rules made under this Act to supply, or (unless with a  
reasonable belief, the burden of proving which shall be upon 
  him, that the information supplied by him is true) supplies 
false information;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>888517</tid>
<number>d</number>attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, any of 
the offences mentioned in clauses (a) and (b) of this 
section;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be punishable,-


<subsubsection><tid>548677</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of an offence relating to any excisable 
goods, the duty leviable thereon under this Act exceeds one 
lakh of rupees, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years and with fine:
Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reasons 
to the contrary to be recorded in the judgment of the Court 
such imprisonment shall not be for a term of less than six 
months;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>817420</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three years or with fine or with both.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1682852</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If any person convicted of an offence under this section is 
again convicted of an offence under this section, then, he shall be 
punishable for the second and for every subsequent offence with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years and with fine:
Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reasons to 
the contrary to be recorded in the judgment of the Court such 
imprisonment shall not be for a term of less than six months.


</section>

<section><tid>1728596</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of sub- sections (1) and (2), the following 
shall not be considered as special and adequate reasons for awarding 
a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than six months, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>17450</tid>
<number>i</number>the fact that the accused has been convicted for the 
first time for an offence under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119742</tid>
<number>ii</number>the fact that in any proceeding under this Act, other 
than a prosecution, the accused has been ordered to pay a 
penalty or the goods in relation to such proceedings have 
been ordered to be confiscated or any other action has been 
taken against him for the same act which constitutes the 
offence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1002841</tid>
<number>iii</number>the fact that the accused was not the principal 
offender and was acting merely as a carrier of goods or 
otherwise was a secondary party in the commission of the 
offence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348222</tid>
<number>iv</number>the age of the accused.]

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1767419</tid>
<number>9A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Certain offences to be non- cognisable. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> 4, (5 of  
  <year>1898</year>) offences under section 9 shall be deemed to be non- cognisable 
within the meaning of that Code.
</article>



<article><tid>1726604</tid>
<number> 9AA</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1566205</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if be 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1973</year>, s. 20, for Certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 20, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 21, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>See now s. 9 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1985383</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>595535</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and' includes a firm or 
other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935549</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.]

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1313996</tid>
<number> 9B</number> Power of Court to publish name, place of business etc., of 
persons convicted under the Act.
<section><tid>687289</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any person is convicted  
under this Act for contravention of any of the provisions thereof, it 
shall be competent for the Court convicting- the person to cause the 
name and place of business or residence of such person, nature of the 
contravention, the fact that the person has been so convicted and such 
other particulars as the Court may consider to be appropriate in the 
circumstances of the case, to be published at the expense of such 
person, in such newspapers or in such manner as the Court may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1601234</tid>
<number>2</number>No publication under sub- section (1) shall be made until the 
period for preferring an appeal against the orders of the Court has 
expired without any appeal having been preferred, or such an appeal, 
having been preferred, has been disposed of.

</section>

<section><tid>1100708</tid>
<number>3</number>The expenses of any publication under sub- section (1) shall 
be recoverable from the convicted person as if it were a fine imposed 
by the Court.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1979502</tid>
<number> 9C</number> Presumption of culpable mental state.
<section><tid>981344</tid>
<number>1</number>In any prosecution  
for an offence under this Act which requires a culpable mental state 
on the part of the accused, the Court shall presume the existence of 
such mental state but it shall be a defence for the accused to prove 
the fact that he had no such mental state with respect to the act 
charged as an offence in that prosecution.
Explanation.- In this section," culpable mental state" includes 
intention motive, knowledge of a fact, and belief in, or reason to 
believe, a fact.


</section>

<section><tid>1589586</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, a fact is said to be 
proved only when the Court believes it to exist beyond reasonable 
doubt and not merely when its existence is established by a 
preponderance of probability.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>265829</tid>
<number> 9D</number> Relevancy of statements under certain circumstances.
<section><tid>858964</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
statement made arid signed by a person before any Central Excise 
Officer of a gazetted rank during the course of any inquiry or 
proceeding under this Act shall be relevant, for the purpose of 
proving, in any prosecution for an offence under this Act, the truth 
of the facts which it contains,-

<subsection><tid>931424</tid>
<number>a</number>when the person who made the statement is dead or 
cannot be found, or is incapable of giving evidence, or is 
kept out of the way by the adverse party, or whose presence 
cannot be obtained without an amount of delay or expense 
which, under the circumstances of the case, the Court 
considers unreasonable; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1429486</tid>
<number>b</number>when the person who made the statement is examined as a 
witness in the case before the Court and the Court is of 
opinion that, having regard to the circumstances of the case, 
the statement should be admitted in evidence in the interests 
of justice.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1493602</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall, so far as may be, 
apply in relation to- any proceedings under this Act, other than a 
proceeding before a Court, as they apply in relation to a proceeding 
before a Court.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>442695</tid>
<number> 9E</number> Application of section 562 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year>, and of the Probation of offenders Act, <year>1958</year>.
<section><tid>1683566</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing  
contained in section 562 of the Code of Criminal Procedure <year>1898</year> 1, (5  
  of <year>1898</year>) or in the Probation of Offenders Act, <year>1958</year>, (20 of <year>1958</year>) 
shall apply to a person convicted of an offence under this Act unless 
that person is under eighteen years of age.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the relevant provisions of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1919817</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3) of section 9.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>359358</tid>
<number>10</number>Power of Courts to order forfeiture. Any Court trying an 
offence under this Chapter may order the forfeiture to Government of 
any goods in respect of which the Court is satisfied that an offence 
under this Chapter has been committed, and may also order the 
forfeiture of any receptacles, packages or coverings in which such 
goods are contained and the animals, vehicles, vessels or other 
conveyances, used in carrying the goods and any implements or 
machinery used in the manufacture of the goods.


</article>



<article><tid>99975</tid>
<number>11</number>Recovery of sums due to Government. In respect of duty and any 
other sums of any kind payable to the Central Government under any of 
the provisions of this Act or of the rules made thereunder, the 
officer empowered by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>] (54 of  
  <year>1963</year>) to levy such duty or require the payment of such sums may deduct 
the amount so payable from any money owing to the person from whom 
such sums may be recoverable or due which may be in his hands or under 
his disposal or control, or may recover the amount by attachment and 
sale of excisable goods belonging to such person; and if the amount 
payable is not so recovered he may prepare a certificate signed by him 
specifying the amount due from the person liable to pay the same and 
send it to the Collector of the district in which such person resides 
or conducts his business and the said Collector, on receipt of such 
certificate, shall proceed to recover from the said person the amount 
specified therein as if it were an arrear of land revenue.
</article>



<article><tid>323464</tid>
<number> 11A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Recovery of duties not levied or not paid or short levied 
or short paid or erroneously refunded.
<section><tid>1638081</tid>
<number>1</number>When any duty of excise has  
not been levied or paid or has been short- levied or short- paid or 
erroneously refunded, a Central Excise Officer may, within six months 
from the relevant date, serve notice on the person chargeable with the 
duty which has not been levied or paid or which has been short- levied 
or short- paid or to whom the refund has erroneously been made, 
requiring him to show cause why he should not pay the amount specified 
in the notice: (54 of <year>1963</year>)
Provided that where any duty of excise has not been levied or 
paid or has been short- levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded by 
reason of fraud, collusion or any wilful misstatement or suppression 
of facts, or contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or of 
the rules made thereunder with intent to evade payment of duty, by 
such person or his agent, the provisions of this sub- section shall 
have effect, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as if (5 xxx),] for the words" six months", the words 
" five years" were substituted.

Explanation.- Where the service of the notice is stayed by an 
order of a Court, the period of such stay shall be excluded in 
computing the aforesaid period of six months or five years, as the 
case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>22356</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The[ Central Excise Officer] 5 shall, after considering 
the representation, if any, made by the person on whom notice is 
served under sub- section (1), determine the amount of duty of excise 
due from such person (not being in excess of the amount specified in  
  the notice) and thereupon such person shall pay the amount so 
determined.

</section>

<section><tid>611708</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section-

<subsection><tid>1255591</tid>
<number>i</number>" refund" includes rebate of duty of excise on excisable 
goods exported out of India or on excisable materials used in 
the manufacture of goods which are exported out of India;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5 for" Central Board of Revenue" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>S. 11A and 11B ins. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 17- 11-  
  <year>1980</year>); vide notification No. G. S. R. 654 (E), dated 15- 11- <year>1980</year> and s. 
11C (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1978</year>); vide notification No. G. S. R. 327 (E), dated 19- 
6- <year>1978</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3, for" as if".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by 9. 3, ibid., for" The Assistant Collector of Central 
Excise".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Omitted and subs. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, s. 113.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1556565</tid>
<number>ii</number>" relevant date" means,.-

<subsubsection><tid>1595929</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of excisable goods on which duty of excise 
has not been levied or paid or has been short- levied or 
short- paid-

<subsubsubsection><tid>1362015</tid>
<number>A</number>where under the rules made under this Act a 
monthly return, showing particulars of the duty paid 
on the excisable goods removed during the month to which 
the said return relates, is to be filed by a 
manufacturer or producer or a licensee of a warehouse, 
as the case may be, the date on which such return is so 
filed;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>130074</tid>
<number>B</number>where no monthly return as aforesaid is filed, the 
last date on which such return is to be filed under the 
said rules;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1317293</tid>
<number>C</number>in any other case, the date on which the duty is 
to be paid under this Act or the rules made thereunder;

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1329374</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where duty of excise is provisionally 
assessed under this Act or the rules made thereunder, the 
date of adjustment of- duty after the final assessment thereof 
;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>265018</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of excisable goods on which duty of excise 
has been erroneously refunded, the date of such refund.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389453</tid>
<number> 11B</number> Claim for refund of duty.
<section><tid>750532</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person claiming refund of  
any duty of excise may make an application for refund of such duty to 
the Assistant Collector of Central Excise before the expiry of six 
months <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> from the relevant date <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in such form as may be prescribed 
and the application shall be accompanied by such documentary or other 
evidence (including the documents referred to in section 12A) as the 
applicant may furnish to establish that the amount of duty of excise 
in relation to which such refund is claimed was collected from, or 
paid by, him and the incidence of such duty had not been passed on by 
him to any other person:
Provided that where an application for refund has been made 
before the commencement of the Central Excises and Customs Laws 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1991</year>, such application shall be deemed to have been 
made under this sub- section as amended by the said Act and the same 
shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of subsection 
 (2) as substituted by that Act]:

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided further that] the limitation of six months shall not 
apply where any duty has been paid under protest.

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1383910</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> if, on receipt of any such application, the Assistant Col- 
lector of Central Excise is satisfied that the whole or any part of 
the duty of excise paid by the applicant is refundable, he may make an 
order accordingly and the amount so determined shall be credited to 
the Fund:
Provided that the amount of duty of excise as determined by the 
Assistant Collector of Central Excise under the foregoing provisions 
of this sub- section shall, instead of being credited to the Fund, be 
paid to the applicant, if such amount is, relatable to--


<subsection><tid>867604</tid>
<number>a</number>rebate of duty of excise on excisable goods exported 
out of India or, on excisable materials used in the manufac- 
ture of goods which are exported out of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1811214</tid>
<number>b</number>unspent advance deposits lying in balance in the 
applicant' s account current maintained with the Collector of 
Central Excise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1501569</tid>
<number>c</number>refund of credit of duty paid on excisable goods used 
as inputs in accordance with the rules made, or any notifica- 
tion issued, under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>984342</tid>
<number>d</number>the duty of excise paid by the manufacturer, if he had 
not passed on the incidence of such duty to any other person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>810141</tid>
<number>e</number>the duty of excise borne by the buyer, if he had not 
passed on the incidence of such duty to any other person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1976349</tid>
<number>f</number>the duty of excise borne by any other such class of 
applicants as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify:
Provided further that no notification under clause (f) of the 
first proviso shall be issued unless in the opinion of the Central 
Government the incidence of duty has not been passed on by the persons 
concerned to any other person.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1341165</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any 
judgment, decree, order or direction of the Appellate Tribunal or any 
Court or in any other provision of this Act or the rules made 
thereunder or any other law for the time being in force, no refund 
shall be made except as provided in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>290302</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notification under clause (f) of the first proviso to 
subsection (2) shall be laid before each House of Parliament, if it is 
sitting, as soon as may be after the issue of the notification, and, 
if it is not sitting, within seven days of its reassembly, and the 
Central Government shall seek the approval of Parliament to the 
notification by a resolution moved within a period of fifteen days 
beginning with the day on which the notification is so laid before the 
House of the People and if Parliament makes any modification in the 
notification or directs that the notification should cease to have 
effect, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, but without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1247955</tid>
<number>5</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any 
notification issued under clause (f) of the first proviso to sub- 
section (2), including any such notification approved or modified 
under sub- section (4), may be rescinded by the Central Government at 
any time by notification in the Official Gazette."]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>419920</tid>
<number>A</number>" refund" includes rebate of duty of excise on excisable 
goods exported out of India or on excisable materials used 
in 
the manufacture of goods which are exported out of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>116655</tid>
<number>B</number>" relevant date" means,-

<subsubsection><tid>221398</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of goods exported out of India where a 
refund of excise duty paid is available in respect of 
the goods themselves or, as the case may be, the 
excisable materials used in the manufacture of such 
goods,-

<subsubsubsection><tid>668939</tid>
<number>i</number>if the goods are exported by sea or air, the date 
on which the ship or the aircraft in which such goods 
are loaded, leaves India, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1399085</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the goods are exported by land, the date on 
which such goods pass the frontier, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 49, for" from the date of payment 
of duty".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Explanation to sub- section (1) omitted by s. 49, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. s. 49, ibid., for Explanation

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. and Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1991</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f. 20- 09- <year>1991</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1679726</tid>
<number>iii</number>if the goals arc exported by post, the date of despatch 
of goods by the Post Office concerned to a place outside 
India;

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1959603</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of goods returned for being remade, 
refined, reconditioned, or subjected to any other similar 
process, in any factory, the date of entry into the factory 
for the purposes aforesaid;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>6379</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of goods to which banderols are required to 
be affixed if removed for home consumption but not so 
required when exported outside India, if returned to a 
factory after having been removed from such factory for 
export out of India, the date of entry into the factory;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>495313</tid>
<number>d</number>in a, case where a manufacturer is required to pay a 
sum, for a certain period, on the basis of the rate fixed by 
the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette in full discharge of his liability for the duty 
leviable on his production of certain goods, if after the 
manufacturer has made the payment on the basis of such rate 
for any period but before the expiry of that period such rate 
is reduced, the date of such reduction;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>667133</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in the case of a person, other than the manufacturer, 
the date of purchase of the goods by such person;"]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1465742</tid>
<number>f</number>in any other case, the date of payment of duty.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1599388</tid>
<number> 11C</number> Power not to recover duty of excise not levied or short- 
levied as a result of general practice.
<section><tid>1112427</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is 
satisfied-

<subsection><tid>276466</tid>
<number>a</number>that a practice was, or is, generally prevalent 
regarding levy of duty of excise (including non- levy thereof) 
on any excisable goods; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1684708</tid>
<number>b</number>that such goods were, or are, liable-

<subsubsection><tid>930992</tid>
<number>i</number>to duty of excise, in cases where according to the 
said practice the duty was not, or is not being, levied, 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>623814</tid>
<number>ii</number>to a higher amount of duty of excise than what 
was, or is being, levied, according to the said 
practice,
then, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that the whole of the duty of excise payable on such 
goods, or, as the case may be, the duty of excise in excess of that 
payable on such goods, but for the said practice, shall not be 
required to be paid in respect of the goods on which the duty of 
excise was not, or is not being, levied, or was, or is being, short- 
levied, in accordance with the said practice.]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1861133</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Where any notification under sub- section (1) in respect of 
any goods has been issued, the whole of the duty of excise paid on 
such goods or, as the case may be, the duty of excise paid in excess 
of that payable on such goods, which would not have been paid if the 
said notification had been in force, shall be dealt with in accordance 
in force, shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- section (2) of section 11B:
Provided that the person claiming the refund of such duty or, as 
the case may be, excess duty, makes an application in this behalf to 
the Assistant Collector of Central Excise, in expiry of six months in 
sub- section (1) Of section 11B, before the expiry of six months from 
the date of issue of the said notification."]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>642563</tid>
<number> 11D</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Duties of excise collected from the buyer to be deposited 
with the Central Government.
<section><tid>472690</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the  
contrary contained in any order or direction of the Appellate Tribunal 
or any Court or in any other provision of this Act or the rules made 
thereunder, every person who has collected any amount from the buyer 
of any goods in any manner as representing duty of excise, shall 
forthwith pay the amount so collected to the credit of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1194486</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount paid to the credit of the Central Government 
under sub- section (1) shall be adjusted against the duty of excise 
payable by the person on finalisation of assessment and where any 
surplus is left after such adjustment, the amount of such surplus 
shall either be credited to the Fund or, as the case may be, refunded 
to the person who has borne the incidence of such amount, in accord- 
ance with the provisions of section 11B and the relevant date for 
making an application under that section in such cases shall be the 
date of the public notice to be issued by the Assistant Collector of 
Central Excise.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1722124</tid>
<number>12</number>Application of the provisions of Act 8 of <year>1878</year> to Central 
excise duties. The Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions of the Sea 
Customs Act, <year>1878</year> 1, relating to the levy of and exemption from 
customs duties, drawback of duty, warehousing, offences and penalties, 
confiscation, and procedure relating to offences and appeals shall, 
with such modifications and alterations as it may consider necessary 
or desirable to adapt them to the circumstances, be applicable in 
regard to like matters in respect of the duties imposed by section 3.
CHAP

INDICATING AMOUNT OF DUTY IN THE PRICE OF GOODS, ETC., FOR PURPOSEOF REFUND AND 
CREDITING CERTAIN AMOUNTS TO THE FUND

<footcitenum>7</footcitenum> CHAPTER IIA

INDICATING AMOUNT OF DUTY IN THE PRICE OF GOODS, ETC., FOR PURPOSE 
OF REFUND AND CREDITING CERTAIN AMOUNTS TO THE FUND

</article>



<article><tid>198912</tid>
<number>12A</number>Price of goods to indicate the amount of duty paid thereon. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for 
the time being in force, every person who is liable to pay duty of 
excise on any goods shall, at the time of clearance of the goods, 
prominently indicate in all the documents relating to assessment, 
sales invoice, and other like documents, the amount of such duty which 
will form part of the price at which such goods are to be sold.
</article>



<article><tid>1242142</tid>
<number>12B</number>Presumption that incidence of duty has been passed on to the 
buyer. Ever person who has paid the duty of excise on any goods under 
this Act shall, unless the, contrary is proved by him, be deemed to 
have passed on the full incidence of such duty to the buyer of such 
goods.
</article>



<article><tid>4871</tid>
<number> 12C</number> Consumer Welfare Fund.
<section><tid>389697</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established by the  
Central Government a fund, to be called the Consumer Welfare Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1032660</tid>
<number>2</number>There shall be credited to the Fund, in such manner as may 
be prescribed,--

<subsection><tid>196198</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of duty of excise referred to in sub- section 
 (2) of section 11B or sub- section (2) of section 11C or sub- 
section (2) of section 11D;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>601029</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of duty of customs referred to in sub- 
section (2) of section 27 or sub- section (2) of section 28A, 
or 
sub- section (2) of section 28B of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1571291</tid>
<number>c</number>any income from investment of the amount credited to 
the Fund and any other monies received by the Central Govern- 
ment for the purposes of this Fund.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>467986</tid>
<number> 12D</number> Utilisation of the Fund.
<section><tid>1105418</tid>
<number>1</number>Any money credited to the Fund  
shall be utilised by the Central Government for the welfare of the 
consumers in accordance with such rules as that Government may make in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1880730</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall maintain or, if it thinks fit, 
specify the authority which shall maintain, proper and separate ac- 
count and other relevant records in relation to the Fund in such form 
as may be prescribed in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India."]
CHAP

POWERS AND DUTIES OF OFFICERS AND LANDHOLDERS

CHAPTER III

POWERS AND DUTIES OF OFFICERS AND LANDHOLDERS


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>819732</tid>
<number> 12E</number> <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Powers of Central Excise Officers.
<section><tid>881989</tid>
<number>1</number>A Central Excise  
Officer may exercise the powers and discharge the duties conferred or 
imposed under this Act on any other Central Excise Officer who is 
subordinate to him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Renumbered and ins. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, S. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1988</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1991</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by S. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by S. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by S. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Renumbered by Act 40 of <year>1991</year>, S. 7 (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1911544</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
Collector of Central Excise (Appeals) shall not exercise the powers 
and discharge the duties conferred or imposed on a Central Excise 
Officer other than those specified in section 14 or Chapter VIA.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1211095</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to arrest.
<section><tid>417962</tid>
<number>1</number>Any Central Excise Officer duly  
empowered by the Central Government in this behalf may arrest any 
person whom he has reason to believe to be liable to punishment under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1596640</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person accused or reasonably suspected' of committing an 
offence under this Act or any rules made thereunder, who on demand of 
any officer duly empowered by the, Central Government in this behalf 
refuses to give his name and residence, or who gives a name or 
residence which such officer has reason to believe to be false, may be 
arrested by such officer in order that his name and residence may be 
ascertained.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>285169</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to summon persons to give evidence and produce 
documents in inquiries under this Act.
<section><tid>201754</tid>
<number>1</number>Any Central Excise Officer  
duly empowered by the Central Government in this behalf shall have 
power to summon any person whose attendance he considers necessary 
either to give evidence or to produce a document or any other thing in 
any inquiry which such officer is making for any of the purposes of 
this Act. A summons to produce documents or other things may be for 
the production of certain specified documents or things or for the 
production of all documents or things of a certain description in the 
possession or under the control of the person summoned.

</section>

<section><tid>70962</tid>
<number>2</number>All persons so summoned shall be bound to attend, either in 
person or by an authorised agent, as such officer may, direct; and all 
persons so summoned shall be bound to state the truth upon any subject 
respecting which they are examined or make statements and to produce 
such documents and other things as may be required:
Provided that the exemptions under sections 132 and 133 of the 
Code of Civil Procedure shall be applicable to requisitions for 
attendance under this section. (5 of <year>1980</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>1512817</tid>
<number>3</number>Every such inquiry as aforesaid shall be deemed to be a 
" judicial proceeding" within the meaning of section 193 and section 
 228 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>538168</tid>
<number>15</number>Officers required to assist Central Excise Officers. All 
officers of Police and Customs and all officers of Government engaged 
in the collection of land revenue, and all village officers are hereby 
empowered and required to assist the Central Excise Officers in the 
execution of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1419531</tid>
<number>16</number>Owners or occupiers of land to report manufacture of 
contraband excisable goods. Every owner or occupier of land, and the 
agent of any such owner or occupier, in charge of the management of- 
that land, if contraband excisable goods are manufactured thereon, 
shall in the absence of reasonable excuse be bound to give notice of 
such manufacture to a Magistrate, or to an officer of the Central 
Excise, Customs, Police, or Land Revenue Department, immediately the 
fact comes to his knowledge.


</article>



<article><tid>169658</tid>
<number>17</number>Punishment or connivance at offences. Any owner or occupier 
of land, or any agent of such owner or occupier in charge of the 
management of that land, who wilfully connives at any offence against 
the provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder shall for 
every Such offence be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1966205</tid>
<number>18</number>Searches and arrests how to be made. All searches made under 
this Act or any rules' made thereunder and all arrests made under this 
Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, 18981, relating respectively to' searches and 
arrests made under that Code. (5 of <year>1898</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1294443</tid>
<number>19</number>Disposal of persons arrested. Every person arrested under 
this Act shall be forwarded without delay to the nearest Central 
Excise Officer empowered to send persons so arrested to a Magistrate, 
or, if there is no such Central Excise Officer within a reasonable 
distance,- to the officer- in- charge of the nearest police- station.


</article>



<article><tid>1218311</tid>
<number>20</number>Procedure to be followed by officer- in- charge of 
police station. The officer- in- charge of a police- station to whom any 
person is forwarded under section 19 shall either admit him to bail to 
appear before the Magistrate having jurisdiction, or in default of 
bail forward him in custody to such Magistrate.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See row the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1733650</tid>
<number> 21</number> Inquiry how to be made by Central Excise Officers against 
arrested persons forwarded to them under section 19.
<section><tid>247140</tid>
<number>1</number>When any  
person is forwarded under section 19 to a Central Excise Officer 
empowered to send persons so arrested to a Magistrate, the Central 
Excise Officer shall proceed to inquire into the charge against him.

</section>

<section><tid>1867192</tid>
<number>2</number>For this purpose the Central Excise Officer may exercise the 
same powers and shall be subject to the same provisions as the 
officer- in- charge of a police- station may exercise and is subject to 
under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 18981, when investigating a 
cognizable case: (5 of <year>1898</year>).
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1900441</tid>
<number>a</number>if the Central Excise Officer is of opinion that there 
is sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion 
against the accused person, he shall either admit him to bail 
lo appear before a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the 
case, or forward him in custody to such Magistrate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1331582</tid>
<number>b</number>if it appears to the Central Excise Officer that there 
is not sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion 
against the accused person, he shall release the accused 
person on his executing a bond, with or without sureties as 
the Central Excise Officer may direct, to appear, if and when 
so required before the Magistrate having jurisdiction, and 
shall make a full report of all the particulars of the case 
to his official superior.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>942270</tid>
<number> 22</number> Vexatious search, seizure, etc., by Central Excise Officer. 
Any Central Excise or other officer exercising powers under this Act 
or under the rules made thereunder who-
<section><tid>307248</tid>
<number>a</number>without reasonable ground of suspicion searches or 
causes to be searched any house, boat or place;

</section>

<section><tid>1058866</tid>
<number>b</number>vexatiously and unnecessarily detains, searches or 
arrests any person;

</section>

<section><tid>1543542</tid>
<number>c</number>vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes the moveable 
property of any person, on pretence of seizing or searching 
for any article liable to confiscation under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1686306</tid>
<number>d</number>commits, as such officer, any other act to the injury 
of any person, without having reason to believe that such act 
is required for the execution of his duty;
shall, for every such offence, be punishable with fine which may 
extend to two thousand rupees.

Any person wilfully and maliciously giving false information and 
so causing an arrest or a search to be made under this Act shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees or with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>551268</tid>
<number>23</number>Failure of Central Excise Officer in duty. Any Central Excise 
Officer who ceases or refuses to perform or withdraws himself from the 
duties of his office, unless he has obtained the express written per- 
mission of the Collector of Central Excise, or has given to his 
superior officer two months' notice in writing of his intention or has 
other lawful excuse, shall on conviction before a Magistrate be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
months or with fine which may extend to three months' pay, or with 
both.
CHAP

TRANSPORT BY SEA

CHAPTER IV

TRANSPORT BY SEA



</article>



<article><tid>1062636</tid>
<number>24</number>Penalties for carrying excisable goods in certain vessels. 
When any excisable goods are carried by sea in any vessel other than a 
vessel of the burden of three hundred tons and upwards, the owner and 
master of such vessel shall each be punishable with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to 
one thousand rupees, or with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>. (Act 2 of  
  <year>1974</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>836991</tid>
<number> 25</number> Exceptions. Nothing in section 24 applies to-
<section><tid>1790913</tid>
<number>a</number>any excisable goods covered by a permit granted under 
rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>878554</tid>
<number>b</number>any excisable goods covered by a pass granted by any 
officer whom the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>] 
may appoint in this behalf; (54 of <year>1963</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1676955</tid>
<number>c</number>such amount of excisable goods carried on board any 
vessel for consumption by her crew or by the passengers or 
animals (if any) on board as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise 
and Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue 
Act, <year>1963</year>] may from time to time exempt from the operation of 
section 24. (54 of <year>1963</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>260109</tid>
<number> 26</number> Power of stoppage, search and arrest. When any officer- 
empowered by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted 
under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>], (54 of <year>1963</year>) to act 
Under this section has reason to believe, from personal knowledge or 
from information taken down in writing, that any excisable goods are 
being carried, or have within the previous twenty- four hours been 
carried, in any vessel so as to render the owner or master of such 
vessel liable to the penalties imposed by section 24, he may require 
such vessel to be brought- to and thereupon may-
<section><tid>607687</tid>
<number>a</number>enter and search the vessel;

</section>

<section><tid>109401</tid>
<number>b</number>require the master of the vessel to produce any 
documents in his possession relating to the vessel or the 
cargo thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>358786</tid>
<number>c</number>seize the vessel if the officer has reason to believe 
it liable to confiscation under this Act, and cause it to be 
brought with its crew and cargo into any port in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India]; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>540599</tid>
<number>d</number>where any excisable goods are found on board the 
vessel, search and arrest without a warrant any person on 
board the vessel whom he has reason to believe to be 
punishable under section 24.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>358607</tid>
<number>27</number>Penalties for resisting officer. Any master of a vessel 
refusing or neglecting to bring- to the vessel or to produce his 
papers when required to do so by an officer acting under section 26, 
and any person obstructing any such officer in the performance of 
his duty, may be arrested by such officer without a warrant, and shall 
be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.


</article>



<article><tid>1452788</tid>
<number> 28</number> Confiscation of vessel and cargo.
<section><tid>1829853</tid>
<number>1</number>Every vessel (including   
  all appurtenances) in which any excisable goods are carried so as to 
render the owner or master of such vessel liable to penalties imposed 
by section 24, the cargo on board such vessel and the excisable goods 
in respect of which an offence under this Act has been committed shall 
be liable to confiscation on the orders of the officer empowered in 
this behalf by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1844993</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any Customs Officer is satisfied that any article 
is liable to confiscation under this section he may seize such 
article, and shall at once report the seizure to his superior officer 
for the information of the officer empowered to order confiscation 
under sub- section (1) and such officer may, if satisfied on such 
report or after making such inquiry as he thinks fit, that the article 
so seized is liable, to confiscation, either declare it to be 
confiscated, or impose a fine in lieu thereof not exceeding the value 
of the article.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>637755</tid>
<number>29</number>Jurisdiction. Any offence punishable under section 24 or 
section 27 may be deemed to have been committed within the limits of 
the jurisdiction of the Magistrate of any place where the offender is 
found, or to which, if arrested under section 26 or section 27, he may 
be brought.


</article>



<article><tid>1897738</tid>
<number>30</number>Power to exempt from operation of his Chapter. The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt the 
carriage of excisable goods within any local limits or in any class of 
vessels from the operation of this Chapter, and, by like notification, 
again subject such carriage to the operation of this Chapter.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for" Central Board of Revenue" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1950</year>, s. 11 and Sch. IV, for the States".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO SALT

CHAPTER V

SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO SALT



</article>



<article><tid>997853</tid>
<number>31</number>Special and permanent rights of manufacturing salt to be 
recognised. The proprietor of a private salt factory who has by virtue 
of a sanad granted by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] or any former Government, a 
special and permanent right to manufacture salt, or to excavate or 
collect natural salt, shall on application made in accordance with the 
rules made under this Act be entitled to a licence for such purpose 
and to the annual renewal thereof, unless on a breach of the 
provisions of this Act, his licence has been cancelled by an officer 
duly empowered by the Central Government in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>861476</tid>
<number>32</number>Rights of ordinary proprietors of existing salt- works. Every 
proprietor of a private salt- work, other than a private salt factory, 
to which section 31 applies, of which, under the provisions of section 
 17 of the Bombay Salt Act, <year>1890</year>, (Bom. Act 11 of <year>1890</year>) the proprietor 
was entitled on application to a licence to manufacture or to excavate 
or collect natural salt at such factory, shall continue to be 
entitled, on, application made in accordance with the rules made under 
this Act, to a licence for such purpose and to the annual renewal 
thereof, unless on a breach of the provisions of this Act his licence 
has been cancelled by an officer duly empowered by the Central 
Government in this behalf:
Provided that the Collector of Central Excise may at any time 
withdraw or withhold a licence from the proprietor of any such salt 
factory, if no salt' has been manufactured, excavated or collected in 
such salt factory for the three years ending on the thirtieth day of 
June last preceding the date of his order, or, with the previous 
sanction of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted 
under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>], (54 of <year>1963</year>) if such 
salt factory has not produced, on an average, during the said three 
years, at least five thousand maunds. of salt per annum.

CHAP

ADJUDICATION OF CONFISCATIONS AND PENALTIES

CHAPTER VI

ADJUDICATION OF CONFISCATIONS AND PENALTIES



</article>



<article><tid>782716</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power of adjudication. Where by the rules made under this Act 
anything is liable to confiscation or any person is liable to a 
penalty, such confiscation or penalty may be adjudged-
<section><tid>150894</tid>
<number>a</number>without limit, by a Collector of Central Excise;

</section>

<section><tid>1308522</tid>
<number>b</number>up to confiscation of goods not exceeding five hundred 
rupees in value and imposition of penalty not exceeding two 
hundred and fifty rupees, by an Assistant Collector of 
Central Excise:
Provided that the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>] (54 of  
  <year>1963</year>) may, in the case of any officer performing the duties of an 
Assistant Collector of Central Excise, reduce the limits indicated in 
clause (b) of this section and may confer on any officer the powers 
indicated in clause (a) or (b) of this section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1306731</tid>
<number>34</number>Option to pay fine in lieu of confiscation. Wherever 
confiscation is adjudged under this Act or the rules made thereunder, 
the officer adjudging it shall give the owner of the goods an option 
to pay in lieu of confiscation such fine as the officer thinks fit.
</article>



<article><tid>337078</tid>
<number>34A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Confiscation or penalty not to interfere with other 
punishments. No confiscation made or penalty imposed under the 
provisions, of this Act or of any rule made thereunder shall prevent 
the infliction of any other punishment to which the person affected 
thereby is liable under the provisions of this Act or under any other 
law.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. 0. <year>1950</year>, for" The British".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for" Central Board of Revenue" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1973</year>, s. 22.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

APPEALS

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> CHAPTER VIA

APPEALS



</article>



<article><tid>1734004</tid>
<number> 35</number> Appeals to Collector (Appeals).
<section><tid>119618</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by  
any decision or order passed under this Act by a Central Excise 
Officer lower in rank than a Collector, of Central Excise may appeal 
to the Collector of Central, Excise (Appeals)[ hereafter in this 
Chapter referred to as the Collector (Appeals)] within three months 
from the date of the communication to him of such decision or order:
Provided that the Collector (Appeals) may, if he is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting 
the appeal within the aforesaid period of three months, allow it to be 
presented within a further period of three months.


</section>

<section><tid>1822200</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal under this section shall be in the prescribed 
form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1229732</tid>
<number> 35A</number> Procedure in appeal.
<section><tid>259523</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector (Appeals). shall give  
an opportunity to the appellant to be heard, if he so desires.

</section>

<section><tid>598436</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector (Appeals) may, at the hearing of an appeal, 
allow an appellant to go into any ground of appeal not specified in 
the grounds of appeal, if the Collector (Appeals) is satisfied that 
the omission of that ground from the grounds of appeal was not wilful 
or unreasonable.

</section>

<section><tid>234972</tid>
<number>3</number>The Collector (Appeals), may, after making such further 
inquiry as may be necessary, pass such order as he thinks fit 
confirming, modifying or annulling the decision or order appealed 
against, or may refer the case back to the adjudicating authority with 
such directions as he may think fit for a fresh adjudication or 
decision, as the case may be, after taking additional evidence, if 
necessary:
Provided that an order enhancing any penalty or fine in lieu of 
confiscation or confiscating goods of greater value or reducing the 
amount of refund shall not be passed unless the appellant has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed 
order:

Provided further that where the Collector (Appeals) is of opinion 
that any duty of excise has not been levied or paid or has been short- 
levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded, no order requiring the 
appellant to pay any duty not levied or paid, short- levied or short- 
paid or erroneously refunded shall be passed unless the appellant is 
given notice within the time limit specified in section 11 A to show 
cause against the proposed order.


</section>

<section><tid>1773945</tid>
<number>4</number>The order of the Collector (Appeals) disposing of the appeal 
shall be in writing and shall state the points for determination the 
decision thereon and the reasons for the decision.

</section>

<section><tid>1411165</tid>
<number>5</number>On the disposal of the appeal, the Collector (Appeals) shall 
communicate the order passed by him to the appellant, the adjudicating 
authority and the Collector of Central Excise.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>62280</tid>
<number> 35B</number> Appeals to the Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1931276</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved  
by any of the following orders may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal 
against such order-

<subsection><tid>988204</tid>
<number>a</number>a decision or order passed by the Collector of Central 
Excise as an adjudicating authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1193204</tid>
<number>b</number>an order passed by the Collector (Appeals) under 
section 35A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488802</tid>
<number>c</number>an order passed by the Central Board of Excise and 
Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 
 <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as  
  the Board) or the Appellate Collector of Central Excise under 
section 35, as it stood immediately before the appointed day;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 50 and Sch. V. for ss. 35, 35A 
and 36 (w. e. f. 11- 10- <year>1982</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1372143</tid>
<number>d</number>an order passed by the Board or the Collector of Central 
Excise, either before or after the appointed day, under 
section 35A, as it stood immediately before that day:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that no appeal shall lie to the Appellate Tribunal 
and the Appellate Tribunal shall not have jurisdiction to 
decide any appeal in respect' of any order referred to in 
clause (b) if such order relates to,-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988204</tid>
<number>a</number>a case of loss of goods, where the loss occurs in 
transit from a factory to a warehouse or to another 
factory, or from one warehouse to another, or during 
the course of processing of the goods in a warehouse or 
in storage, whether in a factory or in a warehouse;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1193204</tid>
<number>b</number>a rebate of duty of excise on goods exported to 
any country or territory outside India or on excisable 
materials used in the manufacture of goods which are 
exported to any country or territory outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488802</tid>
<number>c</number>goods exported outside India (except to Nepal or  
  Bhutan) without payment of duty:
Provided further that] the Appellate Tribunal may, in its 
discretion, refuse, to admit an appeal in respect of an order referred 
to in clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) where-


<subsubsection><tid>698555</tid>
<number>i</number>in any disputed case, other than a case where the 
determination of any question having a relation to the 
rate of duty of excise or to the value, of goods for 
purposes of assessment is in issue or is one of the 
points in issue, the difference in duty involved or the 
duty involved; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1105388</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount of fine or penalty determined by such 
order,
does not exceed[ fifty thousand rupees] 4


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1097434</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every appeal against any order of the nature referred to 
in the first proviso to sub- section (1), which is pending immediately 
before the commencement of section 47 of the Finance Act, <year>1984</year>, (21 of  
  <year>1984</year>) before the Appellate Tribunal and any matter arising out of, or 
connected with, such appeal and which is so pending shall stand 
transferred on such commencement to the Central Government, and the 
Central Government shall deal with such appeal or matter under section 
 35EE as if such appeal or matter were an application or a matter 
arising out of' an application made to it under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>1582693</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector of Central Excise may, if he is of opinion 
that an order passed by the Appellate Collector of Central Excise 
tinder section 35, as it stood immediately before the appointed day, 
or the Collector (Appeals) under section 35A, is not legal or proper, 
direct any Central Excise Officer authorised by him in this behalf 
 (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the authorised officer) to 
appeal on his behalf to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.

</section>

<section><tid>938274</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under this section shall be filed within three 
months from the date on which the order sought to be appealed against 
is communicate to the Collector of Central Excise, or, as the case may 
be, the other party preferring the appeal.

</section>

<section><tid>1069596</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of notice that an appeal has been preferred under 
this section, the party against whom the appeal has been preferred 
may, notwithstanding that. he may not have appealed against such order 
or any part thereof, file, within forty- five days of the receipt of 
the notice, a memorandum of cross objections verified in the 
prescribed manner against any part of the order appealed against and 
such memorandum shall be disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if 
it were an appeal, presented within the time specified in sub- section 
 (3).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 47, for" Provided that".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 47, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Sub- section (2) shall stand subs. by Act 62 of <year>1986</year>, s. 34 
 (date to be notified) as follows:-


(2) The Collector of Central Excise may, if he is of opinion 
that an order passed by--

(a) the Appellate Collector of Central Excise under section 
35, as it stood immediately before the appointed day, or

(b) the Collector (Appeals) under section 35A, is not legal 
or proper, direct any Central Excise Officer authorised by 
him in this behalf (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as  
  the authorised officer) to appeal on his behalf to the 
Appellate Tribunal or, as he case may be, the Customs, and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under section 
3 of 62 of <year>1986</year> the Customs And Excise Revenues Appellate 
Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>, against such order".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1993</year>, S. 45.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1171782</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if 
it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it 
within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>1448496</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and 
shall, in the case of an appeal made on or after the 1st day of June, 
<year>1993</year>, irrespective of the date of demand of duty Pr of levy of penalty 
in relation to which the appeal is made, be accompanied by a fee of,-

<subsection><tid>1457673</tid>
<number>a</number>where the amount of duty demanded and penalty levied by 
any Central Excise Officer in the case to which the appeal 
relates is one lakh rupees or less, two' hundred rupees:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1662927</tid>
<number>b</number>where the amount of duty demanded and penalty levied by 
any Central Excise Officer in the case to which the appeal 
relates is more than one lakh rupees, one thousand rupees:
Provided that no such fee shall be payable in the case of an 
appeal referred to in sub- Section. (2) or a memorandum of cross- 
objections referred to in sub- section (4)."]


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220412</tid>
<number> 35C</number> Orders of Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>643875</tid>
<number>1</number>The Appellate Tribunal  
may, after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being, 
heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming, 
modifying or annulling the decision or order appealed against or may 
refer the case back to the- authority which passed such decision or 
order with such directions as the Appellate Tribunal may think fit, 
for a fresh adjudication or decision, as the case may be, after taking 
additional evidence, if necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1696245</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate Tribunal may, At any time within four years 
from the date of the order, with a view to rectifying any mistake 
apparent from the record, amend any order passed by it under sub- 
section (1) and shall make such amendments if the mistake is brought 
to its notice by the Collector of Central Excise or the other party to 
the appeal:
Provided that an amendment which has the effect of enhancing an 
assessment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability 
of the other party, shall not be made under this sub- section, unless 
the Appellate Tribunal has given notice to him of its intention to do 
so and has allowed him a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1305838</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order 
passed under this section to the Collector of Central Excise and the 
other party to the appeal.

</section>

<section><tid>1576686</tid>
<number>4</number>Save as provided in section 35G or section 35L, orders 
passed by the Appellate Tribunal on appeal shall be final.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748039</tid>
<number> 35D</number> Procedure of Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>448155</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of  
sub- sections (1), (2), (5) and (6) of section 129C of the Customs Act, 
<year>1962</year>, shall apply to the Appellate Tribunal in the discharge of its 
functions under this Act as they apply to it in the discharge of its 
functions under the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>. (52 of <year>1962</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>788334</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal against a decision or order relating, among 
other things, to the determination of any question having a relation 
to the rate of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of 
assessment, shall be heard by a Special Bench constituted by the 
President for hearings such appeals and such Bench- shall consist of 
not less than"[ two members] and shall include at least one judicial 
member and one technical member.

</section>

<section><tid>1760176</tid>
<number>3</number>The President or any other member of the Appellate Tribunal 
authorised in this behalf by the President may, sitting singly, 
dispose of any case which has been allotted to the Bench of which he 
is a member where-

<subsection><tid>1858557</tid>
<number>a</number>in any disputed case, other than a case where the 
determination of any question having a relation to the rate 
of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of 
assessment is in issue or is one of the points in issue, the 
difference in duty involved or the duty involved; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>654370</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of fine or penalty involved,
does not exceed <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> one lakh rupees]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 5, for" three members".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 48 for" ten thousand rupees"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1993</year>, S. 45.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>819902</tid>
<number> 35E</number> Powers of Board or Collector of Central Excise to pass 
certain orders.
<section><tid>844835</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, of its own motion, call for and  
examine the record of any proceeding in which a Collector of Central 
Excise as an adjudicating authority has passed any decision or order 
under this Act for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the legality 
or propriety of any such decision or order and may, by order, direct 
such Collector to' apply to the, Appellate Tribunal <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or, as the case 
may be, the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established 
under section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal 
Act, <year>1986</year>] (62 of <year>1986</year>) for the determination of such points arising 
out of the decision or order as may be specified by the Board in its 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>1729649</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector of Central Excise may, of his own motion, call 
for and examine the record of any proceeding in which an adjudicating 
authority subordinate to him has passed any decision or order under 
this Act for the purpose of satisfying himself as to the legality or 
propriety of any such decision or order and may, by order, direct such 
authority to apply to the Collector (Appeals) for the determination of 
such points arising' out of the decision or order as may be specified 
by the Collector of Central Excise in his order.

</section>

<section><tid>459702</tid>
<number>3</number>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) or sub- section 
 (2) after the expiry of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> one year] from the date of the decision or 
order of the adjudicating authority.

</section>

<section><tid>409424</tid>
<number>4</number>Where in pursuance of an order under subsection (1) or sub- 
section the adjudicating authority or the authorised officer makes an 
application to the Appellate Tribunal <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or, as the case may be, the 
Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under 
section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, 
<year>1986</year>] (62 of <year>1986</year>) or the Collector (Appeals) within a period of three 
months from the date of communication of the order under sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) to the adjudicating authority, such application 
shall be heard by the Appellate Tribunal <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or, as the case may be, the 
Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under 
section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, 
<year>1986</year>] or the Collector (Appeals), as the case may be, as if such 
application were an appeal made against the decision or order of the 
adjudicating authority and the provisions of this Act regarding 
appeals, including the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 35B 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or, as the case may be the provisions of the Customs and Excise 
Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>] shall, so far as may be, apply 
to such application.

</section>

<section><tid>1374269</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The provisions of this section shall not apply to any 
decision or order in which the determination of any question having a 
relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the value of goods for 
the purposes of assessment of any duty is in issue or is one of the 
points in issue.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, the determi- 
nation of a rate of duty in relation to any goods or valuation of any 
goods for the purposes of assessment of duty includes the 
determination of a question-


<subsection><tid>826675</tid>
<number>a</number>relating to the rate of duty of excise for the time 
being in force, whether under the Central Excise Tariff Act, 
 <year>1985</year> or under any other Central Act providing for the levy 
and collection of any duty of excise, in relation to any 
goods on or after the 28th day of February, <year>1986</year>; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932464</tid>
<number>b</number>relating to the value of goods for the purposes of 
assessment of any duty of excise in cases where the 
assessment is made on or after the 28th day of February, 
<year>1986</year>; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>543901</tid>
<number>c</number>whether any goods are excisable goods or whether the 
rate of duty of excise on any goods is nil; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1763061</tid>
<number>d</number>whether any goods fall under a particular heading or 
sub- heading of the Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act, 
<year>1985</year>, (5 of <year>1986</year>) or the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods  
  of Special Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>) or the 
Additional Duties of Excise (Textiles and Textile Articles) 
Act, <year>1978</year>, (40 of <year>1978</year>) or that any goods are or not covered 
by a particular notification or order issued by the Central 
Government or the Board, as the case may be, granting total 
or partial exemption from duty; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>81798</tid>
<number>e</number>whether the value of any goods for the purposes of 
assessment of duty of excise shall be enhanced or reduced by 
the addition or reduction of the amounts in respect of such 
matters as are specifically provided in this Act.]

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1566203</tid>
<number> 35EA</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Powers of revision of Board or Collector of Central 
Excise in certain cases.
<section><tid>1718259</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, of its own motion or on  
the application of any aggrieved person or otherwise, call for and 
examine the record of any proceeding in which a Collector of Central 
Excise has passed any decision or order[ not being a decision or order 
passed under sub- section (2) of this section] of the nature referred 
to in sub- section (5) of section 35E for the purpose of satisfying 
itself as to correctness, legality or propriety of such decision or 
order and may pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>380879</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector of Central Excise may, of his own motion or on 
the application of any aggrieved person or otherwise, call for and 
examine the record of any proceeding in which an adjudicating 
authority subordinate to him has passed any decision or order of the 
nature referred to in sub- section (5) of section 35E for the purpose 
of satisfying himself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of 
such decision or order and may pass such order thereon as he thinks 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>600460</tid>
<number>3</number> (a) No decision or order under this section shall be made so 
as to prejudicially affect any person unless such person is given a 
reasonable opportunity of making representation and if, he so desires, 
of being heard in his defence.

<subsection><tid>935552</tid>
<number>b</number>Where the Board or, as the case may be, the Collector of 
Central Excise is of the opinion that any duty of excise has not 
been levied or has been short- levied or short- paid or erroneously 
refunded, no order requiring the affected person to pay any duty not 
levied or paid, short- levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded 
shall be passed under this section unless such person is given notice 
within the time limit specified in section 11A to show cause against 
the proposed order.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>550603</tid>
<number>4</number>No proceedings shall be initiated under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) in respect of any decision or order after the expiry 
of a period of six months from the date of communication of such 
decision or order:
Provided that in respect of any decision or order passed before 
the commencement of the Customs and Central Excises Laws (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1987</year>, the provisions of this sub- section shall have effect as if 
for the words" six months", the words" one year" were substituted.


</section>

<section><tid>1674339</tid>
<number>5</number>Any person aggrieved by any decision or order passed under 
sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) may appeal to the Customs and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under section 3 the 
Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>, against such 
decision or order."]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>232414</tid>
<number> 35EE</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Revision by Central Government.
<section><tid>1295586</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, on the application of any person aggrieved by any 
order passed under section 35A, where the order is of the nature 
referred to in the first proviso to, sub- section (1) of section 35B, 
annul or modify such order.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," order passed 
under section 35A" includes an order passed under that section before 
the commencement of section 47 of the Finance Act, <year>1984</year> (21 of <year>1984</year>) 
against which an appeal has not been preferred before such 
commencement and could have been. if the said section had not come 
into force, preferred after such commencement, to the Appellate 
Tribunal.


</section>

<section><tid>1863550</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under sub- section (1) shall be made within 
three months from the date of the communication to the applicant of 
the order against which the application is being made:
Provided that the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that 
the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting the 
application within the. aforesaid period of three months, allow it to 
be presented within a further period of three months.


</section>

<section><tid>1924354</tid>
<number>3</number>An application under sub- section (1) shall be in such form 
and shall be verified in such manner as may be specified by rules made 
in this behalf and shall be accompanied by a fee of two hundred 
rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>759225</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, of its own motion, annul or 
modify any order referred to in sub- section (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 62 o.' <year>1986</year>, s. 34 (date to be notified).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 49, for" two years".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 21 of <year>1984</year>, s. 50.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, S. 11 (w. e. f.............)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by S. 12, ibid. (w. e. f..........)




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>656064</tid>
<number>5</number>No order enhancing any penalty or fine in lieu of 
confiscation or confiscating goods of greater value shall be passed 
under this section,-

<subsection><tid>793986</tid>
<number>a</number>in any case in. which an order passed under section 35A 
has enhanced any penalty or fine in lieu of confiscation or 
has confiscated goods of greater value, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1352570</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, unless the person affected by the 
proposed order has been given notice to show cause against it 
within one year from the date of the order sought to be 
annulled or modified.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1514219</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the Central Government is of opinion that any duty of 
excise has not been levied or has been short- levied, no order levying 
or enhancing the duty shall be made under this section unless the 
person affected by the proposed order is given notice to show cause 
against it within the time limit specified in section 11A.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1240075</tid>
<number>35F</number>Deposit, pending appeal of duty demanded or penalty levied. 
Where in any appeal under this Chapter, the decision or order appealed 
against relates to any duty demanded in respect of goods which are not 
under the control of central excise authorities or any penalty levied 
under this Act, the person desirous of appealing against such decision 
or order shall, pending the appeal, deposit with the adjudicating 
authority the duty demanded or the penalty levied:
Provided that where in any particular case, the Collector 
 (Appeals) or the Appellate Tribunal is of opinion that the deposit of 
duty demanded or penalty levied would cause undue hardship to such 
person, the Collector (Appeals) or, as the case may be, the Appellate 
Tribunal, may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as 
he or it may deem fit to impose so as to safeguard the interests of 
revenue.

</article>



<article><tid>482621</tid>
<number> 35G</number> Statement of case to High Court.
<section><tid>969136</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector of  
Central Excise or the other party may, within sixty days of the date 
upon which he is served with notice of an order under section 35C (not  
being an order relating, among other things, to the determination of 
any question having a relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the 
  value of goods for purposes of assessment), by application in the 
prescribed form, accompanied, where the application is made by the 
other party, by a fee of two hundred rupees, require the Appellate 
Tribunal to refer to the High Court any question of law arising out of 
such order and, subject to the other provisions contained in this 
section, the Appellate Tribunal shall, within one hundred and twenty 
days of the receipt of such application, draw up a statement of the 
case and refer it to the High Court:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that 
the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting the 
application within the period hereinbefore specified, allow it to be 
presented within a further period not exceeding thirty days.


</section>

<section><tid>38080</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of notice that an application has been made under 
sub- section (1), the person against whom such application has been 
made, may, notwithstanding that he may not have filed such an 
application, file, within forty- five days of the receipt of the 
notice, a memorandum of cross- objections verified in the prescribed 
manner against any part of the order in relation to which an 
application for reference has been made and such memorandum shall be 
disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an application 
presented within the time specified in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>588485</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on an application made under sub- section (1), the 
Appellate Tribunal refuses to state the case on the ground that no 
question of law arises, the Collector of Central Excise, or, as the 
case may be, the other party may, within six months from the date on 
which he is served with notice of such refusal, apply to the High 
Court and the High Court may, if it is not satisfied with the 
correctness of the decision of the Appellate Tribunal, require the 
Appellate Tribunal to state the case and to refer it, and on receipt 
of any such requisition, the Appellate Tribunal shall state the case 
and refer it accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>830905</tid>
<number>4</number>Where in the exercise of its powers under sub- section (3), 
the Appellate Tribunal refuses to state a case which it has been 
required by an applicant to state, the applicant may, within thirty 
days from the date on which he receives notice of such refusal, 
withdraw his application and, if he does so, the fee, if any, paid by 
him shall be refunded.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975371</tid>
<number>35H</number>Statement of case to Supreme court in certain cases. If, on 
an application made under section 35G, the Appellate Tribunal is of 
opinion that, on account of conflict in the decisions of High Courts 
in respect of any particular question of law, it is expedient that a 
reference should be made direct to the Supreme Court, the Appellate 
Tribunal may draw up a statement of the case and refer it through the 
President direct to the Supreme Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

</article>



<article><tid>1165686</tid>
<number>35I</number>Power of High Court or Supreme Court to require statement to 
be amended. If the High Court or the Supreme Court is not satisfied 
that the statements in a case referred to it are sufficient to enable 
it to determine the questions raised thereby, the Court may refer the 
case back to the Appellate Tribunal, for the purpose of making such 
additions thereto or alterations therein as it may direct in that 
behalf.
</article>



<article><tid>961411</tid>
<number> 35J</number> Case before High Court to be heard by not less than two 
Judges.
<section><tid>216191</tid>
<number>1</number>When any case has been referred to the High Court under  
section 35G, it shall be heard by a Bench of not less than two Judges 
of the High Court and shall be decided in accordance with the opinion 
of such Judges or of the majority, if any, of such Judges.

</section>

<section><tid>989880</tid>
<number>2</number>Where there is no such majority, the Judges shall state the 
point of law upon which they differ and the case shall then be heard 
upon that point only by one or more of the other Judges of the High 
Court, and such point shall be decided according to the opinion of the 
majority of the Judges who have heard the case including those who 
first heard it.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1041170</tid>
<number> 35K</number> Decision of High Court or Supreme Court on the case stated.

<section><tid>639634</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Court or the Supreme Court hearing any such case shall  
decide the questions of law raised therein and shall deliver its 
judgment thereon containing the grounds on which such decision is 
founded and a copy of the judgment shall be sent under the seal of the 
Court and the signature of the Registrar to the Appellate Tribunal 
which shall pass such orders as are necessary to dispose of the case 
in conformity with such judgment.

</section>

<section><tid>58238</tid>
<number>2</number>The costs of any reference to the High Court or the Supreme 
Court which shall not include the fee for making the reference shall 
be in the discretion of the Court.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>885756</tid>
<number> 35L</number> Appeal to Supreme Court. An appeal shall lie to the Supreme 
Court from-
<section><tid>1344972</tid>
<number>a</number>any judgment of the High Court delivered on a reference 
made under section 35G in any case which, on its own motion 
or on an oral application made by or on behalf of the party 
aggrieved, immediately after the passing of the judgment, the 
High Court certifies to be a fit one for appeal to the 
Supreme Court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1525530</tid>
<number>b</number>any order passed by the Appellate Tribunal relating, 
among other things, to the determination of any question 
having a relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the 
value of goods for purposes of assessment.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1752818</tid>
<number> 35M</number> Hearing before Supreme Court.
<section><tid>732439</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of the Code  
of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> 1, (5 of <year>1908</year>) relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court shall, so far as may be, apply in the case of appeals 
under section 35L a, they apply in the case of appeals from decrees of 
a High Court:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to 
affect the provisions of sub- section (1) of section 35K or section 
35N.


</section>

<section><tid>937918</tid>
<number>2</number>The costs of the appeal shall be in the discretion of the 
Supreme Court.

</section>

<section><tid>631982</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the judgment of the High Court is varied or reversed in 
the appeal, effect shall be given to the order of the Supreme Court in 
the manner provided in section 35K in the case of a judgment of the 
High Court.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98604</tid>
<number> 35N</number> Sums due to be paid notwithstanding reference, etc. 
Notwithstanding that a reference has been made to the High Court or 
the Supreme Court or an appeal has been preferred to the Supreme 
Court, sums due to the Government as a result of ail order passed 
under sub- section
<section><tid>1940677</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 35C shall be payable in accordance  
with the order so passed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1581723</tid>
<number>35O</number>Exclusion of time taken for copy. In computing the period 
of limitation prescribed for an appeal or application under this 
Chapter, the day on which the order complained of was served, and if 
the party preferring the appeal or making the application was not 
furnished with a copy of the order when the notice of the order was 
served upon him, the time requisite for obtaining a copy of such order 
shall be excluded.
</article>



<article><tid>616853</tid>
<number> 35P</number> Transfer of certain pending proceedings and transitional 
provisions.
<section><tid>1889975</tid>
<number>1</number>Every appeal which is pending immediately before the  
appointed day before the Board under section 35, as it stood 
immediately before that day, and any matter arising out of or 
connected with such appeal and which is so pending shall stand 
transferred on that day to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate 
Tribunal may proceed with such appeal or matter from the stage at 
which it was on that day:
Provided that the appellant may demand that before proceeding 
further wit] that appeal or matter, he may be re- heard.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the relevant provisions of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (Act 2 of <year>1974</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>141252</tid>
<number>2</number>Every proceeding which is pending immediately before the 
appointed day before the Central Government under section 36, as it 
stood immediately before that day, and any matter arising out of or 
connected with such proceeding and which is so pending shall stand 
transferred on that day to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate 
Tribunal may proceed with such proceeding or matter from the stage at 
which it was on that day as if such proceeding or matter were an 
appeal filed before it:
Provided that if any such proceeding or matter relates to an 
order where-


<subsection><tid>1705793</tid>
<number>a</number>in any disputed case, other than a case where the 
determination of any question having a relation to the rate 
of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of 
assessment is in issue or is one of the points in issue, the 
difference in duty involved or the duty involved; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254766</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of fine or penalty determined by such order,
does not exceed ten thousand rupees, such proceeding or matter shall 
continue to be dealt with by the Central Government as if the said 
section 36 had not been substituted:

Provided further that the applicant or the other party may make a 
demand to the Appellate Tribunal that before proceeding further with 
that proceeding or matter, he may be re- heard.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>547059</tid>
<number>3</number>Every proceeding which is pending immediately before the 
appointed day before the Board or the Collector of Central Excise 
under section 35A, as it stood immediately before that day, and any 
matter arising out of or connected with such proceeding and which is 
so pending shall continue to be dealt with by the Board or the 
Collector of Central Excise, as the case may be, as if the said 
section had not been substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>323045</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person who immediately before the appointed day was 
authorised to appear in any appeal or proceeding transferred under 
sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 35Q, have the right to appear before the 
Appellate Tribunal in relation to such appeal or proceeding.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>877413</tid>
<number> 35Q</number> Appearance by authorised representative.
<section><tid>551678</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who  
is entitled or required to appear before a Central Excise Officer or 
the Appellate Tribunal in connection with any proceedings under this 
Act, otherwise than when required under this Act to appear personally 
for examination on oath or affirmation, may, subject to the other 
provisions of this section, appear by an authorised representative.

</section>

<section><tid>504012</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section," authorised 
representative" means a person authorised by the person referred to in 
sub- section (1) to appear on his behalf, being-

<subsection><tid>1387854</tid>
<number>a</number>his relative or regular employee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1768376</tid>
<number>b</number>any legal practitioner who is entitled to practise in 
any civil court in India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1218521</tid>
<number>c</number>any person who has acquired such qualifications as the 
Central Government may prescribe for this purpose.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1640291</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no 
person who was a member of the Indian Customs and Central Excise 
Service- Group A and has retired or resigned from such Service after 
having served for not less than three years in any capacity in that 
Service, shall be entitled to appear as an authorised representative 
in any proceedings before a Central Excise Officer for a period of two 
years from the date of his retirement or resignation, as the case may 
be.

</section>

<section><tid>1544685</tid>
<number>4</number>No person,-

<subsection><tid>4683</tid>
<number>a</number>who has been dismissed or removed from Government 
service; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728713</tid>
<number>b</number>who is convicted of an offence connected with any 
proceeding under this Act, the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>) 
or the Gold (Control) Act, <year>1968</year>; or (45 of <year>1968</year>)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1231347</tid>
<number>c</number>who has become an insolvent,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall be qualified to represent any person under sub- section (1), for 
all times in the case of a person referred to in clause (a), and for 
such time as the Collector of Central Excise or the competent 
authority under the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>) or the Gold 
 (Control) Act, <year>1968</year>, (45 of <year>1968</year>) as the case may be, may, by order, 
determine in the case of a person referred to in clause (b), and for 
the period during which the insolvency continues in the case of a 
person referred to in clause (c).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>793115</tid>
<number>5</number>If any person,-

<subsection><tid>1346864</tid>
<number>a</number>who is a legal practitioner, is found guilty of 
misconduct in his professional capacity by any authority 
entitled to institute proceedings against him, an order 
passed by that authority shall have effect in relation to his 
right to appear before a Central Excise Officer or the 
Appellate Tribunal as it has in relation to his right to, 
practise as a legal practitioner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180278</tid>
<number>b</number>who is not a legal practitioner, is found guilty of 
misconduct in connection with any proceedings under this Act 
by the prescribed authority, the prescribed authority may 
direct that he shall thenceforth be disqualified to represent 
any person under sub- section (1).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>191620</tid>
<number>6</number>Any order or direction under clause (b) of sub- section (4) 
or clause (b) of sub- section (5) shall be subject to the following 
conditions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1825116</tid>
<number>a</number>no such order or direction shall be made in respect of 
any person unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>766212</tid>
<number>b</number>any person against whom any such order or direction is 
made may, within one month of the making of the order or 
direction, appeal to the Board to have the order or direction 
cancelled; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614095</tid>
<number>c</number>no such order or direction shall take effect until the 
expiration of one month from the making thereof, or, where an 
appeal has been preferred, until the disposal of the appeal.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748907</tid>
<number> 36</number> Definitions. In this Chapter-
<section><tid>1567241</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date 1 of coming into force of 
the amendments to this Act specified in Part II of the Fifth 
Schedule to the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1980</year>; (44 of <year>1980</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1324994</tid>
<number>b</number>" High Court" means,--

<subsection><tid>1822889</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to any State, the High Court for that 
State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257392</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to a Union territory to which the 
jurisdiction of the High Court of a State has been 
extended by law, that High Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>19493</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to the Union territories of Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli and Goa, Daman and Diu, the High Court at 
Bombay,;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21768</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to another Union territory, the 
highest court of civil appeal for that territory other 
than the Supreme Court of India;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>429966</tid>
<number>c</number>" President" means the President of the Appellate 
Tribunal.]
CHAP

PRESUMPTION AS TO DOCUMENTS]

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> CHAPTER VIB

PRESUMPTION AS TO DOCUMENTS]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>859142</tid>
<number> 36A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Presumption as to documents in certain cases. Where any 
document is produced by any person or has been seized from the custody 
or control of any person, in either case, under this Act or under any 
other law and such document is tendered by the prosecution in evidence 
against him or against him and any other person who is tried jointly 
with him, the Court shall,-
<section><tid>515995</tid>
<number>a</number>unless the contrary is proved by such person, presume--

<subsection><tid>967787</tid>
<number>i</number>the truth of the contents of such document;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 11- 10- <year>1982</year>: vide Notification No. G. S. R. 592 (E), dated 11- 10- 
<year>1982</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins, by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 50 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 11- 10- <year>1982</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1973</year>, s. 23.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1218944</tid>
<number>ii</number>that the signature and every other part of such 
document which purports to be in the handwriting of any 
particular person or which the Court may reasonably 
assume to have been signed by, or to be in' the hand- 
writing of, any particular person, is in that person' s 
handwriting, and in the case of a document executed or 
attested, that it was executed or attested by the person 
by whom it purports to have been so executed or attest- 
ed;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1034964</tid>
<number>b</number>admit, the document in evidence, notwithstanding 
that it is not duly. stamped, if such document is 
otherwise admissible in evidence.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1828681</tid>
<number> 36B</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Admissibility of micro films, facsimile copies of 
documents and computer print outs as documents and as evidence.
<section><tid>1843286</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force,-

<subsection><tid>1062284</tid>
<number>a</number>a micro film of a document or the reproduction of the 
image or images embodied in such micro film (whether enlarged  
  or not); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>132047</tid>
<number>b</number>a facsimile copy of a document; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1376376</tid>
<number>c</number>a statement contained in a document and included in a 
printed material produced by a computer (hereinafter referred  
  to as a' computer print out"), if the conditions mentioned in 
subsection (2) and the other provisions contained in this 
section are satisfied in relation to the statement and the 
computer in question,
shall be deemed to be also a document for the purposes of this Act and 
the rules made thereunder and shall be admissible in any proceedings 
thereunder, without further proof or production of the original, as 
evidence of any contents of the original or of any fact stated therein 
of which direct evidence would be admissible.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1774607</tid>
<number>2</number>The conditions referred to in sub- section (1) in respect of 
a computer print out shall be the following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1401279</tid>
<number>a</number>the computer print out containing the statement was 
produced by the computer during the period over which the 
computer was used regularly to store or process information 
for the purposes of any activities regularly carried on over 
that period by the person having lawful control over the use 
of the computer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>896170</tid>
<number>b</number>during the said period, there was regularly supplied to 
the computer in the ordinary course of the said activities, 
information of the kind contained In the statement or of the 
kind from which the information so contained is derived;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1805219</tid>
<number>c</number>throughout the material part of the said period, the 
computer was operating properly or, if not, then any respect 
in which it was not operating properly or was out of 
operation during that part of that period was not such as to 
affect the production of the document or the accuracy of the 
contents; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1270515</tid>
<number>d</number>the information contained in the statement reproduces 
or is derived from information supplied to the computer in 
the ordinary course of the said activities.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1918399</tid>
<number>3</number>Where over any period, the function of storing or processing 
information for the purposes of any activities regularly carried on 
over that period as mentioned in clause (a) of sub- section (2) was 
regularly performed by computers, whether-

<subsection><tid>1056632</tid>
<number>a</number>by a combination of computers operating over that 
period; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1118057</tid>
<number>b</number>by different computers operating in succession over 
that period; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>64459</tid>
<number>c</number>by different combinations of computers operating in 
succession over that period; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1451382</tid>
<number>d</number>in any other manner involving the successive operation 
over that period, in whatever order, of one or more computers 
and one or more combinations of computers,
all the computers used for that purpose during that period shall be 
treated for the purposes of this section as constituting a single com- 
puter; and references in this section to a computer shall be construed 
accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1200239</tid>
<number>4</number>In any proceedings under this: Act and the rules made there- 
under where it is desired to give a statement in evidence, by virtue 
of this section, a certificate doing any of the following things, that 
is to say,--

<subsection><tid>1393869</tid>
<number>a</number>identifying the document containing the statement and 
describing the manner in which It was produced;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>297096</tid>
<number>b</number>giving such particulars of any device involved in the 
production of that document as may be appropriate for the 
purpose of showing that the document was produced by a 
computer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475973</tid>
<number>c</number>dealing with any of the matters to which the conditions 
mentioned in sub- section (2) relate,
and purporting to be signed by a person occupying a responsible 
official position in relation to the operation of the relevant device 
or the management of the relevant activities (whichever is appro-  
  priate) shall be evidence of any matter stated in the certificate; and 
for the purposes of this sub- section it shall be sufficient for a 
matter to; be stated to the best of the knowledge and belief of the 
person stating it.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>111106</tid>
<number>5</number>For the purposes of this section,-

<subsection><tid>1239127</tid>
<number>a</number>information shall be taken to be supplied, to a 
computer if it is supplied thereto in any appropriate form 
and whether It is so supplied directly or (with or without  
  human intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489203</tid>
<number>b</number>whether in the course of activities carried on by any 
official, information is supplied with a view to Its, being 
stored or processed for the purposes of those activities by a 
computer operated otherwise than in. the course of those 
activities, that information, if duly supplied to that 
computer, shall be taken to be supplied to it in the course 
of those activities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>965428</tid>
<number>c</number>a document shall be taken to have been produced by a 
computer whether it was produced by it directly or (with or  
  without human intervention) by means of any appropriate 
equipment.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1239127</tid>
<number>a</number>" computer" means any device that receives, stores and 
processes data, applying stipulated processes to the 
information and supplying results of these processes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489203</tid>
<number>b</number>any reference to information being derived from other 
information shall be a reference to its being derived 
therefrom by calculation comparison or an other process.]
CHAP

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS

CHAPTER VII

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804072</tid>
<number> 37</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>310242</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may make rules to carry into effect the purposes of this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>898284</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may--

<subsection><tid>261927</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> provide for determining under section 4 the nearest 
ascertainable equivalent of the normal price;

<subsubsection><tid>1160037</tid>
<number>ia</number>having regard to the normal practice of the wholesale 
trade, define or specify the kinds of trade discount to be 
excluded from the value under section 4 including the 
circumstances in which and the conditions subject to which 
such discount is to be so excluded;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>849899</tid>
<number>ib</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>] provide for the assessment and collection of duties 
of excise, the authorities by whom functions under this Act 
are to be discharged, the issue of notices requiring payment, 
the manner in which the duties shall be payable, and the 
recovery of duty not paid;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1104106</tid>
<number>ic</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> provide for the remission of duty of excise leviable 
on any excisable goods, which due to any natural cause are 
found to be deficient in quantity, the limit or limits of 
percentage beyond which no such remission shall be allowed 
and the different limit or limits of percentage for different 
varieties of the same excisable goods or for different areas 
or for different seasons;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1235206</tid>
<number>ii</number>prohibit absolutely, or with such exceptions, or 
subject to such conditions as the Central Government thinks 
fit, the production or manufacture, or any process of the 
production or manufacture, of excisable goods, or of any 
component parts or ingredients or containers thereof, except 
on land or premises approved for the purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1166812</tid>
<number>iii</number>prohibit absolutely, or with such exceptions, or 
subject to such conditions as the Central Government thinks 
fit, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the transit of excisable goods from any part of a 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> India] to any other part thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378280</tid>
<number>iv</number>regulate the removal of excisable goods from the place 
where produced, stored or manufactured or subjected to any 
process of production or manufacture and their transport to 
or from the premises of a[ registered] 7 or a bonded 
warehouse, or to a market;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1205031</tid>
<number>v</number>regulate the production or manufacture, or any process 
of the production or manufacture, the possession, storage and 
sale of salt, and so far as such regulation is essential for 
the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by this 
Act, of any other excisable goods, or of any component parts 
or ingredients or containers thereof;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1973</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl (i) renumbered as cl. (ib) by s. 3, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, s. 25 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" the bringing of excisable goods into India from 
the State of Jammu and Kashmir, or" omitted by Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 
and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1950</year>, s. 11 and Sch. IV, for" the States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1988</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, S. 113.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1297852</tid>
<number>vi</number>provide for the employment of officers of the Government to 
supervise the carrying out of any rules made under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>456488</tid>
<number>vii</number>require a manufacturer or the licensee of a warehouse to 
provide accommodation within the precincts of his factory or warehouse 
for officers employed to supervise the carrying out of regulations 
made under this Act and prescribe the scale of such accommodation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064136</tid>
<number>viii</number>provide for the appointment, licensing, management, and 
supervision of bonded warehouses and the procedure to be followed in 
entering goods into and clearing goods from such warehouses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>805219</tid>
<number>ix</number>provide for the distinguishing of goods which have been 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> manufactured after registration] of materials which have been 
imported under licence, and of goods on which duty has been paid, or 
which are exempt from duty under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>130664</tid>
<number>x</number>impose on persons engaged in the production or manufacture, 
storage or sale (whether on their own account or as brokers or  
  commission agents) of salt, and, so far as such imposition is 
essential for the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by 
this Act, of any other excisable goods, the duty of furnishing 
information, keeping records and making returns, and prescribe the 
nature of such information and the form of such records and returns, 
the particulars to be contained therein, and the manner in which they 
shall be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>218819</tid>
<number>xi</number>require that excisable goods shall not be sold or, offered 
or kept for sale in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] except in prescribed containers, bearing 
a banderol, stamp or label of such nature and affixed in such manner 
as may be prescribed;

<subsubsection><tid>1089780</tid>
<number>xii</number>provide for the issue of[ registration certificates] 2 and 
transport permits and the fees, if any, to be charged therefor:
Provided that the fees for the licensing of the manufacture and 
refining of salt and saltpetre shall not exceed. in the case of each 
such licence, the following amounts, namely:-

RS.

Licence to manufacture and refine saltpetre 
and to separate and purify salt in the process 
of such manufacture and refining 50

Licence to manufacture saltpetre

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


Licence to manufacture sulphate of soda 
 (kharinun) by solar heat in evaporating pans 10

Licence to manufacture sulphate of soda 
 (knarinun) by artificial heat 2

Licence to manufacture other saline sub- 
stances 2;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1730599</tid>
<number>xiii</number>provide for the detention of goods, plant, machinery or 
material, for the purpose of exacting the duty, the procedure in 
connection with the confiscation, otherwise than under section 10 or 
section 28, of goods in respect of which breaches of the Act or rules 
have been committed, and the disposal of goods so detained or 
confiscated;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1145543</tid>
<number>xiv</number>authorise and regulate the inspection of factories and 
provide for the taking of samples, and for the making of tests, of any 
substance produced therein, and for the, inspection or search of any 
place or conveyance used for the production, storage, sale or 
transport of salt, and so far as such inspection or search is 
essential for the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by 
this Act, of any other excisable goods;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>81373</tid>
<number>xv</number>authorise and regulate the composition of offences against, 
or liabilities incurred under, this Act or the rules made thereunder;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>883072</tid>
<number>xvi</number>provide for the grant of a rebate of the duty paid on goods 
which are exported out of India or shipped for consumption on a voyage 
to any port outside India;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1950</year>, s. 11 and Sch, IV, for" the States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, S. 113.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>32089</tid>
<number>xvia</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> provide for the credit of duty paid or deemed to have 
been paid on the goods used in, or in relation to, the manufacture of 
excisable goods;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>164950</tid>
<number>xvib</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> provide for the giving of credit of sums of money with 
respect to raw materials used in the manufacture of excisable goods;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>618411</tid>
<number>xvii</number>exempt any goods from the whole or any part of the duty 
imposed by this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1150334</tid>
<number>xviia</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> provide incentives for increased production or 
manufacture of any goods by way of remission of, or any concession 
with respect to, duty payable under this Act;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1899638</tid>
<number>xviii</number>define an area no point in which shall be more than one 
hundred yards from the nearest point of any place in which salt is 
stored or sold by or on behalf of the Central Government, or of any 
factory in which saltpetre is manufactured or refined, and regulate 
the possession, storage and sale of salt within such area;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1549140</tid>
<number>xix</number>define an area round any other place in which salt is 
manufactured, and regulate the possession, storage and sale of salt 
within such area;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1533162</tid>
<number>xx</number>authorise the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>] (54 of  
  <year>1963</year>) or Collectors of Central Excise appointed for the purposes of 
this Act to provide, by written instructions, for supplemental matters 
arising out of any rule made by the Central Government under this 
section;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>424194</tid>
<number>xxi</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> provide for the publication, subject to such conditions 
as may be specified therein, of names and other particulars of persons 
who have been found guilty of contravention of any of the provisions 
of this Act or of any rule made thereunder;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>147384</tid>
<number>xxii</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> provide for the charging of fees for the examination of 
excisable goods intended for export out of India and for rendering any 
other service by a Central Excise Officer under this Act or the rules 
made thereunder.]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1601058</tid>
<number>xxiii</number><footcitenum>9</footcitenum> specify the form in which application for refund shall 
be made under section 11B;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1731539</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>provide for the manner in which money is to be credited to 
the Fund;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>276741</tid>
<number>xxv</number>provide for the manner in which the Fund shall be utilised 
for the welfare of the consumers;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1905154</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>specify the form in which the account and records relating 
to the Fund shall be maintained."]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>942695</tid>
<number>xxvii</number><footcitenum>10</footcitenum> specify the persons who shall get themselves 
registered under section 6 and the manner of their registration.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1194841</tid>
<number>3</number>In making rules under this section, the Central Government 
may provide that any person committing a breach of any rule shall, 
where no other penalty is provided by this Act, be liable to a penalty 
not exceeding two thousand rupees and that any article in respect of 
which any such breach is committed shall be confiscated

</section>

<section><tid>1155239</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), and 
without, prejudice to the provisions of section 9, in making rules 
under this section, the Central Government may provide that if any 
manufacturer, producer or licensee of a warehouse-

<subsection><tid>660713</tid>
<number>a</number>removes any excisable goods in contravention of the 
provisions of any such rule, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1379970</tid>
<number>b</number>does not account for all such goods manufactured, 
produced or stored by him, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1352429</tid>
<number>c</number>engages in the manufacture, production or storage of 
such goods without having applied for the[ registration as] 10 
required section 6, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Proviso to cl. (xvi) omitted by Act 49 of <year>1957</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1986</year>, s. 51.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1987</year> s. 94.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1982</year>, s. 48.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for" Central Board of 
Revenue" (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1973</year>, s. 24.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 6.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. Act 19 of <year>1968</year> s. 38.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1991</year>, S. 8 (w. e. f. 20- 9- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>10</number>Ins. and Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, S. 113.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>808901</tid>
<number>d</number>contravenes the provisions of any such rule with intent to 
evade payment of duty,
then-


<subsubsection><tid>1897121</tid>
<number>i</number>any land, building, plant, machinery, materials, 
conveyance, animal or any other thing used in connection with 
the manufacture, production, storage, removal or disposal of 
such goods, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1031422</tid>
<number>ii</number>all excisable goods on such land or in such building or 
produced or manufactured with such plant, machinery, 
materials or thing,
belonging to such manufacturer, producer or licensee shall be liable 
to confiscation and the manufacturer, producer or licensee shall be 
liable to a penalty not exceeding three times the value' of the 
excisable goods in respect of which any contravention of the nature 
referred to in clause (a), (b), (c) or (d) has been committed, or 
five' thousand rupees, whichever is greater.]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1258625</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), the 
Central Government any make rules to provide for the imposition upon 
any person- who acquires possession of, or is in any way concerned in 
transporting, removing, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or 
purchasing, or in any other manner deals with, any excisable goods 
which he knows or has reason to believe are liable to confiscation 
under this Act or the rules made thereunder, a penalty not exceeding 
three times the value of such goods or five thousand rupees, whichever 
is greater.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>703039</tid>
<number> 37A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that subject to such 
conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification-
<section><tid>873839</tid>
<number>a</number>any power exercisable by the Board under this Act may 
be exercisable also by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a Principal Collector of Central 
Excise or a Collector of Central Excise] empowered in this 
behalf by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1867582</tid>
<number>b</number>any power exercisable by a Collector of Central Excise 
under this Act may be exercisable also by a Deputy Collector 
of Central Excise or an Assistant Collector of Central Excise 
empowered in this behalf by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>648958</tid>
<number>c</number>any power exercisable by a Deputy Collector of Central 
Excise under this Act may be exercisable also by an Assistant 
Collector of Central Excise empowered in this behalf by the 
Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>568202</tid>
<number>d</number>any power exercisable by an Assistant Collector of 
Central Excise under this Act may be exercisable also by a 
gazetted officer of Central Excise empowered in this behalf 
by the Board.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1672330</tid>
<number> 37B</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Instructions to Central Excise Officers. The Central Board 
of Excise and Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue 
Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>) may, if it considers it necessary or expedient 
so to do for the purpose of uniformity in the classification of 
excisable goods or with respect to levy of duties of excise on such 
goods, issue such orders, instructions and directions to the Central 
Excise Officers as it may deem fit, and such officers and all other 
persons employed in the execution of this Act shall observe and follow 
such orders, instructions and directions of the said Board:
Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be 
issued-

<section><tid>1950748</tid>
<number>a</number>so as to require any Central Excise Officer to make a 
particular assessment or to dispose of a particular case in 
a particular manner; or

</section>

<section><tid>660673</tid>
<number>b</number>so as to interfere with the discretion of the Collector 
of Central Excise (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate 
functions.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>505195</tid>
<number> 37C</number> Service of decisions, orders, summons, etc.
<section><tid>954402</tid>
<number>1</number>Any decision  
or order passed or any summons or notice issued under this Act or the 
rules made thereunder, shall be served,-

<subsection><tid>1633946</tid>
<number>a</number>by tendering the decision, order, summons or notice, or 
sending it by registered post with acknowledgment due, to the 
person for whom it is intended or his authorised agent, if 
any;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1973</year>, s. 24.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 79 of <year>1985</year>, s. 7.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, S. 14 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1988</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>44330</tid>
<number>b</number>if the decision, order, summons or notice cannot be 
served in the manner provided in clause (a), by affixing a 
copy thereof to some conspicuous part of the factory or 
warehouse or other place of business or usual place of 
residence of the person for whom such decision, order, 
summons or notice, as the case may be, is intended;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1109748</tid>
<number>c</number>if the decision, order, summons or notice cannot be 
served in the manner provided in clauses (a) and (b), by 
affixing a copy thereof on the notice board of the officer or 
authority who or which passed such decision or order or 
issued such summons or notice.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>763289</tid>
<number>2</number>Every decision or order passed or any summons or notice 
issued under this Act or the rules made thereunder, shall be deemed to 
have been served on the date on which the decision, order, summons or 
notice is tendered or, delivered by post or a copy thereof is affixed 
in the manner provided in sub- section (1),]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519258</tid>
<number>37D</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Rounding off of duty, etc. The amount of duty, interest, 
penalty, fine or any other sum payable, and the amount of refund or 
any other sum due, tinder the provisions of this Act shall be rounded 
off to the nearest rupee and, for this purpose, where such amount 
contains a part of a rupee consisting of paise then, if such part is 
fifty paise or more, it shall be increased to one rupee and if such 
part is less than fifty paise it shall be ignored.]


</article>



<article><tid>1192419</tid>
<number> 38</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Publication of rules and notifications and laying of rules 
before PArliament.
<section><tid>1278201</tid>
<number>1</number>All rules made and notifications issued under  
this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>737661</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act and every notification 
issued under sub- section (1) of section 5A and section 11C shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
notification or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made or 
the notification should not be issued, the rule or notification shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or notification."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1566128</tid>
<number>39</number>[ Repeal of enactments.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1947</year> (2 of <year>1948</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>845464</tid>
<number> 40</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Protection of action taken under the Act.
<section><tid>1900223</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer of the Central Government or a State Gov- 
ernment for anything which is done, or intended to be done, in good 
faith, in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1085234</tid>
<number>2</number>No proceeding, other than a suit, shall be commenced against 
the Central Government or any officer of the Central Government or a 
State Government for anything done or purported to have been done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder, without giving the 
Central Government or such officer a month' s previous notice in 
writing of the intended proceeding and of the cause thereof or after 
the expiration of three months from the accrual of such cause.]
[ The First Schedule.] Rep. by the Central Excise Tariff Act, <year>1985</year> 
 (5 of <year>1986</year>), s. 4 (w. e. f 28- 2- <year>1986</year>).



</section>

</article>



 </act>