<act><tid>639570</tid>
<title>THE DISPLACED PERSONS (CLAIMS) SUPPLEMENTARY ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 18th March, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to provide for the disposal of certain proceedings pending 
under the Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>), and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>35473</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>464500</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Displaced Persons (Claims) Supplementary Act, <year>1954</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>399928</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>699626</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1401710</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 17th day of May, <year>1953</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1301667</tid>
<number>b</number>" claim" means-

<subsection><tid>277687</tid>
<number>i</number>any claim registered under the principal Act 
and pending on the appointed day; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>673899</tid>
<number>ii</number>any claim submitted to any authority under 
the principal Act by any person migrating to India from 
any tribal area and pending on the appointed day;
and includes any application filed on or before the 
 12th December, <year>1952</year> for setting aside an ex- parte order 
of a Claims Officer passed under the principal Act and 
pending on the appointed day, if the application was 
not, on the date on which it was filed, barred by 
limitation under the rules made under the principal 
Act;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>221729</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>936511</tid>
<number>d</number>" principal Act" means the Displaced Persons (Claims) 
Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1143001</tid>
<number>e</number>" tribal areas" means the tribal areas of Tochi and 
Kurram and includes such other Tribal areas adjoining 
the North- West Frontier Province as may be specified in 
this behalf by an order of the Central Government;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>94</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1091577</tid>
<number>f</number>" verified claim" means any claim registered under the 
principal Act in respect of which a final order has 
been passed under that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>346562</tid>
<number>g</number>all words and expressions used but not defined in this 
Act and defined in the principal Act shall have the 
meanings assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1931352</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appointment of Chief Settlement Commissioner, etc.
<section><tid>1624894</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint a Chief Settlement Commissioner, a Joint Chief Settlement 
Commissioner, a Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioner and as many 
Settlement Commissioner, Additional Settlement Commissioners and 
Settlement Officers as may be necessary for the purpose of performing 
the functions assigned to them by or under this Act and may, by 
general or special order, provide for the distribution or allocation 
of work to be performed by them under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>637251</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Joint Chief 
Settlement Commissioner, the Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioner and 
all Settlement Commissioners, Additional Settlement Commissioners and 
Settlement Officers shall perform the functions assigned to them by or 
under this Act under the general superintendence and control of the 
Chief Settlement Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>663576</tid>
<number> 4</number> Verification of Claims.
<section><tid>872605</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules that may be  
made under this Act, a Settlement Officer shall have jurisdiction to 
decide such claims or such classes of claims as may, by general or 
special order, be transferred to him by the Chief Settlement 
Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1773457</tid>
<number>2</number>A Settlement Officer shall hold a summary inquiry into the 
claims transferred to him and, after taking such evidence and 
examining such documents, as he may consider necessary, pass such 
orders as he thinks fit in relation to the verification of the claim 
and the valuation of such claim.

</section>

<section><tid>986539</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Settlement Officer shall be final:
Provided that the Chief Settlement Commissioner may call for the 
record of any case which has been decided by the Settlement Officer 
and may make such order in the case as he thinks fit; but no order 
varying the decision of the Settlement Officer which prejudicially 
affects any person shall be made without giving him an opportunity of 
being heard.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>95</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1427654</tid>
<number> 5</number> Special power of revision in respect of cases decided under 
Act 44 of <year>1950</year>.
<section><tid>240827</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the  
principal Act, the Chief Settlement Commissioner-

<subsection><tid>610681</tid>
<number>a</number>may, on an application for revision made to him within 
time by any person aggrieved by the decision of the 
Claims Officer, call for the record of the case and 
make such order in the case as he thinks fit.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause, an 
application for revision shall be deemed to be or to 
have been made within time, if-


<subsubsection><tid>320560</tid>
<number>i</number>such application was not barred by limitation 
on the appointed day under the rules made under the 
principal Act and is filed within one month from the 
commencement of this Act; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1876159</tid>
<number>ii</number>such application had been filed before the 
appointed day and was not, on the date on which it was 
filed, barred by limitation under the rules made under 
the principal Act;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866125</tid>
<number>b</number>may, on his own motion, but subject to any rules that 
may be made in this behalf, revise any verified claim 
and make such order in relation thereto as he thinks 
fit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>871854</tid>
<number>2</number>No order varying the decision of the Claims Officer or 
revising any verified claim which prejudicially affects any person 
shall be made without giving him an opportunity of being heard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>878335</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of Settlement Officers.
<section><tid>1684782</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Settlement  
Commissioner, the Joint or Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioner or a 
Settlement Commissioner, an Additional Settlement Commissioner or a 
Settlement Officer shall have the same powers as are vested in a Civil 
Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), when trying 
a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1289593</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>181042</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1713147</tid>
<number>c</number>requisitioning any public record from any Court or 
office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1034647</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>442683</tid>
<number>e</number>appointing guardians or next friends of persons who are 
minors or of unsound mind;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>756393</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1974909</tid>
<number>2</number>A Settlement Officer may, if he so thinks fit, and shall, if 
so required by the Chief Settlement Commissioner, appoint one or more 
persons as assessors to advise him in any proceeding before him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1814840</tid>
<number>7</number>Power to transfer cases. The Central Government or the Chief 
Settlement Commissioner may, by order in writing, at any stage 
transfer any case pending before a Settlement Officer to another 
Settlement Officer and the Settlement Officer to whom the case is so 
transferred, may, subject to any special directions in the order of 
transfer, proceed from the stage at which it was transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>45633</tid>
<number>8</number>Certain officers to be public servants. The Chief Settlement 
Commissioner, the Joint or Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioner and 
all Settlement Commissioners, Additional Settlement Commissioners and 
Settlement Officers appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be 
public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>647656</tid>
<number>9</number>Bar of jurisdiction of Civil Court. No Civil Court shall have 
jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the Chief Settlement 
Commissioner or the Settlement Officer is empowered by or under this 
Act to determine, and no injunction shall be granted by any Court or 
other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in 
pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>292249</tid>
<number> 10</number> Delegation of Powers.
<section><tid>98913</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
general or special order, direct that any power exercisable by it 
under this Act shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be 
specified in the order, be exercisable also by the Chief Settlement 
Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>220331</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, the Chief Settlement Commissioner may delegate all or any 
of his powers under this Act to the Joint or Deputy Chief Settlement 
Commissioner or any Settlement Commissioner or Additional Settlement 
Commissioner as may be specified by the Chief Settlement Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>723919</tid>
<number>11</number>Validation of certain proceedings. All proceedings held or 
decisions made in relation to the verification of any claim or the 
valuation of such claim of any person who has migrated to India from 
any tribal area purporting to have been held or made under the 
principal Act shall, notwithstanding anything therein contained, be 
deemed for all purposes to have been validly made under the principal 
Act as if that Act were applicable to such persons as it applied to 
displaced persons from West Pakistan.


</article>



<article><tid>280117</tid>
<number>12</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For Rules, see gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3. p. 297.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1003865</tid>
<number>13</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 3 of <year>1954</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

</article>



 </act>