<act><tid>511573</tid>
<title>THE EMPLOYEES' PROVIDENT FUNDS AND MISCELLANEOUS 
PROVISIONS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 25 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 16th August, <year>1996</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act further to amend the Employees' Provident Funds 
and 
Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1952</year>.





<article><tid>1692930</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1980599</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Employees' Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1996</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>806302</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 16th day 
of November, <year>1995</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>146619</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title. In the long title to the Employees' 
Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1952</year> (19 of <year>1952</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), for the words" family 
pension fund", the words" pension fund" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1796048</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2. In section 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1310259</tid>
<number>a</number>clauses (gg) and (ggg) shall be omitted;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1498402</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (k), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-

<subsection><tid>808895</tid>
<number>kA</number>" Pension Fund" means the Employees' Pension Fund 
established under sub- section (2) of section 6A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>820243</tid>
<number>KB</number>" Pension Scheme" means the Employees' Pension 
Scheme framed under sub- section (1) of section 6A;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>999851</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause. (1) the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-

</section>

<section><tid>1883648</tid>
<number>ll</number>" superannuation", in relation to employee, who is 
the member of the Pension Scheme means the attainment, by 
the, said employee, the age. of fifty- eight Years;'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>319730</tid>
<number>4</number>Substitution of the word" Pension" for the words" Family 
pension". In the principal Act, for the words" Family Pension", 
wherever they occur, the word" Pension" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1654295</tid>
<number>5</number>Substitution of a new section for sections 6A and 6B. For 
sections 6A and 6B of the principal Act, the following section shall 
be substituted, namely-.-


</article>



<article><tid>460749</tid>
<number> 6A</number> Employees' pension Scheme.
<section><tid>1118115</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
frame a scheme to be called the Employees' Pension Scheme for 
the purpose of providing for-

<subsection><tid>174260</tid>
<number>a</number>superannuation pension, retiring pension or 
permanent, total disablement pension to the employees of any 
establishment or class of establishments to which this Act 
applies; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>621170</tid>
<number>b</number>widow or widower' s pension, children pension or 
orphan pension payable to the beneficiaries of such 
employees.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>304688</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6, 
there shall be established, as, soon as may be after framing 
of the Pension Scheme, a Pension Fund into which there shall 
be paid from time to time, in respect of every employee who 
is a member of the Pension Scheme.-

<subsection><tid>1361916</tid>
<number>a</number>such sums from the employer' s contribution under 
section 6, not exceeding eight and one- third per cent. of the 
basic wages, dearness allowance and retaining allowance, it 
any, of the concerned employees, as may be specified in the 
Pension Scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>565058</tid>
<number>b</number>such sums as are payable by the employers of 
exempted establishments under sub- section (6) of section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>688706</tid>
<number>c</number>the net assets of the Employees' Family Pension 
Fund as on the date of the establishment of the Pension Fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1078210</tid>
<number>d</number>such sums as the Central Government may, after due 
appropriation by Parliament by law, in this behalf, specify.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>439872</tid>
<number>3</number>On the establishment of the Pension Fund, the 
Family Pension Scheme (hereinafter referred to as the ceased  
  scheme) shall cease to operate and all assets of the ceased 
scheme shall vest in and shall stand transferred to, and all 
liabilities under the ceased scheme shall be enforceable 
against, the Pension Fund and the beneficiaries under the 
ceased' scheme shall be entitled to draw the benefits, not 
less than the benefits they were entitled to under the ceased 
scheme, from the Pension Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>416941</tid>
<number>4</number>The Pension Fund shall vest in and be administered 
by the Central Board in such manner as may be specified in 
the Pension Scheme.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>842152</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Pension 
Scheme may provide for all or any of the matters specified 
in Schedule III.

</section>

<section><tid>1974615</tid>
<number>6</number>The Pension Scheme may provide that all any of its 
provisions shall take effect either prospectively or 
retrospectively on such date as may be, specified in that 
behalf in that scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>881878</tid>
<number>7</number>A Pension Scheme, framed under subsection (1), 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be, comprised in one session, 
or in two or, more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions Aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the scheme or both Houses agree 
that the scheme Should not be made, the scheme shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that, scheme.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1861424</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 6C. In section 6C of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1903495</tid>
<number>a</number>sub- section (3) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>883876</tid>
<number>b</number>clause (b) of sub- section (4) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248484</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 17. In section 17 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1959062</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (1C), the following sub- section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (1C) The appropriate Government may, by 
notification in the Official' Gazette, and Subject to 
the condition on the pattern of investment of pension 
fund and such other conditions as may be specified 
therein, exempt any establishment or class of 
establishments from the operation of the Pension Scheme, 
if the employees of, such establishment or class of 
establishments are either members of any other pension 
scheme or propose to be members of such pension scheme, 
where the pensionary benefits are at par or more 
favourable than the Pension Scheme tinder this Act.";


</section>

<section><tid>1921182</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (6), the words" as well as the 
employees' contribution" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>327517</tid>
<number>8</number>Substitution of new Schedule for Schedule III. For Schedule 
III to the principal Act, the following Schedule shall, be substi- 
tuted, namely:-

</article>



 </act>