<act><title>


the Declaration of Wild Life 
    Stock Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Declaration of Wild Life Stock Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number> “Act” means the Wild Life 
    (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Form” means the form annexed to 
    these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> all other words and expressions used 
    in these rules shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
    Act.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Publicity of intent of notification and Assistance in making application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government 
    in this regard shall cause to give wide publicity to the intent of this 
    notification in the regional language through electronic or print media or 
    such other means.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government in 
    this regard shall take necessary action to assist the local communities and 
    individuals especially the poor and illiterate in the declaration of their 
    possession, filling up the specified form and any other matter connected 
    therewith and shall make every attempt to ensure that no individual or 
    community associated with animals is deprived of this opportunity.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Procedure for filing applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application to the Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by 
    the State Government in this regard shall be presented in the Form annexed 
    to these rules by the applicant either in person or by an agent or by duly 
    authorized legal practitioner or sent by registered post addressed to the 
    Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government in 
    this regard of the concerned State or the Union territory.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    application under sub-rule (1) shall be presented in four complete sets 
    within a period of one hundred and eighty days from the date of publication 
    of these rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    applicant may attach to and present with his application an acknowledgement 
    slip as is given in the Form which shall be signed by the official receiving 
    the application on behalf of the Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer 
    authorized by the State Government in this regard in acknowledgement of the 
    receipt of the application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Presentation and scrutiny of applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government 
    in this regard shall endorse on every application the date on which it is 
    presented or deemed to have been presented under that rule and shall sign 
    the endorsement.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    on scrutiny, the application is found to be in order, it shall be duly 
    registered and given serial number.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the application, on scrutiny, is found to be defective, the same shall be 
    returned to the applicant within fifteen days for rectifying the defects and 
    resubmitting the corrected application within fifteen days from the date of 
    its receipt.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the applicant fails to rectify the defect within the time allowed under 
    sub‑rule (3), the Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the 
    State Government in this regard may, by order and for the reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, decline to register the application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Place of filing application.—The 
    applicant shall file application with the Chief Wild Life Warden or the 
    officer authorized by the State Government in this regard.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Date and place of hearing to be notified.—The 
    Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government in 
    this regard shall notify to the parties the date, place and time of hearing 
    of each application, if required.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Decision on applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government 
    in this regard shall verify the facts mentioned in the application and make 
    such inquiry as may be required.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chief Wild Life Warden shall, as far as possible, decide the application 
    within six months of the date of its presentation and communicate the same 
    to the applicant in writing under his own signature by registered post.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Hearing on application ex parte.—Where 
    on the date fixed for hearing the application, the applicant fails to appear 
    without intimation, the Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by 
    the State Government in this regard may at their discretion adjourn or 
    decide the application ex parte.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Inquiry by the Chief Wild Life Warden or authorised officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Wild Life Warden or the officer authorized by the State Government 
    in this regard shall conduct a detailed inquiry and take all actions as 
    provided in section 41 of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of the report pertaining to sub‑rule (1) of this rule, shall be 
    provided to the applicant.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Certificate of ownership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Wild Life Warden shall provide a certificate of ownership to the 
    applicant whose claim is found valid.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    certificate of ownership shall be provided as per the provisions of section 
    42 of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    certificate of ownership shall contain the facsimile of the identification 
    mark and in case of live animals the identification number of the 
    transponder (microchip) implanted shall be mentioned in the certificate.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Dealing with declared objects.—Any 
    captive animal, animal article, trophy or uncured trophy declared under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 40A and in respect of which certificate of 
    ownership has not been granted or obtained, shall be treated as government 
    property.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Order to be signed and dated.—Every 
    order of the Chief Wild Life Warden shall be in writing and shall be signed 
    and dated by the Chief Wild Life Warden.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Communication of order to parties.—Every 
    order passed on the application shall be communicated to the applicant 
    either in person or by registered post free of cost.  
  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the Declaration of Wild Life 
    Stock Rules, 2003
 



 



 


FORM
 


APPLICATION UNDER SECTION 40A OF WILD 
    LIFE PROTECTION ACT, 1972 FOR  

    CERTIFICATE OF OWNERSHIP
 

 
 


To
 


The Chief Wildlife Warden or the Authorized 
    Officer
 


State or Union Territory of 
    .......................
 


I, 
    ..................,   .......................,   .......................
 


     (Surname)          
    (First Name)         (Middle Name)
 


son/daughter 
    of .......................      .......................  .......................
 


                                   
    (Surname)             (First Name)         (Middle Name)
 


presently residing at House 
    Number....................... Taluk.......................................... 
    District....................... State....................... (PIN 
    Code)......................... and having permanent residence at House No. 
    ........................................... Taluk....................... 
    District....................... State....................... (PIN 
    Code)....................... hereby declare that I am in control, custody or 
    possession of captive animal and/or its offspring bred in captivity/animal 
    article/trophy/uncured trophy/derived from animal (strike out whichever is 
    not applicable) specified in Schedule I or Part II of Schedule II of the 
    Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972 having following description:—
 


             1. Common name of the 
    animal species                  :
 


             2. Zoological name (Mention 
    sub‑species, if any)     :
 


             3. Description of the 
    item                                    :
 


             4. State the condition of 
    the item (provide four color 
 


                   photographs of size 
    8" x 6" covering front, left and 
 


                   right profiles and a 
    full photograph)                 :
 


             5. Number of 
    item                                              :
 


             6. Method of procurement 
    Purchase/gift/inheritance/
 


                   any other mode 
    specify                                 :
 


             7. Date of 
    procurement                                       :
 


             8. Name of 
    person/institution from whom obtained:
 


             9. Address of 
    person/institution referred to in (6) above:
 


           10. Size (in metres/cms)                                             :
 


                   (i) Length :
 


                   (ii) Width  :
 


                   (iii) Height :
 


           11. Weight (in Kgs./gms)                                       :
 


           12. Any specific mark that 
    can help in identification 
 


                   of the 
    item                                                  :
 


           13. Mention the age and sex 
    in case of live animals     :
 


(ii) I hereby declare that the above referred 
    captive animal/item has been kept, stored or maintained at the following 
    address:—
 


                   
    ..........................................................................................................................................
 


                   
    .......................................................................................................................................
 


                   
    ....................................................................................................................................
 


(iii) I hereby declare that the above 
    referred captive animal / item was acquired by me through legal means but no 
    declaration has been made by me under sub‑section (1) or sub‑section (4) of 
    section 40 of the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972.
 


(iv) I further declare that I have read 
    and understood the provisions contained in sections 40A, 42 and 43 of the 
    Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972 and state that the above shall not be 
    transferred to anyone by any mode except by way of inheritance.  
 


(v) I hereby give my consent for fixing 
    an identification mark to each item and transponder in case of captive 
    animal and assure that the mark or transponder will not be erased, altered 
    or damaged and in the event of any damage, alteration or change of the mark, 
    I shall inform the competent authority within twenty-four hours.
 


I do hereby declare that the information 
    given above is true to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 

 
 


Place 
    .......................               
 


Date 
    .......................                
 


Signature of the person making the 
    declaration
 


(Name)
 

 
 




    Acknowledgement Slip
 



 


Receipt of the application filed by Shri/ 
    Smt /....................... presently residing at ....................... 
    ­(Full Address and Telephone Number)....................... in the office of 
    the ....................... is hereby acknowledged.
 



 


Signature
 



    Office Seal
 



 



 



 



 



 




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>