<act><title>

    THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITY RULES, 19951</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the National Legal Services Authority Rules, 1995. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They Shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Gazette of India.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules unless 
    the context otherwise requires, (39 of 1987)—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Legal Services 
    Authorities Act, 1987;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Central Authority” means the National 
    Legal Services Authority constituted under section 3 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “member” means the members of the 
    Central Authority nominated under clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 3 
    of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Member-Secretary” means the 
    Member-Secretary of the Central Authority appointed under sub-section (3) of 
    section 3 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    all other words and expressions used in 
    these rules but not defined shall have the same meaning assigned to them in 
    the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> The 
    number, experience and qualifications of other members of the Central 
    Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Authority shall consist of not more than twelve members.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    following shall be the ex-offico members of the Central Authority, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Secretary in the Department of Legal 
    Affairs, Ministry of Law, Justice and Company Affairs, Government of India 
    or any of his nominee.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Secretary, Department of Expenditure, 
    Ministry of Finance, Government of India or any of his nominee; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    two Chairmen of the State Legal 
    Services Authorities as may be nominated by the Central Government in 
    consultation with the Chief Justice of India:  
 
Provided that 
    the Patron-in-Chief of the Central Authority may nominate, until the 
    constitution of State Authorities under the Act, Chairman of any two of the 
    State Legal Aid and Advice Boards or Committees, by whatever name called, 
    existing prior to such constitution.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Government may nominate, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, 
    other members from amongst those possessing the experience and 
    qualifications prescribed in sub-rule (4) of this rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> a person 
    shall not be qualified for nomination as a member of the Central Authority 
    unless he is—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an eminent person in the field of law; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a person of repute who is specially 
    interested in the implementation of the Legal Services Schemes; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    an eminent social worker who is engaged 
    in the upliftment of the weaker sections of the people including Scheduled 
    Castes, Scheduled Tribes, women, children, rural and urban labour.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Appointment of Member-Secretary.—The 
    Central Government shall in consultation with the Chief Justice of India 
    appoint a person to be the Member-Secretary of the Central Authority, 
    possessing experience and qualifications as prescribed in rule 5.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> The 
    experience and qualifications of the Member-Secretary of the Central 
    Authority and his powers and functions.—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Member-Secretary unless he 
    is—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    an officer of the Indian Legal Service 
    who has held a post not below the rank of Additional Secretary to the 
    Government of India; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    a member of the State Higher Judicial 
    service who has held the post of District Judge at least for three years; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    an officer of other organised Central 
    Services who has held a post of Joint Secretary to the Government of India 
    or equivalent for a minimum period of three years; or  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    an officer of the organised State 
    Services who has held a post equivalent to the Joint Secretary to the 
    Government of India for a minimum period of five years.  
 
Preference will 
    be given to persons possessing administrative, financial and legal aid 
    experience.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Powers 
    and functions of the Member-Secretary.—The 
    powers and functions of the Member-Secretary, inter alia, shall be—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    to work out modalities of the Legal 
    Services Schemes and Programmes approved by the Central Authority and ensure 
    their effective monitoring and implementation throughout the country;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    to exercise the powers in respect of 
    administrative, finance and budget matters as that of the Head of the 
    Department in a Central Government;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    to manage the properties, records and 
    funds of the Central Authority;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    to maintain true and proper accounts of 
    the Central Authority including checking and auditing in respect thereof 
    periodically;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    to prepare Annual Income and 
    Expenditure Accounts and Balance-sheet of the Central Authority;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    to liaise with the Social Action Groups 
    and the State Legal Services Authorities;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    to maintain up-to-date and complete 
    statistical information, including progress made in the implementation of 
    various Legal Services Programmes from time to time;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    to process project proposals for 
    financial assistance and issue Utilisation Certificates thereof;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    to convene meetings/seminars and 
    workshops connected with Legal Services Programmes and preparation of 
    Reports and follow-up action thereon;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    to produce video/documentary films, 
    publicity material, literature and publications to inform general public 
    about the various aspects of the Legal Services Programmes; and  
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    to perform such other functions as may 
    be expedient for efficient functioning of the Central Authority.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> The terms 
    of office and other conditions relating thereto of members and 
    Member-Secretary of the Central Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The members of the Central Authority nominated by the Central Government 
    under sub-rule (3) of rule 3, shall hold office for a term of two years and 
    a retiring member shall be eligible for renomination for not more than one 
    term.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member of 
    the Central Authority nominated by Central Government under sub-rule (3) of 
    rule 3 may be removed by the Central Government if in the opinion of the 
    Central Government, it is not desirable to continue him as a member.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    member nominated under sub-rule (3) of rule 3 ceases to be a member of the 
    Central Authority, for any reason such as registration or death, the vacancy 
    shall be filled up in the same manner as the original nomination and the 
    person so nominated shall continue to be a member for the remaining term of 
    the member in whose place he is nominated.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All members 
    nominated under sub-rule (3) of rule 3 shall be entitled to payment of 
    travelling allowance and daily allowance in respect of journeys performed in 
    connection with the work of the Central Authority and shall be paid by the 
    Central Authority in accordance with the rules as are applicable to Grade 
    "A" officers, as amended from time to time.  
 </section><section>
 <number>5</number> If a 
    nominated member is a government employee, he shall be entitled to only one 
    set of travelling allowance and daily allowance either from his parent 
    department, or, as the case may be, from the Central Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Member-Secretary shall hold office for a term not exceeding five years or 
    till the age of 62 years, whichever is earlier.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In all 
    matters like pay, allowances, benefits and entitlements, the 
    Member-Secretary shall be governed by rules as are applicable to the persons 
    holding equivalent posts in the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If an 
    officer of the State Higher Judicial Service or, as the case may be, of 
    other organised Central/State Services, is appointed as Member-Secretary he 
    shall be governed by the service conditions of his parent cadre, in so far 
    as disciplinary matters are concerned.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    appointment of the Member-Secretary may be on deputation basis.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> The 
    number of officers and other employees of the Central Authority.—The 
    Central Authority shall have such number of officers and other employees for 
    rendering secretarial assistance and for its day-to-day functions as are set 
    out in Schedule to these rules or as may be notified by the Central 
    Government from time to time.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> The 
    conditions of services and the salary and allowances of officers and other 
    employees of the Central Authority under sub-section (6) of section 3.— 
<section><number>1</number> The officers and other employees of the Central Authority 
    shall be entitled to draw pay and allowances in the scale of pay indicated 
    against each post in the Schedule to these rules or at par with the Central 
    Government employees holding equivalent posts.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In all 
    matters like age of retirement pay and allowances benefits and entitlements 
    and disciplinary matters, the officers and other employees of the Central 
    Authority shall be governed by the Central Government as are applicable to 
    persons holding equivalent posts.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the Central Authority shall be entitled to 
    such other facilities and benefits as may be notified by the Central 
    Government from time to time.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> The 
    number, experience and qualifications of members of the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee shall consist of not more than 
    nine members.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    following shall be the ex-officio members of the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Attorney-General of India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Additional Secretary in the Department 
    of Legal Affairs, Ministry of Law, Justice and Company Affairs, Government 
    of India or his nominee;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    Additional Secretary in the 
    Department of Expenditure, Ministry of Finance, Government of India or his 
    nominee; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    Registrar-General of the Supreme Court 
    of India .  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Government may nominate, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, 
    other members from amongst these possessing the qualification and experience 
    prescribed in sub-rule (4) of this rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A person 
    shall not be qualified for nomination as a member unless he is—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an eminent person in the field of law; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a person of repute who is specially 
    interested in the implementation of the Legal Services Schemes;or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    an eminent social worker who is engaged 
    in the upliftment of the weaker sections of the people including Scheduled 
    Castes, Scheduled Tribes, women, children, rural and urban labour.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> The 
    experience and qualifications of Secretary of the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3A.—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Secretary unless he is—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    an officer of the Supreme Court 
    Registry not below the rank of Joint Registrar; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    officers of the rank of Director from 
    the Central Government, possessing a degree of Law.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    The upper limit of annual income of a person entitling him to legal services 
    under clause (h) of section 12, if the case is before the Supreme Court.—Any 
    citizen of India whose annual income from all sources does not exceed 


    1[fifty thousand 
    rupees] shall be entitled to legal services under clause (h) of section 12 
    of the Act.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12A</number> The 
    Central Authority, State Authorities and the District Authorities, shall 
    maintain their accounts and prepare their annual statement of accounts in 
    the forms appended to these rules.]  
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> The 
    experience and qualifications of other persons of the Lok Adalats organised 
    by the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee specified in sub-section (3) 
    of section 19.—A person shall not 
    be qualified to be included in the Lok Adalat unless he is—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a member of the legal profession; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    a person of repute who is specially 
    interested in the implementation of the Legal Services Schemes and 
    Programmes; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    an eminent social worker who is engaged 
    in the upliftment of the weaker sections of the people, including Scheduled 
    Castes, Scheduled Tribes, women, children, rural and urban labour.  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 


FORM 1A
 


Appendix Forming part of Income and 
    Expenditure for the Period/Year ended................
 


Name of Authority/Committee.............
 



    (Amount Rs.)
 
 
 
 


Appendix 12 — Income From Sales/Service
 


1. Income From Sales
 


(a)   Sale of Finished Goods
 


(b)   Sale of Raw Material
 


(c)   Sale of Scraps
 


2. Income From Services
 


(a)   Labour and Processing Charges
 


(b)   Professional/Consultancy Services
 


(c)   Agency Commission and Brokerage
 


(d)   Maintenance Services 
        (Equipment/Property)
 


(e)   Others (Specify)
 Current Year
 Previous 
        Year

 
  
  

 
 
 

                     
        Total  
  
  


 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES 
      AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 

FORM 1B
 

Appendix Forming part of Income and 
      Expenditure for the Period/Year ended................
 

Name of 
      Authority/Committee.............
 

 
 

(Amount 
      Rs.)
 
 
 
 
 

Appendix 13—Grants/Subsidies
 

(Irrevocable Grants and Subsidies 
            Received)
 

          1. 
              Central Government
 

          2. 
              State Government(s)
 

          3. 
              Government Agencies
 

          4. 
              Institutions/Welfare Bodies
 

          5. 
              International Organisations
 

          6. 
              Others (Specify)
 Current 
            Year
 Previous 
            Year
 
  
  
 
 
 

                     
            Total  
  
  
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES 
      AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 

FORM 1C
 

Appendix Forming part of Income and 
      Expenditure for the Period/Year ended................
 

Name of 
      Authority/Committee.............
 

 
 

(Amount 
      Rs.)
 
 
 
 
 

Appendix 14 — 
            Fees/Subscriptions 
 

          1. 
              Entrance Fees
 

          2. 
              Annual Fees/Subscriptions
 

          3. 
              Seminar/Program Fees
 

          4. 
              Consultancy Fees
 

          5. 
              Others (Specify)
 
 

Current Year
 
 

Previous Year
 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 
 

                     
            Total  
 
 

 
 
 

 
 

 
 

Note.—Accounting Policies towards each item are 
      to be disclosed       
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES 
      AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 

FORM 1D
 

Appendix Forming part of Income and 
      Expenditure for the Period/Year ended................
 

Name of 
      Authority/Committee.............
 

(Amount 
      Rs.)
 
 
 
 
 

Appendix 15—Income From 
            Investments

 

(Income on Invest from 
            Earmarked/                    
            
 

Endowment Funds 
            transferred to 
            Funds)            
            
 

          1. 
              Interest
 

               
            (a)   On Government Securities
 

  
                         
            (b)   Other Bonds/Debentures
 

          2. 
              Dividends:
 

   
                        
            (a)   On Shares
 

    
                       
            (b)   On Mutual Fund Securities
 

          3. 
              Rents
 

          4. 
              Others (Specify)
 
 

Investment from earmarked Fund
 
 

Investment-Others
 
 
 

Current Year
 
 

Previous Year
 
 

Current Year
 
 

Previous Year
 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 
 

                                
            Total
 
 
 

      Transferred 
            to Earmarked/Endowment 
Funds
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 


FORM 3
 


Appendix forming part of Accounts  

    for the Period/Year ended.........
 


Name of Authority/Committee................
 


Significant Accounting Policy Certificates
 


1. Accounting Convention
 


The Financial statements are prepared on the 
    basis of historical cost convention unless otherwise stated and on the 
    actual method of accounting.
 


2. Inventory Valuation
 


1.   Stores and Spares (including machinery 
    spares) are valued at cost.
 


2.   Raw materials semi-finished goods and 
    finished goods are valued at lower of cost and net realizable value. The 
    costs are based on weighed average cost. Cost of finished goods and 
    semi-finished goods is determined by considering material, labour and 
    related overhead.
 


3. Investments
 


(1)   Investments classified as “long term 
    investments” are carried at cost. Provision for decline other than 
    temporary, is made in carrying cost of such investments.
 


(2)   Investments classified as “Current” are 
    carried at lower of cost and fair value. Provision for shortfall on the 
    value of such investments is made for each investment considered 
    individually and not on a global basis.
 


(3)   Cost includes acquisition expenses like 
    brokerage, transfer stamps.
 


4. Excise Duty
 


Liability for excise duty in respect of goods 
    produced by the entity, other than for exports, is accounted upon completion 
    of manufacture and provision is made for excisable manufactured goods as at 
    the year-end.
 


5. Fixed Assets
 


(1)   Fixed Assets are stated at cost of 
    acquisition inclusive of inward freight, duties and taxes and incidental and 
    direct expenses related to acquisition in respect of projects involving 
    construction, related pre-operational expenses (including interest on loans 
    for specific project prior to its completion), form part of the value of the 
    assets capitalized.
 


(2)   Fixed Assets received by way of 
    non-monetary grants, (other than towards the Corpus Fund), are capitalized 
    at values stated, by corresponding credit to Capital Reserve.
 


6. Depreciation
 


(1)   Depreciation is provided on 
    straight-line method as per rates specified in the Income-tax Act, 1961, 
    except depreciation on cost adjustments arising on account of conversion of 
    foreign currency liabilities for acquisition of fixed assets, which is 
    amortized over the residual life of the respective assets.
 


(2)   In respect of additions to/deductions 
    from fixed assets during the year, depreciation is considered on pro-rata 
    basis.
 


(3)   Assets costing Rs. 5,000 or less each 
    are fully provided.
 


7. Miscellaneous Expenditure
 


Deferred revenue expenditure is written off 
    over a period of 5 years from the year it is incurred
 


8. Accounting for Sales
 


Sales include excise duty and are net of sales 
    returns, rebate and trade discount.
 


9. Government Grants/Subsidies
 


(1)   Government grants of the nature of 
    contribution towards capital cost of setting up projects are treated as 
    Capital Reserve.
 


(2) Grants in respect of specific fixed assets 
    acquired are shown as a deduction from the cost of the related assets.
 


(3)   Government grants/subsidy are accounted 
    on realization basis.
 


10. Foreign Currency Transactions
 


(1)   Transactions denominated in foreign 
    currency are accounted at the exchange rate prevailing at the date of the 
    transaction.
 


(2)   Current assets, foreign currency loans 
    and current liabilities are converted at the exchange rate prevailing as at 
    the year end and the resultant gain/loss is adjusted to cost of fixed 
    assets, if the foreign currency liability relates to fixed assets, and in 
    other cases in considered to revenue.
 


11. Lease
 


Lease rentals are expensed with reference to 
    lease terms.
 


12. Retirement Benefits
 


(1)   Liability towards gratuity payable on 
    death/retirement of employees is accrued based on actuarial valuation.
 


(2)   Provision for accumulated leave 
    encashment benefit to the employees is accrued and computed on the 
    assumption that employees are entitled to receive the benefit as at each 
    year end.
 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITY RULES, 1995
 

 
 


FORM 4
 


Appendix forming part of Accounts  

    for the Period/Year ended...........
 


Name of Authority/Committee..............
 

 
 


Certificates in respect of Contingent 
    Liabilities and Notes on Accounts (Illustrative)
 


1. Contingent Liabilities
 


(1)   Claims against the Entity no 
    acknowledged as debts – Rs. .....................  

       (Previous Year Rs..............)
 


(2)   In respect of
 


—Bank Guarantees given by/on behalf of the 
    Entity – Rs. ...................... 

   (Previous Year Rs..............)
 


—Letters of Credit opened by Bank on behalf of 
    the Entity Rs. ................... (Previous Year Rs..............)
 


—Bills discounted with banks Rs. 
    .................... (Previous Year Rs.................)
 


(3)   Disputed demands in respect of
 


Income-tax Rs. ................... (Previous 
    year Rs. ....................)
 


Sales-tax Rs. ..................... (Previous 
    year Rs. .......................)
 


Municipal Tax ................. (Previous year 
    Rs. .......................)
 


(4)   In respect of claims from parties for 
    non-execution of orders, but contested by the Entity Rs. .................. 
    (Previous year Rs.....................)
 


2. Capital Commitments
 


Estimated value of contracts remaining to be 
    executed on capital account and not provided for (net of advances) Rs. 
    ................. (Previous Year Rs..............)
 


3. Lease Obligations
 


Future obligations for rentals under finance 
    lease arrangements for plant and machinery amount to Rs. 
    ...............(Previous Year Rs..............)
 


4. Current Assets, Loans and Advances
 


In the opinion of the Management, the current 
    assets, loans and advances have a value on realization in the ordinary 
    course of business, equal at least to the aggregate amount shown in the 
    Balance Sheet.
 


5. Taxation
 


In view of there being no taxable income under 
    Income-tax Act, 1961, no provision for Income tax has been considered 
    necessary.
 


6.  Foreign Currency Transactions
 


(1)   Value of Imports Calculated on C.I.F. 
    Basis
 


—Purchase of finished Goods
 


—Raw Materials &amp; Components (including in 
    transit)
 


—Capital Goods
 


—Stores, Spares and Consumables
 


(2)   Expenditure in foreign currency
 


(a)   Travel
 


(b)   Remittances and Interest payment to 
    Financial Institutions/Banks in Foreign Currency
 


(c)   Other expenditure
 


—Commission on Sales
 


—Legal and Professional Expenses
 


—Miscellaneous Expenses
 


(3)   Earnings:
 


Value of Exports on FOB basis
 


(4)   Remuneration to auditors:
 


       As 
    Auditors
 


              
    —Taxation matters
 


              
    —For Management Services
 


              
    —For certification
 


       Others
 


7.  Corresponding figures for the previous 
    year have been regrouped/rearranged, wherever necessary.
 


8.  Appendix 1 to 23 are annexed to and form 
    an integral part of the Balance Sheet as at ................and the Income 
    and Expenditure Account for the year ended on that date.
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>