<act><tid>1908921</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAY COMPANIES (SUBSTITUTION OF PARTIES IN CIVIL  
  PROCEEDINGS) ACT, <year>1946</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>1946</year>
[ 18th april, <year>1946</year>.]

An Act to provide forr the substitution of the Governor- General in 
Counicil for certain RAilway Companies in certain civil proceedings.

WHEREAS under certain arrangements madeby the Central Government 
with the Bengal- Nagpur Railway Company, Limited, the Bombay, Baroda 
and Central India Railway Company, the Bengal and North Western 
Railway Company, Limited, and the Rohilkhand and Kumaon Railway 
Company, limited, certain rights and liabilitties of the said 
Companies have been assumed by the Central Government;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the substitution of 
the governor- General in Council in the place and stead of the said 
Companies in all pending civil proceedings founded on any right of 
libility so assumed by the Central Government:

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1899362</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Railway Companies 
 (Substitution of Parties in Civil Proceedings) Act, <year>1946</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1989806</tid>
<number>2</number>Interpretation. In this Act," civil proceeding" includes 
and appeal or execution proceeding.


</article>



<article><tid>83267</tid>
<number> 3</number> Substitution of Governor- General in Council in certain civil 
proceedings.
<section><tid>1830101</tid>
<number>1</number>In every civil proceeding pending at the  
commencement of this Act to which the Bengal- Nagpur Railway Company, 
Limited, or the Bombay, Baroda and Central India Railway Company, or 
the Bengal and North Western Railway Company, Limited, or the 
Rohilkhand and Kumaon Railway Company, Limited, is a party, and which 
is founded on any right 5 or liability assumed by the Central 
Government undercertain arrangements made by the Central Government 
with the said Companies, the Governor- General in Council shall, 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary in the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), be deemed to be substituted in the place 
and stead of the Company; and every such proceeding may be continued 
by or against the Governor- General in Concil accordingly, and the 
Company shall be discharged from all liability in connection with the 
proceeding.

</section>

<section><tid>1367580</tid>
<number>2</number>References in sub- section (1) to any Company shall be 
construed as including references to the liquidators of that Company.

</section>

</article>



 </act>