<act><title>


    The Disturbed areas (Special Courts) Act, 1976</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—This 
    Act may be called the Disturbed Areas (Special Courts) Act, 1976.
 <section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different dates 
    may be appointed for different States or for different parts thereof.
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— —In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Code” means the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “disturbed area” means an area declared 
    as a disturbed area under section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   period of disturbance, in relation to a 
    disturbed area, means the period during which it is to be a disturbed area 
    for the purposes of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “scheduled offence” means an offence 
    specified in the Schedule being an offence forming part or arising out of, 
    or connected with, any such disturbance as is referred to in section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “Special Court” means a Special Court 
    constituted under section 4;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   words and expressions used but not 
    defined in this Act, and defined in the Code shall have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in the Code.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Declaration of an area as disturbed area.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a State Government is satisfied that— —(1) 
    Where a State Government is satisfied that—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   there was, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   there is,
 
in any area within a State extensive 
    disturbance of the public peace and tranquillity, by reason of differences 
    or disputes between members of different religious, racial, language or 
    regional groups or castes or communities, it may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, declare such area to be a disturbed area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    notification issued under sub-section (1) in respect of any area shall 
    specify the period during which the area shall, for the purposes of this 
    section, be a disturbed area and where the State Government is satisfied 
    that there was such disturbance of public peace and tranquillity as is 
    referred to in sub-section (1) in that area from any date prior to the issue 
    of such notification, the period specified in the notification may commence 
    from that date:
 
Provided 
    that—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   no period commencing from a date earlier 
    than three months before the date of publication of the notification shall 
    be specified therein; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   so much of the period specified in such 
    notification as is subsequent to the date of publication of the notification 
    shall not, in the first instance, exceed three months but the State 
    Government may amend such notification to extend such period from time to 
    time by any period not exceeding three months at any one time if in the 
    opinion of State Government their continues to be in such disturbance of 
    public peace and tranquillity as is referred to in sub-section (1):
 


    Provided further that where the State Government is satisfied that there is 
    no longer such disturbance of public peace and tranquillity as is referred 
    to in sub-section (1) in such area, it shall amend the notification issued 
    under that sub-section in respect of that area to limit the period specified 
    therein (whether originally or by amendment under the preceding proviso) 
    accordingly.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Constitution of Special Courts.—The 
    State Government may, for the purpose of providing speedy trial of scheduled 
    offences committed in disturbed areas, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, constitute as many Special Courts as may be necessary in or in 
    relation to such disturbed area or areas as may be specified in the 
    notification. —The 
    State Government may, for the purpose of providing speedy trial of scheduled 
    offences committed in disturbed areas, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, constitute as many Special Courts as may be necessary in or in 
    relation to such disturbed area or areas as may be specified in the 
    notification." 
 <section>
<number>2</number> A 
    Special Court shall consist of a single judge who shall be appointed by the 
    High Court upon a request made by the State Government. 

 

    Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section, the word “appoint” shall have the meaning given to it in 
    the Explanation to section 9 of the Code.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as a judge of a Special Court 
    unless—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   he is qualified for appointment as a 
    judge of a High Court, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   he has, for a period of not less than 
    one year, been a Sessions Judge or an Additional Sessions Judge.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (3), a person shall not be 
    eligible for being appointed as, and for being, a Judge of a Special Court 
    in any State after he has attained the age at which Sessions Judges in that 
    State have to retire from service.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Jurisdiction of Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code or any other law, a scheduled 
    offence committed in any disturbed area at any time during the period during 
    which it is a disturbed area shall be tribal, whether during or after such 
    period, only by the Special Court constituted in or in relation to the 
    disturbed area in which the offence has been committed. —(1) 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code or any other law, a scheduled 
    offence committed in any disturbed area at any time during the period during 
    which it is a disturbed area shall be tribal, whether during or after such 
    period, only by the Special Court constituted in or in relation to the 
    disturbed area in which the offence has been committed." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    trying any scheduled offence, a Special Court may also try any offence other 
    than the scheduled offence with which the accused may, under the Code be 
    charged at the same trial if the offence is connected with the scheduled 
    offence.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Procedure and powers of Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every scheduled offence shall be cognizable. —(1) 
    Every scheduled offence shall be cognizable." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    Special Court may take cognizance of any scheduled offence,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   where under the Code such offence is an 
    offence tribal exclusively by a Court of Session, upon its being committed 
    to it under section 209 of the Code as if the Special Court were a Court of 
    Session;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in any other case, upon a police report 
    of the facts together with a certificate from the public prosecutor to the 
    effect that the offence is tribal exclusively by the Special Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a scheduled offence is an offence tribal exclusively by a Court of 
    Session under the Code, a Special Court shall have all the powers of a Court 
    of Session and shall try such offence as if it were a Court of Session, so 
    far as may be in accordance with the procedure prescribed in the Code for 
    trial before a Court of Session.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where a scheduled offence is an offence which is punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term exceeding three years but which, according to the 
    provisions of the Code, is not an offence tribal exclusively by a Court of 
    Session, a Special Court may on taking cognizance of the offence perform the 
    functions of a Magistrate under section 207 of the Code and thereafter try 
    such offence so far as may be in accordance with the procedure prescribed in 
    the Code for trial before a Court of Session as if the Special Court were a 
    Court of Session and the case had been committed to it for trial under the 
    provisions of the Code.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where a scheduled offence is punishable with imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding three years or with fine or with both, a Special Court, may, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) of section 260 or 
    section 262 of the Code, try the offence in a summary way in accordance with 
    the prescribed in the Code and the provisions of sections 263 to 265 of the 
    Code, shall so far as may be, apply to such trial:
 
Provided 
    that when, in the course of summary trial under this sub-section, it appears 
    to the Special Court that the nature of the case is such that it is 
    undesirable to try it summarily, the Special Court shall recall any 
    witnesses who may have been examined and proceed to re-hear the case in the 
    manner provided by the provisions of the Code for the trial of such offence 
    and the said provisions shall apply to and in relation to a Special Court as 
    they apply to and in relation to a Magistrate:
 
Provided 
    further that in the case of any conviction in a summary trial under this 
    section, it shall be lawful for a Special Court to pass a sentence of 
    imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    Special Court may, with a view to obtaining the evidence of any person 
    suspected to have been directly or indirectly concerned in, or privy to, an 
    offence, tender a pardon to such person on condition of his making a full 
    and true disclosure of the whole circumstances within his knowledge relating 
    to the offence and to every other person concerned whether as principal or 
    abettor in the commission thereof and any pardon so tendered shall, for the 
    purposes of section 308 of the Code be deemed to have been tendered under 
    section 307 thereof.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Power to transfer cases to regular courts.—Where 
    after taking cognizance of any offence, a Special Court is of opinion that 
    the offence is not a scheduled offence, it shall, notwithstanding that it 
    has no jurisdiction to try the case, transfer the case for trial to any 
    court have jurisdiction under the Code and the court to which the case is 
    transferred may proceed with the case as in it had taken cognizance of the 
    offence. —Where 
    after taking cognizance of any offence, a Special Court is of opinion that 
    the offence is not a scheduled offence, it shall, notwithstanding that it 
    has no jurisdiction to try the case, transfer the case for trial to any 
    court have jurisdiction under the Code and the court to which the case is 
    transferred may proceed with the case as in it had taken cognizance of the 
    offence." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Appeal and revision.—The 
    High Court may exercise, so far as they may be applicable, all the powers 
    conferred by Chapters XXIX and XXX of the Code on a High Court, as if a 
    Special Court is a Court of Session trying cases within the local limits of 
    the jurisdiction of the High Court. —The 
    High Court may exercise, so far as they may be applicable, all the powers 
    conferred by Chapters XXIX and XXX of the Code on a High Court, as if a 
    Special Court is a Court of Session trying cases within the local limits of 
    the jurisdiction of the High Court." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Overriding effect of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of this Act shall have 
      effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Code or any other law, 
      but save as expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code 
      shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
      Act apply to the proceedings before a Special Court; and for the purposes 
      of the said provisions of the Code, the Special Court shall be deemed to 
      be a Court of Session and the person conducting a prosecution before a 
      Special Court shall be deemed to be a public 
      prosecutor. —(1) 
    The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Code or any other law, but save as expressly provided in 
    this Act, the provisions of the Code shall, in so far as they are not 
    inconsistent with the provisions of this Act apply to the proceedings before 
    a Special Court; and for the purposes of the said provisions of the Code, 
    the Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court of Session and the person 
    conducting a prosecution before a Special Court shall be deemed to be a 
    public prosecutor." 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
      provisions contained in sub-section (1), the provisions of sections 326 
      and 475 of the Code shall, so far as may be, apply to the proceedings 
      before a Special Court, and for this purpose references in those 
      provisions to a Magistrate shall be construed as references to the Special 
      Court.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in this Act shall affect the jurisdiction exercisable by, or the 
    proceeding applicable to, any court or other authority under any law 
    relating to the naval, military or air forces or any other armed forces of 
    the Union. —(1) 
    Nothing in this Act shall affect the jurisdiction exercisable by, or the 
    proceeding applicable to, any court or other authority under any law 
    relating to the naval, military or air forces or any other armed forces of 
    the Union." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that for the purposes of any 
    such law as is referred to in sub-section (1), a Special Court shall be 
    deemed to be a court of ordinary criminal justice.

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Disturbed areas (Special Courts) Act, 1976
 



 



 




    The Schedule
 




    [See section 2(d)]
 




    1. Offences under the following provisions of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860):—
 


Section 120B;
 


Sections 143 to 145, 147, 148, 151 to 155, 
    157, 158 and 160;
 


Sections 182, 183, 186 
    to 190;
 


Sections 193 to 195, 199, 201 to 203, 211 to 
    214, 216, 216A and 225;
 


Sections 295 to 298;
 


Sections 302, 303, 304, 307, 308, 323 to 335, 
    341 to 348, 352 to 358, 363 to 369 and 376;
 


Sections 379, 380, 382, 384 to 387, 392 to 
    399, 402, 411, 412, 426, 427, 431, 435, 436, 440, 447 to 462;
 


Sections 504 to 506 and 509;
 




    2. Offences under the following provisions of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 
    1959):—
 


            Sections 25 to 30.
 




    3. Offences under the following provisions of the Indian Explosives Act, 
    1884 (4 of 1884):—
 


            Sections 6(3) and 
    8(2).
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came 
    into force on 15th August, 1976 vide S.O. 549(E), dated 13-8-1976, 
    published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 
    13-8-1976.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>