<act><title>

The 
    Elephants Preservation Act, 1879</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—It extends to the 
    territories now respectively administered by the State Governments of Uttar 
    Pradesh, the Madhya Pradesh and the Chief Commissioners of Coorg; and the 
    State Governments may extend it to any other local area which immediately 
    before the 1st of November, 1956, was not comprised in a Part B State by 
    notification in the Official Gazette.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Repeal.—[Repealed 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1930 (8 of 1930), section 3 and Schedule 
    II].
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number>
Killing and capture of wild 
    elephant prohibited.—No person 
    shall kill, injure or capture, or attempt to kill, injure or capture, any 
    wild elephant unless—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in defence of himself or some other 
    preson; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    when such elephant is found injuring 
    houses or cultivation, or upon, or in the immediate vicinity of, any main 
    public road or any railway or canal; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    as permitted by a licence under this 
    Act. 
 
State Amendment 
 
Bengal Amendment.—By 
    Bengal Act 5 of 1932, the following new clause was added to section 3:
 
        “(d)  such 
    elephant is proclaimed under section 5-A.”. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> Rights of 
    Government with respect to certain elephants and tusks.—Every 
    wild elephant captured and the tusks of every wild elephant killed, by any 
    person not licenced under this Act, shall be the property of Government.]1[4. 
    Rights of Government with respect to certain elephants and tusks.—Every 
    wild elephant captured and the tusks of every wild elephant killed, by any 
    person not licenced under this Act, shall be the property of Government.]" 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number>
Licence to kill and capture 
    wild elephants.—The Collector or 
    Deputy Commissioner of any district may, subject to such rules as may for 
    the time being be in force under this Act, grant licences to kill, or to 
    capture or to kill and capture wild elephants in such district: 
 
Provided that 
    no such licence shall authorize any person to enter upon any land without 
    the consent of the owner or occupier thereof. 
 
 
State Amendment
 <section>
<number>Assam</number>—In its 
      application to the State of Assam the principal Act has been amended by 
      Assam Act 14 of 1959 (w.e.f. 14-5-1959) as under:—
 <subsection>
          <number>a</number>  In 
      section 5 of the principal Act, between the words “may” and “subject” the 
      words “with the approval of the State Government and” shall be inserted.
 </subsection><subsection>
          <number>b</number>  After 
      section 5 of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, 
      namely:—
 
                    
      “5A. Any person considering himself aggrieved by an order passed under 
      section 5 for granting licence with the approval of the State Government 
      may file an application for review of the order and the approval, to the 
      State Government within a period of 30 days from the date of the order and 
      thereupon the State Government, after giving a hearing to the parties 
      concerned, may—
 <subsubsection>
                 <number>i</number>  
      reject the application, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                <number>ii</number>  
      where it is of opinion that sufficient ground for review has been 
      established, grant the same,
 <subsubsubsection>
                      
      <number>a</number>  by withdrawing its approval issued under section 5 and remand the 
      applications to the Deputy Commissioner concerned for fresh enquiry, or
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
               <number>iii</number>  
      direct the Deputy Commissioner concerned to issue the licence to any of 
      the applicants.”
 
Bengal Amendment.—By 
      Bengal Act 5 of 1932, the following new section was inserted after section 
      5:
 
      "5A. Proclaimed elephants may be killed.—The 
      Collector or Deputy Commissioner of any district, if satisfied that any 
      wild elephant has become dangerous to human life and property, may, 
      subject to such rules as may for the time being be in force under this 
      Act, issue a proclamation giving a description of the elephant and 
      offering the reward fixed by the State Government from time to time for 
      killing of the proclaimed wild elephants to any person who shall kill the 
      elephant described in the proclamation.”
 

</subsubsection></subsection></section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to 
    State Government to declare what are main road and canals, and to make rules 
    as to licences.—The State 
    Government may from time to time declare what shall be deemed to be main 
    public roads and canals within the meaning of this Act, and make rules 
    consistent with this Act for regulating— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the grant and renewal of licences under 
    this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the fees (if any) in money, tusks or 
    captured elephants to be charged on such grant and renewal; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the time during which such licences 
    shall continue in force; and 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    the conditions (if any) on which they 
    shall be granted. 
 
All such 
    declarations and rules shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall 
    thereupon have the force of law. 
 
 
State Amendment 
 
Bengal Amendment.—By 
      Bengal Act 5 of 1932, the following clause was added to section 6:
 
      “(e) the issue of 
      a proclamation under section 5A.”. 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Penalty 
    for contravening section 3.—Whoever, 
    in contravention of section 3, kills, injures or captures, or attempts to 
    kill, injure or capture, any wild elephant, shall be punished with fine 
    which may extend to five hundred rupees for each elephant concerned; 
 
and whoever 
    breaks any condition contained in a licence granted under this Act shall be 
    punished with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 
Any person 
    convicted of a second offence under this section shall be punished with 
    imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both. 
 
When any 
    person holding a licence under this Act is convicted under this section, 
    such licence shall become void and shall be delivered up to the convicting 
    Magistrate. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Licence 
    to be produced and shown on requisition of certain officers.—Any 
    officer of Revenue or Police, or any forest officer, who may find any person 
    killing, injuring or attempting to kill, injure or capture, any wild 
    elephant, except in the cases mentioned in section 3, clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) 
    may require him to produce and show a licence granted to him under this Act. 
 
Any person 
    who, on such request, wilfully refuses or is unable to produce and show such 
    licence as aforesaid, shall, in addition to any other punishment to which he 
    may be liable under this Act, be punished with fine which may extend toone 
    hundred rupees. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Limitation of prosecution.—Every 
    prosecution under this Act shall be commenced within six months from the 
    commission of the offence in respect of which it is instituted. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Recovery of fees.—The amount or 
    value of any fee payable under any licence granted under this Act may be 
    recovered from the licensee as if it was an arrear of land revenue.
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>