<act> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Atomic Energy Act, 1962.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions and 
interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “atomic energy” means energy 
released from atomic nuclei as a result of any process, including the fission 
and fusion processes.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> “fissile material” means uranium 
233, uranium 235, plutonium or any material containing these substances or any 
other material that may be declared as such by notification by the Central 
Government;
 

     1[(bb)  “Government company” 
means a company in which not less than fifty-one per cent. of the paid up share 
capital is held by the Central Government;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “minerals” include all 
substances obtained or obtainable from the soil (including alluvium or rocks) 
by underground or surface working;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “notification” means 
notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  “plant” includes machinery, 
equipment or appliance, whether affixed to land or not;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  “prescribed equipment” means 
any property which the Central Government may, by notification, prescribe, 
being a property which in its opinion is specially designed or adapted or which 
is used or intended to be used for the production or utilisation of any 
prescribed substance, or for the production or utilisation of atomic energy, 
radioactive substances, or radiation, but does not include mining, milling, 
laboratory and other equipment not so specially designed or adapted and not 
incorporated in equipment used or intended to be used for any of the purposes 
aforesaid;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  “prescribed substance” means any 
substance including any mineral which the Central Government may, by 
notification, prescribe, being a substance which in its opinion is or may be 
used for the production or use of atomic energy or research into matters 
connected therewith and includes uranium, plutonium, thorium, beryllium, 
deuterium or any of their respective derivatives or compounds or any other 
materials containing any of the aforesaid substances;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  “radiation” means gamma rays, 
X-rays, and rays consisting of alpha particles, beta particles, neutrons, 
protons and other nuclear and sub-atomic particles; but not sound or radio 
waves, or visible, infrared or ultraviolet light;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  “radioactive substance” or 
“radioactive material” means any substance or material which spontaneously 
emits radiation in excess of the levels prescribed by notification by the 
Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any reference in this 
Act to the working of minerals shall be construed as including a reference to 
the mining, getting, carrying away, transporting, sorting, extracting or 
otherwise treating of minerals.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any reference in this 
Act to the production or use of atomic energy shall be construed as including a 
reference to the carrying out of any process, preparatory or ancillary to such 
production or use.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> General powers of the Central 
Government.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government shall have power—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to produce, develop, use and 
dispose of atomic energy 

1[either by itself or through any 
authority or corporation established by it or a Government company] and carry 
out research into any matters connected therewith;
 

        2[(b)  to manufacture or 
otherwise produce any prescribed or radioactive substance and any articles 
which in its opinion are, or are likely to be, required for, or in connection 
with, the production, development or use of atomic energy or such research as 
aforesaid and to dispose of such prescribed or radioactive substance or any 
articles manufactured or otherwise produced;
 </section><section>
      <number>bb</number> (i)  to buy or otherwise acquire, 
store and transport any prescribed or radioactive substance and any articles 
which in its opinion are, or are likely to be, required for, or in connection 
with, the production, development or use of atomic energy; and
 <subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  to dispose of such 
prescribed or radioactive substance or any articles bought or otherwise 
acquired by it,
 
              either by itself or through 
any authority or corporation established by it, or a Government company;]
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to declare as “restricted 
information” any information not so far published or otherwise made public 
relating to—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  the location, quality and 
quantity of prescribed substances and transactions for their acquisition, 
whether by purchase or otherwise, or disposal, whether by sale or otherwise;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the processing of 
prescribed substances and the extraction or production of fissile materials 
from them;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  the theory, design, 
construction and operation of plants for the treatment and production of any of 
the prescribed substances and for the separation of isotopes;
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>iv</number>  the theory, design, 
construction and operation of nuclear reactors;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>v</number>  research and technological 
work on materials and processes involved in or derived from items (i) to (iv);
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>d</number>  to declare as “prohibited area” 
any area or premises where work including research, design or development is 
carried on in respect of the production, treatment, use, application or 
disposal of atomic energy or of any prescribed substance;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  to provide for control over 
radioactive substances or radiation generating plant in order to—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  prevent radiation hazards;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  secure public safety and 
safety of persons handling radioactive substances or radiation generating 
plant; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  ensure safe disposal of 
radioactive wastes;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>f</number>  to provide for the production 
and supply of electricity from atomic energy and for taking measures conducive 
to such production and supply and for all matters incidental thereto; 

3[either by itself or through any 
authority or corporation established by it or a Government company]; and
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  to do all such things (including 
the erection of buildings and execution of works and the working of minerals) 
as the Central Government considers necessary or expedient for the exercise of 
the foregoing powers.
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Notification of 
discovery of uranium or thorium.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person who, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, has 
discovered or discovers that uranium or thorium occurs at any place in India 
shall, within three months after the date of commencement of this Act or after 
the discovery, whichever is later, report the discovery in writing to the 
Central Government or to any person or authority authorised by the Central 
Government in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person who has 
reason to believe that uranium or thorium occurs at any place in India shall, 
without delay, send intimation of such belief and the reasons therefor to the 
Central Government or to any such person or authority as aforesaid.


</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Control over mining or 
concentration of substances containing uranium.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Central Government is satisfied that any person is mining or is about to 
mine any substance from which, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
uranium can be or may reasonably be expected to be, isolated or extracted, or 
is engaged or is about to be engaged in treating or concentrating by any 
physical, chemical or metallurgical process any substance from which, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, uranium can be or may reasonably be expected 
to be, isolated or extracted, the Central Government may by notice in writing 
given to that person either—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  require him in conducting the 
mining operations or in treating or concentrating the substance aforesaid to 
comply with such terms and conditions and adopt such processes as the Central 
Government may in the notice, or from time to time thereafter, think fit to 
specify, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  totally prohibit him from 
conducting the mining operations or treating or concentrating the substance 
aforesaid.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any terms and 
conditions are imposed on any person conducting any mining operations or 
treating or concentrating any substance under clause (a) of sub-section (1), 
the Central Government may, having regard to the nature of the terms and 
conditions, decide as to whether or not to pay any compensation to that person 
and the decision of the Central Government shall be final:
 
Provided that where the 
Central Government decides not to pay any compensation, it shall record in 
writing a brief statement giving the reasons for such decision.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Central 
Government decides to pay any compensation under sub-section (2), the amount 
thereof shall be determined in accordance with section 21 but in calculating 
the compensation payable, no account shall be taken of the value of any uranium 
contained in the substance referred to in sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where any mining 
operation or any process of treatment or concentration of any substance is 
prohibited under clause (b) of sub-section (1), the Central Government shall 
pay compensation to the person conducting the mining operations or using the 
process of treatment or concentration and the amount of such compensation shall 
be determined in accordance with section 21 but in calculating the compensation 
payable, no account shall be taken of the value of any uranium contained in the 
substance.


</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Disposal of uranium.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No materials, concentrates and other materials which contain uranium in its 
natural state in excess of such proportion as may be prescribed by notification 
by the Central Government shall be disposed of except with the previous 
permission in writing of the Central Government and in accordance with such 
terms and conditions as it may impose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
Government may serve notice on any person who has produced any mineral, 
concentrate or other material referred to in sub-section (1) that the Central 
Government 

1[proposes to 
compulsorily acquire it and upon the service of the notice], the mineral, 
concentrate or other material shall become the property of the Central 
Government and shall be delivered to the Central Government or as it may 
direct:
 

2[***]
 

3[(3) Compensation 
in respect of acquisition under sub-section (2) shall be paid in accordance 
with section 21 and in determining such compensation regard shall be had to the 
cost of production of such mineral, concentrate or other material and such 
other factors as may be relevant, but no account shall be taken of the value of 
uranium in its natural state contained therein.]
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Powers to obtain 
information regarding materials, plant or processes.—The 
Central Government may, by notice in writing served on any person, require him 
to make such periodical and other returns, or statements at such times and 
containing such particulars and accompanied by such plans, drawings and other 
documents as may be specified in the notice relating to—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  any prescribed substance, 
specified in the notice, in his possession or under his control or present in 
or any land or mine owned or occupied by him which in the opinion of the 
Central Government is or can be a source of any of the prescribed substances, 
including returns in respect of any such land or mine;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  any plant in his possession or 
under his control designed for mining or processing of minerals so specified, 
or adapted for the production or use of atomic energy or research into matters 
connected therewith;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  any contract entered into by him 
or any licence granted by or to him relating to prospecting or mining of 
minerals so specified or the production or use of atomic energy or research 
into matters connected therewith;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  any other information in his 
possession relating to any work carried out by him or on his behalf or under 
his directions, in connection with prospecting or mining of materials so 
specified or the production or use of atomic energy or research into matters 
connected therewith.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power of entry and 
inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person authorised by the Central Government may, on producing, if so 
required, a duly authenticated document showing his authority, enter any mine, 
premises or land—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  where he has reason to believe 
that work is being carried out for the purpose of or in connection with 
production and processing of any prescribed substances or substances from which 
a prescribed substance can be obtained or production, development or use of 
atomic energy or research into matters connected therewith, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where any such plant as is 
mentioned in clause (b) of section 7 is situate,
 
and may inspect the mine, premises or land and any articles contained therein.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The person carrying 
out the inspection may make copies of or extracts from any drawing, plan or 
other document found in the mine, premises or land and for the purpose of 
making such copies or extracts, may remove any such drawing, plan or other 
document after giving a duly signed receipt for the same and retain possession 
thereof for a period not exceeding seven days.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to do work for 
discovering.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, subject to the provisions of this section, do on, 
over or below the surface of any land such work as it considers necessary for 
the purpose of discovering whether there is present in or on the land, either 
in a natural state or in a deposit of waste material obtained form any 
underground or surface working, any substance from which in its opinion any of 
the prescribed substances can be obtained, and the extent to which such 
substance is so present.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before any powers are 
exercised under sub-section (1) in relation to any land, the Central Government 
shall serve on every owner, lessee and occupier of the land a notice writing 
specifying the nature of the work proposed to be done and the extent of the 
land affected, and the time, not being less than twenty-eight days, within 
which and the manner in which objections can be made thereto, and no such 
powers shall be exercised otherwise than in pursuance of the notice or before 
the expiration of the time specified therein for making objections.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government may, after giving the person making the objection an opportunity of 
appearing before and being heard by a person appointed by the Central 
Government for the purpose, and after considering any such objection and the 
report of the person so appointed, make such orders as it may deem proper but 
not so as to increase the extent of the land affected.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Compensation shall be 
determined and paid in accordance with section 21 in respect of any diminution 
in the value of any land or property situate thereon resulting from the 
exercise of powers under this section.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Compulsory 
acquisition of right to work minerals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where it appears to the Central Government that any minerals from which in its 
opinion any of the prescribed substances can be obtained are present in or on 
any land, either in a natural state or in a deposit of waste material obtained 
from any underground or surface working, it may by order provide for 
compulsorily vesting in the Central Government the exclusive right, so long as 
the order remains in force to work those minerals and any other minerals which 
it appears to the Central Government to be necessary to work with those 
minerals, and may also provide, by that order or a subsequent order, for 
compulsorily vesting in the Central Government any other ancillary rights which 
appear to the Central Government to be necessary for the purpose of working the 
minerals aforesaid including (without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provisions)—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  rights to withdraw support;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  rights necessary for the purpose 
of access to or conveyance of the minerals aforesaid or the ventilation or 
drainage of the working; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  rights to use and occupy the 
surface of any land for the purpose of erecting any necessary buildings and 
installing any necessary plant in connection with the working of the minerals 
aforesaid;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  rights to use and occupy for the 
purpose of working the minerals aforesaid any land forming part of or used in 
connection with an existing mine or quarry, and to use or acquire any plant 
used in connection with any such mine or quarry; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  rights to obtain a supply of 
water for any of the purposes connected with the working of the minerals 
aforesaid, or to dispose of water or other liquid matter obtained in 
consequence of working such minerals.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notice of any order 
proposed to be made under this section shall be served by the Central 
Government—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  on all persons who, but for the 
order, would be entitled to work the minerals affected; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  on every owner, lessee and 
occupier (except tenants for a month or for less than a month) of any land in 
respect of which rights are proposed to be acquired under the order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Compensation in 
respect of any right acquired under this section shall be paid in accordance 
with section 21, but in calculating the compensation payable, no account shall 
be taken of the value of any minerals present in or on land affected by the 
order, being minerals specified in the order as those from which in the opinion 
of the Central Government uranium or any concentrate or derivative of uranium 
can be obtained.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Compulsory 
acquisition of prescribed substances, minerals and plants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in any other provision of this Act, the Central 
Government may compulsorily acquire in accordance with the provisions of this 
section—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any prescribed substance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  any minerals from which in the 
opinion of the Central Government any of the prescribed substances can be 
obtained;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  any prescribed equipment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  any plant which is designed or 
adapted for the mining or processing of any minerals referred to in clause (b) 
or substances obtained therefrom or for the production or use of any prescribed 
substance or a radioactive substance or for the production, use or disposal of 
such articles as are or are likely to be required for or in connection with the 
production, use or disposal of atomic energy or for research into matters 
connected therewith.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Central 
Government acquires any plant referred to in clause (d) of sub-section (1), it 
shall also have the right to acquire any buildings, railway sidings, tramway 
lines, or aerial ropeways serving such plant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Central 
Government proposes to acquired any property under sub-section (1), it shall 
serve upon the person appearing to be the owner thereof, a notice in writing 
specifying the property to be acquired and requiring that person to make to the 
Central Government within the time specified in the notice a written 
declaration containing such particulars as may be so specified regarding the 
ownership of such property and any agreement or charge by virtue of which any 
other person has an interest in such property.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Upon the service of a 
notice under sub-section (3), no property to which the notice relates shall be 
disposed of without the previous permission in writing of the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If it appears to the 
Central Government in consequence of any written declaration made to it in 
pursuance of sub-section (3) that any person other than the person on whom the 
notice under sub-section (3) was served is the owner of, or has any interest 
in, the property to which the notice relates, the Central Government shall 
serve a copy of the notice on that other person.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A notice served under 
sub-section (3) shall contain a statement to the effect that an objection may 
be made thereto within such time and in such manner as may be specified, and if 
any such objection is duly made and not withdrawn, the Central Government shall 
afford an opportunity to the person making the objection of appearing before 
and being heard by a person appointed by the Central Government for the 
purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> After considering any 
such objection, and the report of the person appointed by it under sub-section 
(6), the Central Government may serve on the persons upon whom the notice under 
sub-section (3) or a copy thereof was served a further notice in writing either 
withdrawing the notice of acquisition or confirming the said notice as respects 
the property to which it relates or such part of the property as may be 
specified.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Any property with 
respect to which a notice of acquisition is served under this section shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if no objection is duly made to 
the notice, vest in the Central Government at the expiration of the time for 
making such objection;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if such an objection is duly 
made and the notice is confirmed as respects the whole or any part of that 
property by a notice served under sub-section (7), vest accordingly in the 
Central Government on the service of the last mentioned notice; 
 
and shall in either case vest free from all encumbrances.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> Compensation in 
respect of acquisition under this section shall be paid in accordance with 
section 21.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>11A</number> Removal of 
doubts.—For 
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the compulsory acquisition of 
any mineral, concentrate or other material under sub-section (2) of section 6, 
or of any substance, minerals, equipment or plant under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 11, shall not be deemed to be a sale for any purpose whatsoever.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Compensation in case 
of compulsory acquisition of a mine.—Where 
the Central Government acquires, in accordance with any law, any mine or part 
of a mine from which in the opinion of the Central Government any of the 
prescribed substances can be obtained, compensation in respect of such 
acquisition shall be paid in accordance with section 21:
 
Provided that in 
determining the amount of such compensation, no account shall be taken of the 
value of uranium which may be obtained from such mine or part of a mine.


</article> 
 The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
  
 <article><number>13</number> Novation of certain 
contracts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may serve on the parties to a contract relating to 
prospecting or mining of any substance from which any of the prescribed 
substances can be obtained or to production or use of atomic energy or to 
research into matters connected therewith, not being a contract for the 
rendering of personal services, a notice in writing stating that on such date as 
may be specified in the notice the rights and liabilities of any of the parties 
to the contract specified in the notice (hereinafter referred to as the 
specified party) will be transferred to the Central Government, and thereupon 
subject to any withdrawal of the notice under the following provisions of this 
section, the contract shall, as regards may rights exercisable, or liabilities 
incurred, on or after the said date, have effect as if the Central Government 
were a party to the contract instead of the specified party and as if for any 
reference in the contract to the specified party there were substituted a 
reference to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A notice served under 
sub-section (1) shall contain a statement to the effect that an objection may be 
made thereto within such time and in such manner as may be specified, and if any 
such objection is duly made and not withdrawn, the Central Government shall 
afford an opportunity to the person making the objection of appearing before and 
being heard by a person appointed by the Central Government for the 
purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number> After considering any such 
objection and the report of the person appointed by it under sub-section (2), 
the Central Government may make such order as it may deem proper.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the rights and 
liabilities of a party to a contract are transferred to the Central Government 
under this section, there shall be paid to that party such compensation in 
respect of any loss suffered by that party as may be agreed between him and the 
Central Government, and in default of such agreement, as may be determined by 
arbitration.</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Control over 
production and use of atomic energy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, subject to such rules as may be made in this 
behalf, by order prohibit except under a licence granted by it—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the working of any mine or 
minerals specified in the order, being a mine or minerals from which in the 
opinion of the Central Government any of the prescribed substances can be 
obtained;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the acquisition, production, 
possession, use, disposal, export or import—
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number>  of any of the prescribed 
substances; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>b</number>  of any minerals or other 
substances specified in the rules, from which in the opinion of the Central 
Government any of the prescribed substances can be obtained; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>c</number>  of any plant designed or 
adopted or manufactured for the production, development and use of atomic 
energy or for research into matters connected therewith; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>d</number>  of any prescribed 
equipment.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in this 
section shall affect the authority of the Central Government to refuse a 
licence for the purpose of this section or to include in a licence such 
conditions as the Central Government thinks fit or to revoke a licence and the 
Central Government may take any action as aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of the foregoing provisions, the rules referred to in this 
section may provide for—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the extent to which information 
in the possession of, or which has been made available to, the person granted a 
licence for purposes of this section, should be regarded as restricted 
information;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the extent to which the area or 
premises under the control of the person to whom a licence has been granted for 
purposes of this section, should be regarded as a prohibited area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the conditions and criteria for 
location of any installation or operation of any plant in respect of which a 
licence has been granted or is intended to be granted for the purposes of this 
section including those necessary for protection against radiation and safe 
disposal of harmful by-products or wastes;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the extent of the licensee’s 
liability in respect of any hurt to any person or any damage to property caused 
by ionising radiations or any radioactive contamination either at the plant 
under licence or in the surrounding area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  provision by licensee either by 
insurance or by such other means as the Central Government may approve, of 
sufficient funds to be available at all times to ensure settlement of any 
claims in connection with the use of the site or the plant under licence which 
have been or may be duly established against the licensee in respect of any 
hurt to any person or any damage to any property caused by ionising radiations 
emitted at the plant under licence or radioactive contamination either at the 
plant under licence or in surrounding areas;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  obligatory qualifications, 
security clearances, hours of employment, minimum leave and periodical medical 
examination of the persons employed and any other requirement or restriction or 
prohibition on the employer, employed persons and other persons; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  such other incidental and 
supplementary provisions including provisions for inspection and also for the 
sealing of premises and seizure, retention and disposal of any article in 
respect of which there are reasonable grounds for suspecting that a 
contravention of the rules has been committed, as the Central Government 
considers necessary.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
Government may also prescribe the fees payable for issue of licences under 
sub-section (1).
 
 
</section></article> 
 The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
  
 <article><number>15</number> Requisitioning of any 
substance for extracting uranium or plutonium.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
shall have the right to require that any substance which, in the opinion of the 
Central Government, contains uranium, plutonium or any of their isotopes, shall 
be delivered to it and the Central Government may extract from that substance 
the uranium, plutonium or any of their isotopes contained therein and return the 
substance to the person concerned on payment of compensation which shall be 
determined in accordance with section 21:
 Provided that such compensation 
shall not, in any case, exceed the cost incurred by the person in the 
production, mining or irradiation of the substance and in determining the same 
no account shall be taken of the value of the uranium, plutonium or any of their 
isotopes extracted from the substance.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in this section 
shall prevent the Central Government from permitting, subject to such conditions 
as it may deem fit to impose, the use of small quantities of natural uranium for 
the purpose of examination, test or analysis.</section></article> 
 The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
  
 <article><number>16</number> Control over radioactive 
substances.—The 
Central Government may prohibit the manufacture, possession, use, transfer by 
sale or otherwise, export and import and in an emergency, transport and 
disposal, of any radioactive substances without its written 
consent.</article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Special provisions as 
to safety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, as regards any class or description of premises or 
places, being premises or places, in which radioactive substances are 
manufactured, produced, mined, treated, stored or used or any radiation 
generating plant, equipment or appliance is used, make such provision by rules 
as appear to the Central Government to be necessary—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to prevent injury being caused 
to the health of persons employed at such premises or places or other persons 
either by radiations, or by the ingestion of any radioactive substance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to secure that any radioactive 
waste products resulting from such manufacture, production, mining, treatment, 
storage, or use as aforesaid are disposed of safely;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  to prescribe qualifications of 
the persons for employment at such premises or places and the regulation of 
their hours of employment, minimum leave and periodical medical examination;
 
and the rules may, in particular and without prejudice to the generality of 
this sub-section, provide for imposing requirements as to the erection or 
structural alterations of buildings or the carrying out of works.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
Government may, as respects the transport of any radioactive substance or any 
prescribed substance specified by an order issued under this Act as being 
dangerous to health, make such rules as appear to be necessary to prevent 
injury being caused by such transport to the health of persons engaged therein 
and other persons.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Rules made under this 
section may provide for imposing requirements, prohibitions and restrictions on 
employers, employed persons and other persons.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person authorised 
by the Central Government under this section, may, on producing, if so 
required, a duly authenticated document showing his authority, enter at all 
reasonable hours any premises, or any vehicle, vessel or aircraft for the 
purpose of ascertaining whether there has been committed, or is being 
committed, in or in connection with the premises, vehicle, vessel or aircraft, 
any contravention of the rules made under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of any 
contravention of the rules made under this section, the Central Government 
shall have the right to take such measures as it may deem necessary to prevent 
further injury to persons or damage to property arising from radiation or 
contamination by radioactive substances including, without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing provisions, and to the right to take further action 
for the enforcement of penalties under section 24, the sealing of premises, 
vehicle, vessel, or aircraft, and the seizure of radioactive substances and 
contaminated equipment.


</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Restriction on 
disclosure of information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may by order restrict the disclosure of information, 
whether contained in a document, drawing, photograph, plan, model, or in any 
other form whatsoever, which relates to, represents or illustrates—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  an existing or proposed plant 
used or proposed to be used for the purpose of producing, developing or using 
atomic energy, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the purpose or method of 
operation of any such existing or proposed plant, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  any process operated or proposed 
to be operated in any such existing or proposed plant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  disclose, or obtain or attempt 
to obtain any information restricted under sub-section (1), or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  disclose, without the authority 
of the Central Government, any information obtained in the discharge of any 
functions under this Act or in the performance of his official duties.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this 
section shall apply—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  to the disclosure of 
information with respect to any plant of a type in use for purposes other than 
the production, development or use of atomic energy, unless the information 
discloses that plant of that type is used or proposed to be used for the 
production, development or use of atomic energy or research into any matters 
connected therewith; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  where any information has been 
made available to the general public otherwise than in contravention of this 
section, to any subsequent disclosure of that information.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Prevention of entry 
into prohibited areas.—The 
Central Government may by order prohibit—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  entry of any person, without 
obtaining permission, into a prohibited area, and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  taking by any person, without 
permission, of any photograph, sketch, pictures, drawing, map or other document 
from a prohibited area and any permission, if given to do these things, may be 
subject to stipulations which the Central Government may consider necessary.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Special provisions as 
to inventions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As from the commencement of this Act, no patents shall be granted for 
inventions which in the opinion of the Central Government are useful for or 
relate to the production, control, use or disposal of atomic energy or the 
prospecting, mining, extraction, production, physical and chemical treatment, 
fabrication, enrichment, canning or use of any prescribed substance or 
radioactive substance or the ensuring of safety in atomic energy operations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prohibition under 
sub-section (1) shall also apply to any invention of the nature specified in 
that sub-section in respect of which an application for the grant of a patent 
has been made to the Controller of Patents and Designs appointed under the 
Indian Patents and Designs Act, 1911 (2 of 1911), before the commencement of 
this Act and is pending with him at such commencement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government shall have the power to inspect at any time any pending patent 
application and specification before its acceptance and if it considers that 
the invention relates to atomic energy, to issue directions to the Controller 
of Patents and Designs to refuse the application on that ground.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person, who has 
made an invention which he has reason to believe relates to atomic energy, 
shall communicate to the Central Government the nature and description of the 
invention.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person desiring 
to apply for a patent abroad for an invention relating to or which he has 
reason to believe relates to atomic energy shall obtain prior permission from 
the Central Government before making the application abroad or communicating 
the invention to any person abroad, unless three months have elapsed since his 
request for permission was made to the Central Government and no reply was 
received by him.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Controller of 
Patents and Designs shall have the power to refer any application to the 
Central Government for direction as to whether the invention is one relating to 
atomic energy and the direction given by the Central Government shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any invention in the 
field of atomic energy conceived whether in establishments controlled by the 
Central Government or under any contract, sub-contract, arrangement or other 
relationship with the Central Government shall be deemed to have been made or 
conceived by the Central Government, irrespective of whether such contract, 
sub-contract, arrangement or other relationship involves financial 
participation of or assistance from the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Indian Patents and Designs Act, 1911 (2 of 1911), the 
decision of the Central Government on points connected with or arising out of 
this section shall be final.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Principles relating 
to payment of compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in this Act, where by reason of exercise of any 
powers under this Act, any compensation is payable, the amount of such 
compensation shall be determined in the manner and in accordance with the 
principles hereinafter set out, that is to say—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  where the amount of compensation 
is fixed by agreement, it shall be paid in accordance with such agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where no such agreement is 
reached, the Central Government shall appoint as arbitrator a person having 
expert knowledge as to the nature of the right affected who shall determine the 
amount of compensation payable.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In making his award, 
the arbitrator appointed under sub-section (1) shall have regard—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in the case of any compensation 
payable under section 9—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  to the nature of the work 
done;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the manner, extent and 
duration of the exercise of any powers under that section;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  the diminution in the 
rent of the land and of the property situated thereon, which might reasonably 
be expected over any period or diminution in the market value of the land and 
property on the date when the exercise of powers comes to an end; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  the provisions of 
sub-section (1) of section 23 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894), in 
so far as such provisions can be made applicable to the exercise of powers 
under section 9; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the case of any compensation 
payable under section 11 or under section 12, to the price which the owner 
might reasonably have been expected to obtain on a sale of the property 
effected by him immediately before the date of the acquisition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An appeal shall lie 
to the High Court against an award of the arbitrator except in cases where the 
amount claimed thereof does not exceed an amount prescribed in this behalf by 
the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
Government may make rules prescribing the procedure to be followed in 
arbitrations under this Act and the principles to be followed in the 
apportionment of the cost of proceedings before the arbitrator and on appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Save as provided in 
this Act, nothing in any law for the time being in force relating to 
arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this Act.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Special provision as 
to electricity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 
1948), the Central Government shall have authority—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to develop a sound and adequate 
national policy in regard to atomic power, to co-ordinate such policy with the 
Central Electricity Authority and the State Electricity Boards constituted 
under sections 3 and 5 respectively of that Act and other similar statutory 
corporations concerned with the control and utilisation of other power 
resources, to implement schemes for the generation of electricity in pursuance 
of such policy and to operate 

1[either by itself or through any 
authority or corporation established by it or a Government company] atomic 
power stations in the manner determined by it in consultation with the Boards 
or Corporations concerned, with whom it shall enter into agreement regarding 
the supply of electricity so produced;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to fix rates for and regulate 
the supply of electricity from atomic power stations 

2[either by itself or through any 
authority or corporation established by it or a Government company in 
consultation with] the Central Electricity Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> to enter into arrangements with 
the Electricity Board of the State in which an atomic power station is situated


3[either by itself or through any 
authority or corporation established by it or a Government company], for the 
transmission of electricity to any other State:
 
Provided that in case 
there is difference of opinion between the Central Government 

3[or such 
authority or corporation or Government company, as the case may be,] and any 
State Electricity Board in regard to the construction of necessary transmission 
lines, the matter shall be referred to the Central Electricity Authority whose 
decision shall be binding on the parties concerned.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No provision of the 
Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (9 of 1910), or any rule made thereunder or of any 
instrument having effect by virtue of such law or rule shall have any effect so 
far as it is inconsistent with any of the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and 
not in derogation of, the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (9 of 1910), and the 
Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948).
 
 






</section></article> 
 The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
  
 <article><number>23</number> Administration of Factories 
Act, 1948.—Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Factories Act, 1948 (65 of 1948), the authority to administer 
the said Act and to do all things for the enforcement of its provisions, 
including the appointment of inspecting staff and the making of rules 
thereunder, shall vest in the Central Government in relation to any factory 
owned by the Central Government 1[or any authority or corporation 
established by it or a Government company] and engaged in carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.
  



</article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Offences and 
penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  contravenes any order made under 
section 14 or any condition subject to which a licence is granted under that 
section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  contravenes any rule made under 
section 17 or any requirement, prohibition or restriction imposed under any 
such rule; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  obstructs any person authorised 
by the Central Government under sub-section (4) of section 17 in the exercise 
of powers under that sub-section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  contravenes sub-section (2) of 
section 18;
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five 
years, or with fine, or with both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> fails to comply with any notice 
served on him under section 5 or with any terms and conditions that may be 
imposed on him under that section; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  fails to comply with any notice 
served on him under section 7 or knowingly makes any untrue statement in any 
return or statement made in pursuance of any such notice; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  obstructs any person or 
authority in the exercise of powers under section 8 or 9; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  contravenes any other provision 
of this Act or any order made thereunder;
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, 
or with fine, or with both.


</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Offences by 
companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge 
or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence under this Act has 
been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been 
committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect 
on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the 
company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “company” means any body 
corporate and includes a firm and other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “director” in relation to a 
firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Cognizance of 
offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All offences under this Act shall be cognizable under the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), but no action shall be taken in respect of any 
person for any offence under this Act expect on the basis of a written 
complaint made—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in respect of contravention of 
sections 8, 14 or 17 or any rule or order made thereunder, by the person 
authorised to exercise powers of entry and inspection;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in respect of any other 
contravention, by a person duly authorised to make such complaints by the 
Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Proceedings in 
respect of contravention of section 18 shall not be instituted except with the 
consent of the Attorney-General of 
India.


</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Delegation of powers.—The 
Central Government may, by order, direct that any power conferred or any duty 
imposed on it by this Act shall, in such circumstances and subject to such 
conditions as may be specified in the direction, be exercised or discharged 
also by—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  such officer or authority 
subordinate to the Central Government, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  such State Government or such 
officer or authority subordinate to a State Government as may be specified in 
the direction.
</section></article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Effect of other Laws.—The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything consistent 
therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or any other 
instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.
</article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Protection of action 
taken in good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government or 
any person or authority in respect of anything done by it or him in good faith 
in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder.
</article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may 
provide for—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  declaring any information not so 
far published or otherwise made public as restricted information and 
prescribing the measures to be taken to guard against unauthorised 
dissemination or use thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  declaring any area or premises 
as prohibited area and prescribing the measures to be taken to provide against 
unauthorised entry into or departure from such prohibited area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  reporting of information 
relating to the discovery of uranium, thorium and other prescribed substances 
and for payment of rewards for such discoveries;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  control over mining or 
concentration of substances containing uranium;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  regulating by licensing and 
encouraging by award of concessions including rewards, floor prices and 
guarantees, mining of and prospecting for other prescribed substances;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  compulsory acquisition of 
prescribed substances, minerals and plants;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  regulating the production, 
import, export, transfer, refining, possession, ownership, sale, use or 
disposal of the prescribed substances and any other articles that in the 
opinion of the Central Government may be used for, or may result as a 
consequence of, the production, use or application of atomic energy;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  regulating the use of prescribed 
equipment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  regulating the manufacture, 
custody, transport, transfer, sale, export, import, use or disposal of any 
radioactive substance;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  regulating the transport of 
such prescribed substances as are declared dangerous to health under 
sub-section (2) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  developing, controlling, 
supervising and licensing the production, application and use of atomic energy;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  fees for issue of licences 
under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the manner of serving notices 
under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  generally promoting co-operation 
among persons, institutions and countries in the production, use, application 
of atomic energy and in research and investigations in that field.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Rules made under this 
Act may provide that a contravention of the rules shall, save as otherwise 
expressly provided in this Act, be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule made under 
this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may 
be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if


1[before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session] or the successive 
sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.
 
 




</section></article> 
 The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
  
 <article><number>31</number> Act binding on 
Government.—The 
provisions of this Act shall be binding on Government.</article> 
 
The Atomic Energy Act, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Repeal of Act 29 of 
1948.—[Repealed 
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1974 (56 of 1974) sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f.
20-12-1974).]
 
 

</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>