<act><tid>381465</tid>
<title>THE STATE BANK OF INDIA (SUBSIDIARY BANKS) ACT, <year>1959</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 10th September, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to provide for the formation of certain Government or 
Government associated banks as subsidiary of the State Bank of India 
and for the constitution, management and control of the subsidiary 
banks so formed, and for matters connected therewith, or incidental 
thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1998479</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the State Bank of India 
 (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>620832</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>80075</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means,--

<subsection><tid>305949</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to an existing bank, the date on 
which the corresponding new bank is constituted under 
section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1138459</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to a new bank, the date on which 
that new bank is constituted under section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1883996</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to the Hyderabad Bank, the date 
on which the amendments to the State Bank of Hyderabad 
Act, <year>1956</year>, (79 of <year>1956</year>.) take effect under Part VII of 
the Third Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>826266</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to the Saurashtra Bank, the date 
on which the amendments to the Saurashtra State Banks 
 (Amalgamation) Ordinance, <year>1950</year>, (10 of <year>1950</year>.) take 
effect under Part V of the Third Schedule;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>259281</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding bank" means,--

<subsection><tid>1714623</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the State Bank of Bikaner, the 
Bank of Bikaner, Limited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>729674</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the State Bank of Indore, the 
Bank of Indore, Limited;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1743202</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to the State Bank of Mysore, the 
Bank of Mysore, Limited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1643950</tid>
<number>v</number>in relation to the State Bank of Patiala, the 
Bank of Patiala;
the Travancore Bank, Limited;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>325683</tid>
<number>vi</number>in relation to the State Bank of Travancore.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1063276</tid>
<number>c</number>" corresponding new bank" means,--

<subsection><tid>884255</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the Bank of Bikaner, Limited, 
the State Bank of Bikaner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>543894</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the Bank of Indore, Limited, 
the State Bank of Indore;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1746374</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to the Bank of Mysore, Limited, 
the State Bank of Mysore;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>612507</tid>
<number>v</number>in relation to the Bank of Patiala, the State 
Bank of Patiala;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>357712</tid>
<number>vi</number>in relation to the Travancore Bank, Limited, 
the State Bank of Travancore;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>101396</tid>
<number>d</number>" existing bank" means any of the following banks, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1189607</tid>
<number>i</number>Bank of Bikaner, Limited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>38727</tid>
<number>ii</number>Bank of Indore, Limited;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1662841</tid>
<number>iv</number>Bank of Mysore, Limited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1647100</tid>
<number>v</number>Bank of Patiala;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>686890</tid>
<number>vi</number>Travancore Bank, Limited;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1307691</tid>
<number>e</number>" Hyderabad Bank" means the Hyderabad State Bank 
constituted under the Hyderabad State Bank Act, 1350F 
 19 of 1350F, and renamed the State Bank of Hyderabad 
under
<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- cl. (iii) omitted by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


sub- section (1) of section 3 of the State Bank of 
Hyderabad Act <year>1956</year> (79 of <year>1956</year>),


</section>

<section><tid>1701327</tid>
<number>f</number>" new bank" means any of the banks constituted under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1442014</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by regulations made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>465454</tid>
<number>h</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> 
 (2 of <year>1904</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1907684</tid>
<number>i</number>" Saurashtra Bank" means the State Bank of Saurashtra 
constituted under the Saurashtra State Banks 
 (Amalgamation) Ordinance, <year>1950</year> (10 of <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>679518</tid>
<number>j</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted 
under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>53896</tid>
<number>k</number>" subsidiary bank" means any new bank and includes the 
Hyderabad Bank and the Saurashtra Bank;

</section>

<section><tid>797826</tid>
<number>l</number>" Tribunal" means the Tribunal constituted under section 
15;

</section>

<section><tid>161202</tid>
<number>m</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" workman" has the meaning assigned to it in the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>).]
CHAP

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> CONSTITUTION OF NEW BANKS AND CHANGE OF NAME OF ANY SUBSIDIARYBANK]

CHAPTER II

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> CONSTITUTION OF NEW BANKS AND CHANGE OF NAME OF ANY 
SUBSIDIARY BANK]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1715452</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of new banks.- With effect from such date as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf, there shall be constituted the following new 
banks, namely:--
<section><tid>1113640</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Bank of Bikaner;

</section>

<section><tid>871339</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Bank of Indore;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1765015</tid>
<number>d</number>the State Bank of Mysore;

</section>

<section><tid>714419</tid>
<number>e</number>the State Bank of Patiala;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>174</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3. for the former heading. 
3. Cl. (c) omitted by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1095432</tid>
<number>f</number>the State Bank of Travancore;
and different dates may be specified for different new banks.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1772720</tid>
<number> 3A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Change of name of a subsidiary bank.-
<section><tid>1699520</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government after consulting the State Bank and the Reserve Bank may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the name of any 
subsidiary bank shall, with effect from such date as may be specified 
in this behalf, be changed to any other name and thereupon any 
reference to that subsidiary bank in this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force or in any contract, instrument or document shall 
be construed as a reference to that bank by its new name.

</section>

<section><tid>475412</tid>
<number>2</number>The change in the name of a subsidiary bank under sub- section 
 (1) shall not affect any rights or obligations of that bank or render 
defective any legal proceedings by or against it, and any legal 
proceedings which might have been continued or commenced by or against 
that bank by its former name may be continued by or against it by its 
new name.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1079110</tid>
<number> 4</number> New banks to be bodies corporate.-
<section><tid>1433535</tid>
<number>1</number>Every new bank shall be  
a body corporate with perpetual succession and a common seal and shall 
sue and be sued in its name.

</section>

<section><tid>515819</tid>
<number>2</number>The body corporate constituting each of the new banks shall 
consist of the State Bank and other shareholders, if any, for the time 
being of the new bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1225490</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new bank shall carry on the business of banking and 
other business in accordance with the provisions of this Act, and 
shall have power to acquire and hold property, whether movable or 
immovable, for the purposes of its business and to dispose of the 
same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>658524</tid>
<number> 5</number> Head office and branches of new banks.-
<section><tid>1640911</tid>
<number>1</number>The head office of  
each of the new banks shall be at such place as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, from time to time, 
specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1031190</tid>
<number>2</number>Every new bank shall maintain as its branches all branches of 
the corresponding bank in existence immediately before the appointed 
day, and shall not establish any new branch or discontinue any branch 
except in consultation with the State Bank and with the approval of 
the Reserve Bank.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>175</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1882085</tid>
<number> 6</number> Authorised capital of new banks.-
<section><tid>574159</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions  
of this Act, the authorised capital of the State Bank of Mysore and 
the State Bank of Travancore shall be rupees two crores each, and the 
authorised capital of every other new bank shall be rupees one crore.

</section>

<section><tid>885386</tid>
<number>2</number>The authorised capital of every new bank shall be divided 
into shares of one hundred rupees each.

</section>

<section><tid>591596</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the State 
Bank may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, authorise a new bank 
to increase or reduce its authorised capital:
Provided that where the authorised capital is so increased, the 
shares issued shall be of the denomination specified in sub- section 
 (2).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>498979</tid>
<number> 7</number> Issued Capital of new Banks.-
<section><tid>1728851</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the  
issued capital of a new bank shall consist of such amount, divided 
into fully paid- up shares of hundred rupees each, as the State Bank 
may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, fix.

</section>

<section><tid>561256</tid>
<number>2</number>All shares in the issued capital of a new bank shall, on the 
appointed day, stand allotted to the State Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1440103</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be, after the 
determination, if any, by the Tribunal, of the amount of compensation 
payable in respect of an existing bank, consider whether any increase 
in, or reduction of, the issued capital of the corresponding new bank 
as fixed under sub- section (1), by way of adjustment, or transfer 
from, or to, the reserves of such bank, or in any other manner, is 
necessary or expedient and may, thereafter with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank, direct that bank to increase or reduce its issued 
capital.

</section>

<section><tid>550912</tid>
<number>4</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (3), a new bank may, with the approval of the State Bank and the 
Reserve Bank, increase from time to time, its issued capital and the 
capital so increased shall consist of fully paid- up shares to be 
issued in such manner as the State Bank may, with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank, direct.

</section>

<section><tid>199303</tid>
<number>5</number>No increase or reduction in the issued capital of a new bank 
shall be made in such a manner that the State Bank holds at any time 
less than fifty- five per cent. of the issued capital of that bank.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>176</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1719340</tid>
<number> 8</number> Reserve fund of the new banks.-
<section><tid>1279289</tid>
<number>1</number>Every new bank shall  
establish a reserve fund which, subject to the provisions of sub- 
section (3) of section 7 and of sub- section (2) of this section, 
shall--

<subsection><tid>1835186</tid>
<number>a</number>on the appointed day, consist of such sum as the State 
Bank, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, may 
determine; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1072069</tid>
<number>b</number>after the appointed day, consist of the sum aforesaid 
together with such further sums as may be transferred 
to the reserve fund by the new bank out of its annual 
net profits before declaring a dividend.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1140028</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be after the 
determination, if any, of the amount of compensation by the Tribunal, 
in respect of an existing bank, consider whether any increase in, or 
reduction of, the reserve fund of the corresponding new bank, by way 
of adjustment, by transfer from, or to, any account, or towards 
provision for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation of any assets or 
contingencies, or for any other purpose, is necessary, and may, 
thereafter, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, direct that bank to 
so increase or reduce its reserve fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>224457</tid>
<number>9</number>Transfer of shares of existing banks to State Bank.- On the 
constitution of a new bank, all shares in the capital of the 
corresponding bank, where such corresponding bank has a share capital, 
shall stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the State Bank, free of 
all trusts, liabilities and encumbrances.


</article>



<article><tid>1855352</tid>
<number> 10</number> Transfer of undertaking of existing banks to new banks.-
<section><tid>1776714</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, when a new bank 
is constituted, the undertaking of the corresponding bank shall stand 
transferred to, and vest in, the new bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1090121</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the corresponding bank referred to in sub- 
section (1) shall be deemed to include all rights, powers, authorities 
and privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including cash 
balances, reserve funds, investments and all other interests and 
rights in, or arising out of, such property and all books, accounts 
and documents relating thereto as may be in the possession of that 
bank immediately before the appointed day, and shall also be deemed to 
include all debts, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind, then 
existing of that bank.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>177</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1914316</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in this 
Act, all contracts, deeds, bonds, agreements, powers of attorney, 
grants of legal representation and other instruments of whatever 
nature, subsisting or having effect immediately before the appointed 
day and to which any existing banks is a party, or which are in favour 
of that bank, shall be of full force and effect against or in favour 
of the corresponding new bank, as the case may be, and may be enforced 
or acted upon as fully and effectually as if instead of the existing 
bank the corresponding new bank had been a party thereto or as if they 
had been issued in favour of the corresponding new bank.

</section>

<section><tid>991553</tid>
<number>4</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other legal 
proceeding of whatever nature by or against an existing bank is 
pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way 
prejudicially affected by reason of transfer to the corresponding new 
bank of the undertaking of the existing bank, or of anything contained 
in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the corresponding new 
bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>621941</tid>
<number> 11</number> Transfer of services of employees of existing banks.-
<section><tid>660851</tid>
<number>1</number>Save  
as otherwise provided in this Act, every employee of an existing bank 
in the employment of that bank immediately before the appointed day, 
shall, on and from that day, become an employee of the corresponding 
new bank and shall hold his office or service therein by the same 
tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and 
conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to pension, 
gratuity and other matters as he would have held the same on the 
appointed day, if the undertaking of the existing bank had not been 
transferred to and vested in the corresponding new bank, and shall 
continue to do so unless and until his employment in that bank is 
terminated or until his remuneration or other terms and conditions of 
service are revised or altered by the corresponding new bank under, or 
in pursuance of, any law, or in accordance with any provision which, 
for the time being, governs his service:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to an employee of the Bank of Patiala who holds a civil post under the 
State of Punjab unless, prior to the appointed day, he has intimated 
his consent to become an employee of the State Bank of Patiala


<pagefootnote><pagenum>178</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by notice in writing, given to the Government of that State through 
the Bank of Patiala.


</section>

<section><tid>1148324</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who, on the appointed day, is entitled to, or is 
in receipt of, a pension or other superannuation or compassionate 
allowance or other benefit from an existing bank or from any 
provident, pension or other fund or from any authority administering 
such fund, shall be entitled to be paid by, and to receive from, the 
corresponding new bank or any provident, pension or other fund or from 
any authority administering such fund, the same pension, allowance or 
benefit, so long as he observes the conditions on which the pension, 
allowance or benefit was granted, and if any question arises whether 
he has so observed such conditions, the question shall be determined 
by the State Bank and its decision thereon shall be final

</section>

<section><tid>1646997</tid>
<number>3</number>For the persons who immediately before the appointed day are 
the trustees of, or the members of any authority administering, any 
fund constituted for the benefit of the employees of an existing bank, 
there shall be substituted as trustees or members such persons as the 
State Bank may, by general or special order, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1658570</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or any other law or in any agreement for the 
time being in force, the transfer from an existing bank of the 
services of any officer or employee of that bank to the corresponding 
new bank in terms of this section shall not entitle any such officer 
or employee, to any compensation to which he would, but for this 
provision, have been entitled under any such law or agreement, and no 
claim in respect of such compensation shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>461548</tid>
<number> 12</number> Special provision for transfer of foreign assets.-
<section><tid>1828271</tid>
<number>1</number>If,  
according to the laws of any country outside India, the provisions of 
this Act by themselves are not effective to transfer or vest any asset 
or liability situated in that country which forms part of the 
undertaking of an existing bank to, or in, the corresponding new bank, 
the affairs of the existing bank in relation to such asset or 
liability shall, on and from the appointed day, stand entrusted to the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] for the time being of the corresponding new 
bank, and the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] may exercise all powers and do all 
such acts and things as are exercised or done by the existing bank for 
the purpose of effectively winding up the affairs of that bank.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>179</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21, for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1-  
  7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1022962</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] of the corresponding new bank 
shall, in exercise of the powers conferred on him by sub- section (1), 
take all such steps as may be required by the laws of any such country 
outside India for the purpose of effecting such transfer or vesting, 
and in connection therewith the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] may either 
himself or through any person authorised by him in this behalf, 
realise any asset and discharge any liability of the existing bank and 
transfer the net proceeds thereof to the corresponding new bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1881725</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), on and from the appointed day, no person shall make any 
claim or demand or take any proceeding in India against any existing 
bank or any person acting in its name or on its behalf except in so 
far as may be necessary for enforcing the provisions of this section 
or except in so far as it relates to any offence committed by such 
person.

</section>

<section><tid>1501110</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>279973</tid>
<number>a</number>" corresponding new bank" means in relation to the 
Bank of Jaipur Limited, the institution 
constituted under section 3 as the State Bank of 
Bikaner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>496895</tid>
<number>b</number>" existing bank" includes the Bank of Jaipur 
Limited.]
CHAP

COMPENSATION

CHAPTER III

COMPENSATION




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>753945</tid>
<number> 13</number> Compensation to share holders of existing banks other than 
the Bank of Patiala.-
<section><tid>621527</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who and any State Government  
which immediately before the appointed day is registered as a holder 
of shares in the books of an existing bank shall be given by the State 
Bank such compensation in respect of the transfer to the State Bank of 
the shares in the capital of that bank as is determined in accordance 
with the principles contained in the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>608879</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount of compensation to be given in accordance with the 
principles contained in the First Schedule shall be determined in the 
first instance by the State Bank, in consultation with the Reserve 
Bank, and shall be offered by it to all those to whom compensation is 
payable under sub- section (1) in full satisfaction thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1914373</tid>
<number>3</number>If the amount of compensation offered by the State Bank in 
terms of sub- section (2) is not acceptable to any shareholder of an 
existing bank, such shareholder may, before such date as may be 
notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette, request
<pagefootnote><pagenum>180</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21, for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1-  
  7- <year>1974</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the Central Government, in writing, to have the matter referred to the 
Tribunal.


</section>

<section><tid>1237107</tid>
<number>4</number>If, before the date notified under sub- section (3), the 
Central Government receives requests, in terms of that sub- section, 
from not less than one- fourth in number of the shareholders, holding 
not less than one- fourth in value of the paid- up share capital of the 
existing bank, the Central Government shall have the matter referred 
to the Tribunal for decision.

</section>

<section><tid>707560</tid>
<number>5</number>If, before the date notified under sub- section (3), the 
Central Government does not receive requests as provided in that sub- 
section the amount of compensation offered by the State Bank, and 
where a reference has been made to the Tribunal, the amount determined 
by it, shall be the compensation payable under sub- section (1) and 
shall be final and binding on all parties concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1383090</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to the provisions of the succeeding sub- sections, the 
amount of compensation shall be paid,--

<subsection><tid>74879</tid>
<number>a</number>if the shareholder has not applied for shares of the 
corresponding new bank in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section (7), by a cheque drawn on the 
State Bank; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1889538</tid>
<number>b</number>if he has applied for shares of the corresponding new 
bank in accordance with the provisions of that sub- 
section, in shares of the corresponding new bank to the 
extent of the value of such shares allotted to him and 
the balance by a cheque drawn on the State Bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>138765</tid>
<number>7</number>Any shareholder of an existing bank to whom compensation is 
payable under this section may, before the expiry of three months from 
the date of the final determination of the amount of such compensation 
under sub- section (5), or such extended period as the State Bank may 
think fit in any particular case to allow, apply to the State Bank for 
the transfer to him of shares in the capital of the corresponding new 
bank in lieu of such compensation or part thereof; and for the 
purposes of such transfer, the value of each share of the 
corresponding new bank shall be such as may be determined in this 
behalf by the State Bank with the approval of the Reserve Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1132666</tid>
<number>8</number>On receipt of an application under sub- section (7), the State 
Bank shall issue to the corresponding new bank a warrant, in the form 
specified in the rules made under this Act, directing it to transfer 
in favour of the person specified in the warrant such number of shares 
as may be allotted to the applicant in accordance with sub-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>181</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sections (9) and (10), out of the shares in the capital of that bank 
standing allotted to the State Bank under the provisions of this Act, 
and the corresponding new bank shall be bound to comply with such 
warrant.


</section>

<section><tid>1909207</tid>
<number>9</number>A shareholder of an existing bank who has applied for shares 
in the capital of the corresponding new bank shall be allotted--

<subsection><tid>1048906</tid>
<number>a</number>such number of shares, having such total face value as 
would bear to forty- five per cent. of the issued 
capital of the corresponding new bank the same 
proportion as the paid- up value of his shares in the 
capital of the existing bank in respect of which he is 
paid compensation bears to the total paid- up capital of 
that bank; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>875673</tid>
<number>b</number>if the total number of shares allotted under clause (a) 
to all applicants is less than forty- five per cent. of 
the issued capital of the corresponding new bank, such 
number of additional shares as the State Bank may deem 
fit having regard to the provisions of this Act, the 
circumstances of the case and the desirability of 
securing as wide a distribution of shares among as 
large a number of shareholders as possible.
Explanation.-- For the purpose of determining the number of shares 
under this sub- section fractions of a share shall be disregarded.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1667914</tid>
<number>10</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (9), an 
allotment of shares under that sub- section shall not be made in such a 
manner that the State Bank holds at any time less than fifty- five per 
cent. of the issue capital of the corresponding new bank.

</section>

<section><tid>355584</tid>
<number>11</number>A warrant issued by the State Bank under sub- section (8) 
shall not be liable to duty under the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year> (2 of  
  <year>1899</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1953091</tid>
<number>12</number>Nothing contained in this section shall affect the rights 
inter se between the holder of any share in an existing bank, and any 
other person who may have an interest in such share and such other 
person shall be entitled to enforce his interest against the 
compensation awarded to the holder of such share, but not against the 
State Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1213948</tid>
<number>13</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>1185946</tid>
<number>a</number>" corresponding new bank" does not include the State 
Bank of Patiala and means in relation to the Bank 
of Jaipur
<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3, for sub- section (13)  (w. e. f. 1- 1-  
  <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Limited the institution constituted under section 
 3 as the State Bank of Bikaner;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>86468</tid>
<number>b</number>" existing bank" includes the Bank of Jaipur 
Limited, but does not include the Bank of 
Patiala.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>681797</tid>
<number> 14</number> Compensation payable by the State Bank in respect of the Bank 
of patiala, the Saurashtra Bank and the Hyderabad Bank.-
<section><tid>702973</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government of Punjab in respect of the Bank of Patiala, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State 
Government of Gujarat] in respect of the Saurashtra Bank and the 
Reserve Bank in respect of the Hyderabad Bank, shall be given, by 
reason of the provisions of this Act or of the amendments contained in 
Part V or Part VII of the Third Schedule, such compensation by the 
State Bank as is determined in accordance with the principles 
contained in the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1268262</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount of compensation to be given in accordance with the 
principles contained in the First Schedule shall be determined in the 
first instance by the State Bank, and shall be offered by it to the 
State Government of Punjab, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government of Gujarat], or 
the Reserve Bank, as the case may be, in full satisfaction of the 
compensation payable under sub- section (1):
Provided that in determining the amount of compensation to be 
offered to the State Government of Punjab or the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government 
of Gujarat], the State Bank shall consult the Reserve Bank.


</section>

<section><tid>1611328</tid>
<number>3</number>If the amount of compensation offered by the State Bank in 
terms of sub- section (2) is not acceptable to the State Government of 
Punjab, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government of Gujarat] or the Reserve Bank as the 
case may be, the State Government concerned or the Reserve Bank, may 
before such date as may be notified by the Central Government in the 
Official Gazette, request the Central Government to have the matter 
referred to the Tribunal for decision, and where any such request is 
received, the Central Government shall refer the matter accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>654911</tid>
<number>4</number>If, before the date notified under sub- section (3), the State 
Government of Punjab, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government of Gujarat] or the 
Reserve Bank, as the case may be, has not made any such request, the 
amount of compensation offered by the State Bank, and where a 
reference has been made to the Tribunal, the amount determined by it, 
shall be the compensation payable under sub- section (1) and shall be 
final and binding on all parties concerned.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Bombay Reorganisation (Adaptation of Laws on Union  
  Subjects) Order, <year>1961</year>, for" State Government of Bombay" (w. e. f.  
  1- 5- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>734708</tid>
<number>5</number>The amount of compensation shall be paid by a cheque drawn on 
the Reser ve Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>782255</tid>
<number> 15</number> Constitution of the Tribunal.-
<section><tid>588503</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
for the purposes of this Act constitute a Tribunal which shall consist 
of a Chairman and two other members.

</section>

<section><tid>702167</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman shall be a person who is, or has been, a Judge 
of a High Court or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court and of the 
two other members, one shall be a person, who, in the opinion, of the 
Central Government, has had experience of commercial banking and the 
other shall be a person who is a chartered accountant within the 
meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>654546</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for any reason, a vacancy occurs in the office of the 
Chairman or any other member of the Tribunal, the Central Government 
shall fill the vacancy by appointing another person thereto in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (2), and any proceeding 
may be continued before the Tribunal so re- constituted from the stage 
at which the vacancy occurred.

</section>

<section><tid>77214</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal may, for the purpose of determining any 
compensation payable under this Act, choose one or more persons having 
special knowledge or experience of any relevant matter to assist it in 
the determination of such compensation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>53144</tid>
<number> 16</number> Tribunal to have powers of a civil court.-
<section><tid>1096661</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal  
shall have the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), in respect of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1574339</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>770996</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>838117</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1486200</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>529065</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or in 
any other law for the time being in force, the Tribunal shall not 
compel the Reserve Bank, the State Bank or any subsidiary bank--

<subsection><tid>1962037</tid>
<number>a</number>to produce any books of account or other documents which 
the Reserve Bank, the State Bank or the subsidiary bank 
claims to be of a confidential nature;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>212079</tid>
<number>b</number>to make any such books or documents part of the record 
of the proceedings before the Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1993074</tid>
<number>c</number>to give inspection of any such books or documents to any 
party before it or to any other person.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1910203</tid>
<number> 17</number> Procedure of the Tribunal.-
<section><tid>266853</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal shall have power  
to regulate its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>494719</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may hold the whole or any part of its enquiry in 
camera.

</section>

<section><tid>1369785</tid>
<number>3</number>Any clerical or arithmetical mistake in any order of the 
Tribunal or any error arising therein from any accidental slip or 
omission may at any time be corrected by the Tribunal either of its 
own motion or on the application of any of the parties.
CHAP

SHARES OF THE SUBSIDIARY BANKS

CHAPTER IV

SHARES OF THE SUBSIDIARY BANKS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1023670</tid>
<number> 18</number> Transferability of shares.-
<section><tid>594274</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in  
sub- section (2), the shares of a subsidiary bank shall be freely 
transferable.

</section>

<section><tid>1403108</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall entitle the State 
Bank to transfer any shares held by it in any subsidiary bank such 
transfer will result in reducing the shares held by it to less than 
fifty- five per cent of the issued capital of that subsidiary bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>783009</tid>
<number> 19</number> Restriction on individual holdings.-
<section><tid>1377324</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be  
registered as a shareholder in respect of any shares in a subsidiary 
bank held by him, whether in his own name or jointly with any other 
person, in excess of two hundred shares, or be entitled to payment of 
any dividend on the excess shares held by him, or to exercise any of 
the rights of a shareholder in respect of such excess shares otherwise 
than for the purpose of selling them:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to--


<subsection><tid>682914</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136988</tid>
<number>b</number>a State Government;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507085</tid>
<number>c</number>a Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>845110</tid>
<number>d</number>an insurer as defined in the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>898879</tid>
<number>e</number>a local authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1765038</tid>
<number>f</number>a co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681758</tid>
<number>g</number>a trustee of a public or private religious or charitable 
trust;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1022521</tid>
<number>h</number>a shareholder of an existing bank who is allotted any 
shares under sub- section (9) of section 13.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>107286</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), no 
person referred to in the proviso to that sub- section, other than the 
State Bank, shall be entitled to exercise voting rights in respect of 
any shares held by such person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in excess of one per cent.] of the 
issued capital of the subsidiary bank concerned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>692624</tid>
<number>20</number>Shares to be approved securities.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Acts hereinafter mentioned in this section, the 
shares of a subsidiary bank shall be deemed to be included among the 
securities enumerated in section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2  
  of <year>1882</year>), and also to be approved securities for the purposes of the 
Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of <year>1938</year>), and the Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year> 
 (10 of <year>1949</year>),


</article>



<article><tid>767488</tid>
<number> 21</number> Register of shareholders.- Every subsidiary bank shall keep at 
its head office a register, in one or more books, of the shareholders 
and shall enter therein the following particulars so far as they may 
be available:--
<section><tid>770275</tid>
<number>i</number>the names, addresses and occupation, if any, of the 
shareholder, distinguish each share by its denoting 
number; holder, distinguishing each share by its 
denoting number;

</section>

<section><tid>1084689</tid>
<number>ii</number>the date on which each person is so entered as a 
shareholder;

</section>

<section><tid>457464</tid>
<number>iii</number>the date on which any person ceases to be a 
shareholder; and

</section>

<section><tid>1917029</tid>
<number>iv</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248670</tid>
<number>22</number>Trusts not to be entered on the register.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 19, no notice of any trust, express, 
implied or constructive, shall be entered on the register of 
shareholders of a subsidiary bank or be receivable by it in respect of 
its shares.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1963</year>, s. 30, for" in excess of five per cent." 
 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF SUBSIDIARY BANKS

CHAPTER V

MANAGEMENT OF SUBSIDIARY BANKS



</article>



<article><tid>1133949</tid>
<number>23</number>Certain officers to vacate office.- Every person holding 
office as chairman, director, member of the Board of Management 
 (including a member of a local or advisory committee), managing 
director, general manager, manager (other than manager of a branch), 
deputy managing director, deputy general manager, assistant general 
manager or adviser, as the case may be in an existing bank (other than  
  the Bank of Patiala), the Hyderabad Bank and the Saurashtra Bank 
immediately before the appointed day, shall be deemed to have vacated 
that office on the appointed day, and notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or in any other law for the time being in force 
or in any agreement or contract, such person shall not be entitled to 
any compensation for the loss of office or for the premature 
termination of any agreement or contract, relating to his employment, 
except such pension, compensation or other benefit as the 
corresponding new bank, the Hyderabad Bank or the Saurashtra Bank, as 
the case may be, may with the approval of the State Bank, grant to 
him, having regard to what he would have received if this Act had not 
been passed and if his employment had ceased on the appointed day in 
the ordinary course:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
any person who has so vacated his office in any of the said banks from 
being re- nominated or re- appointed to any office in a subsidiary bank 
in accordance with the provisions of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>280305</tid>
<number> 24</number> Management.-
<section><tid>506491</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Bank may, from time to time, give  
directions and instructions to a subsidiary bank in regard to any of 
its affairs and business, and that bank shall be bound to comply with 
the directions and instructions so given.

</section>

<section><tid>1427530</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any such directions and instructions, the general 
superintendence and conduct of the affairs and business of a 
subsidiary bank shall, as from the appointed day, vest in a Board of 
Directors who may, with the assistance of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director], 
exercise all powers and do all such acts and things as may be 
exercised or done by that bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1519048</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board of Directors of a subsidiary bank shall, in 
discharging its functions under this Act, act on business principles, 
regard being had to public interest.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21. for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1-  
  7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>856155</tid>
<number> 25</number> Composition of the Board of Directors.-
<section><tid>621454</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), the Board of Directors of a subsidiary 
bank shall consist of the following:--

<subsection><tid>1048837</tid>
<number>a</number>the chairman for the time being of the State Bank, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1239636</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the managing director appointed under sub- section 
 (1) of section 29, or under section 32;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>253394</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer of the Reserve Bank, to be nominated by that 
bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>107251</tid>
<number>c</number>not more than five directors to be nominated by the 
State Bank of whom not more than three shall be 
officers of that bank;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that any nomination of a director made by the State 
Bank under this clause shall, except in so far as it 
relates to an office of that bank, be in consultation 
with the Central Government.]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1448515</tid>
<number>ca</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> one director, from among the employees of the 
subsidiary bank, who are workmen, to be appointed by 
the Central Government in the manner provided in the 
rules made under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1239457</tid>
<number>cb</number>one director, from among such of the employees of the 
subsidiary bank as are not workmen, to be appointed by 
the Central Government in the manner provided in the 
rules made under this Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1722070</tid>
<number>d</number>two directors to be elected in the prescribed manner by 
the shareholders, other than the State Bank:
Provided that if the total amount of the holdings of all such 
shareholders registered in the books of the subsidiary 
bank three months before the date fixed for election is 
below five per cent. of the total issued capital, or if 
there are no shareholders other than the State Bank 
registered on the books of the subsidiary bank, the 
directors to be elected by the shareholders shall be 
nominated by the State Bank and such directors shall, 
for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be directors 
elected under this clause;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1732306</tid>
<number>e</number>a director, if any to be nominated by the Central 
Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>256886</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (d) of sub- 
section (1), on the first constitution of the Board of Directors, the 
directors referred to in the said clause shall be appointed by the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>188</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 28 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
3. Certain words omitted by s. 18 ibid. (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


State Bank and the directors so appointed shall, for the purposes of 
this Act, be deemed to have been elected within the meaning of the 
said clause.


</section>

<section><tid>1343246</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for any reason, a director of a subsidiary bank nominated 
under clause (b) of sub- section (1) is unable to exercise his 
functions or to discharge his duties as such director, the Reserve 
Bank may nominate any of its officers to exercise all the functions 
and to discharge all the duties of such director whenever he is so 
unable to exercise his functions or discharge his duties, and the 
officer so nominated shall for all purposes of this Act be deemed to 
be a director of the subsidiary bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1502693</tid>
<number>4</number>An officer of the Reserve Bank or the State Bank may be 
nominated as a director of a subsidiary bank by virtue of his office.

</section>

<section><tid>1939254</tid>
<number>5</number>The directors nominated under sub- section (2) shall retire at 
the expiry of one year after the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>28914</tid>
<number>6</number>Any nomination or appointment of a director made by the State 
Bank under this Act shall, except in so far it relates to an officer 
of that bank, be in consultation with the Reserve Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>5798</tid>
<number> 26</number> Term of office of Directors.
<section><tid>1191403</tid>
<number>1</number>A director of a subsidiary  
bank, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (e) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25 or appointed under clause (ca) or clause 
 (cb) of that sub- section] shall hold office during the pleasure of 
the authority <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> nominating or appointing] him.

</section>

<section><tid>1743221</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions contained in section 25, a 
director elected under clause (d) of sub- section (1) of that section 
shall hold office for three years and thereafter until his successor 
is duly elected, and shall be eligible for re- election:
Provided that no such director shall hold office continuously for 
a period exceeding six years.


</section>

<section><tid>496936</tid>
<number>2A</number>Subject to the provisions contained in section 25 and in 
sub- section (1), a director nominated under clause (c) and not being 
an officer of the State Bank or a director appointed under clause (ca) 
or clause (cb) or a director, not being an officer of the Central 
Government, nominated under clause (e) of sub- section (1) of section 
25, shall hold office for such term not exceeding three years, as the 
Central Government may specify and thereafter until his successor 
shall have been duly nominated or appointed, and shall be eligible for 
re- nomination or re- appointment, as the case may be:
Provided that no such director shall hold office continuously for 
a period exceeding six years.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>189</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 19, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 19, ibid. for sub- sections (2) and (2A)  (w. e. f.  
  30- 12- <year>1988</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1447318</tid>
<number> 27</number> Disqualification for directorship.
<section><tid>545952</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be  
disqualified to be a director of a subsidiary bank, if--

<subsection><tid>1762903</tid>
<number>a</number>he holds the office of director, provisional director, 
promoter, agent, or manager of any banking company or a 
banking company for the formation of which a prospectus 
has been issued; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507158</tid>
<number>b</number>he is a salaried officer of Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1322430</tid>
<number>c</number>he has been removed or dismissed from the service of 
Government or a local authority or a corporation or a 
company in which not less than fifty- one per cent. of 
the paid- up share capital is held by Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1982876</tid>
<number>d</number>he holds any office of profit under the subsidiary bank 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> other than the office of the managing director]; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180940</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the case of a director appointed under clause 
 (ca) or clause (cb) of sub- section (1) of section 25,--

<subsubsection><tid>11146</tid>
<number>i</number>he is not serving in the subsidiary bank or has not been 
serving in it for a continuous period of at least five 
years; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>50997</tid>
<number>ii</number>he is of such age that there is a likelihood of his 
attaining the age of superannuation during his term of 
office as a director; or]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>540665</tid>
<number>e</number>he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated an insolvent 
or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded 
with his creditors; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>819096</tid>
<number>f</number>he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a 
competent court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>931056</tid>
<number>g</number>he is, or has been, convicted of any offence which, in 
the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
turpitude; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1689726</tid>
<number>h</number>in the case of an elected director, he is not registered 
as a holder of unencumbered shares in the subsidiary 
bank of a nominal value of at least one thousand 
rupees:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>190</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f.  
  30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 24 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the disqualification mentioned in clause (b) shall 
not apply to an officer of the Central Government 
nominated as a director under clause (e) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 25:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that in the case of a director appointed 
under clause (ca) or clause (cb) of sub- section (1) of 
section 25, the disqualification mentioned in clause 
 (d) shall not operate:

Provided also that] in the case of a director deemed to have been 
elected on the first constitution of the Board of 
Directors, the disqualification mentioned in clause (h) 
shall not operate for a period of six months from his 
becoming such director.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>651627</tid>
<number>2</number>No two persons who are partners of the same firm or are 
directors of the same private company or one of whom is an agent of 
the other or holds a power of attorney from a firm of which the other 
is a partner may be directors of a subsidiary bank at the same time.

</section>

<section><tid>1024773</tid>
<number>3</number>The nomination or election, as a director of any person who 
is a member of either House of Parliament or the Legislature of a 
State shall be void unless within two months of the date of nomination 
or election as such director, he ceases to be a member of Parliament 
or the Legislature of the State, and if any director is elected or 
nominated as a member of Parliament or the Legislature of a State, he 
shall cease to be a director as from the date of such election or 
nomination, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1968204</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in clause (d) of sub- section (1) shall be 
deemed to preclude any person from being a director of a subsidiary 
bank by reason only of his being a legal or technical adviser of that 
bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1721366</tid>
<number>5</number>In this section,--

<subsection><tid>784056</tid>
<number>a</number>" banking company" has the same meaning as in the Banking 
Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>):

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392000</tid>
<number>b</number>" manager" means the chief executive officer, by whatever 
name called, of a banking company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>943847</tid>
<number>c</number>" private company" has the same meaning as in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>191</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 24, for" Provided further that" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1547081</tid>
<number> 28</number> Vacation of office of Directors.- If a director of a 
subsidiary bank--
<section><tid>352524</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has become, subject to any of the 
disqualifications mentioned in section 27; or

</section>

<section><tid>1655065</tid>
<number>b</number>resigns his office by giving notice in writing under his 
hand, in the case of a nominated director to the State 
Bank, and in the case of an elected director to the 
Board of Director of the subsidiary bank, and his 
registration is accepted; or

</section>

<section><tid>235213</tid>
<number>c</number>is absent without leave of the Board of Directors for 
more than three consecutive meetings thereof;
his seat on the Board of Directors shall thereupon become vacant:

Provided that nothing in clause (b) or clause (c) shall apply to 
a director referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 25 
or to a director, being an officer of the State Bank, nominated under 
clause (c) or to a director, being an officer of the Central 
Government nominated under clause (e) of that sub- section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>889323</tid>
<number> 29</number> Managing director.-
<section><tid>1877681</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Bank shall, after consulting  
the Board of Directors of a subsidiary bank, and with the approval of 
the Reserve Bank, appoint a <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] for that subsidiary 
bank:
Provided that in the case of the first appointment of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] no such consulation with the Board of Directors 
of the subsidiary bank shall be necessary.


</section>

<section><tid>1193579</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the general control of the Board of Directors, the 
day to day administration and management of the affairs of a 
subsidiary bank shall vest in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director], and the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be delegated to him by the Board of 
Directors.

</section>

<section><tid>1169903</tid>
<number>3</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] of a subsidiary bank--

<subsection><tid>853780</tid>
<number>a</number>shall devote his whole time to the affairs of that bank:
Provided that the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] of the subsidiary 
bank may, with the approval of the State Bank and the 
Reserve Bank, be a director of any other institution;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>58482</tid>
<number>b</number>shall hold office for such term not exceeding four years 
and subject to such conditions as the State Bank may, 
with the approval of the Reserve Bank, specify at the 
time of his appointment;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>192</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21 for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>539082</tid>
<number>c</number>shall receive such salary and allowances as may be 
determined by the State Bank with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>704043</tid>
<number>4</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] vacating his office shall be 
eligible for re- appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>943804</tid>
<number>5</number>The State Bank may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, 
for any sufficient reason, remove from office the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing 
director] of a subsidiary bank:
Provided that no such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] shall be removed from 
office unless he has been given an opportunity of showing cause 
against such removal.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>982156</tid>
<number>30</number>Remuneration of director.- A director of a subsidiary bank 
shall be paid for attending the meetings of the Board of Directors or 
of any of its committees and for attending to any other business of 
the subsidiary bank such fees and allowances as may be prescribed:
Provided that no fees shall be payable to the chairman of the 
State Bank <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or the managing director of the subsidiary bank] or any 
other director who is a wholetime officer of the Central Government or 
the Reserve Bank or the State Bank.



</article>



<article><tid>680424</tid>
<number> 31</number> Removal from office of director.-
<section><tid>1077856</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Bank may, with  
the approval of the Reserve Bank, for any sufficient reason, remove 
from office a director nominated under clause (c) of sub- section (1) 
of section 25 and not being an officer of the State Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1881240</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, in consultation with the State 
Bank, for any sufficient reason, remove from office a director 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appointed under clause (ca) or clause (cb) or nominated under 
clause (e)] of sub- section (1) of section 25 and not being an officer 
of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1639509</tid>
<number>3</number>Any director elected under clause (d) of sub- section (1) of 
section 25, may be removed from office--

<subsection><tid>142712</tid>
<number>a</number>by the State Bank, with the approval of the Reserve 
Bank, if at the time of the removal there are no 
shareholders other than the State Bank registered in 
the books of the subsidiary bank concerned;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>193</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21 for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1974</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 25, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 26, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1978990</tid>
<number>b</number>by a resolution passed by a majority of the votes of 
such shareholders holding in the aggregate not less 
than one- half of the share capital held by all such 
shareholders:
Provided that if the total amount of the holdings of all 
shareholders, other than the State Bank, registered in 
the books of the subsidiary bank, on the date of the 
resolution, is below five per cent., of the total 
issued capital, the resolution shall not have effect 
unless confirmed by the State Bank.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>33997</tid>
<number>4</number>No director shall be removed from office under sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) unless he has been given an opportunity of 
showing cause against such removal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>800864</tid>
<number>32</number>Appointment of another person for discharging the duties of 
managing director during his absence.- If the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] of 
a subsidiary bank is rendered incapable of discharging his duties by 
reason of infirmity or otherwise or is absent on leave or otherwise in 
circumstances not involving the vacation of his office, the State Bank 
may appoint another person to officiate for the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] 
until the date on which the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing director] resumes duty.


</article>



<article><tid>1968706</tid>
<number> 33</number> Casual vacancies among directors.-
<section><tid>350905</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any vacancy  
occurs before the expiry of the term of office of a director of a 
subsidiary bank, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> other than the managing director or a director 
appointed under clause (ca) or clause (cb) of sub- section (1) of 
section 25] the vacancy shall be filled--

<subsection><tid>315942</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a director nominated under clause (c) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25, not being an officer of 
the State Bank, by nomination by the State Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30689</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a director elected under clause (d) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25, by election or where the 
proviso to that clause is applicable, by nomination by 
the State Bank:
Provided that where the duration of the vacancy in the 
office of an elected director is likely to be less than 
six months, the vacancy may be filled by the remaining 
directors by co- opting a person from amongst the 
shareholders entitled to elect a director under clause 
 (d) of sub- section (1) of section 25 who is not 
disqualified under section 27;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 43 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21 for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1974</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 27, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1609384</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a director nominated under clause (e) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25, not being an officer of 
the Central Government, by nomination by that 
Government in consultation with the State Bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1176075</tid>
<number>2</number>A person nominated or elected or co- opted, as the case may be 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under sub section (1)] shall hold office for the unexpired portion 
of the term of his predecessor.

</section>

<section><tid>986686</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where any vacancy occurs before the expiry of the term of 
office of a director appointed under clause (ca) or clause (cb) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25, such vacancy shall be filled in 
accordance with the said clause (ca) or, as the case may be, clause 
 (cb), and the director so appointed shall hold office for the period 
specified under sub- section (2A) of section 26.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>577704</tid>
<number> 34</number> Meetings of the Board of Directors.-
<section><tid>1045042</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board of  
Directors of a subsidiary bank shall meet at such time and place and 
shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
business at its meetings as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1329000</tid>
<number>2</number>The chairman of the State Bank shall preside at every meeting 
of the Board of Directors of a subsidiary bank and, in his absence 
such one of the directors as may generally or in relation to any 
particular meeting be authorised by the chairman in this behalf shall 
preside; and in the absence of the chairman and also failing such 
authorisation, the directors of the subsidiary bank present at the 
meeting shall elect one from among themselves to preside at the 
meeting.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section," absence from 
a meeting" means non- attendance for any reason whatsoever at the 
meeting or any part of the meeting during which any business is 
transacted.


</section>

<section><tid>299173</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions at a meeting of the Board of Directors of a 
subsidiary bank shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the 
directors present, and in case of equality of votes, the person 
presiding at the meeting shall have a second or casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1765592</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any of the directors specified in clauses (a) and (b) 
of sub- section (1) of section 25 or any of the directors, being an 
officer
<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 27 for" under this section" (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- <year>1974</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 27, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the State Bank specified in clause (c) of that sub- section is 
unable to attend any meeting of the Board of Directors of a subsidiary 
bank, and the State Bank or any other such director as may be present 
at the meeting considers that the State Bank would not be adequately 
or effectively represented at such meeting by reason of the absence of 
any such director, the State Bank or the director present may give 
notice in writing to that subsidiary bank--


<subsection><tid>681929</tid>
<number>i</number>that the meeting should be adjourned to such date as may 
be indicated in the notice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1235111</tid>
<number>ii</number>that any matter, action, step or proceeding proposed to 
be considered, taken or carried out at that meeting, 
should not be so considered, taken or carried out; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1496395</tid>
<number>iii</number>that no decision should be taken at that meeting on 
any such matter, action, step or proceeding;
and that subsidiary bank and its Board of Directors shall be bound to 
comply with such notice and act accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1723456</tid>
<number>5</number>A director of a subsidiary bank who is directly or indirectly 
concerned or interested in any contract, loan, arrangement or 
proposal, entered into or proposed to be entered into or made by or on 
behalf of the subsidiary bank shall, at the earliest possible 
opportunity, disclose the nature of his interest to the Board of 
Directors of that bank; and any such director shall not be present at 
any meeting of the Board of Directors when any such contract, loan, 
arrangement or proposal is discussed, unless his presence is required 
by the other directors for the purpose of eliciting information and 
where any director is so required to be present, he shall not vote on 
any such contract, loan, arrangement or proposal:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall 
apply to such director by reason only of his being--


<subsection><tid>384974</tid>
<number>i</number>a shareholder (other than a director) holding not more 
than two per cent. of the paid- up capital in any public 
company as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), or any corporation established by or under any 
law for the time being in force in India or any co- 
operative society, with which or to which the 
subsidiary bank has entered into or made, or proposes 
to enter into or make, a contract, loan, arrangement or 
proposal; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3, for the proviso.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>925015</tid>
<number>ii</number>a director of the State Bank or of any other subsidiary 
bank being a director under clause (a) or clause (e) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25 or being an officer of 
the Reserve Bank or the State Bank nominated under 
clause (b) or clause (c) of that sub- section;] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479975</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an officer or other employee of the State Bank, or 
any other institution, if he is the managing director 
appointed under sub- section (1) of section 29 or under 
section 32; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911278</tid>
<number>iv</number>an officer or other employee of the subsidiary bank, if 
he is a director appointed under clause (ca) or clause 
 (cb) of sub- section (1) of section 25.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>194942</tid>
<number>6</number>A copy of the minutes of every meeting of the Board of 
Directors of a subsidiary bank, together with copies of all connected 
papers, shall be forwarded to the State Bank and the Reserve Bank as 
soon as possible.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294943</tid>
<number> 35</number> Executive Committee and other committees.-
<section><tid>1257801</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
an executive committee in respect of a subsidiary bank consisting of 
such directors as may be prescribed:
Provided that if any such director being an officer of the State 
Bank and nominated by that bank under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of 
section 25, is for any reason unable to exercise his functions or to 
discharge his duties in relation to the executive committee, the State 
Bank may depute any of its officers to exercise all the functions and 
to discharge all the duties of such director in relation to the 
executive committee whenever such director is so unable to exercise 
his functions or discharge his duties; and the officer so deputed 
shall, for all purposes of this Act, in so far as it applies to the 
executive committee, be deemed to be a director of the subsidiary 
bank.


</section>

<section><tid>1560437</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any regulations made under this Act, the executive 
committee may deal with any matter within the competence of the Board 
of Directors.

</section>

<section><tid>995569</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the minutes of every meeting of the executive 
committee of a subsidiary bank shall be forwarded to the State Bank 
and be laid before the Board of Directors of the subsidiary bank as 
soon as possible after the meeting.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>197</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 31 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>766272</tid>
<number>4</number>Without prejudice to the powers of the executive committee, 
and subject to any regulations made under this Act, the Board of 
Directors of a subsidiary bank may constitute such and so many other 
committees, whether consisting wholly of the directors or wholly of 
other persons, or partly of the directors and partly of other persons, 
as it deems fit, to exercise such powers and perform such duties as 
may, subject to such conditions, if any, as the Board of Directors may 
impose, be delegated to them by the Board of Directors.
CHAP

BUSINESS OF SUBSIDIARY BANKS

CHAPTER VI

BUSINESS OF SUBSIDIARY BANKS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>134749</tid>
<number> 36</number> Subsidiary bank to act as agent of the State Bank.-
<section><tid>1039293</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
subsidiary bank shall, if so required by the State Bank, act as agent 
of the State Bank at any place in India for--

<subsection><tid>901059</tid>
<number>a</number>paying, receiving, collecting and remitting money, 
bullion and securities on behalf of any Government in 
India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1403944</tid>
<number>b</number>undertaking and transacting any other business which the 
Reserve Bank may, from time to time, entrust to the 
State Bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1163959</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions on which any such agency business 
shall be carried on by the subsidiary bank on behalf of the State Bank 
shall be such as may be determined by the State Bank, after 
consultation with the subsidiary bank and with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1124934</tid>
<number> 36A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Subsidiary bank to act as agent of the Reserve Bank.-
<section><tid>404662</tid>
<number>1</number> 
A subsidiary bank shall, if so required by the Reserve Bank, act as 
agent of the Reserve Bank at all places in India, where it has a 
branch, for--

<subsection><tid>1683121</tid>
<number>a</number>paying, receiving, collecting and remitting money, 
bullion and securities on behalf of any Government in 
India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1808746</tid>
<number>b</number>undertaking and transacting any other business which the 
Reserve Bank may from time to time entrust to it.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1629919</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions on which any such agency business 
shall be carried on by the subsidiary bank on behalf of the Reserve 
Bank shall be such as may be agreed upon.

</section>

<section><tid>1784735</tid>
<number>3</number>If, no agreement can be reached on any matter referred to in 
sub- section (2) or if a dispute arises between a subsidiary bank and 
the Reserve Bank as to the interpretation of any agreement between 
them, the matter shall be referred to the Central Government and the 
decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>804947</tid>
<number>4</number>A subsidiary bank may transact any business or perform any 
functions entrusted to it under sub- section (1), by itself or through 
any agent approved by the Reserve Bank.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287610</tid>
<number> 37</number> Other business which a subsidiary bank may transact.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1743969</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, a subsidiary 
bank may carry on and transact the business of banking as defined in 
clause (b) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of  
  <year>1949</year>), and may engage in one or more of the other forms of business 
specified in sub- section (1) of section 6 of that Act.]

</section>

<section><tid>177656</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, after consultation with the 
Reserve Bank and the State Bank, by order in writing--
<pagefootnote><pagenum>198</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- sections (3) and (4) omitted by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f.  
  1- 1- <year>1963</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 49 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 29, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 31-  
  12- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



<subsection><tid>1470303</tid>
<number>a</number>authorise a subsidiary bank to do such other forms of 
business as the Central Government may consider 
necessary or expedient;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1818088</tid>
<number>b</number>direct that any form of business as is mentioned in the 
order, shall be carried on subject to such 
restrictions, conditions and safeguards as may be 
specified therein; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>32507</tid>
<number>c</number>Prohibit a subsidiary bank from carrying on or 
transacting any form of business which, but for this 
clause, it is lawful for the subsidiary bank to engage 
in.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>113441</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (2), a subsidiary 
bank shall not engage in any form of business other than that referred 
to in sub- section (1)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073480</tid>
<number> 38</number> Acquisition of business of other banks.-
<section><tid>922857</tid>
<number>1</number>A subsidiary bank  
may, with the approval of the State Bank, and shall, if the Reserve 
Bank, in consultation with the State Bank, so directs, enter into 
negotiations for acquiring the business, including the assets and 
liabilities of any other banking institution.

</section>

<section><tid>1428524</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions relating to such acquisition, if 
agreed upon by the Board of Directors of the subsidiary bank concerned 
and the directorate or management of the banking institution concerned 
and approved by the Reserve Bank, shall be submitted to the Central 
Government for its sanction and that Government may by order in 
writing (hereafter in this section referred to as the order of  
  sanction) accord its sanction thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1221481</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other 
law for the time being in force or any instrument regulating the 
constitution of the banking institution concerned, the terms and 
conditions as sanctioned by the Central Government shall come into 
effect on the date specified by the Central Government in this behalf 
in the order of sanction and be binding upon the subsidiary bank and 
the banking institution concerned as well as upon the shareholders 
 (or, as the case may be, proprietors) and creditors of that banking 
institution.

</section>

<section><tid>1376428</tid>
<number>4</number>If for any reason the terms and conditions cannot come into 
effect on the date specified in the order of sanction, the Central 
Government may fix another suitable date for that purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>1424343</tid>
<number>5</number>On the date on which the terms and conditions as aforesaid 
come into effect, the business and the assets and liabilities of the 
banking institution concerned as covered by the acquisition shall,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>199</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by virtue, and in accordance with the provisions, of the order of 
sanction stand transferred to, and become respectively the business 
and the assets and liabilities of, the subsidiary bank concerned.


</section>

<section><tid>1461822</tid>
<number>6</number>The consideration for the acquisition of the business and the 
assets and liabilities of any banking institution under this section 
may, if so agreed upon, be paid either in cash or by allotment of 
shares in the capital of the subsidiary bank concerned or partly in 
cash and partly by allotment of shares, and the subsidiary bank may, 
for the purpose of any such allotment, increase, subject to the other 
provisions contained in this Act relating to the increase of capital, 
the capital of the subsidiary bank by the issue of such number of 
shares as may be determined by the subsidiary bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1844143</tid>
<number>7</number>Any business acquired under this section shall thereafter be 
carried on by the subsidiary bank in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act subject to such exemptions or modifications as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make in this 
behalf in consultation with the Reserve Bank:
Provided that no such exemption or modification shall be made so 
as to have effect for a period of more than seven years from the date 
of acquisition.


</section>

<section><tid>1226823</tid>
<number>8</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law or in any agreement for 
the time being in force, on the acquisition of the business and the 
assets and liabilities of any banking institution under this section, 
no officer or other employee of that banking institution shall be 
entitled to any compensation to which he may be entitled under that 
Act or that other law or that agreement, and no claim in respect of 
such compensation shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority if on his having accepted in writing an offer of employment 
by the subsidiary bank concerned on the terms and conditions proposed 
by it he has been employed in accordance with such terms and 
conditions.

</section>

<section><tid>62312</tid>
<number>9</number>The Central Government may, if it consider necessary or 
expedient in the case of any banking institution in relation to which 
an order of sanction has been made under this section, appoint, 
whether before or after the coming into effect of the terms and 
conditions relating to the business and the assets and liabilities of 
that banking institution, a suitable person to take over the 
management of that banking institution for the purposes of winding up 
its affairs and distributing its assets, and the expenditure incurred 
in connection with such management (including the remuneration of the 

<pagefootnote><pagenum>200</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

  person so appointed and his staff, if any) shall be paid out of the 
assets of the banking institution or by the subsidiary bank concerned 
as the Central Government may direct.


</section>

<section><tid>182808</tid>
<number>10</number>Simultaneously with the appointment of a suitable person 
under sub- section (9) or immediately thereafter, the Central 
Government shall issue directions to be followed by that person in the 
management of that banking institution for the purposes aforesaid and 
thereupon--

<subsection><tid>949385</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
or the Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year>, (10 of <year>1949</year>), or 
any other law for the time being in force or any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any such Act or 
law, in so far as they are inconsistent with such 
directions, shall cease to apply to, or in relation to, 
that banking institution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591600</tid>
<number>b</number>all persons in charge of the management, including any 
person holding office as manager or director, of the 
banking institution, immediately before the issue of 
such directions, shall be deemed to have vacated their 
offices as such; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517685</tid>
<number>c</number>the person appointed to take over the management of the 
banking institution shall, in accordance with those 
directions, take all such steps as may be necessary to 
facilitate the winding up of its affairs and the 
distribution of its assets.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1122042</tid>
<number>11</number>The Central Government, when satisfied that nothing further 
remains to be done in order to windup the affairs of the banking 
institution concerned, may, by order in writing, direct that as from 
such date as may be specified therein, the banking institution shall 
stand dissolved and thereupon any such direction shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law.

</section>

<section><tid>1478910</tid>
<number>12</number>No action under this section shall be questioned on the 
ground merely of any defect in the constitution of any banking 
institution in relation to which such action has been taken or in the 
constitution of its Board of Directors or in the appointment of any 
person entrusted with the management of its affairs.

</section>

<section><tid>1439798</tid>
<number>13</number>The provisions of this section shall apply in relation to 
the acquisition by one subsidiary bank of the business, including the 
assets and liabilities, of another subsidiary bank as they apply in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>201</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

relation to the acquisition by a subsidiary bank of the business, 
including the assets and liabilities, of any other banking 
institution.


</section>

<section><tid>133286</tid>
<number>14</number>In this section," banking institution" includes any 
individual or any association of individuals (whether incorporated or  
  not, or whether a department of Government or a separate institution), 
carring on the business of banking.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1587158</tid>
<number> 38A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Arrangement with subsidiary banks on appointment of 
directors to prevail.-
<section><tid>786026</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any arrangement entered into by a  
subsidiary bank with a company provides for the appointment by the 
subsidiary bank of one or more directors of such company, such 
provision and any appointment of directors made in pursuance thereof 
shall be valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the contrary 
contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, or in any other law for the time 
being in force or in the memorandum, articles of association or any 
other instrument relating to the company, and any provision regarding 
share qualification, age limit, number of directorships, removal from 
office of directors and such like conditions contained in any such law 
or instrument aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed by 
the subsidiary bank in pursuance of the arrangement as aforesaid.

</section>

<section><tid>1681306</tid>
<number>2</number>Any director appointed as aforesaid shall--

<subsection><tid>166794</tid>
<number>a</number>hold office during the pleasure of the subsidiary bank 
and may be removed or substituted by any person by 
order in writing of the subsidiary bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>581729</tid>
<number>b</number>not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of 
his being a director or for anything done or omitted to 
be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as 
a director or anything in relation thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754135</tid>
<number>c</number>not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not be 
taken into account for computing the number of 
directors liable to such retirement.]
CHAP

ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER VII

ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1962399</tid>
<number>39</number>Closing of annual accounts.- A subsidiary bank shall cause its 
books to be closed and balanced <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as] on the thirty- first day of 
December <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or such other date in each year as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that with a view to facilitating the transition from 
one period of accounting to another period of accounting under this 
section, the Central Government may, by order published in the 
Official Gazette, make such provisions as it considers necessary or 
expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for other matters 
relating to, the books in respect of the concerned years.]



</article>



<article><tid>1650506</tid>
<number> 40</number> Disposal of profits.-
<section><tid>331030</tid>
<number>1</number>After making provision for bad and  
doubtful debts, depreciation in assets, equalisation of dividends, 
contribution to staff and superannuation funds and for all other 
matters for which provision is necessary by or under this Act or which 
are usually provided for by banking companies, a subsidiary bank may, 
out of its net profits, declare a dividend.

</section>

<section><tid>1147962</tid>
<number>2</number>The rate of dividend shall be determined by the Board of 
Directors of the subsidiary bank concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1067747</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to preclude the 
payment of interim dividends in such manner and to such extent as may 
be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500225</tid>
<number> 41</number> Audit.-
<section><tid>1589462</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of section 42, the  
accounts of a subsidiary bank shall be audited by an auditor duly 
qualified to act as an auditor of companies under sub- section (1) of 
section 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), who shall be 
appointed by the State Bank, with the approval of the Reserve Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1090834</tid>
<number>2</number>The auditor shall receive such remuneration as the State Bank 
may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1414863</tid>
<number>3</number>No director or officer of a subsidiary bank shall be eligible 
to be its auditor during his continuance in office as such director or 
officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1399634</tid>
<number>4</number>The auditor shall be supplied with a copy of the annual 
balance- sheet and profit and loss account, and a list of all books 
kept by the subsidiary bank, and it shall be the duty of the auditor 
to
<pagefootnote><pagenum>202</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 50 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 30 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>). 
3. Subs. and ins by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 20, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 20, ibid. (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


examine the balance- sheet and profit and loss account with the 
accounts and vouchers relating thereto, and in the performance of his 
duties, the auditor--


<subsection><tid>1883553</tid>
<number>a</number>shall have, at all reasonable times, access to the 
books, accounts and other documents of that subsidiary 
bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>961358</tid>
<number>b</number>may, at the expense of that subsidiary bank, employ 
accountants and other persons to assist him in 
investigating such accounts; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>788395</tid>
<number>c</number>may, in relation to such accounts, examine any director 
or any officer of that subsidiary bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1574485</tid>
<number>5</number>The auditor shall hold office for such term not exceeding one 
year as the State Bank may fix at the time of his appointment; and if 
any vacancy arises before the expiry of the term of an auditor, the 
vacancy may be filled by the State Bank, with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1154784</tid>
<number>6</number>The auditor shall on relinquishing office be eligible for re- 
appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>1819593</tid>
<number>7</number>The auditor shall make a report to the State Bank upon the 
annual balance- sheet and accounts of the subsidiary bank, and, in 
every such report, he shall state--

<subsection><tid>380818</tid>
<number>a</number>whether, in his opinion, the balance- sheet is a full and 
fair balance- sheet containing all the necessary 
particulars and is properly drawn up so as to 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> exhibit a true and fair view] of the affairs of that 
subsidiary bank, and in case he has called for any 
explanation or information, whether it has been given 
and whether it is satisfactory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>863798</tid>
<number>b</number>whether or not the transactions of that subsidiary bank 
which have come to his notice have been within the 
competence of the bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1584429</tid>
<number>c</number>whether or not the returns received from the offices and 
branches of that subsidiary bank have been found 
adequate for the purpose of his audit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1719887</tid>
<number>d</number>whether the profit and loss account shows a true balance 
of profit or loss for the period covered by such 
account; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802872</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which he considers should be brought to 
the notice of the State Bank.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>203</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 31, for certain words (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation 1.-- For the purposes of this Act,--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>380818</tid>
<number>a</number>the balance- sheet shall not be treated as not disclosing 
a true and fair view of the affairs of the subsidiary 
bank, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>863798</tid>
<number>b</number>the profit and loss account shall not be treated as not 
showing a true balance of profit or loss for the period 
covered by such account,
merely by reason of the fact that the balance- sheet or, as the case 
may be, the profit and loss account, does not disclose any matters 
which are, by the provisions of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, (10  
  of <year>1949</year>.) read with the relevant provisions of this Act, not required 
to be disclosed.

Explanation 2.-- For the purposes of this Act, the accounts of the 
subsidiary bank shall not be deemed as having not been properly drawn 
up on the ground merely that they do not disclose certain matters if--


<subsubsection><tid>684876</tid>
<number>i</number>those matters are such as the subsidiary bank is, by 
virtue of any provision contained in the Banking 
Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>.), read with the 
relevant provisions of this Act, or any other Act, not 
required to disclose, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>500123</tid>
<number>ii</number>the provisions referred to in clause (i) are specified 
in the balance- sheet and profit and loss account of the 
subsidiary bank or in the auditor' s report.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>572304</tid>
<number>8</number>The auditor shall forward a copy of the audit report to the 
subsidiary bank and to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1722800</tid>
<number>9</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions, the Central 
Government may, at any time, appoint such number of auditors as it 
thinks fit to examine and report on the accounts of a subsidiary bank, 
and the auditors so appointed shall have all the rights, privileges 
and authority in relation to the audit of the accounts of the 
subsidiary bank which an auditor appointed by the State Bank has under 
this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1809105</tid>
<number>42</number>Temporary provision regarding exiesting auditors.- If, on the 
appointed day, any appointment of an auditor made by, or in respect 
of, an existing bank, the Hyderabad Bank or the Saurashtra Bank, as 
the case may be, is subsisting, the State Bank may, on or after such 
day, either confirm the appointment in accordance with the provisions 
of this Act, subject to such modifications
<pagefootnote><pagenum>204</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the terms and conditions of the appointment, as it may deem 
necessary, or terminate the appointment; and may, if it so terminates 
the appointment, fix such remuneration as appears to it to be 
reasonable having regard to the work already done, functions 
discharged, or duties performed by the auditor concerned.



</article>



<article><tid>48670</tid>
<number> 43</number> Returns to be furnished by a subsidiary bank.-
<section><tid>1118080</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
subsidiary bank shall furnish to the State Bank <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, the Reserve Bank 
and the Central Government]

<subsection><tid>474851</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> within three months from the 31st day of December 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or the date notified under section 39, as the case 
may be,] as on which its books are closed and 
balanced], its balance- sheet, together with the profit 
and loss account and the auditor' s report, and a report 
by the Board of Directors on the working <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and 
activities] of the subsidiary bank during the period 
covered by the accounts; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>770411</tid>
<number>b</number>any other information relating to the affairs and 
business of the subsidiary bank which the State Bank or 
the Reserve Bank may require:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that the Reserve Bank may, after consultation with 
the State Bank, extend the said period of three months by such further 
period, not exceeding three months, as it may think fit.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1729918</tid>
<number>2</number>The balance- sheet and the profit and loss account of a 
subsidiary bank shall be signed by the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> managing director] and a 
majority of the directors of the subsidiary bank.

</section>

<section><tid>626347</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The Central Government shall cause the auditor' s report 
and the report by the Board of directors on the working and activitier 
of the subsidiary bank to be laid, as soon as may be after they are 
received, before each House of Parliament.
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>852137</tid>
<number> 44</number> General meetings.-
<section><tid>1019004</tid>
<number>1</number>A general meeting (hereinafter referred   
  to as an annual general meeting) of a subsidiary bank shall be held 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in each year] at the place where the head office of the subsidiary 
bank is situate, and any other general meeting may be convened by the 
Board of Directors at any time:
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Provided that such annual general meeting shall be held before 
the expiry of six weeks from the date on which the balance- sheet, 
together with the profit and loss account and auditor' s report, is, 
under sub- section (1) of section 43, forwarded to <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> the State Bank, 
the Reserve Bank or the Central Government] whichever date is 
earlier.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>205</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 1 of <year>1984</year> s. 51, for certain words (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 34 for certain words (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1973</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 51 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year> s. 32 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>). 
6. Subs. by s. 21, ibid., for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1974</year>). 
7. Omitted by Act 81 of <year>1985</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year> s. 33, for" annually before the end 
of March" (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>). 
9. Added by s. 38, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>). 
10. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year> s. 52 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>309795</tid>
<number>2</number>The shareholders present at an annual general meeting shall 
be entitled to discuss the balance- sheet and profit and loss account 
of the bank concerned, made up to the previous 31st day of December, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the date notified under section 39, as the case may be], the 
report of the Board of Directors on the working <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and activities] 
of that bank for the period covered by the accounts and the auditors' 
report on the balance- sheet and accounts.

</section>

<section><tid>656136</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in this section relating to an annual 
general meeting shall apply in relation to a subsidiary bank if, as on 
the previous 31st day of December <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the date notified under 
section 39, as the case may be] all the shares in the issued capital 
of that bank are held by the State Bank.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VIII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1776182</tid>
<number>45</number>Power to issue directions removing difficulties.- For the 
purpose of facilitating the full and effective transfer of the 
undertaking of an existing bank in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act, or in order to remove any difficulty which in the opinion of 
the Central Government has arisen or is likely to arise in connection 
with such transfer, the Central Government may, in consultation with 
the Reserve Bank, give such direction to any existing bank or the 
State Bank as appear to it to be necessary and the said bank or the 
State Bank, as the case may be, shall comply with such directions.


</article>



<article><tid>501072</tid>
<number> 46</number> Observers for existing banks and the Saurashtra Bank.-
<section><tid>213858</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
State Bank may, in relation to any existing bank or the Saurashtra 
Bank, at any time before the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>1839904</tid>
<number>a</number>depute one or more persons to watch the proceedings at 
any meeting of the Board of Directors, any committee or 
other body of the bank; require the bank to give an 
opportunity to the person or persons so deputed to be 
heard at such meetings and also require such person or 
persons to send a report of such proceedings to the 
State Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>773101</tid>
<number>b</number>require the Board of Directors, any committee or other 
body of the bank to give in writing to any person 
specified by the State Bank in this behalf, at his 
usual address, all notices of, and other communications 
relating to, any meeting of the Board, committee or 
other body, as the case may be;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>206</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 22 (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 52 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>229177</tid>
<number>e</number>appoint one or more persons to observe the manner in 
which the affairs of the bank or of its officers or 
branches are being conducted and make a report thereon; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1955844</tid>
<number>d</number>require the bank to furnish the State Bank, within such 
time as may be specified by the State Bank, with any 
statement or information relating to the business or 
affairs of the bank including copies of the proceedings 
of any meeting of the Board of Directors, any committee 
or other body, of the bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>154327</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person deputed by the State Bank to watch the 
proceedings of any meeting of the Board of Directors, any committee or 
other body, as the case may be, gives notice in writing to the bank 
that such person considers that any action, step or proceeding 
proposed to be taken or carried out by the bank will be detrimental to 
the State Bank or to the bank itself, such action, step or proceeding 
shall not be taken or carried out by the bank unless and until the 
State Bank approves in writing of such action, step or proceeding.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," Board of 
Directors" in relation to the Saurashtra Bank, means its Board of 
Management.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1206866</tid>
<number> 47</number> Inspection.-
<section><tid>872652</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to the other provisions  
contained in this Act, the State Bank may, at any time, cause an 
inspection to be made by one or more of its officers of any existing 
bank, a new bank, the Hyderabad Bank or the Saurashtra Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1394449</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of every person who is, or has, at any 
time, been a director, officer or other employee of a bank which is 
inspected under sub- section (1), to produce to any officer making the 
inspection, all such balances, books, accounts, securities and other 
documents in his custody or power and to furnish the said officer with 
any statements and information relating to the affairs of the bank as 
the said officer may require of him within such time as the said 
officer may specify.

</section>

<section><tid>961389</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person--

<subsection><tid>846611</tid>
<number>a</number>fails, within the stipulated time, to produce any 
balance, books, account, security or other document or 
to furnish any statement or information which under 
sub- section (2) it is his duty to produce or furnish, 
or to answer any question relating to the business of 
the bank under inspection which is asked by an officer 
making the inspection, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>207</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1580357</tid>
<number>b</number>in any document or information required or furnished or 
while answering any question put to him, wilfully makes 
a statement which is false in any material particular, 
knowing it to be false, or wilfully omits to make a 
material statement,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years and shall also be liable to fine.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1318229</tid>
<number> 48</number> Cost of development programme.-
<section><tid>81733</tid>
<number>1</number>A subsidiary bank may  
accept any subsidies offered by the State Bank to meet--

<subsection><tid>1341977</tid>
<number>a</number>the cost of the whole or any part of any specific 
programme of development undertaken by that subsidiary 
bank with the approval of the State Bank; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>483927</tid>
<number>b</number>such losses or expenditure as may be approved by the 
State Bank, with the consent of the Reserve Bank.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1982784</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of  
  <year>1922</year>), any subsidy received by a subsidiary bank under sub- section 
 (1) shall not be treated as income, profits or gains of the subsidiary 
bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>609627</tid>
<number> 49</number> Special provision regarding existing officers and employees.-

<section><tid>1538320</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any of the other provisions  
of this Act, or in any other law or in any contract of service or 
other document, no appointment made or promotion, increment in salary, 
pension or allowance or any other benefit granted to any person by an 
existing bank or the Saurashtra Bank after the 10th day of February, 
<year>1958</year>, and before the appointed day, which would not ordinarily have 
been made or granted or which would not ordinarily have been 
admissible under the rules or authorisations of the said banks or of 
any provident, pension or other fund in force before the 10th day of 
February, <year>1958</year>, shall have effect or be payable or claimable from the 
subsidiary bank concerned, or from any provident, pension or other 
fund, or from any authority administering any such fund, unless the 
State Bank has, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, by a general or 
special order, confirmed the appointment, promotion or increment or 
has directed the grant of the pension, allowance or other benefit, as 
the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1946885</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any officer or other employee of an existing bank or of 
the Saurashtra Bank has received any amount by reason of such 
appointment, promotion or increment or any such pension, allowance or 
other benefit as is referred to in sub- section (1), which has not been 
confirmed or sanctioned by the State Bank under that sub- section, such 
officer or other employee shall be bound to refund such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>208</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

amount to the subsidiary bank concerned, and that bank shall be 
entitled to take all such steps as may be necessary for recovering 
such amount.


</section>

<section><tid>212021</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any managing director, general manager or manager, 
deputy managing director or deputy general manager or other employee 
of an existing bank or the Saurashtra Bank has, after the 10th day of 
February, <year>1958</year>, and before the appointed day, been paid any sum by way 
of compensation or gratuity, the subsidiary bank concerned shall be 
entitled to claim a refund of any sum so paid if the payment is not 
confirmed by the State Bank by a general or special order.

</section>

<section><tid>1703787</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in this section shall apply to, or in relation to, 
any officer or other employee of the Bank of Patiala, who does not 
become an officer or other employee of the State Bank of Patiala under 
the provisions of section 11.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>687191</tid>
<number> 50</number> Staff of a subsidiary bank.-
<section><tid>97432</tid>
<number>1</number>A subsidiary bank may,  
subject to such limitations and conditions as may be prescribed, 
appoint such number of officers, advisers and employees as it 
considers necessary or desirable, for the efficient performance of its 
functions and on such terms and conditions as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>370870</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
officers, advisers and employees of a subsidiary bank, in whatever 
capacity engaged, shall not be deemed to be officers, advisers or 
employees of the State Bank for any purpose, unless otherwise provided 
in the contract or agreement of service of any such officer, adviser 
or employee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>3124</tid>
<number> 50A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Bonus.-
<section><tid>1955635</tid>
<number>1</number>No officer, adviser or other employee[ other  
than a employee within the meaning of clause (13) of section 2 of the 
Payment of Bonus Act, <year>1965</year>] of a subsidiary bank shall be entitled to 
be paid any bonus.

</section>

<section><tid>1787751</tid>
<number>2</number>No employee of a subsidiary bank, being an employee within 
the meaning of clause (13) of section 2 of the Payment of Bonus Act, 
<year>1965</year>, shall be entitled to be paid any bonus except in accordance with 
the provisions of that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1738834</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding any judgment, decree or order of any court, tribunal 
or other authority and notwithstanding anything contained in any other 
provision of this Act or in the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of  
  <year>1947</year>), or any other law for the time being in force or any practice, 
usage or custom or any contract, agreement, settlement, award or other 
instrument.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1054044</tid>
<number>51</number>Establishment of pension and superannuation funds by 
subsidiary banks.- Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained 
in any other law for the time being in force, a subsidiary bank may 
establish and maintain superannuation, pension, provident or other 
funds for the benefit of its officers or employees or the dependants 
of such officers or employees or for the purposes of the subsidiary 
bank, and grant superannuation allowances, annuities and pensions 
payable out of any such fund.


</article>



<article><tid>712651</tid>
<number> 52</number> Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.-
<section><tid>1045419</tid>
<number>1</number>A subsidiary bank  
shall observe, except as otherwise required by law, the practices and 
usages customary among bankers, and in particular, it shall not 
divulge any information relating to, or to the affairs of, its 
constituents except in circumstances in which it is, in accordance 
with the law or practice and usage customary
<pagefootnote><pagenum>209</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 64 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


among bankers, necessary or appropriate for that bank to divulge such 
information.


</section>

<section><tid>345723</tid>
<number>2</number>Every director, auditor, adviser, officer or other employee 
of a subsidiary bank shall, before entering upon his duties, make a 
declaration of fidelity and secrecy as in the form set out in the 
Second Schedule:
Provided that any declaration made under sub- section (2) of 
section 35 of the State Bank of Hyderabad Act shall be deemed to be a 
declaration made to the Hyderabad Bank under this sub- section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>862891</tid>
<number> 53</number> Indemnity of directors.-
<section><tid>156690</tid>
<number>1</number>Every director of a subsidiary  
bank shall be indemnified by that bank against all losses and expenses 
incurred by him in, or in relation to, the discharge of his duties 
except such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>1266922</tid>
<number>2</number>A director of a subsidiary bank shall not be responsible for 
any loss or expense caused to the bank by the insufficiency or 
deficiency of the value of, or title to, any property or security 
acquired or taken on behalf of the bank or by the insolvency or 
wrongful act of any customer or debtor or by anything done in, or 
relation to, the execution of the duties of his office or otherwise 
than for his wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>759076</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the State Bank nominates any of its officers as 
director of a subsidiary bank, such director shall not incur any 
obligation or liability by reason only of his being a director or for 
anything done or omitted to be done in good faith in the discharge of 
his duties as director or anything in relation thereto.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1814632</tid>
<number> 54</number> Defects in appointment or constitution not to invalidate acts 
or proceedings.-
<section><tid>387055</tid>
<number>1</number>No act or proceeding of the Board of Directors of  
a subsidiary bank shall be questioned on the ground merely of the 
existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the 
Board.

</section>

<section><tid>12405</tid>
<number>2</number>All acts done by any person acting in good faith as a 
director of a subsidiary bank shall, notwithstanding that he was 
disqualified to be a director or that there was any other defect in 
his appointment, be deemed to be valid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>157106</tid>
<number>55</number>Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, and Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year>, not to 
apply to certain existing banks.- Subject to the provisions of this Act 
and unless the Central Government, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, otherwise directs, on and from the appointed day, the 
provisions of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>.), and the Banking 
Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>.), shall not apply to an existing 
bank, in so far as the said provisions impose any obligation on, or 
require anything to be done by, any such bank.


</article>



<article><tid>561295</tid>
<number>56</number>Continuance of special provisions respecting recovery of 
loans and advances made by the Bank of Patiala and the State Bank of 
Saurashtra. The State Bank of Patiala and the Saurashtra Bank shall be 
entitled to recover in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue
<pagefootnote><pagenum>210</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 53 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


any moneys due in respect of loans or advances made before the 
appointed day by the Bank of Patiala or the Saurashtra Bank, as the 
case may be, and the provisions of any law, relating to such recovery 
as were applicable to that bank before the appointed day shall 
continue to apply to the State Bank of Patiala or the Saurashtra Bank, 
as the case may be, in respect of such recovery after the appointed 
day.



</article>



<article><tid>1222577</tid>
<number>57</number>Bar to liquidation of a subsidiary bank.- No provision of law 
relating to the winding up of companies shall apply to a subsidiary 
bank nor shall it be placed in liquidation, save as provided in this 
Act or by order of the Central Government and in such manner as the 
Central Government may direct.


</article>



<article><tid>1309248</tid>
<number>58</number>Dissolution of existing banks.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or in any other law for the time being in force 
or in any contract or other instrument, an existing bank shall, on 
such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, stand dissolved.


</article>



<article><tid>1060838</tid>
<number> 59</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Construction of references to existing banks.-
<section><tid>1006712</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purposes of sections 45, 49, 55, 58 and the First Schedule, the 
expression' existing bank' shall include the Bank of Jaipur Limited.

</section>

<section><tid>457788</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as otherwise provided in any general or special order 
made by the Central Government, any reference in any law, other than 
this Act, or in any contract or other instrument--

<subsection><tid>446346</tid>
<number>a</number>to an existing bank, shall be construed as a reference 
to the corresponding new bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1534217</tid>
<number>b</number>to the Bank of Jaipur Limited, shall be construed as a 
reference to the State Bank of Bikaner.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248032</tid>
<number>60</number>Exercise of powers and functions on behalf of the Reserve 
Bank.- Any powers, duties or functions conferred, imposed or entrusted 
by this Act on, or to, the Reserve Bank, shall be exercised or 
performed by the Governor of the Reserve Bank or, in his absence, by a 
Deputy Governor nominated under sub- section (3) of section 7 of the 
Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>, (2 of <year>1934</year>.) or by such officer or 
officers of the Reserve Bank in respect of such matters and subject to 
such conditions and limitations as the Governor of the Reserve Bank 
may specify.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>211</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3, for s. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>866308</tid>
<number> 61</number> Protection of action taken under Act.-
<section><tid>668166</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit or other  
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Reserve 
Bank or the State Bank or any officer of the Central Government, the 
Reserve Bank or the State Bank for any damage caused or likely to be 
caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
in pursuance of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1989137</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall have any right, whether in contract or 
otherwise, to any compensation for any loss incurred or any damage 
caused by reason of the operation of, or anything done in pursuance 
of, the provisions contained in sections 46 and 47.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879648</tid>
<number> 62</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>1583568</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> make rules 
to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or 
expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this 
Act].

</section>

<section><tid>1509350</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>114866</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Chairman, 
members and staff of the Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1354134</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner of, and the procedure for, payment of 
compensation (including allotment of shares in lieu of  
  compensation) under this Act, including the 
requirements subject to which the payment shall be 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>860321</tid>
<number>c</number>the determination of the persons to whom compensation 
shall be payable in all cases including cases where 
shares have been held by more than one person, or where 
they have been transferred before the appointed day, 
but the transfer has not been registered, or where the 
share- holder is dead;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1339697</tid>
<number>d</number>the circumstances under which claims for payment of the 
said compensation from persons claiming through or 
under a shareholder may be entertained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>715201</tid>
<number>e</number>the requirements to be complied with before receipt of 
the said compensation by a shareholder, whose share 
certificate has been lost, destroyed, mutilated or 
stolen;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667535</tid>
<number>f</number>the requirements subject to which information regarding 
the payment of the said compensation may be granted
<pagefootnote><pagenum>212</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 34, for certain words (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or refused and the conditions subject to which such 
information may be given;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>224786</tid>
<number>g</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner of appointment of a director under clause 
 (ca) or clause (cb) of sub- section (1) of section 25, 
and all other matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>432616</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days, which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1674124</tid>
<number> 63</number> Power of the State Bank of make regulations.-
<section><tid>1193280</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Bank of may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> by notification 
in the official Gazette] make in respect of a subsidiary bank 
regulations, not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, to provide for all matters for which provision is 
necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1960185</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for--

<subsection><tid>11706</tid>
<number>a</number>the powers and duties of the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> managing director] of 
the subsidiary bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>797806</tid>
<number>b</number>the fees and allowances which may be paid to directors 
or others for attending any meetings of the Board of 
Directors or of its committees (including the executive  
  committee) or other committees or for attending to any 
other work of the subsidiary bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1731068</tid>
<number>c</number>the time and place at which, and the manner in which, 
the business of the Board of Directors of the 
subsidiary bank shall be transacted and the procedure 
to be followed at the meetings thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1282384</tid>
<number>d</number>the constitution of the executive committee of the 
subsidiary bank and the conditions and limitations 
subject to which the executive committee may exercise 
its powers and the procedure to be followed at the 
meetings thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1700553</tid>
<number>e</number>the formation of any other committees, whether of the 
Board of Directors of the subsidiary bank or otherwise,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1973</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1984</year>, s. 54 (w. e. f. 15- 2- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1988</year>, s. 23 (w. e. f. 30- 12- <year>1988</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year> s. 21, ibid., for" general manager" (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and the delegation of powers and functions of the Board 
to such committees and the conduct of business in such 
committees;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1665764</tid>
<number>f</number>the nature of shares of the subsidiary bank, the manner 
in which, and the conditions subject to which, shares 
may be held and transferred and generally all matters 
relating to the rights and duties of shareholders;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>969312</tid>
<number>g</number>the maintenance of share registers, and the particulars 
to be entered in such registers in addition to those 
specified in section 21, the inspection and closure of 
the registers and all other matters connected 
therewith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>404115</tid>
<number>h</number>the holding and conduct of elections under this Act and 
the final determination of doubts or disputes regarding 
the qualifications of candidates for election or 
regarding the validity of elections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1324172</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner in which general meetings shall be convened, 
the procedure to be followed thereat and the manner in 
which voting rights may be exercised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>730801</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner in which notices may be served on behalf of 
the subsidiary bank upon shareholders or other persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1153997</tid>
<number>k</number>the payment of dividents, including interim dividends;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>953995</tid>
<number>l</number>the delegation of powers and functions of the Board of 
Directors of the subsidiary bank to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> managing 
director] or directors or officers or other employees 
of that bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1336667</tid>
<number>m</number>the conditions and limitations subject to which the 
subsidiary bank may appoint officers, advisers and 
other employees and fix their remuneration and other 
terms and conditions of service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>194738</tid>
<number>n</number>the duties and conduct of officers, advisers and other 
employees of the subsidiary bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140193</tid>
<number>o</number>the establishment and maintenance of superannuation, 
pension, provident or other funds for the benefit of 
the officers or employees of the subsidiary bank or of 
the dependants of such officers or employees or for the 
purposes of the subsidiary bank, and the granting of 
superannuation allowances, annuities and pensions 
payable out of any such fund;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1973</year>, s. 21, for" general manager" (w. e. f. 1-  
  7- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>990962</tid>
<number>p</number>the conduct and defence of legal proceedings by or 
against the subsidiary bank and the manner of signing 
pleadings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>540451</tid>
<number>q</number>the provision of a seal for the subsidiary bank and the 
manner and effect of its use;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>279311</tid>
<number>r</number>the form and manner in which contracts binding on the 
subsidiary bank may be executed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1441579</tid>
<number>s</number>the conditions and requirements subject to which loans 
or advances may be made or bills may be discounted or 
purchased by the subsidiary bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282738</tid>
<number>t</number>the conditions subject to which loans or advances may be 
made by the subsidiary bank to its directors or 
officers or the relatives of such directors or officers 
or to companies, firms or individuals with which or 
with whom such directors or officers or relatives are 
connected as partners, directors, managers, servants, 
shareholders or otherwise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>402201</tid>
<number>u</number>the persons or authorities who shall administer any 
pension, provident or other fund constituted for the 
benefit of the officers or employees of the subsidiary 
bank or their dependants or for the purposes of that 
bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1233154</tid>
<number>v</number>the circumstances in which the specific approval of the 
State Bank shall be required to the grant of loans and 
advances or investment of funds by the subsidiary bank 
or to any contract, arrangement or proposal entered 
into or proposed to be entered into by the subsidiary 
bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108585</tid>
<number>w</number>the preparation and submission to the State Bank and the 
Reserve Bank of statements of programmes of activities 
and financial statements of the subsidiary bank and the 
periods for which, and the time within which, such 
statements and estimates are to be prepared and 
submitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1287959</tid>
<number>x</number>the person or persons in the State Bank by whom any 
powers, duties or functions conferred, imposed or 
entrusted on or to the State Bank under this Act may be 
exercised or performed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>969312</tid>
<number>g</number>generally, for the efficient conduct of the affairs of 
the subsidiary bank.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>41321</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All regulations made under this section shall have effect 
from such earlier or later date as may be specified in the 
regulations.]

</section>

<section><tid>104976</tid>
<number>3</number>All regulations under this section except the first 
regulations, shall be made in consultation with the Board of Directors 
of the subsidiary bank concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>209517</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every regulation shall, as soon as may be after it is made 
under this act by the State Bank, be forwarded to the Central 
Government and that Government shall cause a copy of the same to be 
laid before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
session immediately following the session or the successive sessions, 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be 
made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect as the case may be so, however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that regulation.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>891246</tid>
<number>64</number>[ Amendment of certain enactments.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending act, <year>1964</year> (52 of <year>1964</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1403036</tid>
<number>65</number>Saving.- Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the 
provisions of section 35 of the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of  
  <year>1955</year>).

</article>



 </act>