<act><tid>286252</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN TELEGRAPH (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 8 OF <year>2004</year>
[ 9th January, <year>2004</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Indian Telegraph Act, <year>1885</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1531771</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1451137</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Indian  
Telegraph (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1168256</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of April, 
<year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>453398</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the Indian Telegraph Act, 
 <year>1885</year> (13 of <year>1885</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), 
clause
<section><tid>1727248</tid>
<number>1</number>shall be renumbered as clause (1AA) and before clause (1AA)  
as so renumbered, the following clauses shall be inserted, namely:-
' (1)" Fund" means the Universal Service Obligation Fund established 
under sub- section (1) of section 9A;


</section>

<section><tid>73257</tid>
<number>1A</number>" Universal Service Obligation" means the obligation to provide 
access to basic telegraph services to people in the rural and remote 
areas at affordable and reasonable prices;'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>856274</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 4In section 4 of the principal Act, in sub- 
section 1, the following Explanation shall be inserted at the end, 
namely:-
" Explanation.- The payments made for the grant of a licence under this 
sub- section shall include such sum attributable to the Universal 
Service Obligation as may be determined by the Central Government after 
considering the recommendation made in this behalf by the Telecom 
Regulatory Authority of India established under sub- section (1) of 
section 3 of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, <year>1997</year> (24 of  
  <year>1997</year>).".



</article>



<article><tid>330154</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act, in sub- 
section (2), after clause (ee), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (eea) the manner in which the Fund may be administered;

<section><tid>1859457</tid>
<number>eeb</number>the criteria based on which sums may be released.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>8046</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new Part IIA.- After Part II of the principal Act, the 
following Part shall be inserted, namely:-
PART IIA

UNIVERSAL SERVICE OBLIGATION FUND

" PART IIA 
UNIVERSAL SERVICE OBLIGATION FUND

Establishment of Universal Service Obligation Fund.

</article>



<article><tid>1983427</tid>
<number> 9A</number> Establishment of Universal Service Obligation Fund.-
<section><tid>138978</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from  
the commencement of the Indian Telegraph (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>, there 
shall be deemed to have been established, for the purposes of this Act, 
a Fund to be called the Universal Service Obligation Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1256931</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be under the control of the Central Government and 
there shall be credited thereto-

<subsection><tid>901074</tid>
<number>a</number>any sums of money paid under section 9B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>372728</tid>
<number>b</number>any grants and loans made by the Central Government under 
section 9C.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>260555</tid>
<number>3</number>The balance to the credit of the Fund shall not lapse at the end of 
the financial year.
Crediting of sums to Consolidated Fund of India.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1350409</tid>
<number>9B</number>Crediting of sums to Consolidated Fund of India.- The sums of money 
received towards the Universal Service Obligation under section 4 shall 
first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India, and the Central 
Government may, if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this 
behalf so provides, credit such proceeds to the Fund from time to time 
for being utilised exclusively for meeting the Universal Service 
Obligation.
Grants and loans by Central Government.

</article>



<article><tid>1173572</tid>
<number>9C</number>Grants and loans by Central Government.- The Central Government may, 
after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, 
credit by way of grants and loans such sums of money as that Government 
may consider necessary in the Fund.
Administration and utilization of Fund.

</article>



<article><tid>287062</tid>
<number> 9D</number> Administration and utilization of Fund.-
<section><tid>1805952</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall have the power to administer the Fund in such manner as may be 
prescribed by rules made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1949012</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be utilised exclusively for meeting the Universal 
Service Obligation. 
 (3) The Central Government shall be responsible for the co- ordination 
and ensuring timely utilisation and release of sums in accordance with 
the criteria as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1365311</tid>
<number> 6</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>148669</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Telegraph (Amendment) Ordinance,  
 <year>2003</year> (Ord. 7 of <year>2003</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>354556</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Indian Telegraph (Amendment) 
Ordinance, <year>2003</year> (Ord. 7 of <year>2003</year>), anything done or action taken under 
the principal Act as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended by this 
Act.
T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>