<act><title>THE FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT, 2002 
</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-</title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Freedom of Information Act, 2002. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions.- </title>In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number>"appropriate Government" means in relation to a public authority 
  established, constituted, owned, substantially financed by funds provided 
  directly or indirectly or controlled- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> by the Central Government, the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> by the State Government, the State Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> by the Union territory, the Central Government; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number>"competent authority" means- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the Speaker in the case of the House of the People or the Legislative 
    Assembly and the Chairman in the case of the Council of States or the 
    Legislative Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the Chief Justice of India in the case of the Supreme Court; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Chief Justice of the High Court in the case of a High Court; 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>the President or the Governor, as the case may be, in the case of 
    other authorities created by or under the Constitution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the administrator appointed under article 239 of the Constitution; 
    </subsection>
 </section><section><number>c</number> "freedom of information" means the right to obtain information from any 
  public authority by means of,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> inspection, taking of extracts and notes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> certified copies of any records of such public authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> diskettes, floppies or in any other electronic mode or through 
    print-outs where such information is stored in a computer or in any other 
    device; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>d</number> "information" means any material in any form relating to the 
  administration, operations or decisions of a public authority; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> "prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act by the 
  appropriate Government or the competent authority, as the case may be; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> "public authority" means any authority or body established or 
  constituted,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> by or under the Constitution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> by any law made by the appropriate Government, and includes any 
    other body owned, controlled or substantially financed by funds provided 
    directly or indirectly by the appropriate  Government; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>g</number> "Public Information Officer" means the Public Information Officer 
  appointed under sub-section (1) of section 5; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> "record" includes- 
 
 
 </section><section><number>i</number> any document, manuscript and file; 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> any microfilm, microfiche and facsimile copy of a document; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> any reproduction of image or images embodied in such microfilm 
    (whether enlarged or not); and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> any other material produced by a computer or by any other device; 
    </subsection></section><section><number>i</number> "third party" means a person other than the person making a request for 
  information and includes a public authority. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Freedom of information.- </title>Subject to the provisions of 
this Act, all citizens shall have freedom of information. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Obligations on public authorities.- </title>Every public 
authority shall- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> maintain all its records, in such manner and form as is consistent with 
  its operational requirements duly catalogued and indexed; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> publish at such intervals as may be prescribed by the appropriate 
  Government or competent authority,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the particulars of its organisation, functions and duties; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the powers and duties of its officers and employees and the 
    procedure followed by them in the decision making process; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the norms set by the public authority for the discharge of its 
    functions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> rules, regulations, instructions, manuals and other categories of 
    records under its control used by its employees for discharging its 
    functions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the details of facilities available to citizens for obtaining 
    information; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> the name, designation and other particulars of the Public 
    Information Officer; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>c</number> publish all relevant facts concerning important decisions and policies 
  that affect the public while announcing such decisions and policies; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> give reasons for its decisions, whether administrative or 
  quasi-judicial to those affected by such decisions; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> before initiating any project, publish or communicate to the public 
  generally or to the persons affected or likely to be affected by the project 
  in particular, the facts available to it or to which it has reasonable access 
  which in its opinion should be known to them in the best interests of natural 
  justice and promotion of democratic principles. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Appointment of Public Information Officers.-</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every 
public authority shall for the purposes of this Act, appoint one or more 
officers as Public Information Officers. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Public Information Officer shall deal with requests for information 
and shall render reasonable assistance to any person seeking such information. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The Public Information Officer may seek the assistance of any other 
officer as he considers necessary for the proper discharge of his duties. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any officer whose assistance has been sought under sub-section (3), shall 
render all assistance to the Public Information Officer seeking his assistance. 

  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Request for obtaining information.- </title>A person desirous of 
obtaining information shall make a request in writing or through electronic 
means, to the concerned Public Information Officer specifying the particulars of 
the information sought by him: 
 Provided that where such request cannot be made in writing, the Public 
Information Officer shall render all reasonable assistance to the person making 
the request orally to reduce it in writing. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Disposal of requests.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of a request under 
section 6, the Public Information Officer shall, as expeditiously as possible, 
and in any case within thirty days of the receipt of the request, either provide 
the information requested on payment of such fee as may be prescribed or reject 
the request for any of the reasons specified in sections 8 and 9: 
 Provided that where the information sought for concerns the life and liberty 
of a person, the same should be provided within forty-eight hours of the receipt 
of the request: 
 Provided further that where it is decided to provide the information on 
payment of any further fee representing the cost of providing the information, 
he shall send an intimation to the person making the request, giving the details 
of the fees determine d by him, requesting him to deposit the fees and the 
period intervening between the dispatch of the said intimation and payment of 
fees shall be excluded for the purpose of calculating the period of thirty days 
referred to above. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Before taking any decision under sub-section (1), the Public Information 
Officer shall take into consideration the representation made by a third party 
under section 11. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a request is rejected under sub-section (2), the Public Information 
Officer shall communicate to the person making request,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the reasons for such rejection; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the period within which an appeal against such rejections may be 
  preferred; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the particulars of the appellate authority. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Information shall ordinarily be provided in the form in which it is 
sought unless it would disproportionately divert the resources of the public 
authority or would be detrimental to the safety or preservation of the record in 
question. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Exemption from disclosure of information.-</title>
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, the following information not 
being information relating to any matter referred to in sub-section shall be 
exempted from disclosure, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> information, the disclosure of which would prejudicially affect the 
  sovereignty and integrity of India, security of the State, strategic 
  scientific or economic interest of India or conduct of international 
  relations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> information, the disclosure of which would prejudicially affect public 
  safety and order, detection and investigation of an offence or which may lead 
  to an incitement to commit an offence or prejudicially affect fair trial or 
  adjudication of a pending case; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> information, the disclosure of which would prejudicially affect the 
  conduct of Centre-State relations, including information exchanged in 
  confidence between the Central and State Governments or any of their 
  authorities or agencies; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Cabinet papers including records of deliberations of the Council of 
  Ministers, Secretaries and other officers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> minutes or records of advice including legal advice, opinions or 
  recommendations made by any officer of a public authority during the decision 
  making process prior to the executive decision or policy formulation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> trade or commercial secrets protected by law or information, the 
  disclosure of which would prejudicially affect the legitimate economic and 
  commercial interests or the competitive position of a public authority; or 
  would cause unfair gain or loss to any person; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> information, the disclosure of which may result in the breach of 
  privileges of Parliament or the Legislature of a State, or contravention of a 
  lawful order of a court. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of clause (a) of sub-section (1), any 
information relating to any occurrence, event or matter which has taken place 
occurred or happened twenty-five years before the date on which any request is 
made under section 6 shall be provided to any person making a request under that 
section: 
 Provided that where any question arises as to the date from which the said 
period of twenty-five years has to be computed, the decision of the Central 
Government shall be final. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Grounds for refusal to access in certain cases.</title>Without 
prejudice to the provisions of section 8, a Public Information Officer may 
reject a request for information also where such request- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> is too general in nature or is of such a nature that, having regard to 
  the volume of information required to be retrieved or processed would involve 
  unreasonable diversion of the resources of a public authority or would 
  adversely interfere with the functioning of such authority: 
 Provided that where such request is rejected on the ground that the request 
  is too general, it would be the duty of the Public Information 
 Officer to render help as far as possible to the person making request to 
  reframe his request in such a manner as ay facilitate compliance with it; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> relates to information that is required by law, rules, regulations or 
  orders to be published at a particular time and such information is likely to 
  be so published within thirty days of the receipt of such request; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> relates to information that is contained in published material 
  available to public; or 
 </section><section><number>d</number> relates to information which would cause unwarranted invasion of the 
  privacy of any person. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Severability.-</title>
<section><number>1</number> If a request for access to information 
is rejected on the ground that it is in relation to information which is 
exempted from disclosure, then notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, 
access may be given to that part of the record which does not obtain any 
information that is exempted from disclosure under this Act and which can 
reasonably be severed from any part that contains exempted information. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where access is granted to a part of the record in accordance with 
sub-section (1), the person making the request shall be informed,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that only part of the record requested, after severance of the record 
  containing information which is exempted from disclosure, is being furnished; 
  and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> of the provisions of the Act under which the severed part is exempted 
  from disclosure. </subsection>
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Third party information.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where a public authority 
intends to disclose any information or record, or part thereof, on a request 
made under this Act which relates to, or has been supplied by a third party and 
has been treated as confidential by that third party, the Public Information 
Officer shall, within twenty-five days from the receipt of a request, give 
written notice to such third party of the request and of the fact that the 
public authority intends to disclose the information or record, or part thereof: 

 Provided that except in the case of trade or commercial secrets protected by 
law, disclosure may be allowed if the public interest in disclosure outweighs in 
importance any possible harm or injury to the interests of such third party. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a notice is given by the Public Information Officer under 
sub-section (1) to a third party in respect of any information or record or part 
thereof, the third party shall, within twenty days from the date of issuance of 
notice, be given the opportunity to make representation against the proposed 
disclosure. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, the Public Information 
Officer shall, within sixty days after receipt of the request under section 6, 
if the third party has been given an opportunity to make representation under 
sub-section (2), make a decision as to whether or not to disclose the 
information or record or part thereof and give in writing the notice of his 
decision to the third party. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A notice given under sub-section (3) shall include a statement that the 
third party to whom the notice is given is entitled to prefer an appeal against 
the decision under section 12.12.Appeals. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Appeals.- </title>Any person aggrieved by a decision of the 
Public Information Officer may, within thirty days of receipt of such decision, 
prefer an appeal to such authority as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that such authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the 
said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time. 
 A second appeal against the decision under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> shall lie within 
thirty days of such decision, to the Central Government or the State Government 
or the competent authority, as the case may be: 
 Provided that the Central Government or the State Government or the competent 
authority, as the case may be, may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the 
said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time. 
 The appeals referred to in sub-sections (1) and (2) shall be disposed of 
within thirty days of the receipt of such appeals or within such extended 
period, as the case may be, for reasons to be recorded in writing. 
 If the decision of the Public Information Officer against which the appeal is 
preferred under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) also relates to information 
of third party, the appellate authority shall give a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard t that party. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.- </title>No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule 
made there under. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Act to have overriding effect.- </title>The provisions of this 
Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in the Official Secrets Act, 1923 (19 of 1923), and any other law for the time 
being in force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other 
than this Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Bar of jurisdiction of courts.-</title>No court shall entertain 
any suit, application or other proceeding in respect of any order made under 
this Act and no such order shall be called in question otherwise than by way of 
an appeal under this Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Act not to apply to certain organizations.- </title>Nothing 
contained in this Act shall apply to the intelligence and security 
organisations, specified in the Schedule, being organisations established by the 
Central Government or any information furnished by such organisations to that 
Government. 
 The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend 
the Schedule by including therein any other intelligence or security 
organization established by that Government or omitting there rom any 
organization already specified there n and on the publication of such 
notification, such organisation shall be deemed to be included in or, as the 
case may be, omitted from the Schedule. 
 Every notification issued under sub-section (2) shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament. 
 Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to such intelligence and security 
organisations which may be specified, by a notification in the Official Gazette, 
by a State Government from time to time. 
 Every notification issued under sub-section (4) shall be laid before the 
State Legislature. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Power to make rules by Central Government.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> intervals at which matters referred to in sub-clauses (i) to (vi) of 
  clause (b) of section 4 shall be published; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the fee payable under sub-section (1) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the authority before whom an appeal may be preferred under sub-section 
  (1) of section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Power to make rules by State Government.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out 
the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the fee payable under sub-section (1) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the authority before whom an appeal may be preferred 
  under sub-section (1) of section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
  prescribed: Provided that initially the rules shall be made by the Central 
  Government by notification in the Official Gazette. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Rule making power by competent authority.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
competent authority may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the fee payable under sub-section (1) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the authority before whom an appeal may be preferred under sub-section 
  (1) of section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed. 
</subsection>
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Laying of rules.- </title>Every rule made by the Central 
Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, 
the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule. 
 Every rule made under this Act by a State Government shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is notified, before the State Legislature. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Power to remove difficulties.- </title>If any difficulty arises 
in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by 
order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions necessary or 
expedient for removal of the difficulty: not inconsistent with the provisions of 
this Act s appear to it to be 
 Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two 
years from the date of the commencement of this Act. 
 Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is 
made, be laid before each House of Parliament. </article> 

  
 THE SCHEDULE 
 ( See section 16) 
 Intelligence and Security Organisations Established by the Central Government 
 <article><number>1</number> Intelligence Bureau. 
 </article><article><number>2</number> Research and Analysis Wing of the Cabinet Secretariat. 
 </article><article><number>3</number> Directorate of Revenue Intelligence. 
 </article><article><number>4</number> Central Economic Intelligence Bureau. 
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>