<act><title>THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
(PROCEDURE FOR CONDUCTING INQUIRY AGAINST A MEMBER) RULES, 19991 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Procedure for Conducting 
Inquiry Against a Member) Rules, 1999. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 
  1997); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Judge means a Judge of the Supreme Court appointed for conducting an 
  inquiry under rule 3; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expression used and not defined in these rules but defined in 
the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 1997), shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> The Judge to conduct inquiry. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Whenever the Central 
Government is of the opinion that there are reasonable grounds for making an 
inquiry against a member under sub-section (2) of section 7 of the Act, into 
truth of any imputation of acquisition of such financial or other interest as is 
likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a member or abuse of his 
position as to render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public 
interest, it may, after consulting the Chief Justice of India, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint a Judge for the purpose of conducting such 
inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notice of appointment of a Judge under sub-rule (1) shall also be given 
to such member. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Powers of the Judge. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Judge shall not be bound by 
the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but 
shall be guided by the principles of natural justice and shall have power to 
regulate his own procedure including the fixing of places and times of his 
enquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Judge shall have, for the purposes of discharging his functions under 
these rules, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
  on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
  Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document 
  or copy of such record or document from any office. </subsection>

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>