<act><tid>830564</tid>
<title>THE NATIONAL WATERWAY (ALLAHABAD- HALDIA STRETCH OF THE  
  GANGA- BHAGIRATHI- HOOGHLY RIVER) ACT <year>1982</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>1982</year>
[ 18th October, <year>1982</year>.]

An Act to provide for the declaration of the Allahabad- Haldia Stretch 
of the Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly river to be a national waterway and 
also to provide for the regulation and development of that river for 
purposes of shipping and navigation on the said waterway and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1150895</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1054690</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
National Waterway (Allahabad- Haldia Stretch of the Ganga- Bhagirathi-  
  Hooghly River) Act, <year>1982</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1260287</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1122342</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of a certain stretch of Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly 
river to be national waterway. The Allahabad- Haldia Stretch of the 
Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly river, the limits of which are specified in 
the Schedule, is hereby declared to be a national waterway.


</article>



<article><tid>1710045</tid>
<number>3</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union of Ganga- 
Bhagirathi- Hooghly river for certain purposes. It is hereby declared 
that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union should 
take under its control the regulation and development of Ganga- Bhagi- 
rathi- Hooghly river for purposes of shipping and navigation on the 
national waterway to the extend provided in the Inland Waterways Auth- 
ority of India Act, <year>1985</year>.
 1 27- 10- <year>1986</year>: Vide Notifn. No. s. 0 768 (E), dt. 27- 10- <year>1986</year>. 
 2 Subs. by Act 82 off <year>1985</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 27- 10- <year>1986</year>). 
 3 Omitted by Act 82 of <year>1985</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 27- 10- <year>1986</year>).


</article>



 </act>