<act><title>


The National Tax Tribunal (Salary, Allowances 
and Other Conditions of Service of the Officers 
and Employees) Rules, 20051</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>i</number> 
These rules may be called the National Tax Tribunal (Salary, Allowances and 
other Conditions of Service of the Officers and Exployees) Rules, 2005;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> They shall come into 
force on the date2 of 
their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “employees” means the employees of the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “officers” means the officer of the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal established under section 3 
of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Officers and other 
employees of the Tribunal.—The 
nature and categories of officers and employees of the Tribunal and the scales 
of pay attached thereto shall be as specified in the Schedule annexed hereto.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Conditions of 
service.—The 
conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal in the 
matter of pay, allowances, leave, joining time, joining time pay, provident 
fund, age of superannuation, pension and retirement benefits, medical facilities 
and other conditions of service, shall be regulated in accordance with such 
rules and regulations as are, from time to time, applicable to officers and 
employees of the Central Government belonging to Group ‘A’, Group ‘B’, Group ‘C’ 
and Group ‘D’, as the case may be, and drawing the corresponding scales of pay 
and posted at the same station.
</article><form>
 




The National Tax Tribunal (Salary, Allowances  

and Other Conditions of Service of the Officers  

and Employees) Rules, 2005
 


 
 




Schedule
 


(See rule 3)
 


 


S. No.     
  Name of Post                                                                                           
  Scale of pay
 


    A         
Officers
 


    1.         
Registrar                                                                                                
Rs. 12,000-375-16,500
 


    2.         
Deputy Registrar                                                                                    
Rs. 10,000-325-15,200
 


    3.         
Assistant Registrar                                                                                 
Rs. 7,450-225-11,500
 


    4.         
Private Secretary                                                                                    
Rs. 6,500-200-10,500
 


    B         
Other employees
 


    5.         
Personal Assistant                                                                                  
Rs. 5,500-175-9,000
 


    6.         
Head Clerk                                                                                              
Rs. 5,500-175-9,000
 


    7.         
Upper Division Clerk                                                                                
Rs. 4,000-100-6,000
 


    8.         
Lower Division Clerk                                                                                
Rs. 3,050-75-3,950-80-4,590
 


    9.         
Bench Clerk                                                                                             
Rs. 3,050-75-3,950-80-4,590
 


   10.        
Group D                                                                                                   
Rs. 2,610-60-2,910-65-3,300-70-4,000
 


                                                                                                                                
Rs. 2,550-55-2,660-60-3,200
 


   11.        
Driver                                                                                                       
Rs. 3,050-75-3,950-80-4,590
 


 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>