<act><title>


The Foreigners 
    Act, 1946</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Foreigners Act, 1946. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of 

    1[India] 

    2[***]. 
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act,—  
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>   
    “foreigner” means a person who is not a citizen of India;]  
 

2[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “prescribed” means 
    prescribed by orders made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “specified” means 
    specified by direction of a prescribed authority.  
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Power to make orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may by order1 make 
    provision, either generally or with respect to all foreigners or with 
    respect to any particular foreigner or any prescribed class or description 
    of foreigner, for prohibiting, regulating or restricting the entry of 
    foreigners into 

    2[India] or, their 
    departure therefrom or their presence or continued presence therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    orders made under this section may provide that the foreigner—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   shall not enter
    2[India], 
    or shall enter 
2[India] 
    only at such times and by such route and at such port or place and subject 
    to the observance of such conditions on arrival as may be prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   shall not depart 
    from 2[India], 
    or shall depart only at such times and by such route and from such port or 
    place and subject to the observance of such conditions on departure as may 
    be prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   shall not remain in
    2[India], 
    or in any prescribed area therein;  
 

3[(cc)   
    shall, if he has been required by order under this section not to remain in 
    India, meet from any resources at his disposal the cost of his removal from 
    India and of his maintenance therein pending such removal;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   shall remove 
    himself to, and remain in, such area in 
2[India] 
    as may be prescribed; tc 
    " (d) shall remove himself to, and remain in, such area in 
1[India] 
    as may be prescribed;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   shall comply with 
    such conditions as may be prescribed or specified— tc 
    " (e) shall comply with such conditions as may be prescribed or specified—" 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   requiring him to 
    reside in a particular place; tc 
    " (i) requiring him to reside in a particular place;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   imposing any 
    restrictions on his movements; tc 
    " (ii) imposing any restrictions on his movements;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   requiring him to 
    furnish such proof of his identity and to report such particulars to such 
    authority in such manner and at such time and place as may be prescribed or 
    specified; tc " 
    (iii) requiring him to furnish such proof of his identity and to report such 
    particulars to such authority in such manner and at such time and place as 
    may be prescribed or specified;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   requiring him to 
    allow his photograph and finger impressions to be taken and to furnish 
    specimens of his handwriting and signature to such authority and at such 
    time and place as may be prescribed or specified; tc 
    " (iv) requiring him to allow his photograph and finger impressions to be 
    taken and to furnish specimens of his handwriting and signature to such 
    authority and at such time and place as may be prescribed or specified;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   requiring him to 
    submit himself to such medical examination by such authority and at such 
    time and place as may be prescribed or specified; tc 
    " (v) requiring him to submit himself to such medical examination by such 
    authority and at such time and place as may be prescribed or specified;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   prohibiting him 
    from association with persons of a prescribed or specified description; tc 
    " (vi) prohibiting him from association with persons of a prescribed or 
    specified description;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>   prohibiting him 
    from engaging in activities of a prescribed or specified description; tc 
    " (vii) prohibiting him from engaging in activities of a prescribed or 
    specified description;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>   prohibiting him 
    from using or possessing prescribed or specified articles; tc 
    " (viii) prohibiting him from using or possessing prescribed or specified 
    articles;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ix</number>   otherwise 
    regulating his conduct in any such particular as may be prescribed or 
    specified; tc " 
    (ix) otherwise regulating his conduct in any such particular as may be 
    prescribed or specified;" 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   shall enter into a 
    bond with or without sureties for the due observance of, or as an 
    alternative to the enforcement of, any or all prescribed or specified 
    restrictions or conditions; tc 
    " (f) shall enter into a bond with or without sureties for the due 
    observance of, or as an alternative to the enforcement of, any or all 
    prescribed or specified restrictions or conditions;" 
 

4[(g)   
    shall be arrested and detained or confined;]  
 
and may make provision
    5[for 
    any matter which is to be or may be prescribed and] for such incidental and 
    supplementary matters as may, in the opinion of the Central Government, be 
    expedient or necessary for giving effect to this Act.
 


    5[(3) Any authority 
    prescribed in this behalf may with respect to any particular foreigner make 
    orders under clause (e) 

    6[or clause (f)] of 
    sub-section (2).]
  
  










 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>3A</number> Power to 
    exempt citizens of Commonwealth countries and other persons from application 
    of Act in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by order declare that all or any of the 
    provisions of this Act or of any order made thereunder shall not apply, or 
    shall apply only in such circumstances or with such exceptions or 
    modifications or subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
    order, to or in relation to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the citizens of any 
    such Commonwealth country as may be so specified; or tc 
    " (a) the citizens of any such Commonwealth country as may be so specified; 
    or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any other 
    individual foreigner or class or description of foreigner. tc 
    " (b) any other individual foreigner or class or description of foreigner." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of every order made under this section shall be placed on the table of 
    both Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made.]  
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Internees.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any foreigner (hereinafter referred to as an internee) in respect of whom 
    there is in force any order made under clause (g) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 3, directing that he be detained or confined, shall be detained or 
    confined in such place and manner and subject to such conditions as to 
    maintenance, discipline and the punishment of offences and breaches of 
    discipline as the Central Government may from time to time by order 
    determine.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any foreigner (hereinafter referred to as a person on parole) in respect of 
    whom there is in force an order under clause (e) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 3 requiring him to reside at a place set apart for the residence 
    under supervision of a number of foreigners, shall while residing therein, 
    be subject to such conditions as to maintenance, discipline and the 
    punishment of offences and breaches of discipline as the Central Government 
    may from time to time by order determine.  
 


    2[(3) No person 
    shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   knowingly assist an 
    internee or a person on parole to escape from custody or the place set apart 
    for his residence, or knowingly harbour an escaped internee or person on 
    parole, or tc " 
    (a) knowingly assist an internee or a person on parole to escape from 
    custody or the place set apart for his residence, or knowingly harbour an 
    escaped internee or person on parole, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   give an escaped 
    internee or person on parole any assistance with intent thereby to prevent, 
    hinder or interfere with the apprehension of the internee or the person on 
    parole. tc " (b) 
    give an escaped internee or person on parole any assistance with intent 
    thereby to prevent, hinder or interfere with the apprehension of the 
    internee or the person on parole." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Central Government may, by order, provide for regulating access to, and 
    the conduct of persons in, places in India where internees or persons on 
    parole are detained or restricted, as the case may be, and for prohibiting 
    or regulating the despatch or conveyance from outside such places to or for 
    internees or persons on parole therein of such articles as may be 
    prescribed.]  
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Change of name.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No foreigner who was in 

    1[India] on the date 
    on which this Act came into force shall, while in 

    1[India] after that 
    date, assume or use or purport to assume or use for any purpose any name 
    other than that by which he was ordinarily known immediately before the said 
    date.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where, after the date on which this Act came into force, any foreigner 
    carries on or purports to carry on (whether alone or in association with any 
    other person) any trade or business under any name or style, other than that 
    under which that trade or business was being carried on immediately before 
    the said date, he shall, for the purposes of sub-section (1), be deemed to 
    be using a name other than that by which he was ordinarily known immediately 
    before the said date.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    relation to any foreigner who, not having been in 

    1[India] on the date 
    on which this Act came into force, thereafter enters 

    1[India], 
    sub-sections (1) and (2) shall have effect as if for any reference in those 
    sub-sections to the date on which this Act came into force there were 
    substituted a reference to the date on which he first enters 

    1[India] thereafter.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    For the purposes of this section—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the expression 
    “name” includes a surname; and tc 
    " (a) the expression “name” includes a surname; and" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a name shall be 
    deemed to be changed if the spelling thereof is altered. tc 
    " (b) a name shall be deemed to be changed if the spelling thereof is 
    altered." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall apply to the assumption or use—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   of any name in 
    pursuance of a 
2[***] 
    licence or permission granted by the Central Government; or tc 
    " (a) of any name in pursuance of a 
2[***] 
    licence or permission granted by the Central Government; or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   by any married 
    woman, of her husband’s name. tc 
    " (b) by any married woman, of her husband’s name." 
  
  






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Obligations of masters of vessels, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The master of any vessel landing or embarking at a port in 

    1[India], passengers 
    coming to or going from that port by sea and the pilot of any aircraft 
    landing or embarking at any place in 

    1[India], passengers 
    coming to or going from that place by air, shall furnish to such person and 
    in such manner as may be prescribed a return giving the prescribed 
    particulars with respect to any passengers or members of the crew, who are 
    foreigners.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any District Magistrate and any Commissioner of Police or, where there is no 
    Commissioner of Police, any Superintendent of Police may, for any purpose 
    connected with the enforcement of this Act or any order made thereunder, 
    require the master of any such vessel or the pilot of any such aircraft to 
    furnish such information as may be prescribed in respect of passengers or 
    members of the crew on such vessel or aircraft, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any passenger on such vessel or such aircraft and any member of the crew of 
    such vessel or aircraft shall furnish to the master of the vessel or the 
    pilot of the aircraft, as the case may be, any information required by him 
    for the purpose of furnishing the return referred to in sub-section (1) or 
    for furnishing the information required under sub-section (2).  
 


    2[(4) If any 
    foreigner enters 

    1[India] in 
    contravention of any provision of this Act or any order made thereunder, the 
    prescribed authority may, within two months from the date of such entry, 
    direct the master of the vessel or the pilot of the aircraft on which such 
    entry was effected or the owner or the agent of the owner of such vessel or 
    aircraft, to provide, to the satisfaction of the said authority and 
    otherwise than at the expense of Government, accommodation on a vessel or 
    aircraft for the purpose of removing the said foreigner from India.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    The master of any vessel or the pilot of any aircraft which is about to 
    carry passengers from a port or place in India to any destination outside 
    India, or the owner or the agent of the owner of any such vessel or aircraft 
    shall, if so directed by the Central Government and on tender of payment 
    therefor at the current rates, provide on the vessel or aircraft 
    accommodation to such port or place outside India, being a port or place at 
    which the vessel or aircraft is due to call, as the Central Government may 
    specify, for any foreigner ordered under section 3 not to remain in India 
    and for his dependents, if any, travelling with him.]  
 


    3[(6)] For the 
    purposes of this section—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “master of a 
    vessel” and “pilot of any aircraft” shall include any person authorised by 
    such master or pilot as the case may be, to discharge on his behalf any of 
    the duties imposed on him by this section; tc 
    " (a) “master of a vessel” and “pilot of any aircraft” shall include any 
    person authorised by such master or pilot as the case may be, to discharge 
    on his behalf any of the duties imposed on him by this section;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “passenger” means 
    any person not being a bona fide member of the crew, travelling or 
    seeking to travel on a vessel or aircraft. tc 
    " (b) “passenger” means any person not being a bona fide member of 
    the crew, travelling or seeking to travel on a vessel or aircraft." 
  
  







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Obligation of hotel keepers and others to furnish particulars.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be the duty of the keeper of any premises whether furnished or 
    unfurnished where lodging or sleeping accommodation is provided for reward, 
    to submit to such person and in such manner such information in respect of 
    foreigners accommodated in such premises, as may be prescribed.  
 

    Explanation.—The 
    information referred to in this sub-section may relate to all or any of the 
    foreigners accommodated at such premises and may be required to be submitted 
    periodically or at any specific time or occasion.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every person accommodated in any such premises shall furnish to the keeper 
    thereof a statement containing such particulars as may be required by the 
    keeper for the purpose of furnishing the information referred to in 
    sub-section (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The keeper of every such premises shall maintain a record of the information 
    furnished by him under sub-section (1) and of the information obtained by 
    him under sub-section (2) and such record shall be maintained in such manner 
    and preserved for such period as may be prescribed, and shall at all times 
    be open to inspection by any police officer or by a person authorised in 
    this behalf by the District Magistrate.  
 


    2[(4) If in any area 
    prescribed in this behalf the prescribed authority by notice published in 
    such manner as may in the opinion of the authority be best adapted for 
    informing the persons concerned so directs, it shall be the duty of every 
    person occupying or having under his control any residential premises to 
    submit to such person and in such manner such information in respect of 
    foreigners accommodated in such premises as may be specified; and the 
    provisions of sub-section (2) shall apply to every person accommodated in 
    any such premises.]
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>7A</number> Power to 
    control places frequented by foreigners.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The prescribed authority may, subject to such conditions as may be 
    prescribed, direct the owner or person having control of any premises used 
    as a restaurant or as a place of public resort or entertainment or as a club 
    and frequented by foreigners—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to close such 
    premises either entirely or during specified periods, or tc 
    " (a) to close such premises either entirely or during specified periods, 
    or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to use or permit 
    the use of such premises only under such conditions as may be specified, or tc 
    " (b) to use or permit the use of such premises only under such conditions 
    as may be specified, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to refuse admission 
    to such premises either to all foreigners or to any specified foreigner or 
    class of foreigners. tc 
    " (c) to refuse admission to such premises either to all foreigners or to 
    any specified foreigner or class of foreigners." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person to whom any direction has been given under sub-section (1) shall not, 
    while such direction remain in force, use or permit to be used any other 
    premises for any of the aforesaid purposes, except with the previous 
    permission in writing of the prescribed authority and in accordance with any 
    conditions which that authority may think fit to impose.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any person to whom any direction has been given under sub-section (1) and 
    who is aggrieved thereby may, within thirty days from the date of such 
    direction, appeal to the Central Government; and the decision of the Central 
    Government in the matter shall be final.]
 

 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Determination of nationality.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a foreigner is recognized as a national by the law of more than one 
    foreign country or where for any reason it is uncertain what nationality if 
    any is to be ascribed to a foreigner, that foreigner may be treated as the 
    national of the country with which he appears to the prescribed authority to 
    be most closely connected for the time being in interest or sympathy or if 
    he is of uncertain nationality, of the country with which he was last so 
    connected:  
 

    Provided that where a foreigner acquired a nationality by birth, he shall, 
    except where the Central Government so directs either generally or in a 
    particular case, be deemed to retain that nationality unless he proves to 
    the satisfaction of the said authority that he has subsequently acquired by 
    naturalization or otherwise some other nationality and still recognized as 
    entitled to protection by the Government of the country whose nationality he 
    has so acquired.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    decision as to nationality given under sub-section (1) shall be final and 
    shall not be called in question in any Court:  
 

    Provided that the Central Government, either of its own motion or on an 
    application by the foreigner concerned, may revise any such decision.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Burden of proof.—If 
    in any case not falling under section 8 any question arises with reference 
    to this Act or any order made or direction given thereunder, whether any 
    person is or is not a foreigner of a particular class or description the 
    onus of proving that such person is not a foreigner or is not a foreigner of 
    such particular class or description, as the case may be, shall, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 
    1872), lie upon such person.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Power to exempt from application of Act.—[Rep. 
    by the Foreigners Laws (Amendment) Act, 1957 (11 of 1957), sec. 7 (w.r.e.f.
    19-1-1957)].  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Power to give effect to orders, directions, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any authority empowered by or under or in pursuance of the provisions of 
    this Act to give any direction or to exercise any other power, may, in 
    addition to any other action expressly provided for in this Act, take, or 
    cause to be taken such steps and use, or cause to be used, such force as 
    may, in its opinion, be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with 
    such direction or for preventing or rectifying any breach thereof, or for 
    the effective exercise of such power, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any police officer may take such steps and use such force as may, in his 
    opinion, be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with any order made 
    or direction given under or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or 
    for preventing or rectifying any breach of such order or direction.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The power conferred by this section shall be deemed to confer upon any 
    person acting in exercise thereof a right of access to any land or other 
    property whatsoever.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Power to delegate authority.—Any 
    authority upon which any power to make or give any direction, consent or 
    permission or to do any other act is conferred by this Act or by any order 
    made thereunder may, unless express provision is made to the contrary, in 
    writing authorise, conditionally or otherwise, any authority subordinate to 
    it to exercise such power on its behalf, and thereupon the said subordinate 
    authority shall, subject to such conditions as may be contained in the 
    authorisation, be deemed to be the authority upon which such power is 
    conferred by or under this Act.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number> Attempts, etc., to 
      contravene the provisions of this Act, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person who attempts to 
      contravene, or abets or attempts to abet, or does any act preparatory to, 
      a contravention of, the provisions of this Act or of any order made or 
      direction given thereunder, or fails to comply with any direction given in 
      pursuance of any such order, shall be deemed to have contravened the 
      provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section> <number>2</number> Any person who, 
      knowing or having reasonable cause to believe that any other person has 
      contravened the provisions of this Act or of any order made or direction 
      given thereunder, gives that other person any assistance with intent 
      thereby to prevent, hinder or otherwise interfere with his arrest, trial 
      or punishment for the said contravention shall be deemed to have abetted 
      that contravention.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> The master of any vessel or 
      the pilot of any aircraft, as the case may be, by means of which any 
      foreigner enters or leaves 1[India] in contravention of any 
      order made under, or direction given in pursuance of, section 3 shall, 
      unless he proves that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the said 
      contravention, be deemed to have contravened this Act.
  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>1[<number>14</number> Penalty for 
      contravention of provisions of the Act, etc.—Whoever—  
 <section><number>a</number>   remains in any area in India for a 
      period exceeding the period for which the visa was issued to him; tc " (a) 
    remains in any area in India for a period exceeding the period for which the 
    visa was issued to him;" 
 </section><section><number>b</number>   does any act in violation of the 
      conditions of the valid visa issued to him for his entry and stay in India 
      or any part thereunder; tc 
    " (b) does any act in violation of the conditions of the valid visa issued 
    to him for his entry and stay in India or any part thereunder;" 
 </section><section><number>c</number>   contravenes the provisions of this 
      Act  or of any order made thereunder or any direction given in 
      pursuance of this Act or such order for which no specific punishment is 
      provided under this Act, tc 
    " (c) contravenes the provisions of this Act  or of any order made 
    thereunder or any direction given in pursuance of this Act or such order for 
    which no specific punishment is provided under this Act," 
 shall be punished with 
      imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and shall also be 
      liable to fine; and if he has entered into a bond in pursuance of clause 
      (f) of sub-section (2) of section 3, his bond shall be forfeited, and any 
      person bound thereby shall pay the penalty thereof or show cause to the 
      satisfaction of the convicting Court why such penalty should not be paid 
      by him.  
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
      section, the expression “visa” shall have the same meaning as assigned to 
      it under the Passport (Entry into India) Rules, 1950 made under the 
      Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920 (34 of 1920).]
  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>14A</number> Penalty for entry in restricted areas, etc.—Whoever—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   enters into any 
    area in India, which is restricted for his entry under any order made under 
    this Act, or any direction given in  pursuance thereof, without obtaining a 
    permit from the authority, notified by the Central Government in the 
    Official Gazette, for this purpose or remains in such area beyond the period 
    specified in such permit for his stay; or tc 
    " (a) enters into any area in India, which is restricted for his entry under 
    any order made under this Act, or any direction given in  pursuance thereof, 
    without obtaining a permit from the authority, notified by the Central 
    Government in the Official Gazette, for this purpose or remains in such area 
    beyond the period specified in such permit for his stay; or" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   enters into or 
    stays in any area in India without the valid documents required for such 
    entry or for such stay, as the case may be, under the provisions of any 
    order made under this Act or any direction given in pursuance thereof, tc 
    " (b) enters into or stays in any area in India without the valid documents 
    required for such entry or for such stay, as the case may be, under the 
    provisions of any order made under this Act or any direction given in 
    pursuance thereof," 
 
shall 
    be punished with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two 
    years, but may extend to eight years and shall also be liable to fine which 
    shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but may extend to fifty thousand 
    rupees; and if he has entered into a bond in pursuance of clause (f) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 3, his bond shall be forfeited, and any person 
    bound thereby shall pay the penalty thereof, or show cause to the 
    satisfaction of the convicting Court why such penalty should not be paid by 
    him.]
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>14B</number> Penalty for using forged passport.—Whoever 
    knowingly uses a forged passport for entering into India or remains therein 
    without the authority of law for the time being in force shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two years, but may 
    extend to eight years and shall also be liable to fine which shall not be 
    less then ten thousand rupees but may extend to fifty thousand rupees.]
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>14C</number> Penalty for abetment.—Whoever 
    abets any offence punishable under section 14 or section 14A or section 14B 
    shall, if the act abetted is committed in consequence of the abetment, be 
    punished with the punishment provided for the offence.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   an act or offence 
    is said to be committed in consequence of the abetment, when it is committed 
    in consequence of the instigation, or in pursuance of the conspiracy, or 
    with the aid which constitutes the offence;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   the expression 
    “abetment” shall have the same meaning as assigned to it under section 107 
    of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).] 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>15</number> Protection to persons 
      acting under this Act.—No suit prosecution or other 
      legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in 
      good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Application of other laws not barred.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provisions of the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (16 of 1939), the 
    Indian Passport Act, 1920 (34 of 1920), and of any other enactment for the 
    time being in force.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Repeals.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1950 (35 of 1950) sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f.
    19-4-1950)].  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 16 of 2004, sec. 2, 
    for section 14 (w.e.f. 20-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 16 of 2004, sec. 2, 
    for section 14 (w.e.f. 20-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by Act 16 of 2004, sec. 2, 
    for section 14 (w.e.f. 20-2-2004).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>