<act><title>


    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
    Sites and Remains Rules, 19591</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and 
    Remains Rules, 1959. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    extend to the whole of India, but rules 24, 25, 27, 28, 29 and 30 shall not 
    apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They 
    shall come into force on the 15th day of October, 1959. 


 



</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number> “construction” of any structure includes additions to or
alterations of an existing building; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “copying”, together with its grammatical variations and cognate
expressions, means the preparation of copies by drawing or by photography or by
mould or by squeezing and includes the preparation of a cinematographic film 1[and
video film] with the aid of a hand-camera which is capable of taking films of
not more than eight millimeters and which does not require the use of a stand or
involve any special previous arrangement; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number> “filming”, together with its grammatical variations and cognate
expressions, means the preparation of a cinematographic film 2[including
video film] with the aid of a camera which is capable of taking films of more
than eight millimeters and which requires the use of a stand or involves other
special previous arrangements; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “Form”
means a Form set out in the Third Schedule; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number> “mining operation” means by operation for the purpose of
searching for or obtaining minerals and includes quarrying, excavating, blasting
and any operation of a like nature; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number> “prohibited area” or “regulated area” means an area near or
adjoining a protected monument which the Central Government has, by notification
in the Official Gazette, declared to be a prohibited area, from as the case may
be, a regulated area, for purposes of mining operation or construction or both; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number> “Schedule “ means a Schedule to these rules; and 
 
 


 </section><section>     
<number>h</number> “section”
means a section of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains
Act, 1958 (24 of 1958).
  



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Monuments governed by agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Access to protected monuments in respect of which an agreement has been 
    entered into between the owner and the Central Government under section 6, 
    or in respect of which an order has been made by that Government under 
    section 9, shall be governed by the provisions of the agreement or, as the 
    case may be, the order; and nothing in rule 4, 5, 6 or 7 shall be 
    constructed as affecting any such agreement or order. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of the relevant previsions of every such agreement or order shall be 
    exhibited in a conspicuous part of the monument concerned. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Parts of monuments not open.—The 
    Director-General may, by order, direct that 

    1[any protected 
    monument or any specified part thereof] shall not be open, permanently or 
    for a specified period, to any person other than an archaeological officer, 
    his agents, subordinates and workmen and any other Government servant on 
    duty at such port.
  
  




 



</article> 

   


 <article><number>5</number>
Monuments when kept open.—
<section><number>1</number>
The protected monuments specified in the First Schedule shall remain open during
the hours specified against them in that Schedule; protected monuments which are
not so specified and to which neither rule 3 nor rule 4 applies shall remain
open from sunrise to sunset:
 


 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided
that an archaeological officer, or any officer of the Archaeological Survey of
India authorised by him in this behalf may, by notice to be exhibited in a
conspicuous part of a protected monument, direct that a protected monument or
part thereof shall,—
 


 <subsection>
<number>i</number> Be kept open beyond the
said period; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> Be closed temporarily for
such period as may be specified by the notice]. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Nothing in this rule or in rule 6 shall apply to an archaeological officer, his
agents, subordinates and workman or to any other Government servant on duty at a
protected monuments.  


   




</section></article> 

  
 
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> Entrance fee. </title>—No person above 
the age of 15 years shall enter into a protected monument or part thereof:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> specified as category ‘A' monuments in Part I of the Second 
  Schedule, except on payment of fees as under: 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> Citizens of India and visitors of SAARC ( 
    Bangladesh , Nepal , Bhutan , Sir Lanka , Pakistan , Maldives and 
    Afghanistan ) and BIMSTEC Countries ( Bangladesh , Nepal , Bhutan , Sri 
    Lanka , Thailand and Myanmar ).—Rs. 10 per head] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> others.......Rs. 250 per head. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> specified as category ‘B' monuments in Part II of the Second 
  Schedule, except on payment of fees as under: 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> Citizens of India and visitors of SAARC ( 
    Bangladesh , Nepal , Bhutan , Sir Lanka , Pakistan , Maldives and 
    Afghanistan ) and BIMSTEC Countries ( Bangladesh , Nepal , Bhutan , Sri 
    Lanka , Thailand and Myanmar ).—Rs. 5 per head] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> others.......Rs. 100 per head.] 
</subsection></section>





 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Citizens of India – Rs. 10 per head; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Others – US $ 5 or Indian Rs. 250 per head. 
    </section>
 <section><number>b</number> Specified as category B monuments in Part II of 
  the Second Schedule, except on payment as follows:— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Citizens of India – Rs. 5 per head; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Others – US $ 2 or Indian Rs. 100 per head. 
  </subsection></section>





</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Holding of meetings, etc. in monuments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No protected monuments shall be used for the purpose of holding any meeting, 
    reception, party, conference or entertainment except under and in accordance 
    with a permission in writing granted by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing in sub-rule (1) shall apply to any meeting, reception, party, 
    conference or entertainment which is held in pursuance of a recognised 
    religious usage or custom. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Prohibition of certain acts within 
      monuments.—No person shall within a protected 
      monument,— 
 <section><number>a</number>    do any act 
      which causes or is likely to cause damage or injury to any part of the 
      monument; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>    discharge 
      any fire-arms; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>    cook or 
      consume food except in areas, if any, permitted to be used for that 
      purpose; or
 </section><section><number>d</number>    hawk or sell 
      any goods or wares or canvass any custom for such goods or wares or 
      display any advertisement in any form or show a visitor round for monetary 
      consideration except under the authority of, or under and in accordance 
      with the conditions of a licence granted by, an archaeological officer; 
      or
 </section><section><number>e</number>    beg for 
      alms; or
 </section><section><number>f</number>    violate any 
      practice, usage or custom applicable to or observed in the monument; 
      or
 </section><section><number>g</number>    bring, for 
      any purpose other than the maintenance of the monument,—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    any animal 
      or,
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    any vehicle 
      except in areas reserved for the parking thereof.
  
  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Penalty.—Whoever—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    unlawfully enters any protected 
    monument or part thereof at a time when, under these rules, it is not to be 
    kept open, or
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    unlawfully enters any protected 
    monument in respect of which an order has been made under rule 5, or
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    contravenes any of the provisions of 
    rule 6 or 7 or rule 8, shall be punishable with fine which may be extended 
    to five hundred rupees.
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Permission required for construction, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall undertake any construction or mining operation with a 
    protected area except under and in accordance with a permission granted in 
    this behalf by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every application for permission under sub-rule (1) shall be made to the 
    Central Government in Form I at least three months before the date of 
    commencement of the construction or operation. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Licence required for excavation.—No 
    person other than an archaeological officer or an officer authorised by him 
    in this behalf shall undertake any excavation for archeological purposes in 
    any protected area except under and in accordance with the terms and 
    conditions of a licence granted under rule 13. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Applications for licence.—Every 
    application for licence shall be in Form II and be made to the 
    Director-General at least three months before the proposed date of the 
    commencement for the excavation operations.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Grant or refusal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of an application under rule 12, the Director-General may grant a 
    licence in Form III if he is satisfied that, having regard to the status of 
    the applicant, the competence of the Director of the excavation operations, 
    the adequacy of the staff to be employed and other relevant factors, the 
    licence may be granted to the applicant:
 
Provided 
    that no licence shall be granted unless the applicant has furnished security 
    of such amount not exceeding rupees ten thousand as the Director- General 
    may, having regard to the circumstances of each case, require. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director-General, by order may, for reasons to be recorded in writing refuse 
    to grant a licence in any particular case. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Period of licence.—Every 
    licence shall be in force for such period not exceeding three years as may 
    be specified in the licence: 
 
Provided 
    that the Director-General may, on application made to him at least one month 
    before the expiry of a licence, extend its period by one year at a time so 
    that the aggregate period does not exceed five years.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number>
Cancellation of licence.—The Director General may, by order, cancel a 
    licence granted under rule 13 if he is satisfied that the conduct of the 
    excavation operations has not been satisfactory or in accordance with the 
    conditions of the licence, or if any further security demanded under rule 18 
    has not been deposited within the specified time:
 
Provided 
    that no licence shall be cancelled unless the licensee has been given an 
    opportunity to make his objections.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Conditions of licence.—Every 
    licence shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the licence shall not be transferable;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the licensee shall give to the 
    Director-General, the Collector and the owner of the land to be excavated at 
    least fifteen days’ notice in writing of the commencement of the excavation 
    operations;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the licensee shall produce the licence 
    before the District Magistrate or the District Superintendent of Police 
    concerned or an archaeological officer, if so required;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    the excavation operations shall be 
    conducted under the supervision, of the Director named in the licence who 
    shall be present at the excavation operations for at least three‑fourths of 
    the period of the operations;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    the licensee shall not, without the 
    permission of the Director General, dismantle or disturb any structures 
    found during the excavation operations and shall make adequate arrangements 
    for the safety of such structures and of the excavated antiquities till they 
    are taken charge of by the Director-General;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    the licensee shall not subject any 
    antiquities recovered during the excavation operations to any chemical or 
    electrolytic process of cleaning without the written permission of the 
    Director-General;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    an archaeological officer or his 
    representative may inspect the excavation operations or any antiquities 
    recovered during the operations and make notes on, or copy or film, the 
    excavated structures and antiquities;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    the licensee shall not discontinue the 
    excavation operation unless he has given at least fifteen days’ notice in 
    writing to the Director- General;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    at the conclusion of the excavation 
    operation, the licensee shall give notice in writing to the owner of the 
    land specifying the nature of the antiquities, if any, recovered during the 
    operations;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    the licensee shall, within three months 
    of the completion of the excavation operations submit to the 
    Director-General a summary report of the results of the excavation, and 
    where the operations are carried on for a period of more than three months 
    such report shall be submitted every quarter, and it shall be open to the 
    Director- General to publish the report in his reports or reviews; and
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    the licensee shall as soon as 
    practicable submit a report in Form IV to the Central Government through the 
    Director-General on the antiquities recovered during the excavation 
    operations.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Recovery from security.—The 
    Director-General may, by order, direct the deduction, from the security 
    furnished by the licensee under rule 13, of— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the value of any antiquities recovered 
    during the excavation operations and lost or destroyed while in the custody 
    of the licensee; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any compensation payable by the Central 
    Government under section 27 to the owner or occupier of the land excavated 
    by the licensee.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Demand of further security.—Where 
    during the currency of licence, any amount has been recovered under rule 17, 
    the Director-General may require the licensee, within such time as he may 
    specify, to deposit such further sum as security as is equivalent to the 
    amount so recovered. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Appeal.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of the Director-General passed under rule 13 or 
    rule 15 or rule, 17 may prefer an appeal to the Central Government; and the 
    decision of that Government on such appeal shall be final. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Return of security.—On 
    expiration or earlier cancellation of a licence, the security deposited by 
    the licensee or the balance thereof remaining after deduction of any amount 
    under rule 17 shall be returned to him. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Publication of the result of excavation.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in rule 16, the Director General shall not, without 
    the consent of the licensee, publish the results of the excavation unless 
    the licensee has failed to publish the results within the period specified 
    by the Director-General in this behalf. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Return of antiquities by a licensee.—The 
    Central Government may, by order, subject to such terms and conditions as 
    may be specified, permit the licensee to retain such of the antiquities 
    recovered during the excavation operations as may be specified therein: 
 
Provided 
    that human relics of historical importance and antiquities which, in the 
    opinion of the Central Government, are of national importance, shall not be 
    permitted to be retained by the licensee. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Penalty.—Whoever—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    unlawfully undertakes any excavation 
    for archaeological purposes in any protected area, or
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    contravenes any of the conditions of a 
    licence,
 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
    to five thousand rupees.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Intimation to the Central Government.—Every 
    State Government intending to undertake or authorise any person to undertake 
    any archaeological excavation or other like operation in any area which is 
    not a protected area shall intimate its intention to the Central Government 
    at least three months prior to the proposed date of the commencement of the 
    excavation or operation specifying the following details, namely:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    name, location and other details of the 
    site;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   nature of antiquities previously found;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   details of previously explorations, if 
    any;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   purpose of the excavation or operation;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   proposed extent of the excavation or 
    operation (a plan of the site in triplicate showing in red outline the 
    extent of the proposed excavation or operation should be attached);
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   proposed duration of the excavation or 
    operation;
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>   amount of the proposed expenditure on 
    the excavation or operation; and
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>  name and status of the Director of the 
    excavation or operation.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Approved by the Central Government.—After 
    considering the proposal, the Central Government may either approve it or 
    advise the State Government to modify it or to abandon it altogether. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Deputation of an archaeological officer.—The 
    Central Government may depute an archaeological officer to inspect the 
    excavation or operation while it is progress and render such advice as he 
    deems necessary. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Form of report by an archaeological officer.—Where, 
    as a result of an excavation made by an archaeological officer in any area 
    under section 21 or 22, any antiquities are discovered, the archaeological 
    officer shall, as soon as practicable, submit a report in Form V to the 
    Central Government through the Director-General on the antiquities recovered 
    during the excavation. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Application for moving antiquities.—Every 
    application for permission to move any antiquities or any class of 
    antiquities in respect of which a notification has been issued under 
    sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 25 shall be made in From VI to the 
    Director-General at least three months before the proposed date of the 
    moving. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Grant or refusal or permission.—On 
    receipt of an application under rule 28, the Director-General may, after 
    making such enquiry as he may deem necessary, grant permission for the 
    moving of all or any of the antiquities or, for reasons to the recorded, 
    refuse such permission.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Appeal.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of the Director-General under rule 29 may 
    prefer an appeal to the Central Government and the decision of the 
    Government on such appeal shall be final. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Notice or intention to declare a prohibited or regulated area.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> Before declaring an area near or adjoining a protected monument to be a 
    prohibited area or a regulated area for purposes of mining operation or 
    construction or both, the Central Government shall, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, give one month’s notice of its intention to do so, and a 
    copy of such notification shall be affixed in a conspicuous place near the 
    area. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such notification shall specify the limits of the area which is to be 
    so declared and shall also call for objection, if any, from interested 
    persons. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Declaration of prohibited or regulated area.—After 
    the expiry of one month from the date of the notification under rule 31 and 
    after considering the objections, if any, received within the said period, 
    the Central Government may declare, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    the area specified in the notification under rule 31, or any part of such 
    area, to be a prohibited area, or, as the case may be, a regulated area for 
    purposes of mining operation or construction or both. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Effect of declaration of prohibited or regulated area.—
No person other than an archaeological officer shall undertake any 
    mining operation or any construction,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in a prohibited, area, or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in a regulated area except under and in 
    accordance with the terms and conditions of a licence granted by the 
    Director-General.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Application for licence.—Every 
    person intending to undertake any mining operation or any construction in a 
    regulated area shall apply to the Director-General in Form VI at least three 
    months before the date of commencement of such operation or construction. 
 
  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Grant or refusal of licence. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an application under rule 34, the Director-General 
may grant a licence or, if he is satisfied that the licence asked for should not 
be granted, may for reasons to be recorded, refuse to grant a licence. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Every licence granted under sub-rule (1) shall be in Form 
VIII and be subject to the following conditions, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the licence shall not be transferable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> it shall be valid for the period specified therein; and 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any other condition relating to the manner of carrying out 
  the mining operation or the construction which the Director-General may 
  specify in the licence for ensuring the safety and appearance of, and the 
  maintenance of the approach and access to the protected monument. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Cancellation of licence.—The 
    Director-General may, by order, cancel a licence granted under rule 35 if he 
    is satisfied that any of its conditions had been violated: 
 
Provided 
    that no licence shall be cancelled unless the licensee has been given an 
    opportunity to make his objections. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Appeal.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of the Director-General made under rule 35 or 
    rule 36 may prefer an appeal to the Central Government; and the decision of 
    that Government on such appeal shall be final. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Removal of unauthorised buildings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by order, direct the owner or occupier of an 
    authorised building in a prohibited area or in a regulated area or of a 
    building or part thereof which has been constructed in contravention of any 
    of the conditions of a licence granted under rule 35 to remove such building 
    or part thereof within a period specified in that order. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the owner or occupier refuses or fails to comply with an order made under 
    sub‑rule (1), the Central Government may direct the District Magistrate to 
    cause the building or part thereof to be removed, and the owner or occupier 
    shall be liable to pay the cost of such‑removal. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Penalty.—Whoever— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    unlawfully undertakes any mining 
    operation or construction in a prohibited area or in a regulated area, or
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    contravenes any of the conditions of a 
    licence, or
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    fails or refuses to comply with an 
    order made under sub‑rule (1) of rule 38.
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment which 
    may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand 
    rupees, or with both.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Permission required for copying certain monuments.—The 
    Director-General may, by order, direct that no person other than an 
    archaeological officer or an officer authorised by an archaeological officer 
    in this behalf shall copy any specified monument or part thereof under and 
    in accordance with the terms and conditions of a permission in writing 
    granted by an archaeological officer. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Conditions of copying other monuments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person may copy a protected monument in respect of which no order 
    under rule 40 has been made. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing in sub‑rule (1) shall be construed as authorising any person other 
    than an archaeological officer or an officer authorised by him in this 
    behalf, while copying any such monument, to— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    bring into or use within the precincts 
    of such monument a camera-stand, stool, chair, table large drawing‑board, 
    easel or any such appliance, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    erect any scaffolding within such 
    precincts, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    use within such precincts any 
    artificial light other than a flash‑light synchronised with the exposure of 
    a camera, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    apply any extraneous matter, such as 
    water, oil, grease or any moulding material, on such monument or part 
    thereof, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    prepare a direct tracing or mould or 
    squeeze of such monument or part thereof, except under and in accordance 
    with the terms under and conditions of a permission in writing granted by an 
    archaeological officer.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>42</number>
Licence required for filming.—<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
No person other than archaeological officer or an officer authorised by him in
this behalf shall undertake any filming operation at a protected monument or
part thereof except under and in accordance with the terms and conditions of
licence granted under rule 44.
 


 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
Nothing in sub-rule (1) shall apply to any person undertaking video filming from
exterior of a protected monument except those specified in the Second Schedule
in respect of which video-filming shall be permitted on payment of rupees 25:
 


 Provided
it is for non-commercial purpose and does not involve any cast and use of a
stand or in any way interfere with customary and religious practices and work of
repairs.]
  




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Application for licence.—Every 
    person intending to undertake any filming operation at a protected monument 
    shall apply to the Director-General in Form IX at least three months before 
    the proposed date of the commencement of such operation. 
 
  


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>44</number>
Grant or refusal or licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
On receipt of an application under 
rule 43, the Director-General may grant a licence 1[on
payment of a fee of 
Rs. 5000 (Rupees five thousand) in case of professional and other agencies] or,
if he is satisfied that the licence asked for should not be granted, may, for
reasons to be recorded, refuse to grant a licence:
 


 Provided
that the Director-General shall not grant any licence to film the interior of
any protected monument, that is to say such part of any protected monument as is
covered by a roof of any description, except when the film is for the purpose of
education or of publishing the monument.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every licence granted under sub‑rule (1) shall be in Form X and be subject
to the following conditions, namely:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the
licence shall not be transferable and shall be valid for the period specified
therein; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> nothing
shall be done by the licensee or any member of his party which has, or may have,
the effect of exposing any part of the monument or attached lawn or garden to
the risk of damage; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the
filming operation shall be restricted to that part of the monument in respect of
which the licence has been granted; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> no
extraneous matter, such as water, oil, grease or the like shall be applied on
any part of the monument; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the
generating plant for electric power, wherever required, shall be placed away
from the monument or the attached lawn or garden; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>   
<number>f</number> the
filming operation shall not obstruct or hamper the movement of persons who may
lawfully be within the precincts of the monument; and
 </subsection><subsection>  
<number>g</number> any
other condition which the Director-General may specify in the licence.  


   





</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Cancellation of licence.—The 
    Director-General, by order, may, after giving notice to the licence, cancel 
    a licence granted under rule 44 if he is satisfied that any of its 
    conditions has been violated.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Appeal.— 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the Director-General made under rule 44 
    or rule 45 may prefer an appeal to the Central Government; and the decision 
    of that Government on such appeal shall be final.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Penalty.—Whoever 
    copies or films any protected monument or does any other act in 
    contravention of any provision of this chapter or of any permission or 
    licence granted thereunder shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
    five hundred rupees.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Manner of preferring an appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every appeal to the Central Government under the Ancient Monuments and 
    Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, or under these rules shall be in 
    writing and shall be preferred within one month of the date of receipt of 
    the order appealed against. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such appeal shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed 
    against. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Service of orders and notices.—Every 
    order or notice made or issued under the Ancient Monuments and 
    Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, or these rules shall—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of any order or notice of a 
    general nature or affecting a class of persons, be published in the Official 
    Gazette; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in the case of any order or notice 
    affecting a corporation or firm be served in the manner provided for the 
    service of summons in rule 2 of Order XXIX or rule 3 of Order XX, as the 
    case may be, in the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908; and
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    in the case of any order or notice 
    affecting an individual person, be served on such person—
 <subsection>
                       <number>i</number>    by delivering or 
    tendering it to the person concerned, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                     <number>ii</number>    if it cannot be 
    so delivered or tendered, by delivering or tendering it to any adult male 
    member of the family of such person or by affixing a copy thereof on the 
    outer door or some conspicuous part of the premises in which that person is 
    known to have last resided or carried on business or personally worked for 
    gain, or
 </subsection><subsection>
                    <number>iii</number>    by sending it by 
    registered post, acknowledgement due.
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  


</subsection></section></article><form>
 

THE ANCIENT MONUMENTS AND 
ARCHAEOLOGICAL SITES AND REMAINS RULES, 19591
 

 
 

Form VII 
 

Application for Licence for Mining 
Operation/Construction within a Regulated Area 
 

( Vide rule 34) 
 

1. Name and address of applicant (If the application is on 
behalf of an organisation, the name thereof should be given) 
 

2. Name of the monument near or adjoining which the regulated 
area is situated— 
 

Locality................................. 
District................................. 
State......................................... 
 

3. Nature and details of the proposed mining 
operation/construction in respect of which permission is sought. 
 

(In the case of mining operation, a site-plan in triplicate 
showing in red outline the extent of the operation in relation to the monument 
and the regulated area should be attached; and the details regarding the depth 
down to which the operation is to be carried out, the mode of the operation, the 
method of the muffling of sound, the kind and charge of blasting material and 
the depth and number of blast-holes to be fired at a time should be specified. 

 

In the case of construction, a site-plan in triplicate showing 
in red outline the location of the building in relation to the monument and the 
regulated area and the plan and elevation of the building should be attached; 
and the colour, external appearance and method of the screening of the building 
and depth down to which the soil will be excavated for the appurtenances of the 
building should be specified.) 
 

4. Purpose of the proposed mining operation/construction. 
 

5. Approximate duration and date of commencement of the proposed 
mining operation/construction. 
 

I declare that the above information is correct. I also 
undertake to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made thereunder. 
 

Seal of organisation 
 

Station.................... 
 

Date....................... 
 

Signature of the applicant 
 

(If the application is on behalf of an 
 
organisation, the signature should be  
that of the head of that 
organisation) 
 

---------- 
 

1. Vide S.O. 2307, dated 15th October, 1959, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th October, 1959. 

 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 



Third Schedule
 


Form I
 



Application for permission for construction/mining  

    operation with a Protected Area 
 


(Vide rule 10)
 

 
 


1. Name and address of applicant (If the 
    application is on behalf of an organisation, the name thereof should be 
    given)
 


2. Name of the protected area within which 
    construction/mining operation is proposed—
 


Locality................................... 
    District..................................... 
    State......................................
 


3. Nature and details of the proposed 
    construction/mining operation in respect of which permission is sought.
 


(In the case of construction, a site‑plan in 
    triplicate showing in red outline the location of the building in relation 
    to the protected area and the plan and elevation of the building should be 
    attached; and the colour, external appearance and method of the screening of 
    the building and the depth down to which the soil will be excavated for the 
    appurtenances of the building should be specified. 
 


In the case of mining operation, a site‑plan 
    in triplicate showing in red outline the extent of the operation in relation 
    to the protected area should be attached, and details, regarding the depth 
    down to which the operation is to be carried out, the mode of the operation, 
    the method of the muffling of sound, the kind and charge of blasting 
    material and the depth and number of blast‑holes to be fired at a time 
    should be specified.)
 


4. Purpose of the proposed construction/mining 
    operation.
 


5. Approximate duration and date of 
    commencement of the proposed construction/mining operation.
 


I declare that the above information is 
    correct. I also undertake to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monuments 
    and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made 
    thereunder.
 

 
 


Seal of the organisation
 

 
 



    Station........................                                                                 
 


 Signature of the applicant
 


Date.....................   
 


(If the application is on behalf of an  

    organisation, the signature should be  

    that of the head of the organisation.)
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 



Form X
 



Licence for Filming Operation at a protected Monument
 


(Vide rule 44)
 

 
 


Whereas................of................has 
    applied for a licence for filming operation at the protected monument known 
    as...........located at..............., Distict.............., 
    State.............., and has undertaken to observe the provisions of the 
    Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the 
    rules made thereunder, I,........, Director-General of Archaeology, do 
    hereby grant this licence under rule 44 of the said rules of 
    said............ for the carrying out of filming operation, as per script 
    and details of scenes attached hereto, in the following parts of the 
    monuments, namely: 
 


The licnece is granted subject to the 
    provisions of the said Act, and rules and is further subject to the 
    following conditions, namely:— 
 


The licnece is not transferable. It shall be 
    valid for............. commencing with day of.........19....../20......
 


Seal of the Department of Archaeology of the 
    Government of India
 


Station........................
 


Date...........................            
    
 


Signature of Director-General of Archaeology
    
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 


Form 
    II
 



Application for Licence to excavate in a Protected Area
 


(Vide rule 12)
 

 
 


1. Name and address of applicant (If the 
    application is on behalf of an institution, the name thereof should be 
    given)
 


2. Name of site—
 


                   
    Locality.................................. 
    District............................... 
    State....................................
 


3. Extent of the proposed excavation (a plan 
    of the site in triplicate showing in red outline the extent of the proposed 
    excavation should be attached).
 


4. Approximate duration and date of 
    commencement of the proposed excavation.
 


5. Approximate expenditure on the proposed 
    excavation.
 


6. Name and status of the Director of the 
    proposed excavation.
 


7. Details of photographic, surveying and 
    other equipments available for the proposed excavation.
 


I declare that the above information is 
    correct. I also undertake to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monuments 
    and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made 
    thereunder.
 

 
 


Seal of institution
 



    Station.....................                                                                 
    
 


Signature of the applicant
 


Date........................               
    
 


If the application is on behalf of an 
    institution, the  

    signature should be that of the head of the institution,  

    which term includes the Registrar of a University.)
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 



Form III
 



Licence for Excavation in a Protected Area
 


(Vide rule 13)
 

 
 


Whereas.............. has applied for a 
    licence for carrying out excavation operation in the protected area known as 
    ........... at..........., District............., State..........., and has 
    undertaken to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monuments and 
    Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made thereunder 
    and has further deposited the sum of Rs............. (Rupees...........only) 
    as required by the rules, I,..............., Director-General of 
    Archaeology, do hereby grant this licence under sub-rule (1) of rule 13 of 
    the said rules to the said......... to .........carry out excavation 
    operations in the area indicated in red outline on the plan attached hereto.
 


The licence is granted subject to the 
    provisions of the said Act and rules and is further subject to the 
    conditions that........ of............ shall be the Director of the 
    excavation.
 


The licence is not transferable. It shall be 
    valid for.........commencing with day of.......19......./20.........
 

 
 


Seal of the Department of Archaeology of the 
    Government of India.
 

 
 

 
 


Station..............     
 


Date....................    
 


Signature of the Director-
 


General of Archaeology
 


 
 


 
 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

Form IV
 


Report on antiquities excavated in a 
    Protected Area 

(Vide rule 16)
 


Name of 
    site....................................................................................................
 



    Locality..........................................................................................................
 



    District...........................................................................................................
 



    State.............................................................................................................
 


Report for the 
    period......................19........./20....... to 
    ....................19...../20.... 


 
 
 
Serial No.
 
Class of Antiquities
 
Materiel
 
Number of Antiquities (in the case of 
        potshreds, the approximate number should be stated)
 
Approximate Age
 
Remarks

 
 Complete
 Fragmentary

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  
  


 


Station............................. 

    Date...............................
 


Signature of Licensee

  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

Form IV
 


Report on antiquities excavated
    BY AN ARCHAELOGICAL 
    OFFICER
 

(void 
    rule 27)
 


Name of 
    site....................................................................................................
 



    Locality..........................................................................................................
 



    District...........................................................................................................
 



    State.............................................................................................................
 


Report for the 
    period......................19........./20....... to 
    ....................19...../20.... 


 
 
 
Serial No.
 
Class of Antiquities
 
Materiel
 
Number of Antiquities (in the case of 
        potshreds, the approximate number should be stated)
 
Approximate Age
 
Remarks

 
 Complete
 Fragmentary

 
   

 
  
  
  
  
  
  


 


Station............................. 

    Date...............................
 


Signature of Archaelogical Office
  


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 



    Form VI
 



Application for the moving of Antiquities
 


(Vide rule 28)
 

 
 


1. Name and address of applicant (If the 
    application is on behalf of an organisation, the name thereof should be 
    given)
 


2. Name of the place from which antiquites are 
    to be moved— 
 


  Locality................................... 
    District................................. 
    State......................................
 


3. Description of antiquities proposed to be 
    moved (Photographs showing details of the antiquities should be attached)
 


4. Approximate date of moving
 


5. Purpose of moving
 


6. Whether the antiquities or any of them are 
    objects of worship.
 

 
 


I declare that the above information is 
    correct.
 

 
 


Seal of the Orgnisation
 

 
 



    Station......................                                                                          
    
 


Date.........................              
    
 


Signature of applicant
 


(If the application is on behalf of an  

    Organisation, the signature should be  

    that of the head of that Organisation).
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 

THE ANCIENT MONUMENTS AND 
ARCHAEOLOGICAL SITES AND REMAINS RULES, 19591
 

 
 

Form VII 
 

Application for Licence for Mining 
Operation/Construction within a Regulated Area 
 

( Vide rule 34) 
 

1. Name and address of applicant (If the application is on 
behalf of an organisation, the name thereof should be given) 
 

2. Name of the monument near or adjoining which the regulated 
area is situated— 
 

Locality................................. 
District................................. 
State......................................... 
 

3. Nature and details of the proposed mining 
operation/construction in respect of which permission is sought. 
 

(In the case of mining operation, a site-plan in triplicate 
showing in red outline the extent of the operation in relation to the monument 
and the regulated area should be attached; and the details regarding the depth 
down to which the operation is to be carried out, the mode of the operation, the 
method of the muffling of sound, the kind and charge of blasting material and 
the depth and number of blast-holes to be fired at a time should be specified. 

 

In the case of construction, a site-plan in triplicate showing 
in red outline the location of the building in relation to the monument and the 
regulated area and the plan and elevation of the building should be attached; 
and the colour, external appearance and method of the screening of the building 
and depth down to which the soil will be excavated for the appurtenances of the 
building should be specified.) 
 

4. Purpose of the proposed mining operation/construction. 
 

5. Approximate duration and date of commencement of the proposed 
mining operation/construction. 
 

I declare that the above information is correct. I also 
undertake to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made thereunder. 
 

Seal of organisation 
 

Station.................... 
 

Date....................... 
 

Signature of the applicant 
 

(If the application is on behalf of an 
 
organisation, the signature should be  
that of the head of that 
organisation) 
 

---------- 
 

1. Vide S.O. 2307, dated 15th October, 1959, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th October, 1959. 

 

 </form><form>
 


THE AIR (PREVENTION AND Control of 

Pollution) (Union Territories)  

Rules, 1983
 



 


Form VIII
 


[See rule 18(1)]
 


Form of Notice
 


                  *(Here mention name and designation of the Authority)
 


Before*.....................................................Appellate Authority 
as constituted under section 31(1) of the Air (Prevention and Control of 
Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981).
 


In the matter of appeal No........................................./20.....filed 
under section 31 of the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 
of 1981) by Shri............. 
.......................................................................................................................................................
 


(here mention the name and address of the 
appellant)
 


Whereas Shri...................................................................................................................... 
 

(here mention the name and address of the appellant)
 


has filed before the Authority 
a Memorandum of appeal against the order................ 
dated..................passed by the Central Pollution Control under section 
20/21/22 of the Act.
 


And whereas under sub-section (4) of section 31 of the Act, this authority is 
required to give to the parties an opportunity of being heard. Now, therefore, 
please take notice that this authority has fixed.....................as date of 
hearing of the aforesaid appeal. The hearing shall take place 
at...................AM/PM on that date in the office of the Board 

1[or the Appellate Authority] at 
New Delhi. You are hereby called upon to appear before this Authority at the 
appointed time and date and place, either in person or through a duly authorised 
agent, and explain your case. Please take notice that failure on your part to 
appear on the day of hearing either in person or through authorised agent, 
without showing sufficient cause to the satisfaction of this Authority will make 
your appeal liable to be dismissed or decided ex-parte.
 


Given under the hand and seal of the Appellate Authority 
at..........................................
 


This................................................................day.........................................................................
 



</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Ancient Monuments and Archaeological  

    Sites and Remains Rules, 1959
 

 
 

 
 



    Form IX
 



Application for Licence of Filming Operation at  

    a Protected Monument
 


(Vide rule 43) 
 

 
 


1. Name and address of applicant. (If the 
    application is on behalf of an organisation, the name thereof should be 
    given) 
 


2. Name of the monument at which the proposed 
    filming operation is to be carried out. 
 



     Locality...................................District.....................................State...................................... 
 


3. Part of the monument proposed to be filmed. 
 


4. Nature and purpose of the proposed filming 
    operation and the context in which the monument is proposed to be filmed 
    (relevant extract of the script should be attached in triplicate and details 
    of the scenes to be filmed should be furnished in triplicate). 
 


5. Number of persons in the cast. 
 


6. Approximate duration and date of 
    commencement of proposed filming operation. 
 


I declare that the above information is 
    correct. I also undertake to observe the provisions of the Ancient Monument 
    and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, and the rules made 
    thereunder. 
 

 
 

 
 


Seal of the organisation
 



    Station........................                                                                     
    
 


Date...........................            
    
 


Signature of applicant
 


(If the application is on behalf of an  

    organisation, the signature should be  

    that of the head of the organisation).
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by S.O. 5002, dated
13th December, 1969.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Vide S.O. 2307, dated 15th October, 1959, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th 
October, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 112(E), dated 27th February, 2008, 
for rule 6 (w.e.f. 28-2-2008). Rule 6, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 164(E), dated 5th March, 2008, for 
item (i) of clause (a) (w.e.f. 5-3-2008). Item (i) of clause (a), before 
substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Vide  S.O. 2307, dated 15th October, 1959, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th October, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Rule 42 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 90, dated 30th
January, 1991 (w.e.f.-1-3-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins.
by G.S.R. 90, dated 30th January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-3-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 90, dated 30th January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-3-1991).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>