<act><title>

The Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ 
    Rights Act, 2001</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights 
    Act, 2001.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates may be appointed for 
    different provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to 
    the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming 
    into force of that provision.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Authority” means the Protection of 
    Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights Authority established under sub-section 
    (1) of section 3;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “benefit sharing”, in relation to a 
    variety, means such proportion of the benefit accruing to a breeder of such 
    variety or such proportion of the benefit accruing to the breeder from an 
    agent or a licensee of such variety, as the case may be, for which a 
    claimant shall be entitled as determined by the Authority under section 26;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “breeder” means a person or group of 
    persons or a farmer or group of farmers or any institution which has bred, 
    evolved or developed any variety;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Tribunal;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of 
    the Authority appointed under clause (a) of sub-section (5) of section 3;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “convention country” means a country 
    which has acceded to an international convention for the protection of plant 
    varieties to which India has also acceded, or a country which has a law on 
    protection of plant varieties on the basis of which India has entered into 
    an agreement for granting plant breeders’ right to the citizens of both the 
    countries;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “denomination”, in relation to a 
    variety or its propagating material or essentially derived variety or its 
    propagating material, means the denomination of such variety or its 
    propagating material or essentially derived variety or its propagating 
    material, as the case may be, expressed by means of letters or a combination 
    of letters and figures written in any language;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “essential characteristics” means such 
    heritable traits of a plant variety which are determined by the expression 
    of one or more genes of other heritable determinants that contribute to the 
    principal features, performance or value of the plant variety;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “essentially derived variety”, in 
    respect of a variety (the initial variety), shall be said to be essentially 
    derived from such initial variety when it—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    is predominantly derived from such 
    initial variety, or from a variety that itself is predominantly derived from 
    such initial variety, while retaining the expression of the essential 
    characteristics that result from the genotype or combination of genotype of 
    such initial variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    is clearly distinguishable from such 
    initial variety; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    conforms (except for the differences 
    which result from the act of derivation) to such initial variety in the 
    expression of the essential characteristics that result from the genotype or 
    combination of genotype of such initial variety;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>j</number>    “extant variety” means a variety 
    available in India which is—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    notified under section 5 of the Seeds 
    Act, 1966 (54 of 1966); or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    farmers’ variety; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a variety about which there is common 
    knowledge; or   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    any other variety which is in public 
    domain;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>k</number>    “farmer” means any person who—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    cultivates crops by cultivating the 
    land himself; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    cultivates crops by directly 
    supervising the cultivation of land through any other person; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    conserves and preserves, severally or 
    jointly, with any person any wild species or traditional varieties, or adds 
    value to such wild species or traditional varieties through selection and 
    identification of their useful properties;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>l</number>    “farmers’ variety” means a variety 
    which—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    has been traditionally cultivated and 
    evolved by the farmers in their fields; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    is a wild relative or land race of a 
    variety about which the farmers possess the common knowledge;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>m</number>    “Gene Fund” means the National Gene 
    Fund constituted under sub-section (1) of section 45;  
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    “Judicial Member” means a Member of the 
    Tribunal appointed as such under sub-section (l) of section 55 and includes 
    the Chairman;  
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>    “Member” means a Judicial Member or a 
    Technical Member of the Tribunal and includes the Chairman;  
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>    “member” means a member of the 
    Authority appointed under  
    clause (b) of sub-section (5) of section 3 and includes the member-secretary;  
 </section><section>
<number>q</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>r</number>    “propagating material” means any plant 
    or its component or part thereof including an intended seed or seed which is 
    capable of, or suitable for, regeneration into a plant;  
 </section><section>
<number>s</number>    “Register” means the National Register 
    of Plant Varieties referred to in section 13;  
 </section><section>
<number>t</number>    “Registrar” means a Registrar of Plant 
    Varieties appointed under sub-section (4) of section 12 and includes the 
    Registrar-General;  
 </section><section>
<number>u</number>    “Registrar-General” means the 
    Registrar-General of Plant Varieties appointed under sub-section (3) of 
    section 12;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    “Registry” means the Plant Varieties 
    Registry referred to in sub-section (1) of section 12;  
 </section><section>
<number>w</number>    “regulations” means the regulations 
    made by the Authority under this Act;  
     
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>    “seed” means a type of living embryo or 
    propagule capable of regeneration and giving rise to a plant which is true 
    to such type;  
 </section><section>
<number>y</number>    “Tribunal” means the Plant Varieties 
    Protection Appellate Tribunal established under section 54;  
 </section><section>
<number>z</number>    “Technical Member” meant a Member of 
    the Tribunal who is not a Judicial Member.  
 </section><section>
<number>za</number>    “variety” means a plant grouping 
    except micro organism within a single botanical taxon of the lowest known 
    rank, which can be—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    defined by the expression of the 
    characteristics resulting from a given genotype of that plant grouping;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    distinguished from any other plant 
    grouping by expression of at least one of the said characteristics; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    considered as a unit with regard to 
    its suitability for being propagated, which remains unchanged after such 
    propagation,  
 
and includes propagating material of such 
    variety, extant variety, transgenic variety, farmers’ variety and 
    essentially derived variety;  
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    establish an Authority to be known as the Protection of Plant Varieties and 
    Farmers’ Rights Authority for the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose of 
    properties, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the 
    said name sue and be sued.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The head 
    office of the Authority shall be at such place as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify and the Authority may, 
    with the previous approval of the Central Government, establish branch 
    offices at other places in India.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority shall consist of a Chairperson and fifteen members.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (a) The 
    Chairperson, to be appointed by the Central Government, shall be a person of 
    outstanding calibre and eminence with long practical experience to the 
    satisfaction of that Government especially in the field of plant varietal 
    research or agricultural development.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    members of the Authority, to be appointed by the Central Government, shall 
    be as follows, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Agriculture Commissioner, 
    Government of India, Department of Agriculture and Co-operation, New Delhi,
    ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the Deputy Director General in charge 
    of Crop Sciences, Indian Council of Agricultural Research, New Delhi, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    the Joint Secretary incharge of 
    Seeds, Government of India, Department of Agriculture and Co-operation, New 
    Delhi, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    the Horticulture Commissioner, 
    Government of India, Department of Agriculture and Co-operation, New Delhi, 
    ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    the Director, National Bureau of Plant 
    Genetic Resources, New Delhi, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>    one member not below the rank of Joint 
    Secretary to the Government of India, to represent the Department of 
    Bio-technology, Government of India, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>    one member not below the rank of 
    Joint Secretary to the Government of India to represent the Ministry of 
    Environment and Forests, Government of India, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>    one member not below the rank of 
    Joint Secretary to the Government of India to represent the Ministry of Law, 
    Justice and Company Affairs, Government of India, ex-officio;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ix</number>    one representative from a National or 
    State level farmers’ organisation to be nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>    one representative from a tribal 
    organisation to be nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xi</number>    one representative from the seed 
    industry to be nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>xii</number>    one representative from an 
    agricultural University to be nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiii</number>    one representative from a National 
    or State level women’s organisation associated with agricultural activities 
    to be nominated by the Central Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiv</number>    two representatives of State 
    Governments on rotation basis to be nominated by the Central Government.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The 
    Registrar-General shall be the ex officio member-secretary of the 
    Authority.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The term 
    of office of the Chairperson and the manner of filling the post shall be 
    such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Chairperson shall appoint a Standing Committee consisting of five members, 
    one of whom shall be a member who is a representative from a farmers 
    organisation, to advise the Authority on all issues including farmers’ 
    rights.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Chairperson shall be entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be 
    subject to such conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, 
    provident fund and other matters as may be prescribed. The allowances for 
    non-official members for attending the meetings of the Authority shall be 
    such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    Chairperson may resign his office by giving notice thereof in writing to the 
    Central Government and on such resignation being accepted, he shall be 
    deemed to have vacated his office.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> On the 
    resignation of the Chairperson or on the vacation of the office of the 
    Chairperson for any reason, the Central Government may appoint one of the 
    members to officiate as Chairperson till a regular Chairperson is appointed 
    in accordance with clause (a) of sub-section (5).  
  
























 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Meetings 
    of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The Authority 
    shall meet at such time and place and shall observe such rules of procedure 
    in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings [including the 
    quorum at its meetings and the transaction of business of its Standing 
    Committee appointed under sub-section (7) of section 3] as may be 
    prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Authority shall preside at the meetings of the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, for 
    any reason the Chairperson is unable to attend any meeting of the Authority, 
    any member of the Authority chosen by the members present shall preside at 
    the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    questions which come before any meeting of the Authority shall be decided by 
    a majority of the votes of the members of the Authority present and voting 
    and in the event of equality of votes, the Chairperson of the Authority or 
    in his absence, the person presiding shall have and exercise a second or 
    casting vote.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every 
    member who is in any way, whether directly, indirectly or personally, 
    concerned or interested in a matter to be decided at the meeting shall 
    disclose the nature of his concern or interest and after such disclosure, 
    the member concerned or interested, shall not attend that meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No act or 
    proceeding of the Authority shall be invalid merely by reason of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
    constitution of, the Authority; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any defect in the appointment of a 
    person acting as the Chairperson or a member of the Authority; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any irregularity in the procedure of 
    the Authority not affecting the merits of the case.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Committees of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Authority may appoint such committees as may be necessary for the efficient 
    discharge of its duties and performance of its functions under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    persons appointed as members of committee under sub-section (1) shall be 
    entitled to receive such allowances or fees for attending the meetings of 
    the committee as may be fixed by the Central Government.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Officers 
    and other employees of Authority.—Subject 
    to such control and restriction as may be prescribed, the Authority may 
    appoint such officers and other employees as may be necessary for the 
    efficient performance of its functions and the method of appointment, the 
    salary and allowances and other conditions of service of such other officers 
    and employees of the Authority shall be such as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Chairperson to be Chief Executive.—The 
    Chairperson shall be the Chief Executive of the Authority and shall exercise 
    such powers and perform such duties as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>8</number> General 
    functions of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> It 
    shall be the duty of the Authority to promote, by such measures as it thinks 
    fit, the encouragement for the development of new varieties of plants and to 
    protect the rights of the farmers and breeders.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    provisions, the measures referred to in sub-section (1) may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the registration of new extant plant 
    varieties subject to such terms and conditions and in the manner as may be 
    prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    developing characterisation and 
    documentation of varieties registered under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    documentation, indexing and cataloguing 
    of farmers’ varieties;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    compulsory cataloguing facilities for 
    all varieties of plants;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    ensuring that seeds of the varieties 
    registered under this Act are available to the farmers and providing for 
    compulsory licensing of such varieties if the breeder of such varieties or 
    any other person entitled to produce such variety under this Act does not 
    arrange for production and sale of the seed in the manner as may be 
    prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    collecting statistics with regard to 
    plant varieties, including the contribution of any person at any time in the 
    evolution or development of any plant variety, in India or in any other 
    country, for compilation and publication;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    ensuring the maintenance of the 
    Register.  
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Authentication of orders, etc., of Authority.—All 
    orders and decisions of the Authority shall be authenticated by the 
    signature of the Chairperson or any other member authorised by the Authority 
    in this behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Delegation.—The Authority may, by 
    general or special order in writing, delegate to the Chairperson, any member 
    or officer of the Authority subject to such conditions or limitations, if 
    any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions 
    (except the power to make regulations under section 95) under this Act as it 
    may deem necessary.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Power 
    of Authority.—In all proceedings 
    under this Act before the Authority or the Registrar—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Authority or the Registrar, as the 
    case may be, shall have all the powers of a civil court for the purposes of 
    receiving evidence, administering oaths, enforcing the attendance of 
    witnesses, compelling the discovery and production of documents and issuing 
    commissions for the examination of witnesses;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the Authority or the Registrar may, 
    subject to any rules made in this behalf under this Act, make such orders as 
    to cost as it considers reasonable and any such order shall be executable as 
    a decree of a civil court.  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Registry and offices thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall establish, for the purposes of this Act, a 
    Registry which shall be known as the Plant Varieties Registry.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The head 
    office of the Plant Varieties Registry shall be located in the head office 
    of the Authority, and for the purpose of facilitating the registration of 
    plant varieties, there may be established, at such places, as the Authority 
    may think fit, branch offices of the Registry.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Authority shall appoint a Registrar-General of Plant Varieties who shall be 
    entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such 
    conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and such 
    other matters as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority may appoint such number of Registrars as it thinks necessary for 
    registration of plant varieties under the superintendence and direction of 
    the Registrar-General under this Act and may make regulations with respect 
    to their duties and jurisdiction.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The term 
    of office and the conditions of service of the Registrars shall be such as 
    may be provided by regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Authority may, by notification in the Official Gazette, define the 
    territorial limits within which a branch office of the Registry may exercise 
    its functions.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> There 
    shall be a seal of the Plant Varieties Registry.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    National Register of Plant Varieties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purposes of this Act, a Register called the National Register of 
    Plant Varieties shall be kept at the head office of the Registry, wherein 
    shall be entered the names of all the registered plant varieties with the 
    names and addresses of their respective breeders, the right of such breeders 
    in respect of the registered varieties, the particulars of the denomination 
    of each registered variety, its seed or other propagating material along 
    with specification of salient features thereof and such other matters as may 
    be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the superintendence and direction of the Central Government, the Register 
    shall be kept under the control and management of the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> There 
    shall be kept at each branch office of the Registry a copy of the Register 
    and such other documents as the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, direct.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Application for registration.—Any 
    person specified in section 16 may make an application to the Registrar for 
    registration of any variety—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    of such genera and species as specified 
    under sub-section (2) of section 29; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    which is an extant variety; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    which is a farmers’ variety.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Registerable varieties.—
<section><number>1</number> A new 
    variety shall be registered under this Act if it conforms to the criteria of 
    novelty, distinctiveness, uniformity and stability.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), an extant variety 
    shall be registered under this Act within a specified period if it conforms 
    to such criteria of distinctiveness, uniformity and stability as shall be 
    specified under the regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of sub-sections (1) and (2) as the case may be, a new variety shall 
    be deemed to be—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    novel, if, at the date of filing of the 
    application for registration for protection, the propagating or harvested 
    material of such variety has not been sold or otherwise disposed of by or 
    with the consent of its breeder or his successor for the purposes of 
    exploitation of such variety—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in India, earlier than one year; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    outside India, in the case of trees or 
    vines earlier than six years, or, in any other case, earlier than four 
    years,   
 
 before the 
    date of filing such application:  
 
Provided that a trial of a new variety which 
    has not been sold or otherwise disposed of shall not affect the right to 
    protection:  
 
                             Provided further 
    that the fact that on the date of filing the application for registration, 
    the propagating or harvested material of such variety has become a matter of 
    common knowledge other than through the aforesaid manner shall not affect 
    the criteria of novelty for such variety;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    distinct, if it is clearly 
    distinguishable by at least one essential characteristic from any other 
    variety whose existence is a matter of common knowledge in any country at 
    the time of filing of the application.  
 
      Explanation.—For the removal of 
    doubts, it is hereby declared that the filing of an application for the 
    granting of a breeder’s right to a new variety or for entering such variety 
    in the official register of varieties in any convention country shall be 
    deemed to render that variety a matter of common knowledge from the date of 
    the application in case the application leads to the granting of the 
    breeder’s right or to the entry of such variety in such official register, 
    as the case may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    uniform, if subject to the variation 
    that may be expected from the particular features of its propagation it is 
    sufficiently uniform in its essential characteristics;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    stable, if its essential 
    characteristics remain unchanged after repeated propagation or, in the case 
    of a particular cycle of propagation, at the end of each such cycle.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A new 
    variety shall not be registered under this Act if the denomination given to 
    such variety—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    is not capable of identifying such 
    variety; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    consists solely of figures; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    is liable to mislead or to cause 
    confusion concerning the characteristics, value identity of such variety or 
    the identity of breeder of such variety; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    is not different from every 
    denomination which designates a variety of the same botanical species or of 
    a closely related species registered under this Act; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    is likely to deceive the public or 
    cause confusion in the public regarding the identity of such variety; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    is likely to hurt the religious 
    sentiments respectively of any class or section of the citizens of India; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    is prohibited for use as a name or 
    emblem for any of the purposes mentioned in section 3 of the Emblems and 
    Names (Protection of Improper Use) Act, 1950 (52 of 1950); or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    is comprised of solely or partly of 
    geographical name:  
 
Provided that 
    the Registrar may register a variety, the denomination of which comprises 
    solely or partly of a geographical name, if he considers that the use of 
    such denomination in respect of such variety is an honest use under the 
    circumstances of the case.  
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Persons 
    who may make application.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
    application for registration under section 14 shall be made by—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any person claiming to be the breeder 
    of the variety; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any successor of the breeder of the 
    variety; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any person being the assignee of the 
    breeder of the variety in respect of the right to make such application; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any farmer or group of farmers or 
    community of farmers claiming to be the breeder of the variety; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any person authorised in the prescribed 
    manner by a person specified under clauses (a) to (d) to make application on 
    his behalf; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any university or publicly funded 
    agricultural institution claiming to be the breeder of the variety.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application under sub-section (1) may be made by any of the persons referred 
    to therein individually or jointly with any other person.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Compulsory variety denomination.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application shall assign a single and distinct denomination to a 
    variety with respect to which he is seeking registration under this Act in 
    accordance with the regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall, having regard to the provisions of any international 
    convention or treaty to which India has become a party, make regulations 
    governing the assignment of denomination to a variety.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    denomination assigned to the variety does not satisfy the requirements 
    specified in the regulations, the Registrar may require the applicant to 
    propose another denomination within such time as may be specified by such 
    regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 
    1999), a denomination assigned to a variety shall not be registered as a 
    trade mark under that Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Form of 
    application.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    application for registration under section 14 shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    be with respect to a variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    state the denomination assigned to such 
    variety by the applicant;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    be accompanied by an affidavit sworn by 
    the applicant that such variety does not contain any gene or gene sequence 
    involving terminator technology;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    be in such form as may be specified by 
    regulations;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    contain a complete passport data of the 
    parental lines from which the variety has been derived along with the 
    geographical location in India from where the genetic material has been 
    taken and all such information relating to the contribution, if any, of any 
    farmer, village community, institution or organisation in breeding, evolving 
    or developing the variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    be accompanied by a statement 
    containing a brief description of the variety bringing out its 
    characteristics of novelty, distinctiveness, uniformity and stability as 
    required for registration;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    be accompanied by such fees as may be 
    prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    contain a declaration that the genetic 
    material or parental material acquired for breeding, evolving or developing 
    the variety has been lawfully acquired; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    be accompanied by such other 
    particulars as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided that 
    in case where the application is for the registration of farmers’ variety, 
    nothing contained in clauses (b) to (i) shall apply in respect of the 
    application and the application shall be in such form as may be prescribed;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    application referred to in sub-section (1) shall be filed in the office of 
    the Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where such 
    application is made by virtue of a succession or an assignment of the right 
    to apply for registration, there shall be furnished at the time of making 
    the application, or within such period after making the application as may 
    be prescribed, a proof of the right to make the application.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Test to 
    be conducted.—
<section><number>1</number> Every applicant 
    shall, along with the application for registration made under this Act, make 
    available to the Registrar such quantity of seeds of a variety for 
    registration of which such application is made, for the purpose of 
    conducting tests to evaluate whether seeds of such variety along with 
    parental material conform to the standards as may be specified by 
    regulations:  
 
Provided that 
    the Registrar or any person or test centre to whom such seed has been sent 
    for conducting test shall keep such seed during his or its possession in 
    such manner and in such condition that its viability and quality shall 
    remain unaltered.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    applicant shall deposit such fee as may be prescribed for conducting tests 
    referred to in sub-section (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The tests 
    referred to in sub-section (1) shall be conducted in such manner and by such 
    method as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Acceptance of application or amendment thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of an application under section 14, the Registrar may, after 
    making such inquiry as he thinks fit with respect to the particulars 
    contained in such application, accept the application absolutely or subject 
    to such conditions or limitations as he deems fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    Registrar is satisfied that the application does not comply with the 
    requirements of this Act or any rules or regulations made thereunder, he 
    may, either—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    require the applicant to amend the 
    application to his satisfaction; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    reject the application:  
 
Provided that 
    no application shall be rejected unless the applicant has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of presenting his case.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Advertisement of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an application for registration of a variety has been accepted 
    absolutely or subject to conditions or limitations under sub-section (1) of 
    section 20, the Registrar shall, as soon as after its acceptance, cause such 
    application together with the conditions or limitations, if any, subject to 
    which it has been accepted and the specifications of the variety for 
    registration of which such application is made including its photographs or 
    drawings, to be advertised in the prescribed manner calling objections from 
    the persons interested in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
    may, within three months from the date of the advertisement of an 
    application for registration on payment of the prescribed fee, give notice 
    in writing in the prescribed manner, to the Registrar of his opposition to 
    the registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Opposition 
    to the registration under sub-section (2) may be made on any of the 
    following grounds, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the person opposing the 
    application is entitled to the breeder’s right as against the applicant; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the variety is not registerable 
    under this Act; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the grant of certificate of 
    registration may not be in public interest; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that the variety may have adverse 
    effect on the environment.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar shall serve a copy of the notice of opposition on the applicant 
    for registration and, within two months from the receipt by the applicant of 
    such copy of the notice of opposition, the applicant shall send to the 
    Registrar in the prescribed manner a counter-statement of the grounds on 
    which he relies for his application, and if he does not do so, he shall be 
    deemed to have abandoned his application.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the 
    applicant sends such counter-statement, the Registrar shall serve a copy 
    thereof on the person giving notice of opposition.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any 
    evidence upon which the opponent and the applicant may rely shall be 
    submitted, in the manner prescribed and within the time prescribed, to the 
    Registrar and the Registrar shall give an opportunity to them to be heard, 
    if so desired.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Registrar shall, after hearing the parties, if so required, and considering 
    the evidence, decide whether and subject to what conditions or limitations, 
    if any, the registration is to be permitted and may take into account a 
    ground of objection whether relied upon by the opponent or not.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where a 
    person giving notice of opposition or an applicant sending a 
    counter-statement after receipt of a copy of such notice neither resides nor 
    carries on business in India, the Registrar may require him to give security 
    for the cost of proceedings before him and in default of such security being 
    duly given may treat the opposition or application, as the case may be, as 
    abandoned.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    Registrar may, on request, permit correction of any error in, or any 
    amendment of, a notice of opposition or a counter-statement on such terms as 
    he may think fit.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Registrar to consider grounds of opposition.—The 
    Registrar shall consider all the grounds on which the application has been 
    opposed and after giving reasons for his decision, by order, uphold or 
    reject the opposition.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Registration of essentially derived variety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the registration of an essentially derived variety of the 
    genera or species specified under sub-section (2) of section 29 by the 
    Central Government shall be made to the Registrar by or on behalf of any 
    person referred to in section 14 and in the manner specified in, section 18 
    as if for the word “variety” the words “essentially derived variety” have 
    been substituted therein and shall be accompanied by such documents and fee 
    as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the 
    Registrar is satisfied that the requirements of sub-section (1) have been 
    complied with to his satisfaction, he shall forward the application with his 
    report and all the relevant documents to the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt 
    of an application under sub-section (2), the Authority shall get examined 
    such essentially derived variety to determine as to whether the essentially 
    derived variety is a variety derived from the initial variety by conducting 
    such tests and following such procedure as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the 
    Authority is satisfied on the report of the test referred to in sub-section 
    (3) that the essentially derived variety has been derived from the initial 
    variety, it may direct the Registrar to register such essentially derived 
    variety and the Registrar shall comply with the direction of the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    Authority is not satisfied on the report of the test referred to in 
    sub-section (3) that the essentially derived variety has been derived from 
    the initial variety it shall refuse the application.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The rights 
    of breeder of a variety contained in section 28 shall apply to the breeder 
    of essentially derived variety:  
 
Provided that 
    the authorisation by the breeder of the initial variety to the breeder of 
    essentially derived variety under sub-section (2) of section 28 may be 
    subject to such terms and conditions as both the parties may mutually agree 
    upon.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> An 
    essentially derived variety shall not be registered under this section 
    unless it satisfies the requirements of section 15 as if for the word 
    “variety”, the words “essentially derived variety” have been substituted 
    therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> When an 
    essentially derived variety has been registered by the Registrar in 
    compliance with the direction of the Authority under sub-section (4), the 
    Registrar shall issue to the applicant a certificate of registration in the 
    prescribed form and sealed with the seal of the Registry and send a copy 
    thereof to the Authority and to such other authority, as may be prescribed, 
    for information.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Issue 
    of certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When an application for registration of a variety (other than an essentially 
    derived variety), has been accepted and either—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the application has not been opposed 
    and the time of notice of opposition has expired; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the application has been opposed and 
    the opposition has been rejected,  
     
 
the Registrar shall register the variety.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On the 
    registration of the variety (other than an essentially derived variety), the 
    Registrar shall issue to the applicant a certificate of registration in the 
    prescribed form and sealed with the seal of the Registry and send a copy to 
    the Authority for determination of benefit sharing and to such other 
    authority, as may be prescribed, for information. The maximum time required 
    by the Registrar for issuing the certificate of registration from the date 
    of filing of the application for registration of a variety shall be such as 
    may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    registration of a variety (other than an essentially derived variety), is 
    not completed within twelve months from the date of the application by 
    reason of default on the part of the applicant, the Registrar may, after 
    giving notice to the applicant in the prescribed manner, treat the 
    application as abandoned unless it is completed within the time specified in 
    that behalf in the notice.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may amend the Register or a certificate of registration for the 
    purpose of correcting a clerical error or an obvious mistake.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Registrar shall have power to issue such directions to protect the interests 
    of a breeder against any abusive act committed by any third party during the 
    period between filing of application for registration and decision taken by 
    the Authority on such application.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    certificate of registration issued under this section or sub-section (8) of 
    section 23 shall be valid for nine years in the case of trees and vines and 
    six years in the case of other crops and may be reviewed and renewed for the 
    remaining period on payment of such fees as may be fixed by the rules made 
    in this behalf subject to the condition that the total period of validity 
    shall not exceed,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in the case of trees and vines, 
    eighteen years from the date of registration of the variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in the case of extant varieties, 
    fifteen years from the date of the notification of that variety by the 
    Central Government under section 5 of the Seeds Act, 1966 (54 of 1966); and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    in the other cases, fifteen years 
    from the date of registration of the variety.  
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Publication of list of varieties.—The 
    Authority shall, within such intervals as it thinks appropriate, publish the 
    list of varieties which have been registered during that interval.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Determination of benefit sharing by Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of copy of the certificate of registration under sub-section (8) 
    of section 23 or sub-section (2) of section 24, the Authority shall publish 
    such contents of the certificate and invite claims of benefit sharing to the 
    variety registered under such certificate in the manner as may be 
    prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    invitation of the claims under sub-section (1), any person or group of 
    persons or firm or governmental or non-governmental organisation shall 
    submit its claim of benefit sharing to such variety in the prescribed form 
    within such period, and accompanied with such fee, as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided that 
    such claim shall only be submitted by any—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    person or group of persons, if such 
    person or every person constituting such group is a citizen of India; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    firm or governmental or 
    non-governmental organisation, if such firm or organisation is formed or 
    established in India.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    receiving a claim under sub-section (2), the Authority shall send a copy of 
    such claims to the breeder of the variety registered under such certificate 
    and the breeder may, on receipt of such copy, submit his opposition to such 
    claim within such period and in such manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority shall, after giving an opportunity of being heard to the parties, 
    dispose of the claim received under sub-section (2).  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> While 
    disposing of the claim under sub-section (4), the Authority shall explicitly 
    indicate in its order the amount of the benefit sharing, if any, for which 
    the claimant shall be entitled and shall take into consideration the 
    following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the extent and nature of the use of 
    genetic material of the claimant in the development of the variety relating 
    to which the benefit sharing has been claimed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the commercial utility and demand in 
    the market of the variety relating to which the benefit sharing has been 
    claimed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The amount 
    of benefit sharing to a variety determined under this section shall be 
    deposited by the breeder of such variety in the manner referred to in clause 
    (a) of sub-section (1) of section 45 in the National Gene Fund.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The amount 
    of benefit sharing determined under this section shall, on a reference made 
    by the Authority in the prescribed manner, be recoverable as an arrear of 
    land revenue by the District Magistrate within whose local limits of 
    jurisdiction the breeder liable for such benefit sharing resides.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Breeder 
    to deposit seeds or propagating material.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The breeder shall be required to deposit such quantity of seeds or 
    propagating material including parental line seeds of registered variety in 
    the National Gene Bank as may be specified in the regulations for 
    reproduction purpose at breeder’s expense within such time as may be 
    specified in that regulation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The seeds 
    or propagating material or parental line seeds to be deposited under 
    sub-section (1) shall be deposited to the National Gene Bank specified by 
    the Authority.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Registration to confer right.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the other provisions of this Act, a certificate of registration 
    for a variety issued under this Act shall confer an exclusive right on the 
    breeder or his successor, his agent or licensee, to produce, sell, market, 
    distribute, import or export the variety:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of an extant variety, unless a breeder or his successor 
    establishes his right, the Central Government, and in cases where such 
    extant variety is notified for a State or for any area thereof under section 
    5 of the Seeds Act, 1966 (54 of 1966) the State Government, shall be deemed 
    to be the owner of such right.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A breeder 
    may authorise any person to produce, sell, market or otherwise deal with the 
    variety registered under this Act subject to such limitations and conditions 
    as may be specified in the regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    authorisation under this section shall be in such form as may be specified 
    by regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an 
    agent or a licensee referred to in sub-section (1) becomes entitled to 
    produce, sell, market, distribute, import or export a variety, he shall 
    apply in the prescribed manner and with the prescribed fee to the Registrar 
    to register his title and the Registrar shall, on receipt of application and 
    on proof of title to his satisfaction, register him as an agent or a 
    licensee, as the case may be, in respect of the variety for which he is 
    entitled for such right, and shall cause particulars of such entitlement and 
    conditions or restrictions, if any, subject to which such entitlement is 
    made, to be entered in the register:  
 
Provided that 
    when the validity of such entitlement is in dispute between the parties, the 
    Registrar may refuse to register the entitlement and refer the matter in the 
    prescribed manner to the Authority and withhold the registration of such 
    entitlement until the right of the parties in dispute so referred to has 
    been determined by the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Registrar shall issue a certificate of registration under sub-section (4) to 
    the applicant after such registration and shall enter in the certificate the 
    brief conditions of entitlement, if any, in the prescribed manner, and such 
    certificate shall be the conclusive proof of such entitlement and the 
    conditions or restrictions thereof, if any.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Subject to 
    any agreement subsisting between the parties, an agent or licensee of a 
    right to a variety registered under sub-section (4) shall be entitled to 
    call upon the breeder or his successor thereof to take proceedings to 
    prevent infringement thereof, and if the breeder or his successor refuses or 
    neglects to do so within three months after being so called upon, such 
    registered agent or licensee may institute proceedings for infringement in 
    his own name as if he were the breeder, making the breeder or his successor 
    a defendant.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, a breeder or his 
    successor so added as defendant shall not be liable for any costs unless he 
    enters an appearance and takes part in the proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Nothing in 
    this section shall confer on a registered agent or registered licensee of a 
    variety any right to transfer such right further thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Without 
    prejudice to the registration under sub-section (4), the terms of 
    registration—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    may be varied by the Registrar as 
    regards the variety in respect of which, or any condition or restriction 
    subject to which, it has effect on receipt of an application in the 
    prescribed manner of the registered breeder of such variety or his 
    successor;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    may be cancelled by the Registrar on 
    the application in the prescribed manner of the registered breeder of such 
    variety or his successor or of the registered agent or registered licensee 
    of such variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    may be cancelled by the Registrar on 
    the application in the prescribed manner of any person other than the 
    breeder, his successor, the registered agent or the registered licensee on 
    any of the following grounds, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    that the breeder of a variety or his 
    successor or the registered agent or registered licensee of such variety, 
    misrepresented, or failed to disclose, some fact material to the application 
    for registration under sub-section (4) which if accurately represented or 
    disclosed would have justified the refusal of the application for 
    registration of the registered agent or registered licensee;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    that the registration ought not to 
    have been effected having regard to the right vested in the applicant by 
    virtue of a contract in the performance of which he is interested;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    may be cancelled by the Registrar on 
    the application in the prescribed manner of the breeder of a registered 
    variety, or his successor on the ground that any stipulation in the 
    agreement between the registered agent or the registered licensee, as the 
    case may be, and such breeder or his successor regarding the variety for 
    which such agent or licensee is registered is not being enforced or is not 
    being complied with;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    may be cancelled by the Registrar on 
    the application of any person in the prescribed manner on the ground that 
    the variety relating to the registration is no longer existing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    Registrar shall issue notice in the prescribed manner of every application 
    under this section to the registered breeder of a variety or his successor 
    and to each registered agent or registered licensee (not being the 
    applicant) of such variety.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The 
    Registrar shall, before making any order under sub-section (9), forward the 
    application made in that behalf along with any objection received by any 
    party after notice under sub-section (10) for the consideration of the 
    Authority, and the Authority may, after making such inquiry as it thinks 
    fit, issue such directions to the Registrar as it thinks fit and the 
    Registrar shall dispose of the application in accordance with such 
    directions.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Exclusion of certain varieties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, no registration of a variety 
    shall be made under this Act in cases where prevention of commercial 
    exploitation of such variety is necessary to protect public order or public 
    morality or human, animal and plant life and health or to avoid serious 
    prejudice to the environment.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify 
    the genera or species for the purposes of registration of varieties other 
    than extant varieties and farmers’ varieties under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) and sub-section (1) 
    and (2) of section 15, no variety of any genera or species which involves 
    any technology which is injurious to the life or health of human beings, 
    animals or plants shall be registered under this Act.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, the expression “any technology” includes genetic use 
    restriction technology and terminator technology.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall not delete any genera or species from the list of 
    genera or species specified in a notification issued under sub-section (2) 
    except in the public interest.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    variety belonging to the genera or species excluded under sub-section (4) 
    shall not be eligible for any protection under this Act. 
 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Researcher’s rights.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall prevent—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the use of any variety registered under 
    this Act by any person using such variety for conducting experiment or 
    research; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the use of a variety by any person as 
    an initial source of variety for the purpose of creating other varieties:  
 
Provided that 
    the authorisation of the breeder of a registered variety is required where 
    the repeated use of such variety as a parental line is necessary for 
    commercial production of such other newly developed variety.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Researcher’s rights.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall prevent—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the use of any variety registered under 
    this Act by any person using such variety for conducting experiment or 
    research; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the use of a variety by any person as 
    an initial source of variety for the purpose of creating other varieties:  
 
Provided that 
    the authorisation of the breeder of a registered variety is required where 
    the repeated use of such variety as a parental line is necessary for 
    commercial production of such other newly developed variety.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Special 
    provisions relating to application for registration from citizens of 
    convention countries.—
<section><number>1</number> With a 
    view to the fulfilment of a treaty, convention or arrangement with any 
    country outside India which affords to citizens of India similar privileges 
    as granted to its own citizens, the Central Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, declare such country to be a convention country for 
    the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    person has made an application for the granting of a breeder’s right to a 
    variety or for entering such variety in the official register of varieties 
    in a convention country and that person, or any person entitled to make 
    application on his behalf under section 14 or section 23, makes an 
    application for the registration of such variety in India within twelve 
    months after the date on which the application was made in the convention 
    country, such variety shall, if registered under this Act, be registered as 
    of the date on which the application was made in the convention country and 
    that date shall be deemed for the purposes of this Act to be the date of 
    registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    applications have been made for granting of a breeder’s right to a variety 
    or for entering such variety in the official register of varieties in two or 
    more convention countries, the period of twelve months referred to in 
    sub-section (2) shall be reckoned from the date on which the earlier or 
    earliest of those applications were made.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in 
    this Act shall entitle the breeder of a registered variety for infringement 
    of rights other than protected under this Act which took place prior to the 
    date of application of registration under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Provisions as to reciprocity.—Where 
    any country specified by the Central Government in this behalf by 
    notification in the Official Gazette under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 31 
    does not accord to citizens of India the same rights in respect of the 
    registration and protection of a variety, as it accords to its own 
    nationals, no national of such country shall be entitled, either solely or 
    jointly with any other person, to apply for the registration of a variety or 
    be entitled to get a variety registered under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Surrender of certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A breeder of a variety registered under this Act may, at any time by giving 
    notice in the prescribed manner to the Registrar, offer to surrender his 
    certificate of registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where such 
    an offer is made, the Registrar shall notify in the prescribed manner every 
    registered agent or registered licensee relating to such certificate.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any of 
    such agent or licensee may, within the prescribed period after such 
    notification, give notice to the Registrar of his opposition to the 
    surrender and where any such notice is given, the Registrar shall intimate 
    the contents of such notice to the breeder of such variety.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the 
    Registrar is satisfied after hearing the applicant and all the opponents, if 
    desirous of being heard, that the certificate of registration may properly 
    be surrendered, he may accept the offer and by order revoke the certificate 
    of registration.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Revocation of protection on certain grounds.—Subject 
    to the provisions contained in this Act, the protection granted to a breeder 
    in respect of a variety may, on the application in the prescribed manner of 
    any person interested, be revoked by the Authority on any of the following 
    grounds, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    that the grant of the certificate of 
    registration has been based on incorrect information furnished by the 
    applicant;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    that the certificate of registration 
    has been granted to a person who is not eligible for protection under this 
    Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    that the breeder did not provide the 
    Registrar with such information, documents or material as required for 
    registration under this Act;  
 </section><section>
 <number>d</number>    that the breeder has failed to 
    provide an alternative denomination of the variety which is the subject 
    matter of the registration to the Registrar in case where the earlier 
    denomination of such variety provided to the Registrar is not permissible 
    for registration under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    that the breeder did not provide the 
    necessary seeds or propagating material to the person to whom compulsory 
    licence has been issued under section 47 regarding the variety in respect of 
    which registration certificate has been issued to such breeder;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    that the breeder has not complied with 
    the provisions of this Act or rules or regulations made thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    that the breeder has failed to comply 
    with the directions of the Authority issued under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    that the grant of the certificate of 
    registration is not in the public interest:  
 
Provided that 
    no such protection shall be revoked unless the breeder is given a reasonable 
    opportunity to file objection and of being heard in the matter.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Payment 
    of annual fee and forfeiture of registration in default thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may, with the prior approval of the Central Government, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, impose a fee to be paid annually, by 
    every breeder of a variety, agent and licensee thereof registered under this 
    Act determined on the basis of benefit or royalty gained by such breeder, 
    agent or licensee, as the case may be, in respect of the variety, for the 
    retention of their registration under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    breeder, agent or licensee fails to deposit the fee referred to in 
    sub-section (1) imposed upon him under that sub-section in the prescribed 
    manner up to two consecutive years, the Authority shall issue notice to such 
    breeder, agent or licensee and on service of such notice if he fails to 
    comply with the direction in the notice, the Authority shall declare all the 
    protection admissible under the registration certificate issued to such 
    breeder or agent or licensee forfeited.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    arrears of fee imposed under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be the 
    arrears of land revenue and shall be recoverable accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> Power 
    to cancel or change registration and to rectify the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On an application made in the prescribed manner to the Registrar by any 
    person aggrieved, the Registrar may make such order as he may think fit for 
    cancelling or changing any certificate of registration issued under this Act 
    on the ground of any contravention of the provisions of this Act or failure 
    to observe a condition subject to which such registration certificate is 
    issued.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by the absence or omission from the Register of any entry, or by 
    any entry made in the Register without sufficient cause, or by any entry 
    wrongly remaining on the Register, may apply in the prescribed manner to the 
    Registrar and the Registrar may make such order for making, expunging or 
    varying the entry as he may think fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may, in any proceeding under this section, decide any question 
    that may be necessary or expedient to decide in connection with the 
    rectification of the Register.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar on his own motion, may, after giving notice in the prescribed 
    manner to the parties concerned and after giving them an opportunity of 
    being heard, make any order referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section 
    (2).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Correction of Register.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Registrar may, on an application in the prescribed manner by the breeder of 
    a variety registered under this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    correct any error in the Register in 
    the name, address or description of such breeder or any other entry relating 
    to such variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    enter in the Register any change in the 
    name, address or description of such breeder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    cancel the entry in the Register of the 
    variety in respect of which such application is made; and may make any 
    consequential amendment or alteration in the certificate of registration and 
    for that purpose require the certificate of registration to be produced to 
    him.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar may, on application made in the prescribed manner by a registered 
    agent or a registered licensee of a variety and after notice to the 
    registered breeder of such variety, correct any error or enter any change, 
    in the name, address or description of such registered agent or registered 
    licensee, as the case may be, in the Register or certificate of registration 
    issued under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Alteration of denomination of a registered variety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The breeder of a variety registered under this Act may apply in the 
    prescribed manner to the Registrar to delete any part or to add to or alter 
    the denomination of such variety in any manner not substantially affecting 
    the identity thereof, and the Registrar may refuse leave or may grant it on 
    such terms and subject to such limitations as he may think fit to avoid any 
    conflict with the rights of the other breeders of the varieties registered 
    under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar may cause an application under this section to be advertised in 
    the prescribed manner in any case where it appears to him that it is 
    expedient so to do, and where he does so, if within the prescribed time from 
    the date of the advertisement any person gives notice to the Registrar in 
    the prescribed manner of opposition to the application, the Registrar shall, 
    after hearing the parties if so required, decide the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    leave is granted under this section, the denomination of the variety as 
    altered shall be advertised in the prescribed manner, unless the application 
    has already been advertised under sub-section (2).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Farmers’ right.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    a farmer who has bred or developed a 
    new variety shall be entitled for registration and other protection in like 
    manner as a breeder of a variety under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the farmers’ variety shall be entitled 
    for registration if the application contains declarations as specified in 
    clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 18;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a farmer who is engaged in the 
    conservation of genetic resources of land races and wild relatives of 
    economic plants and their improvement through selection and preservation 
    shall be entitled in the prescribed manner for recognition and reward from 
    the Gene Fund:  
 
     Provided that material so selected and 
    preserved has been used as donors of genes in varieties registrable under 
    this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a farmer shall be deemed to be 
    entitled to save, use, sow, resow, exchange, share or sell his farm produce 
    including seed of a variety protected under this Act in the same manner as 
    he was entitled before the coming into force of this Act:  
 
Provided that 
    the farmer shall not be entitled to sell branded seed of a variety protected 
    under this Act.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    clause (iv), “branded seed” means any seed put in a package or any other 
    container and labelled in a manner indicating that such seed is of a variety 
    protected under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    propagating material of a variety registered under this Act has been sold to 
    a farmer or a group of farmers or any organisation of farmers, the breeder 
    of such variety shall disclose to the farmer or the group of farmers or the 
    organisation of farmers, as the case may be, the expected performance under 
    given conditions, and if such propagating material fails to provide such 
    performance under such given conditions, the farmer or the group of farmers 
    or the organisation of farmers, as the case may be, may claim compensation 
    in the prescribed manner before the Authority and the Authority, after 
    giving notice to the breeder of the variety and after providing him an 
    opportunity to file opposition in the prescribed manner and after hearing 
    the parties, it may direct the breeder of the variety to pay such 
    compensation as it deems fit, to the farmer or the group of farmers or the 
    organisation of farmers, as the case may be.  
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Farmers’ right.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    a farmer who has bred or developed a 
    new variety shall be entitled for registration and other protection in like 
    manner as a breeder of a variety under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the farmers’ variety shall be entitled 
    for registration if the application contains declarations as specified in 
    clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 18;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a farmer who is engaged in the 
    conservation of genetic resources of land races and wild relatives of 
    economic plants and their improvement through selection and preservation 
    shall be entitled in the prescribed manner for recognition and reward from 
    the Gene Fund:  
 
     Provided that material so selected and 
    preserved has been used as donors of genes in varieties registrable under 
    this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a farmer shall be deemed to be 
    entitled to save, use, sow, resow, exchange, share or sell his farm produce 
    including seed of a variety protected under this Act in the same manner as 
    he was entitled before the coming into force of this Act:  
 
Provided that 
    the farmer shall not be entitled to sell branded seed of a variety protected 
    under this Act.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    clause (iv), “branded seed” means any seed put in a package or any other 
    container and labelled in a manner indicating that such seed is of a variety 
    protected under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    propagating material of a variety registered under this Act has been sold to 
    a farmer or a group of farmers or any organisation of farmers, the breeder 
    of such variety shall disclose to the farmer or the group of farmers or the 
    organisation of farmers, as the case may be, the expected performance under 
    given conditions, and if such propagating material fails to provide such 
    performance under such given conditions, the farmer or the group of farmers 
    or the organisation of farmers, as the case may be, may claim compensation 
    in the prescribed manner before the Authority and the Authority, after 
    giving notice to the breeder of the variety and after providing him an 
    opportunity to file opposition in the prescribed manner and after hearing 
    the parties, it may direct the breeder of the variety to pay such 
    compensation as it deems fit, to the farmer or the group of farmers or the 
    organisation of farmers, as the case may be.  
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> Certain 
    information to be given in application for registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A breeder or other person making application for registration of any variety 
    under Chapter III shall disclose in the application the information 
    regarding the use of genetic material conserved by any tribal or rural 
    families in the breeding or development of such variety.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    breeder or such other person fails to disclose any information under 
    sub-section (1), the Registrar may, after being satisfied that the breeder 
    or such person has wilfully and knowingly concealed such information, reject 
    the application for registration.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>41</number> Rights 
    of communities.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person, 
    group of persons (whether actively engaged in farming or not) or any 
    governmental or non-governmental organisation may, on behalf of any village 
    or local community in India, file in any centre notified, with the previous 
    approval of the Central Government by the Authority in the Official Gazette, 
    any claim attributable to the contribution of the people of that village or 
    local community, as the case may be, in the evolution of any variety for the 
    purpose of staking a claim on behalf of such village or local community.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    claim is made under sub-section (1), the centre notified under that 
    sub-section may verify the claim made by such person or group of persons or 
    such governmental or non-governmental organisation in such manner as it 
    deems fit and if it is satisfied that such village or local community has 
    contributed significantly to the evolution of the variety which has been 
    registered under this Act, it shall report its findings to the Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the 
    Authority, on a report under sub-section (2) is satisfied, after such 
    enquiry as it may deem fit, that the variety with which the report is 
    related has been registered under the provisions of this Act, it may issue 
    notice in the prescribed manner to the breeder of that variety and after 
    providing opportunity to such breeder to file objection in the prescribed 
    manner and of being heard, it may subject to any limit notified by the 
    Central Government, by order, grant such sum of compensation to be paid to a 
    person or group of persons or governmental or non-governmental organisation 
    which has made claim under sub-section (1), as it may deem fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    compensation granted under sub-section (3) shall be deposited by the breeder 
    of the variety in the Gene Fund.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    compensation granted under sub-section (3) shall be deemed to be an arrear 
    of land revenue and shall be recoverable by the Authority accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Protection of innocent infringement.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    a right established 
    under this Act shall not be deemed to be infringed by a farmer who at the 
    time of such infringement was not aware of the existence of such right; and  
     
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    a relief which a court 
    may grant in any suit for infringement referred to in section 65 shall not 
    be granted by such court, nor any cognizance of any offence under this Act 
    shall be taken, for such infringement by any court against a farmer who 
    proves, before such court, that at the time of the infringement he was not 
    aware of the existence of the right so infringed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Authorisation of farmers’ variety.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (6) of section 23 and section 28, where an 
    essentially derived variety is derived from a farmers’ variety, the 
    authorisation under sub-section (2) of section 28 shall not be given by the 
    breeder of such farmers' variety except with the consent of the farmers' or 
    group of farmers or community of farmers who have made contribution in the 
    preservation or development of such variety.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Authorisation of farmers’ variety.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (6) of section 23 and section 28, where an 
    essentially derived variety is derived from a farmers’ variety, the 
    authorisation under sub-section (2) of section 28 shall not be given by the 
    breeder of such farmers' variety except with the consent of the farmers' or 
    group of farmers or community of farmers who have made contribution in the 
    preservation or development of such variety.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Exemption from fees.—A farmer or 
    group of farmers or village community shall not be liable to pay any fee in 
    any proceeding before the Authority or Registrar or the Tribunal or the High 
    Court under this Act or the rules made thereunder.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, “fee for any proceeding” includes any fee payable for 
    inspection of any document or for obtaining a copy of any decision or order 
    or document under this Act or the rules made thereunder.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>45</number> Gene 
    Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
    shall constitute a Fund to be called the National Gene Fund and there shall 
    be credited thereto—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the benefit sharing 
    received in the prescribed manner from the breeder of a variety or an 
    essentially derived variety registered under this Act, or propagating 
    material of such variety or essentially derived variety, as the case may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the annual fee payable 
    to the Authority by way of royalty under sub-section (1) of section 35;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the compensation 
    deposited in the Gene Fund under sub-section (4) of section 41;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the contribution from 
    any national and international organisation and other sources;  
     
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Gene 
    Fund shall, in the prescribed manner, be applied for meeting—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any amount to be paid by 
    way of benefit sharing under sub-section (5) of section 26;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the compensation payable 
    under sub-section (3) of section 41;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the expenditure for 
    supporting the conservation and sustainable use of genetic resources 
    including in-situ and ex-situ collections and for 
    strengthening the capability of the Panchayat in carrying out such 
    conservation and sustainable use;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the expenditure of the 
    schemes relating to benefit sharing framed under section 46.  
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>46</number> Framing 
    of schemes, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government shall, for the purposes of section 41 and clause (d) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 45, frame, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, one or more schemes.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of 
    sub-section (1), the scheme may provide for all or any of the following 
    matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the registration of the 
    claims for the purposes of section 41 under the scheme and all matters 
    connected with such registration;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the processing of such 
    claims for securing their enforcement and matters connected therewith;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the maintenance of 
    records and registers in respect of such claims;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the utilisation, by way 
    of disbursal (including apportionment) or otherwise, of any amounts received 
    in satisfaction of such claims;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the procedure for 
    disbursal or apportionment by the Authority in the event of dispute 
    regarding such claims;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the utilisation of 
    benefit sharing for the purposes relating to breeding, discovery or 
    development of varieties;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the maintenance and 
    audit of accounts with respect to the amounts referred to in clause (d).  
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> Power 
    of Authority to make order for compulsory licence in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any time, after the expiry of three years from the date of issue of a 
    certificate of registration of a variety, any person interested may make an 
    application to the Authority alleging that the reasonable requirements of 
    the public for seeds or other propagating material of the variety have not 
    been satisfied or that the seed or other propagating material of the variety 
    is not available to the public at a reasonable price and pray for the grant 
    of a compulsory licence to undertake production, distribution and sale of 
    the seed or other propagating material of that variety.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    application under sub-section (1) shall contain a statement of the nature of 
    the applicant’s interest together with such particulars as may be prescribed 
    and the facts upon which the application is based.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Authority, after consultation with the Central Government, and if satisfied 
    after giving an opportunity to the breeder of such variety to file 
    opposition and after hearing the parties, on the issue that the reasonable 
    requirements of the public with respect to the variety have not been 
    satisfied or that the seed or other propagating material of the variety is 
    not available to the public at a reasonable price, may order such breeder to 
    grant a licence to the applicant upon such terms and conditions as it may 
    deem fit and send a copy of such order to the Registrar to register the 
    title of such applicant as licensee under sub-section (4) of section 28 on 
    payment of such fee by the applicant as is referred to in that sub-section.  
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>48</number>
When requirement of public deemed to have not been satisfied.—In 
    determining the question as to whether the reasonable requirements of the 
    public for seeds of a variety or its propagating material as referred to in 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (3) of section 47, the Authority shall take 
    into account—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the nature of the 
    variety, the time which has elapsed since the grant of the certificate of 
    registration of the variety, price of seed of the variety and the measures 
    taken by the breeder or any registered licensee of the variety to meet the 
    requirement of the public; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the capacity, ability 
    and technical competence of the applicant to produce and market the variety 
    to meet the requirement of the public.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Adjournment of application for grant of compulsory licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the breeder of a variety registered under this Act in respect of which 
    any application has been pending before the Authority under section 47 makes 
    a written request to the Authority on the ground that due to any reasonable 
    factor, such breeder has been unable to produce seed or other propagating 
    material of the variety on a commercial scale to an adequate extent till the 
    date of making such request, the Authority may, on being satisfied that the 
    said ground is reasonable, adjourn the hearing of such application for such 
    period not exceeding twelve months in aggregate as it may consider 
    sufficient for optimum production of the seed or propagating material of 
    such variety, as the case may be, by such breeder.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    adjournment of the application under sub-section (1) shall be granted unless 
    the Authority is satisfied that the breeder of the variety registered under 
    this Act in respect of which such application is made, has taken immediate 
    measures to meet the reasonable requirements of the public for the seeds or 
    other propagating material of such variety.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Duration of compulsory licence.—The 
    Authority shall determine the duration of the compulsory licences granted 
    under this Chapter and such duration may vary from case to case keeping in 
    view the gestation periods and other relevant factors but in any case it 
    shall not exceed the total remaining period of the protection of that 
    variety and when a compulsory licence is granted the prescribed authority 
    shall, in the prescribed manner make available to the licensee of such 
    compulsory licence, the reproductive material of the variety relating to 
    such compulsory licence stored in the National Gene Bank or any other 
    centre.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Authority to settle terms and conditions of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall, while determining the terms and conditions of a 
    compulsory licence under the provisions of this Chapter, endeavour to 
    secure—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    reasonable compensation 
    to the breeder of the variety relating to the compulsory licence having 
    regard to the nature of the variety, the expenditure incurred by such 
    breeder in breeding the variety or for developing it, and other relevant 
    factors;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    that the compulsory 
    licensee of such variety possesses the adequate means to provide to the 
    farmers, the seeds or its other propagating material of such variety, timely 
    and at reasonable market price.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    compulsory licence granted by the Authority shall authorise the licensee to 
    import the variety relating to such licence or any seed or other propagating 
    material of such variety from abroad where such import would constitute an 
    infringement of the rights of the breeder of such variety.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Revocation of compulsory licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may on its own motion or on application from an aggrieved 
    person made to it in the prescribed form, if it is satisfied that a 
    compulsory licensee registered under this Chapter has violated any terms or 
    conditions of this licence or it is not appropriate to continue further such 
    licence in public interest, it may, after giving such licensee an 
    opportunity to file opposition and of being heard, make order to revoke such 
    licence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a 
    licence is revoked under sub-section (1) by an order of the Authority, the 
    Authority shall send a copy of such order to the Registrar to rectify the 
    entry or correct the Register relating to such revocation and the Registrar 
    shall rectify the entry or correct the Register accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Modification of compulsory licence.—The 
    Authority may, on its own motion or on application from the licensee of a 
    compulsory licence, after providing the opportunity of being heard to the 
    breeder of the variety registered under this Act relating to such compulsory 
    licence, if it considers, in public interest, so to do, modify, by order, 
    such terms and conditions as it thinks fit and send a copy of such order to 
    the Registrar to correct the entries and Register according to such 
    modifications and the Registrar shall ensure such corrections to be made 
    accordingly.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Tribunal.—The Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Tribunal to be 
    known as the Plant Varieties Protection Appellate Tribunal to exercise the 
    jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on it by or under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Composition of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman and such number of Judicial Members and 
    Technical Members as the Central Government may deem fit to appoint.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Judicial 
    Member shall be a person who has for at least ten years held a judicial 
    office in the territory of India or who has been a member of the Indian 
    Legal Service and has held a post in Grade-II of that Service or any 
    equivalent or higher post for at least three years or who has been an 
    advocate for at least twelve years.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in computing the period 
    during which a person has held judicial office in the territory of India, 
    there shall be included any period, after he has held any judicial office, 
    during which the person has been an advocate or has held the office of a 
    member of a tribunal or any post, under the Union or a State, requiring 
    special knowledge of law;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in computing the period 
    during which a person has been an advocate, there shall be included any 
    period during which the person has held judicial office or the office of a 
    member of a tribunal or any post, under the Union or a State, requiring 
    special knowledge of law after he became an advocate.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    Technical Member shall be a person who is an eminent agricultural scientist 
    in the field of plant breeding and genetics and possesses an experience of 
    at least twenty years to deal with plant variety or seed development 
    activity, or who has held the post in the Central Government or a State 
    Government dealing with plant variety or seed development equivalent to the 
    Joint Secretary to the Government of India for at least three years and 
    possesses special knowledge in the field of plant breeding and genetics.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall appoint a Judicial Member of the Tribunal to be the 
    Chairman thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government may appoint one of the Member of the Tribunal to be the 
    senior Member thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The senior 
    Member or a Member shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the 
    functions of the Chairman as may be delegated to him by the Chairman by a 
    general or special order in writing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>56</number> Appeals 
    to the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> An appeal 
    shall be preferred to the Tribunal within the prescribed period from any—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    order or decision of the 
    Authority or Registrar, relating to registration of a variety; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    order or decision of the 
    Registrar relating to registration as an agent or a licensee of a variety; 
    or   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    order or decision of the 
    Authority relating to claim for benefit sharing; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    order or decision of the 
    Authority regarding revocation of compulsory licence or modification of 
    compulsory licence; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    order or decision of the 
    Authority regarding payment of compensation, made under this Act or rules 
    made thereunder.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    appeal shall be preferred by the petition in writing and shall be in such 
    form and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Tribunal in disposing of an appeal under this section shall have the power 
    to make any order which the Authority or the Registrar could make under this 
    Act.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 

 <article>
<number>57</number> Orders 
    of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal 
    may, after giving both the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being 
    heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Tribunal may, at any time within thirty days from the date of the order, 
    with a view to rectifying the mistake apparent from the record, amend any 
    order passed by it under sub-section (1), and make such amendment if the 
    mistake is brought to its notice by the appellant or the opposite party.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In every 
    appeal, the Tribunal may where it is possible, hear and decide such appeal 
    within a period of one year from the date of filing of the appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Tribunal shall send a copy of any order passed under this section to the 
    Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The orders 
    of the Tribunal under this Act shall be executable as a decree of a civil 
    court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Procedure of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    powers and functions of the Tribunal may be exercised and discharged by 
    Benches constituted by the Chairman of the Tribunal from among the Members 
    thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Bench 
    shall consist of one Judicial Member and one Technical Member.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    Member of a Bench differ in opinion on any point, they shall state the point 
    or points on which they differ, and the case shall be referred to the 
    Chairman for hearing on such point or points by one or more of the other 
    Members and such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion 
    of the majority of the Members who have heard the case, including those who 
    first heard it.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act, the Tribunal shall have power to regulate its 
    own procedure and the procedure of Benches thereof in all matters arising 
    out of the exercise of its powers or the discharge of its functions, 
    including the places at which the Benches shall hold their sittings.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Tribunal shall, for the purpose of discharging its functions, have all the 
    power which are vested in the Registrar under section 11, and any proceeding 
    before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the 
    meaning of sections 193 and 228 and for the purpose of section 196 of the 
    Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a 
    civil court for all the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other provisions of this Act or in 
    any other law for the time being in force, no interim order (whether by way 
    of injunction or stay or any other manner) shall be made on, or in, any 
    proceedings relating to an appeal unless—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    copies of such appeal 
    and of all documents in support of the plea for such interim order are 
    furnished to the party against whom such appeal is made or proposed to be 
    made; and   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    opportunity is given to 
    such party to be heard in the matter.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Transitional provision.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, till the establishment of the Tribunal under 
    section 54, the Intellectual Property Appellate Board established under 
    section 83 of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 1999) shall exercise the 
    jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on the Tribunal under this Act 
    subject to the modification that in any Bench of such Intellectual Property 
    Appellate Board constituted for the purposes of this section, for the 
    Technical Member referred to in sub-section (2) of section 84 of the said 
    Trade Marks Act, the Technical Member shall be appointed under this Act and 
    he shall be deemed to be the Technical Member for constituting the Bench 
    under the said sub-section (2) of section 84 for the purposes of this Act.  

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>60</number> Grants by Central Government.</title>—The Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this 
behalf, make to the Authority grants and loans of such sums of money as the 
Central Government may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of this 
Act.</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Authority Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall 
    be constituted a fund to be called the Protection of Plant Varieties 
    Authority Account and there shall be credited thereto—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all grants and loans 
    made to the Authority by the Central Government under section 60;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all fees received by the 
    Authority and the Registrars except the annual fee determined on the basis 
    of benefits or royalty under sub-section (1) of section 35;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all sums received by the 
    Authority from such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Protection of Plant Varieties Authority Account shall be applied for 
    meeting—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the salaries, allowances 
    and other remuneration of the Chairperson, officers and other employees of 
    the Authority and allowances, if any, payable to the members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the other expenses of 
    the Authority in connection with the discharge of its functions and for 
    purposes of this Act.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Budget, 
    accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Authority shall prepare a budget, maintain proper accounts and other 
    relevant records (including the accounts and other relevant records of the 
    Gene Fund) and prepare an annual statement of account in such form as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller 
    and Auditor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and 
    any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by 
    the Authority to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by 
    him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have 
    the same right and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as 
    the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India generally has in connection 
    with the audit of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the 
    right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and 
    other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the 
    Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid 
    before each House of Parliament.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Financial and administrative powers of Chairperson.—The 
    Chairperson shall exercise such financial and administrative powers over the 
    functions of the Authority as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided that 
    the Chairperson shall have the authority to delegate such of his financial 
    and administrative powers as he may think fit to a member or any other 
    officer of the Authority subject to the condition that the member or such 
    other officer shall, while exercising such delegated powers, continue to be 
    under the direction, control and supervision of the Chairperson.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Infringement.—Subject to the 
    provisions of this Act, a right established under this Act is infringed by a 
    person—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    who, not being the 
    breeder of a variety registered under this Act or a registered agent or a 
    registered licensee of that variety, sells, exports, imports or produces 
    such variety without the permission of its breeder or within the scope of a 
    registered licence or registered agency without permission of the registered 
    licensee or registered agent, as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    who uses, sells, 
    exports, imports or produces any other variety giving such variety, the 
    denomination identical with or deceptively similar to the denomination of a 
    variety registered under this Act in such manner as to cause confusion in 
    the mind of general people in identifying such variety so registered.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Suit 
    for infringement, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
    suit— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for the infringement of 
    a variety registered under this Act; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    relating to any right in 
    a variety registered under this Act,  
     
 
shall be instituted in any court inferior to a 
    District Court having jurisdiction to try the suit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of clauses (a) and (b) of sub-section (1), “District Court having 
    jurisdiction” shall mean the District Court within the local limits of whose 
    jurisdiction the cause of action arises.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Relief 
    in suit for infringement.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    relief which a court may grant in any suit for infringement referred to in 
    section 65 includes an injunction and at the option of the plaintiff, either 
    damages or a share of the profits.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The order 
    of injunction under sub-section (1) may include an ex parte 
    injunction or any interlocutory order for any of the following matters, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    discovery of documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    preserving of infringing 
    variety or documents or other evidence which are related to the subject 
    matter of the suit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    attachment of such 
    property of the defendant which the court deems necessary to recover 
    damages, costs or other pecuniary remedies which may be finally awarded to 
    the plaintiff.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Opinion 
    of scientific adviser.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
    the court has to form an opinion upon any question of fact or a scientific 
    issue, such court may appoint an independent scientific adviser to suggest 
    it or to inquire into and report upon the matter to enable it to form the 
    desired opinion.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    scientific adviser may be paid such remuneration of expenses as the court 
    may fix.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Prohibition to apply the denomination of a registered variety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person other than the breeder of a variety registered under this Act or a 
    registered licensee or a registered agent thereof shall use the denomination 
    of that variety in the manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    shall be deemed to apply the denomination of a variety registered under this 
    Act who—  
 <subsection>
               <number>a</number>    applies it to the 
    variety itself; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    applies it to any 
    package in or with which the variety is sold, or exposed for sale, or had in 
    possession such package for sale or for any purpose of trade or production; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    places, encloses or 
    annexes the variety which is sold, or exposed for sale, or had in possession 
    for sale or for any purpose of trade or production, in or with any package 
    or other thing to which the denomination of such variety registered under 
    this Act has been applied; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    uses the denomination of 
    such variety registered under this Act in any manner reasonably likely to 
    lead to the belief that the variety or its propagating material in 
    connection with which it is used is designated or described by that 
    denomination; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    in relation to the 
    variety uses such denomination in any advertisement, invoice, catalogue, 
    business letter, business paper, price list or other commercial document and 
    such variety is delivered to a person in pursuance of a request or order 
    made by reference to the denomination as so used.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    denomination shall be deemed to be applied to a variety whether it is woven 
    in, impressed on, or otherwise worked into, or annexed or affixed to, such 
    variety or to any package or other thing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Meaning 
    of falsely applying the denomination or a registered variety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person shall be deemed to falsely apply the denomination of a variety 
    registered under this Act who, without the assent of the breeder of such 
    variety,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    applies such 
    denomination or a deceptively similar denomination to any variety or any 
    package containing such variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    uses any package bearing 
    a denomination which is identical with or deceptively similar to the 
    denomination of such variety registered under this Act, for the purpose of 
    packing, filling or wrapping therein any variety other than such variety 
    registered under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    denomination of a variety registered under this Act falsely applied as 
    mentioned in sub-section (1), is in this Act referred to as false 
    denomination.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In any 
    prosecution for falsely applying a denomination of a variety registered 
    under this Act the burden of proving the assent of the breeder of such 
    variety shall lie on the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Penalty 
    for applying false denomination, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    applies any false 
    denomination to a variety; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    indicates the false name 
    of a country or place or false name and address of the breeder of a variety 
    registered under this Act in the course of trading such variety,
 
shall, unless he proves that he acted, without 
    intent to defraud, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall 
    not be less than three months but which may extend to two years, or with 
    fine which shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees but which may extend 
    to five lakh rupees, or with both.
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Penalty 
    for selling varieties to which false denomination is applied, etc.—Any 
    person who sells, or exposes for sale, or has in his possession for sale or 
    for any purpose of trade or production of any variety to which any false 
    denomination is applied or to which an indication of the country or place in 
    which such variety was made or produced or the name and address of the 
    breeder of such variety registered under this Act has been falsely made, 
    shall, unless he proves—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    that having taken all reasonable 
    precautions against committing an offence against this section, he had at 
    the time of commission of the alleged offence no reason to suspect the 
    genuineness of the denomination of such variety or that any offence had been 
    committed in respect of indication of the country or place in which such 
    variety registered under this Act, was made or produced or the name and 
    address of the breeder of such variety,  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    that, on demand by or on behalf of the 
    prosecutor, he gave all the information in his possession with respect to 
    the person from whom he obtained such variety; or  
     
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    that otherwise he had acted innocently,  
 
be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two years, 
    or with fine which shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees but which 
    may extend to five lakh rupees, or with both.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Penalty 
    for falsely representing a variety as registered.—Whoever 
    makes any representation with respect to the denomination of a variety or 
    its propagating material or essentially derived variety or its propagating 
    material not being variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material registered under this Act, to 
    the effect that it is a variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material registered under this Act or 
    otherwise represents any variety, or its propagating material, or 
    essentially derived variety or its propagating material not registered under 
    this Act to the effect that it is registered under this Act shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term, which shall not be less than six 
    months but which may extend to three years, or with fine which shall not be 
    less than one lakh rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees, or with 
    both. 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Penalty 
    for subsequent offence.—Whoever, 
    having already been convicted of an offence under this Act is again 
    convicted of such offence shall be punishable for the second and for every 
    subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than 
    one year but which may extend to three years, or with fine which shall not 
    be less than two lakh rupees but which may extend to twenty lakh rupees, or 
    both. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>74</number> No 
    offence in certain cases.—The 
    provisions of this Act relating to offences shall be subject to the right 
    created as recognised by this Act and no act or omission shall be deemed to 
    be an offence under the provisions of this Act if such act or omission is 
    permissible under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Exemption of certain persons employed in ordinary course of business.—Where 
    a person accused of an offence under this Act proves that in the ordinary 
    course of his employment, he has acted without any intention to commit the 
    offence and having taken all reasonable precautions against committing the 
    offence charged, he had, at the time of the commission of the alleged 
    offence, no reason to suspect the genuineness of the act so charged as an 
    offence and on demand made by or on behalf of the prosecutor, he gave all 
    the information in his possession with respect to the persons on whose 
    behalf the offence was committed, he shall be acquitted.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Procedure where invalidity of registration is pleaded by the accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the offence charged under this Act is in relation to a variety or its 
    propagating material or essentially derived variety or its propagating 
    material registered under this Act and the accused pleads that the 
    registration of such variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material, as the case may be, is invalid 
    and the court is satisfied that such offence is prima facie not 
    tenable, it shall not proceed with the charge but shall adjourn the 
    proceedings for three months from the date on which the plea of the accused 
    is recorded to enable the accused to file an application before the 
    Registrar under this Act for the rectification of the Register on the ground 
    that the registration is invalid.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    accused proves to the court that he has made such application within the 
    time so limited or within such further time as the court for sufficient 
    cause allow, the further proceedings in the prosecution shall stand stayed 
    till the disposal of such application for rectification.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If within 
    a period of three months or within such extended time as may be allowed by 
    the court, the accused fails to apply the Registrar for rectification of the 
    Register, the court shall proceed with the case as if the registration were 
    invalid.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where 
    before institution of a complaint of an offence referred to in sub-section 
    (1), any application for the rectification of the Register concerning the 
    registration of the variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material, as the case may be, in question 
    on the ground of invalidity of such registration has already been properly 
    made to and is pending before the Registrar, the court shall stay the 
    further proceedings in the prosecution pending the disposal of the 
    application aforesaid and shall determine the charge against the accused in 
    conformity with the result of the application for rectification.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
    person committing an offence under this act is a company, the company as 
    well as every person incharge of, and responsible to, the company for the 
    conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall 
    be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or that the 
    commission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of any 
    director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
    manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of 
    that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Protection of security of India.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, the Authority or the Registrar shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    not disclose any information relating 
    to the registration of a variety or any application relating to the 
    registration of a variety under this Act, which it considers prejudicial to 
    the interest of the security of India; and  
     
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    take any action regarding the 
    cancellation of registration of such varieties registered under this Act 
    which the Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette 
    specify in the interest of the security of India.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, the expression “security of India” means any action necessary 
    for the security of India which relates to the use of any produce of any 
    variety registered under this Act directly or indirectly for the purposes of 
    war or military establishment or for the purposes of war or other emergency 
    in international relations.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>79</number> Implied 
    warranty on sale of registered variety, etc.—Where 
    a denomination of a variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material registered under this Act has 
    been applied to the variety or its propagating material or essentially 
    derived variety or its propagating material, as the case may be, on sale or 
    in the contract for sale of such variety or its propagating material or 
    essentially derived variety or its propagating material, as the case may be, 
    the seller shall be deemed to warrant that the denomination is a genuine 
    denomination and not falsely applied, unless the contrary is expressed in 
    writing signed by or on behalf of the seller and delivered at the time of 
    the sale of the variety or its propagating material or essentially derived 
    variety or its propagating material, as the case may be, on contract to and 
    accepted by the buyer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>80</number> Death 
    of party to a proceeding.—If a 
    person who is a party to a proceeding under this Act (not being a proceeding 
    in a court) dies pending the proceeding, the Authority or the Registrar, as 
    the case may be, may, on request, and on proof to the satisfaction of such 
    Authority or Registrar, of the transmission of the interest of the deceased 
    person, substitute in the proceedings his successor in interest in his 
    place, or, if the Authority or the Registrar is of opinion that the interest 
    of the deceased person is sufficiently represented by the surviving party, 
    permit the proceedings to continue without the substitution of his successor 
    in interest.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>81</number> Right 
    of registered agent and the registered licensee to institute suit.—The 
    registered agent or the registered licensee of a variety or its propagating 
    material or essentially derived variety or its propagating material 
    registered under this Act may institute appropriate proceedings in the court 
    under this Act on behalf of the breeder of such variety or its propagating 
    material or essentially derived variety or its propagating material, as the 
    case may be, if such agent or licensee has been authorised in the prescribed 
    manner by such breeder for doing so.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Evidence of entry in register, etc., and things done by the Authority and 
    the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> A copy of any 
    entry in the register, or of any document issued under this Act purporting 
    to be certified by the Authority or the Registrar and sealed with the seal 
    of such Authority or Registrar, as the case may be, shall be admitted in 
    evidence in all courts and in all proceedings without further proof or 
    production of the original.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    certificate purporting to be under the hand of the Authority or the 
    Registrar, as the case may be, as to any entry, matter or things that such 
    Authority or Registrar is authorised by this Act or the rules to make or do 
    shall be prima facie evidence of the entry having been made, and of 
    the content thereof, or of the matter or things having been done or not 
    done.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Authority, Registrar and other officers not compellable to production of 
    Register, etc.—The Authority or 
    the Registrar or any officer working under the Authority or the Registrar, 
    as the case may be, shall not, in any legal proceedings, be compelled to 
    produce the Register or any other document in its or his custody, the 
    content of which can be proved by the production of a certified copy issued 
    under this Act in the prescribed manner or to appear as a witness to prove 
    the matters therein recorded unless by order of the court, as the case may 
    be, made for special cause.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

  
 <article>
 <number>84</number> 
    Document open to public inspection.—Any person may, on an application to 
    the Authority or the Registrar, as the case may be, and on payment of such 
    fees as may be prescribed, obtain a certified copy of any entry in the 
    Register or any other document in any proceedings under this Act pending 
    before such Authority or Registrar or may inspect such entry or document.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>85</number> Report 
    of the Authority to be placed before Parliament.—The 
    Central Government shall cause to be placed before both Houses of Parliament 
    once a year a report regarding the performance of the Authority under this 
    Act.  
  
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Government to be bound.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be binding on the Government.  
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Proceedings before Authority or Registrar.—All 
    proceedings before the Authority or the Registrar, as the case may be, 
    relating to registration of variety or essentially derived variety, 
    registration of agent, registration of licence or registration of compulsory 
    licensing under this Act shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings within 
    the meaning of sections 193 and 228 and for the purpose of section 196 of 
    the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Authority or the Registrar, as 
    the case may be, shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of 
    section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
    1974).  
 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>88</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government, or against the Chairperson, or members, or the Registrar or any 
    person acting under such Government, Authority or Registrar under the 
    provisions of this Act, for anything which is in good faith done or intended 
    to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule, regulation, scheme or order 
    made thereunder.  
 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>89</number> Bar of 
    jurisdiction.—No civil court 
    shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the Authority or the 
    Registrar or the Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to determine.  
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>90</number> Member 
    and Staff of Authority, etc., to be public servants.—The 
    Chairperson, members, officers and other employees of the Authority and the 
    Registrar-General and the officers and other employees working under him 
    shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of 
    the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>91</number> 
    Exemption from tax on wealth and income.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 (27 of 1957), the Income-tax 
    Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for the time being in force 
    relating to tax on wealth, income, profits or gains, the Authority shall not 
    be liable to pay wealth-tax, income-tax or any other tax in respect of their 
    wealth, income, profits or gains derived.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>92</number> Act to 
    have overriding effect.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than 
    this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>93</number> Power 
    of Central Government to give directions.—The 
    Central Government may give directions to the Authority as it may think 
    necessary in the public interest for the execution of all or any of the 
    functions of the Authority under any provisions of this Act or rules and 
    regulations made thereunder.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>94</number> Power 
    to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:  
 
Provided that 
    no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from 
    the date of commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of 
    Parliament.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>95</number> Power 
    to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Authority may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this 
    Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matter namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    duties and jurisdiction of the 
    Registrars under sub-section (4) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the term of office and the conditions 
    of service of the Registrars under sub-section (5) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the criteria of distinctiveness, 
    uniformity and stability for registration of extant variety under 
    sub-section (2) of section 15;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the manner in which a single and 
    distinct denomination to a variety shall be assigned by the applicant under 
    sub-section (1) of section 17;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the matters governing the assignment of 
    denomination to a variety under sub-section (2) of section 17;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the time within which the Registrar may 
    require the applicant to propose another denomination under sub-section (3) 
    of section 17;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the form of application under clause 
    (d) of sub-section (1) of section 18;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the standards for evaluating seeds 
    during tests under sub-section (1) of section 19;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the quantity of seeds or other 
    propagating material including parental line seeds to be deposited by a 
    breeder to be specified under sub-section (1) of section 27;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the limitations and conditions subject 
    to which a breeder may authorise a person to produce, sell, market or 
    otherwise deal with varieties under sub-section (2) of section 28;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the form for authorisation under 
    sub-section (3) of section 28;  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>96</number> Power 
    of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particulars, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the term of office of the Chairperson 
    and the manner of filling the post under sub-section (6) of section 3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the salary and allowances of the 
    Chairperson and his conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, 
    provident fund and other matters under and the allowances for non-official 
    members for attending the meeting under sub-section (8) of section 3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the time and place of meetings of the 
    Authority and the rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
    business at its meetings [including the quorum at its meetings and the 
    transaction of business of its Standing Committee appointed under 
    sub-section (7) of section 3] under sub-section (1) of section 4;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the control and restriction regarding 
    appointment of the officers and other employees of the Authority and the 
    method of such appointment, salary and allowances and other conditions of 
    service under section 6;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the powers and duties of the 
    Chairperson under section 7;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    the terms and conditions subject to 
    which and the manner in which the measures referred to in sub-section (1) of 
    section 8 may provide for the registration of new extant varieties under 
    clause (a) of sub-section (2) of that section;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    the manner for arranging production 
    and sale of the seeds under clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 8;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    the orders by the Authority or the 
    Registrar as to costs under clause (b) of section 11;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>    the salary and allowances of 
    Registrar-General of Plant Varieties and the conditions of service in 
    respect of his leave, pension, provident fund and other matters under 
    sub-section (3) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    the matters to be included in the 
    National Register of Plant Varieties under sub-section (1) of section 13;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>    the manner of authorising a person 
    under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 16;  
 <subsubsection>
<number>xii</number>    the fee under clause (g) and the 
    other particulars under clause (i) which shall accompany the application 
    under sub-section (1) of section 18;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xiii</number>    the form of application under the 
    proviso to sub-section (1) of section 18;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xiv</number>    the period within which after making 
    application a proof of the right to make the application is to be furnished 
    under sub-section (3) of section 18;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xv</number>    the fee to be deposited by the 
    applicant under sub-section (2) of section 19;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xvi</number>    the manner and method of conducting 
    the tests under sub-section (3) of section 19;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xvii</number>    the manner of advertising 
    application, conditions or limitations and specifications of variety for 
    registration including its photograph or drawings under sub-section (1) of 
    section 21;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xviii</number>    the manner of giving notice and the 
    fee payable therefor under sub-section (2) of section 21;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xix</number>    the manner of sending 
    counter-statement under sub-section (4) of section 21;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xx</number>    the manner of submitting evidence and 
    the time within which such evidence may be submitted under sub-section (6) 
    of section 21;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxi</number>    the documents and fees under 
    sub-section (1) and the tests to be conducted and the procedure to be 
    followed under sub-section (3) of section 23;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxii</number>    the form of a certificate of 
    registration and the other authority to which a copy thereto shall be sent 
    under sub-section (8) of section 23;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxiii</number>    the form of a certificate of 
    registration and the other authority to which a copy thereof and the maximum 
    time for issuing the certificate of registration under sub-section (2) of 
    section 24;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxiv</number>    the manner of giving notice to the 
    applicant under sub-section (3) of section 24;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxv</number>    the fee for review and renewal under 
    sub-section (6) of section 24;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxvi</number>    the contents of the certificate and 
    the manner of publishing such contents and inviting claim of benefits 
    sharing under sub-section (1) of section 26;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxvii</number>    the form for submitting claims of 
    benefit sharing and the fees to be accompanied therewith under sub-section 
    (2) of section 26;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxviii</number>    the manner in which and the time 
    within which opposition to claims shall be submitted under sub-section (3) 
    of section 26;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxix</number>    the manner of making reference under 
    sub-section (7) of section 26;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxx</number>    the manner of making an application 
    for registration for title and the fees to be accompanied therewith under 
    sub-section (4) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxi</number>    the manner of referring the disputes 
    regarding registration of entitlement under the proviso to sub-section (4) 
    of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxii</number>    the manner to enter into a 
    certificate the brief conditions of entitlement under sub-section (5) of 
    section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxiii</number>    the manner of making an 
    application for varying the terms of registration under clause (a) of 
    sub-section (9) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxiv</number>    the manner of making an application 
    by the registered breeder and certain other for cancellation of terms of 
    registration under clause (b) of sub-section (9) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxv</number>    the manner of application by any 
    person other than the breeder, his successor, the registered agent or the 
    registered licensee for cancellation of terms of registration under clause 
    (c) of sub-section (9) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxvi</number>    the manner of application for 
    cancellation of the terms of registration under clause (d) of sub-section 
    (9) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxvii</number>    the manner of application for 
    cancellation of the terms of registration under clause (e) of sub-section 
    (9) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxviii</number>    the manner of issuing notice to 
    the registered breeder of a variety or his successor or to each registered 
    agent or registered licensee (not being the applicant) under sub-section 
    (10) of section 28;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxxix</number>    the manner of giving notice to the 
    Registrar under sub-section (1) of section 33;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xl</number>    the manner of notifying to the 
    registered agent or registered licensee under sub-section (2) of section 33;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xli</number>    the period within which the notice of 
    opposition under sub-section (3) of section 33 may be given;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlii</number>    the manner of making application 
    under section 34;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xliii</number>    the manner of depositing fee 
    payable under sub-section (2) of section 35;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xliv</number>    the manner of making application 
    under sub-section (1) of section 36;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlv</number>    the manner of applying to the 
    Registrar under sub-section (2) of section 36;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlvi</number>    the manner of giving notice under 
    sub-section (4) of section 36;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlvii</number>    the manner of application under 
    sub-section (1) of section 37;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlviii</number>    the manner of making application 
    under sub-section (2) of section 37;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xlix</number>    the manner to apply to the Registrar 
    under sub-section (1) of section 38;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>l</number>    the manner of advertising application 
    and to give notice to the Registrar, and the time from the date of 
    advertisement within which a person may give such notice under sub-section 
    (2) of section 38;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>li</number>    the manner of advertising the 
    denomination of the variety under sub-section (3) of section 38;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lii</number>    the manner of recognition and reward 
    from Gene Fund under clause (iii) of sub-section (1) of section 39;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>liii</number>    the manner of claiming compensation 
    and filing of opposition under sub-section (2) of section 39;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>liv</number>    the manner of issuing notice and 
    filing objection under sub-section (3) of section 41;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lv</number>    the manner of receiving benefit 
    sharing under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 45;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lvi</number>    the manner of applying Gene Fund 
    under sub-section (2) of section 45;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lvii</number>    the particulars to be contained in 
    the application under sub-section (2) of section 47;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lviii</number>    the authority and the manner in 
    which such authority shall make available to the compulsory licensee the 
    reproduction material of the variety under section 50;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lix</number>    the form for making application under 
    sub-section (1) of section 52;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lx</number>    the period within which an appeal 
    shall be preferred under sub-section (1) of section 56;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxi</number>    the form of petition and the 
    particulars which such petition shall contain under sub-section (2) of 
    section 56;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxii</number>    the form for preparing annual 
    statement of accounts under sub-section (1) of section 62;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxiii</number>    the financial and administrative 
    powers which the Chairperson shall exercise under section 63;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxiv</number>    the manner of using the denomination 
    of a variety under sub-section (1) of section 68;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxv</number>    the manner of authorising registered 
    agent or registered licensee under section 81;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxvi</number>    the manner of issuing certified copy 
    of content of Register or any other document under section 83;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxvii</number>    the fee payable for obtaining a 
    certified copy of, or to inspect, any entry in the Register or any other 
    document under section 84;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>lxviii</number>    any other matter which is to be, 
    or may be, prescribed or in respect of which this Act makes no provision or 
    makes insufficient provision and provision is, in the opinion of the Central 
    Government, necessary for the proper implementation of this Act.  

 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>97</number> Rules, 
    regulations and schemes to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation and every scheme made under this Act shall be 
    laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
    while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
    comprised in one session or in two or more successive session, and if, 
    before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
    successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification 
    in the rule or regulation or scheme or both Houses agree that the rule or 
    regulation or scheme should not be made, the rule or regulation or scheme 
    shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
    as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
    shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
    that rule or regulation or scheme.  

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Sections 2 
    to 13 and sections 95 to 97 came into force on 11th November, 2005, vide
    S.O. 1588(E), dated 11th November, 2005.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>