<act><tid>6594</tid>
<title>THE REGISTRATION AND OTHER RELATED LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 48 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 24th September, <year>2001</year>]

An Act further to amend the Registration Act, <year>1908</year>, the Transfer of 
Property Act, <year>1882</year> and the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1452032</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Registration and Other 
Related Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.
CHAP

Amendment of the Registration Act, <year>1908</year>

CHAPTER II

Amendment of the Registration Act, <year>1908</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1144522</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new section 16A.- In the Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16  
  of <year>1908</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the Registration  
  Act), after section 16, the following section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" 16A. Keeping of books in computer floppies, diskettes, etc.- (1) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 16, the books provided 
under sub- section (1) of that section may also be kept in computer 
floppies or diskettes or in any other electronic form in the manner 
and subject to the safeguards as may be prescribed by the 
Inspector- General with the sanction of the State Government.

<section><tid>182743</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law 
for the time being in force, a copy or extracts from the books kept 
under sub- section (1) given by the registering officer under his hand 
and seal shall be deemed to be a copy given u der section 57 for the 
purposes of sub- section (5) of that section.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1396961</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 17.- In section 17 of the Registration Act,-
<section><tid>377949</tid>
<number>a</number>after sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (1A) The documents containing contracts to transfer for 
consideration, any immovable property for the purpose of section 53A 
of the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>) shall be registered 
if they have been executed on or after the commencement of he 
Registration and Other Related Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year> and if such 
documents are not registered on or after such commencement, then, they 
shall have no effect for the purposes of the said section 53A.";


</section>

<section><tid>1796792</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (v), for the opening words" any 
document", the words, brackets, figure and letter" any document other 
than the documents specified in sub- section (1A)" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>349978</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 30.- In section 30 of the Registration Act, 
sub- section (2) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>842150</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new section 32A.- After section 32 of the 
Registration Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 32A. Compulsory affixing of photograph, etc.- Every person presenting 
any document at the proper registration office under section 32 shall 
affix his passport size photograph and fingerprints to the document:

Provided that where such document relates to the transfer of ownership 
of immovable property, the passport size photograph and fingerprints 
of each buyer and seller of such property mentioned in the document 
shall also be affixed to the document.".



</article>



<article><tid>539865</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 49.- In section 49 of the Registration Act, 
in the proviso, the words, figures and letter" or as evidence of part 
performance of a contract for the purposes of section 53A of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 od <year>1882</year>.)," shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>823282</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 52.- In section 52 of the Registration Act, 
in sub- section 1, in clause (a), after the words" and place of 
presentation", the words, figures and letter" the photographs and 
fingerprints affixed under section 32A" shall be insert d.


</article>



<article><tid>187967</tid>
<number>8</number>Omission of section 67.- Section 67 of the Registration Act shall 
be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>889551</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 69. In section 69 of the Registration Act, 
in sub- section 1, after clause (a), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (aa) providing the manner in which and the safeguards subject to 
which the books may be kept in computer floppies or diskettes or in 
any other electronic form under sub- section (1) of section 16A;".

CHAP

Amendment of the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>

CHAPTER III

Amendment of the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1096212</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of section 53A of Act 4 of <year>1882</year>.- In section 53A of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>, the words" the contract, though 
required to be registered, has not been registered, or," shall be 
omitted.
CHAP

Amendment of the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>

CHAPTER IV

Amendment of the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1297506</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of Schedule I of Act 2 of <year>1899</year>.- In Schedule I to the 
Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>,-
<section><tid>1074145</tid>
<number>a</number>under column heading" Description of Instrument", in article No. 
23, in Exemption, the portion beginning with the words" Assignment of 
Copyright" and ending with the word and figure" section 5." shall be 
numbered as clause (a) thereof, and after clau e (a) as so numbered, 
the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (b) for the purpose of this article, the portion of duty paid in 
respect of a document falling under article No. 23A shall be excluded 
while computing the duty payable in respect of a corresponding 
document relating to the completion of the transaction n any union 
territory under this article.";


</section>

<section><tid>975246</tid>
<number>b</number>after article No. 23 and the entries relating thereto, the 
following article No. and the entries shall be inserted, namely:-
Description of Instrument Proper Stamp- duty 
" 23A. CONVEYANCE IN THE NATURE OF PART Ninety per cent. Of 
PERFORMANCE- Contracts for the transfer of immovable the duty as a 
Property in the nature of part performance in any Union Conveyance

Territory under section 53A of the Transfer of Property (No. 23).". 
Act, <year>1882</year>. (4 of <year>1882</year>)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1641215</tid>
<number> 12</number> Saving.- Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 6 and 10, 
any-
<section><tid>1958997</tid>
<number>a</number>right of a transferor or any person claiming under him debarred 
under section 53A of the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>) 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall remain so 
debarred as if section 10 had not come into force in re pect of such 
right; and

</section>

<section><tid>1075197</tid>
<number>b</number>unregistered document relating to the right referred to in clause 
 (a) may be received as evidence of part performance of a contract for 
the purposes of section 53A of the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of  
  <year>1882</year>) as if section 6 had not come into for e in respect of such 
document.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>