<act><tid>445368</tid>
<title>THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES LOANS ACT, <year>1914</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1914</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> PREAMBLE.
[ 28th February, <year>1914</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the grant of loans 
to Local Authorities.

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating 
to the borrowing powers of local authorities; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:--





<article><tid>1896697</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1654477</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Local  
Authorities Loans Act, <year>1914</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1457009</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>212444</tid>
<number>2</number>Definitions.- In this Act," local authority" means any person 
legally entitled to the control or management of any local or 
municipal fund, or legally entitled to impose any cess, rate, duty or 
tax within any local area;
" funds", used with reference to any local authority, includes any 
local or municipal fund to the control or management of which such 
authority is legally entitled, and any cess, rate, duty or tax which 
such authority is legally entitled to impose, and any property vested 
in such authority;

" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and

" work" includes a survey, whether incidental to any other work or 
not.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The Government" or" the appropriate Government" means, in 
relation to cantonment authorities and in relation to port authorities 
in major ports, the Central Government, and in relation to other local 
authorities, the State Government.]



</article>



<article><tid>545878</tid>
<number> 3</number> Borrowing powers of local authorities.-
<section><tid>339812</tid>
<number>1</number>A local authority  
may, subject to the prescribed conditions, borrow on the security of 
its funds or any portion thereof for any of the following purposes, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>63303</tid>
<number>i</number>the carrying out of any works which it is legally 
authorized to carry out.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been amended in its application to the C. P. by the 
Local Authorities Loan (C. P. Amendment) Act, <year>1922</year> (C. P. 1 of  
  <year>1922</year>), Maharashtra by (Maha. Act 31 of <year>1975</year>), Himachal Pradesh by 
 (H. P. Act 4 of <year>1974</year>), Himachal Pradesh by (H. P. Act 35 of <year>1976</year>). 
It has been partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws Act, 
<year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>). 
Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
S. 3 and Schedule. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for sub- section (2). 
3. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
4. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1741387</tid>
<number>ii</number>the giving of relief and the establishment and 
maintenance of relief works in times of famine or 
scarcity,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1427260</tid>
<number>iii</number>the prevention of the outbreak or spread of any 
dangerous epidemic disease.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1460682</tid>
<number>iv</number>any measures which may be connected with or ancillary 
to any purposes specified in clauses (ii) and (iii),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300160</tid>
<number>v</number>the repayment of money previously borrowed in accordance 
with law:
Provided that nothing in clause (v) shall be deemed to empower a 
local authority to fix a period for the repayment of any money 
borrowed thereunder which, when the period fixed for the repayment of 
the money previously borrowed is taken into account, will exceed the 
maximum period fixed for the repayment of a loan by or under any 
enactment for the time being in force:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that, in the case of loans other than loans 
made by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government], no amount exceeding twenty- 
five lakhs of rupees shall be borrowed unless the terms, including the 
date of flotation, of such loan have been approved by the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate Government].]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1143904</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorize any 
local authority--

<subsection><tid>134927</tid>
<number>a</number>to borrow or spend money for any purpose for which, 
under the law for the time being in force, it is not 
authorized to apply its funds, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108506</tid>
<number>b</number>to borrow money by means of the issue of bills or 
promissory notes payable within any period not 
exceeding twelve months.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>727241</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>581520</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate  
Government] may make <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> rules consistent with this Act as to--

<subsection><tid>1307040</tid>
<number>i</number>the nature of the funds on the security of which money 
may be borrowed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1669979</tid>
<number>ii</number>the works for which money may be borrowed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1502587</tid>
<number>iii</number>the manner of making applications for permission to 
borrow money;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
3. Subs., ibid., for" G. G. in C.". 
4. For rules applying to all local authorities in Union territories 
and to Cantonment Authorities and port authorities of major 
ports in the former Part A States, see the Local Authorities 
Loans (Central) Rules, <year>1937</year> (Gazette of India, <year>1937</year>, Pt. I, p.  
  <year>1902</year>); and for rules applying to other local authorities in the 
former Part A States, see the Local Authorities Loans Rules, 
<year>1915</year> (Gazette of India, <year>1915</year>, Pt. I, p. <year>1888</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693321</tid>
<number>iv</number>the inquiries to be made in relation to such loans, and 
the manner of conducting such inquiries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918681</tid>
<number>v</number>the cases and the forms in which particulars of 
applications and proceedings, and orders thereon, shall 
be published;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>755621</tid>
<number>vi</number>the cases in which the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may 
make loans <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131449</tid>
<number>vii</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the cases in which local authorities may take loans 
from persons other than the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government];]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>699814</tid>
<number>viii</number>the manner of recording and enforcing the conditions 
on which money is to be borrowed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1305118</tid>
<number>ix</number>the manner and time of making or raising loans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>906009</tid>
<number>x</number>the inspection of any works carried out by means of 
loans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1924031</tid>
<number>xi</number>the instalments, if any, by which loans shall be 
repaid, the interest to be charged on loans, and the 
manner and time of repaying loans and of paying the 
interest thereon;

<subsubsection><tid>1438179</tid>
<number>xii</number>the sum to be charged against the funds which are to 
form the security for the loan, as costs in 
effecting the loan;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1432361</tid>
<number>xiii</number>the attachment of such funds, and the manner of 
disposing of or collecting them;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1433654</tid>
<number>xiv</number>the accounts to be kept in respect of loans;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1474569</tid>
<number>xv</number>the utilization of unexpended balances of loans either 
in the reduction in any way of the debt of the local 
authority, or in carrying out any works which that 
authority is legally authorized to carry out; and the 
sanction necessary to such utilization;
and as to all other matters incidental to carrying this Act into 
effect.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1512128</tid>
<number>3</number>All rules made under this Act shall be published <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> in the 
Official Gazette; and on such publication, shall have effect as if 
enacted in this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1020540</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>836115</tid>
<number>5</number>Remedy by attachment if loan not repaid.- If any money borrowed 
in accordance with the provisions of this Act, or any interest or 
costs due in respect thereof, is or are not repaid according to the 
conditions of the loan, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government], if itself the 
lender, may, and, if the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
2. Certain words rep. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
3. Subs. by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid., for the original clause. 
4. Sub- section (2) rep. by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid. 
5. Certain words rep. by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid. 
6. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Government] is not the lender, shall, on the application of the 
lender, attach the funds on the security of which the loan was made. 
After such attachment, no person, except an officer appointed in this 
behalf by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government], shall in any way deal with 
the attached funds; but such officer may do all acts in respect 
thereof which the borrowers might have done if such attachment had not 
taken place, and may apply the proceeds in satisfaction of the loan 
and of all interests and costs due in respect thereof and of all 
expenses caused by the attachment and subsequent proceedings:

Attachment not to defeat prior charges legally made.-- Provided that 
no such attachment shall defeat or prejudice any debt for which the 
funds attached were previously pledged in accordance with law; but all 
such prior charges shall be paid out of the proceeds of the funds 
before any part of the proceeds is applied to the satisfaction of the 
liability in respect of which such attachment is made.



</article>



<article><tid>812659</tid>
<number> 6</number> Issue of short term bills.-
<section><tid>1350214</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
section 26 of the Indian Paper Currency Act, <year>1910</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, the local 
authorities mentioned in Schedule I and any other local authority to 
which the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, extend the provisions of this section, may, with the 
previous sanction of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate Government], borrow money by 
means of the issue of bills or promissory notes payable within any 
period, not exceeding twelve months, for any purpose for which such 
local authority may lawfully borrow money under any law for the time 
being in force:
Provided that the amount of the bills or promissory notes which 
may be so issued, shall not exceed, when the amount of the other 
moneys for the time being borrowed by such local authority is taken 
into account, the total amount which such local authority is empowered 
by law to borrow.


</section>

<section><tid>1693698</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, by general or special 
order, regulate the conditions on which money may be borrowed or 
repaid under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1891417</tid>
<number> 7</number> Loans not to be effected except under this Act.- Except as 
provided by or under this Act, no local authority shall, for any 
purpose, borrow money upon, or otherwise charge, its funds; and any 
contract otherwise made for that purpose after the passing of this Act 
shall be void:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2. See now s. 31 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>). 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C."


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that nothing herein contained shall be deemed--

<section><tid>1599240</tid>
<number>a</number>to preclude any local authority from exercising the 
borrowing powers conferred on it by any special 
enactment now or hereafter in force; or

</section>

<section><tid>1824893</tid>
<number>b</number>to affect the power conferred on any local authority by 
any such enactment to charge its funds, by guaranteeing 
the payment of interest on money to be applied to any 
purpose to which the funds of the local authority can 
legally be applied.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>397637</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Application of Act to loans existing previous to the fifth 
of September, <year>1871</year>.- The remedy mentioned in section 5 shall be 
available for the recovery of any money lent by the Secretary of State 
in Council to any local authority before the fifth day of September, 
eighteen hundred and seventy- one, and the interest due on such money.]


</article>



<article><tid>507854</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Repeals.]- Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1927</year> (12 of <year>1927</year>), s. 2 
and Sch.

</article>



 </act>