<act><tid>1706443</tid>
<title>THE WAREHOUSING CORPORATIONS ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 19th December, <year>1962</year>.]

An Act to provide for the incorporation and regulation of corporations 
for the purpose of warehousing of agricultural produce and certain 
other commodities and for matters, connected therewith.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>283854</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1297086</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>172849</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>101815</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1068482</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>856316</tid>
<number>a</number>" agricultural produce" means any of the following 
classes of commodities, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1117282</tid>
<number>i</number>foodstuffs, including edible oil- seeds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1007662</tid>
<number>ii</number>cattle fodder, including oil- cakes and 
other concentrates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1877208</tid>
<number>iii</number>raw cotton, whether ginned or unginned, 
and cotton seed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1230283</tid>
<number>iv</number>raw jute; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865715</tid>
<number>v</number>vegetable oils;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>607201</tid>
<number>b</number>" appropriate Government" means in relation to the 
Central Warehousing Corporation, the Central 
Government, and in relation to a State Warehousing 
Corporation, the State Government;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2. 
2  18th March, <year>1963</year>; vide Notification No. G. S. R. 463, dated 16- 3- 
<year>1963</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 155.

This Act shall, in its application to the States specified in the 
Schedule to Act 20 of <year>1965</year>, have effect as if in clause (e) of section 
2 the words and figures" being a commodity with respect to which 
Parliament has power to make laws by virtue of entry 33 in List III in 
the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution" had been omitted: vide Act 
20 of <year>1965</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 27- 11- <year>1965</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1097622</tid>
<number>c</number>" Central Warehousing Corporation" means the Central 
Warehousing Corporation established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>632575</tid>
<number>d</number>" co- operative society" means a society registered or 
deemed to be registered under the Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>), or under any other 
law with respect to co- operative societies for the time 
being in force in any State, which is engaged in the 
processing, marketing, storage, export or import of 
agricultural produce or any notified commodity or in 
insurance business and includes a co- operative land 
mortgage bank;

</section>

<section><tid>716365</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" nationalised bank" means a corresponding new bank 
specified in the First Schedule to the Banking 
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>); <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or a corresponding new bank 
specified in the First Schedule to the Banking 
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, <year>1980</year> (40 of <year>1980</year>).]

</section>

<section><tid>892669</tid>
<number>e</number>" notified commodity" means any commodity (other than  
  agricultural produce) which the Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
a notified commodity for the purposes of this Act, 
being a commodity with respect to which Parliament has 
power to make laws by virtue of entry 33 in List III in 
the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>529698</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1023460</tid>
<number>g</number>" recognised association" means an association which is 
for the time being recognised by the Central Government 
under section 6 of the Forward Contracts (Regulation) 
Act, <year>1952</year> (74 of <year>1952</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1152387</tid>
<number>h</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> 
 (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>331606</tid>
<number>i</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank for the time being 
included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>.) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, and includes a 
nationalised bank];

</section>

<section><tid>64490</tid>
<number>j</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted 
under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1691451</tid>
<number>k</number>" State Warehousing Corporation" means a Warehousing 
Corporation for a State established or deemed to be 
established under this Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>93</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
2 Added by Act 37 of <year>1989</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1117310</tid>
<number>l</number>" Warehousing Corporation" means a Warehousing 
Corporation established or deemed to be established 
under this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>703176</tid>
<number>m</number>" year" means the financial year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1203792</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Construction of references to any law not in force or any 
functionary not in existence in any State. Any reference in this Act 
to any law which is not in force, or any functionary not in existence, 
in any State, shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a 
reference to the corresponding law in force, or the corresponding 
functionary in existence, in that State.]
CHAP

THE CENTRAL WAREHOUSING CORPORATION

CHAPTER II

THE CENTRAL WAREHOUSING CORPORATION



</article>



<article><tid>985826</tid>
<number> 3</number> The Central Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>491396</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such  
date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify in this behalf, the Central Government shall 
establish a Corporation by the name of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation which shall be a body corporate having perpetual 
succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose 
of property and to contract, and may, by the said name, sue and be 
sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1787369</tid>
<number>2</number>The head- office of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall 
be at New Delhi <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or at such other place as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>72159</tid>
<number> 4</number> Share capital and shareholders.
<section><tid>1141279</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorised share  
capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall be twenty crores 
of rupees divided into two hundred thousand shares of the face value 
of one thousand rupees each; any shares remaining to be issued may be 
issued, with the sanction of the Central Government from time to time, 
as and when the Central Warehousing Corporation may deem fit:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that the Central Government may, from time to time, 
by order notified in the Official Gazette, increase the authorised 
share capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation to such extent 
and in such manner as that Government may determine.]


</section>

<section><tid>765566</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> The Central Government shall, after due appropriation made 
by Parliament by law for the purpose,] subscribe for forty per cent. 
of the share capital issued at any time and the remaining sixty per 
cent. of the share capital may be subscribed for within
<pagefootnote><pagenum>94</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1989</year>, s. 4. 
2  18th March, <year>1963</year>, vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 464, dated 16- 3- <year>1963</year>, 
see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, See. 3 (i), p. 155. 
3 Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1963</year>, s. 4. 
4 Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
5 Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" The Central Government shall" (w. e. f.  
  24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such period and in such proportion as may be specified by the Central 
Government, by the following institutions, namely:--


<subsection><tid>1825573</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1477153</tid>
<number>b</number>other scheduled banks;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>54018</tid>
<number>c</number>co- operative societies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>738242</tid>
<number>d</number>insurance companies, investment trusts and other 
financial institutions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>766388</tid>
<number>e</number>recognised associations and companies dealing in 
agricultural produce or any notified commodity.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1752512</tid>
<number>3</number>If any portion of the sixty per cent. of the share capital 
referred to in sub- section (2) remains unallotted, it may be 
subscribed for by the Central Government and the State Bank in such 
proportion as may be agreed upon between them and in default of such 
agreement, as may be determined by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>106492</tid>
<number>4</number>The shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall not 
be transferable except to the Central Government, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State Bank or 
any other scheduled bank], any insurance company, any investment trust 
or other financial institution or any co- operative society or any 
recognised association or company dealing in agricultural produce or 
any notified commodity, in accordance with the regulations made by the 
Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>723817</tid>
<number> 5</number> Shares to be guaranteed by Central Government and to be 
trusted or approved securities.
<section><tid>567952</tid>
<number>1</number>The shares of the Central  
Warehousing Corporation shall be guaranteed by the Central Government 
as to the repayment of the principal and the payment of the annual 
dividend at such minimum rate as may be fixed by the Central 
Government, by notification published in the Official Gazette, at the 
time of the issue of the shares.

</section>

<section><tid>271630</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Acts mentioned in 
this sub- section, the shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation 
shall be deemed to be included among the securities enumerated in 
section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>), and also to be 
approved securities for the purpose of the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>) and the Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289434</tid>
<number> 6</number> Management of Central Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>1066496</tid>
<number>1</number>The general  
superintendence and management of the affairs and business of the 
Central Warehousing Corporation shall vest in a board of directors 
who, with the assistance of an Executive Committee and a managing 
director, may exercise all the powers and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>94A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for" the State Bank, any scheduled 
bank" (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


discharge all the functions which may be exercised or discharged by 
the Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>651518</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors shall act on business principles 
having regard to public interest and shall be guided by such 
instructions on questions of policy as may be given to them by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1659050</tid>
<number>3</number>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a 
question of policy, the decision of the Central Government shall be 
final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1790690</tid>
<number> 7</number> Directors.
<section><tid>1434747</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of directors referred to in section 6  
shall consist of the following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>401994</tid>
<number>a</number>six directors to be nominated by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>519543</tid>
<number>b</number>one director to be nominated by the National Co- 
operative Development Corporation established under the 
National Co- operative Development Corporation Act, 
 <year>1962</year> (26 of <year>1962</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1052364</tid>
<number>c</number>one director to be nominated by the State Bank;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>95</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>721752</tid>
<number>d</number>one director to be elected by other scheduled banks;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>235203</tid>
<number>e</number>one director to be elected by co- operative societies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>529362</tid>
<number>f</number>one director to be elected by insurance companies, 
investment trusts and other financial institutions, 
recognised associations and companies dealing in 
agricultural produce or notified commodities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>491265</tid>
<number>g</number>a managing director, appointed by the Central Government 
in consultation with the directors referred to in 
clauses (a) to (f):
Provided that the three directors to be elected under clauses 
 (d), (e) and (f) may, for the first constitution of the board of 
directors, be nominated by the Central Government in such manner as to 
give representation to each class of institutions (whether they have  
  become shareholders of the Corporation or not) referred to in those 
clauses, but a director so nominated shall hold office only until he 
is replaced by a director elected as provided in that clause, and the 
director so elected shall hold office only for so long as the director 
replaced would have held office had he not been replaced.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>288624</tid>
<number>2</number>The directors referred to in clauses (d), (e) and (f) of sub- 
section (1) shall be elected in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1114872</tid>
<number>3</number>If, within the period prescribed in this behalf, or within 
such further period as the Central Government may allow, the 
institutions referred to in clause (d) or clause (e) or clause (f) of 
sub- section (1) fail to elect a director, the Central Government may 
nominate a director to fill the vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>868985</tid>
<number>4</number>The board of directors shall have a Chairman and a Vice- 
Chairman who shall be appointed by the Central Government from among 
the directors.

</section>

<section><tid>1858122</tid>
<number>5</number>The managing director shall--

<subsection><tid>1434445</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the 
board of directors or the Central Warehousing 
Corporation may entrust or delegate to him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765003</tid>
<number>b</number>receive such salary and allowances as the Central 
Warehousing Corporation may, with the approval of the 
Central Government, fix.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1594751</tid>
<number>6</number>The directors of the Central Warehousing Corporation other 
than the managing director shall be entitled to receive by way of 
remuneration such sums as the Central Warehousing Corporation may, 
with the approval of the Central Government, fix:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no official director shall be entitled to receive 
any remuneration other than the allowances, if any, admissible to him 
under the rules regulating his conditions of service.


</section>

<section><tid>23753</tid>
<number>7</number>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the directors shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>830244</tid>
<number> 8</number> Disqualification for office of director of the Central 
Warehousing Corporation. A person shall be disqualified for being 
chosen as, and for being, a director of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation--
<section><tid>1471934</tid>
<number>i</number>if he is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound 
mind; or

</section>

<section><tid>1879880</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated 
insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has 
compounded with his creditors; or

</section>

<section><tid>108286</tid>
<number>iii</number>if he is or has been convicted of any offence 
involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect 
thereof to imprisonment for not less than six months, 
unless a period of five years has elapsed from the date 
of expiry of the sentence; or

</section>

<section><tid>684607</tid>
<number>iv</number>if he has been removed or dismissed from the service of 
Government or a Corporation owned and controlled by the 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>1793507</tid>
<number>v</number>except in the case of the managing director, if he is a 
salaried official of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation or any State Warehousing Corporation; or

</section>

<section><tid>1376273</tid>
<number>vi</number>if he is personally interested in any subsisting 
contract made with, or in any work being done for the 
Central Warehousing Corporation except as a shareholder 
 (other than a director) in any public company as 
defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>):
Provided that where any such person is a shareholder, he shall 
disclose to the Central Warehousing Corporation the nature and extent 
of shares held by him in such company.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>473461</tid>
<number> 9</number> Removal of directors from office.
<section><tid>229689</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, at any time in consultation with the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, remove the managing director from office after giving him 
a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed 
removal.

</section>

<section><tid>1661904</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors may remove from office any director 
who--

<subsection><tid>475191</tid>
<number>a</number>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 8; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1447700</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the board of directors for 
more than three consecutive meetings of the board 
without cause sufficient in the opinion of the board, 
to exonerate his absence.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>945223</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appointment of officers, etc., and their conditions of 
service.
<section><tid>1037824</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Warehousing Corporation may appoint such  
officers and other employees as it considers necessary for the 
efficient performance of its functions.

</section>

<section><tid>455586</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person employed by the Central Warehousing Corporation 
under this Act shall be subject to such conditions of service and 
shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by 
regulations made by the Corporation under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1798949</tid>
<number> 11</number> Functions of Central Warehousing Corporation. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Central Warehousing Corporation may--
<section><tid>921723</tid>
<number>a</number>acquire and build godowns and warehouses at such 
suitable places in India as it thinks fit;

</section>

<section><tid>144977</tid>
<number>b</number>run warehouses for the storage of agricultural produce, 
seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural implements 
and notified commodities offered by individuals, co- 
operative societies and other institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>903945</tid>
<number>c</number>arrange facilities for the transport of agricultural 
produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural 
implements and notified commodities to and from 
warehouses;

</section>

<section><tid>1463376</tid>
<number>d</number>subscribe to the share capital of a State Warehousing 
Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>1694543</tid>
<number>e</number>act as agent of the Government for the purposes of the 
purchase, sale, storage and distribution of 
agricultural produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, 
agricultural implements and notified commodities; and

</section>

<section><tid>34688</tid>
<number>f</number>carry out such other functions as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1851947</tid>
<number> 12</number> Executive Committee.
<section><tid>244185</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be an Executive  
Committee of the Central Warehousing Corporation which shall consist 
of--

<subsection><tid>621726</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman of the board of 
directors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>26589</tid>
<number>b</number>the managing director; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>67620</tid>
<number>c</number>two other directors chosen by the Corporation in the 
prescribed manner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>98</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1543097</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman and the Vice- Chairman of the board of directors 
shall be the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman respectively of the 
Executive Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>40590</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the general control, direction and superintendence 
of the board of directors, the Executive Committee shall be competent 
to deal with any matter within the competence of the Central 
Warehousing Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>420045</tid>
<number> 13</number> Meetings of the Corporation.
<section><tid>888540</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual general meeting  
of the Central Warehousing Corporation (hereinafter referred to as the  
  annual general meeting) shall be held every year either at its head- 
office or at any other office of the Corporation within six months of 
the close of the financial year, and any other general meeting may be 
convened by the board of directors at any other time.

</section>

<section><tid>405668</tid>
<number>2</number>The shareholders present at the annual general meeting shall 
be entitled to discuss the annual accounts, the report of the board of 
directors on the working of the Corporation during the year under 
report, as well as the auditors, report on the annual balance- sheet 
and accounts.

</section>

<section><tid>1263220</tid>
<number>3</number>The board of directors of the Central Warehousing Corporation 
shall, on the requisition of one- third of the number of shareholders 
of the Corporation, call a special meeting of the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1864728</tid>
<number>4</number>The requisition for a special meeting under sub- section (3) 
shall state the object of the meeting, and shall be signed by the 
requisitionists and deposited at the head- office of the Corporation, 
and may consist of several documents in like form each signed by one 
or more requisitionists.

</section>

<section><tid>903550</tid>
<number>5</number>If the board of directors of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation do not proceed within twenty- one days from the date of the 
requisition being so deposited to cause the special meeting to be 
called, the requisitionists, or a majority of them, may, themselves 
call the meeting, but in either case, the meeting so called shall be 
held within three months from the date of the deposit of the 
requisition.

</section>

<section><tid>1499266</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Warehousing Corporation shall observe such rules 
of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings 
 (including the quorum at meetings) as may be provided by regulations 
made by the Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>99</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>974577</tid>
<number> 14</number> Grants and loans by the Central Government.
<section><tid>1037907</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, pay to the Central Warehousing Corporation for the 
purposes of either fund maintained by the Corporation--

<subsection><tid>851789</tid>
<number>a</number>by way of grants, such sums of money as the Central 
Government may consider necessary; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1046911</tid>
<number>b</number>by way of loans, such grants and loans as the central 
Government may make for the purposes of the 
Warehousing fund; and

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>748725</tid>
<number>2</number>When making a payment under sub- section (1), the Central 
Government shall specify the fund for the purposes of which the 
payment is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1525771</tid>
<number> 15</number> Corporation to maintain two funds. The Central Warehousing 
Corporation shall maintain two separate funds, namely:--
<section><tid>863729</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Warehousing Fund (hereinafter referred to as  
  the Warehousing Fund); and

</section>

<section><tid>1027853</tid>
<number>b</number>the General Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>9305</tid>
<number> 16</number> Warehousing Fund.
<section><tid>1030860</tid>
<number>1</number>To the Warehousing Fund shall be  
credited--

<subsection><tid>1981811</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys and other securities transferred to the 
Central Warehousing Corporation under clause (c) of 
sub- section (2) of section 43;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1722871</tid>
<number>b</number>such grants and loans as the Central Government way 
make for the purposes of the Warehousing Fund; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1796074</tid>
<number>c</number>such sums of money as may, from time to time, be 
realised out of the loans made from the Warehousing 
Fund or from interest on loans or dividends on 
investments made from that fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>119291</tid>
<number>2</number>The Warehousing Fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>1472647</tid>
<number>a</number>for advancing loans to State Governments on such terms 
and conditions as the Central Warehousing Corporation 
may deem fit for the purpose of enabling them to 
subscribe to the share capital of State Warehousing 
Corporations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>146585</tid>
<number>b</number>for advancing loans and granting subsidies to State 
Warehousing Corporations or to State Governments on 
such terms and conditions as the Central Warehousing 
Corporation may deem fit for the purpose of promoting 
the warehousing and storage of agricultural produce

<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and notified commodities, otherwise than through co- 
operative societies;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>902619</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for meeting the expenses incurred in relation to the 
training of personnel, or publicity and propaganda, for 
the purpose of promoting warehousing and storage of 
agricultural produce and notified commodities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1188243</tid>
<number>d</number>for meeting the expenses, including the salary, 
allowances and other remuneration of the officers and 
other employees, incurred in relation to the 
administration of the Warehousing Fund.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>491846</tid>
<number> 17</number> Central Fund.
<section><tid>1172183</tid>
<number>1</number>To the General Fund shall be credited-- 

<subsection><tid>420131</tid>
<number>a</number>all sums received by the Central Warehousing Corporation 
other than those referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 16; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1161750</tid>
<number>b</number>such grants and loans as the Central Government may make 
for the purposes of the General Fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1425235</tid>
<number>2</number>The General Fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>1038168</tid>
<number>a</number>for meeting the salary, allowances and other 
remuneration of the officers and other employees of the 
Central Warehousing Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>372082</tid>
<number>b</number>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the 
Corporation; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871441</tid>
<number>c</number>for carrying out the purposes of this Act;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that the General Fund shall not be applied for 
meeting the expenses referred to in clause (c) or clause (d) of sub- 
section (2) of section 16.]

CHAP

STATE WAREHOUSING CORPORATIONS

CHAPTER III

STATE WAREHOUSING CORPORATIONS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1151393</tid>
<number> 18</number> State Warehousing Corporations.
<section><tid>1740088</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette and with the approval of the 
Central Warehousing Corporation, establish a Warehousing Corporation 
for the State under such name as may be specified in the notification.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>101</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>924538</tid>
<number>2</number>A State Warehousing Corporation established under sub- section 
 (1) shall be a body corporate by the name notified under that sub- 
section, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to 
acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and may, by the 
said name, sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>63003</tid>
<number>3</number>The head- office of a State Warehousing Corporation shall be 
at such place within the State as may be notified in the Official 
Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1270106</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1), (2) 
and (3), it shall not be necessary for the State Government to 
establish a Corporation under sub- section (1) where, under clause (g) 
of sub- section (2) of section 43, a Corporation is deemed to be 
established for that State under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1637665</tid>
<number> 19</number> Share capital and shareholders.
<section><tid>428558</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorised capital of  
a State Warehousing Corporation shall be such sum not exceeding two 
crores of rupees as may be prescribed, divided into shares of the face 
value of one hundred rupees each, of which such number as may be 
determined by the Corporation in consultation with the State 
Government shall be issued in the first instance and the remaining 
shares may be issued, from time to time, as and when the Corporation 
may deem fit after consultation with the Central Warehousing 
Corporation and with the sanction of the State Government:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that in respect of any State Warehousing Corporation 
the Central Government may, after consultation with the State 
Government concerned, from time to time and by order notified in the 
Official Gazette, increase the maximum limit of the authorised capital 
aforesaid to such extent and in such manner as the Central Government 
may determine.]


</section>

<section><tid>287350</tid>
<number>2</number>Of the share capital issued in the first instance and of any 
subsequent issue of such capital, the Central Warehousing Corporation 
shall, in any case where the State Government has subscribed for fifty 
per cent. of such capital, subscribe for the remaining fifty per cent. 
of the capital.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1588276</tid>
<number> 20</number> Management of a state Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>1824227</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
general superintendence and management of the affairs of a State 
Warehousing Corporation shall vest in a board of directors which shall 
consist of the following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1720439</tid>
<number>a</number>five directors nominated by the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, of whom one shall be nominated in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>102</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


consultation with the State Bank and one at least shall 
be a non- official;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>179883</tid>
<number>b</number>five directors nominated by the State Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>729056</tid>
<number>c</number>a managing director, appointed by the State Government 
in consultation with the directors referred to in 
clauses (a) and (b) and with the previous approval of 
the Central Warehousing Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1049347</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be appointed by 
the State Government from among the directors of the State Warehousing 
Corporation with the previous approval of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>207857</tid>
<number>3</number>The managing director shall--

<subsection><tid>1807079</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the 
board of directors or the State Warehousing Corporation 
may entrust or delegate to him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1429209</tid>
<number>b</number>receive such salary and allowances as the State 
Warehousing Corporation may, in consultation with the 
Central Warehousing Corporation, and with previous 
approval of the State Government, fix.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>729715</tid>
<number>4</number>The board of directors shall act on business principles 
having regard to public interest and shall be guided by such 
instructions on questions of policy as may be given to them by the 
State Government or the Central Warehousing Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1536352</tid>
<number>5</number>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a 
question of policy, or, if the State Government and the Central 
Warehousing Corporation give conflicting instructions, the matter 
shall be referred to the Central Government whose decision thereon 
shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1352742</tid>
<number>6</number>The directors of a State Warehousing Corporation, other than 
the managing director, shall be entitled to receive by way of 
remuneration such sums as may be prescribed:
Provided that no official director shall be entitled to receive 
any remuneration other than any allowances admissible to him under the 
rules regulating his conditions of service.


</section>

<section><tid>1985819</tid>
<number>7</number>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, directors shall be such as may be prescribed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1102718</tid>
<number> 21</number> Disqualification for office of director of the corporation. A 
person shall be disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a 
director of a State Warehousing Corporation--
<section><tid>1344253</tid>
<number>i</number>if he is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound 
mind; or

</section>

<section><tid>556162</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated 
insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has 
compounded with his creditors; or

</section>

<section><tid>705556</tid>
<number>iii</number>if he is or has been convicted of any offence 
involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect 
thereof to imprisonment for not less than six months, 
unless a period of five years has elapsed from the date 
of expiry of the sentence; or

</section>

<section><tid>1898022</tid>
<number>iv</number>if he has been removed or dismissed from service of 
Government or a corporation owned and controlled by the 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>1154628</tid>
<number>v</number>except in the case of the managing director, if he is a 
salaried official of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation or a State Warehousing Corporation; or

</section>

<section><tid>1161392</tid>
<number>vi</number>if he is personally interested in a subsisting contract 
made with, or in any work being done for, the State 
Warehousing Corporation except as a shareholder (other  
  than a director) in any public company as defined in 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>):
Provided that where any such person is a shareholder, he shall 
disclose to the Warehousing Corporation the nature and extent of the 
shares held by him in such company.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>103</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1918467</tid>
<number> 22</number> Removal of directors from office.
<section><tid>1257394</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
may, at any time, with the previous approval of the Central 
Warehousing Corporation, remove the managing director from office 
after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed removal.

</section>

<section><tid>1994336</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors may remove from office any director 
who--

<subsection><tid>1798930</tid>
<number>a</number>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 21; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1405266</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the board of directors for 
more than three consecutive meetings of the board 
without cause sufficient, in the opinion of the board, 
to exonerate his absence.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1376340</tid>
<number> 23</number> Appointment of officers, etc., and their conditions of 
service.
<section><tid>1069876</tid>
<number>1</number>A State Warehousing Corporation may appoint such officers  
and other employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions.

</section>

<section><tid>1606989</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person employed by a State Warehousing Corporation 
under this Act shall be subject to such conditions of service and 
shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by 
regulations made by the Corporation under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>843311</tid>
<number> 24</number> Functions of the State Warehousing Corporation. Subject to 
the provisions of this Act, a State Warehousing Corporation may--
<section><tid>185559</tid>
<number>a</number>acquire and build godowns and warehouses at such places 
within the State as it may, with the previous approval 
of the Central Warehousing Corporation, determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1371740</tid>
<number>b</number>run warehouses in the State for the storage of 
agricultural produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, 
agricultural implements and notified commodities;

</section>

<section><tid>1873757</tid>
<number>c</number>arrange facilities for the transport of agricultural 
produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural 
implements and notified commodities to and from 
warehouses;

</section>

<section><tid>966091</tid>
<number>d</number>act as an agent of the Central Warehousing Corporation 
or of the Government for the purposes of the purchase, 
sale, storage and distribution, of agricultural 
produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural 
implements and notified commodities; and

</section>

<section><tid>1074754</tid>
<number>e</number>carry out such other functions as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>104</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1050243</tid>
<number> 25</number> Executive Committee.
<section><tid>829202</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be an Executive  
Committee of a State Warehousing Corporation which shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>985090</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman of the board of directors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1832447</tid>
<number>b</number>the managing director; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1995838</tid>
<number>c</number>three other directors chosen in the prescribed manner, 
of whom one shall be a director referred to in clause 
 (a) of sub- section (1) of section 20.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>248405</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be the Chairman 
of the Executive Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>433981</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to any general or special directions as the board of 
directors may, from time to time, give, the Executive Committee shall 
be competent to deal with any matter within the competence of the 
State Warehousing Corporation.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1621279</tid>
<number> 26</number> Submission of programme of activities and financial 
estimates.
<section><tid>356252</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Warehousing Corporation shall prepare before the  
commencement of each year a statement of programme of its activities 
during the forthcoming year as well as a financial estimate in respect 
thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>613483</tid>
<number>2</number>A statement prepared under sub- section (1) shall, not later 
than three months before the commencement of each year, be submitted 
for approval--

<subsection><tid>265892</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Central Warehousing Corporation, to 
the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>238951</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a State Warehousing Corporation, to the 
Central Warehousing Corporation and the State 
Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1065688</tid>
<number>3</number>The statement and the financial estimate of a Warehousing 
Corporation referred to in sub- section (1) may, with the approval of 
the Central Government in the case of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, or with the approval of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation and the State Government in the case of a State 
Warehousing Corporation, be revised by the Warehousing Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>514829</tid>
<number> 27</number> Borrowing powers of Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>1345594</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
Warehousing Corporation may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank and 
with the previous approval of the appropriate

<pagefootnote><pagenum>105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government, issue and sell bonds and debentures carrying interest for 
the purpose of raising funds:

Provided that the total amount of bonds and debentures issued and 
outstanding and of the other borrowings of the Corporation shall not 
at any time exceed ten times the amount of the paid- up share capital 
and the reserve fund of the Corporation.


</section>

<section><tid>371752</tid>
<number>2</number>A Warehousing Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying 
out its functions under this Act, borrow money--

<subsection><tid>1619929</tid>
<number>i</number>from the Reserve Bank, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1855929</tid>
<number>ii</number>from the State Bank, for such periods for which, and 
upon any of the securities against which, it is 
authorised to advance and lend moneys, under the 
provisions of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23  
  of <year>1955</year>), or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819171</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> from any nationalised bank, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1109499</tid>
<number>iv</number>from such insurance company, investment trust or other 
financial institution as may be approved by the Central 
Government in this behalf.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>860098</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the proviso to sub- section (1), the Central 
Warehousing Corporation may borrow money from the Central Government 
and a State Warehousing Corporation may borrow money from the State 
Government and the Central Warehousing Corporation on such securities 
and on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon between the 
borrowing corporation and the lender, in each case.

</section>

<section><tid>315955</tid>
<number>4</number>The bonds and debentures of a Warehousing Corporation may be 
guaranteed by the appropriate Government as to the repayment of 
principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by 
the appropriate Government on the recommendation of the board of 
directors of the Corporation at the time the bonds or debentures are 
issued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1147031</tid>
<number>28</number>Deposit account. All moneys belonging to a Warehousing 
Corporation shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank or the State Bank 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or any nationalised bank] or, subject to any rules made under this 
Act, in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any other scheduled bank] or co- operative bank.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>106</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 7, for certain words (w. e. f. 24- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for" any scheduled bank" (w. e. f. 24- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1910934</tid>
<number>29</number>Investment of funds. A Warehousing Corporation may invest its 
funds in the securities of the Central or any State Government or in 
such other manner as may be prescribed by the appropriate Government.


</article>



<article><tid>803849</tid>
<number> 30</number> Disposal of profits.
<section><tid>1965850</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Warehousing Corporation shall  
establish a reserve fund out of its annual net profits.

</section>

<section><tid>1608294</tid>
<number>2</number>After making provision for bad and doubtful debts, 
depreciation on assets and all other matters which are usually 
provided for by companies registered and incorporated under the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), a Warehousing Corporation may, out 
of its net annual profits, declare a dividend:
Provided that for so long as the reserve fund is less than the 
paid- up share capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation and until 
there has been repaid to the Central Government such sum, if any, as 
that Government may have paid under a guarantee given in pursuance of 
sub- section (1) of section 5 or sub- section (4) of section 27, the 
rate of such dividend, in the case of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, shall not exceed the rate guaranteed by the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 5.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1375512</tid>
<number> 31</number> Accounts and audit of Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>22629</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
Warehousing Corporation shall maintain proper accounts and other 
relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts including 
the profit and loss account and the balance sheet in such form as may 
be prescribed:
Provided that, in the case of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, the accounts relating to the Warehousing Fund and the 
General Fund shall be maintained separately.


</section>

<section><tid>959002</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of a Warehousing Corporation shall be audited by 
an auditor duly qualified to act as an auditor of companies under 
section 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1583116</tid>
<number>3</number>The said auditor shall be appointed by the appropriate 
Government on the advice of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India.

</section>

<section><tid>590594</tid>
<number>4</number>The auditor shall be supplied with a copy of the annual 
balance sheet and the profit and loss account of the Warehousing 
Corporation and it shall be his duty to examine them together with the 
accounts and vouchers relating thereto, and he shall have a list 
delivered to him of all books kept by the Corporation and shall at all 
reasonable times have access to the books, accounts and other 
documents of the Corporation and may require from any officer of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>107</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Corporation such information and explanations as the auditor may 
think necessary for the performance of his duties as auditor.


</section>

<section><tid>45858</tid>
<number>5</number>The auditor shall make a report to the shareholders on the 
accounts examined by him and on the annual balance sheet and the 
profit and loss account and in every such report, he shall state 
whether in his opinion the accounts give a true and fair view--

<subsection><tid>250579</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the balance sheet, of the state of the 
Corporation' s affairs at the end of its financial year, 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>289003</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the profit and loss account, of the 
profit or loss for its financial year,
and in case he has called for any explanation or information from the 
officers, whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>665439</tid>
<number>6</number>The appropriate Government may, after consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at any time issue directions 
to the auditor requiring him to report to the appropriate Government 
upon the adequacy of measures taken by a Warehousing Corporation for 
the protection of its shareholders and creditors or upon the 
sufficiency of his procedure in auditing the accounts of the 
Corporation and may enlarge or extend the scope of the audit or direct 
that a different procedure in audit may be adopted or direct that any 
other examination may be made by the auditor if in the opinion of the 
appropriate Government public interest so requires.

</section>

<section><tid>222916</tid>
<number>7</number>A Warehousing Corporation shall send a copy of every report 
of the auditor to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and to 
the Central Government at least one month before it is placed before 
the shareholders.

</section>

<section><tid>1342407</tid>
<number>8</number>Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained in this 
section, the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India may, either of 
his own motion or on a request received in this behalf from the 
appropriate Government, undertake in respect of a Warehousing 
Corporation such audit and at such time as he may consider necessary:
Provided that where the Central Government is required to make 
any payment on account of the guarantee given by it under sub- section 
 (1) of section 5, such audit shall be undertaken by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India or any person authorised by him in this 
behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>245862</tid>
<number>9</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
authorised by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of a

<pagefootnote><pagenum>108</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Warehousing Corporation shall have the same rights, privileges and 
authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General has in connection with the audit of Government 
accounts and in particular, shall have the right to demand the 
production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents 
and papers and to inspect the office of the Corporation.


</section>

<section><tid>1966283</tid>
<number>10</number>The annual accounts of a Warehousing Corporation together 
with the audit report thereon shall be placed before the annual 
general meeting of the Corporation within six months of the close of 
the financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1903762</tid>
<number>11</number>Every audit report under this section shall be forwarded to 
the appropriate Government within a month of its being placed before 
the annual general meeting and that Government shall as soon 
thereafter as may be cause the same to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament or the Legislature of the State, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1605414</tid>
<number>31A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Returns and reports. A Warehousing Corporation shall 
furnish to the appropriate Government such returns, statistics, 
accounts and other information with respect to its property or 
activities as that Government may, from time to time, require.]
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1158398</tid>
<number>32</number>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceedings of 
Warehousing Corporations. No act or proceeding of a Warehousing 
Corporation shall be invalid by reason only of the existence of any 
vacancy among its directors or any defect in the constitution thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>183209</tid>
<number>33</number>Delegation. A Warehousing Corporation may, by general or 
special order in writing, delegate to the Secretary or other officer 
of the Corporation, subject to such conditions and limitations, if 
any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and 
functions under this Act as it may deem necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions.


</article>



<article><tid>1543739</tid>
<number>34</number>Voting rights of shareholders. In any meeting of the 
shareholders of a Warehousing Corporation, every member shall have one 
vote in respect of each share held by him in the Corporation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>109</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>632104</tid>
<number>35</number>Disputes between Central Warehousing Corporation and State 
Warehousing Corporation. If there is any difference of opinion between 
the Central Warehousing Corporation and a State Warehousing 
Corporation regarding their respective functions and powers under this 
Act, such difference shall be referred to the Central Government whose 
decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1228358</tid>
<number>36</number>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. Every director, auditor, 
officer or other employee of a Warehousing Corporation shall, before 
entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy 
in the form set out in the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>864040</tid>
<number> 37</number> Indemnity of directors.
<section><tid>1614116</tid>
<number>1</number>Every director of a Warehousing  
Corporation shall be indemnified by the Corporation concerned against 
all losses and expenses incurred in the discharge of his duties except 
such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>614546</tid>
<number>2</number>A director of a Warehousing Corporation shall not be 
responsible for any other director or for any officer or other 
employee of the Corporation or for any loss or expense resulting to 
the Corporation by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or 
title to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the 
Corporation in good faith, or by the wrongful act of any person under 
obligation to the Corporation or by anything done in good faith in the 
execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1475212</tid>
<number> 38</number> Offences.
<section><tid>486142</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever, without the consent in writing of a  
Warehousing Corporation, uses the name of that Corporation in any 
prospectus or advertisement, shall be punishable with imprisonment 
which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>905444</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under sub- 
section (1) otherwise than on a complaint in writing by an officer 
authorised in this behalf by the Warehousing Corporation concerned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1138028</tid>
<number>39</number>Provisions relating to income- tax and super- tax. For the 
purposes of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), a Warehousing 
Corporation shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of that 
Act and shall be liable to income- tax and super- tax accordingly on its 
income, profits and gains:
Provided that, in the case of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation, any sum paid by the Central Government under the 
guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section (1) of section 5 or, in 
the case of a


<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Warehousing Corporation, any sum paid by the Central or a State 
Government under any guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section (4) 
of section 27 shall not be treated as income, profits and gains of a 
Warehousing Corporation, and any interest on the debentures or bonds 
issued by that Corporation out of such sums shall not be treated as 
expenditure incurred by it:

Provided further that in the case of any shareholder or 
debenture- holder, such portion of a dividend or interest as has been 
paid out of any such sum advanced by the Central Government shall be 
deemed to be his income from interest on securities declared to be 
income- tax- free within the meaning of section 86 of that Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1871097</tid>
<number>40</number>Winding up of Warehousing Corporations. No provision of law 
relating to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to 
a Warehousing Corporation and any such Corporation shall not be placed 
in liquidation save by order of the appropriate Government and in such 
manner as it may direct.


</article>



<article><tid>1808870</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1971887</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>596557</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>255180</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional functions which a Warehousing Corporation 
may perform;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1276021</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner of nomination and election of the directors 
of the Central Warehousing Corporation and the period 
within which such directors shall be nominated or 
elected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1297001</tid>
<number>c</number>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, and the remuneration payable to, the 
directors of a Warehousing Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>899864</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner of choosing directors on the Executive 
Committee of a Warehousing Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1164600</tid>
<number>e</number>the authorised capital of a State Warehousing 
Corporation <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> within the maximum limit specified by or 
under sub- section (1) of section 19];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>117046</tid>
<number>f</number>the form of the annual statement of accounts and the 
balance- sheet to be prepared by a Warehousing 
Corporation;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>110A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 10, for certain words (w. e. f. 24- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1273663</tid>
<number>g</number>the deposit of moneys of a Warehousing Corporation in a 
scheduled bank or a co- operative bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>455876</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner of issuing shares of a Warehousing 
Corporation, the calls to be made in respect thereof, 
and all other matters incidental to the issue of 
shares;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>27703</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the form and manner in which returns, statistics, 
accounts and other information are to be furnished, 
under section 31A, by a Warehousing Corporation;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607804</tid>
<number>j</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>] any other matter which has to be or may be 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1135278</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> if before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session] or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1976</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
2 Cl. (i) re- lettered as cl. (j) thereof by s. 10, ibid. (w. e. f.  
  24- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 10, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 24- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>287485</tid>
<number> 42</number> Power of Warehousing Corporations to make regulations.
<section><tid>182363</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
Warehousing Corporation may, with the previous sanction of the 
appropriate Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary 
or expedient for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>756565</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for--

<subsection><tid>609724</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions of service of, and the remuneration 
payable to, the officers and other employees of a 
Warehousing Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>112268</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to 
which, shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation 
may be transferred;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1729309</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which meetings of a Warehousing 
Corporation and the Executive Committee thereof shall 
be convened, the fees for attending such meetings and 
the procedure to be followed thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1625106</tid>
<number>d</number>the duties and conduct of officers and employees of a 
Warehousing Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1228388</tid>
<number>e</number>the powers and duties which may be entrusted or 
delegated to the managing director of a Warehousing 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1956312</tid>
<number>f</number>generally, the efficient conduct of the affairs of a 
Warehousing Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1834912</tid>
<number>3</number>The appropriate Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, rescind any regulation which it has sanctioned and 
thereupon the regulation shall cease to have effect.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1092533</tid>
<number> 43</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1223966</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from the date on which  
the Central Warehousing Corporation is established under section 3, 
the Agricultural Produce (Development and Warehousing) Corporations 
Act, <year>1956</year> (28 of <year>1956</year>), in so far as it has not been repealed by the 
National Co- operative Development Corporation Act, <year>1962</year> (26 of <year>1962</year>), 
shall stand repealed:

</section>

<section><tid>1871664</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal,--

<subsection><tid>1032304</tid>
<number>a</number>the shares allotted and the share certificates issued by 
the Central Warehousing Corporation established under 
the repealed Act (hereinafter referred to as the said  
  Corporation) shall be deemed to have been allotted and 
issued by the Corporation established under section 3 
of this Act as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

if this Act had been in force on the day on which the 
shares were allotted and the share certificates were 
issued;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>28775</tid>
<number>b</number>every shareholder of the said Corporation shall become 
the holder of as many shares in the Corporation 
established under section 3 of this Act as are 
equivalent in number and value to the shares held by 
him in the said Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>564457</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys and other securities belonging to the 
National Warehousing Development Fund which, 
immediately before the said date, was maintained by the 
said Corporation shall stand transferred to and be 
maintained by the Corporation established under section 
 3 of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8267</tid>
<number>d</number>anything done or any action taken (including any  
appointment, nomination, delegation, rule or regulation 
  made) under the repealed Act shall, in so far as it is 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be 
deemed to have been done or taken under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744062</tid>
<number>e</number>every share held by the said Corporation in a State 
Warehousing Corporation under the repealed Act shall be 
deemed to be a share held by the Corporation 
established under section 3 of this Act in the 
corresponding State Warehousing Corporation deemed to 
be established under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1638313</tid>
<number>f</number>all rights, liabilities and obligations of the said 
Corporation, whether arising out of any contract or 
otherwise, shall be the rights, liabilities and 
obligations respectively of the Corporation established 
under section 3 of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1288860</tid>
<number>g</number>a State Warehousing Corporation established for a State 
under the repealed Act shall be deemed to be the State 
Warehousing Corporation established for that State 
under this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>