<act><tid>1824188</tid>
<title>THE REHABILITATION FINANCE ADMINISTRATION ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 23rd March, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to establish the Rehabilitation Finance Administration.

WHEREAS it is expedient to establish a Rehabilitation Finance 
Administration, for the purpose of giving financial assistance on 
reasonable terms to displaced persons to enable them to settle in 
business or industry;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>487799</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1746053</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Rehabilitation Fiance Administration Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>688347</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.]

</section>

<section><tid>1921703</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>536456</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context.--
<section><tid>1644225</tid>
<number>a</number>" Act" means the Rehabilitation Finance Administration 
Act, <year>1948</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1586240</tid>
<number>b</number>" Administration" means the Rehabilitation Fiance 
Administration constituted under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1464637</tid>
<number>c</number>" borrower" means an individual, company, association or 
body of individuals, whether incorporated or not, to 
whom a loan has been advanced under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1048441</tid>
<number>d</number>" displaced person" means--

<subsection><tid>1004634</tid>
<number>i</number>a person who, being displaced from any 
area <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> now forming part of Pakistan] on account 
of civil disturbances or fear of such 
disturbances, has settled and is engaged or 
intends to engage in any business or industry in 
India, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1734603</tid>
<number>ii</number>a person in India who, having had his 
business, industry or property, wholly or 
partially <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in any area
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section (2). 
2.  1st June, <year>1948</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, p. 735. 
3. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 3, for" outside India."


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


now forming part of Pakistan], has lost, wholly or 
partially, such business, industry, or property on 
account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances, and who is engaged, or intends to 
engage in any business or industry in India;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1261628</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>' loan' means a sum of money advanced by the 
Administration--

<subsection><tid>550958</tid>
<number>i</number>to a displaced person for the purpose of 
any business or industry in which he is engaged or 
intends to engage himself, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1328795</tid>
<number>ii</number>in respect of any business or industry, 
a substantial portion of which is owned by 
displaced persons; and]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1921837</tid>
<number>f</number>' prescribed' means prescribed by rules made under 
section 23 or regulations made under section 24.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879106</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment and incorporation.
<section><tid>1986074</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall constitute <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a Corporation called the Rehabilitation Finance 
Administration for giving financial assistance on reasonable terms to 
displaced persons to enable them to settle in business and industry 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or to any business or industry, a substantial portion of which is 
owned by displaced persons].

</section>

<section><tid>353676</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall be a body corporate by the name of the 
Rehabilitation Finance Administration having perpetual succession and 
a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to 
acquire, hold and transfer property, both movable and immovable, and 
shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>709362</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administration shall have its head office at Delhi and 
may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, open 
branches at such places in India as it may consider necessary to 
discharge effectively its functions under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>542026</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of the Administration.
<section><tid>811385</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administration  
shall consist of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1850931</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government 
who shall be called the Chief Administrator;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>591673</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> four] officials appointed by the Central Government; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>372287</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> four] non- officials nominated by the Central 
Government.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 3, for the original clause. 
2. See Gazette of India, <year>1948</year>, Extraordinary, p. 735. 
3. Added by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 4. 
4. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" three".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1778019</tid>
<number>2</number>No act done by the Administration shall be called in question 
on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy or any defect in 
the constitution of the Administration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>801900</tid>
<number> 5</number> Advisory Board.
<section><tid>1755384</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall constitute an  
Advisory Board to advise the Administration on matters of policy and 
may where necessary constitute a Regional Committee to advise each 
branch of the Administration.

</section>

<section><tid>1373533</tid>
<number>2</number>The Advisory Board shall consist of such members, no 
exceeding fifteen in number, as may be nominated by the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>323505</tid>
<number> 6</number> Terms of office of the members of the Administration and the 
Advisory Board.
<section><tid>1410996</tid>
<number>1</number>A member appointed under clauses (a) and (b) of  
sub- section (1) of section 4 shall hold office during the pleasure of 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>482300</tid>
<number>2</number>A member nominated under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of 
section 4 or sub- section (2) of section 5 shall hold office for a term 
of two years from the date of his nomination and shall be eligible for 
re- nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>1103673</tid>
<number>3</number>A nominated member may resign his membership by writing under 
his hand addressed to the Central Government and he shall thereupon 
cease to be a member.

</section>

<section><tid>958622</tid>
<number>4</number>A casual vacancy created by resignation under sub- section (3) 
or by any other reason shall be filled by fresh nomination and the 
person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the 
remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes was 
nominated.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389461</tid>
<number> 7</number> Disclosure of interest.
<section><tid>723853</tid>
<number>1</number>No member of the Administration  
shall have any interest, direct or indirect, in any business, industry 
or concern to which any assistance under section 12 has been given or 
is to be given and if any such member acquires such interest at any 
time during the continuance of such assistance, he shall immediately 
disclose it to the Administration and shall either resign his 
membership or dispose of his interest in such manner and within such 
time as he may be directed by it.

</section>

<section><tid>1120811</tid>
<number>2</number>Any member of the Advisory Board who has any interest, direct 
or indirect, in any business, industry or concern to which any 
assistance under section 12 has been given or is to be given or 
acquires such interest at any time during the continuance of such 
assistance shall immediately disclose it to the Administration and 
shall not participate in the proceedings of the Advisory Board 
relating to such assistance.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1051070</tid>
<number>8</number>Removal from membership. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
section 6, the Central Government may, for any reason which may appear 
to it to be sufficient, remove any member at any time from the 
Administration or the Advisory Board.


</article>



<article><tid>1979600</tid>
<number>9</number>The Chief Administrator. The Chief Administrator shall be a 
whole- time servant of the Administration and shall receive such 
salaries and allowances and shall be subject to such terms and 
conditions as may be determined by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>518363</tid>
<number> 10</number> Staff. The Administration may, in the manner prescribed 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>,--
<section><tid>709199</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint a Deputy Chief nAdministrator and such other 
officers and servants as may be required to enable it 
to carry out the functions under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>500170</tid>
<number>b</number>fix the salary and allowances or other conditions of 
service of the Deputy Chief Administrator, other 
officers and servants;

</section>

<section><tid>1445143</tid>
<number>c</number>fix the remuneration and allowances payable to the 
members of the Administration and of the Advisory 
Board:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that the appointment and the fixation of the 
salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Deputy 
Chief Administrator and such other officers as may be prescribed 
by the Central Government, shall be subject to the previous 
sanction of that Government.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>895254</tid>
<number> 11</number> Funds of the Administration. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>432702</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may from time to time advance money to the Administration for its 
business, the aggregate amount of which,--

<subsection><tid>1215892</tid>
<number>a</number>for the purpose of enabling the Administration to 
advance loans, shall not, save as hereinafter provided, 
exceed twelve crores and fifty lakhs of rupees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1224513</tid>
<number>b</number>for the purpose of enabling the Administration to meet 
any liability which it may incur in guaranteeing losses 
in respect of loans advanced by scheduled banks, shall 
no exceed two crores of rupees:
Provided that if, after the lapse of such period from the 
commencement of this Act as the Central Government may think fit to 
fix in this behalf, any sum of money earmarked for the purpose 
specified

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" and with the prior sanction of the Central Government" 
omitted by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 6. 
2. Added by s. 6, ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in clause (b) is found not to have been actually advanced for that 
purpose and is not, in the opinion of the Central Government, likely 
to be required for the said purpose, the Central Government may 
utilize the money for making advances from time to time to the 
Administration for the purpose specified in clause (a), and when any 
such advance is made, the limit specified in clause (a) shall be 
deemed to have been correspondingly increased.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1118094</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Subject to any regulations that may be made in this 
behalf, all moneys belonging to the Administration which are not 
immediately required by the Administration for any purpose] shall be 
deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or any agents thereof or 
invested in such securities as may be approved by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>166645</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administration shall pay interest on the money so 
advanced at the rate of 3 per cent. per annum to the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1830369</tid>
<number> 12</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Business of the Administration. The Administration may--
<section><tid>1061343</tid>
<number>a</number>subject to the provisions of section 13, advance loans;

</section>

<section><tid>1640714</tid>
<number>b</number>guarantee, on such terms and conditions as may be 
agreed upon, losses which a scheduled bank may suffer 
in respect of any loan advanced by it and approved by 
the Administration:
Provided that the total amount which may be 
guaranteed in respect of any scheduled bank and 
the terms and conditions on which such guarantee 
may be given shall be subject to the prior 
approval of the Central Government:

Provided further that the maximum liability 
of the Administration under such guarantee shall 
not exceed the amount for the time being available 
under clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 11;


</section>

<section><tid>189466</tid>
<number>c</number>do all such acts and things as may be incidental to or 
consequential upon the performance of its functions 
under this Act including the running of the 
Administration.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628465</tid>
<number> 13</number> Loans.
<section><tid>1741091</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may prescribe the limits as  
to amounts within which loans may be advanced by the Administration.

</section>

<section><tid>291675</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of advancing any loan under sub- section (1), 
the Administration may call for any report either through its own 
staff, or through the District Officer of the district in which the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1950</year>, s. 7 for" All moneys belonging to the 
Administration". 
2 Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1953</year>, s. 3, for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


borrower resides or carries on business, or through any State <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
Government, or through any Bank or any other appropriate agency.


</section>

<section><tid>488528</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administration shall charge interest from the borrower at 
such rate not exceeding 6 per cent, per annum as may be specified by 
it.

</section>

<section><tid>1925305</tid>
<number>4</number>The period of the loan shall not exceed <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fifteen] years.

</section>

<section><tid>594462</tid>
<number>5</number>The loan may be advanced either for fixed capital or working 
capital or for both.
The assets created from the loan shall, notwithstanding any law 
or usage to the contrary, be deemed to be mortgaged to the 
Administration for the repayment of the loan together with the 
interest thereon and the amount of the loan and the interest thereon 
shall be first charge on such assets.


</section>

<section><tid>423169</tid>
<number>6</number>The Administration may also take such further security for 
any loan as it may consider necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>544360</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to call for repayment before agreed period. 
Notwithstanding any agreement to the contrary, the Administration may, 
be notice, require any borrower forthwith to repay in full with 
interest thereon any loan borrowed from it,--
<section><tid>164286</tid>
<number>a</number>if it appears to the Administration that false or 
misleading information in any material particular was 
given by the borrower for obtaining the loan or while 
furnishing any information under section 17; or

</section>

<section><tid>871632</tid>
<number>b</number>if the borrower has failed to comply with the terms of 
the contract with the Administration in the matter of 
the loan; or

</section>

<section><tid>1412575</tid>
<number>c</number>if there is a reasonable apprehension that the borrower 
is unable to pay his debts or that insolvency 
proceedings or proceedings for liquidation may be 
commenced against him; or

</section>

<section><tid>1633122</tid>
<number>d</number>if for any other reason it is necessary in the opinion 
of the Administration to protect the interests of the 
Administration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>964682</tid>
<number> 15</number> Mode of recovery. If the amount of loan or any instalment 
thereof or interest thereon which is due, in accordance with the terms 
of the contract or under the provisions of section 14, has not been 
repaid the Administration may,--
<section><tid>1321260</tid>
<number>a</number>without prejudice to any other remedy provided by law, 
recover such loan, instalment or interests as arrears 
of land revenue, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or a State" omitted by Act 36 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
II. 
2 Subs, by Act 36 of <year>1953</year>, s. 4, for" ten".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1969690</tid>
<number>b</number>take charge of the business or industry of the borrower 
on such terms and conditions as it may deem fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>685508</tid>
<number> 16</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>730284</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administration shall maintain  
proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual 
statement of accounts including the profit and loss account and the 
balance- sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India.

</section>

<section><tid>255922</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Administration shall be audited annually 
by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure 
incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Administration to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>641302</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Administration shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Administration.

</section>

<section><tid>1654438</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Administration as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1621167</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power of inspection.
<section><tid>1624196</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Administrator or any other  
officer authorized by him in writing in this behalf may, be order, 
require any borrower to furnish such information or to produce such 
books of accounts and other documents for inspection at such time and 
place as may be specified in the order and the borrower shall comply 
with such order.

</section>

<section><tid>357290</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Administrator or such officer may inspect such 
books of accounts or documents produced and take extracts therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>683651</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Administrator or the officer making the inspection 
or any person working under his order shall not communicate or allow 
to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any 
information relating to the affairs of the borrower.

</section>

<section><tid>938957</tid>
<number>4</number>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (3) he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may 
extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees or with both.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1953</year>, s. 5, for the former section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1061218</tid>
<number> 18</number> Returns.
<section><tid>140062</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administration shall furnish to the Central  
Government a half- yearly report together with accounts and such other 
information within such time and in such manner as may be specified by 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>311396</tid>
<number>2</number>The report shall be laid before <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Parliament] as soon as may 
be after it is prepared.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1438385</tid>
<number>19</number>Power of Central Government to give direction. For the 
purposes of this Act, the Central Government may, from time to time, 
give to the Administration such general or special directions as it 
thinks fit, and the Administration shall, in the exercise of its 
functions under this Act, comply with any such directions.


</article>



<article><tid>1190380</tid>
<number>20</number>Exemption from taxes. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>), or in any other 
enactment for the time being in force relating to income- tax, super- 
tax or business profits tax, the Administration shall not be liable to 
pay any income- tax, super- tax or business profits tax on any incomes, 
profits or gains.


</article>



<article><tid>1694331</tid>
<number> 21</number> Liquidation of the Administration.
<section><tid>1887076</tid>
<number>1</number>No provision of law  
relating to insolvency or to the winding up of companies or 
corporation shall apply to the Administration and the Administration 
shall not be placed in liquidation save by the order of the Central 
Government and in such manner as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1394283</tid>
<number>2</number>In the event of the Administration being placed in 
liquidation, the assets of the Administration, after meeting the 
liabilities, if any, shall vest in the Central Government shall 
thereupon have all the powers of the Administration in recovering the 
loans remaining unpaid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635558</tid>
<number>22</number>Delegation. The Administration may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that any power or duty which under any of the 
provisions of this Act is conferred or imposed upon the Administration 
shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may 
be specified in the direction, be exercised or discharged by the Chief 
Administrator, Deputy Chief Administrator or any other person 
subordinate to the Administration.


</article>



<article><tid>830237</tid>
<number>23</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for the purpose of 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Central Legislature." 
2. For the Rehabilitation Finance Administration Rules, <year>1948</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1948</year>, Extraordinary, p. 955.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1678960</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1012823</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administration may, with  
the previous sanction of the Central Government, make regulations, not 
inconsistent with this Act or the rules made thereunder, to provide 
for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the 
purpose of giving effect tot he provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>31873</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power such regulation may provide for--

<subsection><tid>915495</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions on which a person may be recognised as a 
displaced person,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1271658</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner and the time of the general meetings of the 
Administration, or Advisory Board or Regional Committee 
and the procedure to the followed thereat and the 
manner in which right of voting may be exercised,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1371270</tid>
<number>c</number>the terms on which the Administration may grant loans.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1286095</tid>
<number>d</number>forms of returns and statements required under this 
Act,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200906</tid>
<number>e</number>the duties and conduct, salaries, allowances and 
conditions of service of officers, servants and agents 
of the Administration,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>113127</tid>
<number>f</number>manner and form of application for loans and contracts.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>230774</tid>
<number>g</number>manner in which accounts of the Administration shall be 
kept and audited.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95098</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which and the conditions under which the 
business or industry of a person to whom a loan has 
been advanced may be taken charge of and administered 
under section 15,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>103294</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which has to be or may be specified 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>288124</tid>
<number>3</number>All regulations made under this section shall be published in 
the Official Gazette and shall came into force on such date as may be 
specified therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1422618</tid>
<number>25</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Laying of rules and regulations before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>