<act><title>THE RAILWAY CLAIMS TRIBUNAL 
(PROCEDURE FOR INVESTIGATION OF MISBEHAVIOUR OR INCAPACITY OF THE CHAIRMAN, 
VICE-CHAIRMAN AND MEMBERS) RULES, 1991 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Railway Claims Tribunal (Procedure 
for Investigation of Misbehaviour or Incapacity of the Chairman, Vice-Chairman 
and Members) Rules, 1991. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the 
date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  

</section></article> 

 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. 
</title>In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Judge means the Judge of the Supreme Court appointed for 
  conducting an inquiry under rule 3; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Member means the Member of the Claims Tribunal 
  established under section 3 of the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987 (54 of 
  1987) and includes the Chairman, Vice-Chairman of such Tribunal against whom 
  investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity is being made under these rules; 
  
 </section><section><number>c</number> words and expressions used herein and not 
  defined but defined in the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987 (54 of 1987), 
  shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act. 
</section></article> 

 <article><title><number>3</number> Judge to conduct 
inquiry. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Whenever the Central Government is of the opinion that 
there are reasonable grounds for making an inquiry into truth of any imputation 
of misbehaviour or incapacity of a Member, it may, after consulting the Chief 
Justice of India, by notification in the Official Gazette appoint a judge for 
the purpose of conducting such inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notice of appointment of a Judge under sub-rule 
(1) shall also be given to such Member. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Powers of Judge. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The Judge shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the 
Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, but shall be guided by the principles of natural 
justice and shall have power to regulate his own procedure including the fixing 
of places and times of his enquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Judge shall have, for the purposes of discharging his 
functions under these rules, the same powers as are vested in a civil court 
under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
  examining him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> subject to the provisions of sections 123 &amp; 
  124 of Indian Evidence Act, 1872, requisitioning any public record or document 
  or copy of such record or document from any office. 
</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 26-11-1991.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>