<act><title>


The Limestone and Dolomite Mines Labour 
    Welfare Fund Rules, 19731</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Limestone and Dolomite Mines Labour Welfare Fund 
    Rules, 1973.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the 1st day of December, 1973. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>   ‘The Act’ means the Limestone and 
    Dolomite Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972 (62 of 1972);
 

1[***]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   ‘Central Advisory Committee’ means a 
    Committee constituted under section 7 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   ‘Chairman’ means the Chairman of an 
    Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   ‘Commissioner’ means a Limestone and 
    Dolomite Mines Welfare Commissioner appointed by the Central Government 
    under section 8, for the State or States concerned;  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   ‘Form’ means a form appended to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>   ‘Fund’ means the Limestone and Dolomite 
    Mines Labour Welfare Fund;  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>   ‘Member’ means a member of an Advisory 
    Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>   ‘Schedule’ means a schedule appended to 
    these Rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number>   ‘section’ means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number>   ‘Treasury’ means any Government 
    Treasury or sub-treasury.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number>
Composition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The Central Advisory Committee shall consist of 
    the following persons, to be appointed by the Central Government namely:—  
 

1[(i)   
    Chairman;  
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   an officer of the Central Government 
    who shall be the Vice-chairman, ex offico;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   two officers of the Central Government 
    to be nominated by the Government, ex officio;  
 

2[(iv)   
    Three Welfare Commissioners to be nominated by the Central Government, ex 
    officio;]  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   such number of persons to represent the 
    owners of limestone and dolomite mines as are equal in number to the 
    aggregate of those provided in sub-clauses (ii) to (iv) to be appointed, 
    after consultation with such organisations, if any, of the owners as may be 
    recognised by the Central Government in this behalf;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   such number of persons, of whom one 
    shall be a woman, to represent the persons employed in limestone and 
    dolomite mines as are equal in number to those provided in sub-clause (v) to 
    be appointed, after consultation with such organisations, if any, of persons 
    so employed, as may be recognised by the Central Government in this behalf.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> An officer 
    of the Central Government shall be the Secretary of the Central Advisory 
    Committee and shall be entitled to attend and take part in the meetings of 
    the Committee, but shall not be entitled to vote.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Each 
    Advisory Committee constituted under section 6 shall consist of the 
    following persons, to be appointed by the Central Government, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the Chairman;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   an officer called the Limestone and 
    Dolomite Mines Welfare Commissioner, who shall be the Vice-Chairman—ex 
    officio;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   one representative of the Central 
    Government—ex officio;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   a member of the Legislative Assembly 
    appointed in consultation with the Government of the State concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   two persons to represent the owners of 
    the limestone and dolomite mines, to be appointed, after consultation with 
    the organisations of the owners, if any, as may be recognised by the Central 
    Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   two persons to represent the persons 
    employed in the Limestone and Dolomite Mines, to be appointed after 
    consultation with the organisations of the persons employed, if any, as may 
    be recognised by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   a woman if no woman has been appointed 
    under sub-clause (vi).  
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> An officer 
    of the Limestone and Dolomite Mines labour Welfare Organisation of the State 
    or States concerned shall be the Secretary of the Advisory Committee and 
    shall be entitled to attend and take part in the meetings of the Committee, 
    but shall not be entitled to vote.  
 
 







 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Term of 
    office.—
<section><number>1</number> A member shall, 
    unless he resigns his office or dies an earlier date, hold office for a 
    period not exceeding three years, as may be determined by the Central 
    Government in each case, from the date of publication of the notification 
    appointing him a member of the Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory 
    Committee as the case may be, and shall be eligible for re-appointment:  
 
Provided that 
    an outgoing member may continue in office until the appointment of his 
    successor is notified in the Gazette of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member 
    appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for as long as the 
    member whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office if the 
    vacancy had not occurred.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a 
    member is unable to attend a meeting of the Advisory Committee or the 
    Central Advisory Committee the Central Government may nominate, or the body 
    which is represented by him may, by notice in writing signed on its behalf 
    and by the said member, addressed to the Chairman of the Committee, depute a 
    substitute in his place to attend the meeting and such nominated or deputed 
    member shall have all the rights of a member in respect of that meeting.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Resignation.—A non-official 
    member may resign his office by letter addressed to the Chairman and the 
    resignation shall take effect from the date of its acceptance or on the 
    expiry of thirty days from the date of its receipt by the Chairman whichever 
    is earlier.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Absence 
    from India.—
<section><number>1</number> Before a 
    non-official member leaves India he shall intimate to the Chairman the date 
    of his departure from and the date of his expected return to India, and if 
    he intends to be absent from India for a period longer than six months, he 
    shall tender his resignation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    such member leaves India without taking action as required under sub-rule 
    (1), he shall be deemed to have resigned with effect from the date of his 
    departure from India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Vacation 
    of office.—A non-official member 
    shall be deemed to have vacated has office—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if he becomes of unsound mind or is 
    declared insolvent; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if he is convicted for any offence which 
    in the opinion of the Central Government involves moral turpitude; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   if he is absent from three-consecutive 
    meetings of the Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee without 
    leave of absence from the Chairman; or  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   if, in the opinion of the Central 
    Government it is not desirable that he should continue to be a member of the 
    committee; or  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   if he ceases to represent the interest 
    for representing which he was appointed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    co-opt.—
<section><number>1</number> An Advisory Committee 
    or the Central Advisory Committee may, at any time and for such period as it 
    thinks fit, co-opt any person or persons to the Advisory committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    co-opted under sub-rule (1) shall exercise all the powers and functions of a 
    member under these rules, but shall not be entitled to vote.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    invite persons to attend meetings.—An 
    Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee or its Chairman may at 
    any time and for such meeting or meetings as is or are considered necessary, 
    invite any person or persons to attend the meeting or meetings of the 
    Committee and a person or persons so invited shall exercise all the powers 
    of a member under these rules, except that he or they shall not be entitled 
    to vote on any question coming before the Committee.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Remuneration to members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every non-official member, including a non-official member co-opted under 
    rule 8, shall be entitled to receive travelling allowance and daily 
    allowance 

    1[and conveyance 
    allowance] in accordance with the instructions contained in the Ministry of 
    Finance Office Memorandum No. F. 6 (26)-E. IV/59, dated the 5th September, 
    1960, as for the time being in force.  
 


    2[***]  
 


    3[(2)] The allowances 
    under this rule shall be admissible only on production of a certificate by 
    the non-official members to the effect that they have not claimed or drawn 
    travelling or daily allowance 

    1[or conveyance 
    allowance] in respect of the journeys and halts from any other source.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Disposal of Business.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    question which an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee is 
    required to take into consideration shall be considered either at a meeting 
    or, if the Chairman so directs, by sending the necessary papers to every 
    member for opinion:  
 
Provided that 
    the papers may not be sent to a member who is absent from India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a 
    question is referred to an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory 
    Committee for opinion, any member may request that the question be 
    considered at a meeting and thereupon the Chairman may, and if, the request 
    is made by three or more members, shall, direct that it be so considered.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If not 
    less than three members of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory 
    Committee request the Chairman thereof to refer any matter to the Committee, 
    the Chairman shall refer that matter to it accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Time 
    and place of meeting.—An Advisory 
    Committee or the Central Advisory Committee shall meet at such places and 
    times as may be appointed by the Chairman.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Notice 
    of meetings and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notice shall be given to every member present in India of the time and place 
    fixed for each ordinary meeting at least fifteen days before such meeting 
    and every member shall be furnished with a list of business to be considered 
    at the meeting:  
 
Provided that 
    when an emergency meeting is called by the Chairman such notice shall not be 
    necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    business which is not on the list shall be considered at a meeting without 
    the permission of the Chairman.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Presiding at meetings.—The 
    Chairman shall preside at every meeting at which he is present and in his 
    absence, the Vice-Chairman shall preside.  
   

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Quorum.—No 
    business shall be transacted at a meeting of an Advisory Committee or the 
    Central Advisory Committee whether an ordinary or emergency meeting unless 
    at least three members in the case of an Advisory Committee and ten members 
    in the case of the Central Advisory Committee having the right to vote are 
    present, of whom the Chairman or Vice-Chairman shall be one:  
 
Provided that 
    if at any meeting less than three or ten, as the case may be of such members 
    attend, the Chairman may adjourn the meeting to a date not less than seven 
    days later, informing the members present and sending notice to the other 
    members that he proposes to dispose of the business at the adjourned meeting 
    whether there is a quorum or not and it shall thereupon be lawfully dispose 
    of the business at the adjourned meeting irrespective of the number of 
    members attending it.  
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Recommendation by majority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every question at a meeting of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory 
    Committee shall be decided by majority of votes of the members present and 
    voting on that question; but the minority shall in all cases have the right 
    of requiring their dissent to be noted.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    question referred to the members for opinion shall, unless the Chairman in 
    pursuance of sub-rule (2) of rule 11 reserves it for consideration at a 
    meeting, be decide in accordance with the opinion of the majority of members 
    recording opinion with the time allowed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the 
    case of an equal division of votes or opinion, the Chairman shall be given 
    an additional vote or opinion.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Minutes 
    of meetings.—The proceedings of 
    each meeting of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee 
    shall be circulated to all members present in India, as soon as possible 
    after the meeting, shall be read out and confirmed at the next meeting of 
    the Committee, shall be signed by the Chairman or the Vice-Chairman 
    presiding, as the case may be, and shall thereafter be recorded in a minute 
    book, which shall be kept for permanent record.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Headquarters of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee.—The 
    headquarters of an Advisory Committee shall be at such place or places as 
    may be fixed by the Central Government and the headquarters of the Central 
    Advisory Committee shall be in New Delhi.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Executive of an Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioner shall be the Chief Executive of an Advisory Committee and 
    exercise the executive functions of the Committee on its behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Secretary of an Advisory Committee shall carry out routine duties and shall 
    exercise such powers and discharge such duties as the Commissioner may, with 
    the approval of the Central Government, delegate to him.  
  
 



 



 

 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 


    1[***]  
 
 







 



 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number> Conditions of service of persons appointed 
      under section 8 of the Act.—Until other provision is made in this behalf, 
      persons appointed under section 8 of the Act shall be governed by such 
      rules relating to the terms and conditions of service of Government 
      servants generally, as may be made applicable, with modification, if any, 
      to such persons by the Central Government.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Schemes 
    of expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> The sanction 
    of the Central Government to the budget shall, if no specific mention is 
    made to the contrary, be deemed to include sanction to expenditure on all 
    approved schemes included in the budget.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commissioner shall have power, subject to the provision in the sanctioned 
    budget, to incur expenditure on administrative staff and welfare schemes:  
 
Provided that—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   he shall have no powers to sanction any 
    scheme, not included in the budget, if it involves expenditure exceeding Rs. 
    50,000 non-recurring and Rs. 5,000 recurring a year; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any new scheme within these limits 
    shall requires the approval of the Finance Sub-Committee before any 
    expenditure on it is incurred.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may sanction without reference to the Advisory Committee, 
    expenditure on contingencies, supplies and services and purchases of 
    articles required for the running of the organisation under him subject to 
    financial provision in the sanctioned budget and to the condition that the 
    expenditure on any single object shall not exceed Rs. 2,000 non-recurring 
    and Rs. 400 recurring.
  
 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The annual budget as prepared by the executive in consultation with the 
    Finance Sub-Committee shall be considered by the Advisory Committee, 
    concerned each year and thereafter a copy of the budget, as approved by the 
    Advisory Committee, shall be forwarded not later than the 1st day of October 
    each year for sanction to the Central Government which may make such 
    alterations therein as it considers necessary before according its sanction.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The budget 
    to be forwarded to the Central Government shall be accompanied by detailed 
    self-contained notes explaining new schemes included therein.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Other 
    matters to be considered by an Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An Advisory Committee shall, besides carrying out its statutory duties, 
    consider and advise upon any matter concerning these rules referred to it by 
    the Central Government or State Government for advice.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    Advisory committee shall also consider the budget and any other matter that 
    may be laid before it by the Commissioner.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Committee to be informed of expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A memorandum setting forth any grant made or expenditure incurred since the 
    last meeting shall be laid at each meeting of an Advisory Committee.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Finance 
    Sub-Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> An Advisory 
    Committee shall elect from among its members two persons of whom one shall 
    be a person representing owners of the limestone mines or dolomite mines or 
    of both and the other representing the workers of the limestone mines or 
    dolomite mines or of both, to constitute a Finance Sub-Committee of which 
    the Commissioner shall be an additional member and president.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    Advisory Committee may at any time co-opt a person or persons to the Finance 
    Sub-Committee and any person so co-opted shall exercise all the powers and 
    functions of a member of such sub-committee, but shall not be entitled to 
    vote and shall not solely by reason of being so co-opted by a member of that 
    Advisory Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notice of 
    every meeting of the Finance Sub-Committee shall be sent to the Chairman of 
    the Advisory Committee who may attend such meeting if he desires, and if he 
    does so attend, he shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule 
    (1), preside and shall be entitled to vote.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Duties 
    of the Finance Sub-Committee.—The 
    duties of the Finance Sub-Committee shall be to frame schemes of 
    expenditure, to advise on the budget drawn up by the executive of the 
    Advisory Committee and on the accounts of the Advisory Committee and also in 
    regard to all expenditure and to consider all schemes referred to in proviso 
    (ii) to run 22.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Other 
    Sub-Committees.—An Advisory 
    Committee, may as and when considered necessary, constitute from among its 
    members, as many sub-committees as it may deem necessary for considering and 
    reporting on such matters as may be specifically assigned to it.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Meetings of Sub-Committees.—The 
    meetings and proceedings of the Finance Sub-Committee and any other 
    sub-committee which may be constituted under rule 28 shall be governed by 
    the provisions herein contained for regulating the meetings and proceedings 
    of an Advisory Committee in so far as the same are applicable.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Grants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In each case in which a grant is made by or with the approval of the Central 
    Government to a State Government, a local authority, the owner of a 
    limestone or dolomite mine, or any other person, in aid of any scheme 
    approved by the Central Government for the purposes of the Act, the Central 
    Government may impose conditions necessary for ensurings—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the work for which the grant is 
    made is duly and promptly executed and the money is actually utilsed for the 
    purpose for which it is granted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the date on which the grant is 
    calculated are in accordance with facts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that any particulars which the Central 
    Government may from time to time require for the proper discharge of its 
    responsibilities are promptly supplied;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that all necessary facilities for 
    inspection are accorded to persons duty authorised by the Central Government 
    for the purpose of clause (a) or for checking the correctness of any 
    particulars supplied under clause (c) or for the collection of any such 
    particulars;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that proper accounts of the money 
    granted are kept and are submitted for audit by such persons as the Central 
    Government may authorise in this behalf; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   that an additional statement of accounts 
    together with a certificate of a Registered Accountant or other recognised 
    body of auditors to the effect that the accounts are correct, is furnished 
    by the grantee.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Before 
    making a grant to a local authority, or the owner of a limestone or dolomite 
    mine or any other person the Central Government shall require such local 
    authority or owner or such person to execute a bond for the fulfilment of 
    conditions imposed by the Central Government under sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    be the condition of every bond executed under sub-rule (2) that in the event 
    of the local authority or owner of the mine or such person violating any 
    condition imposed under sub-rule (1) such local authority or owner or person 
    shall be liable to pay to the Central Government such sum by way of penalty 
    as may be specified in the bond in addition to the refund of the entire 
    remaining grant-in-aid.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>31</number> Standard of 
    dispensary or hospital services.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The standard of dispensary or hospital services to be provided by owners of 
    limestone or dolomite mines for the purpose of getting the grants-in-aid 
    envisaged under clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act shall 
    be as specified in Scheduled I and IA as the case may be (hereafter in this 
    rule and in rules 32 and 33 referred to as the prescribed standard).  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There 
    shall be maintained an independent dispensary or hospital at the site of 
    each limestone or dolomite mine according to the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that 
    a common main dispensary or hospital may be maintained for several limestone 
    or dolomite mines with branch dispensaries or hospitals attached to each 
    limestone or dolomite mine subject to the following conditions, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the common main dispensary or hospital 
    shall maintain the standards prescribed for the aggregate number of workers 
    of all the limestone or dolomite mines served by it or the standard 
    maintained by it during the year 1973 in case of common main dispensary and 
    before the publication of these rules in case of maintenance of hospitals, 
    whichever is higher;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   every branch dispensary or hospital 
    shall have a qualified doctor and a qualified compounder (Pharmacist);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the common main dispensary or hospital 
    shall be so situated that none of the limestone or dolomite mines served by 
    it is more than fifteen kilometres away from it; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the common main dispensary or hospital 
    shall maintain an ambulance van for taking serious cases of injury and 
    sickness from the branch dispensary or hospital to the common main 
    dispensary or hospital.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Welfare Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that any dispensary or hospital 
    is being efficiently run and saves the purpose for which it is established, 
    for reasons to be recorded in writing, waive any of the requirement 
    specified in the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that 
    no such dispensary or hospital shall contain any room other than a store 
    room which is less than four metres by three metres in area:  
 
Provided 
    further that a medical licentiate may be appointed to be in charge of a 
    dispensary or hospital catering to more than 250 workers only if he has ten 
    year’s experience as a medical officer in independent charge of a main 
    dispensary.]
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>32</number> Inspection of 
    dispensary or hospital.—The dispensary or hospital maintained by owners 
    of Limestone or Dolomite Mines shall be inspected annually by the Welfare 
    Commissioner of the region and the Senior Most Medical Officer jointly. They 
    shall, if the dispensary or hospital conforms to the prescribed standard of 
    the dispensaries or hospitals of the Labour Welfare Organisation, as the 
    case may be, issue a certificate in Form A which shall be valid for a period 
    of one year from the date of the issue.]
 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number>†
 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Standard of maternity centre.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The standard of maternity centre to be provided by owners of limestone or 
    dolomite mines for the purpose of getting the grants-in-aid envisaged in 
    clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act shall be as specified 
    in Schedule II, hereinafter in this rule and in rules 35, 36 and 37 referred 
    to as the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There 
    shall be maintained an independent maternity centre at each limestone or 
    dolomite mine according to the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that 
    a common main maternity centre may be maintained for several limestone or 
    dolomite mines with branch maternity centres attached to each limestone or 
    dolomite mine subject to the following conditions, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the common main maternity centre shall 
    maintain the standards prescribed for the aggregate number of workers of all 
    the limestone or dolomite mines served by it or the standard maintained by 
    it during the year 1972, whichever is higher;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   every branch maternity centre shall 
    have a qualified doctor and a qualified compounder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the common main maternity centre shall 
    be so situated that none of the limestone or dolomite mines served by it is 
    more than fifteen kilometres away from it; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the common maternity centre shall 
    maintain an ambulance van for taking serious cases from the branch maternity 
    centres to the common maternity centre.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that a maternity centre is being 
    efficiently run and serves the purpose for which it is established, waive 
    any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that 
    the functions of a lady health visitor may be performed by a fully qualified 
    and registered mid-wife who has not less than ten years experience a 
    mid-wife:  
 
Provided 
    further that a lady medical licenciate may be appointed to be in charge of a 
    maternity centre catering to more than 1,000 workers if she has ten years 
    experience as a medical officer in independent charge of a mine maternity 
    centre.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>35</number> Inspection of 
    maternity centre.—The 
    maternity centre maintained by owners of Limestone or Dolomite Mines shall 
    be inspected annually by the Welfare Commissioner of the region and the 
    Senior Most Medical Officer jointly. They shall, if the maternity centre 
    conforms to the prescribed standard of the maternity centre of the Labour 
    Welfare Organisation, issue a certificate in Form B which shall be valid for 
    a period of one year from the date of the issue.]  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Submission of periodic returns.—Every 
    owner of a limestone or dolomite mine who maintains a maternity centre 
    according to the prescribed standard shall submit to the Commissioner in 
    January of each year a certified statement of the expenditure incurred on 
    the maternity centre during the preceding twelve months.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>37</number> Extent of 
    grant-in-aid.—
<section><number>1</number> Every owner of a Limestone or Dolomite Mine who 
    maintains a dispensary, hospital or a maternity centre for the benefit of 
    labour employed in his mine which conforms to the prescribed standard under 
    rule 31 or 34, as the case may be, and is subject to inspection under rule 
    32 or 35, as the case may be, shall, if he desires to carry on improvement 
    of the 

    2[existing 
    facilities], in case of dispensary and maternity centre, and before the 
    publication of Limestone and Dolomite Mines labour Welfare Fund (Amendment) 
    Rules, 1981, in case of hospital be eligible for grant-in-aid in respect of 
    non-recurring expenditure on such improvement as the Central Government may 
    decide, subject to the condition that it shall not exceed 50 per cent of the 
    said expenditure.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    owner of Limestone or Dolomite Mine who maintains a dispensary, hospital or 
    maternity centre for the benefit of the labour employed in his mine shall, 
    if the Welfare Commissioner is of the opinion that the dispensary, hospital 
    or maternity centre conforms to the prescribed standard, be eligible to a 
    grant-in-aid which shall not exceed—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the amount of duty at the rate of
    3[forty 
    paise] per metric tonne of Limestone or Dolomite, as the case may be, 
    produced by the mine less the proportionate cost of recovery; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   75 per cent of amount spent by the 
    owner of the mine on the maintenance of the dispensary, hospital or 
    maternity centre as determined by the Welfare Commissioner, whichever is 
    less:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of a dispensary, hospital or maternity centre which serves other 
    workers and the members of the public, the amount spent by the owner of the 
    mine on the maintenance of the dispensary, hospital or maternity centre 
    services for the purpose of this clause may, if separate expenditure figures 
    are not available, be determined by the Chairman on proportionate basis.]  
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Standard of facilities for education and recreation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The standard of facilities for education and recreation of workers to be 
    provided by owners of limestone or dolomite mines for the purpose of getting 
    grants-in-aid as envisaged in clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 of 
    the Act shall be as specified in Schedule III, hereinafter in this rule and 
    in rules 39 and 40 referred to as the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There 
    shall be maintained an independent welfare centre at each limestone or 
    dolomite mine according to the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the centre is being efficiently 
    maintained and serves the purpose for which it is established, waive any of 
    the requirements specified in the prescribed standard.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> Inspection.—The 
    welfare centre maintained by owners of limestone and dolomite mines shall be 
    intervals at internals not exceeding one year by such officer as may be 
    authorised by the Commissioner for the purpose or by the Commissioner 
    himself whenever he considers it necessary and the inspecting officer or the 
    Commissioner, as the case may be, shall issue a certificate in Form ‘C’, 
    indicating whether the centre conforms to the prescribed standard or not, 
    which shall be valid for a period of one year from the date of issue.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Submission of periodic returns.—Every 
    owner of a limestone or dolomite mine who maintains a welfare centre 
    according to the prescribed standard shall submit to the Commissioner—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   immediately on the establishment of the 
    welfare centre, adequate proof to the satisfaction of the Commissioner 
    showing the capital expenditure incurred on the construction and equipment 
    of the welfare centre; and  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   in January each year a certified 
    statement of the expenditure incurred on the welfare centre during the 
    preceding twelve months:  
 
Provided that 
    the statement shall not include expenditure, if any, incurred on repairs and 
    replacements.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Extent of grant-in-aid.—Every 
    owner of a limestone or a dolomite mine who maintains a welfare centre for 
    the benefit of the labour employed in his mine which conforms to the 
    prescribed standard under rule 38 and subject to inspection under rule 39 be 
    eligible to grant-in-aid which shall not exceed 50 per cent. of the amount 
    spent by the owner of the mine in the construction and equipment of the 
    welfare centre subject to a maximum of Rs. 

    1[15,000].
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Assessing and collecting authority for duty of excise.—The 
    Commissioner shall be responsible for the assessment and collection of the 
    cess levied under the Act.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Maintenance of registers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> 
    Every owner of a limestone or dolomite mine shall maintain in Form D a 
    date-wise register of production and disposal of limestone or dolomite.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> at the 
    close of each month, the entries made against each date in the register 
    shall be totalled and the total production and disposal during the month 
    shall be entered therein.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The duty 
    of excise, as fixed under section 3, payable by the owner of the mine to the 
    Central Government on the limestone or dolomite used by such owner for any 
    purpose in connection with the manufacture of cement, iron or steel shall be 
    worked out and recorded in the register itself.  
 

    Explanation.—In calculating the 
    duty of excise payable, a fraction of less than half a tonne in the total of 
    limestone or dolomite used during the month shall be ignored and a fraction 
    of half or more than half of a tonne shall be reckoned as one tonne.  
 


    1[(1A) (a) Every 
    purchasing agent or stockiest of limestone or dolomite shall maintain in 
    Form D1 a date-wise register of the receipts and disposal of limestone or 
    dolomite.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> At the 
    close of each month the entries made against each date in the register shall 
    be totalled and the total receipt and disposal during the month shall be 
    entered therein.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The duty 
    of excise as fixed under section 3 payable by the purchasing agent or the 
    stockiest under section 4 in relation to such limestone or dolomite to the 
    occupier of factory shall be calculated and recorded in the register itself 
    along with the amount of duty actually paid.  
 

    Explanation.—In calculating the 
    duty of excise payable, a fraction of less than half a tonne in total of 
    limestone or dolomite sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of any 
    factory during the month shall be ignored and a fraction of half or more 
    than half a tonne shall be reckoned as one tonne.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Every 
    occupier of a factory receiving limestone or dolomite shall maintain in Form 
    E a date-wise register of receipt of limestone or dolomite and the amount of 
    duty of excise collected under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 4, 
    in the manner specified in sub-rule (4) of rule 47.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> At the 
    close of each month, the entries made against each date in the register 
    shall be totalled and the total quantity of limestone of dolomite and amount 
    of duty of excise collected during the month shall be entered therein.  
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Submission of returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every owner of a limestone or dolomite mine 

    1[purchasing agent or 
    stockiest] and every occupier of a factory receiving limestone or dolomite 
    shall submit to the Commissioner, in duplicate, a return in Form D 


    1[Form D1] and Form E 
    respectively for each month in accordance with the entries made in the 
    register maintained under sub-rule (1) 

    1[or sub-rule (1A)] or 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 43, as the case may be, duly signed by him or any other 
    person authorised by him in this behalf, so as to reach the Commissioner not 
    later than the last day of the month following the month to which the return 
    pertains.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    by reason of the fact that no limestone or dolomite was produced or disposed 
    of in any manner by the owner of a mine, 

    1[or no limestone or 
    dolomite was received or sold or otherwise disposed of in any manner by the 
    purchasing agent or stockist] or like-wise no limestone or dolomite was 
    received or no duty of excise collected by the occupier of the factory, 
    during any month, such owner 

    1[purchasing agent or 
    stockist] or the occupier as the case may be, shall submit to the 
    Commissioner, in duplicate, a nil return for that month, accompanied by a 
    certificate to the effect duly signed by him or any other person duly 
    authorised by him in this behalf, so as to reach the Commissioner not later 
    than the last day of the month following the month to which the return 
    pertains.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), if the 
    Commissioner is satisfied with respect to the owner of any mine that no 
    limestone or dolomite was produced or disposed of by him. 

    1[or with respect to 
    the purchasing agent or stockist of limestone or dolomite that no limestone 
    or dolomite was received or disposed of by him] or with respect to the 
    occupier of any factory that no limestone or dolomite or duty of excise was 
    received by him, during the preceding twelve months, he may by a permit in 
    writing allow such owner 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or occupier to submit in place of a monthly return in Form D
    

    1[or Form D1] or Form 
    E, as the case may be, for such period not exceeding one year as may be 
    specified in the permit and the consolidated return so submitted shall reach 
    the Commissioner not later than the last day of the month immediately 
    following the period specified in the permit.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A return 
    under sub-rule (1), (2) or (3) shall be sent by registered post with 
    acknowledgement due.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Penalty for delay in submission of returns.—If 
    the return for any month or period does not reach the Commissioner within 
    the time specified in rule 44, the owner of the limestone or dolomite mine
    

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or the occupier of the factory, as the case may be, shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Late returns and revision of returns.—If 
    the owner of any mine 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or the occupier of any factory has not finished the return 
    under rule 44 within the specified date or having furnished it, discovers 
    any omission or wrong statement therein, he may furnish the return or 
    revised return, as the case may be, at any time before the order of final 
    assessment under rule 49 or 50, as the case may be, is passed.  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Provisional assessment and payment of duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The amount of duty of excise payable by the owner of a mine for any month 
    and recorded in the register specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 43 shall be 
    deemed to be a provisional assessment of the duty of excise for that month 
    and shall be subject to final assessment under rule 49.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    owner of the mine shall pay the duty of excise assessed under sub-rule (1)
    

    1[by sending to the 
    Commissioner crossed change or crossed demand draft drawn in his favour and 
    payable at the station at which the Commissioner is stationed] not later 
    than the last day of the month following the month for which the duty of 
    excise is payable.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The duty 
    of excise on the limestone or dolomite, as fixed under section 3, payable to 
    the occupier of a factory, by the person by whom such limestone or dolomite 
    is sold or otherwise disposed of to such occupier, shall be worked out by 
    the said occupier and shall be deemed to be a provisional assessment of the 
    duty of excise and shall be subject to a final assessment under rule 50.  
 

    Explanation.—In calculating the 
    duty of excise payable, a fraction of less than half a tonne in the total of 
    the limestone or dolomite sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of 
    any factory at a time shall be ignored and a fraction of half or more than 
    half of a tonne shall be reckoned as one tonne.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The amount 
    so worked out shall be deducted by the said occupier from the bill of 
    payment of the person concerned, unless already paid by him to such occupier 
    in cash or by bank draft, and the fact shall be intimated forthwith by the 
    said occupier to the person concerned in Form F, a copy of which shall also 
    be endorsed to the Commissioner and despatched to him by registered post 
    acknowledgement due.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    amount received or collected by the occupier of any factory under sub-rule 
    (4) shall be paid by him 

    1[by sending to the 
    Commissioner crossed cheque or crossed demand draft drawn in his favour and 
    payable at the station at which the Commissioner is stationed] not later 
    than the last day of the month following the month for which the duty of 
    excise is payable.  
 



 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>48</number> Manner of 
    payment of duty.—
<section><number>1</number> the payment of the duty of excise by the owner of a 
    mine under sub-rule (2) of rule 47, or of the amount collected by the 
    occupier of any factory under sub-rule (4) of rule 47, shall be made by 
    sending to the Commissioner a crossed cheque or crossed demand draft drawn 
    in his favour and payable at the station at which he is stationed along with 
    a treasury challan duly filled in indicating the head of Account as 


    1[0038]—Union Excise 
    duties—Cess on Commodities—Limestone and Dolomite Cess” creditable to the 
    account of P.A.O. [Main Secretariat), Ministry of Labour, New Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Cheque or bank draft shall be credited by the Commissioner in favour of the 
    P.A.O. (Main Secretariat), Ministry of Labour, New Delhi, in the branch of 
    the 

    1[accredited bank of 
    the Ministry of Labour, New Delhi] with which the Commissioner has been 
    placed in account.]  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Final 
    assessment of duty of excise payable by owner of a mine.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
    If the Commissioner is satisfied that the return submitted by any owner of a 
    mine is correct and complete, he shall confirm the provisional assessment 
    referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 47 as final and send an intimation to 
    that effect to the owner of the mine in Form G within ninety days of the 
    date of receipt of the return.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> If the 
    Commissioner is not so satisfied or no return is filed by the owner of a 
    mine, he may issue a notice in Form H on the owner of the mine requiring him 
    to submit a return or a revised return in Form D, as the case may be, within 
    such time as may be specified in the notice and he may also depute an 
    officer for the purpose of verification of the correctness and completeness 
    of the return submitted under rule 44 with reference to the books and 
    accounts and other relevant records of the mine at its premises.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The 
    officer deputed by the Commissioner shall be afforded all necessary 
    facilities at the premises of the mine for the purpose of verification.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> If on 
    consideration of the return or the revised return received in compliance of 
    the notice in Form H or after verification of the return as aforesaid, or if 
    no such return is received within the specified time, on the basis of the 
    information in his possession, the Commissioner is satisfied that any amount 
    on account of duty of excise is due from the owner of the mine, he shall 
    issue on him a Demand Notice in Form I requiring him the payment of the 
    amount due within the time specified therein and the owner shall further be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees as provided in 
    rule 45, for non-submission of the return in Form D.  
 


    1[(2) The mode of 
    payment of the amount specified in Demand Notice in Form I shall be the same 
    as laid down in rule 48 and the crossed cheque or crossed demand draft sent 
    to the Commissioner shall be accompanied by a covering letter quoting 
    reference to the Demand Notice.]
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Final 
    assessment of duty of excise payable by persons selling or otherwise 
    disposing limestone or dolomite to the occupier of any factory.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
    If the Commissioner is satisfied that the amount of duty of excise received 
    or collected by the occupier of the factory from the person by whom the 
    limestone or dolomite is sold or otherwise disposed of to such occupier, is 
    the total amount of the duty of excise payable by him as fixed under section 
    3, he shall confirm the provisional assessment referred to in rule (3) of 47 
    as final and send an intimation to that effect to the said occupier in Form 
    J within ninety days of the receipt of the intimation in Form F.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> If the 
    Commissioner is not so satisfied or no return in Form E is filed or 
    information in Form F for any month furnished by the occupier of any factory 
    by the specified date in the manner laid down in rules 44 and 47, the 
    Commissioner may issue a notice in Form K on the occupier of the factory 
    concerned requiring him to submit a return or revised return in Form E, or 
    information or revised information in Form F, or both, as the case may be, 
    within such time as may be specified in the notice and he may also depute an 
    officer for the purpose of verification of the correctness and completeness 
    of the return or the information furnished by the occupier concerned in Form 
    F, with reference to the books and accounts and other relevant records of 
    the factory at its premises.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The 
    officer deputed by the Commissioner shall be afforded all necessary 
    facilities at the premises of the factory for the purpose of verification.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> If on 
    consideration of the return or revised return, or information or revised 
    information or both, received in compliance of the notice in Form K or after 
    verification of the return or information or both, as aforesaid, or if no 
    such return or revised return, or information or revised information, or 
    both, is or ore received within the specified time, on the basis of the 
    information in him possession, the Commissioner is satisfied that any amount 
    on account of duty of excise is due from the occupier of the factory, he 
    shall issue on him a demand notice in Form L requiring him the payment of 
    the amount within the time specified therein and the occupier of the factory 
    shall further be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
    rupees as provided in rule 45 for non-submission of the return in Form E or 
    information in Form F.   
 


    1[(2) The mode of 
    payment of amount specified in Demand Notice in Form L shall be the same as 
    laid down in rule 48 and the crossed cheque or crossed demand draft sent to 
    the Commissioner shall be accompanied by a covering letter quoting reference 
    to the Demand Notice.]  
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Penalty 
    for non-payment of duty of excise.—The 
    penalty under section 12 be imposed by the Commissioner after giving notice 
    to the defaulter in Form M and the Demand Notice shall be issued in Form N.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Recovery of duty of excise on limestone or dolomite which has escaped 
    assessment.—If—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the Commissioner has reason to 
    believe that by reason of the concealment, by the owner of a mine 
1[or 
    purchasing agent or stockist] or by the occupier of any factory, of any 
    particulars of any limestone or dolomite on which duty of excise is payable 
    under section 4 of the Act, has escaped the levy of duty of excise; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   notwithstanding any such concealment of 
    particulars as is mentioned in clause (a), the Commissioner has in 
    consequence of information in his possession, reason to believe that any 
    limestone or dolomite on which duty of excise is payable has escapd levy of 
    the duty of excise,  
 
the Commissioner may, in cases falling under 
    clause (a), at any time within four years, and in cases falling under clause 
    (b), at any time within two years of the end of the month during which the 
    duty of excise should have been paid, assess the duty of excise payable 
    thereon and all the provisions of these rules shall apply to the duty of 
    excise so assessed as if assessment were included in the final assessment 
    order as provided under rule 49 or 50 as the case may be:
 
Provided 
    that the Commissioner, before exercising the powers conferred upon him under 
    this rule, shall give the owner 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or the occupier, as the case may be, a reasonable opportunity 
    of being heard.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Recovery of unpaid duty of excise and penalty.—
<section><number>1</number>The 
    Commissioner shall (in order to recover the unpaid amount of the duty of 
    excise, interest and the penalty) apply to the Collector of the district in 
    which the mine or the factory is situated, as the case may be, for the 
    recovery of the amount remaining unpaid as arrears of land revenue under 
    section 13.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Collector of the district shall send a report to the Commissioner by the 
    10th day of each month showing the amount recovered by him as arrears of 
    land revenue during the preceding month.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Review.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Within 30 day from the date of issue of a Demand Notice, any owner of the 
    mine 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or any occupier of a factory, as the case may be may submit a 
    petition to the Central Government with a copy to the Commissioner, asking 
    for a review of such assessment or orders under section 11 or 12:  
 
Provided that 
    no such petition shall be entertained unless the Central Government is 
    satisfied that the amount demanded has been paid as required under rule 49 
    or 50, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every petition for review shall be accompanied by a memorandum setting forth 
    clearly the principal grounds of objections against the assessment made
    

    2[quoting the number 
    and date of crossed cheque or crossed demand draft and number and date of 
    letter with which it was forwarded to the Commissioner] showing that the 
    amount assessed has been paid.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall after making such enquiry as necessary pass such 
    order in writing as it thinks fit, which shall be final.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    petitioner shall be entitled to a copy of such order on the petition for 
    review free of cost and it shall be furnished to him as soon as possible 
    after the orders are possed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> So much of 
    the amount originally demanded and paid by the owner of the mine or the 
    occupier of the factory, as the case may be, as is found not to be due from 
    him as a result of review under sub-rule (1) shall be refunded to the 
    petitioner.  
 


    2[(6) Any refund under 
    sub-rule (5) shall be made by the Commissioner by cheque or demand draft by 
    drawing the amount from the Pay and Accounts Office on an ordinary 
    contingent bill on which shall be specified the review case number and date 
    of the order therein and the amount and date of the challan with which the 
    deposit was made by him in the branch of the 

    3[accredited bank of 
    the Ministry of Labour, New Delhi].]  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Records 
    of collection.—
<section><number>1</number> For the proper 
    accounting of duty collected under these rules, the Commissioner shall 
    maintain records to show the following particulars along with any other 
    particulars required, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   Assessment and collection of duty;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   interest payable under section 11;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   penalty imposed for non-payment of duty 
    under section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   particulars of petitions and orders 
    thereon; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   refunds.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All the 
    papers relating to the assessment of duty in respect of a mine or factory 
    shall be kept together and shall form an assessment case record.  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>56</number> Liability of owner of mine selling or 
      otherwise disposing of limestone or dolomite to the occupier of a 
      factory.—In these rules, the 
      reference to the person by whom limestone or dolomite is sold or otherwise 
      disposed of to the occupier of the factory shall be construed to mean 
      reference to the owner of a mine where such owner happens to be the person 
      selling or otherwise disposing of limestone or dolomite produced in the 
      mine to the occupier of the factory and shall be liable as such.  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Maintenance of the accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The amount of the cess collected under the Act shall be credited to Major 
    Head 

    1[2[0038]—Union 
    Excise Duties— Cess on Commodities—Limestone and Dolomite].  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    proceeds of the cess, reduced by the cost of collection as may be determined 
    by the Central Government, shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament 
    by law, be transferred to 

    1[Limestone and 
    Dolomite Mines Labour Welfare Fund in Section J:— (a) Reserve Funds; (b) 
    Reserve Funds not bearing interest under the Major Head 

    2[8229]—Development 
    and Welfare Funds—Mines Welfare Funds”] in the Public Account of the Central 
    Government for expenditure on measures for the welfare of labour employed in 
    the limestone and dolomite mining industry.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    miscellaneous receipts accruing from the investment of the amount in the 
    Fund and other moneys received in connection with the measures for the 
    welfare of the labour employed in the limestone and dolomite mining industry 
    shall be credited in the first instance to the Head 

    1[B-Non-Tax Revenue 
    (C) Other Non-Tax Revenue—(ii) Social and Community Services— 

    2[0230]—Labour and 
    Employment—Receipts under Labour Laws] and subsequently transferred, after 
    due appropriation made by Parliament by law, to the Reserve Fund referred to 
    in sub-rule (2).  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Allocation.—The proceeds of the 
    cess transferred to the Limestone and Dolomite Mines Labour Welfare Fund 
    every year and such other moneys as may be received in the Fund shall be 
    distributed by the Central Government for expenditure in limestone and 
    dolomite producing areas in proportion to their production or in such manner 
    as may be decided in consultation with the Government of those areas.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Statistics and other information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The owner of a limestone or dolomite mine 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] and the occupier of any factory shall furnish such statistics 
    or other information as the Central Government or any other person 
    authorised by the Central Government in writing in this behalf, may by 
    written order, require for the purposes of the Act in such form or manner 
    and within such time as may be specified in the order.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    owner of a limestone or dolomite mine 

    1[or purchasing agent 
    or stockist] or the occupier of a factory who, without reasonable excuse, 
    fails to furnish the statistics or other information required under sub-rule 
    (1) or furnishes statistics or other information containing a statement, 
    entry or detail which is not to the best of his knowledge or belief true, 
    shall be punishable with fine which may extend to Rs. 500.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Prosecution.—No. court shall take 
    cognizance of any offence punishable under rule 45, sub-clause (d) of 
    sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 49, sub-clause (d) of sub-rule (1) of rule 50, and rule 
    59 save on a written complaint made by or under the authority of the 
    Commissioner.  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>