<act><title>

    THE SICK INDUSTRIAL COMPANIES (SPECIAL PROVISIONS) ACT, 1985</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) 
    Act, 1985.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be 
    appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any 
    provision of this Act to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as 
    a reference to the commencement of that provision.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall 
    apply, in the first instance, to all the scheduled industries other than the 
    scheduled industry relating to ships and other vessels drawn by power.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank of India, by 
    notification, apply the provisions of this Act, on and from such date as may 
    be specified in the notification, to the scheduled industry relating to 
    ships and other vessels drawn by power.
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Declaration.—It
is hereby declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State
towards securing the principles specified in clauses (b) and (c) of article 39
of the Constitution.
  
 

  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
“Appellate Authority” means the Appellate Authority for Industrial 
    and Financial Reconstruction constituted under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
“Board” means the Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction 
    established under section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
“Chairman” means the Chairman of the Board, or as the case may be, 
    the Appellate Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
“Company” means a company as defined in section 3 of the Companies 
    Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), 1[***];
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>da</number>
“date of finalisation of the duly audited accounts” means the date on 
    which the audited accounts of the company are adopted at the annual general 
    meeting of the company;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> 
“industrial company” means a company which owns one or more 
    industrial undertakings;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> “industrial undertaking” means any 
    undertaking pertaining to a scheduled industry carried on in one or more 
    factories by any company but does not include—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> an ancillary industrial undertaking as 
    defined in clause (aa) of 
    section 3 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 
    1951); and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> a small scale industrial undertaking as 
    defined in clause (j) 
    of the aforesaid section 3;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> 
“Member” means a Member of the Board or, as the case may be, the 
    Appellate Authority and includes the Chairman thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ga</number>
“net worth” means the sum total of the paid-up capital and free 
    reserves.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this clause, “free reserves” means all reserves credited out 
    of the profits and share premium account but does not include reserves 
    credited out of re-evaluation of assets, write back of depreciation 
    provisions and amalgamation;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> 
“notification” means a notification published in the Official 
    Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>i</number>
     “operating 
    agency” means any public financial institution, State level institution, 
    scheduled bank or any other person as may be specified by general or special 
    order as its agency by the Board;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> 
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> 
“Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under 
    section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> 
“scheduled bank” means a bank for the time being included in the 
    Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number> 
“scheduled industry” means any of the industries specified for the 
    time being in the First Schedule to the Industries (Development and 
    Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951);
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>o</number>
“sick industrial company” means an industrial company (being a 
    company registered for not less than five years) which has at the end of any 
    financial year accumulated losses equal to or exceeding its entire net 
    worth.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that an industrial company 
    existing immediately before the commencement* of the Sick Industrial 
    Companies (Special Provisions) Amendment Act, 1993, registered for not less 
    than five years and having at the end of any financial year accumulated 
    losses equal to or exceeding its entire net worth, shall be deemed to be a 
    sick industrial company;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number> 
“State level institution” means any of the following institutions, 
    namely:—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> State Financial Corporations established 
    under section 3 or section 3A and institutions notified under section 46 of 
    the State Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> State industrial development corporations 
    registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number> Such other institutions, being companies 
    and not being public financial institutions, engaged in the development or 
    financing of industrial undertakings, as the Central Government may, by 
    notification, specify:
 
Provided that 
    no institution shall be so specified unless not less than fifty-one per 
    cent. of the paid-up share capital thereof is held by any State Government 
    or Governments or by any institution or institutions mentioned in 
    sub-clauses (i) and (ii) or partly by one or more public financial 
    institutions or institutions mentioned in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) and 
    partly by one or more State Governments.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Words 
    and expressions used and not defined in this Act shall have the meanings, if 
    any, respectively assigned to them in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Words and 
    expressions used but not defined either in this Act or in the Companies Act, 
    1956 (1 of 1956), shall have the meanings, if any, respectively assigned to 
    them in the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to any other enactment or any provision thereof, 
    shall, in relation to an area in which such enactment or such provision is 
    not in force, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law or the 
    relevant provision of the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.
  











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Establishment of Board.—
<section><number>1</number>
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification,
appoint, there shall be established a Board to be known as the “Board for
Industrial and Financial Reconstruction” to exercise the jurisdiction and
powers and discharge the functions and duties conferred or imposed on the Board
by or under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Board shall consist of a Chairman and not less than two and not more than
fourteen other Members, to be appointed by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Chairman and other Members of the Board shall be persons who are or have
been or are qualified to be High Court Judges, or persons of ability, integrity
and standing who have special knowledge of, and professional experience of not
less than fifteen years in science, technology, economics, banking industry,
law, labour matters, industrial finance, industrial management, industrial
reconstruction, administration, investment, accountancy, marketing or any other
matter, the special knowledge of, or professional experience in which, would in
the opinion of the Central Government be useful to the Board.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Constitution of Appellate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, by notification, constitute, with effect from such
date as may be specified therein, an appellate authority to be called the
“Appellate Authority for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction” consisting
of a Chairman and not more than three other Members, to be appointed by that
Government, for hearing appeals against the orders of the Board under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman shall be a person who is or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court
or who is or has been a Judge of a High Court for not less than five years.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A Member of the Appellate Authority shall be a person who is or has been a Judge
of a High Court or who is or has been an officer not below the rank of a
Secretary to the Government of India or who is or has been a Member of the Board
for not less than three years.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Term of office, conditions of service, etc., of Chairman and other
Members.—
<section><number>1</number>
Before appointing any person as the Chairman or other Member, the Central
Government shall satisfy itself that the person does not and will not, have any
such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his
functions as such Member.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman and every other Member shall hold office for such period, not
exceeding five years, as may be specified by the Central Government in the order
of his appointment, but shall be eligible for reappointment:
 Provided
that no person shall hold office as the Chairman or other Member after he has
attained the age of sixty-five years.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), a Member may—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 by writing under his hand and
addressed to the Central Government resign his office at any time;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 be removed from his office in
accordance with the provisions of section 7.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
A vacancy caused by the resignation or removal of the Chairman or any other
Member under sub-section (3) or otherwise shall be filled by fresh appointment.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
In the event of the occurrence of a vacancy in the office of the Chairman by
reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, such one of the Members as the
Central Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf shall act as
the Chairman till the date on which a new Chairman, appointed in accordance with
the provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy, enters upon his office.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
When the Chairman is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness
or any other cause, such one of the Members as the Chairman may authorise in
writing in this behalf, shall discharge the functions of the Chairman, till the
date on which the Chairman resumes his duties.
 </section><section><number>7</number>
The salaries and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of
service of the Chairman and other Members shall be such as may be prescribed:
 Provided
that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of
service of the Chairman or any other Member shall be varied to his disadvantage
after his appointment.
 </section><section><number>8</number>
The Chairman and every other Member shall, before entering upon his office, make
a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule.
 </section><section><number>9</number>
The Chairman or any other Member ceasing to hold office as such shall not hold
any appointment or be connected with the management or administration in any
company in relation to which any matter has been the subject-matter of
consideration before the Board or, as the case may be, the Appellate Authority,
for a period of five years from the date on which he ceases to hold such office.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Removal of Members from office in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may remove from office any Member, who—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 has been adjudged as
insolvent, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 has been convicted of an
offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral
turpitude, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 has become physically or
mentally incapable of acting as a Member, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 has acquired such financial or
other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a Member,
or
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 has so abused his position as
to render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), no Member shall be
removed from his office on the ground specified in clause (d) or clause (e) of
that sub-section unless the Supreme Court on a reference being made to it in
this behalf by the Central Government, has, on an inquiry held by it in
accordance with such procedure as it may specify in this behalf, reported that
the Member ought, on such grounds, to be removed.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Secretary, officers and other employees of Board or Appellate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall appoint a Secretary to the Board and a 
    Secretary (by whatever name called) to the Appellate Authority to exercise 
    and perform, under the control of the Chairman, such powers and duties as 
    may be prescribed or as may be specified by the Chairman.
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The Central Government may provide the Board and the Appellate Authority 
    with such other officers and employees as may be necessary for the efficient 
    performance of the functions of the Board and the Appellate Authority.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salaries and allowances payable to and the conditions of service of the 
    Secretary and other officers and employees of the Board and the Appellate 
    Authority shall be such as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that 
    such Secretary, officer or other employee shall, before entering upon his 
    duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in 
    the Schedule.  

 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Salaries, etc., be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India.—The
salaries and allowances payable to the Members and the administrative expenses,
including salaries, allowances and pension, payable to or in respect of the
officers and other employees of the Board and the Appellate Authority shall be
defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Board and Appellate
Authority.—No
act or proceeding of the Board or, as the case may be, the Appellate Authority
shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy or
defect in the constitution of the Board or the Appellate Authority or any defect
in the appointment of a person acting as a Member of the Board or the Appellate
Authority.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Members and staff of Board and Appellate Authority to be public servants.—The Chairman and other Members and the officers and other
employees of the Board and the Appellate Authority shall be deemed to be public
servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Constitution of Benches of Board or Appellate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Board or the Appellate 
    Authority may be exercised by Benches thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Benches 
    shall be constituted by the Chairman and each Bench shall consist of not 
    less than two Members.
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    If the Members of a Bench differ in opinion on any point, the point shall be 
    decided according to the opinion of the majority, if there is a majority, 
    but if the Members are equally divided, they shall state the point or points 
    on which they differ, and make a reference to the Chairman of the Board or, 
    as the case may be, the Appellate Authority who shall either hear the point 
    or points himself or refer the case for hearing on such point or points by 
    one or more of the other Members and such point or points shall be decided 
    according to the opinion of the majority of the Members who have heard the 
    case including those who first heard it.]  

 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>13</number> Procedure of Board and Appellate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Board or, as the case may be, the 
    Appellate Authority, shall have powers to regulate—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the procedure and conduct of the business;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the procedure of the Benches, including the places at which the 
    sittings of the Benches shall be held;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
the delegation to one or more Members of such powers or functions as 
    the Board or, as the case may be, the Appellate Authority may specify.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    provisions, the powers of the Board or, as the case may be, the Appellate 
    Authority, shall include the power to determine the extent to which persons 
    interested or claiming to be interested in the subject-matter of any 
    proceeding before it may be allowed to be present or to be heard, either by 
    themselves or by their representatives or to cross-examine witnesses or 
    otherwise to take part in the proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    or the Appellate Authority shall, for the purposes of any inquiry or for any 
    other purpose under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil 
    court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying suits 
    in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any witness and 
    examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the discovery and production of document or other material object 
    producible as evidence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
the reception of evidence on affidavit;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
the requisitioning of any public record from any court or office;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> 
the issuing of any commission for the examination of witnesses;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> 
any other matter which may be prescribed.
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Proceedings before Board or Appellate Authority to be judicial proceedings.—The
Board or the Appellate Authority shall be deemed to be a civil court for the
purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973
(2 of 1974) and every proceeding before the Board or the Appellate Authority
shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193
and 228 and for the purposes of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of
1860).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Reference to Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When an industrial company has become a sick industrial company, the Board 
    of Directors of the company, shall, within sixty days from the date of 
    finalisation of the duly audited accounts of the company for the financial 
    year as at the end of which the company has become a sick industrial 
    company, make a reference to the Board for determination of the measures 
    which shall be adopted with respect to the company:
 
Provided that 
    if the Board of Directors had sufficient reasons even before such 
    finalisation to form the opinion that the company had become a sick 
    industrial company, the Board of Directors shall, within sixty days after it 
    has formed such opinion, make a reference to the Board for the determination 
    of the measures which shall be adopted with respect to the company:
 

<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided 
    further that no reference shall be made to the Board for Industrial and 
    Financial Reconstruction after the commencement* of the Securitisation and 
    Reconstruction of Financial Assets and Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 
    2002, where financial assets have been acquired by any securitisation 
    company or reconstruction company under sub-secton (1) of section 5 of that 
    Act:
 
Provided also 
    that on or after the commencement 
    of the Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and Enforcement 
    of Security Interest Act, 2002, where a reference is pending before the 
    Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction, such reference shall 
    abate if the secured creditors, representing not less than three-fourth in 
    value of the amount outstanding against financial assistance disbursed to 
    the borrower of such secured creditors, have taken any measures to recover 
    their secured debt under sub-section (4) of section 13 of that Act.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the Central Government or 
    the Reserve Bank or a State Government or a public financial institution or 
    a State level institution or a scheduled bank may, if it has sufficient 
    reasons to believe that any industrial company has become, for the purposes 
    of this Act, a sick industrial company, make a reference in respect of such 
    company to the Board for determination of the measures which may be adopted 
    with respect to such company:
 
Provided that a 
    reference shall not be made under this sub-section in respect of any 
    industrial company by—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the Government of any State unless all or any of the industrial 
    undertakings belonging to such company are situated in such State;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
a public financial institution or a State level institution or a 
    scheduled bank unless it has, by reason of any financial assistance or 
    obligation rendered by it, or undertaken by it, with respect to, such 
    company, an interest in such company.
 
   





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Inquiry 
    into working of sick industrial companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may make such inquiry as it may deem fit for determining whether 
    any industrial company has become a sick industrial company—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
upon receipt of a reference with respect to such company under 
    section 15; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
upon information received with respect to such company or upon its 
    own knowledge as to the financial condition of the company.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    may, if it deems necessary or expedient so to do for the expeditious 
    disposal of an inquiry under sub-section (1), require by order any operating 
    agency to enquire into and make a report with respect to such matters as may 
    be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    or, as the case may be, the operating agency shall complete its inquiry as 
    expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made to complete the 
    inquiry within sixty days from the commencement of the inquiry.
 

<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, an inquiry shall be deemed to have 
    commenced upon the receipt by the Board of any reference or information or 
    upon its own knowledge reduced to writing by the Board].
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    Board deems it fit to make an inquiry or to cause an inquiry to be made into 
    any industrial company under sub-section (1) or, as the case may be, under 
    sub-section (2), <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[it 
    may appoint] one or more persons to be a special director or special 
    directors of the company for safeguarding the financial and other interests 
    of the company 
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[or 
    in the public interest.]
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> 
    The Board may issue such directions to a special director appointed under 
    sub-section (4) as it may deem necessary or expedient for proper discharge 
    of his duties.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    appointment of a special director referred to in sub-section (4) shall be 
    valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the contrary, contained in 
    the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or in any other law for the time being 
    in force or in the memorandum and articles of association or any other 
    instrument relating to the industrial company, and any provision regarding 
    share qualification, age limit, number of directorships, removal from office 
    of directors and such like conditions contained in any such law or 
    instrument aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed by the 
    Board.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any special 
    director appointed under sub-section (4) shall—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
hold office during the pleasure of the Board and may be removed or 
    substituted by any person by order in writing by the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of his being a 
    director or for anything done or omitted to be done in good faith in the 
    discharge of his duties as a director or anything in relation thereto;  
   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not be taken into 
    account for computing the number of directors liable to such retirement;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>
     not be liable to be 
    prosecuted under any law for anything done or omitted to be done in good 
    faith in the discharge of his duties in relation to the sick industrial 
    company.]
  











 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Powers 
    of Board to make suitable order on the completion of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If after making an inquiry under section 16, the Board is satisfied that a 
    company has become a sick industrial company, the Board shall, after 
    considering all the relevant facts and circumstances of the case, decide, as 
    soon as may be by order in writing, whether it is practicable for the 
    company to 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[make 
    its net worth exceed the accumulated losses] within a reasonable time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    Board decides under sub-section (1) that it is practicable for a sick 
    industrial company to <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[make 
    its net worth exceed the accumulated losses] within a reasonable time, the 
    Board, shall, by order in writing and subject to such restrictions or 
    conditions as may be specified in the order, give such company as it may 
    deem fit to 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[make 
    its net worth exceed the accumulated losses.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    Board decides under sub-section (1) that it is not practicable for a sick 
    industrial company to <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[make 
    its net worth exceed the accumulated losses] within a reasonable time and 
    that it is necessary or expedient in the public interest to adopt all or any 
    of the measures specified in section 18 in relation to the said company it 
    may, as soon as may be, by order in writing, direct any operating agency 
    specified in the order to prepare, having regard to such guidelines as may 
    be specified in the order, a scheme providing for such measures in relation 
    to such company.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Board 
    may,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
if any of the restrictions or conditions specified in an order made 
    under sub-section (2) are not complied with by the company concerned, <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[or 
    if the company fails to revive in pursuance of the said order,] review such 
    order on a reference in that behalf from any agency referred to in 
    sub-section (2) of section 15 or on its own motion and pass a fresh order in 
    respect of such company under sub-section (3);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
if the operating agency specified in an order made under sub-section 
    (3) makes submission in that behalf, review such order and modify the order 
    in such manner as it may deem appropriate.
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Preparation and sanction of Schemes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an order is made under sub-section (3) of section 17 in relation to 
    any sick industrial company, the operating agency specified in the order 
    shall prepare, as expeditiously as possible and ordinarily within a period 
    of ninety days from the date of such order, a scheme with respect to such 
    company providing for any one or more of the following measures, namely:—
 <subsection>

<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>
     the financial 
    reconstruction of the sick industrial company;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the proper management of the sick industrial company by change in, or 
    take over of, management of the sick industrial company;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>
     the amalgamation of—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> the sick industrial company with any other 
    company, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> any other company with the sick 
    industrial company;
 
(hereafter in this section, in the case of 
    sub-clause (i), the other company, and in the case of sub-clause (ii), the 
    sick industrial company, referred to as “transferee company”);]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
the sale or lease of a part or whole of any industrial undertaking of 
    the sick industrial company;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>da</number>
the rationalisation of managerial personnel, supervisory staff and 
    workmen in accordance with law;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> 
such other preventive, ameliorative and remedial measures as may be 
    appropriate;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> 
such incidental, consequential or supplemental measures as may be 
    necessary or expedient in connection with or for the purposes of the 
    measures specified in clauses (a) to (e).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The scheme 
    referred to in sub-section (1) may provide for any one or more of the 
    following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the constitution, name and registered office, the capital, assets, 
    powers, rights, interests, authorities and privileges, duties and 
    obligations of the sick industrial company or, as the case may be, of the
    <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[transferee company];
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the transfer to the <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[transferee 
    company] of the business, properties, assets and liabilities of the sick 
    industrial company on terms and conditions as may be specified in the 
    scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
any change in the Board of Directors, or the appointment of a new 
    Board of Directors, of the sick industrial company and the authority by 
    whom, the manner in which and the other terms and conditions on which, such 
    change or appointment shall be made and in the case of appointment of a new 
    Board of Directors or of any director, the period for which such appointment 
    shall be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
the alteration of the memorandum or articles of association of the 
    sick industrial company or, as the case may be, of the <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[transferee company] for 
    the purpose of altering the capital structure thereof or for such other 
    purposes as may be necessary to give effect to the reconstruction or 
    amalgamation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> 
the continuation by, or against, the sick industrial company or, as 
    the case may be, the <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[transferee 
    company] of any action or other legal proceeding pending against the sick 
    industrial company immediately before the date of the order made under 
    sub-section (3) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> 
the reduction of the interest or rights which the shareholders have 
    in the sick industrial company to such extent as the Board considers 
    necessary in the interests of the reconstruction, revival or rehabilitation 
    of the sick industrial company or for the maintenance of the business of the 
    sick industrial company;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> 
the allotment to the shareholders of the sick industrial company of 
    shares in the sick industrial company or, as the case may be, in the
    <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[transferee company] 
    and where any shareholder claims payment in cash and not allotment of 
    shares, or where it is not possible to allot shares to any shareholder the 
    payment of cash to those shareholders in full satisfaction of their claims—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> in respect of their interest in shares in 
    the sick industrial company before its reconstruction or amalgamation; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> where such interest has been reduced 
    under clause (f) in respect of their interest in shares as so reduced;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> 
any other terms and conditions for the reconstruction or amalgamation 
    of the sick industrial company;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> 
sale of the industrial undertaking of the sick industrial company 
    free from all encumbrances and all liabilities of the company or other such 
    encumbrances and liabilities as may be specified, to any person, including a 
    co-operative society formed by the employees of such undertaking and fixing 
    of reserve price for such sale;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> 
lease of the industrial undertaking of the sick industrial company to 
    any person, including a co-operative society formed by the employees of such 
    undertaking;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> 
method of sale of the assets of the industrial undertaking of the 
    sick industrial company such as by public auction or by inviting tenders or 
    in any other manner as may be specified and for the manner of publicity 
    therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> 
transfer or issue of the shares in the sick industrial company at the 
    face value or at the intrinsic value which may be at discount value or such 
    other value as may be specified to any industrial company or any person 
    including the executives and employees of the sick industrial company;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> 
such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as may be 
    necessary to secure that the reconstruction or amalgamation or other 
    measures mentioned in the scheme are fully and effectively carried out.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 

<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[(a) The Scheme prepared 
    by the operating agency shall be examined by the Board and a copy of the 
    scheme with modification, if any, made by the Board shall be sent, in draft, 
    to the sick industrial company and the operating agency and in the case of 
    amalgamation, also to any other company concerned, and the Board shall 
    publish or cause to be published the draft scheme in brief in such daily 
    newspapers as the Board may consider necessary, for suggestions and 
    objections, if any, within such period as the Board may specify.]
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Board 
    may make such modifications, if any, in the draft scheme as it may consider 
    necessary in the light of the suggestions and objections received from the 
    sick industrial company and the operating agency and also from the 
    transferee industrial company and 

<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[any 
    other company] concerned in the amalgamation and from any shareholder or any 
    creditors or employees of<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[such 
    companies]:
 
Provided that 
    where the scheme relates to amalgamation 

<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[***] 
    the said scheme shall be laid before 
<footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[the 
    company other than the sick industrial company] in the general meeting for 
    the approval of the scheme by its shareholders and no such scheme shall be 
    proceeded with unless it has been approved, with or without modification, by 
    a special resolution passed by the shareholders of <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[the company 
    other than the sick industrial company].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The scheme 
    shall thereafter be sanctioned, as soon as may be, by the Board (hereinafter 
    referred to as the ‘sanctioned scheme’) and shall come into force on such 
    date as the Board may specify in this behalf:
 
Provided that 
    different dates may be specified for different provisions of the scheme.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Board 
    may on the recommendations of the operating agency or otherwise, review any 
    sanctioned scheme and make such modifications as it may deem fit or may by 
    order in writing direct any operating agency specified in the order, having 
    regard to such guidelines as may be specified in the order, to prepare a 
    fresh scheme providing for such measures as the operating agency may 
    consider necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When a 
    fresh scheme is prepared under sub-section (5), the provisions of 
    sub-sections (3) and (4) shall apply in relation thereto as they apply to in 
    relation to a scheme prepared under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>6A</number> 
    Where a sanctioned scheme provides for the transfer of any property or 
    liability of the sick industrial company in favour of any other company or 
    person or where such scheme provides for the transfer of any property or 
    liability of any other company or person in favour of the sick industrial 
    company, then, by virtue of, and to the extent provided in, the scheme, on 
    and from the date of coming into operation of the sanctioned scheme or any 
    provision thereof, the property shall be transferred to, and vest in, and 
    the liability shall become the liability of, such other company or person 
    or, as the case may be, the sick industrial company.]
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    sanction accorded by the Board under sub-section (4) shall be conclusive 
    evidence that all the requirements of this scheme relating to the 
    reconstruction or amalgamation, or any other measure specified therein have 
    been complied with and a copy of the sanctioned scheme certified in writing 
    by an officer of the Board to be a true copy thereof, shall, in all legal 
    proceedings (whether in appeal or otherwise) be admitted as evidence.
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
    On and from the date of the coming into operation of the sanctioned scheme 
    or any provision thereof, the scheme or such provision shall be binding on 
    the sick industrial company and the transferee company or, as the case may 
    be, the other company and also on the shareholders, creditors and guarantors 
    and employees of the said companies.]
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of the sanctioned 
    scheme, the Board may, on the recommendation of the operating agency 

<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[or 
    otherwise], by order do anything, not inconsistent with such provisions, 
    which appears to it to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing 
    difficulty.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The Board 
    may, if it deems necessary or expedient so to do, by order in writing, 
    direct any operating agency specified in the order to implement a sanctioned 
    scheme with such terms and conditions and in relation to such sick 
    industrial company as may be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Where the 
    whole of the undertaking of the sick industrial company is sold under a 
    sanctioned scheme, the Board may distribute the sale proceeds to the parties 
    entitled thereto in accordance with the provisions of section 529A and other 
    provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> 
    The Board may monitor periodically the implementation of the sanctioned 
    scheme.]
  

















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Rehabilitation by giving financial assistance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the scheme relates to preventive, ameliorative, remedial and other 
    measures with respect to any sick industrial company, the scheme may provide 
    for financial assistance by way of loans, advances or guarantees or reliefs 
    or concessions or sacrifices from the Central Government, a State 
    Government, any scheduled bank or other bank, a public financial institution 
    or State level institution or any institution or other authority (any 
    Government, bank, institution or other authority required by a scheme to 
    provide for such financial assistance being hereafter in this section 
    referred to as the person required by the scheme to provide financial 
    assistance) to the sick industrial company.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    scheme referred to in sub-section (1) shall be circulated to every person 
    required by the scheme to provide financial assistance for his consent 
    within a period of sixty days from the date of such circulation 
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[or 
    within such further period, not exceeding sixty days, as may be allowed by 
    the Board, and if no consent is received within such period or further 
    period, it shall be deemed that consent has been given].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in 
    respect of any scheme the consent referred to in sub-section (2) is given by 
    every person required by the scheme to provide financial assistance, the 
    Board may, as soon as may be, sanction the scheme and on and from the date 
    of such sanction the scheme shall be binding on all concerned.
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> 
    On the sanction of the scheme under sub-section (3), the financial 
    institutions and the banks required to provide financial assistance shall 
    designate by mutual agreement a financial institution and a bank from 
    amongst themselves which shall be responsible to disburse financial 
    assistance by way of loans or advances or guarantees or reliefs or 
    concessions or sacrifices agreed to be provided or granted under the scheme 
    on behalf of all financial institutions and banks concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3B</number> The 
    financial institution and the bank designated under sub-section (3A) shall 
    forthwith proceed to release the financial assistance to the sick industrial 
    company in fulfilment of the requirement in this regard.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where in 
    respect of any scheme consent under sub-section (2) is not given by any 
    person required by the scheme to provide financial assistance, the Board may 
    adopt such other measures, including the winding up of the sick industrial 
    company, as it may deem fit.  

 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>19A</number> 
    Arrangement for continuing operations, etc., during inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any time before completion of the inquiry under section 16, the sick 
    industrial company or the Central Government or the Reserve Bank or a State 
    Government or a public financial institution or a State level institution or 
    a scheduled bank or any other institution, bank or authority providing or 
    intending to provide any financial assistance by way of loans or advances or 
    guarantees or reliefs or concessions to the sick industrial company may make 
    an application to the Board—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
agreeing to an arrangement for continuing the operations of the sick 
    industrial company; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
suggesting a scheme for the financial reconstruction of the sick 
    industrial company.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    may, within, sixty days of the receipt of the application under sub-section 
    (1), pass such orders therein as it may deem fit.]  

  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Winding 
    up of sick industrial company.—<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Board, after making inquiry under section 16 and after 
    consideration of all the relevant facts and circumstances and after giving 
    an opportunity of being heard to all concerned parties, is of opinion that 
    the sick industrial company is not likely to make its net worth exceed the 
    accumulated losses within a reasonable time while meeting all its financial 
    obligations and that the company as a result thereof is not likely to become 
    viable in future and that it is just and equitable that the company should 
    be wound up, it may record and forward its opinion to the concerned High 
    Court.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The High 
    Court shall, on the basis of the opinion of the Board, order winding up of 
    the sick industrial company and may proceed and cause to proceed with the 
    winding up of the sick industrial company in accordance with the provisions 
    of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purpose of winding up of the sick industrial company, the High Court may 
    appoint any officer of the operating agency, if the operating agency gives 
    its consent, as the liquidator of the sick industrial company and the 
    officer so appointed shall for the purposes of the winding up of the sick 
    industrial company be deemed to be, and have all the powers of, the official 
    liquidator under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) or sub-section (3), 
    the Board may cause to be sold the assets of the sick industrial company in 
    such manner as it may deem fit and forward the sale proceeds to the High 
    Court for orders for distribution in accordance with the provisions of 
    section 529A, and other provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Operating agency to prepare complete inventory, etc.—Where
    <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[for 
    the proper discharge of the functions of the Board under this Act] the 
    circumstances so require, the Board may, through any operating agency, cause 
    to be prepared—
 <section>
<number>a</number> 
with respect to <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[a 
    company], a complete inventory of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> all assets and liabilities of whatever 
    nature;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> all books of account, registers, maps, 
    plans, records, documents of title or ownership of property and all other 
    documents of whatever nature relating thereto;

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> 
a list of shareholders and a list of creditors showing separately in 
    the list of creditors, the secured creditors and the unsecured creditors;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> 
a valuation report in respect of the shares and assets in order to 
    arrive at the reserve price for the sale of a part or whole of the 
    industrial undertaking of the company or for fixation of the lease rent or 
    share exchange ratio;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> 
an estimate of reserve price, lease rent or share exchange ratio; and
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> 
proforma accounts, where no up-to-date audited accounts, are 
    available.
 
   





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Suspension of legal proceedings, contracts, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where in respect of an industrial company, an inquiry under section 16 is 
    pending or any scheme referred to under section 17 is under preparation or 
    consideration or a sanctioned scheme is under implementation or where an 
    appeal under section 25 relating to an industrial company is pending, then, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), 
    or any other law or the memorandum and articles of association of the 
    industrial company or any other instrument having effect under the said Act 
    or other law, no proceedings for the winding up of the industrial company or 
    for execution, distress or the like against any of the properties of the 
    industrial company or for the appointment of a receiver in respect thereof
    <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[and 
    no suit for the recovery of money or for the enforcement of any security 
    against the industrial company or of any guarantee in respect of any loans 
    or advance granted to the industrial company] shall lie or be proceeded with 
    further, except with the consent of the Board or, as the case may be, the 
    Appellate Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    management of the sick industrial company is taken over or changed 

<footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[in 
    pursuance of any scheme sanctioned under section 18], notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or any other law 
    or in the memorandum and articles of association of such company or any 
    instrument having effect under the said Act or other law—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of such company or any 
    other person to nominate or appoint any person to be a director of the 
    company;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders of such 
    company shall be given effect to unless approved by the Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 

<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[Where 
    an inquiry under section 16 is pending or any scheme referred to in section 
    17 is under preparation or during the period] of consideration of any scheme 
    under section 18 or where any such scheme is sanctioned thereunder, for due 
    implementation of the scheme, the Board may by order declare with respect to 
    the sick industrial company concerned that the operation of all or any of 
    the contracts, assurances of property, agreements, settlements, awards, 
    standing orders or other instruments in force, to which such sick industrial 
    company is a party or which may be applicable to such sick industrial 
    company immediately before the date of such order, shall remain suspended or 
    that all or any of the rights, privileges, obligations and liabilities 
    accruing or arising thereunder before the said date, shall remain suspended 
    or shall be enforceable with such adoptions and in such manner as may be 
    specified by the Board:
 
Provided that 
    such declaration shall not be made for a period exceeding two years which 
    may be extended by one year at a time so, however, that the total period 
    shall not exceed seven years in the aggregate.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    declaration made under sub-section (3) with respect to a sick industrial 
    company shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or any other law, the memorandum and 
    articles of association of the company or any instrument having effect under 
    the said Act or other law or any agreement or any decree or order of a 
    court, tribunal, officer or other authority or of any submission, settlement 
    or standing order and accordingly,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
any remedy for the enforcement of any right, privilege, obligation 
    and liability suspended or modified by such declaration, and all proceedings 
    relating thereto pending before any court, tribunal, officer or other 
    authority shall remain stayed or be continued subject to such declaration; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
on the declaration ceasing to have effect—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> any right, privilege, obligation or 
    liability so remaining suspended or modified, shall become revived and 
    enforceable as if the declaration had never been made; and

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> any proceeding so remaining stayed shall 
    be proceeded with, subject to the provisions of any law which may then be in 
    force, from the stage which had been reached when the proceedings became 
    stayed.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for the enforcement of any right, 
    privilege, obligation or liability, the period during which it or the remedy 
    for the enforcement thereof remains suspended under this section shall be 
    excluded.
  















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>22A</number> 
    Direction not to dispose of assets.—The 
    Board may, if it is of opinion that any direction is necessary in the 
    interest of the sick industrial company or creditors or shareholders or in 
    the public interest, by order in writing direct the sick industrial company 
    not to dispose of, except with the consent of the Board, any of its assets—
 <section>
<number>a</number> 
during the period of preparation or consideration of the scheme under 
    section 18; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> 
during the period beginning with the recording of opinion by the 
    Board for winding up of the company under sub-section (1) of section 20 and 
    up to commencement of the proceedings relating to the winding up before the 
    concerned High Court.]
 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Loss of 
    fifty per cent. net worth by industrial companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the accumulated losses of an industrial company, as at the end of any 
    financial year (hereinafter referred to as the relevant financial year) have 
    resulted in erosion of fifty per cent., or more of its peak net worth during 
    the immediately <footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[preceding 
    four financial years],—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the company shall, within a period of sixty days from the date 
    (hereinafter referred to as the relevant date) of finalisation of the duly 
    audited accounts of the company for the relevant financial year—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> report the fact of such erosion to the 
    Board; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> hold a general meeting of the 
    shareholders of the company for considering such erosion;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the Board of Directors shall, at least twenty-one days before the 
    date on which the meeting under sub-clause (ii) of clause (a) is held, 
    forward to every member of the company a report as to such erosion and the 
    causes for such erosion;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>
     the company may, by 
    ordinary resolution passed at the meeting held under clause (a) remove a 
    director (being a director appointed by the members of the company) and fill 
    the vacancy created by such removal, so far as may be, in accordance with 
    the procedure provided in sub-sections (2) to (6) of section 284 of the 
    Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A director 
    removed under sub-section (1) shall not be entitled to any compensation or 
    damages for termination of his appointment as director or of any appointment 
    terminating with that as director.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If default 
    is made in complying with the provisions of this section, every director or 
    other officer of the company who is in default shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to 
    two years and with fine.  

 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[<number>23A</number> 
    Proceedings on report, etc., of loss of fifty per cent. net worth.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of 
    section 23, the Central Government or the Reserve Bank or a State Government 
    or a public financial institution or a State level institution or a 
    scheduled bank may, if it has sufficient reasons to believe that the 
    accumulated losses of any industrial company have resulted in erosion of 
    fifty per cent. or more of its peak net worth during the immediately 
    preceding four financial years, report the fact of such erosion to the 
    Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    Board has, upon information received or upon its own knowledge, reason to 
    believe that the accumulated losses of any industrial company have resulted 
    in erosion of fifty per cent. or more of its peak net worth during the 
    immediately preceding four financial years, it may call for such information 
    from the company as it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    Board is of the opinion that an industrial company referred to in 
    sub-section (1) is not likely to make its net worth exceed its accumulated 
    losses within a reasonable time while meeting all its financial obligations 
    and that the company as a result thereof is not likely to become viable in 
    future, it may require by order an operating agency to inquire into and make 
    a report with respect to such matters as may be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After 
    consideration of the report of the operating agency, the Board may publish 
    or cause to be published a notice in such daily newspapers as the Board may 
    consider necessary, for suggestions and objections, if any, within such 
    period as the Board may specify, as to why the company should not be wound 
    up.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    Board, after consideration of the relevant facts and circumstances and after 
    giving an opportunity of being heard to all concerned parties, is of the 
    opinion that the industrial company is not likely to make its net worth 
    exceed the accumulated losses within a reasonable time while meeting all its 
    financial obligations and that the company as a result thereof, is not 
    likely to become viable in future and that it is just and equitable that the 
    company should be wound up, the Board may record and forward its opinion to 
    the concerned High Court in relation to the company as if it were a sick 
    industrial company and the provisions of sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) of 
    section 20 shall apply accordingly].  

 
   



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>23B</number> 
    Power of Board to call for periodic information.—On 
    receipt of a report under sub-clause 
<section><number>i</number> of clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of 
    section 23 or under sub-section (1) of section 23A or upon information or 
    its own knowledge under sub-section (2) of section 23A, the Board may call 
    for any periodic information from the company as to the steps taken by the 
    company to make its net worth exceed the accumulated losses and the company 
    shall furnish such information.]  

 
   




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number> Misfeasance proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> If, in the course of scrutiny 
      or implementation of any scheme or proposal, it appears to the Board that 
      any person who has taken part in the promotion, formation or management of 
      the sick industrial company or its undertaking, including any pass or 
      present director, manager or officer or employee of the sick industrial 
      company—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  has misapplied or retained, 
      or become liable or accountable for, any money or property of the sick 
      industrial company; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  has been guilty of any 
      misfeasance, malfeasance or non-feasance or breach of trust in relation to 
      the sick industrial company,
 the Board may, by order, direct 
      him to repay or restore the money or property or any part thereof, with or 
      without interest, as it thinks just, or to contribute such sum to the 
      assets of the sick industrial company or the other person entitled thereto 
      by way of compensation in respect of the misapplication, retainer 
      misfeasance or breach of trust, as the Board thinks just, and also report 
      the matter to the Central Government for any other action which that 
      Government may deem fit.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If the Board is satisfied on the basis of information and 
      evidence in its possession with respect to any person who is or was a 
      director or an officer or other employee of the sick industrial company, 
      that such person by himself or along with others had diverted the funds or 
      other property of such company for any purpose other than a bona fide 
      purpose of the company or had managed the affairs of the company in a 
      manner highly detrimental to the interests of the company, the Board 
      shall, by order, direct the public financial institutions, scheduled banks 
      and State level institutions not to provide, during a period of ten years 
      from the date of the order, any financial assistance to such person or any 
      firm of which person is a partner or any company or other body corporate 
      of which such person is a director (by whatever name 
      called).
 </section><section><number>3</number> No order shall be made by the Board under this section against 
      any person unless such person has been given an opportunity for making his 
      submissions.
 </section><section><number>4</number> This section shall apply notwithstanding that the matter is one 
      for which the person may be criminally liable.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the Board made under this Act may, 
    within forty-five days from the date on which a copy of the order is issued 
    to him, prefer an appeal to the Appellate Authority:
 
Provided that 
    the Appellate Authority may entertain any appeal after the said period of 
    forty-five days but not after sixty days from the date aforesaid if it is 
    satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing 
    the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of an appeal under sub-section (1), the Appellate Authority may, after 
    giving an opportunity to the appellant to be heard, if he so desires, and 
    after making such further inquiry as it deems fit, confirm, modify or set 
    aside the order appealed against <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[or 
    remand the matter to the Board for fresh consideration].  

 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number>
Bar of jurisdiction.—No
order passed or proposal made under this Act shall be appealable except as
provided therein and no civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any
matter which the Appellate Authority or the Board is empowered by, or under,
this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other
authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any
power conferred by or under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number>
Delegation of powers.—The
Board may, by general or special order, delegate, subject to such conditions and
limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, to any Member or
Secretary or other officer or employee of the Board or other person authorised
by the Board to manage any industrial company or industrial undertaking or any
operating agency, such powers and duties [except the powers and duties under
sub-sections (2) and (4) of section 16, section 17, sub-sections (3) and (4) of
section 19, sub-sections 
<section><number>1</number> and (4) of section 20, sub-section (3) of section
22 and section 24] under this Act as it may deem necessary.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Returns 
    and information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall furnish from time to time to the Central Government such 
    returns as the Central Government may require.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    may, for the purpose of efficient discharge of its functions under this Act, 
    collect from, or furnish to,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
the Central Government,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
the Reserve Bank,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
the scheduled bank or any other bank,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
the public financial institution, 
<footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> 
the State-level institution, 
<footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[or]
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[<number>f</number>
     the sick industrial 
    company and in case of amalgamation, the other company,]  
   
 
such information as it may consider useful for 
    the purpose in such manner and within such time as it may think fit.
  





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number>
Power to seek the assistance of Chief Metropolitan Magistrate and District
Magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Board or any operating agency, on being directed by the Board, may, in order
to take into custody or under its control all property, effects and actionable
claims to which a sick industrial company is or appears to be entitled, request,
in writing, the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District Magistrate within
whose jurisdiction any property, books of account or any other documents of such
sick industrial company be situate or be found, to take possession thereof, and
the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District Magistrate, as the case may
be, shall, on such request being made to him,—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
 take possession of such
property, books of accounts or other documents; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
 cause the same to
be entrusted to the Board or the operating agency.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
For the purpose of securing compliance with the provisions of sub-section (1),
the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District Magistrate may take or cause
to be taken such steps and use or cause to be used such force as may, in his
opinion, be necessary.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
No act of the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District Magistrate done in
pursuance of this section shall be called in question in any court or before any
authority on any ground whatsoever.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>30</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No
suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or the Appellate
Authority, or the Chairman or any other Member, officer or other employee of the
Board or the Appellate Authority, or operating agency or any other person
authorised by the Board or the Appellate Authority to discharge any function
under this Act for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by any
action which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this
Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Saving 
    of pending proceedings.—Where 
    a receiver or an official liquidator has been appointed in any proceeding 
    pending immediately before the commencement of this Act, in any High Court 
    for winding up of an industrial company such proceeding shall not abate but 
    continue in that High Court 
<footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[and 
    no proceeding in respect of such industrial company shall lie or be 
    proceeded with further before the Board].  

 
   




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Effect 
    of the Act on other laws.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of this Act and of any rules or schemes made thereunder shall 
    have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any 
    other law except the provisions of the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 
    (46 of 1973) and the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976 (33 of 
    1976) for the time being in force or in the Memorandum or Articles of 
    Association of an industrial company or in any other instrument having 
    effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there 
    has been under any scheme under this Act an amalgamation of a sick 
    industrial company with another company, the provisions of section 72A of 
    the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), shall, subject to the modifications 
    that the power of the Central Government under that section may be exercised 
    by the Board without the Central Government under that section may be 
    exercised by the Board without any recommendation by the specified authority 
    referred to in that section, apply in relation to such amalgamation as they 
    apply in relation to the amalgamation of a company owning an industrial 
    undertaking with another company.
 

<footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[***]
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Penalty 
    for certain offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever violates the provisions of this Act or any scheme, or any order of 
    the Board, or the Appellate Authority and whoever makes a false statement or 
    gives false evidence to the Board or the Appellate Authority, shall be 
    punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    years and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of any offence under sub-section (1) except 
    on a complaint in writing of the Secretary or any such other officer of the 
    Board or the Appellate Authority or any such officer of an operating agency 
    as may be authorised in this behalf by the Board or the Appellate 
    Authority.]
 

   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>34</number>
Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any offence, punishable under this Act has been committed by a company,
every person who, at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and
was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company,
as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 Provided
that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable
to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his
knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission
of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence
punishable under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that
the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is
attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer
shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be
proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection><number>a</number> 
“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other
association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> 
“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number>
Power to remove difficulties.—If
any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act or the
rules, schemes or orders made thereunder, the Central Government may, by
notification, remove the difficulty:
 Provided
that no such notification shall be made by the Central Government after the
expiry of a period of three years from the date on which this Act receives the
assent of the President.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 the salaries and allowances
payable to and other terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other
Members under sub-section (7) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 the powers which may be
exercised and the duties which may be performed by the Secretary to the Board or
the Appellate Authority under sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 the restrictions and
conditions subject to which officers and employees may be appointed to the Board
or the Appellate Authority under sub-section (2) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 the salaries and allowances
and other conditions of service of the Secretary and other officers and
employees of the Board or the Appellate Authority under sub-section (3) of
section 8;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 the additional matters
referred to in sub-section (3) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 any other matter which is
required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rule.

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE SICK INDUSTRIAL COMPANIES (SPECIAL PROVISIONS) ACT, 1985
 

 
 

 
 


THE SCHEDULE
 


[See sections 6(8) and 8(3) ] 


 


DECLARATION OF FIDELITY AND SECRECY  

 

 
 


I, ........................, do hereby declare 
    that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability, 
    execute and perform the duties required of me as the 
    Chairman/Member/Secretary/other officer or employee of the Board for the 
    Industrial and Financial Reconstruction/the Appellate Authority for 
    Industrial and Financial Reconstruction and which properly relate to the 
    office or position held by me in or in relation to the said Board/Appellate 
    Authority.
 


I further declare that I will not communicate 
    or allow to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any 
    information relating to the affairs of the Board/ Appellate Authority, nor 
    will I allow any such person to inspect or have access to any books or 
    documents belonging to or in possession of the Board/ Appellate Authority or 
    the business of any person having any dealing with the said Board/ Appellate 
    Authority.
 


   

 


Signed before me.
 


Signature
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
     Came into force on 12-1-1987 
    (except sections 15 to 34), vide
G.S.R. 24(E), dated 12th January, 1987 and sections 15 to 34 came 
    into force on 15-5-1987, vide S.O. 444(E), dated 28th April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
     The words and figures “, but 
    does not include a Government Company as defined in section 617 of that Act” 
    omitted by Act 57 of 1991, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-12-1991). tc 
    " 1. The words and figures “, but does not include a Government Company as 
    defined in section 617 of that Act” omitted by Act 57 of 1991, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    28-12-1991)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994). tc " 2. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 2, 
    for cluse (i) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 3. Subs. by Act 
    12 of 1994, sec. 2, for cluse (i) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
     Clause (k) omitted by Act 12 of 
    1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 4. Clause (k) 
    omitted by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 2, 
    for clause (o) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 1. Subs. by Act 
    12 of 1994, sec. 2, for clause (o) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 3, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994). tc " 1. Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 3, 
    for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 4. tc " 1. Subs. 
    by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 4."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Ins. by Act 54 of 2002, sec. 41 and Sch. (w.r.e.f. 21-6-2002). tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 54 of 2002, sec. 41 and Sch. (w.r.e.f. 21-6-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994). tc " 1. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 5, 
    for “it shall appoint”. tc " 2. Subs. by Act 12 of 
    1994, sec. 5, for “it shall appoint”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994). tc " 1. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 6, 
    for “make its net worth positive”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, for clause (a) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, for clause (c) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>
Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, 
    for “transferee industrial company” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, 
    for “transferee industrial company” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, 
    for clause (a) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, for “any other industrial company” (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, for “such industrial companies” (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>
The words “of the sick industrial company” omitted by Act 12 of 1994, 
    sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, for “transferee industrial company” 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 7, 
    for sub-section (8) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>
Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 
    10, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 
    11, for “in relation to an inquiry or scheme” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 11, for “in relation to an inquiry or 
    scheme” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 11, for
“an industrial company” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 
    1. Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 11, for
“an industrial company” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 12 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 12 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>
Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 12, for “During the period” (w.e.f. 
    1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 13 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 1. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, 
    sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 
    14, for “preceding five financial years” (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>
     Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 15 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 2. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, 
    sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>
Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>
     Added by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 16 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 1. Added by Act 12 of 1994, 
    sec. 16 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>
     The word “or” omitted by Act 12 
    of 1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 1. The word 
    “or” omitted by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>
     The word “or” ins. by Act 12 of 
    1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 2. The word “or” 
    ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>
Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>
     Added by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 18 
    (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 1. Added by Act 12 of 1994, 
    sec. 18 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>
Sub-section (3) omitted by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 1-2-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>
     Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 
    20, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994). tc " 3. 
    Subs. by Act 12 of 1994, sec. 20, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-2-1994)."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>