<act><title>


THE GUARDIANS AND WARDS ACT, 1890</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Guardians and Wards Act, 1890.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India 

1[except the State 
of Jammu and Kashmir] 

2[***]; 

3[***].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on the first day of July, 1890.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number>
[Repealed by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Schedule].
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Saving of 
jurisdiction of Courts of Wards and Chartered High Courts.—This 
Act shall be read subject to every enactment here­tofore or hereafter passed 
relating to any Court of Wards by 

1[any competent 
Legislature, authority or person in 

2[any State to 
which this Act extends]]; and nothing in this Act shall be construed to effect 
or in any way derogate from, the jurisdiction or authority of any Court of 
Wards, or to take away any power possessed by 

3[any High Court


4[***]].
 
 






</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
        <number>1</number>  “minor” means 
a person who, under the provisions of the Indian Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875), 
is to be deemed not to have attained his majority;
 </section><section>
        <number>2</number>  “guardian” 
means a person having the care of the person of a minor or of his property or of 
both his person and property;
 </section><section>
        <number>3</number>  “ward” means 
a minor for whose person or property or both there is a guardian;
 </section><section>
        <number>4</number>  “District 
Court” has the meaning assigned to that expression in the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1, 
and includes a High Court in the exercise of its ordinary original civil 
jurisdiction;
 

         2[(5)  
“the Court” means—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  the 
District Court having jurisdiction to entertain an appli­cation under this Act 
for an order appointing or declaring a person to be a guardian; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  where a 
guardian has been appointed or declared in pursuance of any such application—
 <subsubsection>
                   <number>i</number>  
the Court which, or the Court of the officer who, appointed or declared the 
guardian or is under this Act deemed to have appointed or declared the guardian; 
or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>ii</number>  in 
any matter relating to the person of the ward the Dis­trict Court having 
jurisdiction in the place where the ward for the time being ordinarily resides; 
or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             <number>c</number>  in 
respect of any proceeding transferred under section 4A, the Court of the officer 
to whom such proceeding has been trans­ferred;]
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>6</number>  “Collector” 
means the chief officer in charge of the revenue-administration of a district 
and includes any officer whom the State Government, by notification in the 
Official Ga­zette may, by name or in virtue of his office, appoint to be a 
Collector in any local area or with respect to any class of persons, for all or 
any of the purposes of this Act;
 

  3[***]; and
 </section><section>
        <number>8</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by rules made by the High Court under this Act.
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>4A</number> Power to 
confer jurisdiction on subordinate judicial officers and to transfer proceedings 
to such officers.—
<section><number>1</number> The High Court may, by general or special order, 
empower any officer exercising original civil jurisdiction subordinate to a 
district court, or authorize the Judge of any District Court to empower any such 
officer subordinate to him, to dispose of any proceed­ings under this Act 
transferred to such officer under the provi­sions of this section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Judge of a 
district court may, by order in writing, transfer at any stage any proceeding 
under this Act pending in his Court for disposal to any officer subordinate to 
him empow­ered under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Judge of a 
district court may at any stage transfer to his own Court or to any officer 
subordinate to him empowered under sub-section (1) any proceeding under this Act 
pending in the Court of any other such officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When any proceedings 
are transferred under this section in any case in which a guardian has been 
appointed or declared, the Judge of the District Court may, by order in writing, 
declare that the Court of the Judge or officer to whom they are transferred 
shall, for all or any of the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be the Court 
which appointed or declared the guardian.]









</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power of parents to 
appoint in case of European British subjects.—[Rep. 
by the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951 (3 of 1951), sec. 3 and Schedule].
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Saving of power to 
appoint in other cases.—In 
the case of a minor 

1[***], nothing in 
this Act shall be construed to take away or derogate from any power to appoint a 
guardian of his person or property or both, which is valid by the law to which 
the minor is subject.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of the Court 
to make order as to guardianship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Court is satisfied that it is for the welfare of a minor that an order 
should be made—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  appointing a 
guardian of his person or property or both, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  declaring a 
person to be such a guardian
 
the Court may make an 
order accordingly.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order under this 
section shall imply the removal of any guardian who has not been appointed by 
will or other instrument or appointed or declared by the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a guardian has 
been appointed by will or other instru­ment or appointed or declared by the 
Court, an order under this section appointing or declaring another person to be 
guardian in his stead shall not be made until the powers of the guardian 
appointed or declared as aforesaid have ceased under the provi­sions of this 
Act.












</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Persons entitled to 
apply for order.—An 
order shall not be made under the last foregoing section except on the 
application of—
 <section>
 
<number>a</number>  the person desirous 
of being, or claiming to be, the guardian of the minor; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  any relative 
or friend of the minor; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the Collector 
of the district or other local area within which the minor ordinarily resides or 
in which he has property; or
 </section><section>
 
<number>d</number>  the Collector having 
authority with respect to the class to which the minor belongs.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Court having 
jurisdiction to entertain application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the application is with respect to the guardianship of the person of the 
minor, it shall be made to the District Court having jurisdiction in the place 
where the minor ordinarily resides.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the application is 
with respect to the guardianship of the property of the minor, it may be made 
either to the District Court having jurisdiction in the place where the minor 
ordinarily resides or to a District Court having jurisdiction in a place where 
he has property.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If an application with 
respect to the guardianship of the property of a minor is made to a District 
Court other than that having jurisdiction in the place where the minor 
ordinarily resides, the Court may return the application if in its opinion the 
application would be disposed of more justly or conveniently by any other 
District Court having jurisdiction.







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Form of 
application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the application is not made by the Collector, it shall be by petition signed 
and verified in manner prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 
1882)1, 
for the signing and verification of a plaint, and stat­ing, so far as can be 
ascertained,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the name, 
sex, religion, date of birth and ordinary residence of the minor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  where the 
minor is a female, whether she is married and if so, the name and age of her 
husband;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the nature, 
situation and approximate value of the property, if any, of the minor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the name and 
residence of the person having the custody or possession of the person or 
property of the minor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  what near 
relations the minor has and where they reside;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  whether a 
guardian of the person or property or both, of the minor has been appointed by 
any person entitled or claiming to be entitled by the law to which the minor is 
subject to make such an appointment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  whether an 
application has at any time been made to the Court or to any other Court with 
respect to the guardianship of the person or property or both, of the minor and 
if so, when, to what Court and with what result;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  whether the 
application is for the appointment or declaration of a guardian of the person of 
the minor, or of his property, or of both;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  where the 
application is to appoint a guardian, the qualifi­cations of the proposed 
guardian;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  where the 
application is to declare a person to be a guardian, the grounds on which that 
person claims;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  the causes 
which have led to the making of the application; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>l</number>  such other 
particulars, if any, as may be prescribed or as the nature of the application 
renders it necessary to state.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the application is 
made by the Collector, it shall be by letter addressed to the Court and 
forwarded by post or in such other manner as may be found convenient, and shall 
state as far as possible the particulars mentioned in sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application must 
be accompanied by a declaration of the willingness of the proposed guardian to 
act, and the declaration must be signed by him and attested by at least two 
witnesses.








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Procedure on 
admission of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Court is satisfied that there is ground for proceeding on the 
application, it shall fix a day for the hearing thereof and cause notice of the 
application and of the date fixed for the hearing—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  to be served 
in the manner directed in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1 on—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  the 
parents of the minor if they are residing in 

2[any State to 
which this Act extends];
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  the 
person, if any, named in the petition or letter as having the custody or 
possession of the person or property of the minor;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  the 
person proposed in the application or letter to be appointed or declared 
guardian, unless that person is himself the applicant, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iv</number>  any 
other person to whom, in the opinion of the Court, spe­cial notice of the 
application should be given; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  to be posted 
on some conspicuous part of the Court-house and of the residence of the minor, 
and otherwise published in such manner as the Court, subject to any rules made 
by the High Court under this Act, thinks fit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
may, by general or special order, re­quire that when any part of the property 
described in a petition under section 10, sub-section (1), is land of which a 
Court of Wards could assume the superintendence, the Court shall also cause a 
notice as aforesaid to be served on the Collector in whose dis­trict the minor 
ordinarily resides and on every Collector in whose district any portion of the 
land is situate, and the Collec­tor may cause the notice to be published in any 
manner he deems fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No charge shall be 
made by the Court or the Collector for the service or publication of any notice 
served or published under sub-section (2).







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to make 
interlocutory order for production of minor and interim protection of person and 
property.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Court may direct that the person, if any, having the custody of the minor, 
shall produce him or cause him to be produced at such place and time and before 
such person as it appoints, and may make such order for the temporary custody 
and protection of the person or property of the minor as it thinks proper.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the minor is a 
female who ought not to be compelled to appear in public, the direction under 
sub-section (1) for her production shall require her to be produced in 
accordance with the customs and manners of the country.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this 
section shall authorise—
 <subsection>
 
<number>a</number>  the Court to place a 
female minor in the temporary custody of a person claiming to be her guardian on 
the ground of his being her husband, unless she is already in his custody with 
the consent of her parents, if any, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  any person to 
whom the temporary custody and protection of the property of a minor is 
entrusted to dispossess otherwise than by due course of law any person in 
possession of any of the property.



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Hearing of evidence 
before making of order.—On 
the day fixed for the hearing of the application or as soon afterwards as may 
be, the Court shall hear such evidence as may be adduced in support of or in 
opposition to the application.


</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Simultaneous 
proceedings in different Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If pro­ceedings for the appointment or declaration of a guardian of a minor are 
taken in more Courts than one, each of those Courts shall, on being apprised of 
the proceedings in the other Court or Courts, stay the proceedings before 
itself.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Courts are both 
or all subordinate to the same High Court, they shall report the case to the 
High Court, and the High Court shall determine in which of the Courts the 
proceedings with respect to the appointment or declaration of a guardian of the 
minor shall be had.
 

1[(3) In any other 
case in which proceedings are stayed under sub-section (1), the Courts shall 
report the case to and be guided by such orders as they may receive from their 
respective State Governments.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Appointment or 
declaration of several guardians.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the law to which the minor is subject admits of his having two or more joint 
guardians of his person or property or both, the Court may, if it thinks fit, 
appoint or declare them.
 

1[***]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Separate guardians may 
be appointed or declared of the person and of the property of a minor.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If a minor has several 
properties, the Court may, if it thinks fit, appoint or declare a separate 
guardian for any one or more of the properties.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Appointment or 
declaration of guardian for property beyond jurisdiction of the Court.—If 
the Court appoints or declares a guardian for any property situate beyond the 
local limits of its jurisdiction, the Court having jurisdiction in the place 
where the property is situate shall, on production of a certified copy of the 
order appointing or declaring the guardian accept him as duly appointed or 
declared and give effect to the order.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Matters to be 
considered by the Court in appointing guardian.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In appointing or declaring the guardian of a minor, the Court shall, subject to 
the provisions of this sec­tion, be guided by what, consistently with the law to 
which the minor is subject, appears in the circumstances to be for the welfare 
of the minor.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In considering what 
will be for the welfare of the minor, the Court shall have regard to the age, 
sex and religion of the minor, the character and capacity of the proposed 
guardian and his nearness of kin to the minor, the wishes, if any, of a 
de­ceased parent, and any existing or previous relations of the proposed 
guardian with the minor or his property.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If minor is old enough 
to form an intelligent preference, the Court may consider that preference.
 

1[***]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Court shall not 
appoint or declare any person to be a guardian against his will.










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appointment or 
declaration of Collector in virtue of office.—Where 
a Collector is appointed or declared by the Court in virtue of his office to be 
guardian of the person or property or both, of a minor, the order appointing or 
declaring him shall be deemed to authorize and require the person for the time 
being holding the office to act as guardian of the minor with respect to his 
person or property or both, as the case may be.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Guardian not to be 
appointed by the Court in certain cases.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall authorize the Court to appoint or declare a guardian of 
the property of a minor whose property is under the superintendence of a Court 
of Wards or to appoint or declare a guardian of the person—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  of a minor 
who is married female and whose husband is not, in the opinion of Court, unfit 
to be guardian of her person; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  

1[***] of a minor 
whose father is living and is not in the opinion of the Court, unfit to be 
guardian of the person of the minor; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  of a minor 
whose property is under the superintendence of a Court of Wards competent to 
appoint a guardian of the person of the minor.






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Fiduciary relation 
of guardian to ward.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A guardian stands in a fiduciary relation to his ward, and, save as provided by 
the will or other instrument, if any, by which he was appointed, or by his Act, 
he must not make any profit out of his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fiduciary relation 
of a guardian to his ward extends to and affects purchases by the guardian of 
the property of the ward, and by the ward of the property of the guardian, 
immediate­ly or soon after the ward has ceased to be a minor and generally all 
transactions between them while the influence of the guardian still lasts or is 
recent.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>21</number> Capacity of minors to act as 
guardians.—A 
minor is incompe­tent to act as guardian of any minor except his own wife or 
child or where he is the managing member of an undivided Hindu family, the wife 
or child of another minor member of that family.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Remuneration of 
guardian.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
guardian appointed or de­clared by the Court shall be entitled to such 
allowance, if any, as the Court thinks fit for his care and pains in the 
execution of his duties.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When an officer of the 
Government, as such officer, is so appointed or declared to be guardian, such 
fees shall be paid to the Government out of the property of the ward as the 
State Government, by general or special order, directs.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Control of 
Collector as guardian.—A 
Collector appointed or declared by the Court to be guardian of the person or 
property or both, of a minor shall, in all matters connected with the 
guard­ianship of his ward, be subject to the control of the State Government or 
of such authority as that Government, by notifica­tion in the Official Gazette, 
appoints in this behalf.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Duties of guardian 
of the person.—A 
guardian of the person of a ward is charged with the custody of the ward and 
must look to his support, health and education, and such other matters as the 
law to which the ward is subject requires.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Title of guardian 
to custody of ward.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a ward leaves or is removed from the custody of a guardian of his person, the 
Court, if it is of opinion that it will be for the welfare of the ward to return 
to the custody of his guardian, may make an order for his return and for the 
purpose of enforcing the order may cause the ward to be arrested and to be 
delivered into the custo­dy of the guardian.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
arresting the ward, the Court may exercise the power conferred on a Magistrate 
of the first class by section 100 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 
1882)1.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The residence of a 
ward against the will of his guardian with a person who is not his guardian does 
not of itself terminate the guardianship.


















</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Removal of ward 
from jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A guardian of the person appointed or declared by the Court, unless he is the 
Collector or is a guardian appointed by will or other instrument, shall not, 
without the leave of the Court by which he was ap­pointed or declared, remove 
the ward from the limits of its jurisdiction except for such purposes as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The leave granted by 
the Court under sub-section (1) may be special or general and may be defined by 
the order granting it.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Duties of guardian 
of property.—A 
guardian of the property of a ward is bound to deal therewith as carefully as a 
man of ordinary prudence would deal with it, if it were his own and subject to 
the provisions of this Chapter, he may do all acts which are reasonable and 
proper for the realisation, protection or benefit of the property.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Powers of 
testamentary guardian.—Where 
a guardian has been appointed by will or other instrument, his power to mortgage 
or charge, or transfer by sale, gift, exchange or otherwise, immova­ble property 
belonging to his ward is subject to any restriction which may be imposed by the 
instrument, unless he has under this Act been declared guardian and the Court 
which made the declara­tion permits him by an order in writing, notwithstanding 
the restriction, to dispose of any immovable property specified in the order in 
a manner permitted by the order.
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Limitation of powers of guardian of property appointed or declared by the Court. </title>—Where a person other than a Collector, or than a guardian appointed by will or other instrument, has been appointed or declared by the Court to be guardian of the property of a ward, he shall not, without the previous permission of the Court,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> mortgage or charge, or transfer by sale, gift, exchange or otherwise, any part of the immovable property of his ward, or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> lease any part of that property for a term exceeding five years or for any term extending more than one year beyond the date on which the ward will cease to be a minor. 
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Voidability of transfers made in contravention of section 28 or section 29. </title>—A disposal of immovable property by a guardian in contravention of either of the two last foregoing sections is voidable at the instance of any other person affected thereby. 


</article> 

  
 <article><number>31</number> Practice with respect to 
permitting transfers under section 29.—
<section><number>1</number> Permission to the guardian to 
do any of the acts men­tioned in section 29 shall not be granted by the 
Court except in case of necessity or for an evident advantage to the 
ward.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The order granting the 
permission shall recite the necessity or advantage, as the case may be, describe 
the property with respect to which the act permitted is to be done, and specify 
such conditions, if any, as the Court may see fit to attach to the permission; 
and it shall be recorded, dated and signed by the Judge of the Court with his 
own hand, or, when from any cause he is prevented from recording the order with 
his own hand, shall be taken down in writing from his dictation and be dated and 
signed by him.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Court may in its 
discretion attach to the permission the following among other conditions, 
namely:—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  that a sale shall not be completed without the sanction of the 
Court;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  that a sale shall be made to the highest bidder by public auction 
before the Court or some person specially appointed by the Court for that 
purpose, at a time and place to be specified by the Court, after such 
proclamation of the intended sale as the Court subject to any rules made under 
this Act by the High Court, directs;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  that a lease shall not be made in consideration of a premium or shall 
be made for such term of years and subject to such rents and covenants as the 
Court directs;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>d</number>  that the whole or any part of the proceeds of the act permit­ted 
shall be paid into the Court by the guardian, to be disbursed therefrom or to be 
invested by the Court on prescribed securities or to be otherwise disposed of as 
the Court directs.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Before granting permission to 
a guardian to do an act men­tioned in section 29, the Court may cause notice 
of the applica­tion for the permission to be given to any relative or friend 
of the ward who should, in its opinion, receive notice thereof, and shall hear 
and record the statement of any person who appears in opposition to the 
application.</section></article> 

  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>32</number> Variation of powers of guardian of property appointed or declared by the Court. </title>—Where a guardian of the property of a ward has been appointed or declared by the Court and such guard­ian is not the Collector, the Court may, from time to time, by order, define, restrict or extend his powers with respect to the property of the ward in such manner and to such extent as it may consider to be for the advantage of the ward and consistent with the law to which the ward is subject. <title></title>
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Right of guardian 
so appointed or declared to apply to the Court for opinion in management of 
property of ward.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A guardian appointed or declared by the Court may apply by petition to the Court 
which appointed or declared him for its opinion, advice or direction on any 
present question respecting the man­agement or administration of the property of 
his ward.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Court considers 
the question to be proper for summary disposal, it shall cause a copy of the 
petition to be served on, and the hearing thereof may be attended by, such of 
the persons interested in the application as the Court thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The guardian stating 
in good faith the facts in the petition and acting upon the opinion, advice or 
direction given by the Court shall be deemed, so far as regards his own 
responsibility, to have performed his duty as guardian in the subject-matter of 
the application.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Obligations on 
guardian of property appointed or declared by the Court.—Where 
a guardian of the property of a ward has been appointed or declared by the Court 
and such guardian is not the Collector, he shall,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if so 
required by the Court, give a bond, as nearly as may be in the prescribed form, 
to the Judge of the Court to ensure for the benefit of the Judge for the time 
being, with or without sureties, as may be prescribed, engaging duly to account 
for what he may receive in respect of the property of the ward;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  if so 
required by the Court, deliver to the Court, within six months from the date of 
his appointment or declaration by the Court, or within such other time as the 
Court directs, a state­ment of the immovable property belonging to the ward, of 
the money and other movable property which he has received on behalf of the ward 
up to the date of delivering the statement, and of the debts due on that date to 
or from the ward;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  if so 
required by the Court, exhibit his accounts in the Court at such times and in 
such form as the Court from time to time directs;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  if so 
required by the Court, pay into the Court at such time as the Court directs the 
balance due from him on those accounts, or so much thereof as the Court directs; 
and
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  apply for the 
maintenance, education and advancement of the ward and of such persons as are 
dependent on him, and for the celebration of ceremonies to which the ward or any 
of those per­sons may be a party, such portion of the income of the property of 
the ward as the Court from time to time directs, and, if the Court so directs, 
the whole or any part of that property.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>34A</number> Power to 
award remuneration for auditing accounts.—When accounts are exhibited by a 
guardian of the property of a ward in pursuance of a requisition made under 
clause (c) of section 34 or otherwise, the Court may appoint a person to audit 
the accounts, and may direct that remuneration for the work be paid out of the 
income of the property.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Suit against 
guardian where administration-bond was taken.—Where 
a guardian appointed or declared by the Court has given a bond duly to account 
for what he may receive in respect of the property of his ward, the Court may, 
on application made by petition and on being satisfied that the engagement of 
the bond has not been kept, and upon such terms as to security, or provid­ing 
that any money received be paid into the Court, or otherwise as the Court thinks 
fit, assign the bond to some proper person, who shall thereupon be entitled to 
sue on the bond in his own name as if the bond had been originally given to him 
instead of to the Judge of the Court, and shall be entitled to recover thereon, 
as trustee for the ward, in respect of any breach there­of.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Suit against 
guardian where administration-bond was not taken.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a guardian appointed or declared by the Court has not given a bond as 
aforesaid, any person, with the leave of the Court, may, as next friend, at any 
time during the continu­ance of the minority of the ward, and upon such terms as 
afore­said, institute a suit against the guardian, or, in case of his death, 
against his representative, for an account of what the guardian has received in 
respect of the property of the ward, and may recover in the suit, as trustee for 
the ward, such amount as may be found to be payable by the guardian or his 
representative, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
sub-section (1) shall, so far as they relate to a suit against a guardian, be 
subject to the provisions of section 440 of the Code of Civil Procedure, as 
amended by this Act, 1882 (14 of 1882)1.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> General liability 
of guardian as trustee.—Nothing 
in either of the two last foregoing sections shall be construed to deprive a 
ward or his representative of any remedy against his guardian, or the 
representative of the guardian, which, not being expressly provided in either of 
those sections, any other beneficiary or his representative would have against 
his trustee or the repre­sentative of the trustee.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Right of 
survivorship among joint guardians.—On 
the death of one of two or more joint guardians, the guardianship continues to 
the survivor or survivors until a further appointment is made by the Court.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Removal of 
guardian.—The 
Court may, on the application of any person interested, or of its own motion, 
remove a guardian ap­pointed or declared by the Court, or a guardian appointed 
by will or other instrument, for any of the following causes, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  for abuse of 
his trust;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  for continued 
failure to perform the duties of his trust;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  for 
incapacity to perform the duties of his trust;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  for 
ill-treatment, or neglect to take proper care, of his ward;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  for 
contumacious disregard of any provision of this Act or of any order of the 
Court;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  for 
conviction of an offence implying, in the opinion of the Court, a defect of 
character which unfits him to be the guardian of his ward;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  for having an 
interest adverse to the faithful performance of his duties;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  for ceasing 
to reside within the local limits of the juris­diction of the Court;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  in the case 
of a guardian of the property, for bankruptcy or insolvency;
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  by reason of 
the guardianship of the guardian ceasing, or being liable to cease, under the 
law to which the minor is sub­ject:
 
Provided that a guardian 
appointed by will or other instrument, whether he has been declared under this 
Act or not, shall not be removed— 
 </section><section>
 
<number>a</number>  for the cause 
mentioned in clause (g) unless the adverse interest accrued after the death of 
the person who appointed him, or it is shown that that person made and 
maintained the appoint­ment in ignorance of the existence of the adverse 
interest, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  for the cause 
mentioned in clause (h) unless such guardian has taken up such a residence as, 
in the opinion of the Court, renders it impracticable for him to discharge the 
functions of guardian.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Discharge of 
guardian.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a guardian appointed or de­clared by the Court desires to resign his office, 
he may apply to the Court to be discharged.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Court finds 
that there is sufficient reason for the application, it shall discharge him, and 
if the guardian making the application is the Collector and the State Government 
ap­proves of his applying to be discharged, the Court shall in any case 
discharge him.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Cessation of 
authority of guardian.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The powers of a guardian of the person cease—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  by his death, 
removal or discharge;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  by the Court 
of Wards assuming superintendence of the person of the ward;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  by the ward 
ceasing to be a minor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  in the case 
of a female ward, by her marriage to a husband who is not unfit to be guardian 
of her person or, if the guardian was appointed or declared by the Court, by her 
marriage to a husband who is not, in the opinion of the Court, so unfit; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  in the case 
of a ward whose father was unfit to be guardian of the person of the ward, by 
the father ceasing to be so or, if the father was deemed by the Court to be so 
unfit, by his ceasing to be so in the opinion of the Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The powers of a 
guardian of the property cease—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  by his death, 
removal or discharge;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  by the Court 
of Wards assuming superintendence of the proper­ty of the ward; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  by the ward 
ceasing to be a minor.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> When for any cause the 
powers of a guardian cease, the Court may require him or, if he is dead, his 
representative to deliver as it directs any property in his possession or 
control belonging to the ward or any accounts in his possession or control 
relating to any past or present property of the ward.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When he has delivered 
the property or accounts as required by the Court, the Court may declare him to 
be discharged from his liabilities save as regards any fraud which may 
subsequently be discovered.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Appointment of 
successor to guardian dead, discharged or removed.—When 
a guardian appointed or declared by the Court is discharged, or, under the law 
to which the ward is subject, ceases to be entitled to act, or when any such 
guardian or a guardian appointed by Will or other instrument is removed or dies, 
the Court, of its own motion or on application under Chapter II, may, if the 
ward is still a minor, appoint or declare another guardian of his person or 
property, or both, as the case may be.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Orders for 
regulating conduct or proceedings of guardians, and enforcement of those orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Court may, on the application of any person interested or of its own motion, 
make an order regulating the conduct or proceedings of any guardian appointed or 
declared by the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there are more 
guardians than one of a ward and they are unable to agree upon a question 
affecting his welfare, any of them may apply to the Court for its direction, and 
the Court may make such order respecting the matter in difference as it thinks 
fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Except where it 
appears that the object of making an order under sub-section (1) or sub-section 
(2) would be defeated by the delay, the Court shall, before making the order, 
direct notice of the application therefor or of the intention of the Court to 
make it, as the case may be, to be given, in a case under sub-section (1), to 
the guardian or, in a case under sub-section (2), to the guardian who has not 
made the application.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In case of 
disobedience to an order made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the 
order may be enforced in the same manner as an injunction granted under section 
492 or section 493 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1, 
in a case under sub-section (1), as if the ward were the plaintiff and the 
guardian were the defendant or, in a case under sub-section (2), as if the 
guardian who made the application were the plaintiff and the other guardian were 
the defendant.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Except in a case under 
sub-section (2), nothing in this section shall apply to a Collector who is, as 
such, a guardian.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Penalty for removal 
of ward from jurisdiction.—If, 
for the purpose or with the effect of preventing the Court from exercis­ing its 
authority with respect to a ward, a guardian appointed or declared by the Court 
removes the ward from the limits of the jurisdiction of the Court in 
contravention of the provisions of section 26, he shall be liable, by order of 
the Court, to fine not exceeding one thousand rupees, or to imprison­ment in the 
civil jail for a term which may extend to six months.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Penalty for 
contumacy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the following cases, namely:—
 <subsection>
 
<number>a</number>  If a person having 
the custody of a minor fails to produce him or cause him to be produced in 
compliance with a direction under section 12, sub-section (1), or to do his 
utmost to compel the minor to return to the custody of his guardian in obedience 
to an order under section 25, sub-section (1); or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if a guardian 
appointed or declared by the Court fails to deliver to the Court, within the 
time allowed by or under clause (b) of section 34, a statement required under 
that clause, or to exhibit accounts in compliance with a requisition under 
clause (c) of that section, or to pay into the Court the balance due from him on 
those accounts in compliance with a requisition under clause (d) of that 
section;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  if a person 
who has ceased to be a guardian, or the represen­tative of such a person, fails 
to deliver any property or ac­counts in compliance with a requisition under 
section 41, sub-section (3),
 
the person, guardian or 
representative, as the case may be, shall be liable, by order of the Court, to 
fine not exceeding one hun­dred rupees, and in case of recusancy to further fine 
not exceed­ing ten rupees for each day after the first during which the default 
continues, and not exceeding five hundred rupees in the aggregate, and to 
detention in the civil jail until he undertakes to produce the minor or cause 
him to be produced, or to compel his return, or to deliver the statement, or to 
exhibit the ac­counts, or to pay the balance, or to deliver the property or 
accounts, as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If a person who has 
been released from detention on giving an undertaking under sub-section (1) 
fails to carry out the under­taking within the time allowed by the Court, the 
Court may cause him to be arrested and recommitted to the civil jail.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Reports by 
Collectors and subordinate Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Court may call upon the Collector, or upon any Court subordinate to the 
Court, for a report on any matter arising in any proceeding under this Act and 
treat the report as evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
preparing the report the Collector or the Judge of the subordinate Court, as the 
case may be, shall make such inquiry as he deems necessary, and may for the 
purposes of the inquiry exercise any power of compelling the attendance of a 
witness to give evidence or produce a document which is conferred on a Court by 
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Orders appealable.—An 
appeal shall lie to the High Court from an order made by a 

1[***] Court,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  under section 
7, appointing or declaring or refusing to appoint or declare a guardian; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  under section 
9, sub-section (3), returning an application; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  under section 
25, making or refusing to make an order for the return of a ward to the custody 
of his guardian; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  under section 
26, refusing leave for the removal of a ward from the limits of the jurisdiction 
of the Court, or imposing conditions with respect thereto; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  under section 
28 or section 29, refusing permission to a guardian to do an act referred to in 
the section; or
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  under 
section 32, defining, restricting or extending the powers of a guardian; or
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  under section 
39, removing a guardian; or
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  under section 
40, refusing to discharge a guardian; or
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  under 
section 43, regulating the conduct or proceedings of a guardian or settling a 
matter in difference between joint guardians or enforcing the order; or
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  under 
section 44 or section 45, imposing a penalty.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Finality of other 
orders.—Save as 
provided by the last foregoing section and by section 622 of the Code of Civil 
Proce­dure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1, 
an order made under this Act shall be final, and shall not be liable to be 
contested by suit or other­wise.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Costs.—The 
costs of any proceeding under this Act, including the costs of maintaining a 
guardian or other person in the civil jail, shall, subject to any rules made by 
the High Court under this Act, be in the discretion of the Court in which the 
proceed­ing is, had.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Power of High Court 
to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In addition to any other power to make rules conferred expressly or impliedly by 
this Act, the High Court may from time to time make rules con­sistent with this 
Act—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  as to the 
matters respecting which, and the time at which, reports should be called for 
from Collectors and subordinate Courts;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  as to the 
allowances to be granted to, and the security to be required from, guardians, 
and the cases in which such allowances should be granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  as to the 
procedure to be followed with respect to applica­tions of guardians for 
permission to do acts referred to in sections 28 and 29;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  as to the 
circumstances in which such requisitions as are mentioned in clauses (a), (b), 
(c) and (d) of section 34 should be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  as to the 
preservation of statements and accounts delivered and exhibited by guardians;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  as to the 
inspection of those statements and accounts by persons interested;
 

        1[(ff)  as 
to the audit of accounts under section 34A, the class of persons who should be 
appointed to audit accounts, and the scales of remuneration to be granted to 
them;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  as to the 
custody of money, and securities for money, belonging to wards;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  as to the 
securities on which money belonging to wards may be invested;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  as to the 
education of wards for whom guardians, not being Collectors, have been appointed 
or declared by the Court; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  generally, 
for the guidance of the Courts in carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Rules under clauses 
(a) and (i) of sub-section (1) shall not have effect until they have been 
approved by the 

2[State 
Govern­ment], nor shall any rule under this section have effect until it has 
been published in the Official Gazette.
 
 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>51</number> Applicability of Act to 
guardians already appointed by Court.—A guardian appointed by, or 
holding a certificate of administration from, a Civil Court under any enactment 
repealed by this Act shall, save as may be prescribed, be subject to the 
provisions of this Act, and of the rules made under it, as if he had been 
appointed or declared by the Court under Chapter II.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Amendment of Indian 
Majority Act.—[Rep. 
by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), section 2 and Schedule].
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Amendment of 
Chapter XXXI of the Code of Civil Procedure.—[Rep. 
by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), section 156 and Sch.V].
</article><form>
 




THE GUARDIANS AND WARDS ACT, 1890
 


 
 


THE SCHEDULE.—Enactments 
repealed.—[Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), section 2 and 
Schedule].
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>