<act><title>

THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (APPEAL) 
    RULES, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Money-laundering (Appeal) Rules, 2005. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Prevention of 
    Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Adjudicating Authority” means an 
    Adjudicating Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Appellate Tribunal” means the 
    Appellate Tribunal established under section 25 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “appellant” means an aggrieved person 
    who prefers an appeal before the Appellate Tribunal;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Director” means the Director appointed 
    under sub-section (1) of section 49 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “Form” means the form appended to these 
    rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “order” means an order passed by the 
    Director under sub-section (2) of section 13 of the Act or by the 
    Adjudicating Authority under section 8 of the Act, as the case may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “Registrar” means the Registrar of the 
    Appellate Tribunal;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “section” means a section of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 
    Act, shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Form of 
    Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every appeal 
    preferred before the Appellate Tribunal against the order of the 
    Adjudicating Authority or the Director, as the case may be, under section 26 
    of the Act shall be in the Form as appended to these rules and the appeal 
    shall be in quadruplicate and accompanied by four copies of the order 
    appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At the 
    time of filing, every appeal shall be accompanied with an amount of fee as 
    given in the Table below, in the form of demand draft payable in favour of 
    the Registrar, Appellate Tribunal, New Delhi:
 

 
TABLE
 
 
  

 
 
Sl. No.
 
Amount of fine imposed
 
Amount of fee payable

 
  

 
 
1.
 
 
Where the 
        amount of fine imposed under sub-section (2) of section 13 of the Act is
        Rs. 
        10,000.
 
Rs. 1,000

 
  

 
 
2.
 
 
Where the 
        amount of fine imposed under sub-section (2) of section 13 of the Act is
        more 
        than Rs. 10,000 and upto Rs. 50,000
 
Rs. 2,500

 
  

 
 
3.
 
 
Where the 
        amount of fine imposed under sub-section (2) of section 13 of the Act is 
        more than Rs. 50,000 and upto Rs. 1 lakh.
 
Rs. 5,000

 
  

 
 
Appeal against attachment of any property 
      or 
      retention of the seized property or record.

 
  

 
 
4.
 
 
Where appeal 
    is against the orders made by the Adjudicating Authority under sub-section (3) or sub-section (6) of section 8 of the Act. 

 
Rs. 10,000

 
  


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The appeal 
    shall set forth concisely and under distinct head the grounds of objection 
    to the order appealed against and such grounds shall be numbered 
    consecutively; and shall specify the address of service at which notice or 
    other processes of the Appellate Tribunal may be served on the appellant and 
    the date on which the order appealed against was served on the appellant.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    appeal is preferred after the expiry of the period of forty-five days 
    referred to in sub-section (3) of section 26 of the Act, it shall be 
    accompanied by a petition, in quadruplicate, duly verified and supported by 
    the documents, if any, relied upon by the appellant, showing cause as to how 
    the appellant had been prevented from preferring the appeal within the 
    period of forty-five days.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any notice 
    required to be served on the appellant shall be served on him in the manner 
    prescribed in rule 5 of these rules at the address of service specified in 
    the appeal.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Order of 
    the Appellate Tribunal.—The order 
    of the Appellate Tribunal shall be in writing and shall state the reasons 
    for the decision.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Service 
    of notice, requisitions or orders.—A 
    notice, requisition or an order issued under these rules shall be served on 
    any person in the following manner:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    by delivering or tendering the notice 
    or requisition or order to that person or the person duly authorized by him; 
    or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    by sending the notice or requisition or 
    order to him by registered post with acknowledgement due to the address of 
    his place of residence or his last known place of residence or the place 
    where he carried on, or last carried on, business or personally works or 
    last worked for gain; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    by affixing it on the outer door or 
    some other conspicuous part of the premises in which the person resides or 
    is known to have last resided or carried on business or personally works or 
    has worked for gain and that written report thereof should be witnessed by 
    two persons; or  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    if the notice or requisition or order 
    cannot be served under clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c), then by 
    publishing in a leading newspaper (both in vernacular and in English) having 
    wide circulation in the area or jurisdiction in which the person resides or 
    is known to have last resided or carried on business or personally works or 
    last worked for gain.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be 
    referred to the Central Government and the decision of the Central 
    Government shall be final. 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


FORM  
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 3]  
 

 
 


From...........................................................................................................................................
 


       (Mention 
    name and address of the appellant here)  
 


To
 


The Registrar,  
 


Appellate Tribunal  
 


(Address)  
 


Sir,  
 


The above-named appellant, begs to prefer this 
    appeal under section 26 of the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 
    against order Number...................dated .....................passed by 
    the Director or the Adjudicating Authority (strike out whichever is 
    inapplicable) under the said Act on the following facts and grounds.  
 

 
 


FACTS  
 


(Mention briefly the facts of the case here. 
    Enclose copy of the order passed by the Director or Adjudicating Authority (strike 
    out whichever is inapplicable) and copies of other relevant documents, 
    if any)  
 

 
 


GROUNDS  
 


(Mention here the grounds on which appeal is 
    preferred)  
 

 
 


PRAYER  
 


In the light of what is stated above, the 
    appellant prays for the following relief:—  
 


RELIEF SOUGHT  
 


(Specify the relief sought)  
 


DECLARATION  
 


The fee payable for this appeal as shown in 
    Table given in sub-rule (2) of rule 3 of these rules has been deposited in 
    the form of demand draft with the Registrar, Appellate Tribunal, New Delhi
    vide receipt number...................dated ...................  
 

 
 


Signature of the Appellant
 



    ................................................
 



                                                                                                                                            
    Name of the Appellant
 


List of documents
 


Place........................
 


Date.........................
 


Signature of the Appellant
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>