<act><tid>108849</tid>
<title>THE INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA ACT, <year>1985</year></title>

ACT NO. 82 OF <year>1985</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1985</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of an Authority for the 
regulation and development of inland waterways for purposes of 
shipping and navigation and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>56768</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>92489</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Inland Waterways Authority of India Act, <year>1985</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>959914</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1260840</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>908346</tid>
<number>a</number>" appurtenant land" means all lands appurtenant to a 
national waterway, whether demarcated or not;

</section>

<section><tid>337705</tid>
<number>b</number>" Authority" means the Inland Waterways Authority of 
India constituted under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>351131</tid>
<number>c</number>" channel" means any waterway, whether natural or 
artificial;

</section>

<section><tid>354474</tid>
<number>d</number>" conservancy" includes dredging, training, closure, 
diversion or abandoning channels;

</section>

<section><tid>1613865</tid>
<number>e</number>" conservancy measures" means measures for purposes of 
conservancy, but does not include measures for protection of 
banks against floods or for restricting banks which have become 
eroded mainly on account of reasons not connected with shipping 
and navigation;

</section>

<section><tid>513700</tid>
<number>f</number>" infrastructure" includes structures such as docks, 
wharves, jetties, landing stages, locks, buoys, inland ports, 
cargo handling equipment, road and rail access and cargo storage 
spaces, and the expression" infrastructural facilities" shall be 
construed accordingly;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>460</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 27- 10- <year>1986</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 763 (E), dated 27- 10- 
<year>1986</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1986</year>, Part II, section 3 (ii).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>533906</tid>
<number>g</number>" member" means a member of the Authority appointed under 
sub- section (3) of section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1337688</tid>
<number>h</number>" national waterway" means the inland waterway declared 
by section 2 of the National Waterway (Allahabad- Haldia Stretch  
  of the Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly River) Act, <year>1982</year> (49 of <year>1982</year>), 
to be a national waterway.
Explanation.-- If Parliament declares by law any other 
waterway to be a national waterway, then from the date on which 
such declaration takes effect, such other waterway--


</section>

<section><tid>1217076</tid>
<number>i</number>shall be deemed also to be a national waterway 
within the meaning of this clause; and

<subsection><tid>1251905</tid>
<number>ii</number>the provisions of this Act shall, with necessary 
modifications (including modification for construing any  
reference to the commencement of this Act as a reference to 
  the date aforesaid), apply to such national waterway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>188248</tid>
<number>i</number>" navigable channel" means a channel navigable during the 
whole or a part of the year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>828562</tid>
<number>j</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>619841</tid>
<number>k</number>" regulations" means regulations made by the Authority 
under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1840618</tid>
<number>l</number>" rules" means rules made by the Central Government under 
this Act.
CHAP

INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA

CHAPTER II

INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>403718</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and incorporation of the Inland Waterways 
Authority of India.
<section><tid>1744289</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf, there shall be constituted for the purposes of this Act 
an Authority, to be called the Inland Waterways Authority of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1042678</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name 
aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of 
property, both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the 
said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1996254</tid>
<number>3</number>The Authority shall consist of the following members, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1480647</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>243369</tid>
<number>b</number>a Vice- Chairman; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1597103</tid>
<number>c</number>such number of persons, not exceeding five, to be 
appointed by the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1518864</tid>
<number>4</number>The Authority may associate with itself, in such manner and 
for such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any person 
whose assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any of the 
provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the right 
to take part
<pagefootnote><pagenum>461</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 27- 10- <year>1986</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 764 (E), dated 27- 10- 
<year>1986</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1986</year>, Part II, section 3 (ii).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in the discussions of the Authority relevant to the purpose for which 
he has been associated, but shall not be entitled to vote.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>15840</tid>
<number>4</number>Conditions of service of members. The term of office and other 
conditions of service of the members shall be such as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>716664</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of Chairman and Vice- Chairman.
<section><tid>793745</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman of the  
Authority shall, in addition to presiding over the meetings of the 
Authority, exercise and discharge such powers and duties of the 
Authority as may be delegated to him by the Authority and such other 
powers and duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>218775</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chairman of the Authority shall exercise and 
discharge such of the powers and duties of the Chairman as may be 
prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1960</tid>
<number> 6</number> Removal, etc., of members.
<section><tid>1647840</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
remove from the Authority any member who, in its opinion,--

<subsection><tid>611915</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses to act,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221509</tid>
<number>b</number>has become incapable to act,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1561431</tid>
<number>c</number>has so abused his office as to render his continuance in 
office detrimental to the public interest, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>263539</tid>
<number>d</number>is otherwise unsuitable to continue as a member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1330491</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may suspend any member pending an 
inquiry against him.

</section>

<section><tid>475921</tid>
<number>3</number>No order of removal under this section shall be made unless 
the member concerned has been given an opportunity to submit his 
explanation to the Central Government and when such order is passed, 
the seat of the member removed shall be declared vacant.

</section>

<section><tid>1848538</tid>
<number>4</number>A member who has been removed under this section shall not be 
eligible for re- appointment as a member or in any capacity under the 
Authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879667</tid>
<number> 7</number> Vacancy, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Authority. 
No act or proceeding of the Authority shall be invalidated merely by 
reason of--
<section><tid>1648929</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Authority; or

</section>

<section><tid>1308417</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Authority; or

</section>

<section><tid>755014</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not 
affecting the merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1949113</tid>
<number> 8</number> Secretary and other officers.
<section><tid>351306</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may appoint  
the Secretary and such other officers and employees as it considers 
necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1094613</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Secretary and 
other officers and employees of the Authority shall be such as may be 
determined by regulations.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>462</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1243173</tid>
<number> 9</number> Advisory Committees.
<section><tid>1426838</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules made in this  
behalf, the Authority may from time to time constitute such Advisory 
Committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
functions.

</section>

<section><tid>1802310</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Advisory Committee shall consist of such number of 
persons connected with shipping and navigation and allied aspects as 
the Authority may deem fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>241741</tid>
<number>10</number>Authority to act on business principles. In the discharge of 
its functions under this Act, the Authority shall act, so far as may 
be, on business principles.
CHAP

PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS

CHAPTER III

PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS



</article>



<article><tid>401054</tid>
<number> 11</number> Transfer of assets and liabilities of the Central Government 
to the Authority.
<section><tid>38410</tid>
<number>1</number>As from such day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government  
may, appoint by notification in the official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>588686</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties and other assets vested in the Central 
Government for the purposes of Inland Water Transport 
Directorate, and administered by the Chief Engineer- cum- 
Administrator, Inland Water Transport Directorate, immediately 
before such day shall vest in the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461405</tid>
<number>b</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all 
contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged to be 
done by, with, or for the Central Government immediately before 
such day for or in connection with the purposes of Inland Water 
Transport Directorate shall be deemed to have been incurred; 
entered into and engaged to be done by, with, or for the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>938404</tid>
<number>c</number>all non- recurring expenditure incurred by the Central 
Government for or in connection with the purposes of Inland Water 
Transport Directorate up to such day and declared to be capital 
expenditure by the Central Government shall, subject to such 
terms and conditions as may be determined by the Central 
Government, be treated as capital provided by the Central 
Government to the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>46209</tid>
<number>d</number>all sums of money due to the Central Government in 
relation to Inland Water Transport Directorate immediately before 
such day shall be deemed to be due to the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>106726</tid>
<number>e</number>all suits and other legal proceedings with respect to 
any matter in relation to Inland Water Transport Directorate 
which having been instituted by or against the Central Government 
are pending, or which could have been so instituted, immediately 
before such date shall on and after such date be continued or 
instituted by or against the Authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>525894</tid>
<number>f</number>every employee holding any office under the Central 
Government immediately before such day solely or mainly for or in 
connection with such affairs of Inland Water Transport 
Directorate as are relevant to the functions of the Authority 
under this
<pagefootnote><pagenum>463</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 27- 10- <year>1986</year>: Vice Notification No. S. O. 767 (E), dated 27- 10- 
<year>1986</year>, Extraordinary, <year>1986</year>, Part II, section 3 (ii).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Act shall be treated as on deputation with the Authority but 
shall hold his office in the Authority by the same tenure and 
upon the same terms and conditions of service as respects 
remuneration, leave, provident fund, retirement or other terminal 
benefits as he would have held such office, if the Authority had 
not been constituted and shall continue to do so until the 
Central Government, either on its own motion or at the request of 
the Authority, recalls such employee to its service or until the 
Authority, with the concurrence of the Central Government, duly 
absorbs such employee in its regular service, whichever is 
earlier:

Provided that during the period of deputation of any such 
employee with the Authority, the Authority shall pay to the 
Central Government in respect of every such employee, such 
contribution towards his leave salary, pension and gratuity as 
the Central Government may, by order, determine:

Provided further that any such employee, who has, in respect 
of the proposal of the Authority to absorb him in its regular 
service, intimated within such time as may be specified in this 
behalf by the Authority his intention of not becoming a regular 
employee of the Authority, shall not be absorbed by the Authority 
in its regular service.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1502536</tid>
<number>2</number>If any dispute or doubt arises as to which of the properties, 
rights or liabilities of the Central Government have been transferred 
to the Authority or as to which of the employees serving under the 
Central Government are to be treated as on deputation with the 
Authority, under this section, such dispute or doubt shall be decided 
by the Central Government in consultation with the Authority and the 
decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1782276</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the absorption of any employee by the Authority in its regular 
service under this section shall not entitle such employee to any 
compensation under that Act or other law and no such claim shall be 
entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1532049</tid>
<number>12</number>Contracts by the Authority. Subject to the provisions of 
section 13, the Authority shall be competent to enter into and perform 
any contract necessary for the discharge of its functions under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>11292</tid>
<number> 13</number> Mode of executing contracts on behalf of the Authority.
<section><tid>1498208</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every contract shall, on behalf of the Authority, be made by the 
Chairman or such other member or such officer of the Authority as may 
be generally or specially empowered in this behalf by the Authority 
and such contracts or class of contracts as may be specified in the 
regulations shall be sealed with the common seal of the Authority:
Provided that no contract exceeding such value or amount as the 
Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix in this 
behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by the 
Authority:

Provided further that no contract for the acquisition or sale of 
immovable property or for the lease of any such property for a term 
exceeding thirty years and no other contract exceeding such value or


<pagefootnote><pagenum>464</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

amount as the Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix 
in this behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by 
the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>289760</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the form and 
manner in which any contract shall be made under this Act shall be 
such as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>676273</tid>
<number>3</number>No contract which is not in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act and the regulations shall be binding on the Authority.
CHAP

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE AUTHORITY

CHAPTER IV

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE AUTHORITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1308314</tid>
<number> 14</number> Functions of the Authority.
<section><tid>1873610</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may-- 

<subsection><tid>1346620</tid>
<number>a</number>carry out surveys and investigations for the 
development, maintenance and better utilisation of the national 
waterways and the appurtenant land for shipping and navigation 
and prepare schemes in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>676806</tid>
<number>b</number>provide or permit setting up of infrastructural 
facilities for national waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>727812</tid>
<number>c</number>carry out conservancy measures and training works and do 
all other acts necessary for the safety and convenience of 
shipping and navigation and improvement of the national 
waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>473949</tid>
<number>d</number>control activities such as throwing rubbish, dumping or 
removal of material, in or from the bed of the national waterways 
and appurtenant land, in so far as they may affect safe and 
efficient, shipping and navigation, maintenance of navigable 
channels, river training and conservancy measures;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378462</tid>
<number>e</number>remove or alter any obstruction or impediment in the 
national waterways and the appurtenant land which may impede the 
safe navigation or endanger safety of infrastructural facilities 
or conservancy measures where such obstruction or impediment has 
been lawfully made or has become lawful by reason of long 
continuance of such obstruction or impediment or otherwise, after 
making compensation to person suffering damage by such removal or 
alteration;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728707</tid>
<number>f</number>provide for the regulation of navigation and traffic 
 (including the rule of the road) on national waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>585568</tid>
<number>g</number>regulate the construction or alteration of structures 
on, across or under the national waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568581</tid>
<number>h</number>disseminate navigational meteorological information 
about national waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>113709</tid>
<number>i</number>ensure co- ordination of inland water transport on 
national waterways with other modes of transport; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>325441</tid>
<number>j</number>establish and maintain pilotage on national waterways.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>465</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>269877</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority may also--

<subsection><tid>198251</tid>
<number>a</number>advise the Central Government on matters relating to 
inland water transport;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1346466</tid>
<number>b</number>study the transport requirement with a view to co- 
ordinating inland water transport with other modes of transport;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1855392</tid>
<number>c</number>carry out hydrographic surveys and publish river charts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1112593</tid>
<number>d</number>assist, on such terms and conditions as may be mutually 
agreed upon, any State Government in formulation and 
implementation of scheme for inland water transport development;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383970</tid>
<number>e</number>develop consultancy services and provide such services, 
on such terms and conditions as may be mutually agreed upon, in 
India and abroad in relation to planning and development of 
waterways for shipping and navigation or any facility thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645085</tid>
<number>f</number>conduct research in matters relating to inland water 
transport including development of craft design, mechanisation of 
country crafts, technique of towage, landing and terminal 
facilities, port installations and survey techniques;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1967222</tid>
<number>g</number>lay down standards for classification of inland 
waterways;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1928957</tid>
<number>h</number>arrange programme of technical training for inland water 
transport personnel within and outside the country; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1665891</tid>
<number>i</number>perform such other functions as may be necessary to 
carry out the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>108951</tid>
<number>3</number>Any dispute arising out of or concerning the compensation 
referred to in clause (e) of sub- section (1) shall be determined 
according to the law relating to like disputes in the case of land 
required for public purposes.

</section>

<section><tid>988401</tid>
<number>4</number>Every scheme, prepared by the Authority to carry out 
functions under sub- sections (1) and (2), involving capital 
expenditure exceeding the amount as may be prescribed, shall be 
submitted to the Central Government for approval.

</section>

<section><tid>908495</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may either approve the scheme 
submitted to it under sub- section (4) without modification or with 
such modifications as it may consider necessary or reject the scheme 
with directions to the Authority to prepare a fresh scheme according 
to such directions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1992003</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of schemes. The Authority shall not make any 
material change in the scheme approved under sub- section (5) of 
section 14 without the prior approval of the Central Government.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," material change" 
means an increase in the cost of the scheme by more than twenty per 
cent. of its cost or a change in the benefit and cost ratio which 
either makes the cost component in the ratio exceeds the benefit or 
reduces the benefit component by more than twenty per cent.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>466</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER V

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT



</article>



<article><tid>1706160</tid>
<number> 17</number> Levy and collection of fees and charges.
<section><tid>1011328</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority  
may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, levy fees 
and charges at such rates as may be laid down by regulations made in 
this behalf for services or benefits rendered in relation to the use 
of the national waterways for the purposes of shipping, navigation, 
infrastructural facilities, including facilities for passengers and 
facilities relating to the berthing of vessels, handling of cargoes 
and storage of cargoes.

</section>

<section><tid>1773870</tid>
<number>2</number>The fees and charges levied under sub- section (1) shall be 
collected in such manner as may be determined by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>822595</tid>
<number>18</number>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, make to the Authority grants and loans of such sums of 
money as that Government may consider necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>1823651</tid>
<number> 19</number> Constitution of the Fund.
<section><tid>861910</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be constituted a  
Fund to be called the Inland Waterways Authority of India Fund and 
there shall be credited thereto--

<subsection><tid>1412043</tid>
<number>a</number>any grants and loans made to the Authority by the 
Central Government under section 18;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1111663</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees and charges received by the Authority under 
this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>575267</tid>
<number>c</number>all sums received by the Authority from such other 
sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>456486</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be applied for meeting--

<subsection><tid>108678</tid>
<number>a</number>salary, allowances and other remuneration of the 
members, officers and other employees of the Authority;
 1 Omitted by Act 8 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>467</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1026979</tid>
<number>b</number>expenses of the Authority in the discharge of its 
functions under section 14; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>516762</tid>
<number>c</number>expenses on objects and for purposes authorised by this 
Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1489303</tid>
<number>20</number>Budget. The Authority shall prepare, in such form and at such 
time each financial year as may be prescribed, its budget for the next 
financial year, showing the estimated receipts and expenditure of the 
Authority and forward the same to the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>195532</tid>
<number>21</number>Investment of funds. The Authority may invest its funds 
 (including any reserve fund) in the securities of the Central 
Government or in such other manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1527150</tid>
<number>22</number>Annual report. The Authority shall prepare, in such form and 
at such time each financial year as may be prescribed, its annual 
report, giving a full account of its activities during the previous 
financial year, and submit a copy thereof to the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>139017</tid>
<number>23</number>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Authority shall be 
maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed and the 
Authority shall furnish, to the Central Government, before such date 
as may be prescribed, its audited copy of accounts together with the 
auditors' report thereon.


</article>



<article><tid>949390</tid>
<number>24</number>Annual report and auditors' report to be laid before 
Parliament. The Central Government shall cause the annual report and 
auditors' report to be laid, as soon as may be after they are 
received, before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>728969</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power of Central Government to issue directions.
<section><tid>55713</tid>
<number>1</number>Without  
prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority 
shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be 
bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
Government may give in writing to it from time to time:
Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be 
given opportunity to express its views before any direction is given 
under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>599721</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is 
one of policy or not shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1327797</tid>
<number>26</number>Compulsory acquisition of land for the Authority. Any land 
required by the Authority for discharging its functions under this Act 
shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land may be 
acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the Land 
Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>.) or of any other corresponding law 
for the time being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>468</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1628711</tid>
<number> 27</number> Application, etc., of certain laws.
<section><tid>1648132</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of  
this Act shall be in addition to the provisions of the Indian Ports 
Act, <year>1908</year> (15 of <year>1908</year>) and the Major Port Trusts Act, <year>1963</year> (38 of  
  <year>1963</year>) and in particular nothing in this Act shall affect any 
jurisdiction, functions, powers or duties required to be exercised, 
performed or discharged by--

<subsection><tid>878893</tid>
<number>a</number>the conservator of any port or by any officer or 
authority under the Indian Ports Act, <year>1908</year> (15 of <year>1908</year>) or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>173449</tid>
<number>b</number>the Board of Trustees for any major port or by any 
officer or authority under the Major Port Trusts Act, <year>1963</year> (38 of  
  <year>1963</year>) in or in relation to any portion of an inland waterway 
 (including the national waterway) falling within the limits of 
such port or major port.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1891641</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this Act shall affect the operation of the Inland 
Vessels Act, <year>1917</year> (1 of <year>1917</year>) or any other Central Act other than 
the Indian Ports Act, <year>1908</year> (15 of <year>1908</year>) and the Major Port Trusts 
Act, <year>1963</year> (38 of <year>1963</year>) or any State or provincial Act in force 
immediately before the commencement of this Act with respect to 
shipping and navigation on any national waterway <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>844985</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to enter. Subject to any rules made in this behalf, any 
person, generally or specially authorised by the Authority in this 
behalf, may, whenever it in necessary so to do for any of the purposes 
of this Act, at all reasonable times, enter upon any land or premises 
and--
<section><tid>136965</tid>
<number>a</number>make any inspection, survey, measurement, valuation or 
inquiry;

</section>

<section><tid>842239</tid>
<number>b</number>take levels;

</section>

<section><tid>1267360</tid>
<number>c</number>dig or bore into sub- soil;

</section>

<section><tid>1777248</tid>
<number>d</number>set out boundaries and intended lines of work;

</section>

<section><tid>1824632</tid>
<number>e</number>mark such level boundaries and lines by placing marks 
and cutting trenches; or

</section>

<section><tid>835834</tid>
<number>f</number>do such other acts or things as may be prescribed:
Provided that no such person shall enter any building or any 
enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling- house (unless with the  
  consent of the occupier thereof) without previously giving such 
occupier at least twenty- four hours' notice in writing of his 
intention to do so.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>513878</tid>
<number>29</number>Delegation. The Authority may, by general or special order in 
writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member or to any 
officer of the Authority, subject to such conditions and limitations, 
if any, as may be specified in the order such of its powers and 
functions under this Act (except the powers under section 35) as it 
may deem necessary.
</article>



<article><tid>56768</tid>
<number>1</number>Certain words omitted by Act 8 of <year>1994</year>, s. 3.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>469</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authentication of orders and other instruments of the Authority.

</article>



<article><tid>22829</tid>
<number>30</number>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the 
Authority. All orders and decisions of the Authority shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the Chairman or any other member 
authorised by the Authority in this behalf and all other instruments 
executed by the Authority shall be authenticated by the signature of 
an officer of the Authority authorised by the Authority in this 
behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>539062</tid>
<number>31</number>Members, officers and employees of the Authority to be public 
servants. All members, officers and other employees of the Authority 
shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any 
of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1072647</tid>
<number> 32</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>1095082</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the 
Government or any officer of the Government or any member, officer or 
employee of the Authority for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regulations made 
thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1549057</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the 
Authority for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything in 
good faith done or purported to be done under this Act or the rules or 
regulations, and in particular, it shall not be the responsibility of 
the Authority to provide for relief measures necessitated by floods or 
by breaches and failures of works.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>435808</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power of Central Government to supersede the Authority.
<section><tid>1118781</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion--

<subsection><tid>1412487</tid>
<number>a</number>that on account of a grave emergency, the Authority is 
unable to discharge the functions and duties imposed on it by or 
under the provisions of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1165195</tid>
<number>b</number>that the Authority has persistently made default in 
complying with any direction issued by the Central Government 
under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and duties 
imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act and as a 
result of which default the financial position of the Authority 
or the administration of any national waterway has deteriorated; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>978373</tid>
<number>c</number>that circumstances exist which render it necessary in 
the public interest so to do, the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, supersede the Authority for 
such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in the 
notification:
Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub- 
section for the reasons mentioned in clause (b), the Central 
Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Authority to 
show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the 
explanations and objection, if any, of the Authority.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>470</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1547346</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the publication of a notification under sub- section (1) 
superseding the Authority,--

<subsection><tid>1213602</tid>
<number>a</number>all the members shall, as from the date of supersession, 
vacate their offices as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>154287</tid>
<number>b</number>all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or 
under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or discharged by 
or on behalf of the Authority, shall, until the Authority is 
reconstituted under sub- section (3), be exercised and discharged 
by such person or persons as the Central Government may direct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85347</tid>
<number>c</number>all property owned or controlled by the Authority shall, 
until the Authority is reconstituted under sub- section (3), vest 
in the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1236063</tid>
<number>3</number>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in 
the notification issued under sub- section (1), the Central Government 
may--

<subsection><tid>1111908</tid>
<number>a</number>extend the period of supersession for such further term, 
not exceeding six months, as it may consider necessary; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1215734</tid>
<number>b</number>reconstitute the Authority by fresh appointment and in 
such case any persons who vacated their offices under clause (a) 
of sub- section (2) shall not be deemed disqualified for 
appointment:
Provided that the Central Government may, at any time before the 
expiration of the period of supersession, whether as originally 
specified under sub- section (1) or as extended under this sub- section, 
take action under clause (b) of this sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>208640</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause a notification issued 
under sub- section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this 
section and the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before 
such House of Parliament at the earliest opportunity.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>982787</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>574673</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>366497</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>816947</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office and other conditions of service of 
the members of the Authority under section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373677</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers and duties of the Chairman and Vice- Chairman 
under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>212691</tid>
<number>c</number>the matters with respect to the Advisory Committee 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1936361</tid>
<number>d</number>the amount required to be prescribed under sub- section 
 (4) of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>354438</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which, and the time at which, the Authority 
shall prepare its budget under section 20 and its annual report 
under section 22;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>471</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>61864</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which the Authority may invest its funds 
under section 21;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1154623</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner in which the accounts of the Authority shall 
be maintained and audited under section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>411552</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions and restrictions with respect to exercise 
of the power to enter under section 28 and the matters referred 
to in clause (f) of that section; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>321917</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed 
or in respect of which provision is to be, or may be, made by 
rules.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1162068</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>396917</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may, with the  
previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this Act and the 
rules generally to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1657100</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>373546</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which and the purposes for which, the 
Authority may associate with itself any person under sub- section 
 (4) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>81730</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Secretary and 
other officers and employees of the Authority under sub- section 
 (2) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1650694</tid>
<number>c</number>the contracts or class of contracts which are to be 
sealed with the common seal of the Authority and the form and 
manner in which a contract may be made by the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730360</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to 
which, any functions in relation to the matters referred to in 
sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 14 may be performed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985822</tid>
<number>e</number>the rule of the road on a national waterway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1480239</tid>
<number>f</number>the safe, efficient and convenient use, management and 
control of the infrastructures and infrastructural facilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>111509</tid>
<number>g</number>the reception, porterage, storage and removal of goods 
brought on a national waterway, and the procedure to be followed 
for taking charge of goods which may have been damaged before 
landing, or may be alleged to have been so damaged;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413567</tid>
<number>h</number>regulating, declaring and defining the docks, wharfs, 
jetties, landing stages on which goods shall be landed from 
vessels and shipped on board vessels;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728646</tid>
<number>i</number>regulating the manner in which and the conditions under 
which the loading and unloading of vessels on a national waterway 
shall be carried out; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1260628</tid>
<number>j</number>the exclusion from a national waterway of disorderly or 
other undesirable persons and of trespassers.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>472</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1936487</tid>
<number>3</number>Any regulation made under any of the clauses (c) to (j) of 
sub- section (2) may provide that a contravention thereof shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in 
the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine which 
may extend to twenty rupees for every day during which such 
contravention continues after conviction for the first such 
contravention.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>568691</tid>
<number>36</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
regulation or both House agree that the rule or regulation should not 
be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in 
such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule 
or regulation.


</article>



<article><tid>478644</tid>
<number> 37</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1999226</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of five years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>269213</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1219555</tid>
<number> 38</number> Amendment of Act 49 of <year>1982</year>. In the National Waterway 
 (Allahabad- Haldia Stretch of the Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly River) Act, 
<year>1982</year>,--
<section><tid>1876325</tid>
<number>a</number>in section 3, for the words" Central Government", the 
word" Union" shall be substituted, and for the words" to the 
extent hereinafter provided", the words and figures" to the 
extent provided in the Inland Waterways Authority of India Act, 
<year>1985</year>" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1698856</tid>
<number>b</number>sections 4 to 15 shall be omitted.

</section>

</article>



 </act>