<act><title>

The
Central Mental Health
Authority Rules, 19901</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Central Mental Health Authority Rules, 1990. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of commencement of the Act.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number> ‘Act’ means the Mental Health Act, 1987 (14 of 1987); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number> ‘authority’ means the Central Mental Authority established under
section 3 of the Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number> ‘Chairman’ means the chairmen nominated under rule 5; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number> ‘member’ means member of the authority appointed under rule 3; 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number> ‘membership’ means the membership of the authority established
under rule 3; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number> ‘non-official member’ means a member appointed under sub-rule (2)
of rule 3; 
 

 </section><section><number>g</number> ‘Official Member’ means a member appointed under sub-rule (1) of
rule 3; 
 

 </section><section><number>h</number> ‘Secretary’ means the Secretary to the authority appointed under 
rule 13; 
 

 </section><section><number>i</number> words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the
Act shall respectively have the meaning assigned to them in the Act. 
 

  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Constitution of the authority.—The
authority shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 


 <section><number>1</number>
Official members.—(a) Secretary or Additional Secretary, Ministry of
Health and Family Welfare, Government of India. 
 

 <subsection><number>b</number> Joint Secretary, Ministry of Health and
Family Welfare dealing with Mental Health. 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Additional Director General of Health Service dealing with Mental
Health. 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Director, Central Institute of Psychiatry, Ranchi. 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Director, National Institute of Mental Health and Neuro Sciences,
Bangalore. 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> Medical Superintendent, Hospital for Mental Diseases, Shahdara,
Delhi. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Non-Official Members.—Three members including one Social Worker, one
Clinical Psychologist and one Medical Psychiatrist who, in the opinion of the
Central Government, have special interest in the field of Mental Health. 
 

  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Disqualification.—A person shall be
disqualified for being appointed as a member or shall be removed from membership
by the Central Government if he,—
 


 <section><number>a</number> has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which
in the opinion of the Central Government involves moral turpitude; or 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number> is an undischarged insolvent; or 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number> is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number> has been removed or dismissed from the service of Government or a
body corporate owned or controlled by the Government.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government
may nominate any official member to act as the Chairman of the authority.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman shall cease to hold office when he ceases to be a member of the
authority.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Term of office of members.—
<section><number>1</number> Every
official member shall hold office as such member so long as he holds the office
by virtue of which he was so appointed.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every non-official member shall hold office for a period of three years from the
date of his appointment and shall be eligible for re-appointment.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A non-official member may at any time resign from membership of the authority by
forwarding his letter of resignation of the Chairman and such resignation shall
take effect only from the date on which it is accepted.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Where a vacancy occurs by regination of a non-official member under sub-rule (3)
or otherwise, the Central Government shall fill the vacancy by appointing from
amongst category of persons referred to in sub-clause (2) of 
rule 3 and the person so appointed, shall hold office for the remainder of the
term of office of the member in whose place he was so appointed.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Where the term of office of any non-official member is about to expire the
Central Government may appoint a successor at any time within three months
before the expiry of the term of such member but the successor shall not assume
office until the term of the members expires.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Meetings of the authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The
authority shall ordinarily meet once in every six months at such time and place
as may be fixed by the Chairman: 
 


 Provided
that the Chairman,— 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number> may call a special meeting at any time to deal with any urgent matter
requiring the attention of the authority. 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
shall call a special meetings if he receives a requisition in writings
signed by not less than four members and stating the purpose for which they
desire the meeting to be called. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The first meeting of the authority to be held in any calender year shall be the
annual meeting for that year.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Subjects for special meeting.—Where
a meeting referred to in the proviso to sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 7 has been
convened, only the subjects for the consideration of which the meeting was
convened, shall be discussed.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Subjects for the annual meeting.—At
the annual meetings of the authority, the following subjects shall be considered
and disposed of, namely:—
 


 <section><number>a</number> review of the progress of implementation of the various provisions of
Mental Health Act during the preceding one year;
 </section><section><number>b</number> other business on the agenda; and
 </section><section><number>c</number> any other business brought forward with the consent of the Chairman
or where he is absent, with the consent of officer presiding at the meeting.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Procedure for holding meetings.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every notice calling for a meeting of the authority shall,—
 <subsection><number>a</number> specify the place, date and hour of the meeting; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> be served upon every member of the authority not less than twenty-one
clear days in the case of annual meeting and fifteen clear days in the case of
other meetings before the day appointed for the meeting.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Secretary shall prepare and circulate to the members alongwith the notice of
the meeting, an agenda for such meeting showing the business to be transacted.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A member who wishes to move a resolution on any matter included in the agenda
shall give notice thereof to the Secretary not less than seven days before the
date fixed by the meeting.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A member who wishes to move any motion not included in the agenda shall give
notice thereof to the Secretary not less than fourteen days before the date
fixed for the meeting.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Proceedings of the authority.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Chairman or in his absence any member authorised by him shall preside at
meeting of the authority.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The quorum for the meeting of the authority shall be four members.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
If within half an hour from time appointed for holding a meeting of the
authority quorum is not present, the meeting shall be adjourned to the same day
in the following week at the same time and place and the presiding officer of
such meetings shall inform the members present and send notice to other members.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
If at the adjourned meeting also, quorum is not present within half an hour from
the time appointed for holding the meeting, the members present shall constitute
the quorum.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
In the adjourned meeting if the Chairman is not present and no member has been
authorised to preside at such meeting, the members present shall elect a member
to preside at the meeting.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Each member including the Chairman shall have one vote. In the case of an
equality of votes, the Chairman or any member presiding over such meeting shall
in addition, have enacasting vote.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
All decisions of the meetings of the authority shall be taken by a majority of
the members present and voting.
 


  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Approval by circulation.—Any
business which may be necessary for the authority to transact except such as may
be placed before the annual meeting, may be carried out by circulation among all
members and any resolutions so circulated and approved by a majority of members,
shall be valid and binding as if such resolution has been passed at the meetings
of the authority.
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Secretary to the authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Chairman shall cause to be appointed a Secretary to the authority from amongst
persons possessing post-graduate degree in psychiatry and having three years
experience in the field of psychiatry.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Secretary shall be a full-time or part-time servant of the authority and
shall function as the Administrative Officer of the authority.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Secretary shall be responsible for the control and management of office
accounts and correspondence.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Secretary shall attend and take notes of the proceedings of the meetings of
the authority.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
The Secretary shall cause to be appointed such members of the ministerial and
non-ministerial staff which are essential for the efficient functioning of the
authority.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The Secretary shall exercise such other powers and discharge such other
functions as may be authorised in writing by the Chairman for the efficient
functioning of the authority.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Forwarding of copies of the proceedings of the authority to the Central
Government.—The Secretary shall
forward copies of the proceedings of the authority to the Central Government
periodically.
  
  

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>