<act><tid>1486627</tid>
<title>THE RESERVE AND AUXILIARY AIR FORCES ACT, <year>1952</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1952</year>
[ 22nd August, <year>1952</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution and regulation of Certain. Air 
Force Reserve and also an Auxiliary Air Force and for matters 
connected therewith.

Be it enacted by Parliament as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>453828</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>502922</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Reserve and Auxiliary Air Forces Act, <year>1952</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>553847</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1580103</tid>
<number>3</number>This Chapter shall come into force at once, and the 
remaining provisions shall come into force on such date 2 as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804542</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1891283</tid>
<number>a</number>" Air Force Reserve" means any of the Air Force Reserves 
raised and maintained under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1596848</tid>
<number>b</number>" competent authority" means an air officer or a 
committee consisting of two or more air officers appointed 
under section 3;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>278</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to-

and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>);

and comes into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>);

the State of Sikkim vide Notification No. S. R. O. 25 (E), dated 20- 4- 
<year>1976</year> (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Chapters II and III and provisions of Chapters V and VI except 
so far as they relate to the Auxiliary Air Force came into force on 
the 15th August, <year>1955</year>, vide S. R. O. 322, dated 20th August, <year>1955</year>, 
Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 4, P. 189.

Chapter IV and provisions of Chapters V and VI relating to the 
Auxiliary Air Force came into force on the 15th October, <year>1955</year>, vide 
S. R. O. 395, dated the 15th October, <year>1955</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, 
Sec. 4, p. 259.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>225377</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>990951</tid>
<number>d</number>all other words and expressions used herein and 
defined in the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year> (15 of <year>1950</year>) and not 
hereinbefore defined shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them by that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1350956</tid>
<number>3</number>Appointment of competent authority. The Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint an air 1officer or a 
committee consisting of two or more air officers to perform all or any 
of the functions of the competent authority under this Act for such 
area as may be specified in the notification.
CHAP

REGULAR AIR FORCE RESERVE

CHAPTER II

REGULAR AIR FORCE RESERVE



</article>



<article><tid>248098</tid>
<number>4</number>Constitution of Regular Air Force Reserve. The Central 
Government may raise and maintain in the manner hereafter in this 
Chapter provided an Air Force Reserve to be designated the Regular Air 
Force Reserve which shall consist solely of persons transferred or 
appointed to it under section 5.


</article>



<article><tid>1472044</tid>
<number> 5</number> Recruitment to the Regular Air Force Reserve.
<section><tid>418147</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
competent authority may, by general or special order, transfer to the 
Regular Air Force Reserve-

<subsection><tid>1311954</tid>
<number>a</number>any officer or airman of the Air Force who under the 
terms and conditions of his service is liable to serve in any 
Air Force Reserve if and when constituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>93681</tid>
<number>b</number>any officer or airman of the Air Force whose commission 
or engagement in the Air Force has been terminated before the 
commencement of this Act and who under the terms of his 
commission or engagement was liable to serve in any Air Force 
Reserve if and when constituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824132</tid>
<number>c</number>any officer or airman who has served in the Air Force 
and has retired therefrom;
and any officer or airman so transferred shall be deemed to be a 
member of the said Reserve.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>278A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Deputy Chief of Air Staff, vide S. R. O. 321. dated the 20th 
August, <year>1955</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 4, p. 189.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1873766</tid>
<number>2</number>The competent authority may, in such circumstances and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, by special order, 
appoint to the Regular Air Force Reserve any member of the Air Defence 
Reserve or the Auxiliary Air Force raised and maintained under this 
Act, and where any such member is so appointed, he shall cease to be a 
member of the Air Defence Reserve or the Auxiliary Air Force, as the 
case may be, and shall as from the date of such appointment be deemed 
to be a member of the Regular Air Force Reserve.

</section>

<section><tid>1203672</tid>
<number>3</number>The competent authority may, for reasons which in its opi- 
nion are sufficient, cancel any order made under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) and on the cancellation of such order the person in 
respect of whom the order had been made shall cease to be a member of 
the Regular Air Force Reserve.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1478625</tid>
<number> 6</number> Classes of person in the Regular Air Force Reserve. Members of 
the Regular Air Force Reserve shall be divided into the following 
classes, namely:-
<section><tid>1826511</tid>
<number>a</number>general duties officers;

</section>

<section><tid>1753052</tid>
<number>b</number>ground duties officers, and

</section>

<section><tid>1186963</tid>
<number>c</number>airmen,
and every officer shall be entitled on transfer or appointment to 
the Reserve to hold the same rank as that which he last held in the 
Air Force, or the Air Defence Reserve or the Auxiliary Air Force, as 
the case may be, before such transfer or appointment.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>279</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1733449</tid>
<number> 7</number> Period of service.
<section><tid>1803965</tid>
<number>1</number>Every member of the Regular Air Force  
Reserve shall be liable to serve in the Reserve-

<subsection><tid>1880650</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is transferred to the Reserve under sub- section 
 (1) of section 5, for the period of his Reserve liability; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282705</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is appointed to the Reserve under sub- section (2) 
of section 5, for the remainder of the period for which he 
was liable to serve in the Air Defence Reserve or the 
Auxiliary Air Force, as the case may be:
Provided that the competent authority may require any such member 
to serve in the Reserve for such further period or periods not 
exceeding in the aggregate five years as it may think fit.

Explanation I.- For the purposes of this sub- section," period of 
Reserve liability" in relation to any member of the Regular Air Force 
Reserve means the period for which under the terms and conditions of 
his service in the Air Force he was liable to serve in any Air Force 
Reserve if and when constituted.

Explanation II.- In computing the period of Reserve liability in 
relation to any member of the Regular Air Force Reserve whose 
commission or engagement in the Air Force was terminated before the 
commencement of this Act, the period which has elapsed between such 
termination and the date of such commencement shall be included.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>276490</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), no 
person shall be liable to serve in the Reserve after attaining the 
prescribed age.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1544296</tid>
<number>8</number>Termination of service in the Reserve. Every member of the 
Regular Air Force Reserve shall, on completion of the period of his 
service therein, cease to be a member of the Reserve.
CHAP

AIR DEFENCE RESERVE

CHAPTER III

AIR DEFENCE RESERVE



</article>



<article><tid>1205199</tid>
<number>9</number>Constitution of Air Defence Reserve. The Central Government 
may raise and maintain in the manner hereafter in this Chapter 
provided an Air Force Reserve to be designated the Air Defence Reserve 
which shall consist of persons deemed under the provisions of section 
 16 to be enrolled therein.


</article>



<article><tid>995784</tid>
<number> 10</number> Classes of persons in the Air Defence Reserve. Members of the 
Air Defence Reserve shall be divided into the following classes, 
namely:-
<section><tid>10051</tid>
<number>a</number>general duties officers; 
 (b) ground duties officers; and 
 (c) airmen.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>280</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13442</tid>
<number> 11</number> Obligation to register.
<section><tid>1494129</tid>
<number>1</number>Every citizen of India who- 

<subsection><tid>1751400</tid>
<number>a</number>holds or has held a public transport pilot' s licence 
 (" B" Licence) issued under the Indian Aircraft Rules, <year>1937</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1668212</tid>
<number>b</number>has had not less than two hundred hours' experience of 
solo flying, including not less than thirty landings, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930849</tid>
<number>c</number>holds or has held a first class navigator' s licence 
issued under the Indian Aircraft Rules, <year>1937</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>361290</tid>
<number>d</number>has had at least four years' aviation experience during 
which at least six hundred hours shall have been spent in the 
air, not less than one hundred hours of such experience being 
experience of navigation in the air, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1525752</tid>
<number>e</number>holds or has held a first class radio telegraph 
operator' s licence issued under the Indian Aircraft Rules, 
<year>1937</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1650516</tid>
<number>f</number>holds or has held a radio telephone operator' s licence 
issued under the Indian Aircraft Rules, <year>1937</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1580973</tid>
<number>g</number>holds or has held a licence as ground engineer in any 
of the categories A, B, C, D or X issued under the Indian 
Aircraft Rules, <year>1937</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>215011</tid>
<number>h</number>is or was at any time employed in connection with any 
aerodrome or in connection with the control and movement of 
aircraft, in such capacity as may be prescribed,
shall within the prescribed period correctly fill up, or cause to be 
filled up, to the best of his knowledge and belief the prescribed 
form, and sign and lodge it with the competent authority nearest to 
his usual place of residence or business:

Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1847354</tid>
<number>i</number>to any person belonging to any of the classes specified 
in clauses (a) to (f), if he has attained the age of thirty- 
seven years; or

<subsubsection><tid>1364228</tid>
<number>ii</number>to any person belonging to any of the classes specified 
in clauses (g) and (h), if he has attained the age of fifty 
years.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1183892</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (1), the competent authority may, if it is satisfied that the 
provisions of that sub- section apply to any person, by order in 
writing, require that person to furnish within such time such 
particulars as may be specified in the order and such person shall 
within the specified time furnish correctly to the best of his 
knowledge and belief the said particulars to the said authority in 
such form and manner as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>281</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1366547</tid>
<number> 12</number> Liability to be called up for inquiry. Every person to whom 
the provisions of section 11 are applicable shall be liable to be 
called up for inquiry under section 13,-
<section><tid>821715</tid>
<number>a</number>if he belongs to any of the classes specified in 
clauses (a) to (f) of sub- section (1) of section 11, until he 
has completed his thirty- seventh year, and

</section>

<section><tid>1745476</tid>
<number>b</number>if he belongs to any of the classes specified in 
clauses (g) and (h) of the said sub- section, until he has 
completed his fiftieth year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>852757</tid>
<number>13</number>Calling- up for inquiry. The competent authority may cause to 
be served on any person for the time being liable to be called up for 
inquiry under section 12 a written notice stating that he is called up 
for inquiry regarding his fitness for service in the Air Defence 
Reserve and requiring him to present himself to such person and at 
such place and at such time as may be specified in the notice and to 
submit himself to inquiry by the said person.


</article>



<article><tid>952768</tid>
<number>14</number>Medical examination. Every person called up for inquiry under 
section 13 shall, if and when required by the competent authority, 
present himself for examination before such medical officer as may be 
directed by that authority and, for the purposes of such examination, 
shall comply with the directions of the medical officer.


</article>



<article><tid>111180</tid>
<number>15</number>Registration of persons considered fit for enrolment. If, 
after such inquiry and medical examination as aforesaid, the competent 
authority considers a person fit for enrolment in the Air Defence 
Reserve, it shall inform him accordingly and enter his name and other 
prescribed particulars in a register maintained in such form and 
manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>139932</tid>
<number>16</number>Calling up for service. The competent authority may cause to 
be served on any person whose name is entered in the register 
maintained in pursuance of section 15 a written notice stating that he 
is called up for service in the Air Defence Reserve and requiring him 
to present himself at such place and time and to such authority as may 
be specified in the notice; and the person upon whom the notice is 
served shall be deemed to be enrolled in the Reserve as from the day 
so specified.


</article>



<article><tid>1069714</tid>
<number> 17</number> Period of service.
<section><tid>511378</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person deemed to be enrolled in  
the Air Defence Reserve shall be liable for service-

<subsection><tid>1849580</tid>
<number>a</number>if he belongs to any of the classes specified in 
clauses (a) to (f) of sub- section (1) of section 11, until he 
has completed his forty- second year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1706638</tid>
<number>b</number>if he belongs to any of the classes specified in 
clauses (g) and (h) of the said sub- section, until he has 
completed his fifty- fifth year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1725759</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such person, on attaining the age specified in sub- 
section (1), shall cease to be a member of the Air Defence Reserve.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>282</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

AUXILIARY AIR FORCE

CHAPTER IV

AUXILIARY AIR FORCE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1561781</tid>
<number> 18</number> Constitution of Auxiliary Air Force.
<section><tid>976417</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may raise and maintain in the manner hereafter in this 
Chapter provided an Air Force to be designated the Auxiliary Air 
Force.

</section>

<section><tid>112171</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may constitute such number of squadrons 
and units of the Auxiliary Air Force as it thinks fit and may disband 
or reconstitute any squadron or unit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>755708</tid>
<number> 19</number> Classes of persons in the Auxiliary Air Force. Members of the 
Auxiliary Air Force shall be divided into the following classes, 
namely:-
<section><tid>648616</tid>
<number>a</number>general duties officers;

</section>

<section><tid>1945279</tid>
<number>b</number>ground duties officers; and

</section>

<section><tid>1699950</tid>
<number>c</number>airmen.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>603206</tid>
<number>20</number>Officers of the Auxiliary Air Force. The President may grant 
to such person as he thinks fit a commission as an officer in the 
Auxiliary Air Force with designation of rank corresponding to that of 
any commissioned officer in the Air Force.


</article>



<article><tid>1883968</tid>
<number>21</number>Persons eligible for enrolment. Any citizen of India may offer 
himself for enrolment in the Auxiliary Air Force and may, if he 
satisfies the prescribed conditions, be so enrolled on such terms as 
may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>311591</tid>
<number>22</number>Period of service. Every officer and every enrolled person 
shall, subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf under this 
Act, be required to serve in the Auxiliary Air Force for a period of 
five years from the date of his appointment or enrolment but may, 
after the completion of his period of service, volunteer to serve 
therein for further periods each of not more than five years' 
duration.


</article>



<article><tid>1817501</tid>
<number>23</number>Termination of service. The service of any officer or 
enrolled person in the Auxiliary Air Force may, at any time before the 
completion of his period of service, be terminated by such authority 
and under such conditions as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>906471</tid>
<number> 24</number> Advisory Committees.
<section><tid>1833343</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall, as  
soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, constitute-

<subsection><tid>862348</tid>
<number>a</number>for the whole of India, a Central Advisory Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1068591</tid>
<number>b</number>for each State, a State Advisory Committee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079901</tid>
<number>c</number>for every unit of the Auxiliary Air Force, a Unit 
Advisory Committee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1303831</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Central Advisory Committee to 
advise the Central Government on matters connected with the Auxiliary 
Air Force generally, of the State Advisory Committee to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>283</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

advise the Central Government on matters connected with the formation 
of squadrons or units in the State and squadrons or units already 
stationed in the State.


</section>

<section><tid>1564478</tid>
<number>3</number>The duties, powers and procedure of Advisory Committees and 
in particular the matters in respect of which the Advisory Committees 
may be called upon to give advice shall be such as may be prescribed.
CHAP

LIABILITY AND DISCIPLINE OF MEMBERS OF RESERVEAND AUXILIARY AIR FORCES

CHAPTER V

LIABILITY AND DISCIPLINE OF MEMBERS OF RESERVE 
AND AUXILIARY AIR FORCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1940565</tid>
<number> 25</number> Liability to be called up for service. Every member of an 
Air Force Reserve or the Auxiliary Air Force shall, during the period 
of his service, be liable to be called up-
<section><tid>80921</tid>
<number>a</number>for training for such period as may be prescribed and 
for medical examination,

</section>

<section><tid>40027</tid>
<number>b</number>for service in aid of the civil power,

</section>

<section><tid>46633</tid>
<number>c</number>for Air Force service in India or abroad.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>534846</tid>
<number>26</number>Application of Air Force Act, <year>1950</year>. Every member of an Air 
Force Reserve or the Auxiliary Air Force shall, when called up for 
training, medical examination or for service under this Act, be 
subject to the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year> (45 of <year>1950</year>), and the rules made 
thereunder in the same manner as a person belonging to the Air Force 
and holding the same rank is subject to the said Act and rules and 
shall continue to be so subject until duly released from such 
training, medical examination or service, as the case may be.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1554111</tid>
<number> 27</number> Reinstatement in civil employ of persons required to perform 
service under this Act.
<section><tid>1202501</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of every employer by  
whom a person called up under section 25 is employed to grant him such 
leave as may be necessary and to reinstate him in his employment on 
the termination of the period during which he has been so called up in 
an occupation and under conditions not less favourable to him than 
those which would have been applicable to him had he not been so 
called up:
Provided that if the employer refuses to reinstate such person or 
denies his liability to reinstate such person, or if for any reason 
the


<pagefootnote><pagenum>284</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

reinstatement of such person is represented by the employer to be 
impracticable, either party may refer the matter to the prescribed 
authority and that authority shall, after considering all matters 
which may be put before him and after making such further inquiry into 
the matter as may be prescribed, pass an order-


<subsection><tid>1138864</tid>
<number>a</number>exempting the employer from the provisions of this 
section, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>279734</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring him to re- employ such person on such terms as 
that authority thinks suitable, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1437982</tid>
<number>c</number>requiring him to pay to such person by way of 
compensation for failure or inability to re- employ a sum not 
exceeding an amount equal to six months' remuneration at the 
rate at which his last remuneration was payable to him by the 
employer.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1473205</tid>
<number>2</number>If any employer fails to obey the order of any such 
authority as is referred to in the proviso to sub- section (1), he 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
and the court by which an employer is convicted under this section 
shall order him (if he has not already been so required by the said  
  authority) to pay to the person whom he has failed to re- employ a sum 
equal to six months' remuneration at the rate at which his last 
remuneration was payable to him by the employer, and any amount so 
required to be paid either by the said authority or by the court shall 
be recoverable as if it were a fine imposed by such court.

</section>

<section><tid>1936694</tid>
<number>3</number>In any proceeding under this section it shall be a defence 
for an employer to prove that the person formerly employed did not 
apply to the employer for reinstatement within a period of two months 
from the termination of the period during which he was called up under 
section 25.

</section>

<section><tid>1824133</tid>
<number>4</number>The duty imposed by sub- section (1) upon an employer to 
grant leave to a person such as is described in that sub- section or to 
reinstate him in his employment shall attach to an employer who, 
before such person is actually called up under section 25, terminates 
his employment in circumstances such as to indicate an intention to 
evade the duty imposed by that sub- section and such intention shall be 
presumed until the contrary is proved if the termination takes place 
after the issue of an order relating to that person under section 25.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>790561</tid>
<number>28</number>Preservation of certain rights persons called up for 
service. When any person called up under section 25 has any rights 
under any provident fund or superannuation fund or other scheme for 
the benefit of employees maintained in connection with the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>285</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

employment he relinquishes, he shall continue, during the period for 
which he has been so called up and if he is reinstated, until such 
reinstatement under the provisions of this Act, to have in respect of 
such fund or scheme such rights as may be prescribed.



</article>



<article><tid>1618925</tid>
<number> 29</number> Pay and allowances.
<section><tid>1772300</tid>
<number>1</number>Every member of an Air Force Reserve  
or the Auxiliary Air Force shall, during the period of training or 
active service, receive such pay and allowances as are admissible to 
an officer or airman, as the case may be, in the corresponding rank, 
branch or trade of the Air Force.

</section>

<section><tid>297725</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such member was in any employment immediately before 
he is called up for training under section 25, the employer 
shall, during the period of the training, be liable to pay to him the 
difference, if any, between the pay and allowances which he would have 
received from the employer if he had not been called up for such 
training and the pay and allowances which he receives as such member 
while under training.

</section>

<section><tid>1341963</tid>
<number>3</number>If any employer refuses or fails to pay to any such member 
the difference in pay and allowances as provided in sub- section (2), 
such difference in pay and allowances may, on application by the 
member to the prescribed authority, be recovered from the employer in 
such manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1796841</tid>
<number> 30</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>64303</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person refuses or without lawful excuse  
 (the burden of proving which shall lie upon such person) neglects to 
comply fully with the requirements of sub- section (1) of section 11 or 
of any order made under sub- section (2) of that section or with the 
requirements of section 14, he shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>45099</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person wilfully fails to comply with any notice 
issued under section 13 or section 16, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1454729</tid>
<number>31</number>Service of notice. Any notice or order to be served on any 
person for the purposes of this Act may be sent by post to that person 
at his last known address or may be served upon him in such other 
manner as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>1270989</tid>
<number>32</number>Competent authority to be public servant. For the purposes 
of this Act every competent authority and where the competent 
authority consists of a committee of two or more air officers, every 
member of the committee shall be deemed to be a public servant within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>320763</tid>
<number>33</number>Power of Central Government to grant exemptions. The Central 
Government may, for special reasons and subject to such conditions as 
may be prescribed, by order exempt any person

<pagefootnote><pagenum>286</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

from any obligation or liability under this Act or any particular 
provision thereof.



</article>



<article><tid>1886925</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1520334</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 1 for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>736300</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>120369</tid>
<number>a</number>the composition and strength of any Air Force Reserve;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>677304</tid>
<number>b</number>the circumstances in which and the conditions subject 
to which any officer or airman may be transferred or 
appointed to the Regular Air Force Reserve under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1061685</tid>
<number>c</number>the age beyond which persons shall not be liable to 
serve in the Regular Air Force Reserve;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>262632</tid>
<number>d</number>the form and manner in which the particulars required 
by sub- section (2) of section 11 shall be furnished;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1573516</tid>
<number>e</number>the form and manner in which registers shall be 
maintained in pursuance of section 15, the particulars to be 
entered therein, and the correction or revision of such 
particulars from time to time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1048904</tid>
<number>f</number>the pay or allowances payable to persons called up for 
inquiry or medical examination under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400747</tid>
<number>g</number>the terms and conditions subject to which a person may 
be enrolled as a member of the Auxiliary Air Force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>557545</tid>
<number>h</number>the authority by which and the conditions subject to 
which the service of any officer or enrolled person in the 
Auxiliary Air Force may be terminated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>31203</tid>
<number>i</number>the constitution and the duties, powers and procedure 
of Advisory Committees to be constituted under section 24;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>319209</tid>
<number>j</number>the period and manner of training of members of any Air 
Force Reserve and the Auxiliary Air Force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>982834</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
the rank of any member of an Air Force Reserve may be 
determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330606</tid>
<number>l</number>the constitution of the authority for the purpose of 
section 27 and the manner in which such authority may conduct 
any inquiry under this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>287</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See the Reserve and Auxiliary Air Forces Act Rules, <year>1953</year>, 
Gazette of India <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, sec. 4, p. 187.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>827473</tid>
<number>m</number>the authority to which an application under sub- section 
 (3) of section 29 may be made and the manner in which the 
difference in the pay and allowances may be recovered under 
that sub- section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>207604</tid>
<number>n</number>the manner in which any notice or order issued or made 
under this Act may be served;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720067</tid>
<number>o</number>the conditions subject to which any person may be 
exempted from any obligation or liability under this Act or 
any particular provision thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411989</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which under this Act is to be, or may 
be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>443970</tid>
<number>3</number>Any rule made under this section may provide that a con- 
travention thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1263853</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
session immediately following the session or the successive 
sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modi- 
fication in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect 
only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case 
may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1456213</tid>
<number>35</number>[ Amendment of sections 2, 4 and 31, Act 45 of <year>1950</year>.] Rep. by 
the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1957</year> (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>640527</tid>
<number>36</number>[ Repeal of Act 36 of <year>1939</year>.] Rep. by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>288</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>