<act><tid>129292</tid>
<title>THE JAYANTI SHIPPING COMPANY (ACQUISITION OF SHARES) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 63 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition of the shares of the Jayanti 
Shipping Company Limited in order to serve better the shipping needs 
of the nation and to facilitate the promotion and development, in the 
interests of the general public, of national shipping and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1644195</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1062238</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Jayanti Shipping Company (Acquisition of Shares) Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1251809</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th day of 
October, <year>1971</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1969150</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1447228</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1729405</tid>
<number>b</number>" company" means the Jayanti Shipping Company Limited, 
being a company as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (1 of <year>1956</year>), having its registered office at Bombay;

</section>

<section><tid>1202468</tid>
<number>c</number>" shareholder" means a person, who, immediately before 
the appointed day, was registered as a shareholder in 
the capital of the company;

</section>

<section><tid>1313002</tid>
<number>d</number>" Shipping Corporation of India" means the Shipping 
Corporation of India Limited, being a Government 
company as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), having its registered office at Bombay;

</section>

<section><tid>1383642</tid>
<number>e</number>words and expression used but not defined in this Act 
and defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
in that Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ACQUISITION OF SHARES OF THE COMPANY

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF SHARES OF THE COMPANY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1068840</tid>
<number> 3</number> Vesting of shares of company in Central Government and 
compensation therefor.
<section><tid>648701</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day,-- 

<subsection><tid>750185</tid>
<number>a</number>all shares in the capital of the company shall, by 
virtue of this Act, be deemed to be transferred to and 
vested in the Central Government free from all trusts, 
liabilities and encumbrances; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>39119</tid>
<number>b</number>as compensation therefor the Central Government shall, 
in accordance with the provisions of section 4, pay to 
the shareholders the sum of rupees four crores and 
fifty lakhs only in the aggregate.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>77466</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that the 
transfer and vesting of shares effected under clause (a) of sub- 
section (1) shall not be deemed to affect any right of the company 
subsisting immediately before the appointed day against any 
shareholder to recover from him any sum of money on the ground that 
the shareholder has not paid or credited to the company the whole or 
any part of the value of the shares held by him or on any other ground 
whatsoever.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1839947</tid>
<number> 4</number> Apportionment and manner of payment of compensation.
<section><tid>943095</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
amount of compensation payable under clause (b) of sub- section (1) of 
section 3 to the shareholders shall be apportioned among the 
shareholders according to the number of shares held by such 
shareholders.

</section>

<section><tid>966059</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount of compensation payable to a shareholder in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1) shall be given to 
him, at his option--

<subsection><tid>1980217</tid>
<number>a</number>in cash (to be paid by cheque drawn on the Reserve Bank  
  of India) in three equal annual instalments, the amount 
of each instalment carrying interest at the rate of 
four per cent. per annum from the appointed day, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>133198</tid>
<number>b</number>in saleable or otherwise transferable promissory notes 
or stock certificates of the Central Government issued 
and repayable at par, and maturing at the end of--

<subsubsection><tid>899158</tid>
<number>i</number>ten years from the appointed day and carrying 
interest from that day at the rate of four and a half 
per cent. per annum, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1116602</tid>
<number>ii</number>thirty years from the appointed day and 
carrying interest from that day at the rate of five and 
a half per cent. per annum, or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>862328</tid>
<number>c</number>partly in cash (to be paid by cheque drawn on the  
  Reserve Bank of India) and partly in such number of 
securities, specified in sub- clause (i) or sub- clause 
 (ii), or both, of clause (b), as may be required by the 
shareholder, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>580487</tid>
<number>d</number>partly in such number of securities specified in sub- 
clause (i) of clause (b) and partly in such number of 
securities specified in sub- clause (ii) of that clause, 
as may be required by the shareholder.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>399117</tid>
<number>3</number>The first of the three equal annual instalments referred to 
in clause (a) of sub- section (2) shall be paid, and the securities 
referred to in clause (b) of that sub- section shall be issued, within 
sixty days from the date of receipt by the Central Government of the 
option referred to in that sub- section, or where no such option has 
been exercised, from the latest date before which such option ought to 
have been exercised.

</section>

<section><tid>1625835</tid>
<number>4</number>The option referred to in sub- section (2) shall be exercised 
by a shareholder before the expiry of a period of three months from 
the appointed day (or within such further time, not exceeding three  
months, as the Central Government may, on the application of the 
  shareholder, allow) and the option so exercised shall be final and 
shall not be altered or rescinded after it has been exercised.

</section>

<section><tid>1037601</tid>
<number>5</number>If a shareholder omits or fails to exercise the option 
referred to in sub- section (2), within the time specified in sub- 
section (4), he shall be deemed to have opted for payment in 
securities specified in sub- clause (i) of clause (b) of sub- section 
 (2).

</section>

<section><tid>223924</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, a 
shareholder may, before the expiry of three months from the appointed 
day (or within such further time, not exceeding three months, as the  
  Central Government may, on the application of the shareholder, allow) 
make an application in writing to the Central Government for--

<subsection><tid>1033239</tid>
<number>a</number>the full payment of the compensation payable to him, if 
the compensation payable to him does not exceed rupees 
two lakhs; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>98</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>381430</tid>
<number>b</number>an interim payment of an amount equal to seventy- five 
per cent, of the face value of the shares in respect of 
which compensation is payable to him, or rupees two 
lakhs, whichever is greater, if the compensation 
payable to him exceeds rupees two lakhs,
indicating in such application whether the payment is desired in cash 
or in securities specified in sub- section (2), or in both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>443105</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government shall, within sixty days from the 
receipt of the application referred to in sub- section (6), make the 
full payment or, as the case may be, the interim payment to the 
shareholder in accordance with the option indicated in such 
application.

</section>

<section><tid>1895502</tid>
<number>8</number>The interim payment made to a shareholder under sub- section 
 (7) shall be set off against the total amount of compensation payable 
to him under this Act and the balance of the compensation remaining 
outstanding after such payment shall be given to the shareholder in 
accordance with the option exercised, or deemed to have been 
exercised, under sub- section (4) or sub- section (5), as the case may 
be:
Provided that where any part of the interim payment is obtained 
by the shareholder in cash, the payment so obtained shall be set off, 
in the first instance, against the first instalment of the cash 
payment referred to in sub- section (2), and in case the payment so 
obtained exceeds the amount of the first instalment, the excess amount 
shall be adjusted against the second instalment and the balance of 
such excess amount, if any, against the third instalment of the cash 
payment.


</section>

<section><tid>1411201</tid>
<number>9</number>If any dispute arises as to the person entitled to receive 
the compensation payable in respect of any share, the Central 
Government shall deposit the amount of such compensation in the court 
for being paid to the person or persons entitled to be paid.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF COMPANY

CHAPTER III

MANAGEMENT OF COMPANY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>657536</tid>
<number> 5</number> Allocation of shares to Shipping Corporation of India and 
certain other persons.
<section><tid>601078</tid>
<number>1</number>All the shares of the company vested in the  
Central Government by virtue of this Act, except one hundred thereof, 
shall immediately after they have so vested, stand transferred to and 
vested in the Shipping Corporation of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>99</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>68870</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may by order transfer the remaining 
shares to such persons as may be specified in the order to enable the 
company to function as a Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>310281</tid>
<number>3</number>On the transfer of shares to the Shipping Corporation of 
India under sub- section (1) or to any person under sub- section (2), 
the company shall forthwith register each transferee as a member of 
the company.

</section>

<section><tid>1010204</tid>
<number>4</number>The amount paid by the Central Government for the acquisition 
of the shares which stand transferred to and vested in the Shipping 
Corporation of India under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to be the 
contribution by the Central Government to the equity capital of the 
Corporation and that Corporation shall issue (if necessary, after  
  amending its memorandum and articles of association) to the Central 
Government paid- up shares in its capital for a corresponding amount.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>29187</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of memorandum and articles of association of 
company. For the purpose of enabling the company to function as a 
Government company, the Central Government may, by notification 
published in the Official Gazette, make such amendments in the 
memorandum and articles of association of the company as it may 
consider necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>357134</tid>
<number> 7</number> Interim management of company.
<section><tid>1708949</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in the 
memorandum or articles of association of the company, on and from the 
appointed day and till a new Board of directors of the company is duly 
constituted, the persons specified in the Schedule shall be the 
directors of the company and shall constitute the Board of directors 
of the company.

</section>

<section><tid>813234</tid>
<number>2</number>If any vacancy arises in the Board of directors specified in 
the Schedule, it shall be filled by the Central Government in such 
manner as it thinks fit and thereupon the Schedule shall be deemed to 
be amended accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1843658</tid>
<number>3</number>No act or proceeding of the Board of directors specified in 
the Schedule shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of any 
vacancy in the membership of the Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>446422</tid>
<number>8</number>Directors, etc., not entitled to compensation. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no director 
or managerial personnel specified in section 197A of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or other person entitled to manage the whole 
or a substantial part of the business and affairs of the company under 
a special agreement or otherwise shall be entitled to any compensation 
against the company or the Central Government for the loss of office 
or for the premature termination of any contract of management entered 
into by him with the company whether such loss or termination was due 
to the provisions of the Jayanti Shipping Company (Taking Over of  
  Management) Act, <year>1966</year> (24 of <year>1966</year>) or this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>939195</tid>
<number> 9</number> Contracts in bad faith, etc., may be cancelled or varied. The 
company may, within three years from the appointed day, make an 
application to any court having jurisdiction in this behalf for the 
purpose of cancelling or varying any contract or agreement entered 
into, at any time before the issue of the notified order under sub- 
section
<section><tid>1032881</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 of the Jayanti Shipping Company (Taking Over   
  of Management) Act, <year>1966</year> (24 of <year>1966</year>), between the company and any 
other person and the court may, if satisfied after due inquiry that 
such contract or agreement had been entered into in bad faith and is 
detrimental to the interests of the company, make an order cancelling 
or varying (either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it  
  may think fit to impose) that contract or agreement, and the contract 
or agreement shall have effect accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>279470</tid>
<number>10</number>Duty to deliver possession of property of company and 
documents relating to company. Any person who has in his possession, 
custody or under his control any property of, or any books, documents 
or other papers relating to the property and assets of, the company, 
including any letters, memoranda, notes or other communications 
between him and the company, shall be liable to account for the said 
property, books, documents and other papers (including such letters,  
  memoranda, notes or other communications) to the company and shall 
deliver them up to the company or to such other person as may be 
authorised for the purpose by the company.


</article>



<article><tid>1476174</tid>
<number> 11</number> Powers of inspection.
<section><tid>1225547</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of ascertaining  
whether any property is the property of the company or for any other 
purpose mentioned in this Act or the rules made thereunder, any person 
authorised by the Central Government in this behalf shall have the 
right to--

<subsection><tid>1564337</tid>
<number>a</number>enter and inspect any premises;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>101</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>286507</tid>
<number>b</number>require any person having the possession, custody or 
control of any register or record of the company to 
produce such register or record;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1390485</tid>
<number>c</number>require the occupier of any property belonging to, or 
claimed to be the property of, the company, to submit 
to the person so authorised such accounts, books or 
other documents or to furnish to him such information 
as he may reasonably think necessary; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1199225</tid>
<number>d</number>examine any person having the control of, or employed in 
connection with, the company and require him to make 
any statement touching the affairs of the company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1097190</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person authorised by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>667577</tid>
<number> 12</number> Penalty for false statements.
<section><tid>1929533</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person,-- 

<subsection><tid>611306</tid>
<number>a</number>when required by this Act or by any order under this Act 
to make any statement or furnish any information, makes 
any statement or furnishes any information which is 
false in any material particular and which he knows or 
believes to be false or does not believe to be true; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>495850</tid>
<number>b</number>makes any such statement as aforesaid in any book, 
account, record, return or other document which he is 
required by any order made under this Act to submit,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>531382</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person, who--

<subsection><tid>6912</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of the assets of the company, 
wrongfully withholds such property from the company, or any 
person authorised by the company, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>783318</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of any property 
forming part of the assets of the company, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1190518</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully withholds or fails to produce to any 
person authorised under this Act, any register, record or 
other document which may be in his possession, custody or 
control, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>102</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>60962</tid>
<number>d</number>fails, without any reasonable cause, to submit any 
accounts, books or other documents, when required to do so,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1000846</tid>
<number>13</number>Limitation on prosecution. No court shall take cognizance of 
an offence under this Act except with the previous sanction of the 
Central Government or of an officer authorised by that Government in 
this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1359134</tid>
<number>14</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act or 
any notification, order or rule made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any law 
other than this Act or in any instrument having effect by virtue of 
any law other than this Act or in any order made by a civil court.


</article>



<article><tid>1133363</tid>
<number>15</number>Protection of action taken under this Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the Shipping Corporation of India or any officer or 
other employee serving in connection with the affairs of the company 
for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>224912</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1206006</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1604883</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740652</tid>
<number>17</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order as occasion requires, do anything (not inconsistent with  
  the provisions of this Act) which appears to it to be necessary for 
the purpose of removing the difficulty:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>103</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that no such order shall be issued after the expiration 
of two years from the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>178850</tid>
<number> 18</number> Repeals and saving.
<section><tid>500200</tid>
<number>1</number>The Jayanti Shipping Company (Taking   
  Over of Management) Act, <year>1966</year> (24 of <year>1966</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1931385</tid>
<number>2</number>The Jayanti Shipping Company (Acquisition of Shares) 
Ordinance, <year>1971</year> (14 of <year>1971</year>), is hereby repealed:
Provided that notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any 
action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provision of this Act.



</section>

</article>



 </act>