<act><tid>766852</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAY PASSENGER FARES ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 25 OF <year>1957</year>
[]

This Act has been repealed by the Railway Passenger Fares (Repeal) 
Act, <year>1961</year> (8 of <year>1961</year>), s. 2 w. e. f. Ist April, <year>1961</year>.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1621391</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1856272</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1351852</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>296725</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1957</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>136255</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>539483</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appellate Assistant Commissioner" means a person 
empowered to exercise the functions of an Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax under section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>1139571</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Appellate Tribunal 
constituted under section 252 of the Income- tax Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1843875</tid>
<number>c</number>" assessee" means a person by whom wealth- tax or any 
other sum of money is payable under this Act, and 
includes--

<subsection><tid>860300</tid>
<number>i</number>every person in respect of whom any proceeding 
under this Act has been taken for the determination of 
wealth- tax payable by him or by any other person or the 
amount of refund due to him or such other person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>933411</tid>
<number>ii</number>every person who is deemed to be an assessee 
under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064606</tid>
<number>iii</number>every person who is deemed to be an assessee 
in default under this Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>181716</tid>
<number>ca</number>" assessment" includes re- assessment;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>778</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended with modifications to Dadra and Nagar 
Haveli, Goa, Daman and Diu, and Pondicherry by Reg. 3 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 
 (1) and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for cls. (b), (c) and (d)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>782524</tid>
<number>d</number>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months 
commencing on the 1st day of April every year;]

</section>

<section><tid>1593279</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" assets" includes property of every description, 
movable or immovable, but does not include,--

<subsection><tid>1306909</tid>
<number>1</number>in relation to the assessment year commencing 
on the 1st day of April, <year>1969</year> or any earlier assessment 
year--

<subsubsection><tid>1256302</tid>
<number>i</number>agricultural land and growing crops, 
grass or standing trees on such land;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>246438</tid>
<number>ii</number>any building owned or occupied by a 
cultivation of, or receiver of rent or revenue out 
of, agricultural land:
Provided that the building is on or in the 
immediate vicinity of the land and is a building 
which the cultivator or the receiver of rent or 
revenue by reason of his connection with the land 
requires as a dwelling- house or a store- house or 
an outhouse;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>867509</tid>
<number>iii</number>animals;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1342478</tid>
<number>iv</number>a right to any annuity in any case where 
the terms and conditions relating thereto preclude 
the commutation of any portion thereof into a lump 
sum grant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1861932</tid>
<number>v</number>any interest in property where the 
interest is available to an assessee for a period 
not exceeding six years from the date the interest 
vests in the assessee;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930778</tid>
<number>2</number>in relation to the assessment year commencing 
on the 1st day of April, <year>1970</year> or any subsequent 
assessment year--

<subsubsection><tid>1232316</tid>
<number>i</number>animals;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1074674</tid>
<number>ii</number>a right to any annuity in any case where the 
terms and conditions relating thereto preclude the 
commutation of any portion thereof into a lump sum 
grant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1102660</tid>
<number>iii</number>any interest in property where the interest 
is available to an assessee for a period not exceeding 
six years from the date the interest vests in the 
assesse:]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that, in relation to the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir, this sub- clause shall have effect 
sub-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>778A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 14 of <year>1969</year>, s. 24, for cl. (e)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


ject to the modification that for the assets specified 
in items (i) to


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1102660</tid>
<number>iii</number>of this sub- clause, the assets specified in 
items (i) to (v) of sub- clause (1) shall be substituted 
and the other provisions of this Act shall be construed 
accordingly;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>755965</tid>
<number>f</number>" Board" means the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Board of Direct Taxes 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act 
 <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1705479</tid>
<number>g</number>" Commissioner" means a person empowered to exercise the 
functions of a Commissioner of Wealth- tax under section 
10;

</section>

<section><tid>189318</tid>
<number>h</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" company" means a company as defined in section 3 of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) and includes--

</section>

<section><tid>1960259</tid>
<number>i</number>a company within the meaning of any law in 
force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir relating to 
companies; <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<subsection><tid>1191006</tid>
<number>ii</number>a company incorporated outside India which 
has a place of business in India; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>779</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 1-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1958</year>, s. 14, for cl. (h)  (with retrospective  
  effect). 
3 The word" and" omitted by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1967</year>). 
4 Ins. by s. 34, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1967</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1600357</tid>
<number>ha</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" co- operative society" means a co- operative society 
registered under the Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> 
 (2 of <year>1912</year>.) or under any other law for the time being 
in force in any State for the registration of co- 
operative societies;]

</section>

<section><tid>227939</tid>
<number>hb</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>]" Director of Inspection" includes an Additional 
Director of Inspection, a Deputy Director of Inspection 
and an Assistant Director of Inspection;]

<subsection><tid>4490</tid>
<number>i</number>" executor" means an executor or administrator of the 
estate of a deceased person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>901516</tid>
<number>j</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43  
  of <year>1961</year>.);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1484799</tid>
<number>k</number>" Income- tax Officer" means a person appointed to be an 
Income- tax Officer under the Income- tax Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>163593</tid>
<number>l</number>" Inspecting Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax" means 
a person empowered to exercise the functions of an 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax under 
section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>185423</tid>
<number>la</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" Inspector of Wealth- tax" means an Inspector of 
Income- tax empowered to work as an Inspector of Wealth- 
tax under section 11A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>984162</tid>
<number>lb</number>" legal representative" has the meaning assigned to it 
in clause (11) of section 2 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>842821</tid>
<number>m</number>" net wealth" means the amount by which the aggregate 
value computed in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act of all the assets, wherever located, belonging 
to the assessee on the valuation date, including assets 
required to be included in his net wealth as on that 
date under this Act, is in excess of the aggregate 
value of all the debts owed by the assessee on the 
valuation date other than,--

<subsubsection><tid>1589123</tid>
<number>i</number>debts which under section 6 are not to be 
taken into account; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1787763</tid>
<number>ii</number>debts which are secured on, or which have 
been incurred in relation to, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> any property in 
respect of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>780</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34 (retrospectively). 
2 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for cl. (j)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 The word" and" omitted by Act 12 of <year>1959</year>, s. 20 
 (retrospectively). 
5 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
6 Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 44 (retrospectively). 
7 Relettered ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


which wealth- tax is not chargeable] under this Act; 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and]


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1016387</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the amount of the tax, penalty or 
interest payable in consequence of any order passed 
under or in pursuance of this Act or any law relating 
to taxation of income or profits, or the Estate Duty 
Act, <year>1953</year>, (34 of <year>1953</year>.) the Expenditure- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, 
 (29 of <year>1957</year>.) or the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year>, (18 of <year>1958</year>.)- 
-

<subsubsubsection><tid>436588</tid>
<number>a</number>which is outstanding on the valuation date and 
is claimed by the assessee in appeal, revision or other 
proceeding as not being payable by him, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>164880</tid>
<number>b</number>which, although not claimed by the assessee as 
not being payable by him, is nevertheless outstanding 
for a period of more than twelve months on the 
valuation date;]

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1183432</tid>
<number>n</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>550293</tid>
<number>o</number>" principal officer", used with reference to a company, 
means the secretary, manager, managing agent or 
managing director of the company, and includes any 
person connected with the management of the affairs of 
the company upon whom the Wealth- tax Officer has served 
a notice of his intention of treating him as the 
principal officer thereof;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1557771</tid>
<number>oa</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" public servant" has the same meaning as in section 
 21 of the Indian Penal Code; (45 of <year>1860</year>.)

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1846003</tid>
<number>ob</number>" regular assessment" means the assessment made under 
section 16;]

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>45017</tid>
<number>p</number>" Ruler" means a Ruler as defined in clause (22) of 
article 366 of the Constitution; 
 (q)" valuation date", in relation to any year for which an 
assessment is to be made under this Act, means the last 
day of the previous year as defined in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> section 3] of 
the Income- tax Act if an assessment were to be made 
under that Act for that year:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that--


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1589123</tid>
<number>i</number>where in the case of an assessee there are 
different previous years under the Income- tax Act for
<pagefootnote><pagenum>781</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 12 of <year>1959</year>, s. 20 (retrospectively). 
2 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" clause (11) of section 2" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for the proviso (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 15- 11- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


different sources of income, the valuation date for the 
purposes of this Act shall be the last day of the last 
of the previous years aforesaid;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1787763</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a person who is not an 
assessee within the meaning of the Income- tax Act, the 
valuation date for the purposes of this Act shall be 
the 31st day of March immediately preceding the 
assessment year;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1016387</tid>
<number>iii</number>where an assessment is made in pursuance of 
section 19A, the valuation date shall be the same 
valuation date as would have been adopted in respect of 
the net wealth of the deceased if he were alive;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859696</tid>
<number>r</number>" valuer" means a valuer appointed under section 4 of the 
Estate Duty Act, <year>1953</year> (34 of <year>1953</year>.);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1704585</tid>
<number>s</number>" Wealth- tax Officer" means the Income- tax Officer 
authorised to perform the functions of a Wealth- tax 
Officer under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> this Act].
CHAP

CHARGE OF WEALTH- TAX AND ASSETS SUBJECT TO SUCH CHARGE

CHAPTER II

CHARGE OF WEALTH- TAX AND ASSETS SUBJECT TO SUCH CHARGE




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1708625</tid>
<number>3</number>Charge of wealth tax. Subject to the other provisions 
contained in this Act, there shall be charged for every <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> assessment 
year] commencing on and from the first day of April, <year>1957</year>, a tax 
 (hereinafter referred to as wealth- tax) in respect of the net wealth 
on the corresponding valuation date of every individual, Hindu 
undivided family and company at the rate or rates specified in the 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>643923</tid>
<number> 4</number> Net wealth to include certain assets.
<section><tid>1260360</tid>
<number>1</number>In computing the net  
wealth of an individual, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> there shall be included, as belonging to 
that individual]--

<subsection><tid>195629</tid>
<number>a</number>the value of assets which on the valuation date are 
held--

<subsubsection><tid>1792166</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> by the spouse of such individual to whom 
such assets have been transferred by the individual, 
direct--
<pagefootnote><pagenum>782</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for" section 8" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Sub. by s. 3, ibid., for" financial year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for" there shall be included, as belonging 
to him" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for sub- clauses (i), (ii) and (iii)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


ly or indirectly, otherwise than for adequate 
consideration or in connection with an agreement to 
live apart, or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1045092</tid>
<number>ii</number>by a minor child, not being a married 
daughter, of such individual, to whom such assets have 
been transferred by the individual, directly or 
indirectly, otherwise than for adequate consideration, 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>895275</tid>
<number>iii</number>by a person or association of persons to 
whom such assets have been transferred by the 
individual otherwise than for adequate consideration 
for the immediate or deferred benefit of the 
individual, his or her spouse or minor child (not being  
  a married daughter) or both, or]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1339940</tid>
<number>iv</number>by a person or association of persons to whom 
such assets have been transferred by the individual 
otherwise than under an irrevocable transfer,
whether the assets referred to in any of the sub- clauses aforesaid are 
held in the form in which they were transferred or otherwise:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that where the transfer of such assets or any 
part thereof is either chargeable to gift- tax under the 
Gift- taxt Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>) or is not chargeable 
under section 5 of that Act, for any assessment year 
commencing <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> after the 31st day of March, <year>1964</year>, but 
before the 1st day of April, <year>1972</year>], the value of such 
assets or part thereof, as the case may be, shall not 
be included in computing the net wealth of the 
individual;]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1848286</tid>
<number>b</number>where the assessee is a partner in a firm or a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> member 
of an association of persons (not being a co- operative  
  housing society)] the value of his interest in the firm 
or association determined in the prescribed manner.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1539258</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where, in the case of an individual being a member 
of a Hindu undivided family, any property having been 
the separate property of the individual has, at any 
time after the 31st day of December, <year>1969</year>, been 
converted by the individual into property belonging to 
the family through the act of impressing such separate 
property with the character of property belonging to 
the family or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>783</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 31, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1972</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 31, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


throwing it into the common stock of the family (such property being  
  hereinafter referred to as the converted property), then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision of this Act 
or in any other law for the time being in force, for the purpose of 
computing the net wealth of the individual under this Act for any 
assessment year commencing on or after the 1st day of April, <year>1972</year>,--


<subsection><tid>1493650</tid>
<number>a</number>the individual shall be deemed to have transferred the 
converted property, through the family, to the members 
of the family for being held by them jointly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1752207</tid>
<number>b</number>the converted property or any part thereof, in so far as 
it is attributable to the interest of the individual in 
the property of the family, shall be deemed to be 
assets belonging to the individual and not to the 
family;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>56133</tid>
<number>c</number>any part of the converted property in so far as it is 
attributable to the interest of the spouse or any minor 
child of the individual in the property of the family 
and where there is a partition (partial or total) 
amongst the members of the family, the converted 
property or any part thereof which is received by the 
spouse or minor child on such partition shall be deemed 
to be assets transferred indirectly by the individual 
to the spouse or minor child and the provisions of sub- 
section (1) shall, so far as may be, apply accordingly:
Provided that the property referred to in clause (b) or 
clause (c) shall, on being included in the net wealth 
of the individual, be excluded from the net wealth of 
the family or, as the case may be, the spouse or minor 
child of the individual.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1218643</tid>
<number>2</number>In making any rules with reference to the valuation of 
the interest referred to in clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1), the Board shall have regard to the law for the 
time being in force relating to the manner in which 
accounts are to be settled between partners of a firm 
and members of an association on the dissolution of a 
firm or association, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>872681</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the value of any assets is to be included in the 
net wealth of an assessee in accordance with clause (a) 
of sub- section (1), there shall be deducted from such 
value any debts owing on the valuation date by the 
transferee mentioned in that sub- section in so far as 
such debts are referable to the assets.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>784</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1389184</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in clause (a) of sub- section (1) shall 
apply to any such transfer as is referred to therein made by an 
individual before the 1st day of April, <year>1956</year>, and the value of any 
assets so transferred shall not be included in the computation of his 
net wealth.

</section>

<section><tid>882039</tid>
<number>5</number>The value of any assets transferred under an irrevocable 
transfer shall be liable to be included in computing the net wealth of 
the transferor as and when the power to revoke arises to him.

</section>

<section><tid>1316595</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the purposes of this Act, the holder of an impartible 
estate shall be deemed to be the individual owner of all the 
properties comprised in the estate.

</section>

<section><tid>1400271</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where the assessee is a member of an association of 
persons, being a co- operative housing society, and a building or part 
thereof is allotted or leased to him under a house building scheme of 
the society, the assessee shall, notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act or any other law for the time being in force, be deemed to be 
the owner of such building or part and the value of such building or 
part shall be included in computing the net wealth of the assessee; 
and, in determining the value of such building or part, the value of 
any outstanding instalments of the amount payable under such scheme by 
the assessee to the society towards the cost of such building or part 
and the land appurtenant thereto shall, whether the amount so payable 
is described as such or in any other manner in such scheme, be 
deducted as a debt owned by him in relation to such building or part.]
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1994233</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" transfer" includes any disposition, 
settlement, trust, covenant, agreement or arrangement, 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>938712</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" irrevocable transfer" includes a 
transfer of assets which, by the terms of the 
instrument effecting it, is not revocable for a period 
exceeding six years or during the life- time of the 
transferee, and under which the transferor derives no 
direct or indirect benefit, but does not include a 
transfer of assets if such instrument--

<subsubsection><tid>40273</tid>
<number>i</number>contains any provision for the re- transfer, 
directly or indirectly, of the whole or any part of the 
assets or income therefrom to the transferor, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>785</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 4, for the Explanation (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 31 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
3 The word" and" omitted by s. 31, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>701635</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any way gives the transferor a right to 
reassume power, directly or indirectly, over the whole 
or any part of the assets or income therefrom.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1102574</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the expression" property" includes any interest in 
property, movable or immovable, the proceeds of sale 
thereof and any money or investment for the time being 
representing the proceeds of sale thereof and where the 
property is converted into any other property by any 
method, such other property; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>350867</tid>
<number>d</number>the expressions" interest of the individual in the 
property of the family" and" interest of the spouse or 
any minor child of the individual in the property of 
the family" mean, respectively, the proportion in which 
the individual or, as the case may be, the spouse or 
minor child would be entitled to share the property of 
the family if there had been a total partition in the 
family as on the valuation date of the family relevant 
to the assessment year for which the individual is to 
be assessed under sub- section (1A).]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>444821</tid>
<number> 5</number> Exemptions in respect, of certain assets.
<section><tid>1587288</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Subject to  
the provisions of sub- section (1A), wealth- tax shall not be payable by 
an assessee in respect of the following assets] and such assets shall 
not be included in the net wealth of the assessee--

<subsection><tid>1503811</tid>
<number>i</number>any property held by him under trust or other legal 
obligation for any public purpose of a charitable or 
religious nature in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776357</tid>
<number>ii</number>the interest of the assessee in the occupation property 
of any Hindu undivided family of which he is a member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1345710</tid>
<number>iii</number>any one building in the occupation of a Ruler declared 
by the Central Government as his official residence 
under paragraph 13 of the Merged States (Taxation  
  Concessions) Order, <year>1949</year>, or paragraph 15 of the Part B 
States (Taxation Concessions) Order, <year>1950</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1233488</tid>
<number>iv</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> one house or part of a house belonging to the 
assessee
Provided that, where the value of such house or part exceeds 
one hundred thousand rupees, the amount that shall not

<pagefootnote><pagenum>786</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 31 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1971</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 26, ibid., for" clause (iv)" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
4 Certain words omitted by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


be included in the net wealth of the assessee under 
this clause shall be one hundred thousand rupees;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979045</tid>
<number>iva</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> agricultural land belonging to the assessee subject 
to a maximum of one hundred and fifty thousand rupees 
in value:
Provided that where the assessee owns any house or part of a 
house situate in a place with a population exceeding 
ten thousand and to which the provisions of clause (iv) 
apply and the value of such house or part of a house 
together with the value of the agricultural land 
exceeds one hundred and fifty thousand rupees, then the 
amount that shall not be included in the net wealth of 
the assessee under this clause shall be one hundred and 
fifty thousand rupees as reduced by so much of the 
value of such house or part of house as is not to be 
included in the net wealth of the assessee under clause 
 (iv):]


<subsubsection><tid>1389306</tid>
<number>ivb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> one building or one group of buildings owned by a 
cultivator of, or receiver of rent or revenue out of, 
agricultural land:
Provided that such building or group of buildings is on or 
in the immediate vicinity of the land and is required 
by the cultivator or the receiver of rent or revenue, 
by reason of his connection with the land, as dwelling 
house, store- house or outhouse;]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1504178</tid>
<number>v</number>the rights under any patent or copyright belonging to 
the assessee:
Provided that they are not held by him as assets of a 
business, profession or vocation and no income or 
benefit accrues to him therefrom;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>232148</tid>
<number>vi</number>the right or interest of the assessee in any policy of 
insurance before the moneys covered by the policies 
become due and payable to the assessee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1494465</tid>
<number>via</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the right of the assessee to receive any annuity 
payable by the Central Government under the provisions 
of section 280D of the Income- tax Act;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1969</year>, s. 24 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1970</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>982707</tid>
<number>vii</number>the right of the assessee to receive a pension or 
other life annuity in respect of past services under an 
employer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1060595</tid>
<number>viii</number>furniture, household utensils, wearing apparel, 
provisions and other articles intended for the personal 
or household use of the assessee <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> but not including 
jewellery]:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that the furniture, utensils or other articles 
are neither made wholly or partly of, nor contain 
 (whether by way of embedding, covering or otherwise), 
gold, silver, platinum or any other precious metal or 
any alloy containing one or more of such precious 
metals:

Provided further that nothing in this clause shall operate 
to exclude from the net wealth of the assessee any 
conveyance or conveyances to the extent the value or 
the aggregate value thereof exceeds the sum of 
twentyfive thousand rupees.

Explanation 1.-- For the purposes of this clause and clause 
 (xiii)," jewellery" includes--


<subsubsection><tid>14964</tid>
<number>a</number>ornaments made of gold, silver, platinum or 
any other precious metal or any alloy containing one or 
more of such precious metals, whether or not containing 
any precious or semi- precious stone, and whether or not 
worked or sewn into any wearing apparel;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>236953</tid>
<number>b</number>precious or semi- precious stones, whether or 
not set in any furniture, utensil or other article or 
worked or sewn into any wearing apparel.
Explanation 2.-- For the purposes of this clause, 
" conveyance" means any motor car or other mechanically 
propelled vehicle, aircraft or boat;]


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1793082</tid>
<number>viiia</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> growing crops (including fruits on trees) on 
agricultural land and grass on such land;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1937104</tid>
<number>ix</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the tools, implements and equipment used by the 
assessee for the cultivation, conservation, improvement
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1969</year>, s. 24 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1970</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 14 of <year>1969</year>, s. 24 for clause (ix)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or maintenance of agricultural land, or for the raising 
or harvesting of any agricultural or horticultural 
produce on such land.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause, tools, 
implements and equipment do not include any plant or 
machinery used in any tea or other plantation in 
connection with the processing of any agricultural 
produce or in the manufacture of any article from such 
produce;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>251106</tid>
<number>x</number>the tools and instruments necessary to enable the 
assessee to carry on his profession or vocation, 
subject to a maximum of twenty thousand rupees in 
value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1091648</tid>
<number>xi</number>instruments and other apparatus used by the assessee 
for purposes of scientific research;

<subsubsection><tid>559682</tid>
<number>xii</number>any works of art, archaeological, scientific or art 
collections, books or manuscripts belonging to the 
assessee and not intended for sale;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>269165</tid>
<number>xiii</number>any drawings, paintings, photographs, prints and any 
other heirloom not falling within clause (xii) and not 
intended for sale, but not including jewellery;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1741927</tid>
<number>xiv</number>jewellery in the possession of any Ruler, not being 
his personal property, which has been recognised before 
the commencement of this Act by the Central Government 
as his heirloom or, where no such recognition exists, 
which the Board may, subject to any rules that may be 
made by the Central Government in this behalf, 
recognise as his heirloom at the time of his first 
assessment to wealth- tax under this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>93786</tid>
<number>xv</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> deposits] under any scheme framed by the Central 
Government and notified by it in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette, to the extent to which the amounts of 
such deposits do not exceed the maximum amount 
permitted to be deposited therein;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>799920</tid>
<number>xvi</number>ten year treasury savings deposit certificates, 
fifteen year annuity certificates, deposits in post 
office savings banks, post office cash certificates, 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> post office national savings
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1968</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26, for" fixed deposits" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1971</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1958</year>, s. 14, for" and post office national 
savings certificates" (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


certificates, post office national plan certificates 
and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> twelve year national plan savings certificates, 
ten year defence deposit certificates and twelve year 
national defence certificates <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, to the extent to 
which the amount of such certificates or deposits do 
not exceed in each case the maximum amount permitted to 
be invested or deposited therein]];


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>781854</tid>
<number>xvia</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>  6 1 2 per cent. Gold Bonds, <year>1977</year>, 7 per cent. Gold 
Bonds, <year>1980</year> and National Defence Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year>;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>106285</tid>
<number>xvii</number>the amount standing to the credit of an assessee, 
being a salaried employee, in any provident fund 
maintained by his employer to which the Provident Funds 
Act, <year>1925</year>, (19 of <year>1925</year>.) applies or which is a 
recognised provident fund within the meaning of 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> clause (38) of section 2] of the Income- tax Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>76684</tid>
<number>xviia</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the amount standing to the credit of an 
individual in any provident fund set up by the Central 
Government and notified by it in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>519419</tid>
<number>xviii</number>the property received by an assessee from Government 
in pursuance of any gallantry or merit award instituted 
or approved by the Central Government;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1840553</tid>
<number>xix</number>the value of any shares held by the assessee in any 
other company in any case where the assessee is a 
company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1414100</tid>
<number>xx</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the value of any equity shares held by the assessee 
in any company of the type referred to in clause (d) of 
section 45, where such shares form part of the initial 
issue of equity share capital made by the company 
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> after the 31st day of March <year>1964</year>, but before the 1st 
day of June, <year>1971</year>], for a period of five successive 
assessment years commencing with the assessment year 
next
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1963</year>, s. 21, for" twelve year national plan 
savings certificates held by the assessee" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>). The 
words in italics were subs. by Act 11 of <year>1958</year>, s. 14. 
2 The words" held by the assessee" omitted by Act 19 of <year>1968</year>, s. 32 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1965</year>, s. 6, for cl. (xvia). 
4 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 5, for" Chapter IXA" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1968</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>). 
6 Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 70 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). The original cl. 
 (xx) was omitted by Act 20 of <year>1962</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
7 Sub. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32, for" after the 31st day of March, 
<year>1964</year>" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


following the date on which such company commences the 
operations for which it has been established;]


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1447409</tid>
<number>xxi</number>that portion of the net wealth of a company 
established with the object of carrying on an 
industrial undertaking in India within the meaning of 
the Explanation to clause (d) of section 45, as is 
employed by it in a new and separate unit set up after 
the commencement of this Act by way of substantial 
expansion of its undertaking:
Provided that--


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>4765</tid>
<number>a</number>separate accounts are maintained in respect of 
such unit; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1671881</tid>
<number>b</number>the conditions specified in clause (d) of 
section 45 are complied with in relation to the 
establishment of such unit:
Provided further that this exemption shall apply of any such 
company only for a period of five successive assessment 
years commencing with the assessment year next 
following the date on which the company commences 
operations for the establishment of such unit;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1854449</tid>
<number>xxii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any security of the Central Government or a State 
Government[ not being a security referred to in clause 
 (xvi) or clause (xvia)];

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1665553</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>any shares[ not being shares referred to in clause 
 (xx)] held by the assessee in any Indian company where 
the assessee is an individual or a Hindu undivided 
family;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1438552</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>such debentures, issued by any co- operative society 
 (including a co- operative land mortgage bank or a co-  
  operative land development bank) or any other 
institution or authority, as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify 
in this behalf;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1540736</tid>
<number>xxv</number>units in the Unit Trust of India established under the 
Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> (52 of <year>1963</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>937043</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>any deposits with a banking company to which the 
Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, (10 of <year>1949</year>) applies 
 (including any bank or banking institution referred to  
  in section 51 of that Act), or with a co- operative 
society engaged in carrying on the business of banking 
 (including a co- operative land 
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786E</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  mortgage bank or a co- operative land development bank);


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>198457</tid>
<number>xxvii</number>any deposits with a financial corporation which is 
engaged in providing long- term finance for industrial 
development in India and which is approved by the 
Central Government for the purposes of clause (viii) of 
sub- section (1) of section 36 of the Income- tax Act;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>985726</tid>
<number>xxviii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any shares held by the assessee in any co- 
operative society;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>921650</tid>
<number>xxix</number>any deposits with a co- operative society, not being 
deposits referred to in clause (xxvi) or clause (xxx), 
made by a member of the society;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>318462</tid>
<number>xxx</number>any deposits with a co- operative housing society made 
by a member of the society to whom a building or part 
thereof is allotted or leased under a house building 
scheme of the society, where such deposits have been 
made under such scheme.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>69684</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall operate to 
exclude from the net wealth of the assessee any assets referred to in 
clauses (xv), (xvi), (xxii), (xxiii), (xxiv), (xxv), <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (xxvi), 
 (xxvii), (xxviii), and (xxix)][ not being deposits under the Post 
Office Savings bank (Cumulative Time Deposits) Rules, <year>1959</year>], to the 
extent the value thereof exceeds in the aggregate, a sum of one 
hundred and fifty thousand rupees:
Provided that where the assets include any assets referred to in 
clause (xv) or clause (xvi)[ not being deposits under the Post Office 
Savings Bank (Cumulative Time Deposits) Rules, <year>1959</year>] which have been 
held by the assessee continuously from a date prior to the 1st day of 
March, <year>1970</year> and the value of the assets so included exceeds the limit 
of one hundred and fifty thousand rupees by any amount, such limit 
shall be raised by the said amount.]


</section>

<section><tid>518477</tid>
<number>2</number>Wealth- tax shall not be payable by an assessee in respect of 
any deposit made by the assessee with the Government or in any 
security of the Government or of a local authority not specified in 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> clause (xv) or] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> clause (xvi) or clause (xvia)] of sub- section 
 (1)
<pagefootnote><pagenum>786F</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Sub. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32, for (xxvi) and (xxvii)" (w. e. f. 1-  
  4- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1968</year>, s. 32 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Sub. by Act 54 of <year>1962</year>, s. 5, for" clause (xvi)..


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


which the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, exempt from wealth- tax; but the value of any deposit or 
security so exempted shall be included in computing the net wealth of 
the assessee.


</section>

<section><tid>114366</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
wealth- tax shall be payable by an assessee in respect of the assets 
referred to in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clauses (xv), (xvi), (xix), (xxii), (xxiii), (xxiv), 
 (xxv), <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (xxvi), (xxvii), (xxviii), and (xxix)] of sub- section (1) or 
in sub- section (2) for any assessment year unless the assets are held 
by him--

<subsection><tid>1955083</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of shares in a company, from the date on 
which the shares were first issued by the company, or 
for a
<pagefootnote><pagenum>787</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26, for' clause (xvi) and clause 
 (xix)" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 32, for" (xxvi) and (xxvii)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


period of at least six months ending with the relevant 
valuation date, whichever is shorter; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1442541</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of other assets, for a period of at least 
six months ending with the relevant valuation date:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that for the purpose of making any assessment for the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> assessment year] commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1963</year>, the 
provisions of clause (b) shall not apply to ten year defence deposit 
certificates and twelve year national defence certificates held by the 
assessee on the relevant valuation date.]

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Explanation.-- For the purposes of clause (a) or clause (b) of 
this sub- section, in computing the period of six months in relation to 
any asset (not being any share or security held as stock- in- trade for  
  the purposes of the business of the assessee) in a case where such 
asset (hereafter in this Explanation referred to as the relevant  
  asset) was acquired by the assessee by conversion of, or in exchange 
for, or with the proceeds of, or with the money constituting, any 
other asset exempt from wealth- tax under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), there shall be included, if the assessee acquired the 
relevant asset within thirty days after he <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> ceased to own] such 
other asset, so much of the period for which the assessee <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> has owned 
such other asset] as falls within the period of twelve months ending 
with the relevant valuation date.]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747659</tid>
<number> 6</number> Exclusion of assets and debts outside India. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> In computing 
the net wealth of an individual who is not a citizen of India or of an 
individual] or a Hindu undivided family not president in India or 
resident but not ordinarily resident in India, or of a company not 
resident in India during the year ending on the valuation date--
<section><tid>1708640</tid>
<number>i</number>the value of the assets and debts located outside India; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>37610</tid>
<number>ii</number>the value of the assets in India represented by any 
loans or debts owing to the assessee in any case where 
the interest, if any, payable on such loans or debts is 
not to be included in the total income of the assessee 
under <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> section 10] of the Income- tax Act;
shall not be taken into account.

Explanation 1.-- An individual or a Hindu undivided family shall 
be deemed to be not resident in India or resident but not ordinarily 
resident in India during the year ending on the valuation date if in 
respect of that year the individual or the Hindu undivided family, as 
the case may be, is not resident in India or resident but not 
ordinarily resident in India within the meaning of the Income- tax Act.

Explanation 2.-- A company shall be deemed to be resident in India 
during the year ending on the valuation date, if--


<subsection><tid>1541626</tid>
<number>a</number>it is a company formed and registered under the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) or is an existing 
company within the meaning of that Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1305120</tid>
<number>b</number>during that year the control and management of its 
affairs is situated wholly in India.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>788</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 13 of <year>1963</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 5, for" financial year" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1958</year>, s. 14, for certain words (with  
  retrospective effect).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 6, for" sub- section (3) of section 4" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 45 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1973</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1975</year>, s. 27 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>353184</tid>
<number> 7</number> Value of assets how to be determined.
<section><tid>574822</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Subject to any  
rules made in this behalf, the value] of any asset, other than cash, 
for the purposes of this Act, shall be estimated to be the price which 
in the opinion of the Wealth- tax Officer it would fetch if sold in the 
open market on the valuation date.

</section>

<section><tid>1298240</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1173095</tid>
<number>a</number>where the assessee is carrying on a business for which 
accounts are maintained by him regularly, the Wealth- 
tax Officer may, instead of determining separately the 
value of each asset held by the assessee in such 
business, determine the net value of the assets of the 
business as a whole having regard to the balance- sheet 
of such business as on the valuation date and making 
such adjustments therein as <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may be prescribed];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1022154</tid>
<number>b</number>where the assessee carrying on the business, is a 
company not resident in India and a computation in 
accordance with clause (a) cannot be made by reason of 
the absence of any separate balance- sheet drawn up for 
the affairs of such business in India, the Wealth- tax 
Officer may take the net value of the assets of the 
business in India to be that proportion of the net 
value of the assets of the business as a whole wherever 
carried on determined as aforesaid as the income 
arising from the business in India during the year 
ending with the valuation date bears to the aggregate 
income from the business wherever arising during that 
year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1515003</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
where the valuation of any asset is referred by the Wealth- tax officer 
to the Valuation Officer under section 16A, the value of such asset 
shall be estimated to be the price which, in the opinion of the 
Valuation Officer, it would fetch if sold in the open market on <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the 
valuation date, or, in the case of an asset being a house referred to 
in sub- section (4), the valuation date referred to in that sub- 
section]

</section>

<section><tid>1069696</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
value of a house belonging to the assessee and exclusively used by him 
for residential purposes throughout the period of twelve months 
immediately preceding the valuation date may, at the option of the 
assessee, be taken to be the price which, in the opinion of the 
Wealth- tax Officer, it would fetch if sold in the open market on the 
valuation date next following the date on which he became the owner of 
the house, or on the valuation date relevant to the assessment year 
commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1971</year>, whichever valuation date is 
later:
Provided that where more than one house belonging to the assessee 
is exclusively used by him for residential purposes, the provisions of 
this sub- section shall apply only in respect of one of such houses 
which the assessee may, at his option, specify in this behalf in the 
return of net wealth.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section--


<subsection><tid>1995812</tid>
<number>i</number>where the house has been constructed by the assessee, he 
shall be deemed to have become the owner thereof on the date on 
which the construction of such house was completed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>794515</tid>
<number>ii</number>" house" includes a part of a house, being an 
independent residential unit.]
CHAP

WEALTH- TAX AUTHORITIES

CHAPTER III

WEALTH- TAX AUTHORITIES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291184</tid>
<number>8</number>Wealth- tax Officers. Every Income- tax Officer having 
jurisdiction or exercising powers as such under the Income- tax Act in 
respect of any individual, Hindu undivided family or company shall 
perform the functions of a Wealth- tax Officer under this Act in 
respect of such individual, Hindu undivided family or company:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that where two or more Income- tax Officers have 
jurisdiction or exercise powers under the Income- tax Act in respect of 
any individual, Hindu undivided family or company, they shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>789</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 7, for" The value" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" the circumstances of the case may 
require" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34, for Explanation (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, s. 27 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


have concurrent jurisdiction <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and shall perform their functions in 
respect of such individual, Hindu undivided family or company, as the 
case may be, in accordance with such general or special orders in 
writing as the Commissioner or the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner 
authorised by the Commissioner in this behalf may make for the purpose 
of facilitating the performance of such functions.]

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, the Income- tax 
Officer or the Income- tax Officers having jurisdiction in relation to 
a person who is not an assessee within the meaning of the Income- tax 
Act, shall be the Income- tax Officer or Income- tax Officers in respect 
of the area in which that person resides.]



</article>



<article><tid>1401381</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power of Commissioner respecting specified areas, cases or 
persons.
<section><tid>1303227</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may, by general or special order in  
writing, direct that such of the functions assigned to the Wealth- tax 
Officer by or under this Act as are specified in any such order may, 
in respect of any specified area or specified cases or classes of 
cases or specified persons or classes of persons, be performed by an 
Inspector of Wealth- tax or any member of the ministerial staff, 
appointed to work under the Commissioner or any other Wealth- tax 
authority subordinate to him, and specified in such order, subject to 
such conditions, restrictions or limitations as may be specified 
therein:
Provided that the Commissioner shall not, unless he is authorised 
in this behalf by the Board by general or special order in writing, 
make an order under this sub- section in relation to the functions of a 
Wealth- tax Officer mentioned in the following provisions of this Act, 
namely, sections 15B, 16, 17, 18, 20, 22, 24, 32, 37 and 37A.


</section>

<section><tid>1704250</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of any case or person or proceeding under 
this Act in respect of which or whom any order under sub- section (1) 
applies, references in this Act or in any rule made hereunder to the 
Wealth- tax Officer shall be deemed to include references to the 
Inspector of Wealth- tax or the member of the ministerial staff 
specified in such order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>556531</tid>
<number> 8AA</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Concurrent jurisdiction of Inspecting Assistant.
<section><tid>36532</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Commissioner may, by general or special order in writing, direct that 
all or any of the powers or functions conferred on or assigned to the 
Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers by or under this Act in 
respect of any area, or cases or classes of cases, or persons or 
classes of persons shall be exercised or performed concurrently by the 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner.
Commissioner and Wealth- tax Officer.


</section>

<section><tid>524581</tid>
<number>2</number>Where under sub- section (1), an Inspecting Assistant 
Commissioner exercises concurrent jurisdiction with one or more 
Wealth- tax Officers in respect of any area, cases or classes of cases, 
or persons or classes of persons, the Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax 
Officers shall exercise the powers and perform the functions under 
this Act in relation thereto as the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner 
may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>322400</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in sub- section (2) of section 13, every Wealth- tax Officer 
shall also observe and follow such instructions as may be issued to 
him for his guidance by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within 
whose jurisdiction he performs his functions in relation to any 
particular proceeding or the initiation of any proceeding under this 
Act.
Provided that no instructions which are prejudicial to the 
assesee shall be issued before an opportunity is given by the 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner to the assessee to be heard.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section, no 
instruction as to the lines on which an investigation connected with 
the assesment should be made shall be deemed to be an instruction 
prejudcial to the assessee.


</section>

<section><tid>31288</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an order is made under sub- section (1) and the 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner exercises the powers or performs the 
functions of a Wealth- tax Officer in respect of any case or person or 
proceeding, references in this Act or in any rule made thereunder to 
the Wealth- tax Officer and the Appellate Assistant Commissioner shall 
be construed as references to the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner 
and the Commissioner respectively and, accordingly,--

<subsection><tid>357163</tid>
<number>i</number>any provision of this Act requiring approval or sanction 
of the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner shall not 
apply;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1778677</tid>
<number>ii</number>any appeal which would otherwise have lain to the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner shall lie to the 
Commissioner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1653646</tid>
<number>iii</number>any appeal which would have lain from an order of the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner to the Appellate 
Tribunal shall lie from the order of the Commissioner.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>106463</tid>
<number> 8B</number> Power to transfer cases. <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>
<section><tid>97488</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may, after  
giving the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the 
matter, wherever it is possible to do so, and after recording his 
reasons for doing so, transfer any case from one or more of the 
following officers subordinate to him, namely:--

<subsection><tid>945140</tid>
<number>a</number>any Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1772550</tid>
<number>b</number>any Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers having 
concurrent jurisidiction with the Inspecting Assistant 
Commissioner,
to any other Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers (whether with  
or without concurrent jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant 
  Commissioner) also subordinate to him and the Board any similarly 
transfer any case from--


<subsubsection><tid>1190795</tid>
<number>i</number>any Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>127061</tid>
<number>ii</number>any Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers having 
concurrent jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant 
Commissioner,
to any other Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers (whether with  
or without concurrent jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant 
  Commissioner):

Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to 
require any such opportunity to be given where a transfer is from any 
Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers (whether with or without  
  concurrent jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner) to 
any other Wealth- tax Officer or Wealth- tax Officers (whether with or  
without concurrent jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant 
  Commissioner) and the offices of all such officers are situated in the 
same city, locality or place:

Provided further that--


<subsubsubsection><tid>1668963</tid>
<number>a</number>where any case has been transferred from any Wealth- tax 
Officer or Wealth- tax Officers to two or more Wealth- tax Officers to 
whom the case is so transferred shall have concurrent jurisdiction 
over such case and shall perform their functions in accordance with 
such general or special orders in writing as the Board or the 
Commissioner or the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner authorised by 
the Commissioner in this behalf, may make for the purpose of 
facilitating the performance of such functions;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>364042</tid>
<number>b</number>where any case has been transferred from any Wealth- tax 
Officer or Wealth- tax Officers (whether with or without concurrent  
  jurisdiction with the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner) to two or 
more Wealth- tax Officers with concurrent jurisdiction with the 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner, the officers (including the  
  Inspecting Assistant Commissioner) to whom the case is so transferred 
shall have concurrent jurisdiction over such case and shall perform 
their functions in accordance with such general or special orders in 
writing as the Board or the Commissioner may make for the purpose of 
facilitating the performance of such functions and the Wealth- tax 
Officers shall perform their functions also in accordance with such 
orders or directions as the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner may make 
under section 8 or, as the case may be, under sub- section (2) of 
section 8AA.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>790</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34, for s. 8A (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 84 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 85, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 86, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1851506</tid>
<number>2</number>The transfer of a case under sub- section (1) may be made at 
any stage of the proceedings, and shall not render necessary the 
reissue of any notice already issued by the Wealth- tax Officer or 
Wealth- tax Officers from whom the case is transferred.
Explanation.-- In this section and in section 8A, the word" case", 
in relation to any person whose name is specified in any order made 
thereunder, means all proceedings under this Act in respect of any 
year which may be pending on the date of such order, or which may have 
been completed on or before such date, and includes also all 
proceedings under this Act which may be commenced after the date of 
such order in respect of any year.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378734</tid>
<number>9</number>Appellate Assistant Commissioners of Wealth- tax. The Board may 
empower as many persons as it thinks fit to exercise under this Act 
the functions of an Appellate Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax, 
and on being so empowered the Appellate Assistant Commissioners shall 
perform their functions in respect of such areas or such persons or 
such classes of persons as the Board may direct, and where such 
directions have assigned to two or more Appellate Assistant 
Commissioners the same area or the same persons or the same classes of 
persons they shall perform their functions in accordance with such 
orders as the Board may make for the distribution and allocation of 
the work to be performed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>791</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1519846</tid>
<number>10</number>Commissioners of Wealth- tax. The Board may empower as many 
persons as it thinks fit to exercise under this Act the functions of a 
Commissioner of Wealth- tax, and on being so empowered the 
Commissioners of Wealth- tax shall perform their functions in respect 
of such areas or such persons or such classes of persons as the Board 
may direct and where such directions have assigned to two or more 
Commissioners the same area or the same persons or the same classes of 
persons they shall have concurrent jurisdiction <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and shall perform 
such functions in relation to the said area or persons or classes of 
persons as the Board may, by general or special order in writing, 
specify, for the distribution and allocation of the work to be 
performed].


</article>



<article><tid>112304</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Directors of Inspection.
<section><tid>1114436</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may empower as  
many persons as it thinks fit to exercise under this Act the functions 
of a Director of Inspection.

</section>

<section><tid>1032204</tid>
<number>2</number>A Director of Inspection shall perform such functions of any 
other Wealth- tax authority as may be assigned to him by the Board.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>893810</tid>
<number>11</number>Inspecting Assistant Commissioners of Wealth- tax. The 
Commissioner of Wealth- tax may empower as many persons as he thinks 
fit to exercise under this Act the functions of an Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax, and on being so empowered the 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioners of Wealth- tax shall perform their 
functions in respect of such areas or such persons or such classes of 
persons as the Commissioner may direct, and where such directions have 
assigned to two or more Inspecting Assistant Commissioners the same 
area or the same persons or the same classes of persons <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> they shall 
have concurrent jurisdiction and shall perform such functions in 
respect of the said areas or persons or classes of persons as the 
Commissioner may, by general or special order in writing, specify, for 
the distribution and allocation of the work to be performed].



<pagefootnote><pagenum>792</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1967</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 11, ibid., for s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34, for the former section (w. e. f. 1-  
  4- <year>1967</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




<pagefootnote><pagenum>11AA</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>







</article>



<article><tid>770381</tid>
<number> 11B</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Wealth- tax Officer competent to perform any function or 
functions. In respect of any function to be performed by a Wealth- tax 
Officer under any provision of this Act, in relation to any assessee, 
the Wealth- tax Officer referred to therein shall,--
<section><tid>1067009</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where only one Wealth- tax Officer has 
jurisdiction over such assessee, be such Wealth- tax 
Officer;

</section>

<section><tid>273786</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where two or more Wealth- tax Officers have 
concurrent jurisdiction over such assessee, be the 
Wealth- tax Officer empowered to perform such function 
by the Board, or, as the case may be, the Wealth- tax 
Officer to whom such function has been assigned by an 
order of the Commissioner or of the Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax authorised by the 
Commissioner in this behalf.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1132536</tid>
<number> 12</number> Control of Wealth- tax authorities.
<section><tid>1010983</tid>
<number>1</number>Inspecting Assistant  
Commissioners shall be subordinate to the Commissioner within whose 
jurisdiction they perform their functions and also to the Director of 
Inspection.

</section>

<section><tid>1180338</tid>
<number>2</number>Wealth- tax Officers shall be subordinate to the Commissioner 
and the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within whose jurisdiction 
they perform their functions and also to the Director of Inspection.

</section>

<section><tid>253168</tid>
<number>3</number>Inspectors of Wealth- tax shall be subordinate to the Wealth- 
tax Officer or other Wealth- tax authority under whom they are 
empowered to work and to any other Wealth- tax authority to whom the 
said officer or other authority is subordinate.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>793</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1967</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Explanation.-- For the purposes of sub- section (1)," Director of 
Inspection" does not include a Deputy Director of Inspection or an 
Assistant Director of Inspection; and for the purposes of sub- section 
 (2) of this section and sub- section (2) of section 13," Director of 
Inspection" does not include an Assistant Director of Inspection.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1153547</tid>
<number> 13</number> Wealth- tax authorities to follow orders, etc., of the Board.

<section><tid>1246254</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] All officers and other persons employed in the execution of  
this Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and 
directions of the Board:
Provided that no orders, instructions or directions shall be 
given by the Board so as to interfere with the discretion of the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax in the exercise of his 
appellate function.


</section>

<section><tid>747217</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every Wealth- tax Officer employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow such instructions as may be issued to him 
for his guidance by the Director of Inspection or by the Commissioner 
or by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within whose jurisdiction 
he performs his functions.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664297</tid>
<number>13A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Powers of Director of Inspection, Commissioner and 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner to make enquiries. The Director of 
Inspection, the Commissioner of Wealth- tax and the Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner of Wealth- tax shall be competent to make any 
enquiry under this Act, and for this purpose shall have all the powers 
that a Wealth- tax Officer has under this Act in relation to the making 
of enquiries.]
CHAP

ASSESSMENT

CHAPTER IV

ASSESSMENT



</article>



<article><tid>772462</tid>
<number> 14</number> Return of wealth. <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>
<section><tid>716324</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person, if his net wealth or  
the net wealth of any other person in respect of which he is 
assessable under this Act on the valuation date was of such an amount 
as to render him liable to wealth- tax under this Act, shall, before 
the 30th day of June of the corresponding assessment year, furnish to 
the Wealth- tax Officer a return in the prescribed form and verified in 
the prescribed manner setting forth the net wealth as on that 
valuation date.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>794</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 13 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 46 of 
<year>1964</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 13, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that in the case of a person whose net wealth or the 
net wealth of any other person in respect of which he is assessable 
under this Act includes the value of any assets held in a business or 
profession and the time (whether fixed originally or on extension) for 
furnishing the return of his total income or, as the case may be, of 
the total income of the other person aforesaid for the said assessment 
year under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) of 
section 139 of the Income- tax Act, expires on or after the 30th day of 
June aforesaid, the return in respect of such net wealth for the 
assessment year may be furnished before the expiry of the time for 
furnishing such return of income.]


</section>

<section><tid>1460230</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Wealth- tax Officer is of the opinion that <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any 
person is assessable under this Act, whether in respect of his net 
wealth or the net wealth of any other person,] then, notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub- section (1), he may serve a notice upon such 
person requiring him to furnish within such period, not being less 
than thirty days, as may be specified in the notice, a return in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, setting 
forth (along with such other particulars as may be required by the  
  notice)], the net wealth of such person as on the valuation date 
mentioned in the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>1868289</tid>
<number>3</number>The Wealth- tax Officer may, if he is satisfied that it is 
necessary so to do, extend the date for the delivery of the return 
under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1821213</tid>
<number>15</number>Return after due date and amendment of return. If any person 
has not furnished a return within the time allowed under section 14, 
or having furnished a return under that section discovers any omission 
or a wrong statement therein, he may furnish a return or a revised 
return, as the case may be, at any time before the assessment is made.


</article>



<article><tid>1521813</tid>
<number> 15A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Return by whom to be signed. The return made under 
section 14 or section 15 shall be signed and verified--
<section><tid>214565</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an individual, by the individual himself; 
where the individual is absent from India, by the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>795</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1970</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 14, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 58 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3 and Sch II, for certain words. 
4 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


individual concerned or by some person duly authorised 
by him in this behalf; where the individual is mentally 
incapacitated from attending to his affairs, by his 
guardian or any other person competent to act on his 
behalf; and where for any other reason it is impossible 
for the individual to sign the return, by any person 
competent to act on his behalf;


</section>

<section><tid>1681848</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a Hindu undivided family, by the karta, 
and, where the karta is absent from India or is 
mentally incapacitated from attending to his affairs, 
by any other adult member of such family; and

</section>

<section><tid>1293257</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a company, by the principal officer 
thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>103260</tid>
<number> 15B</number> Self assessment.
<section><tid>1760346</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a return has been furnished under  
section 14 or section 15 and the tax payable on the basis of that 
return exceeds five hundred rupees, the assessee shall pay the tax so 
payable within thirty days of furnishing the return.

</section>

<section><tid>1062641</tid>
<number>2</number>After a provisional assessment under section 15C or a regular 
assessment under section 16 has been made, any amount paid under sub- 
section (1) shall be deemed to have been paid towards the provisional 
assessment or regular assessment, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1276274</tid>
<number>3</number>If any assessee fails to pay the tax or any part thereof in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1), he shall, unless a 
provisional assessment under section 15C or a regular assessment under 
section 16 has been made before the expiry of thirty days referred to 
in that sub- section, be liable, by way of penalty, to pay such amount 
as the Wealth- tax Officer may direct, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and in the case of a 
continuing failure, such further amount or amounts as the Wealth- tax 
Officer may from time to time direct, so, however, that the total 
amount of penalty does not exceed fifty per cent. of the amount of 
such tax or part, as the case may be:]
Provided that before levying any such penalty, the assessee shall 
be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1899341</tid>
<number> 15C</number> Provisional assessment.
<section><tid>1064573</tid>
<number>1</number>The Wealth- tax Officer may, at  
any time after the receipt of a return made under section 14 or 
section 15, proceed to make, in a summary manner, a provisional 
assessment of the tax payable by the assessee, on the basis of his 
return and the accounts and documents, if any, accompanying it.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>796</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 60 for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>595084</tid>
<number>2</number>After a regular assessment has been made, any amount paid 
towards the provisional assessment made under sub- section (1), shall 
be deemed to have been paid towards the regular assessment; and where 
the amount paid towards the provisional assessment exceeds the amount 
payable under the regular assessment, the excess shall be refunded to 
the assessee.

</section>

<section><tid>1160087</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing done or suffered by reason or in consequence of any 
provisional assessment made under this section shall prejudice the 
determination, on the merits, of any issue which may arise in the 
course of the regular assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1521428</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be no right of appeal against a provisional 
assessment made under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1773969</tid>
<number>5</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
provisions of section 31 excepting sub- section (6) thereof, and 
section 32 shall apply in relation to any tax payable in pursuance of 
a provisional assessment made under this section as if it were a 
regular assessment under section 16.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1929648</tid>
<number> 16</number> Assessment.
<section><tid>557313</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Wealth- tax Officer is satisfied  
without requiring the presence of the assessee or production by him of 
any evidence that a return made under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 14 or section 15 is 
correct and complete], he shall assess the net wealth of the assessee 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and determine the amount of wealth- tax payable by him or the amount 
refundable to him on the basis of such return].

</section>

<section><tid>1243785</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Wealth- tax Officer is not so satisfied, he shall serve 
a notice on the assessee either to attend in person at his office on a 
date to be specified in the notice or to produce or cause to be 
produced on that date any evidence on which the assessee may rely in 
support of his return.

</section>

<section><tid>1312720</tid>
<number>3</number>The Wealth- tax Officer, after hearing such evidence as the 
person may produce and such other evidence as he may require on any 
specified points <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and after taking into account all relevant 
material which the Wealth- tax Officer has gathered], shall, by order 
in writing, assess the net wealth of the assessee <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and determine the 
amount of wealth- tax payable by him or the amount refundable to him on 
the basis of such assessment].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>797</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 16, for" section 14 is complete" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 16, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>940250</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of making an assessment under this Act the 
Wealth- tax Officer may serve, on any person who has made a return 
under sub- section (1) of section 14 or upon whom a notice has been 
served under sub- section (2) of that section <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or who has made a 
return under section 15], a notice requiring him to produce or cause 
to be produced on a date specified in the notice such accounts, 
records or other documents as the Wealth- tax Officer may require.

</section>

<section><tid>72079</tid>
<number>5</number>If any person fails to make a return in response to any 
notice under sub- section (2) of section 14, or fails to comply with 
the terms of any notice issued under sub- section (2) or sub- section 
 (4), the Wealth- tax Officer <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> after taking into account all relevant 
material which he has gathered, shall estimate the net wealth to the 
best of his judgment and determine the amount of wealth- tax payable by 
the person or the amount refundable to him on the basis of such 
assessment].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>338600</tid>
<number> 17</number> Wealth escaping assessment. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1372</tid>
<number>1</number>] If the Wealth- tax  
Officer--

<subsection><tid>720441</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> has reason to believe that by reason of the omission 
or failure on the part of any person to make a return 
under section 14 of his net wealth or the net wealth of 
any other person in respect of which he is assessable 
under this Act for any assessment year or to disclose 
fully and truly all material facts necessary for 
assessment of his net wealth or the net wealth of such 
other person for that year, the net wealth chargeable 
to tax has escaped assessment for that year, whether by 
reason of under- assessment or assessment at too low a 
rate or otherwise; or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48077</tid>
<number>b</number>has, in consequence of any information in his 
possession, reason to believe, notwithstanding that 
there has been no such omission or failure as is 
referred to in clause (a), that the net wealth 
chargeable to tax has escaped assessment for any year, 
whether by reason of under- assessment or assessment at 
too low a rate or otherwise;
he may, in cases falling under clause (a) at any time within eight 
years and in cases falling under clause (b) at any time within four

<pagefootnote><pagenum>798</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 S. 17 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by s. 17, 
ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 17, ibid., for cl. (a)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


years of the end of that assessment year, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> serve on such person] a 
notice containing all or any of the requirements which may be included 
in a notice under sub- section (2) of section 14, and may proceed to 
assess or re- assess such net wealth, and the provisions of this Act 
shall, so far as may be, apply as if the notice had issued under that 
sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1251240</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Nothing contained in this section limiting the time within 
which any proceeding for assessment or re- assessment may be commenced, 
shall apply to an assessment or re- assessment to be made on such 
person in consequence of or to give effect to any finding or direction 
contained in an order under section 23, 24, 25, 27 or 29:
Provided that the provisions of this sub- section shall not apply 
in any case where any such assessment or re- assessment relates to an 
assessment year in respect of which an assessment or re- assessment 
could not have been made at the time the order which was the subject 
matter of the appeal, reference or revision, as the case may be, was 
made by reason of any provision limiting the time within which any 
action for assessment or re- assessment may be taken.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>120967</tid>
<number> 18</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Penalty for failure to furnish returns, to comply with 
notices and concealment of assets, etc.
<section><tid>1439512</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Wealth- tax Officer,  
Appellate Assistant Commissioner, Commissioner or Appellate Tribunal 
in the course of any proceedings under this Act is satisfied that any 
person--

<subsection><tid>1406037</tid>
<number>a</number>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish the 
return which he is required to furnish under sub- 
section (1) of section 14 or by notice given under sub- 
section (2) of section 14 or section 17, or has without 
reasonable cause failed to furnish it within the time 
allowed and in the manner required by sub- section (1) 
of section 14 or by such notice, as the case may be; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>228354</tid>
<number>b</number>has without reasonable cause failed to comply with a 
notice under sub- section (2) or sub- section (4) of 
section 16; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1780332</tid>
<number>c</number>has concealed the particulars of any assets or furnished 
inaccurate particulars of any assets or debts;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>799</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 17, for" serve on the assessee" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 17, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 18, ibid., for s. 18 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


he or it may, by order in writing, direct that such person shall pay 
by way of penalty--


<subsubsection><tid>819918</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the cases referred to in clause (a), in addition 
to the amount of wealth- tax, if any, payable by him, a 
sum, for every month during which the default 
continued, equal to one- half per cent. of--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1038643</tid>
<number>A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the net wealth assessed under section 16 as 
reduced by the amount specified in sub- section (1A), or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1491284</tid>
<number>B</number>the net wealth assessed under section 17, 
where assessment has been made under that section, as 
reduced by--

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1135106</tid>
<number>1</number>the net wealth, if any, assessed 
previously under section 16 or section 17, or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>285430</tid>
<number>2</number>the amount specified in sub- section (1A), 
whichever is greater,]
but not exceeding, in the aggregate, an amount equal to 
the net wealth assessed under section 16, or, as the 
case may be, the net wealth assessed under section 17, 
as reduced in either case in the manner aforesaid;


</subsubsubsubsection>

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>538099</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the cases referred to in clause (b), in addition to 
the amount of wealth- tax payable by him, a sum which 
shall not be less than one per cent. of the assessed 
net wealth but which shall not exceed the amount of the 
assessed net wealth.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of clause (ii)," assessed net 
wealth" shall be taken to be the net wealth assessed 
under section 16 as reduced by the net wealth declared 
in the return, if any, furnished by such person, or, as 
the case may be, the net wealth assessed under section 
 17 as reduced by--


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>819918</tid>
<number>i</number>the net wealth, if any, assessed 
previously under section 16 or section 17, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>538099</tid>
<number>ii</number>the net wealth declared in the return, 
if any, furnished by such person under section 17, 
whichever is greater;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>800</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 14 of <year>1969</year>, s. 24, for sub- clause (i) and (ii) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1969</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 33, for item (A)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>315348</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the cases referred to in clause (c), in addition 
to any wealth- tax payable by him, a sum which shall not 
be less than, but which shall not exceed twice, the 
amount representing the value of any assets in respect 
of which the particulars have been concealed or any 
assets or debts in respect of which inaccurate 
particulars have been furnished.]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Explanation 1.-- Where,--


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>819918</tid>
<number>i</number>the value of any asset returned by any person is less 
than seventy- five per cent. of the value of such asset 
as determined in an assessment under section 16 or 
section 17 (the value so assessed being referred to  
hereafter in this Explanation as the correct value of 
  the asset), or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>538099</tid>
<number>ii</number>the value of any debt returned by any person exceeds 
the value of such debt as determined in an assessment 
under section 16 or section 17 by more than twenty- five 
per cent. of the value so assessed (the value so  
assessed being referred to hereafter in this 
  Explanation as the correct value of the debt), or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>315348</tid>
<number>iii</number>the net wealth returned by any person is less than 
seventy- five per cent. of the net wealth as assessed 
under section 16 or section 17 (the net wealth so  
assessed being referred to hereafter in this 
  Explanation as the correct net wealth),
then, such person shall, unless he proves that the failure to return 
the correct value of the asset or, as the case may be, the correct 
value of the debt or the correct net wealth did not arise from any 
fraud or any gross or wilful neglect on his part, be deemed to have 
concealed the particulars of assets or furnished inaccurate 
particulars of assets or debts for the purposes of clause (c) of this 
sub- section.

Explanation 2.-- For the purposes of clause (iii),--


<subsubsubsection><tid>1262364</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount representing the value of any assets in 
respect of which the particulars have been concealed or 
any assets in respect of which inaccurate particulars 
have been furnished, shall be the value of such assets 
determined for the purposes of this Act as reduced by 
the value thereof, if any, declared in the return made 
under section 14 or section 15;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>800A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1968</year>, s. 32, for clause (iii)  (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1968</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 32, ibid., for Explanation (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1968</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1205739</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount representing the value of any debts in 
respect of which inaccurate particulars have been 
furnished, shall be the amount by which the value of 
such debts declared in the return made under section 14 
or section 15 exceeds the value thereof determined for 
the purposes of this Act.]

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>673790</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The amount referred to in sub- clause (A) and sub- clause 
 (B)  (2) of clause (i) of sub- section (1) shall be,--

<subsection><tid>1473267</tid>
<number>a</number>in the cause of an individual, Rs. 1, 00, 000;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>41534</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a Hindu undivided family, Rs. 2, 00, 000; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951967</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a company, Rs. 5, 00, 000.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1019081</tid>
<number>2</number>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) unless the 
person concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.

</section>

<section><tid>1987093</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i) or 
clause (iii) of sub- section (1), the Commissioner may, in his 
discretion,--

<subsection><tid>1212125</tid>
<number>i</number>reduce or waive the amount of minimum penalty imposable 
on a person under clause (i) of sub- section (1) for failure, 
without reasonable cause, to furnish the return of net wealth 
which such person was required to furnish under sub- section (1) 
of section 14, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>322169</tid>
<number>ii</number>reduce or waive the amount of minimum penalty imposable 
on a person under clause (iii) of sub- section (1),
if he is satisfied that such person--


<subsubsection><tid>174375</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case referred to in clause (i) of this sub- 
section has, prior to the issue of notice to him under 
sub- section (2) of section 14, voluntarily and in good 
faith, made full disclosure of his net wealth; and in 
the case referred to in clause (ii) of this sub- section 
has, prior to the detection by the Wealth- tax Officer 
of the concealment of particulars of assets or of the 
inaccuracy of particulars furnished in respect of the 
assets or debts in respect of which the penalty is 
imposable, voluntarily and in good faith, made full and 
true disclosure of such particulars;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>800B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 33 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1965</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 11- 9- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>314384</tid>
<number>b</number>has co- operated in any enquiry relating to the 
assessment of the wealth represented by such assets; 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>851885</tid>
<number>c</number>has either paid or made satisfactory arrangements for 
payment of any tax or interest payable in consequence 
of an order passed under this Act in respect of the 
relevant assessment year:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that if in a case falling under clause (c) of sub- 
section (1) the amount in respect of which penalty is imposable for 
the relevant assessment year, or where such disclosure relates to more 
than one assessment year, such amount for any one of the relevant 
assessment years, exceeds five hundred thousand rupees, no order 
reducing or waiving the penalty shall be made by the Commissioner 
unless the previous approval of the Board has been obtained.]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1090365</tid>
<number>2B</number>An order under sub- section (2A) shall be final and shall not 
be called in question before any court of law or any other authority.]

</section>

<section><tid>1868265</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (iii) of sub- 
section (1), if in a case falling under clause (c) of that sub- 
section, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the amount (as determined by the Wealth- tax Officer on  
  assessment) in respect of which penalty is imposable under clause (c) 
of sub- section (1) exceeds a sum of twenty- five thousand rupees], the 
Wealth- tax Officer shall refer the case to the Inspecting Assistant 
Commissioner who shall, for the purpose, have all the powers conferred 
under this section for the imposition of penalty.

</section>

<section><tid>503445</tid>
<number>4</number>An Appellate Assistant Commissioner, a Commissioner or the 
Appellate Tribunal on making an order under this section imposing a 
penalty, shall forthwith send a copy of the same to the Wealth- tax 
Officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1589977</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> No order imposing a penalty under this section shall be 
passed--

<subsection><tid>841600</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where the assessment to which the proceedings 
for imposition of penalty relate is the subject- matter 
of an appeal to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner 
under section 23 or an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal
<pagefootnote><pagenum>800C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 61 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 61, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 61, ibid., for sub- section (5)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


under sub- section (2) of section 24, after the 
expiration of a period of--


<subsubsection><tid>1538313</tid>
<number>i</number>two years from the end of the financial 
year in which the proceedings, in the course of 
which action for imposition of penalty has been 
initiated, are completed, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1913435</tid>
<number>ii</number>six months from the end of the month in 
which the order of the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner or, as the case may be, the Appellate 
Tribunal is received by the Commissioner,
whichever period expires later;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>594220</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, after the expiration of two years 
from the end of the financial year in which the 
proceedings, in the course of which action for 
imposition of penalty has been initiated, are 
completed.
Explanation.-- In computing the period of limitation for the 
purposes of this section, the time taken in giving an opportunity to 
the assessee to be reheard under the proviso to section 39 and any 
period during which a proceeding under this section for the levy of 
penalty is stayed by an order or injunction of any court shall be 
excluded.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>801</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

LIABILITY TO ASSESSMENT IN SPECIAL CASES

CHAPTER V

LIABILITY TO ASSESSMENT IN SPECIAL CASES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1483873</tid>
<number> 19</number> Tax of deceased person payable by legal representative.
<section><tid>1858732</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a person dies, his executor, administrator or other legal 
representative shall be liable to pay out of the estate of the 
deceased person, to the extent to which the estate is capable of 
meeting the charge, the wealth- tax assessed as payable by such person, 
or any sum, which would have been payable by him under this Act if he 
had not died.

</section>

<section><tid>1847331</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person dies without having furnished a return under 
the provisions of section 14 or after having furnished a return which 
the Wealth- tax Officer has reason to believe to be incorrect or 
incomplete, the Wealth- tax Officer may make an assessment of the net 
wealth of such person and determine the wealth- tax payable by the 
person on the basis of such assessment, and for this purpose may, by 
the issue of the appropriate notice which would have had to be served 
upon the deceased person if he had survived, require from the 
executor, administrator or other legal representative of the deceased 
person any accounts, documents or other evidence which might under the 
provisions of section 16 have been required from the deceased person.

</section>

<section><tid>1260433</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sections 14, 15 and 17 shall apply to an 
executor, administrator or other legal representative as they apply to 
any person referred to in those sections.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>487101</tid>
<number> 19A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Assessment in the case of executors.
<section><tid>1982100</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject as  
hereinafter provided, the net wealth of the estate of a deceased 
person shall be chargeable to tax in the hands of the executor or 
executors.

</section>

<section><tid>223570</tid>
<number>2</number>The executor or executors shall for the purposes of this Act 
be treated as an individual.

</section>

<section><tid>899379</tid>
<number>3</number>The status of the executor or executors shall for the 
purposes of this Act as regards residence and citizenship be the same 
as that of the deceased on the valuation date immediately preceding 
his death.

</section>

<section><tid>1815903</tid>
<number>4</number>The assessment of an executor under this section shall be 
made separately from any assessment that may be made on him in respect 
of his own net wealth or on the net wealth of the deceased under 
section 19.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>802</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1964</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>494588</tid>
<number>5</number>Separate assessments shall be made under this section in 
respect of the net wealth as on each valuation date as is included in 
the period from the date of the death of the deceased to the date of 
complete distribution to the beneficiaries of the estate according to 
their several interests.

</section>

<section><tid>1763531</tid>
<number>6</number>In computing the net wealth on any valuation date under this 
section, any assets of the estate distributed to, or applied to the 
benefit of, any specific legatee of the estate prior to that valuation 
date shall be excluded, but the assets so excluded shall, to the 
extent such asset are held by the legatee on any valuation date, be 
included in the net wealth of such specific legatee on that valuation 
date.
Explanation.-- In this section," executor" includes an 
administrator or other person administering the estate of a deceased 
person.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248615</tid>
<number> 20</number> Assessment after partition of a Hindu undivided family.
<section><tid>555131</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where, at the time of making an assessment, it is brought to the 
notice of the Wealth- tax Officer that a partition has taken place 
among the members of a Hindu undivided family, and the Wealth- tax 
Officer, after inquiry, is satisfied that the joint family property 
has been partitioned as a whole among the various members or groups of 
members in definite portions, he shall record an order to that effect 
and shall make assessments on the net wealth of the undivided family 
as such for the assessment year or years, including the year relevant 
to the previous year in which the partition has taken place, if the 
partition has taken place on the last day of the previous year and 
each member or group of members shall be liable jointly and severally 
for the tax assessed on the net wealth of the joint family as such.

</section>

<section><tid>1250693</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Wealth- tax Officer is not so satisfied, he may, by 
order, declare that such family shall be deemed for the purposes of 
this Act to continue to be a Hindu undivided family liable to be 
assessed as such.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>310371</tid>
<number> 21</number> Assessment when assets are held by courts of wards, 
administrators- general, etc.
<section><tid>1351524</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of assets chargeable to  
tax under this Act which are held by a court of wards or an 
administrator- general or an official trustee or any receiver or 
manager or any other person, by whatever name called, appointed under 
any order of a court to manage property on behalf of another, or any 
trustee appointed under a trust declared by a duly executed instrument 
in writing, whether testamentary or otherwise (including a trustee  
  under a valid deed of wakf), the wealth- tax shall be levied upon and 
recoverable from the court of wards, administrator- general, official 
trustee, receiver,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>803</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

manager or trustee, as the case may be, in the like manner and to the 
same extent as it would be leviable upon and recoverable from the 
person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> on whose behalf or for whose benefit] the assets are held, 
and the provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1647154</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall prevent either the 
direct assessment of the person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> on whose behalf or for whose 
benefit] the assets above referred to are held, or the recovery from 
such person of the tax payable in respect of such assets.

</section>

<section><tid>600079</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the guardian or trustee of any person being a minor, 
lunatic or idiot <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> holds any assets <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> on behalf or for the benefit 
of such beneficiary,] the tax under this Act shall be levied upon and 
recoverable from such guardian or trustee, as the case may be, in the 
like manner and to the same extent as it would be leviable upon and 
recoverable from any such beneficiary if of full age or sound mind and 
in direct ownership of such assets.

</section>

<section><tid>324921</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where 
the shares of the persons on whose behalf or for whose benefit any 
such assets are held are indeterminate or unknown, the wealth- tax 
shall be levied upon and recovered from the court of wards, 
administrator- general, official trustee, receiver, manager, or other 
person aforesaid as if the persons on whose behalf or for whose 
benefit the assets are held were an individual who is a citizen of 
India and resident in India for the purposes of this Act, and--

<subsection><tid>209504</tid>
<number>a</number>at the rates specified in Part I of the Schedule <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1805579</tid>
<number>b</number>at the rate of one and one- half per cent.,
whichever course would be more beneficial to the revenue:

Provided that in a case where--


<subsubsection><tid>399648</tid>
<number>i</number>such assets are held under a trust declared by will; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>606879</tid>
<number>ii</number>such assets are held under a trust created before the 
 1st day of March, <year>1970</year>, by a non- testamentary 
instrument and the Wealth- tax Officer is satisfied, 
having regard to all the circumstances existing at the 
relevant time, that the trust was created bona fide 
exclusively
<pagefootnote><pagenum>804</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 20, for" on whose behalf" (w. e. f. 1-  
  4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Certain words omitted by s. 20, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 20, ibid., for" on behalf of such beneficiary" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 26, for sub- section (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1971</year>). 
5 The words" in the case of an individual" omitted by Act 32 of 
<year>1971</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for the benefit of the relatives of the settlor or 
where the settlor is a Hindu undivided family, 
exclusively for the benefit of the members of such 
family, in circumstances where such relatives or 
members were mainly dependent on the settlor for their 
support and maintenance; or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>716561</tid>
<number>iii</number>such assets are held by the trustees on behalf of a 
provident fund, superannuation fund, gratuity fund, 
pension fund or any other fund created bona fide by a 
person carrying on a business or profession exclusively 
for the benefit of persons employed in such business or 
profession,
wealth- tax shall be charged at the rates specified in Part I of the 
[ Schedule <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.]

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Explanation.-- Notwithstanding anything contained in section 5, 
in computing the net wealth for the purposes of this sub- section in 
any case, not being a case referred to in the proviso, any assets 
referred to in clauses (xv), (xvi), (xxii), (xxiii), (xxiv), (xxv), 
 (xxvi), (xxvii), (xxviii) and (xxix) of sub- section (1) of that 
section shall not be excluded.]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>934605</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Any person who pays any sum by virtue of the provisions of 
this section in respect of the net wealth of any beneficiary, shall be 
entitled to recover the sum so paid from such beneficiary, and may 
retain out of any assets that he may hold on behalf or for the benefit 
of such beneficiary, an amount equal to the sum so paid.
Explanation.-- In this section, the term" beneficiary" means any 
person including a minor, lunatic or idiot on whose behalf or for 
whose benefit assets are held by any other person.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904648</tid>
<number> 22</number> Assessment of persons residing Outside India.
<section><tid>404124</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
person liable to tax under this Act resides outside India, the tax may 
be levied upon and recovered from his agent, and the agent shall be 
deemed to be, for all the purposes of this Act, the assessee in 
respect of such tax.

</section>

<section><tid>23770</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person employed by or on behalf of a person referred to 
in sub- section (1) or through whom such person is in the receipt of 
any income, profits or gains, or who is in possession or has custody 
of any asset of such person and upon whom the Wealth- tax Officer
<pagefootnote><pagenum>804A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" in the case of an individual" omitted by Act 32 of 
<year>1971</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 34, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


has caused a notice to be served of his intention of treating him as 
the agent of such person shall, for the purposes of sub- section (1), 
be deemed to be the agent of such person.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1606827</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> No person shall be deemed to be the agent of any person 
residing outside India unless he has had an opportunity of being heard 
by the Wealth- tax Officer as to his being treated as such.

</section>

<section><tid>1477068</tid>
<number>4</number>Any agent, who, as such, pays any sum under this Act, shall 
be entitled to recover the sum so paid from the person on whose behalf 
it is paid or to retain out of any moneys that may be in his 
possession or may come to him in his capacity as such agent, an amount 
equal to the sum so paid.

</section>

<section><tid>1173198</tid>
<number>5</number>Any agent, or any person who apprehends that he may be 
assessed as an agent, may retain out of any money payable by him to 
the person residing outside India on whose behalf he is liable to pay 
tax (hereinafter in this section referred to as the principal), a sum 
equal to his estimated liability under this section, and in the event 
of any disagreement between the principal and such agent or person, as 
to the amount to be so retained, such agent or person may secure from 
the Wealth- tax Officer a certificate stating the amount to be so 
retained pending final settlement of the liability, and the 
certificate so obtained shall be his warrant for retaining that 
amount.

</section>

<section><tid>1088653</tid>
<number>6</number>The amount recoverable from such agent or person at the time 
of final settlement shall not exceed the amount specified in such 
certificate, except to the extent to which such agent or person may at 
such time have in his hands additional assets of the principal.

</section>

<section><tid>812280</tid>
<number>7</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, any 
arrears of tax due from a person residing outside India may be 
recovered also in accordance with the provisions of this Act from any 
assets of such person which are or may at any time come within India.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>805</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Proviso omitted by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 21, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

APPEALS, REVISIONS AND REFERENCES

CHAPTER VI

APPEALS, REVISIONS AND REFERENCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236181</tid>
<number> 23</number> Appeal to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner from orders of 
Wealth- tax Officers.
<section><tid>1366258</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person,-- 

<subsection><tid>1970357</tid>
<number>a</number>objecting to the amount of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> net wealth] determined 
under this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1268986</tid>
<number>b</number>objecting to the amount of wealth- tax determined as 
payable by him under this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1480434</tid>
<number>c</number>denying his liability to be assessed under this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425382</tid>
<number>d</number>objecting to any penalty imposed by the Wealth- tax 
Officer under <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 15B or] section 18; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1465991</tid>
<number>e</number>objecting to any order of the Wealth- tax Officer under 
sub- section (2) of section 20; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85503</tid>
<number>f</number>objecting to any penalty imposed by the Wealth- tax 
Officer under the provisions of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> section 221] of the 
Income- tax Act as applied under section 32 for the 
purposes of wealth- tax; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>390215</tid>
<number>g</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> objecting to any order made by the Wealth- tax Officer 
under section 22 treating him as the agent of a person 
residing outside India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>104221</tid>
<number>h</number>objecting to any order of the Wealth- tax Officer under 
section 35 having the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing a refund or refusing to allow 
the claim made by the assessee under the said section; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1516190</tid>
<number>ha</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> objecting to any order of the Valuation Officer 
under section 35 having the effect of enhancing the 
valuation of any asset or refusing to allow the claim 
made by the assessee under the said section; or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48918</tid>
<number>i</number>objecting to an order of the[ Wealth tax Officer or 
Valuation Officer] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> imposing a fine under sub- section 
 (2) of section 37;]
may appeal to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner against the 
assessment or order, as the case may be, in the prescribed form and 
verified in the prescribed manner.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1680324</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the 
receipt of the notice of demand relating to the assessment or penalty 
objected to, or the date on which any order objected to, is 
communicated to him, but the Appellate Assistant Commissioner may 
admit an appeal after the expiration of the period aforesaid if he is 
satisfied that the appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting 
the appeal within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>751897</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Where a return has been filed by an assessee, no appeal 
under this section shall be admitted unless at the time of filing of 
the appeal he has paid the tax due on the net wealth returned by him:
Provided that, on an application made by the appellant in this 
behalf, the Appellate Assistant Commissioner may, for any good and 
sufficient reason to be recorded in writing, exempt him from the 
operation of the provision of this sub- section.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>806</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 22, for" his net wealth" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 22, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 22, ibid., for" sub- section (1) of section 46" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Ins. and Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 94 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>954290</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Assistant Commissioner shall fix a day and 
place for the hearing of the appeal and may, from time to time, 
adjourn the hearing.

</section>

<section><tid>262386</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> If the valuation of any asset is objected to in an appeal 
under clause (a) of sub- section (1), the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner shall,--

<subsection><tid>413923</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where such valuation has been made by a 
Valuation Officer under section 16A, give such Valuation Officer 
an opportunity of being heard;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767064</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, on a request being made in this 
behalf by the Wealth- tax Officer, give an opportunity of being 
heard to any Valuation Officer nominated for the purpose by the 
Wealth- tax Officer.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>51507</tid>
<number>4</number>The Appellate Assistant Commissioner may--

<subsection><tid>824270</tid>
<number>a</number>at the hearing of an appeal, allow an appellant to go 
into any ground of appeal not specified in the grounds 
of appeal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1541701</tid>
<number>b</number>before disposing of an appeal, make such further inquiry 
as he thinks fit or cause further inquiry to be made by 
the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Wealth- tax Officer or, as the case may be, the 
Valuation Officer].

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>24203</tid>
<number>5</number>In disposing of an appeal, the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner may pass such order as he thinks fit which may include an 
order enhancing the assessment or penalty:
Provided that no order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall 
be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>1818037</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In disposing of an appeal, the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner may consider and decide any matter arising out of the 
proceedings in which the order appealed against was passed, 
notwithstanding that such matter was not raised before the Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner by the appellant.

</section>

<section><tid>800730</tid>
<number>5B</number>The order of the Appellate Assistant Commissioner disposing 
of the appeal shall be in writing and shall state the points for 
determination, the decision thereon and the reasons for the decision.]

</section>

<section><tid>1289592</tid>
<number>6</number>A copy of every order passed by the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner under this section shall be forwarded to the appellant 
and the Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407796</tid>
<number> 24</number> Appeal to the Appellate Tribunal from orders of the Appellate 
Assistant Commissioners. <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1159898</tid>
<number>1</number>An assessee objecting to an order  
passed by the Appellate Assistant Commissioner under section 18 or 
section 18A or section 23 or sub- section (2) of section 37, or to an 
order passed by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner under section 
18A, may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal within sixty days of the 
date on which the order is communicated to him.]

</section>

<section><tid>1133993</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, if he is not satisfied as to the 
correctness of any order passed by an Appellate Assistant Commissioner 
under section 23, direct the Wealth- tax Officer to appeal to the 
Appellate Tribunal against such order, and such appeal may be made at
<pagefootnote><pagenum>807</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 22 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 23, ibid., for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Ins. and Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 11 
4 Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 95 (w. e. f. 1- 4- 76).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


any time before the expiry of sixty days of the date on which the 
order is communicated to the Commissioner.


</section>

<section><tid>1871867</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Wealth- tax Officer or the assessee, as the case may 
be, on receipt of notice that an appeal against the order of the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner has been preferred under sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) by the other party, may, notwithstanding that 
he may not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, 
within thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file a memorandum of 
cross objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part 
of the order of the Appellate Assistant Commissioner and such 
memorandum shall be disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it 
were an appeal presented within the time specified in sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (2).]

</section>

<section><tid>216304</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) or 
sub- section (2A), if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause 
for not presenting it within that period.]

</section>

<section><tid>278825</tid>
<number>4</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and 
shall, except in the case of an appeal referred to in sub- section (2), 
be accompanied by <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a fee of one hundred and twenty- five rupees].

</section>

<section><tid>1718768</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may, after giving both parties to the 
appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it 
thinks fit, and any such orders may include an order enhancing the 
assessment or penalty:
Provided that no order enhancing an assessment or penalty shall 
be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>437138</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> (a) Where the appellant object to the valuation of any 
property, the Appellate Tribunal may, and if the appellant so 
requires, shall, refer the question of the disputed value to the 
arbitration of two valuers, one of whom shall be nominated by the 
appellant and the other by the respondent, and the Tribunal shall, so 
far as that question is concerned, pass its orders under sub- section 
 (5) conformably to the decision of the valuers:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 23 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 23, ibid., for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 62, for" a fee of rupees one hundred 
" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 23, for sub- sections (6), (7) and (8) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that--


<subsection><tid>1317963</tid>
<number>i</number>where the appellant or the respondent does not nominate 
any valuer within the time specified by the Appellate 
Tribunal or within such further time as the Appellate 
Tribunal may allow, the Appellate Tribunal may nominate 
a valuer on his behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1156792</tid>
<number>ii</number>if there is a difference of opinion between the two 
valuers, the matter shall be referred to a third valuer 
nominated by agreement, or failing agreement, by the 
Appellate Tribunal, and the decision of that valuer on 
the question of valuation shall be final;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>551753</tid>
<number>iii</number>where any person has at any time expressed any opinion 
on the valuation of any property to which the 
provisions of this clause apply, such person shall not 
be nominated as a valuer in relation to that property.

<subsubsection><tid>1132086</tid>
<number>b</number>The valuers to whom a reference under clause (a) has been 
made by the Appellate Tribunal shall communicate their decision to the 
Appellate Tribunal within six months of the date of such reference or 
within such further time as the Tribunal may allow:
Provided that if the decision of the valuers is not communicated 
within the period aforesaid, the Appellate Tribunal may order that the 
reference made under this sub- section shall be deemed to be withdrawn 
and proceed to dispose of the case on the evidence before it, 
including the report of either of the valuers if any such report has 
been submitted.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>556548</tid>
<number>7</number>The extent to which the costs of arbitration proceedings 
 (including a case where a reference is deemed to be withdrawn) under 
sub- section (6) shall be borne by the appellant or the respondent 
shall be at the discretion of the Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>474849</tid>
<number>8</number>The valuers may, in disposing of any matter referred to them 
for arbitration under this section, hold or cause to be held such 
enquiry as they think fit and after giving the appellant and the 
respondent an opportunity of being heard, make such decision as they 
think fit and shall communicate such decision in writing to the 
Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1746260</tid>
<number>8A</number>The valuers appointed under this section, while acting as 
such, shall have all powers of a Civil Court while trying a suit under 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.) in respect of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1818072</tid>
<number>i</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>612926</tid>
<number>9</number>A copy of every order passed by the Appellate Tribunal under 
this section shall be forwarded to the assessee and the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1415199</tid>
<number>10</number>Save as provided in section 27, any order passed by the 
Appellate Tribunal on appeal shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>709535</tid>
<number>11</number>The provisions of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> sub- sections (1), (4) and (5) of 
section 255] of the Income- tax Act shall apply to the Appellate 
Tribunal in the discharge of its functions under this Act as they 
apply to it in the discharge of its functions under the Income- tax 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1386602</tid>
<number> 25</number> Powers of Commissioner to revise orders of subordinate 
authorities.
<section><tid>1825403</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may, either of his own motion or on  
application made by an assessee in this behalf, call for the record of 
any proceeding under this Act in which an order has been passed by any 
authority subordinate to him, and may make such inquiry, or cause such 
inquiry to be made, and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass 
such order thereon, not being an order prejudicial to the assessee, as 
the Commissioner thinks fit:
Provided that the Commissioner shall not revise any order under 
this sub- section in any case--


<subsection><tid>1680836</tid>
<number>a</number>where an appeal against the order lies to the Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner or to the Appellate Tribunal, 
the time within which such appeal can be made has not 
expired or in the case of an appeal to the Appellate 
Tribunal the assessee has not waived his right of 
appeal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205071</tid>
<number>b</number>where the order is the subject of an appeal before the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner or the Appellate 
Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>506853</tid>
<number>c</number>where the application is made by the assessee for such 
revision, unless--

<subsubsection><tid>1233536</tid>
<number>i</number>the application is accompanied by a fee 
of twenty- five rupees; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 23, for" sub- sections (5), (7) and 
 (8) of section 5A" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1242723</tid>
<number>ii</number>the application is made within one year 
from the date of the order sought to be revised or 
within such further period as the Commissioner may 
think fit to allow on being satisfied that the 
assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from 
making the application within that period; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1904610</tid>
<number>d</number>where the order is sought to be revised by the 
Commissioner of his own motion, if such order is made 
more than one year previously.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1680836</tid>
<number>a</number>the Appellate Assistant Commissioner 
shall be deemed to be an authority subordinate to 
the Commissioner; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205071</tid>
<number>b</number>an order by the Commissioner declining to 
interfere shall be deemed not to be an order 
prejudicial to the assessee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1303878</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (1), the Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any 
proceeding under this Act, and if he considers that any order passed 
therein by a Wealth- tax Officer is erroneous in so far as it is 
prejudicial to the interests of revenue, he may, after giving the 
assessee an opportunity of being heard, and after making or causing to 
be made such inquiry as he deems necessary pass such order thereon as 
the circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or 
modifying the assessment or cancelling it and directing a fresh 
assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1643335</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> No order shall be made under sub- section (2) after the 
expiry of two years from the date of the order sought to be revised.

</section>

<section><tid>373311</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), an 
order in revision under sub- section (2) may be passed at any time in 
the case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to 
give effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the 
Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.
Explanation.-- In computing the period of limitation for the 
purposes of sub- section (3), the time taken in giving an opportunity 
to the assessee to be re- heard under the proviso to section 39 and any 
period during which any proceeding under this section is stayed by an 
order or injunction of any court shall be excluded.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 24 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>186265</tid>
<number> 26</number> Appeal to the Appellate Tribunal from orders of enhancement 
by Commissioners.
<section><tid>1695231</tid>
<number>1</number>Any assessee objecting to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an order passed by  
the Commissioner under section 18 or sub- section (2) of section 25] 
may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal within sixty days of the date on 
which the order is communicated to him.

</section>

<section><tid>907557</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under sub- section (1) 
shall be in the prescribed form and shall be verified in the 
prescribed manner and shall be accompanied by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a fee of one hundred 
and twenty- five rupees].

</section>

<section><tid>581869</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- sections (3) and (5) to (10) inclusive 
of section 24 shall apply in relation to any appeal under this section 
as they apply in relation to any appeal under that section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1384056</tid>
<number> 27</number> Reference to High Court. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>942311</tid>
<number>1</number>The assessee or the  
Commissioner may, within sixty days of the date upon which he is 
served with notice of an order under section 24 or section 26, by 
application in the prescribed form, accompanied, where the application 
is made by the assessee, by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a fee of one hundred and twenty- five 
rupees], require the Appellate Tribunal to refer to the High Court any 
question of law arising out of such order and, subject to the other 
provisions contained in this section, the Appellate Tribunal shall, 
within one hundred and twenty days of the receipt of such application, 
draw up a statement of the case and refer it to the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1049242</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the 
applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting the 
application within the period specified in sub- section (1), allow it 
to be presented within a further period not exceeding thirty days.]

</section>

<section><tid>1394185</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on an application made under sub- section (1), the 
Appellate Tribunal,--

<subsection><tid>1919777</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses to state a case on the ground that no question 
of law arises; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>291717</tid>
<number>b</number>rejects it on the ground that it is time barred;
the applicant may, within <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> ninety days] from the date on which he is 
served with a notice of refusal or rejection, as the case may be, 
apply to the High Court, and the High Court may, if it is not 
satisfied

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 25, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 63 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 26, for sub- sections (1) and (2) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 64 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
5 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 26, for" three months" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


with the correctness of the decision of the Appellate Tribunal, 
require the Appellate Tribunal to state the case to the High Court, 
and on receipt of such requisition the Appellate Tribunal shall state 
the case:

Provided that, if in any case where the Appellate Tribunal has 
been required by an assessee to state a case the Appellate Tribunal 
refuses to do so on the ground that no question of law arises, the 
assessee may, within thirty days from the date on which he receives 
notice of refusal to state the case, withdraw his application, and if 
he does so, the fee paid by him under sub- section (1) shall be 
refunded to him.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>777286</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If, on an application made under this section the 
Appellate Tribunal is of the opinion that, on account of a conflict in 
the decisions of the High Courts in respect of any particular question 
of law, it is expedient that a reference should be made direct to the 
Supreme Court, the Appellate Tribunal may draw up a statement of the 
case and refer it through its President direct to the Supreme Court.]

</section>

<section><tid>1718298</tid>
<number>4</number>The statement to the High Court <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the Supreme Court] 
shall set forth the facts, the determination of the Appellate Tribunal 
and the question of law which arises out of the case.

</section>

<section><tid>86907</tid>
<number>5</number>If the High Court <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the Supreme Court] is not satisfied 
that the case as stated is sufficient to enable it to determine the 
question of law raised thereby, it may require the Appellate Tribunal 
to make such modifications therein as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>578244</tid>
<number>6</number>The High Court <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the Supreme Court], upon hearing any 
such case, shall decide the question of law raised therein, and in 
doing so, may, if it thinks fit, alter the form of the question of law 
and shall deliver judgment thereon containing the ground on which such 
decision is founded and shall send a copy of the judgment under the 
seal of the Court and the signature of the Registrar to the Appellate 
Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall pass such orders as are 
necessary to dispose of the case conformably to such judgment.

</section>

<section><tid>24454</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The costs of any reference to the High Court or the 
Supreme Court which shall not include the fee for making the 
reference, shall be in the discretion of the Court.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808DD</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 26, ibid. for sub- sections (7), (8) and (9)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>897078</tid>
<number>28</number>Hearing by High Court. When a case has been stated to the 
High Court under section 27, it shall be heard by a Bench of not less 
than two Judges of the High Court and shall be decided in accordance 
with the opinion of such Judges or of the majority of such Judges, if 
any:
Provided that where there is no such majority, the Judges shall 
state the point of law upon which they differ and the case shall then 
be heard upon that point only by one or more of the Judges of the


<pagefootnote><pagenum>808E</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

High Court, and such point shall be decided according to the opinion 
of the majority of the Judges who have heard the case, including those 
who first heard it.



</article>



<article><tid>1312764</tid>
<number> 29</number> Appeal to Supreme Court.
<section><tid>1311946</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the  
Supreme Court from any judgment of the High Court delivered on a case 
stated under section 27 in any case which the High Court certifies as 
a fit case for appeal to the Supreme Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1463960</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the judgment of the High Court is varied or reversed on 
appeal under this section, effect shall be given to the order of the 
Supreme Court in the manner provided in sub- section (6) of section 27.

</section>

<section><tid>1759431</tid>
<number>3</number>The High Court may, on application made to it for the 
execution of any order of the Supreme Court in respect of any costs 
awarded by it, transmit the order for execution to any court 
subordinate to the High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>762273</tid>
<number>29A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Tax to be paid not withstanding reference, etc. 
Notwithstanding that a reference has been made to the High Court or 
the Supreme Court, or an appeal has been preferred to the Supreme 
Court, wealth- tax shall be payable in accordance with the assessment 
made in the case.


</article>



<article><tid>577699</tid>
<number> 29B</number> Definition of High Court. In this Chapter," High Court" 
means--
<section><tid>206152</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to any State, the High Court of that State;

</section>

<section><tid>1231280</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in relation to the Union territory of Delhi, the 
High Court of Delhi;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> xxx


</section>

<section><tid>1628953</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in relation to the Union territories of Arunachal 
Pradesh and Mizoram, the Gauhati High Court (the High  
Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and 
  Tripura);]

</section>

<section><tid>1604416</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to the Union territory of Andaman and 
Nicobar Islands, the High Court at Calcutta;

</section>

<section><tid>418438</tid>
<number>v</number>in relation to the Union territory of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Lakshadeep] the 
High Court of Kerala;

</section>

<section><tid>1975238</tid>
<number>vi</number>in relation to the Union territories of Dadra and Nagar 
Haveli and Goa, Daman and Diu, the High Court at 
Bombay;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808F</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 27 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by the Punjab Reorganisation and Delhi High Court 
 (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1968</year>, for cl. (ii) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>). 
3 Omitted by the State of Himachal Pradesh (Adaptation of Law on  
  Union Subjects) Order, <year>1973</year> (w. e. f. 25- 1- <year>1971</year>). 
4 Subs. by the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1974</year>. (w. e. f. 21- 1- <year>1972</year>). 
5 Subs. by the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindives Islands (Alteration  
  of Name) Adaptation of Laws Order, <year>1974</year> (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>809492</tid>
<number>vii</number>in relation to the Union territory of Pondicherry, the 
High Court at Madras;

</section>

<section><tid>1648776</tid>
<number>viii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in relation to the Union territory of Chandigarh, 
the High Court of Punjab and Haryana].]
CHAP

PAYMENT AND RECOVERY OF WEALTH- TAX

CHAPTER VII

PAYMENT AND RECOVERY OF WEALTH- TAX




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1797615</tid>
<number>30</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notice of demand. When any tax, interest, penalty, fine or 
any other sum is payable in consequence of any order passed under this 
Act, the Wealth- tax Officer shall serve upon the assessee a notice of 
demand in the prescribed form specifying the sum so payable.


</article>



<article><tid>517031</tid>
<number> 31</number> When tax, etc., payable and when assessee deemed in default.

<section><tid>437209</tid>
<number>1</number>Any amount specified as payable in a notice of demand under  
section 30 shall be paid within thirty- five days of the service of the 
notice at the place and to the person mentioned in the notice:
Provided that, where the Wealth- tax Officer has any reason to 
believe that it will be detrimental to revenue if the full period of 
thirty- five days aforesaid is allowed, he may, with the previous 
approval of the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner, direct that the sum 
specified in the notice of demand shall be paid within such period 
being a period less than the period of thirty- five days aforesaid, as 
may be specified by him in the notice of demand.


</section>

<section><tid>1828559</tid>
<number>2</number>If the amount specified in any notice of demand under section 
 30 is not paid within the period limited under sub- section (1), the 
assessee shall be liable to pay simple interest at <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> twelve per 
cent.] per annum from the day commencing after the end of the period 
mentioned in sub- section (1):
Provided that where as a result of an order under section 23, or 
section 24, or section 25, or section 26, or section 27, or section 
29, or section 35, the amount on which interest was payable under this 
section had been reduced, the interest shall be reduced accordingly 
and the excess interest paid, if any, shall be refunded.


</section>

<section><tid>340110</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (2), on an application made by the assessee before the expiry of the 
due date under sub- section (1), the Wealth- tax Officer may extend the 
time for payment or allow payment by instalments, subject to such 
conditions as he may think fit to impose in the circumstances of the 
case.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Punjab Re- organisation and Delhi High Court 
 (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1968</year> (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 28, for ss. 30, 31 and 32 (w. e. f. 1-  
  10- <year>1967</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 27 of <year>1967</year>, s. 2 for" six per cent." (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1967</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 47 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>68261</tid>
<number>4</number>If the amount is not paid within the time limited under sub- 
section (1) or extended under sub- section (3), as the case may be, at 
the place and to the person mentioned in the said notice, the assessee 
shall be deemed to be in default.

</section>

<section><tid>332228</tid>
<number>5</number>If in a case where payment by instalments is allowed under 
sub- section (3), the assessee commits default in paying any one of the 
instalments within the time fixed under that sub- section, the assessee 
shall be deemed to be in default as to the whole of the amount then 
outstanding, and the other instalment or instalments shall be deemed 
to have been due on the same date as the instalment actually in 
default.

</section>

<section><tid>1831883</tid>
<number>6</number>Where an assessee has presented an appeal under section 23, 
the Wealth- tax Officer may, in his discretion, and subject to such 
conditions, as he may think fit to impose in the circumstances of the 
case, treat the assessee as not being in default in respect of the 
amount in dispute in the appeal, even though the time for payment has 
expired, as long as such appeal remains undisposed of.

</section>

<section><tid>423265</tid>
<number>7</number>Where an assessee has been assessed in respect of assets 
located in a country outside India, the laws of which prohibit or 
restrict the remittance of money to India, the Wealth- tax Officer 
shall not treat the assessee as in default in respect of that part of 
the tax which is attributable to those assets, and shall continue to 
treat the assessee as not in default in respect of that part of the 
tax until the prohibition or restriction of remittance is removed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1113946</tid>
<number>32</number>Mode of recovery. The provisions contained in sections 221 to 
227, 229, 231 and 232 of the Income- tax Act and the Second and Third 
Schedules to that Act and any rules made thereunder shall, so far as 
may be, apply as if the said provisions were provisions of this Act 
and referred to wealth- tax and sums imposed by way of penalty, fine 
and interest under this Act instead of to Income- tax and sums imposed 
by way of penalty, fine and interest under that Act and to Wealth- tax 
Officer and Commissioner of Wealth- tax instead of to Income- tax 
Officer and Commissioner of Income- tax.
Explanation I.-- Any reference to section 173 and sub- section (2) 
or sub- section (6) or sub- section (7) of section 220 of the Income- tax 
Act in the said provisions of that Act or the rules made thereunder 
shall be construed as references to sub- section (7) of section 22 and


<pagefootnote><pagenum>808H</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sub- section (2) or sub- section (6) or sub- section (7) of section 31 of 
this Act respectively.

Explanation II.-- The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Tax Recovery Commissioner and the Tax 
Recovery Officer referred to in the Income- tax Act shall be deemed to 
be the Tax Recovery Commissioner and the Tax Recovery Officer] for the 
purposes of recovery of wealth- tax and sums imposed by way of penalty, 
fine and interest under this Act.]



</article>



<article><tid>686614</tid>
<number> 33</number> Liability of transferees of properties in certain cases.
<section><tid>1681437</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where by reason of the provisions contained in section 4, the value of 
any assets transferred to any of the persons mentioned in that section 
have to be included in the net wealth of an individual, the person in 
whose name such assets stand shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
in any law to the contrary, be liable, on the service of a notice of 
demand by the Wealth- tax Officer in this behalf, to pay that portion 
of the tax assessed on the assessee as is attributable to the value of 
the asset standing in his name as aforesaid:
Provided that where any such asset is held jointly by more than 
one person, they shall be jointly and severally liable to pay the tax 
as is attributable to the value of the asset so jointly held.


</section>

<section><tid>606131</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such person as is referred to in sub- section (1) 
defaults in making payment of any tax demanded from him, he shall be 
deemed to be an assessee in default in respect of such sum, and all 
the provisions of this Act relating to recovery shall apply 
accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1168319</tid>
<number>34</number>[ Restrictions on registration of transfers of immovable 
property in certain cases.] Rep. by the Wealth- tax (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1964</year> (46 of <year>1964</year>), s. 29 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).
CHAP

REFUNDS

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> CHAPTER VIIA

REFUNDS



</article>



<article><tid>165814</tid>
<number> 34A</number> Refunds.
<section><tid>272117</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, as a result of any order passed in  
appeal or other proceeding (including a rectification proceeding) 
under this Act, refund of any amount becomes due to the assessee, the 
Wealth- tax Officer shall, except as otherwise provided in this Act, 
refund
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808HH</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1971</year>, s. 35, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 1-  
  <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 30 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the amount to the assessee without his having to make any claim in 
that behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>709390</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an order giving rise to a refund is the subject matter 
of an appeal or further proceeding or where any other proceeding under 
this Act is pending and the Wealth- tax Officer is of the opinion that 
the grant of the refund is likely to adversely affect the revenue, the 
Wealth- tax Officer may, with the previous approval of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808I</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Commissioner, withhold the refund till such time as the Commissioner 
may determine.


</section>

<section><tid>519074</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a refund is due to the assessee in pursuance of an 
order referred to in sub- section (1) and the Wealth- tax Officer does 
not grant the refund within a period of six months from the date of 
such order, the Central Government shall pay to the assessee simple 
interest at <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> twelve per cent.] per annum on the amount of refund due 
from the date immediately following the expiry of the period of six 
months aforesaid to the date on which the refund is granted.

</section>

<section><tid>107082</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Where the whole or any part of the refund referred to in 
sub- section (3) is due to the assessee as a result of any amount 
having been paid by him after the 31st day of March, <year>1975</year> in pursuance 
of any order of assessment or penalty and such amount or any part 
thereof having been found in appeal or other proceeding under this Act 
to be in excess of the amount which such assessee is liable to pay as 
tax or penalty, as the case may be, under this Act, the Central 
Government shall pay to such assessee simple interest at the rate 
specified in sub- section (3) on the amount so found to be in excess 
from the date on which such amount was paid to the date on which the 
refund is granted:
Provided that, where the amount so found to be in excess was paid 
in instalments, such interest shall be payable on the amount of each 
such instalment or any part of such instalment, which was in excess, 
from the date on which such instalment was paid to the date on which 
the refund is granted:

Provided further that no interest under this sub- section shall be 
payable for a period of one month from the date of the passing of the 
order in appeal or other proceeding:

Provided also that, where any interest is payable to an assessee 
under this sub- section, no interest under sub- section (3) shall be 
payable to him in respect of the amount so found to be in excess.]


</section>

<section><tid>805814</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a refund is withheld under the provisions of sub- 
section (2), the Central Government shall pay interest at the 
aforesaid rate on the amount of refund ultimately determined to be due 
as a result of the appeal or further proceeding for the period 
commencing after the expiry of six months from the date of the order 
referred to in that sub- section to the date the refund is granted.

</section>

<section><tid>1154725</tid>
<number>5</number>Where under any of the provisions of this Act, a refund is 
found to be due to any person, the Wealth- tax Officer, Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner or Commissioner, as the case may be, may, in 
lieu of payment of the refund, set off the amount to be refunded or 
any part of that amount, against the sum, if any, remaining payable 
under this Act by the person to whom the refund is due, after giving 
an intimation in writing to such person of the action proposed to be 
taken under this section.]
CHAP

REGISTERED VALUERS

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> CHAPTER VIIB

REGISTERED VALUERS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>34AA</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Appearance by registered valuers.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1101296</tid>
<number>34AA</number>Appearance by registered valuers. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, any assessee who is entitled to or required to 
attend before any wealth- tax authority or the Appellate Tribunal in 
connection with any matter relating to the valuation of any asset, 
except where he is required under this Act to attend in person, may 
attend by a registered valuer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34AB</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Registration of valuers.

</article>



<article><tid>1770199</tid>
<number> 34AB</number> Registration of valuers.
<section><tid>1337432</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain a  
register to be called the Register of Valuers in which shall be 
entered the names and addresses of persons registered under sub- 
section (2) as valuers.

</section>

<section><tid>1627627</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who possesses the qualifications prescribed in 
this behalf may apply to the Board in the prescribed form for being 
registered as a valuer under this section:
Provided that different qualification may be prescribed for 
valuers of different classes of assets.


</section>

<section><tid>1382053</tid>
<number>3</number>Every application under sub- section (2) shall be verified in 
the prescribed manner, shall be accompanied by such fees as may be 
prescribed and shall contain a declaration to the effect that the 
applicant will--

<subsection><tid>1377986</tid>
<number>i</number>make an impartial and true valuation of any asset which 
he may be required to value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291181</tid>
<number>ii</number>furnish a report of such valuation in the prescribed 
form;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1864902</tid>
<number>iii</number>charge fees at a rate not exceeding the rate or rates 
prescribed in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>735817</tid>
<number>iv</number>not undertake valuation of any asset in which he has a 
direct or indirect interest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>680423</tid>
<number>4</number>The report of valuation of any asset by a registered valuer 
shall be in the prescribed form and be verified in the prescribed 
manner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34AC</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Restrictions on practice as registered valuer.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1574136</tid>
<number> 34AC</number> Restrictions on practice as registered valuer.
<section><tid>198815</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
person, either alone or in partnership with any other person, shall 
practise, describe himself or hold himself out as registered valuer 
for the purposes of this Act or permit himself to be so described or 
held out, unless he is registered as a valuer or, as the case may be, 
unless he and all his partners are so registered under this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>761554</tid>
<number>2</number>No company or other body corporate shall practise, describe 
itself or hold itself out as registered valuers for the purposes of 
this Act or permit itself to be so described or held out.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34AD</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Removal from register of names of valuers and restoration.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1121121</tid>
<number> 34AD</number> Removal from register of names of valuers and restoration.

<section><tid>1679293</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may remove the name of any person from the register of  
valuers where it is satisfied, after giving that person a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard and after such further inquiry, if any, as 
it thinks fit to make,--

<subsection><tid>1243039</tid>
<number>i</number>that his name has been entered in the register by error 
or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of a material 
fact;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>878741</tid>
<number>ii</number>that he has been convicted of any offence and sentenced 
to a term of imprisonment or has been guilty of misconduct in his 
professional capacity which, in the opinion of the Board, renders 
him unfit to be kept in the register.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1614</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, on application and on sufficient cause being 
shown, restore to the register the name or any person removed 
therefrom.]
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VIII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1514084</tid>
<number> 34B</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Transfers to defraud revenue to be void.
<section><tid>1789211</tid>
<number>1</number>Where,  
during the pendency of any proceeding under this Act or after the 
completion thereof, but before the service of notice under rule 2 of 
the Second Schedule to the Income- tax Act as made applicable to this 
Act by section 32, any assessee creates a charge on, or parts with (by  
way of sale, mortgage, gift, exchange or any other mode of transfer 
  whatsoever) the possession of, any of his assets in favour of any 
other person, such charge or transfer shall be void as against any 
other person, such charge or transfer shall be void as against any 
claim in respect of any tax or any other sum payable by the assessee 
as a result of the completion of the said proceeding or otherwise:
Provided that such charge or transfer shall not be void, if it is 
made--


<subsection><tid>462199</tid>
<number>i</number>for adequate consideration and without notice of the 
pendency of such proceeding or, as the case may be, without 
notice of such tax or other sum payable by the assessee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>992557</tid>
<number>ii</number>with the previous permission of the Wealth- tax Officer.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1675098</tid>
<number>2</number>This section applies to cases where the amount of tax or 
other sum payable or likely to be payable exceeds five thousand 
rupees and the assets charged or transferred exceed ten thousand 
rupees in value.
Explanation.-- In this section," assets" means land, 
building, machinery, plant, shares, securities and fixed deposits 
in banks to the extent to which any of the assets aforesaid does 
not form part of the stock in trade of the business of the 
assessee.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1751346</tid>
<number> 34C</number> Provisional attachment to protect revenue in certain cases.

<section><tid>1107453</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, during the pendency of any proceeding for the assessment of  
net wealth or for the assessment or re- assessment of net wealth which 
has escaped assessment, the Wealth- tax Officer is of the opinion that 
for the purpose of protecting the interests of the revenue it is 
necessary so to do, he may, with the previous approval of the 
Commissioner, by order in writing, attach provisionally any property 
belonging to the assessee in the manner provided in the Second 
Schedule to the Income- tax Act as made applicable to this Act by 
section 32.

</section>

<section><tid>1050273</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such provisional attachment shall cease to have effect 
after the expiry of a period of six months from the date of the order 
made under sub- section (1):
Provided that the Commissioner may, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, extend the aforesaid period by such further period or periods 
as he thinks fit, so however, that the total period of extension shall 
not in any case exceed two years.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808J</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 27 of <year>1967</year>, s. 2, for" six per cent." (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1967</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 31 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 47 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>). 
4 Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 15- 11- <year>1972</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 97 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75). 
6 Subs. by s. 98 ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220885</tid>
<number> 35</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rectification of mistakes.
<section><tid>1140658</tid>
<number>1</number>With a view to rectifying  
any mistake apparent from the record--

<subsection><tid>61155</tid>
<number>a</number>the Wealth- tax Officer may amend any order of assessment 
or of refund or any other order passed by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1618794</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Valuation Officer may amend any order passed by 
him under section 16A;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>100438</tid>
<number>b</number>the Appellate Assistant Commissioner may amend any order 
passed by him under section 18 or under section 23;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> xxx


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1693804</tid>
<number>d</number>the Commissioner may amend any order passed by him under 
section 18 or under section 25;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>970962</tid>
<number>e</number>the Appellate Tribunal may amend any order passed by it 
under section 18 or under section 24.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>303088</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the amount of tax, penalty or interest determined as a 
result of the first appeal or revision against the order referred to 
in sub- clause (iii) of clause (m) of section 2 is paid within six 
months of the date of the order passed in such appeal or revision, the 
Wealth- tax Officer may, notwithstanding anything to the contrary in 
this Act, rectify the assessment by allowing a deduction to the extent 
the tax, penalty or interest so paid stood disallowed therein as if 
such rectification were rectification of a mistake apparent from the 
record.

</section>

<section><tid>1360999</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this section, the 
authority concerned--

<subsection><tid>1645351</tid>
<number>a</number>may make an amendment under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2) of its own motion; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1447656</tid>
<number>b</number>shall make such amendment for rectifying any such 
mistake which has been brought to its notice by the 
assessee, and where the authority concerned is the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Valuation Officer or the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner] or the Appellate Tribunal, by the Wealth- 
tax Officer also.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>784167</tid>
<number>4</number>An amendment, which has the effect of enhancing an assessment 
or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability of the 
assessee, shall not be made under this section unless the authority 
concerned has given notice to the assessee of its intention so to do 
and has allowed the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>38629</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an amendment is made under this section, an order shall 
be passed in writing by the Wealth- tax authority concerned or the 
Tribunal, as the case may be.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808K</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 32, for s. 35 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. and Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Omitted by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 99 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1652953</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing a refund already made, the Wealth- tax Officer 
shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the prescribed form 
specifying the sum payable, and such notice of demand shall be deemed 
to be issued under section 30 and the provisions of this Act shall 
apply accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>417742</tid>
<number>6A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where any amendment made by the Valuation Officer under 
clause (aa) of sub- section (1) has the effect of enhancing the 
valuation of any asset, he shall send a copy of his order to the 
Wealth- tax Officer who shall thereafter proceed to amend the order of 
assessment in conformity with the order of the Valuation Officer and 
the provisions of sub- section (6) shall apply accordingly.]

</section>

<section><tid>1770905</tid>
<number>7</number>No amendment under this section shall be made after the 
expiry of four years--

<subsection><tid>782324</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an amendment under sub- section (2), from 
the date of the order passed in the first appeal or 
revision referred to in that sub- section; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>46862</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, from the date of the order sought to 
be amended.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1573391</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (7), 
where the valuation of any asset has been enhanced by the Valuation 
Officer under this section, the consequential amendment to the order 
of assessment may be made by the Wealth- tax Officer at any time before 
the expiry of one year from the date of the order of the Valuation 
Officer under this section.]

</section>

<section><tid>50920</tid>
<number>8</number>Where any matter has been considered and decided in a 
profiling by way of an appeal or revision relating to an order 
referred to in sub- section (1), the authority passing such order may, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, amend the order under this section in relation to any matter 
other than the matter which has been so considered and decided.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>804272</tid>
<number> 35A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Wilful attempt to evade tax, etc.
<section><tid>328003</tid>
<number>1</number>If a person  
wilfully attempts in any manner whatsoever to evade any tax, penalty 
or interest chargeable or imposable under this Act, he shall, without 
prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him under any other 
provision of this Act, be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>344527</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount sought to be evaded exceeds 
one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend 
to seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1433732</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
which shall not be less than three months but which may extend to 
three years and with fine.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1878229</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person wilfully attempts in any manner whatsoever to 
evade the payment of any tax, penalty or interest under this Act, he 
shall, without prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him 
under any other provision of this Act, be punishable with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but 
which may extend to three years and shall, in the discretion of the 
court, also be liable to fine.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, a wilful attempt 
to evade any tax, penalty or interest chargeable or imposable under 
this Act or the payment thereof shall include a case where any person- 
-


<subsection><tid>1537799</tid>
<number>a</number>has in his possession or control any books of account or 
other documents (being books of account or other documents  
  relevant to any proceeding under this Act) containing a false 
entry or statement or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1014392</tid>
<number>b</number>makes, or causes to be made, any false entry or 
statement in such books of account or other documents, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126598</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully omits, or causes to be omitted, any relevant 
entry or statement in such books of account or other documents, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1332785</tid>
<number>d</number>causes any other circumstance to exist which will have 
the effect of enabling such person to evade any tax, penalty or 
interest chargeable or imposable under this Act or the payment 
thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Failure to furnish returns of net wealth.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>203422</tid>
<number> 35B</number> Failure to furnish returns of net wealth. If a person 
wilfully fails to furnish in due time the return of his net wealth 
which he is required to furnish under sub- section
<section><tid>1863115</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 14 or  
by notice given under sub- section (2) of section 14 or under sub- 
section (1) of section 17, he shall be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>956075</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax, which would have been 
evaded if the failure had not been discovered, exceeds one 
hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to 
seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475233</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine:
Provided that a person shall not be proceeded against under this 
section for failure to furnish in due time the return of net wealth 
under sub- section (1) of section 14--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>956075</tid>
<number>i</number>for any assessment year commencing prior to the 1st day 
of April, <year>1975</year>; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475233</tid>
<number>ii</number>for any assessment year commencing on or after the 1st 
day of April, <year>1975</year>, if--

<subsubsection><tid>530250</tid>
<number>a</number>the return is furnished by him before the expiry of 
the assessment year; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>474407</tid>
<number>b</number>the tax payable by him on his net wealth determined 
on regular assessment does not exceed three thousand rupees.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>328454</tid>
<number>35C</number>Failure to produce accounts, records, etc. If a person 
wilfully fails to produce, or cause to be produced, on or before the 
date specified in any notice under sub- section (4) of section 16, such 
accounts, records and documents as are referred to in the notice, he 
shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one year or with fine equal to a sum calculated at a rate 
which shall not be less than four rupees or more than ten rupees for 
every day during which the default continues, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1074642</tid>
<number> 35D</number> False statement in verification, etc. made under certain 
provisions of the Act. If a person makes a statement in any 
verification under this Act (other than under section 34AB) or under 
any rule made thereunder, or delivers an account or statement which is 
false, and which he either knows or believes to be false, or does not 
believe to be true, he shall be punishable,--
<section><tid>1354947</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax which would have been 
evaded if the statement or account had been accepted as true, 
exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may 
extend to seven years and with fine;

</section>

<section><tid>657401</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>603519</tid>
<number>35E</number>False statement in verification mentioned in section 34AB. 
If a person makes a statement in a verification mentioned in section 
 34AB which is false, and which he either knows or believes to be 
false, or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or 
with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1859664</tid>
<number> 35F</number> Abetment of false return, etc. If a person abets or induces 
in any manner another person to make and deliver an account, statement 
or declaration relating to any net wealth chargeable to tax which is 
false and which he either knows to be false or does not believe to be 
true or to commit an offence under sub- section
<section><tid>1246385</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 35A, he  
shall be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>249220</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax, penalty or interest, 
which would have been evaded, if the declaration, account or 
statement had been accepted as true, or which is wilfully 
attempted to be evaded, exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six 
months but which may extend to seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1765977</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>783685</tid>
<number> 35G</number> Punishment for second and subsequent offences. If any person 
convicted of an offence under sub- section
<section><tid>1552820</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 35A or  
section 35B or section 35D or section 35F is again convicted of an 
offence under any of the aforesaid provisions, he shall be punishable 
for the second and for every subsequent offence with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months but 
which may extend to seven years and with fine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>75055</tid>
<number> 35H</number> Offences by Hindu undivided families.
<section><tid>1663206</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence  
under this Act has been committed by a Hindu undivided family, the 
Karta thereof shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
the Karta liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was 
committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1305254</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a Hindu undivided 
family and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the 
part of, any member thereof, such member shall also be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>318873</tid>
<number> 35I</number> Prosecutions to be at the instance of Commissioner and power 
of Commissioner to compound offences.
<section><tid>386934</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall not be  
proceeded against for an offence under this Act except at the instance 
of the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>429698</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, either before or after the institution 
of proceedings, compound any offence under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1827658</tid>
<number>35J</number>Certain offences to be non- cognizable. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>, an offence 
punishable under section 35A or section 35B or section 35D or section 
 35F shall be deemed to be non- cognizable within the meaning of that 
Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1638078</tid>
<number> 35K</number> Bar on prosecutions and on inadmissibility of evidence in 
certain circumstances.
<section><tid>1299565</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall not be proceeded against for  
an offence under section 35A or section 35D in relation to the 
assessment for an assessment year in respect of which the penalty 
imposed or imposable on him under clause (iii) of sub- section (1) of 
section 18 has been reduced or waived by an order under section 18B.

</section>

<section><tid>355865</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any proceeding for prosecution has been taken against 
any person under this Act, any statement made or account or other 
document produced by such person before any of the wealth- tax 
authorities specified in sections 8, 9, 10, 10A and 11 shall not be 
inadmissible as evidence for the purpose of such proceedings merely on 
the ground that such statement was made or such account or other 
document was produced in the belief that the penalty imposable would 
be reduced or waived under section 18B or that the offence in respect 
of which such proceeding was taken would be compounded.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1883092</tid>
<number>35L</number>Jurisdiction of courts. No court inferior to that of a 
Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try 
any offence under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>343504</tid>
<number>35M</number>Section 360 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> and the 
Probation of Offenders Act, <year>1958</year>, not to apply. Nothing contained in 
section 360 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>, or in the 
Probation of Offenders Act, <year>1958</year>, shall apply to a person convicted of 
an offence under this Act unless that person is under eighteen years 
of age.


</article>



<article><tid>68456</tid>
<number> 35N</number> Presumption as to books of account, etc., in certain cases.

<section><tid>901367</tid>
<number>1</number>Where during the course of any search made under section 37A, any  
books of account or other documents, articles or things including 
money have been found in the possession or control of any person and 
such books of account or other documents are tendered, or such 
articles or things including money are relied upon, by the prosecution 
in evidence against such person or against such person and the person 
referred to in section 35F for an offence under this Act, the 
provisions of sub- section (5) of section 37A shall, so far as may be, 
apply in relation to such books of account or other documents articles 
or things including money.

</section>

<section><tid>1912465</tid>
<number>2</number>Where--

<subsection><tid>320002</tid>
<number>i</number>any books of account or other documents taken into 
custody, from the possession or control of any person by any 
officer or authority under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- 
section (1) of section 37B, are delivered to the requisitioning 
officer under sub- section (2) of that section; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1972015</tid>
<number>ii</number>any note or inventory of any articles or things 
including money taken into custody, from the possession of any 
person, by any officer or authority under clause (c) of sub- 
section (1) of section 37B, is furnished to the requisitioning 
officer under sub- section (2) of that section,
and such books of account or other documents are tendered, or such 
note or inventory is relied upon, by the prosecution in evidence 
against such person or against such person and the person referred to 
in section 35F for an offence under this Act, the provisions of sub- 
section (5) of section 37A shall, so far as may be, apply in relation 
to such books of account or other documents or, as the case may be, 
the articles or things including money, covered by such note or 
inventory.]

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> xxx

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808M</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words", on conviction before a magistrate," omitted by Act 
46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 33 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 100 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75). 
4 Omitted by s. 101, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>197222</tid>
<number> 36A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to tender immunity from prosecution.
<section><tid>839463</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, if it is of opinion (the reasons for such  
  opinion being recorded in writing) that with a view to obtaining the 
evidence of any person appearing to have been directly or indirectly 
concerned in or privy to the concealment of particulars of net wealth 
or the evasion of payment of tax on net wealth, it is necessary or 
expedient so to do, tender to such person immunity from prosecution 
for any offence under this Act or under the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.) or under any other Central Act for the time being in force and 
also from the imposition of any penalty under this Act on condition of 
his making a full and true disclosure of the whole circumstances 
relating to the concealment of particulars of net wealth or evasion of 
payment of tax on net wealth.

</section>

<section><tid>797165</tid>
<number>2</number>A tender of immunity made to, and accepted by, the person 
concerned shall, to the extent to which the immunity extends, render 
him immune from prosecution for any offence in respect of which the 
tender was made or from the imposition of any penalty under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1108022</tid>
<number>3</number>If it appears to the Central Government that any person to 
whom immunity has been tendered under this section has not complied 
with the condition on which the tender was made or is wilfully 
concealing anything or is giving false evidence, the Central 
Government may record a finding to that effect, and thereupon the 
immunity shall be deemed to have been withdrawn, and any such person 
may be tried for the offence in respect of which the tender of 
immunity was made or for any other offence of which he appears to have 
been guilty in connection with the same matter and shall also become 
liable to the imposition of any penalty under this Act to which he 
would otherwise have been liable.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>986302</tid>
<number> 37</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to take evidence on oath, etc.
<section><tid>276283</tid>
<number>1</number>[ The Wealth- tax  
officer, Valuation Officer,] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Appellate Assistant Commissioner, 
Commissioner and the Appellate Tribunal shall, for the purposes of 
this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a court under the Code 
of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.), when trying a suit in respect 
of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>399789</tid>
<number>a</number>discovery and inspection;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1107624</tid>
<number>b</number>enforcing the attendance of any person, including any 
officer of a banking company and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1128968</tid>
<number>c</number>compelling the production of books of account and other 
documents; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1323548</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808N</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 35, ibid. for s. 37 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1294763</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of any other law for the 
time being in force, where a person to whom a summons is issued either 
to attend to give evidence or produce books of account or other 
documents at a certain place and time, intentionally omits to attend 
or produce the books of account or documents at the place or time, the 
authority empowered to issue such summons may impose upon him such 
fine not exceeding five hundred rupees, as it thinks fit, and the fine 
so levied may be recovered in the manner provided in Chapter VII of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1670512</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, any authority 
referred to in sub- section (1) may impound and retain in its custody 
for such period as it thinks fit any books of account or other 
documents produced before it in any proceeding under this Act;
Provided that <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a Wealth- tax Officer or a Valuation Officer] 
shall not--


<subsection><tid>934946</tid>
<number>a</number>impound any books of account or other documents without 
recording his reasons for so doing, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>900897</tid>
<number>b</number>retain in his custody any such books or documents for a 
period exceeding fifteen days (exclusive of holidays) 
without obtaining the approval of the Commissioner 
therefor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1142126</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding under this Act before a wealth- tax authority 
or the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the 
meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 196, 
of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1761161</tid>
<number> 37A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power of search and seizure.
<section><tid>811114</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Director of  
Inspection or the Commissioner or any such Deputy Director of 
Inspection or Inspecting Assistant Commissioner as may be empowered in 
this behalf by the Board, in consequence of information in his 
possession, has reason to believe that--

<subsection><tid>1672478</tid>
<number>a</number>any person to whom a notice under sub- section (4) of 
section 16 or a summons under section 37 was issued to produce, 
or cause to be produced, any books of account or other documents, 
has omitted or failed to produce, or cause to be produced, such 
books of account or other documents as required by such notice or 
summons, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85568</tid>
<number>b</number>any person to whom a notice or summons as aforesaid has 
been or might be issued will not, or would not, produce, or cause 
to be produced, any books of account or other documents which 
will be useful for, or relevant to, any proceeding under this 
Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>339636</tid>
<number>c</number>any person is in possession of any articles or things 
including money disproportionate to his known assets, particulars 
of which will be useful for, or relevant to, any proceeding under 
this Act,
then,--


<subsubsection><tid>541883</tid>
<number>A</number>the Director of Inspection or the Commissioner, as the 
case may be, may authorise any Deputy Director of Inspection, 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner, Assistant Director of 
Inspection or Wealth- tax Officer, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>291587</tid>
<number>B</number>such Deputy Director of Inspection or Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner may authorise any Assistant Director of 
Inspection or Wealth- tax Officer,
 (the officer so authorised in all cases being hereafter in this  
  section referred to as the authorised officer) to--


<subsubsubsection><tid>1737778</tid>
<number>i</number>enter and search any building, place, vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft where he has reason to suspect that such books of 
account or other documents, articles or things including money 
are kept;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>579078</tid>
<number>ii</number>search any person who has got out of, or is about to 
get into, or is in, the building, place, vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft, if the authorised officer has reason to suspect that 
such person has secreted about his person any such books of 
account or other documents, articles or things including money;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1347457</tid>
<number>iii</number>break open the lock of any door, box, locker, safe, 
almirah or other receptacle for exercising the powers conferred 
by clause (i) where the keys thereof are not available;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>263004</tid>
<number>iv</number>seize any such books of account or other documents;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>284721</tid>
<number>v</number>place marks of identification on any such books of 
account or other documents or make, or cause to be made, extracts 
or copies therefrom;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1825710</tid>
<number>vi</number>make a note or an inventory of any articles or things 
including money found which, in his opinion, will be useful for, 
or relevant to, any proceeding under this Act:
Provided that where any building, place, vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft referred to in clause (i) is within the area of jurisdiction 
of any Commissioner but such Commissioner has no jurisdiction over the 
person referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c) of this 
sub- section, then, notwithstanding anything contained in section 10, 
it shall be competent for him to exercise the powers under this sub- 
section in all cases where he has reason to believe that any delay in 
getting the authorisation from the Commissioner having jurisdiction 
over such person may be prejudicial to the interests of the revenue.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1608391</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any Commissioner, in consequence of information in his 
possession, has reason to suspect that any books of account or other 
documents, articles or things including money in respect of which an 
officer has been authorised by the Director of Inspection or 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner as may be empowered in this behalf 
by the Board to take action under clauses (i) to (vi) of sub- section 
 (1) are kept in any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft not 
mentioned in the authorisation under sub- section (1), such 
Commissioner may, notwithstanding anything contained in section 10, 
authorise the said officer to take action under any of the clauses 
aforesaid in respect of such building, place, vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft.

</section>

<section><tid>1713426</tid>
<number>3</number>The authorised officer may requisition the services of any 
police officer or of any officer of the Central Government, or of both 
to assist him for all or any of the purposes specified in sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) and it shall be the duty or every such officer 
to comply with such requisition.

</section>

<section><tid>246210</tid>
<number>4</number>The authorised officer may, during the course of the search 
or seizure, examine on oath any person who is found to be in 
possession or control of any books of account or other documents, 
articles or things including money and any statement made by such 
person during such examination may thereafter be used in evidence in 
any proceeding under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1258587</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any books of account or other documents, articles or 
things including money are found in the possession or control of any 
person in the course of a search, it may be presumed that--

<subsection><tid>1091729</tid>
<number>i</number>such books of account or other documents, articles or 
things including money belong to such person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1163439</tid>
<number>ii</number>the contents of such books of account or other 
documents are true; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130209</tid>
<number>iii</number>the signature and every other part of such books of 
account or other documents which purport to be in the hand- 
writing of any particular person or which may reasonably be 
assumed to have been signed by, or to be in the handwriting of, 
any particular person, are in that person' s handwriting, and in 
the case of a document stamped, executed or attested, that it was 
duly stamped and executed or attested by the person by whom it 
purports to have been so executed or attested.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1297504</tid>
<number>6</number>The books of account or other documents seized under sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (2) shall not be retained by the authorised 
officer for a period exceeding one hundred and eighty days from the 
date of the seizure unless the reasons for retaining the same are 
recorded by him in writing and the approval of the Commissioner for 
such retention is obtained:
Provided that the Commissioner shall not authorise the retention 
of the books of account or other documents for a period exceeding 
thirty days after all the proceedings under this Act in respect of the 
years for which the books of account or other documents are relevant 
are completed.


</section>

<section><tid>1731712</tid>
<number>7</number>The person from whose custody any books of account or other 
documents are seized under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) may make 
copies thereof, or take extracts therefrom, in the presence of the 
authorised officer or any other person empowered by him in this behalf 
at such place and time as the authorised officer may appoint in this 
behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1207621</tid>
<number>8</number>Where the authorised officer has no jurisdiction over the 
person referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c) of sub- 
section (1), the books of account or other documents seized under that 
sub- section shall be handed over by the authorised officer to the 
Wealth- tax Officer having jurisdiction over such person within a 
period of fifteen days of such seizure and thereupon the powers 
exercisable by the authorised officer under sub- section (6) or sub- 
section (7) shall be exercisable by such Wealth- tax Officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1625022</tid>
<number>9</number>If a person legally entitled to the books of account or other 
documents seized under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) objects for 
any reason to the approval given by the Commissioner under sub- section 
 (6), he may make an application to the Board stating therein the 
reasons for such objection and requesting for the return of the books 
of account or other documents.

</section>

<section><tid>816558</tid>
<number>10</number>On receipt of the application under sub- section (9), the 
Board may, after giving the applicant an opportunity of being heard, 
pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1365886</tid>
<number>11</number>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> 
relating to searches shall apply, so far as may be, to searches under 
this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1760407</tid>
<number>12</number>The Board may make rules in relation to searches or seizure 
under this section; and in particular and without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for the 
procedure to be followed by the authorised officer--

<subsection><tid>118401</tid>
<number>i</number>for obtaining ingress into any building, place, vessel, 
vehicle or aircraft to be searched where free ingress thereto is 
not available;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1144519</tid>
<number>ii</number>for ensuring the safe custody of any books of account 
or other documents seized.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>247335</tid>
<number> 37B</number> Power to requisition books of account, etc.
<section><tid>97846</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
Director of Inspection or the Commissioner, in consequence of 
information in his possession, has reason to believe that--

<subsection><tid>1223801</tid>
<number>a</number>any person to whom a notice under sub- section (4) of 
section 16 or a summons under section 37 was issued to produce, 
or cause to be produced, any books of account or other documents 
has omitted or failed to produce, or cause to be produced, such 
books of account or other documents as required by such notice or 
summons and the said books of account or other documents have 
been taken into custody by any officer or authority under any 
other law for the time being in force, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>749098</tid>
<number>b</number>any books of account or other documents will be useful 
for, or relevant to, any proceeding under this Act and any person 
to whom a notice or summons as aforesaid has been or might be 
issued will not, or would not, produce or cause to be produced 
such books of account or other documents on the return of such 
books of account or other documents by any officer or authority 
by whom or which such books of account or other documents have 
been taken into custody under any other law for the time being in 
force, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1388776</tid>
<number>c</number>any articles or things including money disproportionate 
to the known assets of any person, particulars of which will be 
useful for, or relevant to, any proceeding under this Act, have 
been taken into custody by any officer or authority, under any 
other law for the time being in force, from the possession of 
such person,
then, the Director of Inspection or the Commissioner may authorise any 
Deputy Director of Inspection, Inspecting Assistant Commissioner. 
Assistant Director of Inspection or Wealth- tax Officer (hereafter in  
  this section referred to as the requisitioning officer) to require 
such officer or authority,--


<subsubsection><tid>1848811</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case falling under clause (a) or clause (b), to 
deliver such books of account or other documents to the 
requisitioning officer;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>794866</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case falling under clause (c), to furnish a note 
or an inventory of such articles or things including money to the 
requisitioning officer.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>384405</tid>
<number>2</number>On a requisition being made under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1106518</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case falling under clause (a) or clause (b) of that 
sub- section, the officer or authority referred to therein shall 
deliver the books of account or other documents to the 
requisitioning officer either forthwith or when such officer or 
authority is of the opinion that it is no longer necessary to 
retain the same in his or its custody;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>692875</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case falling under clause (c), the officer or 
authority referred to therein shall furnish the note or inventory 
to the requisitioning officer within a reasonable period.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>99260</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any books of account or other documents have been 
delivered to the requisitioning officer, the provisions of sub- 
sections (5) to (12)  (both inclusive) of section 37A shall, so far as 
may be, apply as if such books of account or other documents had been 
seized under sub- section (1) of that section by the requisitioning 
officer from the custody of the person referred to in clause (a) or 
clause (b), as the case may be, of sub- section (1) of this section and 
as if for the words" the authorised officer" occurring in any of the 
aforesaid sub- sections, the words" the requisitioning officer" were 
substituted."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808P</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 36 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1975</year>, s. 102 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>826378</tid>
<number>38</number>Information, returns and statements. Where, for the purposes 
of determining the wealth- tax payable by any person, it appears 
necessary for the Wealth- tax Officer to obtain any statement or 
information from any, individual, company, firm, Hindu undivided 
family or other person, the Wealth- tax Officer may serve a notice 
requiring such individual, company, firm, Hindu undivided family or 
other person, on or before a date to be therein specified, to furnish 
such statement or information on the points specified in the notice, 
and the individual or the principal officer concerned or the manager 
of the Hindu undivided family, as the case may be, shall, 
notwithstanding anything in any law to the contrary, be bound to 
furnish such statement or information to the Wealth- tax Officer:
Provided that no legal practitioner shall be bound to furnish any 
statement or information under this section based on any professional 
communications made to him otherwise than as permitted by section 126 
of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>.).



</article>



<article><tid>253429</tid>
<number> 38A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Powers of Valuation Officer, etc.
<section><tid>268903</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes  
of this Act, a Valuation Officer or any overseer, surveyor or assessor 
authorised by him in this behalf may, subject to any rules made in 
this behalf and at such reasonable times as may be prescribed,--

<subsection><tid>598979</tid>
<number>a</number>enter any land within the limits of the area assigned to 
the Valuation Officer, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1837794</tid>
<number>b</number>enter any land, building or other place belonging to or 
occupied by any person in connection with whose assessment a 
reference has been made section 16A to the Valuation Officer, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>201074</tid>
<number>c</number>inspect any asset in respect of which a reference under 
section 16A has been made to the Valuation Officer,
and require any person in charge of, or in occupation or possession 
of, such land, building or other place or asset to afford him the 
necessary facility to survey or inspect such land, building or other 
place or asset or estimate its value or inspect any books of account, 
document or record which may be relevant for the valuation of such 
land, building or other place or asset and gather other particulars 
relating to such land, building or other place or asset;

Provided that no Valuation Officer, overseer, surveyor or 
assessor shall enter any building or place referred to in clause (b) 
or inspect any asset referred to in clause (c)  (unless with the  
consent of the person in charge of, or in occupation or possession of, 
  such building, place or asset) without previously giving to such 
person at least two days' notice in writing of his intention to do so.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1781461</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person who, under sub- section (1), is required to afford 
any facility to the Valuation Officer or the overseer, surveyor or 
assessor, either refuses or evades to afford such facility, the 
Valuation Officer shall have all the powers under sub- sections (1) and 
 (2) of section 37 for enforcing compliance of the requirements made."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>121113</tid>
<number>39</number>Effect to transfer of authorities on pending proceedings. 
Whenever in respect of any proceeding under this Act wealth- tax 
authority ceases to exercise jurisdiction and is successive by another 
who has and exercises such jurisdiction, the authority so succeeding 
may continue the proceeding from the stage at which the proceeding was 
left by his predecessor:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that the assessee concerned may demand that before 
the proceeding is so continued the previous proceeding or any part 
thereof be re- opened or that before any order of assessment is passed 
against him, he be re- heard.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808Q</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 37 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1972</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 15- 11- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>857596</tid>
<number>40</number>Computation of periods of limitation. In computing the period 
of limitation prescribed for an appeal under this Act or for an 
application under section 27, the day on which the order complained of 
was made and the time requisite for obtaining a copy of such order 
shall be excluded.


</article>



<article><tid>1915412</tid>
<number> 41</number> Service of notice.
<section><tid>1225071</tid>
<number>1</number>A notice or a requisition under this  
Act may be served on the person therein named either by post or as if 
it were a summons issued by a court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
 <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.).

</section>

<section><tid>1613702</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such notice or requisition may, in the case of a firm or 
a Hindu undivided family, be addressed to any member of the firm or to 
the manager or any adult male member of the family, and in the case of 
any other association of persons be addressed to the principal officer 
thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>211616</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> After a finding of total partition has been recorded by 
the Wealth- tax Officer under section 20 in respect of any Hindu 
family, notices under this Act in respect of the net wealth of the 
Hindu family shall be served on the person who was the last manager of 
the Hindu family, or, if such person is dead, then on all surviving 
adults who were members of the Hindu family immediately before the 
partition.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1670383</tid>
<number>42</number>[ Prohibition of disclosure of information.] Rep. by the 
Finance Act, <year>1964</year> (5 of <year>1964</year>), s. 50 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>160449</tid>
<number> 42A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Publication of information respecting assessees.
<section><tid>1574690</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient 
in the public interest to publish the names of any assessees and any 
other particulars relating to any proceedings[ or prosecutions] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
under this Act in respect of such assessees, it may cause to be 
published such names and particulars in such manner as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>723207</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> No publication under this section shall be made in 
relation to any penalty imposed under this Act until the time for 
presenting an appeal to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner has 
expired without an appeal having been presented or the appeal, if 
presented, has been disposed of."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808R</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 50, for ss. 42A and 42B (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1964</year>), Ss. 42A and 42B were ins. by Act 28 of <year>1960</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1960</year>). 
3 Ins and subs. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 103 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>450003</tid>
<number>42B</number>Disclosure of information respecting assessees. Where a 
person makes an application to the Commissioner in the prescribed from 
for any information relating to any assessee in respect of any 
assessment made under this Act, the Commissioner may, if he is 
satisfied that it is in the public interest so to do, furnish or cause 
to be furnished the information asked for in respect of that 
assessment only and his decision in this behalf shall be final and 
shall not be called in question in any court of law.]


</article>



<article><tid>314725</tid>
<number>42C</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Return of wealth, etc., not to be invalid on certain 
grounds. No return of wealth, assessment, notice, summons or other 
proceeding furnished or made or issued or taken or purported to have 
been furnished or made or issued or taken in pursuance of any of the 
provisions of this Act shall be invalid or shall be deemed to be 
invalid merely by reason of any mistake, defect or omission in such 
return of wealth, assessment, notice, summons or other proceeding if 
such return of wealth, assessment, notice, summons or other proceeding 
is in substance and effect in conformity with or according to the 
intent and purpose of this Act."]


</article>



<article><tid>777944</tid>
<number>43</number>Bar of jurisdiction. No suit shall lie in any civil court to 
set aside or modify any assessment made under this Act, and no 
prosecution, suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Government or] any officer of the Government for anything in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>907327</tid>
<number> 44</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appearance before wealth- tax authorities by authorised 
representatives.
<section><tid>698256</tid>
<number>1</number>Any assessee who is entitled to or required to  
attend before any Wealth- tax authority or the Appellate Tribunal in 
connection with any proceeding under this Act, except where he is 
required under this Act to attend in person, may attend by a person 
who would be entitled to represent him before any income- tax authority 
or the Appellate Tribunal under section 288 of the Income- tax Act.

</section>

<section><tid>985501</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything in sub- section (1)--

<subsection><tid>1051181</tid>
<number>i</number>no person who has been convicted of an offence connected 
with any wealth- tax proceeding or on whom a penalty has 
been imposed under this Act other than a penalty 
imposed on him under clause (i) or clause (ii) of sub- 
section (1) of section 18 shall be qualified to 
represent an assessee under sub- section (1) for such 
time as the Commissioner may be order determine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1072841</tid>
<number>ii</number>if any person who is not a legal practitioner or a 
chartered accountant, if found guilty of misconduct in 
connection with any wealth- tax proceeding by the 
prescribed authority, the prescribed authority may 
direct that he shall thenceforth be disqualified to 
represent an assessee under sub- section (1);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1272527</tid>
<number>iii</number>no person not qualified to represent an assessee under 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>.), the 
Estate Duty Act, <year>1953</year> (34 of <year>1953</year>.), the Expenditure- 
tax Act, <year>1957</year> (29 of <year>1957</year>.), or the Gift- tax
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808S</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 50 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 39, for s. 44 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 104 (w. e. f. 1- 10- 75).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>.), shall be entitled to appear on 
behalf of any assessee under this Act:

Provided that any order or direction under clause (i) or clause 
 (ii) shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:--


<subsubsection><tid>1626660</tid>
<number>a</number>no such order or direction shall be made in respect of 
any person unless he has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>136224</tid>
<number>b</number>any person against whom any such order or direction is 
made may, within one month of the making of the order 
or direction, appeal to the Board to have the order or 
direction cancelled; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1297910</tid>
<number>c</number>no such order or direction shall take effect until the 
expiration of one month from the making thereof, or, 
where an appeal has been preferred, until the disposal 
of the appeal.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1529510</tid>
<number>44A</number>Agreement for avoidance or relief of double taxation with 
respect to wealth- tax. The Central Government may enter into any 
agreement with the Government of any reciprocating country for the 
avoidance or relief of double taxation with respect to wealth- tax 
payable under this Act and under the corresponding law in force in the 
reciprocating country and may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make such provision as may be necessary for implementing the 
agreement.
Explanation.-- The expression" reciprocating country" for the 
purposes of this Act means any country which the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
reciprocating country.



</article>



<article><tid>1728815</tid>
<number> 44B</number> Countries with which no agreement exists. Where the net 
wealth of any assessee includes any foreign wealth and he proves that, 
in respect of such foreign wealth, he has paid in any country, with 
which there is no reciprocal arrangement under section 44A for the 
relief or avoidance of double taxation, a tax in respect of wealth, 
under the law in force in that country, he shall be entitled to the 
deduction from the Indian wealth- tax payable by him of a sum 
calculated on such doubly taxed foreign wealth at the Indian rate of 
tax or the rate of tax of the said country, whichever is the lower, or 
at the Indian rate of tax if both the rates are equal.
Explanation.-- In this section--

<section><tid>1396985</tid>
<number>1</number>the expression" Indian wealth- tax" means wealth- tax 
charged in accordance with the provisions of this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808T</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1636335</tid>
<number>2</number>the expression" Indian rate of tax" means the rate 
determined by dividing the amount of Indian wealth- tax 
after deduction of any relief due under the provisions 
of this Act but before the deduction of any relief due 
under this section by the net wealth;

</section>

<section><tid>309480</tid>
<number>3</number>the expression" rate of tax of the said country" means 
any tax in respect of wealth, actually paid in the said 
country, in accordance with the corresponding laws in 
force in the said country after deduction of all relief 
due, but before deduction of any relief due in the said 
country in respect of double taxation, divided by the 
whole amount of the wealth assessed in the said 
country;

</section>

<section><tid>638802</tid>
<number>4</number>the expression" foreign wealth" in relation to any 
assessee means the value of all his assets located in 
any country outside India as reduced by the value of 
his debts in that country.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>168854</tid>
<number>44C</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rounding off of net wealth. The amount of net wealth 
computed in accordance with the foregoing provisions of this Act shall 
be rounded off to the nearest multiple of one hundred rupees and, for 
this purpose, any part of a rupee consisting of paise shall be ignored 
and thereafter, if such amount contains a part of one hundred rupees, 
then, if such part is fifty rupees or more, the amount shall be 
increased to the next higher amount which is a multiple of one hundred 
and, if such part is less than fifty rupees, the amount shall be 
reduced to the next lower amount which is a multiple of one hundred; 
and the amount so rounded off shall be deemed to be the net wealth of 
the assessee for the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1919931</tid>
<number>44D</number>Rounding off of tax, etc. The amount of wealth- tax, 
interest, penalty, fine or any other sum payable, and the amount of 
refund due, under the provisions of this Act, shall be rounded off to 
the nearest rupee and, for this purpose, where such amount contains a 
part of a rupee consisting of paise, then, if such part is fifty paise 
or more, it shall be increased to one rupee, and if such part is less 
than fifty paise, it shall be ignored.]


</article>



<article><tid>651980</tid>
<number> 45</number> Act not to apply in certain cases. The provisions of this Act 
shall not apply to--
<section><tid>287632</tid>
<number>a</number>a banking company as defined in section 5 of the Banking 
Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>.);
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808U</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>170784</tid>
<number>b</number>an insurer within the meaning of the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> 
 (4 of <year>1938</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1563909</tid>
<number>c</number>any company established with the object of financing, 
whether by way of making loans or advances to, or 
subscribing to the capital of, private industrial 
enterprises in India, in any case where the Central 
Government has made or agreed to make to the company a 
special advance for the purpose or has guaranteed or 
agreed to guarantee the payment of moneys borrowed by 
the company from any institution outside India;

</section>

<section><tid>895019</tid>
<number>d</number>any company established with the object of carrying on 
an industrial undertaking in India in any case where 
the company is not formed by the splitting up, or the 
reconstruction of a business already in existence or by 
the transfer to a new business of any building, 
machinery or plant used in a business which was being 
previously carried on:
Provided that the exemption granted by clause (d) 
shall apply to any such company as is referred to 
therein only for a period of five successive assessment 
years commencing with the assessment year next 
following the date on which the company is established, 
which period shall, in the case of a company 
established before the commencement of this Act, be 
computed in accordance with this Act from the date of 
its establishment as if this Act had been in force on 
and from the date of its establishment;

Explanation.-- For the purposes of clause (d), 
" industrial undertaking" means an undertaking engaged 
in the manufacture, production or processing of goods 
or articles or in mining or in the generation or 
distribution of electricity or any other form of power;


</section>

<section><tid>1127998</tid>
<number>e</number>any company solely engaged in the business of 
transporting goods or passengers by ships:

</section>

<section><tid>505058</tid>
<number>f</number>any company registered under section 25 of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>.).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>225754</tid>
<number> 46</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>888108</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, by notification in  
the Official Gazette make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808V</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>914419</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1284504</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the market value of any asset may be 
determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>748576</tid>
<number>b</number>the form in which returns under this Act shall be made 
and the manner in which they shall be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607820</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which appeals and applications under this 
Act may be made, and the manner in which they shall be 
verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1368280</tid>
<number>d</number>the form of any notice of demand under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>289044</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the procedure to be followed in calculating interest 
payable by assessees or interest payable by the 
Government to assessees under any provision of this 
Act, including the rounding off of the period for which 
such interest is to be calculated in cases where such 
period includes a fraction of a month, and specifying 
the circumstances in which and the extent to which 
petty amounts of interest payable by assessees may be 
ignored;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1851619</tid>
<number>e</number>the areas for which lists of valuers may be drawn up;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1205927</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
for the purposes of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1850720</tid>
<number>3</number>The powers to make rules conferred by this section shall on 
the first occasion of the exercise thereof include the power to give 
retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not 
earlier than the date of commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1768494</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Central Government shall cause every rule made under 
this Act to be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive 
sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so 
laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making 
any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>808W</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 66 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1964</year>, s. 40, for sub- section (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



 </act>