<act><title>

THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the FORMS 
    AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING A COPY OF ORDER OF ARREST OF A PERSON ALONG 
    WITH THE MATERIAL TO THE ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) 
    RULES, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Money-laundering (the Forms and the 
    Manner of Forwarding a Copy of Order of Arrest of a Person along with the 
    Material to the Adjudicating Authority and its Period of Retention) Rules, 
    2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Prevention of 
    Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003),  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Adjudicating Authority” means an 
    Adjudicating Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Arresting Officer” means the Director, 
    Deputy Director, Assistant Director or any other officer, authorized in this 
    behalf by the Central Government by general or special order to exercise the 
    power to arrest any person under sub-section (1) of section 19 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “designated officer” means the officer 
    designated by the Adjudicating Authority for the purpose of sub-rule (1) of 
    rule 4;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Director” or “Deputy Director” or 
    “Assistant Director” means a Director or a Deputy Director or an Assistant 
    Director, as the case may be, appointed under sub-section (1) of section 49 
    of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “Form” means forms appended to these 
    rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “material” means any information or 
    material in the possession of the Director or Deputy Director or Assistant 
    Director or any authorised officer, as the case may be, on the basis of 
    which he has recorded reasons under sub-section (1) of section 19 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “order” means the order of arrest of a 
    person and includes the grounds for such arrest under sub-section (1) of 
    section 19 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “section” means a section of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 
    Act shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Manner 
    of forwarding a copy of the order of arrest and the material to the 
    Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Arresting Officer shall prepare an index of the copy of the order and the 
    material in possession and sign each page of such index of the copy of the 
    order and the material and shall also write a letter while forwarding such 
    index, order and the material to the Adjudicating Authority in a sealed 
    envelope.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Arresting Officer shall place an acknowledgement slip in Form I appended to 
    these rules inside the envelope before sealing it.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Arresting Officer shall indicate a reference number and date of despatch on 
    the sealed envelope.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The sealed 
    envelope shall be marked “Confidential” and “To be opened by the addressee 
    only”, the complete address of the Adjudicating Authority including his name 
    shall be mentioned on the sealed envelope with the official seal.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Arresting Officer shall place the sealed envelope inside an outer envelope, 
    along with an acknowledgement slip in Form II appended to these rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The outer 
    envelope shall be sealed and complete address of the Adjudicating Authority 
    shall be mentioned on the sealed outer envelope.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Arresting Officer shall maintain registers and other records such as 
    acknowledgement slip register, dak register for the purposes of this rule 
    and shall ensure that necessary entries are made in the register immediately 
    as soon the copy of the order and the material are forwarded to the 
    Adjudicating Authority.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Acknowledgement of receipt of the copy of the order of arrest and the 
    material by the Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of the outer sealed envelope along with Form II, the Adjudicating 
    Authority or in his absence, the designated officer of the office of 
    Adjudicating Authority shall forward Form II duly filled in, signed and his 
    name legibly written below his signature. The seal of the office of the 
    Adjudicating Authority shall be affixed before forwarding the Form II to the 
    Arresting Officer as a token of receipt of the sealed envelope.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Adjudicating Authority shall, on opening of the sealed envelope, forward 
    Form I duly filled in, signed and his name legibly written below his 
    signature. The seal of the office of the Adjudicating Authority shall be 
    affixed before forwarding the Form I to the Arresting Officer as a token of 
    receipt of the copy of order of the arrest and the material.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Adjudicating Authority shall maintain registers and other records such as 
    acknowledgement slip register, dak register, and register showing details of 
    receipt of the copy of the order of the arrest along with the material for 
    the purposes of this rule and shall ensure that necessary entries are made 
    in the registers immediately on receipt of such order and the material.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Period 
    of retention of a copy of the order of arrest and the material by the 
    Adjudicating Authority.—The 
    Adjudicating Authority shall retain the copy of order of the arrest and the 
    material for a period of ten years, or, if before the expiry of the said 
    period of ten years,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    any proceedings under section 8 of the 
    Act have been commenced, until the disposal of such proceedings; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    where an appeal has been preferred to 
    the Appellate Tribunal under section 26 of the Act, until the disposal of 
    such appeal by the Appellate Tribunal; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    where an appeal has been filed in the 
    High Court under section 42 of the Act, until the disposal of such appeal by 
    the High Court;  
 
whichever is 
    later.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Forms of 
    records.—The Arresting Officer 
    while exercising powers under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 19 of the Act shall 
    sign the Arrest Order in Form III appended to these Rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be 
    referred to the Central Government and the decision of the Central 
    Government shall be final.  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the FORMS AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING A 
    COPY OF ORDER OF ARREST OF A PERSON ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL TO THE 
    ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 


FORM I
 


[See sub-rule (2) of rule 3]
 


ACKNOWLEDGEMENT SLIP
 


Serial Number.....................
 


Received a copy of the order of arrest 
    of..................................... [Name of the person arrested] 
    bearing No. ...............................................dated 
    ............................ from the Director/Deputy Director/Assistant 
    Director/authorized officer on ......................... [date] 
    at............ [time]. 
 

 
 


Signature of the Adjudicating Authority
 



    Date............................                       
 



                                                         
    ....................................................
 


Name of the Adjudicating Authority       
    
 


Office seal                                       
    
 


To
 



    .................................................... 
 


[Arresting Officer] 
 


Address: ............................ 
 


................................................... 
 


................................................... 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the FORMS AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING A 
    COPY OF ORDER OF ARREST OF A PERSON ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL TO THE 
    ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 


FORM II 
 


[See sub-rule (5) of rule 3]
 


ACKNOWLEDGEMENT SLIP
 


Serial Number.................... 
 


Received a sealed envelope bearing No. 
    .............................. dated............... from the Director/Deputy 
    Director/Assistant Director/authorized officer on ................. [date] 
    at............ [time]. 
 



 


Signature of the Adjudicating Authority/ 

                                                                  designated officer of the office of         
     

                                                                      
    Adjudicating Authority.                       
    
 



    ....................................................
 


Name of the Adjudicating Authority/ 

                                                                                
    designated officer of the office of      

                                                                               
    Adjudicating Authority.                   
    
 


Office seal                                    
    
 


 To 
 


......................................... 
 


[Arresting Officer] 
 


Address: 
 


......................................... 
 


......................................... 
 


......................................... 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the FORMS AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING A 
    COPY OF ORDER OF ARREST OF A PERSON ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL TO THE 
    ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 


FORM III 
 


(See rule 6) 
 


ARREST ORDER 
 


Whereas, 
    I ............................. Director/Deputy Director/ Assistant 
    Director/Officer authorised in this behalf by the Central Government, have 
    reason to believe that.............................[name of the person 
    arrested]  resident of..................... has been guilty of an offence 
    punishable under the provisions of the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 
    2002 (15 of 2003);  
 


Now, 
    Therefore, in exercise of the powers conferred on me under 
    sub-section (1) of section 19 of the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 
    2002 (15 of 2003), I hereby arrest the said 
    .............................................. [name of the person arrested] 
    at................ hours on .................. and he has been informed of 
    the grounds for such arrest.  
 


Dated at ............ on this ............ day 
    of ................. Two thousand ..................................... 
 

 
 


Arresting Officer
 


Signature with Seal
 


To
 


.........................................
 


.........................................
 


[Name and complete address of the person 
    arrested]
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>