<act><title>The 
      Information Technology (Qualification and Experience of Adjudicating 
      Officers and Manner of Holding Enquiry) Rules, 
      20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>a</number> These rules may be called the Information 
      Technology (Qualification and Experience of Adjudicating Officers and 
      Manner of Holding Enquiry) Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> These shall come into force on the date of 
      their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the context otherwise 
      requires,—  
 <section><number>a</number>   “Act” means the 
      Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000);  
 </section><section><number>b</number>   “Adjudicating Officer” 
      means an adjudicating officer appointed under sub-section (1) of section 
      46 of the Act;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>   “Proforma” means a 
      proforma appended to these rules;  
 </section><section><number>d</number>   words and expressions 
      used herein and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meaning 
      respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Eligibility for Adjudicating 
      Officer.—Whereas the purpose 
      and intent of section 46(3) of I T Act is that the Adjudicating Officer 
      should be a person so qualified and experienced to take decisions with a 
      view in relation to information technology aspects as well as in a 
      position to determine the complaints keeping in view the legal or judicial 
      mannerism on the principle of compensation of damages of I T Act.  
 A 
      person shall not be qualified for appointment as Adjudicating Officer 
      unless the person—  
 <section><number>a</number>   possesses a University 
      Graduate Bachelor Degree or equivalent, recognized by Central 
      Government/State Government for the purpose of recruitment to Grade I 
      Service in a Government Department through Union/State Public Service 
      Commission;   
 </section><section><number>b</number>   possesses information 
      technology experience in the areas of relevance to public interface with 
      Central/State Government functioning and experience obtained though the 
      in-service training imparting competence to operate computer system to 
      send and receive e-mails or other information through the computer 
      network, exposure and awareness about the method of carrying information, 
      data, sound, images or other electronic records through the medium of 
      network including Internet;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>   possesses legal or 
      judicial experience to discharge responsibilities connected with the role 
      of Central/State Government in respect of making decisions or orders in 
      relation to administration of laws as a District Magistrate, or Additional 
      District Magistrate or Sub-Divisional Magistrate or an Executive 
      Magistrate or in other administrative or quasi-judicial capacity for a 
      cumulative period of 5 years;  
 </section><section><number>d</number>   is working and holding 
      a post in Grade I in Government Department either in State 
      Government/Union Territories to perform functional duty and discharge job 
      responsibility in the field of information technology;  
 </section><section><number>e</number>   is an in-service 
      officer not below the rank of Director to the Government of India or an 
      equivalent officer of State Government.  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Scope and manner of holding 
      inquiry.—
<section><number>a</number> The Adjudicating 
      Officers shall exercise jurisdiction in respect of the contraventions in 
      relation to Chapter IX of I T Act, 2000 and the matter or matters or 
      places or area or areas in a State or Union Territory of the posting of 
      the person.  
 </section><section><number>b</number> The complaint shall be made to the 
      Adjudicating Officer of the State or Union Territory on the basis of 
      location of Computer System, Computer Network as defined in sub-section 2 
      of section 75 of I T Act on a plain paper on the proforma attached to 
      these rules together with the fee payable calculated on the basis of 
      damages claimed by way of compensation.  
 </section><section><number>c</number> The Adjudicating Officer, shall issue a 
      notice together with all the documents to all the necessary parties to the 
      proceedings, fixing a date and time for further proceedings. The notice 
      shall contain such particulars as far as may be as to the time and place 
      of the alleged contravention, and the person (if any) against whom, or the 
      thing (if any) in respect of which, it was committed.  
 </section><section><number>d</number> On the date so fixed, the Adjudicating 
      Officer shall explain to such person or persons to whom notice is issued 
      about the contravention alleged to have been committed in relation to any 
      of the provisions of the Act or of any rule, regulation, direction or 
      order made thereunder.   
 </section><section><number>e</number> If the person in respect of whom notice is 
      issued pleads guilty, the Adjudicating Officer shall record the plea, and 
      may impose penalty or award such compensation as he thinks fit in 
      accordance with the provisions of the Act, rules, regulations, order or 
      directions made thereunder.   
 </section><section><number>f</number> Alternatively on the date fixed the person 
      or persons against whom a matter is filed may show cause why an enquiry 
      should not be held in the alleged contravention or that why the report 
      alleging the contravention should be dismissed.   
 </section><section><number>g</number> The Adjudicating Officer on the basis of the 
      report of the matter, investigation report (if any), other documents and 
      on the basis of submissions shall form an opinion that there is sufficient 
      cause for holding an enquiry or that the report into the matter should be 
      dismissed and on that basis shall either by order dismiss the report of 
      the matter, or shall determine to hear the matter.  
 </section><section><number>h</number> If any person or persons fails, neglects or 
      refuses to appear, or present himself as required by sub-rule (d), before 
      the Adjudicating Officer, the Adjudicating Officer shall proceed with the 
      inquiry in the absence of such person or persons after recording the 
      reasons for doing so.  
 </section><section><number>i</number> At any time or on receipt of a report of 
      contravention from an aggrieved person, or by a Government agency or 
      suo-moto, the Adjudicating Officer, may get the matter or the 
      report investigated from an officer in the Office of Controller or 
      CERT-IND or from the concerned Deputy Superintendent of Police, to 
      ascertain more facts and whether prima facie there is a case for 
      adjudicating on the matter or not.  
 </section><section><number>j</number> The Adjudicating Officer, shall fix a date 
      and time for production of documents or evidence and for this purpose may 
      also rely on electronic records or communications and as far as may be, 
      shall use or make available the infrastructure for promoting on-line 
      settlement of enquiry or disputes or for taking evidence including the 
      services of an adjudicating officer and infrastructure in another State. 
        
 </section><section><number>k</number> As far as possible, every application shall 
      be heard and decided in four months and the whole matter in six months. 
        
 </section><section><number>l</number> Adjudicating Officer, when convinced that 
      the scope of the case extends to the Offence(s) (under Chapter XI of I T 
      Act) instead of contravention, needing appropriate punishment instead of 
      mere financial penalty, should transfer the case to the Magistrate having 
      jurisdiction to try the case, through Presiding 
    Officer.
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Order of the Adjudicating 
      Officer.—
<section><number>a</number> If, upon 
      consideration of the evidence produced before the Adjudicating Officer and 
      other records and submissions, the Adjudicating Officer is satisfied that 
      the person has become liable to pay damages by way of compensation or to 
      pay penalty under any of the provisions of the Act or rules, regulations, 
      directions or orders, the Adjudicating Officer may, by order in writing, 
      order payment of damages by way of compensation or impose such penalty, as 
      deemed fit.  
 </section><section><number>b</number> While adjudging the quantum of compensation 
      or penalty, the Adjudicating Officer shall have due regard to the 
      following factors, namely:—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   the amount of gain of 
      unfair advantage, wherever quantifiable, made as a result of the 
      default;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   the amount of loss 
      caused to any person as a result of the default;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   the repetitive nature 
      of the default.  
       
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Copy of the order.—Adjudicating Officers shall deliver a certified 
      copy of the order to the complainant and respondent.  
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Service of notices and 
      orders.—A notice or an order 
      issued under these rules shall be served on the person in any of the 
      following manners, that is to say:—  
 <section><number>a</number>   by delivering or 
      tendering it to that person or the person’s authorized agent in an 
      electronic form provided that there is sufficient evidence of actual 
      delivery of the electronic record to the concerned person; or  
 </section><section><number>b</number>   by sending it to the 
      person by registered post with acknowledgement due to the address of his 
      place of residence or the last known place of residence or business place;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>   if it cannot be served 
      under clause (a) or (b) above then by affixing it, in the presence of two 
      witnesses, on the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the 
      premises in which that person resides or is known to have last resided, or 
      carried on business or personally works or last worked for gain.   
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Fee.—Every complaint of a matter to the Adjudicating 
      Officer shall be accompanied by fee, payable by a bank draft drawn in 
      favour of “Adjudicating Officer Information Technology Act” at the place 
      of functioning of Adjudicating Officer in the States or Union Territories, 
      calculated on the basis of the damages claimed by way of compensation from 
      the contraveners on the rates provided below:
  
 Table of 
      Fee
 <section><number>I</number> Damages by way of 
      compensation                                                    
      Fee               
      
 <subsection><number>a</number>   Upto Rs.10,000 
                              10% 
      ad valorem rounded of to nearest next hundred
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   From 10001 to 
      Rs.50000 
                  Rs. 
      1000 plus 5% of the amount exceeding 
                                                                  Rs.10,000 
      rounded of to nearest next 
      hundred               
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   From Rs.50001 to 
      Rs.100000       Rs. 3000/- plus 4%of the 
      amount exceeding 
                                                                   Rs. 
      50,000 rounded of to nearest next 
      hundred               
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   More than Rs. 
      100000 
                      
      Rs. 5000/- plus 2% of the amount exceeding 
                                                                  Rs. 
      1,00,000 rounded of to nearest next 
      hundred               
      
 </subsection></section><section><number>II</number> Fee for every application 
                                  
      Rs. 
      50/-                
      
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Duplicity avoided.—When an adjudication into a matter of 
      contravention is pending before an Adjudicating Officer, same matter shall 
      not be pursued before any court or Tribunal or Authority in any proceeding 
      whatsoever and if there is already filed a report in relation to the same 
      matter, the proceedings before such other court, Tribunal or Authority 
      shall be deemed to be withdrawn.  
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Frivolous complaints.—If a person files a frivolous report of the 
      matter, the adjudicating officer in his discretion may order the 
      complainant, to make good the cost of the persons against whom the 
      complaint was filed and to pay a damage of not exceeding rupees twenty 
      five thousand and the adjudicating officer may also order payment of a 
      fine up to an amount not exceeding rupees ten thousand only.   
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Compounding of 
      contraventions.—
<section><number>a</number> A person, 
      against whom a report of contravention of the Act, Rules or Regulations, 
      directions or orders or conditions has been filed before an Adjudicating 
      Officer, may make an application for compounding the contravention during 
      the adjudicating proceedings to the concerned adjudicating officer:  
 Provided that an application for compounding may 
      be filed even before the contravention is reported, in which case the 
      contravener himself shall state the contravention undertaken or committed 
      and the likely loss to various parties and the amount of compensatory 
      damages tendered by the contravener.   
 </section><section><number>b</number> The applicant desirous of compounding the 
      contravention shall deposit the sum determined by the officer compounding 
      the contravention into the office of Adjudicating Officer:  
 Provided that sum determined as compounding fee 
      shall not exceed the maximum amount of penalty, which may be imposed under 
      this Act for the contraventions so compounded.   
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Certifying Authorities and other 
      Governmental agencies to assist.—All the licensed or recognized Certifying 
      Authorities, the Controller and other officers and agencies established 
      under the Act and other Government agencies like CERT-IND shall promptly 
      assist the Adjudicating Officers in any proceedings filed or pending 
      before the Adjudicating Officers.  
  
  </article><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

The 
      Information Technology (Qualification and Experience of Adjudicating 
      Officers and Manner of Holding Enquiry) Rules, 
      2003
 

 
 

 
 

APPENDIX
 

PROFORMA FOR COMPLAINT TO 
      ADJUDICATING OFFICER 
UNDER INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY ACT, 
      2000
 

 
 

 I   1.     Name of the 
      Complainant
 

           
      2.     E-mail address  
 

           
      3.     Telephone No.  
 

           
      4.     Address for correspondence  
 

           
      5.     Digital Signature Certificate, if any  
 

     II 
         1.     Name of the Respondent  
 

           
      2.     E-mail address  
 

           
      3.     Telephone No.  
 

           
      4.     Address for correspondence  
 

           
      5.     Digital Signature Certificate, if any  
 

    
      III    Damages claimed  
 

           
      Fee deposited  
 

           
      Demand Draft No................... dated................... 
      Branch.................
 

IV   Complaint under 
      Section/Rule/Direction/Order, etc.   
 

V   Time of 
      Contravention  
 

VI   Place of 
      Contravention  
 

VII   Cause of 
      action  
 

VIII   Brief facts of 
      the case  
 

 
 

Signature of 
      the Complainant
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
  </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>