<act><title>THE PARSI
MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE ACT, 1936

</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1936.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[It
extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir]:
 


 Provided
that the Central Government may, in respect of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[terri­tories
which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B
States] by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of
this Act relating to the constitution and powers of Parsi Matrimonial Courts and
to ap­peals from the decisions and orders of such Courts shall apply with such
modifications as may be specified in the notification:
 


 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Provided
further that nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the Renoncants of the
Union territory of Pondicherry.]
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>
as the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Central
Govern­ment] may, by notification in the 6[Official Gazette], appoint. 


   









</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 


 <section>
<number>1</number>
“Chief Justice” includes senior Judge; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
“Court” means a Court constituted under this Act; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number>
to “desert”, together with its grammatical variations and cognate
expressions, means to desert the other party to a mar­riage without reasonable
cause and without the consent, or against the will, of such party; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number>
“grievous hurt” means— 
 
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> emasculation;
 </subsection><subsection>  
                    
<number>b</number> permanent
privation of the sight of either eye;
 </subsection><subsection>  
                    
<number>c</number>  permanent privation of the
hearing of either ear; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> privation of any member or
joint; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> destruction or permanent
impairing of the powers of any member or joint; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> permanent disfiguration of the
head or face; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> any hurt which endangers life; 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number>
“husband” means a Parsi husband; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>6</number>
“marriage” means a marriage between Parsis whether contracted before
or after the commencement of this Act; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>7</number>
a “Parsi” means a Parsi Zoroastrian; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>8</number>
“priest” means a Parsi priest and includes Dastur and Mobed; and 
 </section><section> 
 <number>9</number>
“wife” means a Parsi wife. 
 
 
 
 


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Requisites to validity of Parsi marriages.—<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
No marriage shall be valid if—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the contracting parties are related to each other in any of the degrees
of consanguinity or affinity set forth in Schedule I; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
such marriage is not solemnized according to the Parsi form of ceremony
called “Ashirvad” by a priest in the presence of two Parsi witnesses other
than such priest; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>
in the case of any Parsi (whether such Parsi has changed his or her
religion or domicile or not) who, if a male, has not completed twenty-one years
of age, and if a female, has not completed eighteen years of age];
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
Notwithstanding that a marriage is invalid under any of the provisions of
sub-section (1), any child of such marriage who would have been legitimate if
the marriage had been valid, shall be legitimate.]
 


   

 









</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>4</number>
Remarriage when unlawful.—
<section><number>1</number>
No Parsi (whether such Parsi has changed his or her religion or domicile or not)
shall contract any marriage under this Act or any other law in the lifetime of
his or her wife or husband, whether a Parsi or not, except after his or her
lawful divorce from such wife or husband or after his or her marriage with such
wife or husband has lawfully been declared null and void or dissolved, and, if
the marriage was contracted with such wife or husband under the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>Parsi
Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865), or under this Act, except after a
divorce, declaration or dissolution as aforesaid under either of the said Acts.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every marriage contracted contrary to the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be
void.
 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Punishment of bigamy.—Every Parsi 
    who during the lifetime of his or her wife or husband, whether a Parsi or 
    not, contracts a marriage without having been lawfully divorced from such 
    wife or husband, or without his or her marriage with such wife or husband 
    having legally been declared null and void or dissolved, shall be subject to 
    the penalties provided in sections 494 and 495 of the Indian Penal Code (45 
    of 1860) for the offence of marrying again during the lifetime of a husband 
    or wife.  
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Certificate and registry of marriage.—Every 
    marriage contract­ed under this Act shall, immediately on the solemnization 
    there­of, be certified by the officiating priest in the form contained in 
    Schedule II. The certificate shall be signed by the said priest, the 
    contracting parties <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***] and two 
    witnesses present at the marriage and the said priest shall thereupon send 
    such certificate together with a fee of two rupees to be paid by the husband 
    to the Registrar of the place at which such marriage is solemnized. The 
    Registrar on receipt of the certificate and fee shall enter the certificate 
    in a register to be kept by him for that purpose and shall be entitled to 
    retain the fee. 
 









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Appointment of Registrar.—For 
    the purposes of this Act a Registrar shall be appointed. Within the local 
    limits of the ordinary civil jurisdiction of a High Court, the Registrar 
    shall be appointed by the Chief Justice of such High Court, and without such 
    limits, by the <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[State Government]. 
    Every Registrar so appoint­ed may be removed by the Chief Justice or <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    ap­pointing him.
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Marriage 
    register to be open for public inspection.—The 
    register of marriages mentioned in section 6 shall, at all reaso­nable 
    times, be open for inspection, and certified extracts therefrom shall, on 
    application, be given by the Registrar on payment to him by the applicant of 
    two rupees for each such extract. Every such register shall be evidence of 
    the truth of the statements therein contained.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Copy of certificate to be sent to Registrar-General of Births, Deaths and 
    Marriages.—Every 
    Registrar, except the Registrar appointed by the Chief Justice of the High 
    Court of Judicature at Bombay, shall, at such intervals as the 


    1[State Government] by 
    which he was appointed from time to time directs, send to the 
    Regis­trar-General of Births, Deaths and Marriages for the territories 
    administered by such 

    1[State Government] a 
    true copy certified by him in such form as such 

    1[State Government] 
    from time to time prescribes, of all certificates entered by him in the said 
    regis­ter of marriages since the last of such intervals.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Registration of divorces.—When a 
    Court passes a decree for divorce, nullity or dissolution, the Court shall 
    send a copy of the decree for registration to the Registrar of Marriages 
    within its jurisdiction appointed under section 7; the Registrar shall enter 
    the same in a register to be kept by him for the purpose, and the provisions 
    of Part II applicable to the Registrars and registers of marriages shall be 
    applicable, so far as may be, to the Registrars and registers of divorces 
    and decrees of nullity and dissolution. 
 

  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Penalty 
    for solemnizing marriage contrary to section 4.—Any 
    priest knowingly and wilfully solemnizing any marriage contrary to and in 
    violation of
    section 4 shall, on conviction thereof, be punished with simple imprisonment 
    for a term which may extend to six-months, or with fine which may extend to 
    two hundred rupees, or with both. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty 
    for priest’s neglect of requirements of section 6.—Any 
    priest neglecting to comply with any of the requisitions affecting him 
    contained in section 6 shall, on conviction there­of, be punished for every 
    such offence with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    months, or with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or with both.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Penalty 
    for omitting to subscribe and attest certificate.—Every 
    other person required by section 6 to subscribe or attest the said 
    certificate who shall wilfully omit or neglect so to do, shall, on 
    conviction thereof, be punished for every such offence with a fine not 
    exceeding one hundred rupees.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Penalty 
    for making false certificate, etc.—Every 
    person making or signing or attesting any such certificate containing a 
    statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes to be false, 
    shall be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    three months, or with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or with 
    both; and if the act amounts to forgery as defined in the Indian Penal Code 
    (45 of 1860) then such person shall also be liable, on conviction thereof, 
    to the penal­ties provided in section 466 of the said Code.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Penalty 
    for failing to register certificate.—Any 
    Registrar failing to enter the said certificate pursuant to section 6 shall 
    be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to one 
    year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Penalty 
    for secreting, destroying or altering register.—Any 
    person secreting, destroying, or dishonestly or fraudulently altering the 
    said register in any part thereof, shall be punished with imprisonment of 
    either description as defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) for a 
    term which may extend to two years, or if he be a Registrar, for a term 
    which may extend to five years and shall be liable to fine which may extend 
    to five hundred rupees.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number> Constitution of Special Courts under the 
      Act.—For 
      the pur­pose of hearing suits under this Act, a special Court shall be 
      constituted in each of the Presidency-towns of Calcutta, Madras and 
      Bombay, and in such other places in the territories of the several 
      <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[State Governments] as such Governments respectively shall 
      think fit.
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Parsi Chief Matrimonial Courts.—The 
    Court so constituted in each of the Presidency-towns shall be entitled the 
    Parsi Chief Matrimonial Court of Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, as the case may 
    be. The local limits of the jurisdiction of a Parsi Chief Matri­monial Court 
    shall be conterminous with the local limits of the ordinary original civil 
    jurisdiction of the High Court. The Chief Justice of the High Court, or such 
    other Judge of the same Court, as the Chief Justice shall from time to time 
    appoint, shall be the Judge of such Matrimonial Court, and, in the trial of 
    cases under this Act, he shall be aided <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[by five delegates, 
    except in regard to—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   interlocutory applications and 
    proceedings;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   alimony and maintenance, both permanent 
    as well as pendente lite;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   custody, maintenance and education of 
    children; and
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   all matters and proceedings other than 
    the regular hearing of cases].
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Parsi District Matrimonial Courts.—Every 
    Court so constitut­ed at a place other than a Presidency-town shall be 
    entitled the Parsi District Matrimonial Court of such place. Subject to the 
    provisions contained in section 21, the local limits of the jurisdiction of 
    such Court shall be conterminous with the limits of the district in which it 
    is held. The Judge of the principal Court of original civil jurisdiction at 
    such place shall be the Judge of such Matrimonial Court, and, in the trial 
    of cases under this Act, he shall be aided <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[by five delegates, 
    except in regard to—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   interlocutory applications and 
    proceedings;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   alimony and maintenance, both permanent 
    as well as pendente lite;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   custody, maintenance and education of 
    children; and  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   all matters and proceedings other than 
    the regular hearing of cases]. 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Power to alter territorial jurisdiction of District Courts.—The
    <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    may from time to time alter the local limits of the jurisdiction of any 
    Parsi District Matrimo­nial Court, and may include within such limits any 
    number of districts under its Government.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Certain districts to be within jurisdiction of the Chief Matrimonial Court.—Any 
    district which the <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[State Government], 
    on account of the fewness of its Parsi inhabitants, shall deem it 
    inexpedient to include within the jurisdiction of any District Matrimonial 
    Court, shall be included within the jurisdiction of the Parsi Chief 
    Matrimonial Court for the territories under such <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    where there is such a Court.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Court 
    seals.—A seal shall be made for 
    every Court constitut­ed under this Act, and all decrees and orders and 
    copies of de­crees and orders of such Courts shall be sealed with such seal, 
    which shall be kept in the custody of the presiding Judge.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Appointment of delegates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    shall, in the Presidency towns and districts subject to their respective 
    Governments, respectively appoint persons to be delegates to aid in the 
    adjudication of cases arising under this Act, after giving the local Parsis 
    an opportunity of expressing their opinion in such manner as the respective 
    Governments may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    persons so appointed shall be Parsis, their names shall be published in the
    <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[Official Gazette] 
    and their number shall, within the local limits of the ordinary original 
    civil jurisdiction of a High Court, be not more than thirty, and in 
    districts beyond such limits, not more than twenty.
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Power to appoint new delegates.—The 
    appointment of a dele­gate shall be for ten years; but he shall be eligible 
    for re-appointment for the like term or terms. Whenever a delegate shall 
    die, or have completed his term of office, or be desirous of relinquishing 
    his office, or refuse or become incapable or unfit to act or cease to be a 
    Parsi, or be convicted of an offence under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860) or other law for the time being in force <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[involving moral 
    turpitude], or be adjudged insolvent, then and so often the <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    may appoint any person being a Parsi to be a delegate in his stead; and the 
    name of the person so appointed shall be published in the <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Official Gazette].
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Delegates to be deemed public servants.—All 
    delegates appointed under this Act shall be considered to be public 
    ser­vants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Selection of delegates under sections 19 and 20 to be from those appointed 
    under section 24.—The 
    delegates selected under sections 19 and 20 to aid in the adjudication of 
    suits under this Act, shall be taken under the orders of the presiding Judge 
    of the Court in due rotation from the delegates appointed by the <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    under section 24:
 
Provided 
    that such party to the suit may, without cause assigned, challenge any <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[two] of the 
    delegates attending the Court before such delegates are selected and no 
    delegate so challenged shall be selected.
  
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>28</number> Practitioners in Matrimonial 
      Courts.—All legal practitioners 
      entitled to practise in a High Court shall be entitled to prac­tise in 
      any Court constituted under this Act, and all legal practitioners entitled 
      to practise in a District Court shall be entitled to practise in any Parsi 
      District Matrimonial Court constituted under this 
Act.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Court in which suits to be brought—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All suits instituted under this Act shall be brought in the Court within the 
    limits of whose jurisdiction the defendant resides at the time of the 
    institution of the suit 

    1[or where the 
    marriage under this Act was solemnised]. <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    the defendant shall at such time have left <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[the territo­ries to 
    which this Act extends] such suit shall be brought in the Court at the place 
    where the plaintiff and defendant last resided together.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    any case, whether the defendant resides in <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[the territo­ries to 
    which this Act extends] or not, such suit may be brought in the Court at the 
    place where the plaintiff resides or at the place where the plaintiff and 
    the defendant last resided to­gether, if such Court, after recording its 
    reasons in writing, grants leave so to do.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> Suits 
    for nullity—In any case in which 
    consumation of the marriage is from natural causes impossible, such marriage 
    may, at the instance of either party thereto, be declared to be null and 
    void.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Suits 
    for dissolution.—If a husband or 
    wife shall have been continually absent from his or her wife or husband for 
    the space of seven years, and shall not have been heard of as being alive 
    within that time by those persons who would have naturally heard of him or 
    her, had he or she been alive, the marriage of such hus­band or wife may, at 
    the instance of either party thereto, be dissolved.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> Grounds 
    for divorce.—Any married person 
    may sue for divorce on any one or more of the following grounds, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   that the marriage has not been 
    consummated within one year after its solemnization owing to the wilful 
    refusal of the defendant to consummate it;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   that the defendant at the time of the 
    marriage was of unsound mind and has been habitually so up to the date of 
    the suit:  
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground, unless the plaintiff: (1) was ignorant of the fact at the time 
    of the marriage, and (2) has filed the suit within three years from the date 
    of the marriage;  
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>bb</number>   
    that the defendant has been incurable of the unsound mind for a period of 
    two years or upwards immediately preceding the filing of the suit or has 
    been suffering continuously or intermit­tently from mental disorder of such 
    kind and to such an extent that the plaintiff cannot reasonably be expected 
    to live with the defendant.  
 
Explanation.—In this clause,—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   the expression “mental disorder” means 
    mental illness, ar­rested or incomplete development of mind, psychopathic 
    disorder or any other disorder or disability of mind and includes 
    schizo­phrenia;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the expression “psychopathic disorder” 
    means a persistent disorder of disability of mind (whether or not including 
    subnor­mality of intelligence) which results in abnormally aggressive or 
    seriously irresponsible conduct on the part of the defendant, and whether or 
    not it requires or is susceptible to medical treat­ment;]  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   that the defendant was at the time of 
    marriage pregnant by some person other than the plaintiff :  
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground unless: (1) the plaintiff was at the time of the marriage 
    ignorant of the fact alleged, (2) the suit has been filed within two years 
    of the date of marriage, and (3) marital intercourse has not taken place 
    after the plaintiff came to know of the fact;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   that the defendant has since the 
    marriage committed adultery or fornication or bigamy or rape or an unnatural 
    offence :
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground, if the suit has been filed more than two years after the 
    plaintiff came to know of the fact;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>dd</number>   
    that the defendant has since the solemnization of the marriage treated the 
    plaintiff with cruelty or has behaved in such a way as to render it in the 
    judgment of the Court improper to compel the plaintiff to live with the 
    defendant:
 
Provided that in every suit for divorce on 
    this ground it shall be in the discretion of the Court whether it should 
    grant a decree for divorce or for judicial separation only;]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   that the defendant has since the 
    marriage voluntarily caused grievous hurt to the plaintiff or has infected 
    the plaintiff with venereal disease or, where the defendant is the husband, 
    has compelled the wife to submit herself to prostitution:  
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground, if the suit has been filed more than two years (i) after the 
    infliction of the grievous hurt, or (ii) after the plaintiff came to know of 
    the infection, or (iii) after the last act of compulsory prostitution;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   that the defendant is undergoing a 
    sentence of imprisonment for seven years or more for an offence as defined 
    in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860):
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground, unless the defendant has prior to the filing of the suit 
    undergone at least one year’s imprisonment out of the said period;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   that the defendant has deserted 
    the plaintiff for at least 
2[two 
    years];  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   that <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[***] 
    an order has been passed against the defendant by a Magistrate awarding 
    separate maintenance to the plaintiff, and the parties have not had marital 
    intercourse for <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[one 
    year] or more since such decree or order;
 
<footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   that the defendant has ceased to 
    be a Parsi <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[by 
    conversion to another religion]:
 
Provided that divorce shall not be granted on 
    this ground if the suit has been filed more than two years after the 
    plaintiff came to know of the fact.
  
























 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>32A</number> 
    Non-resumption of cohabitation or restitution of conjugal rights within one 
    year in pursuance of a decree to be ground for divorce.—
<section><number>1</number> Either party 
    to a marriage, whether solemnized before or after the commencement of the 
    Parsi Marriage and Di­vorce (Amendment) Act, 1988,<footcitenum>33</footcitenum> may 
    sue for divorce also on the ground,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   that there has been no resumption of 
    cohabitation as between the parties to the marriage for a period of one year 
    or upwards after the passing of a decree for judicial separation in a 
    proceeding to which they were parties; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   that there has been no restitution of 
    conjugal rights as between the parties to the marriage for a period of one 
    year or upwards after the passing of a decree for restitution of conjugal 
    rights in a proceeding to which they were parties.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No decree 
    for divorce shall be granted under sub-section (1) if the plaintiff has 
    failed or neglected to comply with an order for maintenance passed against 
    him under section 40 of this Act or section 488 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) or section 125 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).]
  







 



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>32B</number>
Divorce by mutual consent.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions of this Act, a suit for divorce may be filed by both
the parties to a marriage together, whether such marriage was solemnized before
or after the commencement of the Parsi Marriage and Divorce (Amendment) Act,
1988, on the ground that they have been living separately for a period of one
year or more, that they have not been able to live together and that they have
mutually agreed that the marriage should be dissolved:
 Provided that no suit under this sub-section
shall be filed unless at the date of the filing of the suit one year has lapsed
since the date of the marriage.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Court shall, on being satisfied, after hearing the par­ties and after
making such inquiry as it thinks fit, that a marriage has been solemnized under
this Act and the averments in the plaint are true and that the consent of either
party to the suit was not obtained by force or fraud, pass a decree declaring
the marriage to be dissolved with effect from the date of the decree].
 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> Joining 
    of co-defendant.—In every such 
    suit for divorce on the ground of adultery, the plaintiff shall, unless the 
    Court shall otherwise order, make the person with whom the adultery is 
    alleged to have been committed a co-defendant, and in any such suit by the 
    husband the Court may order the adulterer to pay the whole or any part of 
    the costs of the proceedings.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Suits for judicial separation.—Any 
    married person may sue for judicial separation on any of the ground for 
    which such person could have filed a suit for divorce <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[**].
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Decrees in certain suits.—In 
    any suit under sections 30, 31, 32, <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[32A] or 34, whether 
    defended or not, if the Court be satisfied that any of the grounds set forth 
    in those sections for granting relief exist, that none of the grounds 
    therein set forth for withholding relief exist and that—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the act or omission set forth in the 
    plaint has not been condoned;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the husband and wife are not colliding 
    together;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the plaintiff has not connived at or 
    been accessory to the said act or omission;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   (save where a definite period of 
    limitation is provided by this Act) there has been no unnecessary or 
    improper delay in instituting the suit; and   
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   there is no other legal ground why 
    relief should not be granted;   
 
then and in such case, but not otherwise, the 
    Court shall decree such relief accordingly.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> Suit 
    for restitution of conjugal rights.—Where 
    a husband shall have deserted or without lawful cause ceased to cohabit with 
    his wife, or where a wife shall have deserted or without lawful cause ceased 
    to cohabit with her husband, the party so deserted or with whom cohabitation 
    shall have so ceased may sue for the restitution of his or her conjugal 
    rights and the Court, if satisfied of the truth of the allegations contained 
    in the plaint, and that there is no just ground why relief should not be 
    granted, may proceed to decree such restitution of conjugal rights 
    accordingly.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Counter-claim by defendant for any relief.—In 
    any suit under this Act, the defendant may make a counter-claim for any 
    relief he or she may be entitled to under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>38</number> Documentary 
    evidence.—Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
    time being in force, no document shall be inadmissible in evidence in any 
    proceeding at the trial of a suit under this Act on the ground that it is 
    not duly stamped or registered.].
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[<number>39</number> Alimony 
    pendente lite.—Where in any suit under this Act, it appears to the 
    Court that either the wife or the husband, as the case may be, has no 
    independent income sufficient for her or his support and the necessary 
    expenses of the suit, it may, on the application of the wife or the husband, 
    order the defendant to pay to the plain­tiff, the expenses of the suit, and 
    such weekly or monthly sum, during suit, as, having regard to the 
    plaintiff’s own income and the income of the defendant, it may seem to the 
    Court to be reasonable.  
 
<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[Provided that the 
    application for the payment of the expenses of the suit and such weekly or 
    monthly sum during the suit, shall, as far as possible, be disposed of 
    within sixty days from the date of service of notice on the wife or the 
    husband, as the case may be.]  
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Permanent alimony and maintenance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any Court exercising jurisdiction under this Act may, at the time passing 
    decree or at any time subsequent thereto, on an application made to it for 
    the purpose by either the wife or the husband, order that the defendant 
    shall pay to the plaintiff for her or his maintenance and support, such 
    gross sum or such monthly or periodical sum, for a term not exceeding the 
    life of the plaintiff as having regard to the defendant’s own income and 
    other property, if any, the income and other property of the plaintiff, the 
    conduct of the parties and other circumstances of the case, it may seem to 
    the Court to be just, and any such payment may be secured, if neces­sary, by 
    a charge on the movable or immovable property of the defendant.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    if it is satisfied that there is change in the circumstances of either party 
    at any time after it has made an order under sub-section (1), it may, at the 
    instance of either party, vary, modify, or rescind any such order in such 
    manner as the Court may deem just.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court 
    if it is satisfied that the party in whose favour an order has been made 
    under this section has remarried or, if such party is the wife, that she has 
    not remained chaste, or, if such party is the husband, that he had sexual 
    intercourse with any woman outside wedlock, it may, at the instance of the 
    other party, vary, modify or rescind any such order in such manner as the 
    Court may deem just].  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Payment of alimony to wife or to her trustee.—In 
    all cases in which the Court shall make any decree or order for alimony it 
    may direct the same to be paid either to the wife herself, or to any trustee 
    on her behalf to be approved by the Court <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[or to a guardian 
    appointed by the Court] and may impose any terms or restrictions which to 
    the Court may seem expedient, and may from time to time appoint a new 
    trustee <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[or guardian] the 
    Court expedient so to do.
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Disposal of joint property.—In 
    any suit under this Act the Court may make such provisions in the final 
    decree as it may deem just and proper with respect to property presented at 
    or about the time of marriage which may belong jointly to both the husband 
    and wife.  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[<number>43</number> Suits to be 
    heard in camera and may not be printed or published.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    suit filed under this Act shall be tried in camera and it shall not 
    be lawful for any person to print or publish any matter in relation to any 
    such case except a judg­ment of the Court printed or published with the 
    previous permis­sion of the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person prints or publishes any matter in contraven­tion of the provisions 
    contained in sub-section (1), he shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to one thousand rupees.]
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Validity of trial.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 19 or section 20, where in the case of a trial 
    in a Parsi Matrimonial Court not less than <footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[three] delegates 
    have attended throughout the proceedings, the trial shall not be invalid by 
    reason of the absence during any part thereof of the other delegates.
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Provisions of Civil Procedure Code to apply to suits under the Act.—The 
    provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall, so far 
    as the same may be applicable, apply to proceedings in suits instituted 
    under this Act including proceed­ings in execution and orders subsequent to 
    decree:  
 
<footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[Provided that the 
    presiding judge shall read out to the dele­gate the relevant sections of 
    this Act, and may, if he considers it necessary so to do, explain the same:  
 
Provided 
    further that a verbatim record shall be made of what the presiding 
    Judge reads out or explains to the delegates.]  
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Determination of questions of law and procedure and of fact.— 
    In suits under this Act all questions of law and proce­dure shall be 
    determined by the presiding Judge; but the deci­sion on the facts shall be 
    the decision of the majority of the delegates before whom the case is tried:  
 
Provided that, 
    where such delegates are equally divided in opin­ion, the decision on the 
    facts shall be the decision of the pre­siding Judge.  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Appeal to High Court.—<footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    An appeal shall lie to the High Court from—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the decision of any Court established 
    under this Act, whether a Chief Matrimonial Court or District Matrimonial 
    Court, on the ground of the decision being contrary to some law or usage 
    having the force of law, or of a substantial error or defect in the 
    procedure or investigation of the case which may have produced error or 
    defect in the decision of the case upon the merits, and on no other ground; 
    and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the granting of leave by any such Court 
    under sub-section (3) of section 29:  
 
Provided that 
    such appeal shall be instituted within three calen­dar months after the 
    decisions appealed from shall have been pronounced.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Every appeal 
    under sub-section (1) shall be heard by a Bench of two Judges of the High 
    Court].
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Liberty to parties to marry again.—When 
    the time <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[***] limited for 
    appealing against any decree granting a divorce or annulling or dissolving a 
    marriage shall have expired, and no appeal shall have been presented against 
    such decree, or when any such appeal shall have been dismissed, or when in 
    the result of any appeal a divorce has been granted or a marriage has been 
    declared to be annulled or dissolved, but not sooner, it shall be lawful for 
    the respective parties thereto to marry again <footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[***].
  













 



</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>49</number>
Custody of children.—In
any suit under this Act, the Court may from time to time pass such interim
orders and make such provisions in the final decree as it may deem just and
proper with respect to the custody, maintenance and education of the children
under the age of <footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[eighteen
years] the marriage of whose parents is the subject of such suit, and may, after
the final decree upon application, by petition for this purpose, make, revoke,
suspend or vary from time to time all such orders and provisions with respect to
the custody, maintenance and education of such children as might have been made
by such final decree or by interim orders in case the suit for obtaining such
decree were still pending.
 


 <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[Provided
that the application with respect to the maintenance and education of such
children during the suit, shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty
days from the date of service of notice on the respondent.]
   





</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Settlement of wife’s property for benefit of children.—In 
    any case in which the Court shall pronounce a decree of divorce or judicial 
    separation for adultery of the wife, if it shall be made to appear to the 
    Court that the wife is entitled to any property either in possession or 
    reversion, the Court may order­ such settlement as it shall think reasonable 
    to be made of any part of such property, not exceeding one half thereof, for 
    the benefit of the children of the marriage or any of them.
  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Superintendence of High Court.—The 
    High Court shall have superintendence over all Courts constituted under this 
    Act sub­ject to its appellate jurisdiction in the same manner as it has over 
    other Courts under <footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[Article 227 of the 
    Constitution] and all the provisions of <footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[that article] shall 
    apply to such Courts.
  
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>52</number> Applicability of provisions of the 
      Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of this 
      Act shall apply to all suits to which the same are appli­cable whether 
      the circumstances relied on occurred before or after the passing of this 
      Act, and whether any decree or order referred to was passed under this Act 
      or under the law in force before the passing of this Act, and where any 
      proceedings are pending in any Court at the time of the commencement of 
      this Act, the Court shall allow such amendment of the pleadings as may be 
      necessary as the result of the coming into operation of this 
      Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A Parsi who has contracted a marriage under the 
      <footcitenum>51</footcitenum>Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865), or under 
      this Act, even though such Parsi may change his or her religion or 
      domicile, so long as his or her wife or husband is alive and so long as 
      such Parsi has not been lawfully divorced from such wife or husband or 
      such marriage has not lawfully been declared null and void or dissolved 
      under the decree of a competent Court under either of the said Acts, shall 
      remain bound by the provisions of this Act.
  
  







 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number>
Repeal.—[Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1937 (20 of 1937) 
    section 3 and Schedule II.]
  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PARSI MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE ACT, 1936
 



 



 



 



Schedule I
 


(See section 3)
 



    Table of prohibited degrees of consanguinity and affinity
 


A man shall not marry his—
 
 
 


Paternal grand-father’s mother.
 
 


Paternal grand-mother’s mother.
 
 


Maternal grand-father’s mother.
 
 


Maternal grand-mother’s mother.
 
 


Paternal grand-mother.
 
 


Paternal grand-father’s wife.
 
 


Maternal grand-mother.
 
 


Maternal grand-father’s wife.
 
 


Mother or step-mother.
 
 


Father’s sister or step-sister.
 
 


Mother’s sister or step-sister.
 
 


Sister or step-sister.
 
 


Brother’s daughter or step-brother’s 
      daughter or any direct lineal descendant of a brother or step-brother.
 
 


Sister’s daughter or step-sister’s daughter 
      or any direct lineal descendant of a sister or step-sister.
 
 


Daughter or step-daughter, or any direct 
      lineal descendant of either.
 
 


Son’s daughter or step-son’s daughter, or 
      any direct lineal descendant of a son or step-son.
 
 


Wife of son or step-son, or of any direct 
      lineal descendant of a son or step-son.
 
 


Wife of daughter’s son or step-daughter’s 
      son, or of any direct lineal descendant of a daughter or step-daughter.
 
 


Mother of daughter’s husband.
 
 


Mother of son’s wife.
 
 


Mother of wife’s paternal grand-father.
 
 


Mother of wife’s paternal grand-mother.
 
 


Mother of wife’s maternal grand-father.
 
 


Mother of wife’s maternal grand-mother.
 
 


Wife’s paternal grand-mother.
 
 


Wife’s maternal grand-mother.
 
 


Wife’s mother or step-mother.
 
 


Wife’s father’s sister.
 
 


Wife’s mother’s sister.
 
 


Father’s brother’s wife.
 
 


Mother’s brother’s wife.
 
 


Brother’s son’s wife.
 
 


Sister’s son’s wife.

 


A woman shall not marry her—
 
 
 


Paternal grand-father’s father.
 
 


Paternal grand-mother’s father.
 
 


Maternal grand-father’s father.
 
 


Maternal grand-mother’s father.
 
 


Paternal grand-father.
 
 


Paternal grand-mother’s husband.
 
 


Maternal grand-father.
 
 


Maternal grand-mother’s husband.
 
 


Father or step-father.
 
 


Father’s brother or step-brother.
 
 


Mother’s brother or step-brother.
 
 


Brother or step-brother.
 
 


Brother’s son or step-brother’s son or any 
      direct lineal descendant of a brother or step-brother.
 
 


Sister’s son or step-sister’s son or any 
      direct lineal descendant of a sister or step-sister.
 
 


Son or step-son, or any direct lineal 
      descendant of either.
 
 


Daughter’s son or step-daughter’s son, or 
      any direct lineal descendant of a daughter or step-daughter.
 
 


Husband of daughter or step-daughter, or of 
      any direct lineal descendant of a daughter or step-daughter.
 
 


Husband of son’s daughter or step-son’s 
      daughter, or of any direct lineal descendant of a son or step-son.
 
 


Father of daughter’s husband.
 
 


Father of son’s wife.
 
 


Father of husband’s paternal grand-father.
 
 


Father of husband’s paternal grand-mother.
 
 


Father of husband’s maternal grand-father.
 
 


Father of husband’s maternal grand-mother.
 
 


Husband’s paternal grand-father.
 
 


Husband’s maternal grand-father.
 
 


Husband’s father or step-father.
 
 


Brother of husband’s father.
 
 


Brother of husband’s mother.
 
 


Husband’s brother’s son, or his direct 
      lineal descendant.
 
 


Husband’s sister’s son, or his direct lineal 
      descendant.
 
 


Brother’s daughter’s husband.
 
 


Sister’s daughter’s husband.

 


Note.—In the above table the words 
    “brother” and “sister” denote brother and sister of the whole as well as 
    half blood. Relationship by step means relationship by marriages. 
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PARSI MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE ACT, 1936
 



 


 
 




    Schedule II
 



(See section 6)
 



    Certificate of Marriage
 
 


Date and Place of Marriage:
 


Names of the husband and wife:
 


Condition at the time of marriage:
 


Rank or profession:
 


Age:
 


Residence:
 


Names of the fathers or guardians:
 


Rank or profession:
 


Signature of the officiating priest:
 


Signatures of the contracting parties:
 


Signatures of the fathers or guardians of the
     

    contracting parties under 21 years of age :
 


Signature of witnesses:
 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for certain words (w.e.f.
1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, 1956, for “Part B
States” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Ins. by Act 26 of 1968, sec. 3 and Sch., Pt. I (w.e.f. 24-5-1968).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Came into force on 22nd June, 1936 vide Gazette of India, 1936,
Pt. I, p. 621.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General in Council”</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Section 3 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 2
(w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 2, for clause (c) (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins.
by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Repealed by this Act.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
      1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 4, for “by seven delegates” (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 4, for “by seven delegates” (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Governments”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 5 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 6, for “three”  (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 7 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 8, for “three years”  (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Clause (i) omitted by 
    Act 5 of 1988, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 9 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   15 April, 1988.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 11 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 12, for section 38 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 13, for sections 39 and 40 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   Ins. by Act 49 of 
    2001, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 24-9-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 14 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 15, for section 43 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>   Subs. by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 16, for “three” (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>   Added by Act 5 of 
    1988, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>   Section 47 renumbered 
    as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>   Ins. by Act 5 of 1988, 
    sec. 18 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>   The word “hereby” 
    omitted by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>   The words “, as if the 
    prior marriage had been terminated by death” omitted by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 
    19 (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>Subs.
by Act 5 of 1988, sec. 20, for “sixteen years” (w.e.f. 15-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>Ins.
by Act 49 of 2001, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 24-9-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “section 107 of the Government of India Act”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>   Subs. by Act 36 of 
    1957, sec. 3 and Sch. II, for “that section” (w.e.f. 17-9-1957).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>   Repealed by 
      this Act.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>