<act> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises Development Act, 2006.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall come into force on 
such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification, appoint; and different dates may be 
appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any such 
provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to 
the coming into force of that provision.
  


</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Advisory Committee” means the committee 
constituted by the Central Government under sub-section (2) of section 7;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “appointed day” means the day following 
immediately after the expiry of the period of fifteen days from the day of 
acceptance or the day of deemed acceptance of any goods or any services by a 
buyer from a supplier.
  Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
clause,—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  “the day of acceptance” means,—
 <subsubsection>                 <number>a</number>  the day of the actual delivery of 
goods or the rendering of services; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 <number>b</number>  where any objection is made in writing 
by the buyer regarding acceptance of goods or services within fifteen days from 
the day of the delivery of goods or the rendering of services, the day on which 
such objection is removed by the supplier;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  “the day of deemed acceptance” means, 
where no objection is made in writing by the buyer regarding acceptance of goods 
or services within fifteen days from the day of the delivery of goods or the 
rendering of services, the day of the actual delivery of goods or the rendering 
of services;
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Board” means the National Board for Micro, 
Small and Medium Enterprises established under section 3;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “buyer” means whoever buys any goods or receives 
any services from a supplier for consideration;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “enterprise” means an industrial undertaking or 
a business concern or any other establishment, by whatever name called, engaged 
in the manufacture or production of goods, in any manner, pertaining to any 
industry specified in the First Schedule to the Industries (Development and 
Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951) or engaged in providing or rendering of any 
service or services;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “goods” means every kind of movable property 
other than actionable claims and money;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  “medium enterprise” means an enterprise 
classified as such under sub-clause (iii) of clause (a) or sub-clause (iii) of 
clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 7;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “micro enterprise” means an enterprise 
classified as such under sub-clause (i) of clause (a) or sub-clause (i) of 
clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 7;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  “National Bank” means the National Bank for 
Agriculture and Rural Development established under section 3 of the National 
Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development Act, 1981 (61 of 1981);
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>  “notification” means a notification published 
in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section>       <number>k</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act;
 </section><section>        <number>l</number>  “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </section><section>       <number>m</number>  “small enterprise” means an enterprise 
classified as such under sub-clause (ii) of clause (a) or sub-clause (ii) of 
clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 7;
 </section><section>       <number>n</number>  “supplier” means a micro or small enterprise, 
which has filed a memorandum with the authority referred to in sub-section (1) 
of section 8, and includes,—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  the National Small Industries Corporation, 
being a company, registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  the Small Industries Development 
Corporation of a State or a Union territory, by whatever name called, being a 
company registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  any company, co-operative society, trust 
or a body, by whatever name called, registered or constituted under any law for 
the time being in force and engaged in selling goods produced by micro or small 
enterprises and rendering services which are provided by such enterprises;
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>o</number>  “Small Industries Bank” means the Small 
Industries Development Bank of India established under sub-section (1) of 
section 3 of the Small Industries Development Bank of India Act, 1989 (39 of 
1989);
 </section><section>       <number>p</number>  “State Government”, in relation to a Union 
territory, means the Administrator thereof appointed under Article 239 of the 
Constitution.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Establishment of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, 
appoint, there shall be established, for the purposes of this Act, a Board to be 
known as the National Board for Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The head office of the Board 
shall be at Delhi.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Board shall consist of 
the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the Minister in charge of the Ministry or 
Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the micro, 
small and medium enterprises who shall be the ex officio Chairperson of 
the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the Minister of State or a Deputy Minister, if 
any, in the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having 
administrative control of the micro, small and medium enterprises who shall be
ex officio Vice-Chairperson of the Board, and where there is no such 
Minister of State or Deputy Minister, such person as may be appointed by the 
Central Government to be the Vice-Chairperson of the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  six Ministers of the State Governments having 
administrative control of the departments of small scale industries or, as the 
case may be, micro, small and medium enterprises, to be appointed by the Central 
Government to represent such regions of the country as may be notified by the 
Central Government in this behalf, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  three Members of Parliament of whom two shall be 
elected by the House of the People and one by the Council of States;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the Administrator of a Union territory to be 
appointed by the Central Government, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  the Secretary to the Government of India in 
charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having 
administrative control of the micro, small and medium enterprises, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  four Secretaries to the Government of India, to 
represent the Ministries of the Central Government dealing with commerce and 
industry, finance, food processing industries, labour and planning to be 
appointed by the Central Government, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the 
National Bank, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  the chairman and managing director of the Board 
of Directors of the Small Industries Bank, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  the chairman, Indian Banks Association, ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  one officer of the Reserve Bank, not below the 
rank of an Executive Director; to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the Reserve Bank;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  twenty persons to represent the associations of 
micro, small and medium enterprises, including not less than three persons 
representing associations of women’s enterprises and not less than three persons 
representing associations of micro enterprises, to be appointed by the Central 
Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  three persons of eminence, one each from the 
fields of economics, industry and science and technology, not less than one of 
whom shall be a woman, to be appointed by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  two representatives of Central Trade Union 
Organisations, to be appointed by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>o</number>  one officer not below the rank of Joint 
Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of the micro, small and medium 
enterprises to be appointed by the Central Government, who shall be the 
Member-Secretary of the Board, ex officio.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The term of office of the 
members of the Board, other than ex officio members of the Board, the 
manner of filling vacancies, and the procedure to be followed in the discharge 
of their functions by the members of the Board, shall be such as may be 
prescribed:
 Provided that the term of office 
of an ex officio member of the Board shall continue so long as he holds 
the office by virtue of which he is such a member.
 </section><section><number>5</number> No act or proceedings of the 
Board shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
constitution of, the Board; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  any defect in the appointment of a person acting 
as a member of the Board; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  any irregularity in the procedure of the Board 
not affecting the merits of the case.
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The Board shall meet at 
least once in every three months in a year.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Board may associate with 
itself, in such manner and for such purposes as it may deem necessary, any 
person or persons whose assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any 
of the provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the right to 
take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to the purposes for which he 
has been associated but shall not have the right to vote.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Without prejudice to 
sub-section (7) the Chairperson of the Board shall, for not less than two of the 
meetings of the Board in a year, invite such Ministers of the State Governments 
having administrative control of the departments of small scale industries or, 
as the case may be, the micro, small and medium enterprises, or the 
Administrators of Union territories and representatives of such other 
associations of micro, small and medium enterprises, as he may deem necessary 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>9</number> It is hereby declared that 
the office of member of the Board shall not disqualify its holder for being 
chosen as, or for being, a member of either House of Parliament.


</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>4</number> Removal of member from 
Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may 
remove a member of the Board from it, if he—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  is, or at any time has been, adjudged as 
insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  is, or becomes, of unsound mind and stands so 
declared by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting as 
a member of the Board; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  has been convicted of an offence which, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  has so abused, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, his position as a member of the Board as to render his continuance 
in the Board detrimental to the interests of the general public.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), no member shall be removed from his office on the 
grounds specified in clauses (c) to (e) of that sub-section unless he has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>5</number> Functions of Board.—The 
Board shall, subject to the general directions of the Central Government, 
perform all or any of the following functions, namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  examine the 
factors affecting the promotion and development of micro, small and medium 
enterprises and review the policies and programmes of the Central Government in 
regard to facilitating the promotion and development and enhancing the 
competitiveness of such enterprises and the impact thereof on such enterprises;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  make 
recommendations on matters referred to in clause (a) or on any other matter 
referred to it by the Central Government which, in the opinion of that 
Government, is necessary or expedient for facilitating the promotion and 
development and enhancing the competitiveness of the micro, small and medium 
enterprises; and
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  advise the 
Central Government on the use of the Fund or Funds constituted under section 12.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>6</number> Powers and functions of 
Member-Secretary of Board.—Subject to 
other provisions of this Act, the Member-Secretary of the Board shall exercise 
such powers and perform such functions as may be prescribed.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>7</number> Classification of 
enterprises.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 11B of the Industries (Development and Regulation) 
Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), the Central Government may, for the purposes of this 
Act, by notification and having regard to the provisions of sub-sections (4) and 
(5), classify any class or classes of enterprises, whether proprietorship, Hindu 
undivided family, association of persons, co-operative society, partnership 
firm, company or undertaking, by whatever name called,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  in the case 
of the enterprises engaged in the manufacture or production of goods pertaining 
to any industry specified in the First Schedule to the Industries (Development 
and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), as—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number>  a micro enterprise, where the investment in plant and machinery does 
not exceed twenty-five lakh rupees;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number>  a small enterprise, where the investment in plant and machinery is 
more than twenty-five lakh rupees but does not exceed five crore rupees; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>iii</number>  a medium enterprise, where the investment in plant and machinery is 
more than five crore rupees but does not exceed ten crore rupees;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in the case 
of the enterprises engaged in providing or rendering of services, as—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number>  a micro enterprise, where the investment in equipment does not exceed 
ten lakh rupees;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number>  a small enterprise, where the investment in equipment is more than 
ten lakh rupees but does not exceed two crore rupees; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>iii</number>  a medium enterprise, where the investment in equipment is more than 
two crore rupees but does not exceed five crore rupees.
 Explanation 1.—For 
the removal of doubts, it is hereby clarified that in calculating the investment 
in plant and machinery, the cost of pollution control, research and development, 
industrial safety devices and such other items as may be specified, by 
notification, shall be excluded.
 Explanation 2.—It 
is clarified that the provisions of section 29B of the Industries (Development 
and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), shall be applicable to the enterprises 
specified in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) of this 
section.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall, by notification, constitute an Advisory Committee consisting of the 
following members, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in the Ministry or Department of the Central 
Government having administrative control of the small and medium enterprises who 
shall be the Chairperson, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  not more than 
five officers of the Central Government possessing necessary expertise in 
matters relating to micro, small and medium enterprises, members, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  not more than 
three representatives of the State Governments, members, ex officio; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  one 
representative each of the associations of micro, small and medium enterprises, 
members, ex officio.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Member-Secretary of the 
Board shall also be the ex officio Member-Secretary of the Advisory 
Committee.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall, prior to classifying any class or classes of enterprises under 
sub-section (1), obtain the recommendations of the Advisory Committee.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Advisory Committee shall 
examine the matters referred to it by the Board in connection with any subject 
referred to in section 5 and furnish its recommendations to the Board.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government may 
also seek the advice of the Advisory Committee on any of the matters specified 
in sections 9, 10, 11, 12 or 14 of Chapter IV.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The State Government may 
seek advice of the Advisory Committee on any of the matters specified in the 
rules made under section 30.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Advisory Committee 
shall, after considering the following matters, communicate its recommendations 
or advice to the Central Government or, as the case may be, State Government or 
the Board, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the level of 
employment in a class or classes of enterprises;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the level of 
investments in plant and machinery or equipment in a class or classes of 
enterprises;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the need of 
higher investment in plant and machinery or equipment for technological 
upgradation, employment generation and enhanced competitiveness of the class or 
classes of enterprises;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the 
possibility of promoting and diffusing entrepreneurship in a micro, small or 
medium enterprises; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the 
international standards for classification of small and medium enterprises.
 </subsection></section><section><number>9</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 11B of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 
1951 (65 of 1951) and clause (h) of section 2 of the Khadi and Village 
Industries Commission Act, 1956 (61 of 1956), the Central Government may, while 
classifying any class or classes of enterprises under sub-section (1), vary, 
from time to time, the criterion of investment and also consider criteria or 
standards in respect of employment or turnover of the enterprises and include in 
such classification the micro or tiny enterprises or the village enterprises, as 
part of small enterprises.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>8</number> Memorandum of micro, small 
and medium enterprises.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
person who intends to establish,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  a micro or 
small enterprise, may, at his discretion, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  a medium 
enterprise engaged in providing or rendering of services may, at his discretion; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  a medium 
enterprise engaged in the manufacture or production of goods pertaining to any 
industry specified in the First Schedule to the Industries (Development and 
Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951),
 shall file the memorandum of micro, small or, as the case may be, 
of medium enterprise with such authority as may be specified by the State 
Government under sub-section (4) or the Central Government under sub-section 
(3):
 Provided that any person who, 
before the commencement of this Act, established—
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>a</number>  a small scale 
industry and obtained a registration certificate, may, at his discretion; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  an industry 
engaged in the manufacture or production of goods pertaining to any industry 
specified in the First Schedule to the Industries (Development and Regulation) 
Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), having investment in plant and machinery of more than 
one crore rupees but not exceeding ten crore rupees and, in pursuance of the 
notification of the Government of India in the erstwhile Ministry of Industry 
(Department of Industrial Development) number S.O.477(E) dated the 25th July, 
1991 filed an Industrial Entrepreneur’s Memorandum,
 shall within one hundred and eighty days from the commencement of 
this Act, file the memorandum, in accordance with the provisions of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The form of the memorandum, 
the procedure of its filing and other matters incidental thereto shall be such 
as may be notified by the Central Government after obtaining the recommendations 
of the Advisory Committee in this behalf.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authority with which the 
memorandum shall be filed by a medium enterprise shall be such as may be 
specified by notification, by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government shall, 
by notification, specify the authority with which a micro or small enterprise 
may file the memorandum.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The authorities specified 
under sub-sections (3) and (4) shall follow, for the purposes of this section, 
the procedure notified by the Central Government under sub-section (2).


</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>9</number> Measures for promotion and 
development.—The Central Government 
may, from time to time, for the purposes of facilitating the promotion and 
development and enhancing the competitiveness of micro, small and medium 
enterprises, particularly of the micro and small enterprises, by way of 
development of skill in the employees, management and entrepreneurs, 
provisioning for technological upgradation marketing assistance or 
infrastructure facilities and cluster development of such enterprises with a 
view to strengthening backward and forward linkages, specify, by notification, 
such programmes, guidelines or instructions, as it may deem fit.


</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>10</number> Credit facilities.—The 
policies and practices in respect of credit to the micro, small and medium 
enterprises shall be progressive and such as may be specified in the guidelines 
or instructions issued by the Reserve Bank, from time to time, to ensure timely 
and smooth flow of credit to such enterprises, minimise the incidence of 
sickness among and enhance the competitiveness of such enterprises.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>11</number> Procurement preference 
policy.—For facilitating promotion 
and development of micro and small enterprises, the Central Government or the 
State Government may, by order notify from time to time, preference policies in 
respect of procurement of goods and services, produced and provided by micro and 
small enterprises, by its Ministries or departments, as the case may be, or its 
aided institutions and public sector enterprises.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>12</number> Funds.—There 
shall be constituted, by notification, one or more Funds to be called by such 
name as may be specified in the notification and there shall be credited thereto 
any grants made by the Central Government under section 13.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>13</number> Grants by Central 
Government.—The Central Government 
may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, credit to 
the Fund or Funds by way of grants for the purposes of this Act, such sums of 
money as that Government may consider necessary to provide.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>14</number> Administration and 
utilisation of Fund or Funds.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government shall have the power to administer the Fund or Funds in such 
manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Fund or Funds shall be 
utilised exclusively for the measures specified in sub-section (1) of section 9.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government shall 
be responsible for the co-ordination and ensuring timely utilisation and release 
of sums in accordance with such criteria as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>15</number> Liability of buyer to 
make payment.—Where any supplier, 
supplies any goods or renders any services to any buyer, the buyer shall make 
payment therefor on or before the date agreed upon between him and the supplier 
in writing or, where there is no agreement in this behalf, before the appointed 
day:
 Provided that in no case the 
period agreed upon between the supplier and the buyer in writing shall exceed 
forty-five days from the day of acceptance or the day of deemed acceptance.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>16</number> Date from which and rate 
at which interest is payable.—Where 
any buyer fails to make payment of the amount to the supplier, as required under 
section 15, the buyer shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any agreement 
between the buyer and the supplier or in any law for the time being in force, be 
liable to pay compound interest with monthly rests to the supplier on 
that amount from the appointed day or, as the case may be, from the date 
immediately following the date agreed upon, at three times of the bank rate 
notified by the Reserve Bank.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>17</number> Recovery of amount due.—For 
any goods supplied or services rendered by the supplier, the buyer shall be 
liable to pay the amount with interest thereon as provided under section 16.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>18</number> Reference to Micro and 
Small Enterprises Facilitation Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, 
any party to a dispute may, with regard to any amount due under section 17, make 
a reference to the Micro and Small Enterprises Facilitation Council.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of a reference 
under sub-section (1), the Council shall either itself conduct conciliation in 
the matter or seek the assistance of any institution or centre providing 
alternate dispute resolution services by making a reference to such an 
institution or centre, for conducting conciliation and the provisions of 
sections 65 to 81 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (26 of 1996) 
shall apply to such a dispute as if the conciliation was initiated under Part 
III of that Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the conciliation 
initiated under sub-section (2) is not successful and stands terminated without 
any settlement between the parties, the Council shall either itself take up the 
dispute for arbitration or refer to it any institution or centre providing 
alternate dispute resolution services for such arbitration and the provisions of 
the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (26 of 1996) shall then apply to the 
dispute as if the arbitration was in pursuance of an arbitration agreement 
referred to in sub-section (1) of section 7 of that Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, the Micro and Small 
Enterprises Facilitation Council or the centre providing alternate dispute 
resolution services shall have jurisdiction to act as an Arbitrator or 
Conciliator under this section in a dispute between the supplier located within 
its jurisdiction and a buyer located anywhere in India.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every reference made under 
this section shall be decided within a period of ninety days from the date of 
making such a reference.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>19</number> Application for setting 
aside decree, award or order.—No 
application for setting aside any decree, award or other order made either by 
the Council itself or by any institution or centre providing alternate dispute 
resolution services to which a reference is made by the Council, shall be 
entertained by any court unless the appellant (not being a supplier) has 
deposited with it seventy-five per cent of the amount in terms of the decree, 
award or, as the case may be, the other order in the manner directed by such 
court:
 Provided that pending disposal 
of the application to set aside the decree, award or order, the court shall 
order that such percentage of the amount deposited shall be paid to the 
supplier, as it considers reasonable under the circumstances of the case subject 
to such conditions as it deems necessary to impose.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>20</number> Establishment of Micro 
and Small Enterprises Facilitation Council.—The 
State Government shall, by notification, establish one or more Micro and Small 
Enterprises Facilitation Councils, at such places, exercising such jurisdiction 
and for such areas, as may be specified in the notification.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>21</number> Composition of Micro and 
Small Enterprises Facilitation Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Micro and Small Enterprise Facilitation Council shall consist of not less 
than three but not more than five members to be appointed from among the 
following categories, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  
Director of Industries, by whatever name called, or any other officer not below 
the rank of such Director, in the Department of the State Government having 
administrative control of the small scale industries or, as the case may be, 
micro, small and medium enterprises; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  one or 
more office-bearers or representatives of associations of micro or small 
industry or enterprises in the State; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  one or more 
representatives of banks and financial institutions lending to micro or small 
enterprises; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  one or more 
persons having special knowledge in the field of industry, finance, law, trade 
or commerce.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The person appointed under 
clause (i) of sub-section (1) shall be the Chairperson of the Micro and Small 
Enterprises Facilitation Council.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The composition of the Micro 
and Small Enterprises Facilitation Council, the manner of filling vacancies of 
its members and the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their functions 
by the members shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>22</number> Requirement to specify 
unpaid amount with interest in the annual statement of accounts.—Where 
any buyer is required to get his annual accounts audited under any law for the 
time being in force, such buyer shall furnish the following additional 
information in his annual statement of accounts, namely:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  the 
principal amount and the interest due thereon (to be shown separately) remaining 
unpaid to any supplier as at the end of each accounting year;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  the 
amount of interest paid by the buyer in terms of section 16, along with the 
amounts of the payment made to the supplier beyond the appointed day during each 
accounting year;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  the amount 
of interest due and payable for the period of delay in making payment (which 
have been paid but beyond the appointed day during the year) but without adding 
the interest specified under this Act;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  the amount 
of interest accrued and remaining unpaid at the end of each accounting year; and
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  the amount of 
further interest remaining due and payable even in the succeeding years, until 
such date when the interest dues as above are actually paid to the small 
enterprise, for the purpose of disallowance as a deductible expenditure under 
section 23.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>23</number> Interest not to be 
allowed as deduction from income.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), the amount of 
interest payable or paid by any buyer, under or in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act, shall not, for the purposes of computation of income 
under the Income-tax Act, 1961, be allowed as deduction.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>24</number> Overriding effect.—The 
provisions of sections 15 to 23 shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>25</number> Scheme for closure of 
business of micro, small and medium enterprises.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law for the time being in force, the Central 
Government may, with a view to facilitating closure of business by a micro, 
small or medium enterprise, not being a company registered under the Companies 
Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), notify a Scheme within one year from the date of 
commencement of this Act.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>26</number> Appointment of officers 
and other employees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government or the State Government may appoint such officers with such 
designations and such other employees as it thinks fit for the purposes of this 
Act and may entrust to them such of the powers and functions under this Act as 
it may deem fit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Officers appointed under 
sub-section (1) may, for the purposes of this Act, by order require any person 
to furnish such information, in such form, as may be prescribed.


</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>27</number> Penalty for contravention 
of section 8 or section 22 or section 26.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever intentionally contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the 
contravention of any of the provisions contained in sub-section (1) of section 8 
or sub-section (2) of section 26 shall be punishable—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  in the case 
of the first conviction, with fine which may extend to rupees one thousand; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in the case 
of any second or subsequent conviction, with fine which shall not be less than 
rupees one thousand but may extend to rupees ten thousand.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where a buyer contravenes 
the provisions of section 22, he shall be punishable with a fine which shall not 
be less than rupees ten thousand.


</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>28</number> Jurisdiction of courts.—No 
court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first 
class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.
</article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>29</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the term of 
office of the members of the Board, the manner of filling vacancies, and the 
procedure to be followed in the discharge of functions by the members of the 
Board under sub-section (4) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the powers 
and functions of the Member-Secretary under section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the manner in 
which the Fund may be administered under sub-section (1) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the criteria 
based on which sums may be released under sub-section (3) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the 
information to be furnished and the form in which it is to be furnished under 
sub-section (2) of section 26; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  any 
other matter which is to be or may be prescribed under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every notification issued 
under section 9 and every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may 
be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the notification or rule or both Houses agree that the notification or rule 
should not be made, the notification or rule shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
anything previously done under that notification or rule.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>30</number> Power to make rules by 
State Government.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this 
Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the 
composition of the Micro and Small Enterprises Facilitation Council, the manner 
of filling vacancies of the members and the procedure to be followed in the 
discharge of their functions by the members of the Micro and Small Enterprises 
Facilitation Council under sub-section (3) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  any other 
matter which is to be or may be, prescribed under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The rule made under this 
section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of 
the State Legislature where there are two Houses, and where there is one House 
of the State Legislature, before that House.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  
Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>31</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be necessary for 
removing the difficulty:
 Provided that no order shall be 
made under this section after the expiry of two years from the commencement of 
this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every order made under this 
section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.
</section></article> 
 The Micro, Small and Medium 
Enterprises  Development Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>32</number> Repeal of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The Interest on Delayed Payments to 
Small Scale and Ancillary Industrial Undertakings Act, 1993 (32 of 1993) is 
hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the Act so repealed under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>