<act><tid>733461</tid>
<title>THE DELHI SIKH GURDWARAS ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 82 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the proper management of the Sikh Gurdwaras and 
Gurdwara property in Delhi and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1941372</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1542910</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>161497</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>332296</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1530530</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1671064</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act shall come into 
force;

</section>

<section><tid>1102876</tid>
<number>b</number>" Board" means the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board constituted under 
section 3 of the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras (Management) Act, <year>1971</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>797994</tid>
<number>c</number>" Committee" means the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Management Committee 
established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1322848</tid>
<number>d</number>" Delhi" means the Union territory of Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>1247136</tid>
<number>e</number>" Director Gurdwara Elections" means the Director Gurdwara 
Elections appointed by the Central Government under section 13;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>509</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> 17- 4- <year>1972</year>; Vide Notification No. GSR 241 (E), deted 7- 4- 
<year>1972</year>; Gazette of India, Extraodinary part II, Section 3 (I), P. 233




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>597013</tid>
<number>f</number>" Gurdwaras" means the Sikh Gurdwaras situated in Delhi as were, 
immediately before the appointed day, being managed by or affiliated 
to the Board and includes such other local Gurdwaras as may, after the 
appointed day, be affiliated to or managed by the Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>740795</tid>
<number>g</number>" Gurdwara property" means,-

<subsection><tid>53667</tid>
<number>i</number>all movable and immovable property which, immediately before the 
appointed day, vested or was kept in deposit in the name of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1947056</tid>
<number>ii</number>all property which stands in the name of the Gurdwaras or in the 
name of the Board or the present or old managers of the historic 
Gurdwaras;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>378298</tid>
<number>iii</number>all offerings in cash or kind made in various Gurdwaras or 
institution, managed or controlled by the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1566694</tid>
<number>iv</number>all property in cash or kind, movable as well as immovable that 
may be acquired by purchase, exchange or otherwise by the Gurdwaras, 
or the Committee, from time to time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>405316</tid>
<number>v</number>all grants, donations or contributions made, from time to time, by 
any person or authority to the Gurdwaras or the Committee,
and includes any actionable claim with respect to such Gurdwara 
property;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>766426</tid>
<number>h</number>" local Gurdwara" means a Gurdwara in Delhi, other than a Gurdwara 
under the control or management of the Board immediately before the 
appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>820134</tid>
<number>i</number>a person shall not be deemed to be" ordinarily resident" in a ward 
on the ground only that he owns or is in possession of a dwelling- 
house therein and a person absenting himself temporarily from his 
place of ordinary residence shall not by reason thereof cease to be 
ordinarily resident therein;

</section>

<section><tid>1094182</tid>
<number>j</number>" patit" means a Sikh who trims or shaves his beard or hair 
 (keshas) or who after taking Amrit commits any one or more of the four 
Kurahitis;

</section>

<section><tid>1395158</tid>
<number>k</number>" registered Singh Sabha" means a Singh Sabha registered as a 
society under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year>, (21 of <year>1860</year>.) 
which is managing or controlling a local Gurdwara in Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>1073198</tid>
<number>l</number>" regulation" means a regulation made under this Act by the 
Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>1488529</tid>
<number>m</number>" rule" means a rule made under this Act by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>311688</tid>
<number>n</number>" Sikh" means a person who professes the Sikh religion, believes 
and follows the teachings of Sri Guru Granth Sahib and the ten Gurus 
only and keeps unshorn hair (Keshas). For the purposes of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>510</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

if any question arises as to whether any living person is or is not a 
Sikh, he shall be deemed respectively to be or not to be a Sikh 
according as he makes or refuses to make in the manner prescribed by 
rules the following declaration:-

" I solemnly affirm that I am a Keshadhari Sikh, that I believe in and 
follow the teachings of Sri Guru Granth Sahib and the ten Gurus only, 
and that I have no other religion.";


</section>

<section><tid>547944</tid>
<number>o</number>" Amritdhari Sikh" means and includes every Sikh who has taken 
Khande ka Amrit or Khanda Pahul, prepared and administered according 
to the tenets of Sikh religion and rites at the hands of five Pyaras 
or" beloved ones".
PART

THE COMMITTEE

PART II

THE COMMITTEE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362284</tid>
<number> 3</number> Incorporation of the Committee.
<section><tid>1634330</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date  
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint, there shall be established a Committee to be called 
the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Management Committee for the proper management 
and control of the Gurdwaras and Gurdwara property.

</section>

<section><tid>1978486</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall be a body corporate with the name 
aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by 
such name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1711574</tid>
<number>3</number>The Committee shall have its head office in Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1735033</tid>
<number> 4</number> Composition of the Committee. The Committee shall consist of-
<section><tid>1472279</tid>
<number>a</number>forty- six members to be elected from various wards into which 
Delhi shall be divided in accordance with the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>254370</tid>
<number>b</number>nine members to be co- opted by the elected members of the 
Committee referred to in clause (a) in the manner hereinafter ap- 
pearing,-

<subsection><tid>1614105</tid>
<number>i</number>two members to represent the registered Singh Sabhas of Delhi who 
shall be chosen by drawing of lots out of the Presidents of those 
registered Singh Sabhas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>367308</tid>
<number>ii</number>four members, each being the head priest of the (1) Sri Akal 
Takhat Sahib, Amritsar, (2) Sri Takhat Kesgarh Sahib, Anandpur, (3) 
Sri Takhat Patna Sahib, Patna, and (4) Sri Takhat Hazur Sahib, Nanded:
Provided that the head priest shall have no right to vote for 
the purpose of election of office- bearers and other members of the 
Executive Board under sub- section (1) and sub- section (2) of section 
16;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>68201</tid>
<number>iii</number>one member, being the nominee of the Shromani Gurdwara 
Parbandhak Committee, Amritsar;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>511</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>252991</tid>
<number>iv</number>two members to represent the Sikh community of Delhi, other than 
those referred to in sub- clause (i), sub- clause (ii) and sub- clause 
 (iii), to be chosen in accordance with the system of proportional 
representation by means, of a single transferable vote.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>174952</tid>
<number> 5</number> Term of office.
<section><tid>1955150</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, Vie term of office or a member of the Committee shall be four 
years and shall commence from the date on which the first meeting of 
the Committee is held under section 15, and no longer.

</section>

<section><tid>1758422</tid>
<number>2</number>When a vacancy occurs in the Committee owing to death, 
resignation, removal or otherwise of a member, a new member shall be 
elected or co- opted, as the case may be, in the manner in which the 
member whose seat is to be filled was elected or co- opted and every 
such member shall continue to hold office so long only as the member 
in whose place he is elected or co- opted would have been entitled to 
hold office, if the vacancy had not occurred.

</section>

<section><tid>70652</tid>
<number>3</number>An outgoing member shall continue in office until the 
notification of election or co- option of his successor is published 
under section 12,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>160491</tid>
<number> 6</number> Delimitation of wards.
<section><tid>923069</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of election of  
members of the Committee, Delhi shall be divided into single member 
wards.

</section>

<section><tid>1051385</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director Gurdwara Elections shall by order determine-

<subsection><tid>1733908</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of wards; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1485904</tid>
<number>b</number>the extent of each ward.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>673721</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director Gurdwara Elections may, from time to time, in 
consultation with the Committee, alter or amend any order made under 
subsection (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1792202</tid>
<number> 7</number> Electoral roll.
<section><tid>1866169</tid>
<number>1</number>An electoral roll shall be prepared in  
such manner as may be prescribed by rules for every ward notified 
under section 6 on which shall be entered the names of all persons 
entitled to be registered as voters in that ward.

</section>

<section><tid>526136</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral 
roll for any ward more than once.

</section>

<section><tid>747793</tid>
<number>3</number>No person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral 
roll for more than one ward.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>814580</tid>
<number> 8</number> Qualifications of elector. Every person who-
<section><tid>845991</tid>
<number>a</number>has been ordinarily resident in a ward for not less than one 
hundred and eighty days during the qualifying period,

</section>

<section><tid>1226145</tid>
<number>b</number>is a Sikh of not less than twenty- one years of age on 
qualifying date,
shall, be entitled to be registered in the electoral roll for that 
ward:

Provided that no person shall be registered as an elector who-


</section>

<section><tid>845991</tid>
<number>a</number>trims or shaves his beard or keshas;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>512</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1226145</tid>
<number>b</number>smokes;

</section>

<section><tid>877062</tid>
<number>c</number>takes alcoholic drinks.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, the" qualifying 
date" and the" qualifying period"-


<subsection><tid>593673</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of electoral rolls first prepared under this Act, 
shall be the 1st day of January, <year>1972</year>, and the period beginning on the 
 1st day of January, <year>1971</year> and ending on the 31st day of December, <year>1971</year>, 
respectively; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>792529</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of every electoral roll subsequently prepared under 
this Act, shall be the 1st day of January of the year in which it is 
prepared and the year immediately preceding that year respectively.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>690764</tid>
<number>9</number>Right to vote. Every person registered on the electoral roll 
for the time being in force for any ward for the election of a member 
of the Committee, shall be entitled while so registered to vote at an 
election of a member for that ward, provided that no person shall be 
entitled to vote at an election in more than one ward.


</article>



<article><tid>406613</tid>
<number> 10</number> Qualifications of member.
<section><tid>991670</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall not be qualified  
to be chosen or co- opted as a member of the Committee if such person-

<subsection><tid>568046</tid>
<number>a</number>has not attained the age of twenty- five years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1545257</tid>
<number>b</number>is not a citizen of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1890619</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of an elected member, if he is not registered as an 
elector in the electoral roll for any ward;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92818</tid>
<number>d</number>is not an Amritdhari Sikh;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918846</tid>
<number>e</number>being an Amritdhari Sikh, trims or shaves his beard or keshas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1388333</tid>
<number>f</number>takes alcoholic drinks;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>266295</tid>
<number>g</number>smokes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1857411</tid>
<number>h</number>is a patit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>81330</tid>
<number>i</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1028263</tid>
<number>j</number>is an undischarged insolvent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119067</tid>
<number>k</number>has been convicted of an offence involving moral turpitude or has 
been dismissed from service by Government, Board, Committee or any 
local authority, on account of moral turpitude;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>531246</tid>
<number>l</number>is a paid servant of any Gurdwara or a local Gurdwara;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614961</tid>
<number>m</number>not being a blind person cannot <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> read and write] Gurmukhi.
Explanation.- A person shall be deemed to-


<subsubsection><tid>1107871</tid>
<number>i</number>be able to read Gurmukhi if he is able to recite Sri Guru Granth 
Sahib, in Gurmukhi, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>513</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>768399</tid>
<number>ii</number>write Gurmukhi if he fills his nomination paper for election to 
the Committee in Gurmukhi in his own handwriting.
If any question arises whether a candidate is or is not able to 
read an write Gurmukhi, the question shall be decided in such manner 
as may be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> prescribed by rules].


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1241688</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person sits or votes as a member of the Committee when 
he knows that he is not qualified for such membership, he shall be 
liable in respect of each day on which he so sits or votes to a 
penalty of three hundred rupees which shall be recoverable as an 
arrear of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1710909</tid>
<number>11</number>Elections. Election of members under clause (a) of section 4 
whether for the purpose of initial constitution of the Committee under 
section 3, or for filling vacancies arising by efflux of time or a 
casual vacancy, shall be conducted by the Director Gurdwara Elections 
in accordance with the rules made in this behalf:
Provided that no election shall be held to fill a casual vacancy 
occurring within four months prior to the holding of a general 
election under this section.



</article>



<article><tid>1922737</tid>
<number> 13</number> Director Gurdwara Elections.
<section><tid>1374168</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a suitable person to 
be the Director Gurdwara. Election in whom shall vest the 
superintendence, direction and control of the preparation of electoral 
rolls for, and the conduct of, elections of members of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1213637</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as Director 
Gurdwara Elections unless he is a citizen of India and possesses 
judicial or administrative experience for a period of not less than 
ten years.

</section>

<section><tid>1765365</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of section 37, the term of office, 
and the terms and conditions of service of the Director Gurdwara 
Elections shall be such as may be prescribed by rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1685248</tid>
<number> 14</number> First meeting of the elected members.
<section><tid>332583</tid>
<number>1</number>The persons to be  
co- opted as members of the Committee under clause (b) of section 4 
shall be chosen at the first meeting of the elected members which 
shall be convened by the Director Gurdwara Elections as early as 
possible and not later than fifteen days after publication of the 
results of the election under sub- section (1) of section 12.

</section>

<section><tid>1262019</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director Gurdwara Elections may adjourn the first meeting 
of the elected members to any other date or dates, being not later 
than fifteen days from the date of the first meeting aforesaid, if the 
elected members are unable to choose all persons to be co- opted at 
that first meeting.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>514</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>406309</tid>
<number> 15</number> First meeting of the Committee.
<section><tid>1167751</tid>
<number>1</number>The Director Gurdwara  
Elections shall summon the first meeting of the Committee to meet on 
such date, not being later than tee, fifteen days after the 
publication of the names of the members co- opted Under sub- section (2) 
of section 12, as he thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1356160</tid>
<number>2</number>The first meeting shall be held at such time and place as the 
Director Gurdwara Elections may appoint and shall be presided by him:
Provided that while so presiding at the meeting of the Committee, 
the Director Gurdwara Elections shall have no right to vote.


</section>

<section><tid>612233</tid>
<number>3</number>Every member of the Committee shall, before taking his seat 
make and subscribe before the Director Gurdwara Elections an oath 
according to the form set out for the purpose in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1768174</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of the Committee shall proceed thereafter to 
elect from amongst themselves a pro tempore Chairman in such manner as 
may be prescribed by rules, who shall preside at the meeting until the 
Committee elects the President.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585290</tid>
<number> 16</number> Election of office- bearers.
<section><tid>260551</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall, at its  
first meeting after the election of the pro tempore Chairman under 
sub- section (4) of section 15, elect from amongst its members a 
President, who shall conduct the election if other office- bearers and 
members of the Executive Board under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>856218</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall also at its first meeting elect from 
amongst its members a Senior Vice- President, Junior Vice- President, 
General Secretary and a Joint Secretary (hereinafter referred to as  
  office- bearers of the Committee), and shall also at the same meeting 
in like manner elect ten of its members to be members of the Executive 
Board of the Committee, and the office- bearers and members so elected 
shall be the Executive Board of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1549182</tid>
<number>3</number>No person shall be eligible for election as the President or 
other office- bearer unless he is at least a matriculate or has passed 
Higher Secondary Examination of any recognised University or Board or 
is a Giani or possesses any other equivalent educational 
qualification.

</section>

<section><tid>956207</tid>
<number>4</number>No member of the Committee shall, at the same time, bold any 
of the offices referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) in 
more than one capacity.

</section>

<section><tid>1333544</tid>
<number>5</number>The President and other members of the Executive Board 
elected under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall hold office for 
a term of one year but shall be eligible for re- election for one more 
term only:
Provided that an outgoing office- bearer or member shall continue 
it office until election of his successor is held.


</section>

<section><tid>569223</tid>
<number>6</number>The election of the President and other office- bearers and 
members of the Executive Board under sub- section (1) or sub- section 
 (2) or any subsequent annual election to any of those offices shall be 
held in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.

</section>

<section><tid>785398</tid>
<number>7</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 5 shall apply 
so far as may be to the filling of a casual vacancy in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> office of 
the President, any other office- bearer or member of the Executive 
Board]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>515</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as they apply in relation to casual vacancies in the membership of the 
Committee.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1952974</tid>
<number> 16A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to convene another meeting for election of 
office- bearers.
<section><tid>1087929</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Committee at its first meeting is unable to  
elect a pro tempore Chairman or a President or any other office- bearer 
or member of the Executive Board under sub- section (4) of section 15 
or sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) of section 16, the Director 
Gurdwara Elections shall summon another meeting of the Committee, 
being not later than fifteen days from the date of the first meeting, 
for the election of the pro tempore Chairman, the President or the 
remaining office- bearers or members of the Executive Board, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>828790</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 15 and 16 shall, so far as may 
be, apply to the conduct of election under sub- section (1).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1258381</tid>
<number> 17</number> Vacation, resignation and removal of members and office- 
bearers.
<section><tid>84478</tid>
<number>1</number>A member of the Committee may resign his office by  
writing under his hand addressed to the President.

</section>

<section><tid>672918</tid>
<number>2</number>An office- bearer or any other member of the Executive Board 
shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of the Committee;

<subsection><tid>917966</tid>
<number>b</number>may at any time by writing under his hand addressed to the 
Committee resign his office; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>203670</tid>
<number>c</number>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the Com- 
mittee passed by a three- fourth majority of the total members thereof:
Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall 
be moved unless it is supported by not less than seventeen members of 
the Committee and fourteen days' notice has been given of their 
intention to move the resolution.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>815728</tid>
<number>3</number>The resignation of office under sub- section (1) or clause (b) 
of sub- section (2) shall be effective from the date from which it is 
accepted by the Executive Board or the Committee, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1958903</tid>
<number>18</number>Fees and allowances of members. Any office- bearer or other 
member of the Executive Board or any other member of the Committee 
may, if he so desires, draw such fees and allowances for attending the 
meetings of the Executive Board or the Committee and for attending to 
any other work of the Executive Board or the Committee, as the case 
may be, as may be prescribed by regulations.


</article>



<article><tid>1313866</tid>
<number> 19</number> Meetings of the Committee and the Executive Board.
<section><tid>1388923</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
annual general meeting of the Committee shall be held in every year.

</section>

<section><tid>1261961</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Board shall meet at least once in every 
fortnight or at such intervals as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1102533</tid>
<number>3</number>The President, or in his absence the Senior Vice- President an 
in the absence of both, the Junior Vice- President, and in the absence 
of all the three, any other member elected from amongst themselves 
shall preside at any meeting of the Committee or of the Executive 
Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1438685</tid>
<number>4</number>The Committee or the Executive Board shall observe such rules 
of procedure in regard to transaction of the business at its meetings 
a may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>589709</tid>
<number>5</number>Save as otherwise provided, all questions which come up 
before any meeting of the Committee or the Executive Board shall be 
decide by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in 
the event of equality of votes, the person presiding shall have a 
second or casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1543331</tid>
<number>6</number>All proceedings of the meetings of the Committee or the 
Executive Board shall be recorded in Punjabi in Gurmukhi script.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>516</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1974</year>, s. 4.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1818510</tid>
<number> 20</number> Sub- committees.
<section><tid>1434206</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Board may constitute such  
number of subcommittees from amongst the members of the Committee as 
it thinks fit and for such purpose as it may decide.

</section>

<section><tid>1743845</tid>
<number>2</number>A sub- committee constituted under sub- section (1) shall meet 
at such time and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in 
regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be 
prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1535716</tid>
<number>3</number>A member of a sub- committee may, if he so desires, draw such 
fees and allowances for attending its meetings and for attending to 
any other work of the sub- committee, as may be prescribed by 
regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1718868</tid>
<number>22</number>Validity of acts of Committee, Executive Board or sub- 
committees not to be questioned by reason of vacancy, etc. No act or 
proceeding of the Committee or the Executive Board or any sub- 
committee shall be invalidated by reason only of the existence of any 
vacancy amongst its members or any defect in the constitution thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>517</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1656378</tid>
<number> 23</number> Officers and other employees of the Committee.
<section><tid>1228723</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as 
it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its functions, 
and may, from time to time, determine the number, designations, grades 
and scales of pay or other remuneration of the officers and other 
employees, and may at any time reduce, suspend, remove or dismiss or 
impose any other penalty on any officer or other employee for 
carelessness, unfitness, neglect of duty or other misconduct.

</section>

<section><tid>1981338</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers and other employees appointed under sub- section 
 (1) shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by regulations or as may, from time to time, be delegated 
by the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1438424</tid>
<number>3</number>The terms and conditions of service of the officers and other 
employees shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.
PART

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMITTEE

PART III

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMITTEE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1432334</tid>
<number> 24</number> Powers and functions of the Committee. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the control, 
direction and general superintendence over all the Gurdwaras and 
Gurdwara property in Delhi shall vest in the Committee, and it shall 
be the duty of the Committee-
<section><tid>928767</tid>
<number>i</number>to arrange for the proper performance of the religious rites and 
ceremonies in the Gurdwaras,

</section>

<section><tid>536810</tid>
<number>ii</number>to provide facilities for worship by the devotees at the 
Gurdwaras,

</section>

<section><tid>1979449</tid>
<number>iii</number>to ensure safe custody of its funds, movable and immovable 
properties, deposits, offerings in cash or kind,

</section>

<section><tid>357586</tid>
<number>iv</number>to do all such things as may be incidental and conducive to the 
efficient management of the affairs of Gurdwaras, educational and 
other institutions under the Committee and their properties or to the 
convenience of devotees,

</section>

<section><tid>980150</tid>
<number>v</number>to provide suitable accommodation and facilities for pilgrims,

</section>

<section><tid>1729579</tid>
<number>vi</number>to maintain free langars,

</section>

<section><tid>991613</tid>
<number>vii</number>to manage the historic and other Gurdwaras, educational and 
other institutions and their properties in such a way as to make them 
inspiring centres of the Sikh tradition, culture and religion,

</section>

<section><tid>1986495</tid>
<number>viii</number>to ensure maintenance of order, discipline and proper hygienic 
conditions in Gurdwaras, educational and other institutions under its 
management,

</section>

<section><tid>1340344</tid>
<number>ix</number>to open free dispensaries,

</section>

<section><tid>1232281</tid>
<number>x</number>to spread education, especially the knowledge of Punjabi, in 
Gurmukhi script,

</section>

<section><tid>40059</tid>
<number>xi</number>to establish educational institutions, research centres and 
libraries.

<subsection><tid>1602778</tid>
<number>xii</number>to render financial assistance to religious and educational 
institutions, societies and needy persons,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>518</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>859658</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to give stipends to needy and deserving students,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>255062</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to render help in the case of the uplift of the Sikh community 
and propagation of Sikh religion,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1267487</tid>
<number>xv</number>to perform such other functions and to do such religious or 
charitable acts, as may be prescribed by regulations for carrying out 
the purposes of this Act.
PART

GURDWARA FUND, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

PART IV

GURDWARA FUND, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1880564</tid>
<number> 26</number> Prohibition regarding making of contributions for political 
purposes. Nothing contained in this Act shall, or shall be deemed to, 
authorise the Committee to contribute any amount or amounts-
<section><tid>230960</tid>
<number>a</number>to any political party, or

</section>

<section><tid>1627736</tid>
<number>b</number>for the benefit of any political party, or

</section>

<section><tid>1420349</tid>
<number>c</number>for any political purpose to any individual or body.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>315864</tid>
<number> 27</number> Budget.
<section><tid>646530</tid>
<number>1</number>In respect of every financial year, budget  
 (annual financial statement) of the estimated receipts and expenditure 
of the Committee for the year shall be placed before the Committee and 
duly passed.

</section>

<section><tid>1063743</tid>
<number>2</number>No moneys out of the Gurdwara Fund shall be appropriated ex- 
cept as passed and approved by the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>639908</tid>
<number> 28</number> Maintenance of accounts.
<section><tid>1233716</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall maintain  
proper accounts showing receipts on account of and expenditure out of 
Gurdwara Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>242611</tid>
<number>2</number>At the end of each calendar month, a statement of income and 
expenditure relating to that month shall be prepared and placed before 
the Committee and it shall be pasted at prominent places outside all 
Gurdwaras; and a consolidated annual statement, showing income and 
expenditure relating to a financial year shall likewise be prepared 
and placed before the Committee and outside the Gurdwaras at the end 
of each financial year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>148579</tid>
<number> 29</number> Audit of Accounts.
<section><tid>412436</tid>
<number>1</number>The accounts of the Committee  
including those of the Gurdwaras, and Gurdwara property including 
educational and other charitable institutions administered by the 
Committee, shall be audited by one or more auditors duly qualified to 
act as auditor under subsection (1) of section 226 of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (hereinafter referred to as the auditor) who shall be 
appointed by the Committee within sixty days of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>519</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

close of every financial year and shall receive such remuneration as 
the Committee may fix:

Provided that the first appointment of auditors shall be made by 
the Committee within sixty days from the date of its first meeting 
held under section 15.


</section>

<section><tid>1234322</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of any such audit and examination of accounts 
the auditors may, by a demand in writing, require from the Committee 
or any office- bearer or member or employee of the Committee or any 
Gurdwara, educational or other institution of the Committee, the pro- 
duction before him of all books, deeds, vouchers and all other docu- 
ments and papers which he deems necessary, and may require any person 
holding or accountable for any such books, deeds, vouchers, documents 
and papers to appear before him at any audit and examination, to 
answer all questions which may be put to him with respect to the same 
or to prepare and submit any further statement which such auditor may 
consider necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>298199</tid>
<number>3</number>Within thirty days after the audit and examination have been 
completed, the auditor shall submit a report to the Committee upon 
each account audited and examined.

</section>

<section><tid>1291325</tid>
<number>4</number>The audit report shall be published in, at least two daily 
papers of Delhi (one in English and one in Punjabi) as well as in 
Gurdwara Journal, if any, within thirty days of its receipt.

</section>

<section><tid>1380892</tid>
<number>5</number>The report of the auditor shall, among other matters, specify 
all items of expenditure which in his opinion are illegal, irregular 
or improper, all cases of failure of recoveries of money or property 
due to the Committee, all instances of loss or wasteful expenditure of 
money or property due to negligence or misconduct and all instances in 
which any money or property has been devoted to any purpose not 
authorised by this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>339759</tid>
<number>30</number>Consideration of the auditor' s report by the Committee. The 
Committee, in meeting next following the date of receipt of the 
auditor' s report, shall consider such report and satisfy itself that 
no expenditure shown therein has been incurred otherwise than in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act and shall pass such orders 
as are, in its opinion, necessary and proper to rectify the illegal, 
unauthorised or improper expenditure and may also pass such further 
orders upon the report, as it may deem proper:
Provided that if the next meeting falls on a day earlier than two 
months after the receipt of the report it may be considered in the 
meeting next following which shall be convened before the expiry of a 
period of three months from the date of receipt of the said report.

PART

SETTLEMENT OF ELECTIONS AND OTHER DISPUTES

PART V

SETTLEMENT OF ELECTIONS AND OTHER DISPUTES



</article>



<article><tid>1872057</tid>
<number>31</number>Election disputes, electoral offences, etc. The provisions of 
sections 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 22, 23, 24, 25, 27, 28, 29 and 30 of 
the Delhi Municipal Corporation Act, <year>1957</year> (66 of <year>1957</year>.), shall mutatis 
mutandis apply, subject to such modifications as the Central 
Government may by order direct, in relation to settlement of disputes 
regarding elections, corrupt practices and electoral offences in 
respect of election or co- option of members of the Committee.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>520</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>705836</tid>
<number> 32</number> Jurisdiction of District Court in other matters. The Court of 
the District Judge in Delhi shall also have jurisdiction in respect 
of the following matters, namely:--
<section><tid>682909</tid>
<number>c</number>Petitions regarding complaints, irregularities, breach of 
trust, mismanagement in any Gurdwara, educational or other institu- 
tions against any member, office- bearer or officer or other employee 
of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>606620</tid>
<number>d</number>Petitions arising out of any type of disputes between the 
Committee and its employees including past employees.

</section>

<section><tid>1956049</tid>
<number>e</number>Applications regarding failure of publication of, or non- 
implementation or non- clearance of the objections raised in, any 
annual report of the auditors of the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1843740</tid>
<number> 33</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>1944545</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an order passed by the  
District Judge may, within sixty days of the order, prefer an appeal 
to the High Court at Delhi and the orders of the High Court on such 
appeal shall be final and conclusive.

</section>

<section><tid>638912</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act, 
<year>1963</year>, shall, so far as may be, apply to appeals under this section.
PART

MISCELLANEOUS

PART VI

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1985051</tid>
<number> 34</number> Procedure for affiliation of local Gurdwaras.
<section><tid>1028922</tid>
<number>1</number>A registered  
Singh Sabha may, in relation to any local Gurdwara under its control, 
decide by a resolution adopted by three- fourth majority of its total 
membership for affiliating that local Gurdwara to the Committee and if 
the Committee consents thereto, the said local Gurdwara shall be 
deemed to be affiliated to the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>831039</tid>
<number>2</number>All assets and liabilities of the local Gurdwara so 
affiliated and of the registered Singh Sabha shall thereafter vest in 
the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1495410</tid>
<number> 35</number> Act not to affect rites and practices of Sikh religion. 
Nothing contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force shall-
<section><tid>306500</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act or the rules or 
regulations made thereunder, affect any honour, emolument or 
perquisite to which any person is entitled by custom or otherwise in 
any Gurdwara;

</section>

<section><tid>284835</tid>
<number>b</number>authorise any interference with the religious or spiritual func- 
tions performed in any Gurdwara.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>722030</tid>
<number> 37</number> Salary, etc., of the Director Gurdwara Elections to be 
defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India in the first instance.
<section><tid>629639</tid>
<number>1</number>The salaries and allowances payable to the Director Gurdwara 
Elections or to the officers and other employees engaged for the 
conduct of elections to the Committee, shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India in the first instance, but shall be 
recoverable from the Committee by debit to the Gurdwara Fund after the 
close of each financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1930566</tid>
<number>2</number>Any sum due to the Central Government under sub- section (1) shall, 
if not paid within three months after the demand has been made, be 
recoverable as arrears of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>501519</tid>
<number>38</number>Protection of action taken. No suit, prosecution or other 
legal proceedings shall lie against any member of the Committee, the 
Executive Board or any sub- committee, the Director Gurdwara Elections 
or any other officer or employee of the Committee for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any 
rule or regulation made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1247945</tid>
<number> 39</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>723385</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>816063</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for or regulate all or any of 
the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>824686</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which a declaration for the purpose of clause (n) of 
section 2 shall be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1479220</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner and the criterion for deciding whether a candidate 
for election as a member of the Committee is able to read and write 
Gurmukhi;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1808116</tid>
<number>b</number>the particulars to be entered in the electoral rolls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1678724</tid>
<number>c</number>the preliminary publication of electoral rolls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1659237</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which and the time within which claims and 
objections as to entries in electoral rolls may be preferred;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1265701</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which notices of claims or objections shall be 
published;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>90194</tid>
<number>f</number>the place date and time at which claims or objections shall be 
heard and the manner in which claims or objections shall be heard and 
disposed of;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>650716</tid>
<number>g</number>the final publication of electoral rolls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1843383</tid>
<number>h</number>the revision and correction of electoral rolls and inclusion of 
names therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>745414</tid>
<number>i</number>the appointment of returning officers, assistant returning 
Officers, Presiding officers and polling officers for the conduct of 
elections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1588193</tid>
<number>j</number>the nomination of candidates, form of nomination papers, 
objections to nominations and scrutiny of nominations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>490061</tid>
<number>k</number>the deposits to be made by candidates, time and manner of making 
such deposits and the circumstances under which such deposits may be 
refunded to candidates or forfeited to the Committee

<pagefootnote><pagenum>522</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1974</year>, s. 6.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>664683</tid>
<number>l</number>the withdrawal of candidatures;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>249947</tid>
<number>m</number>the appointment of agents of candidates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1604775</tid>
<number>n</number>the procedure in contested and uncontested elections,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>89836</tid>
<number>o</number>the date, time and place for poll and other matters relating 
to the conduct of elections including-

<subsubsection><tid>552571</tid>
<number>i</number>the appointment of polling stations for each ward,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>458234</tid>
<number>ii</number>the hours during which the polling station shall be kept open for 
the casting of votes,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>998620</tid>
<number>iii</number>the printing and issue of ballot papers,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>179601</tid>
<number>iv</number>the checking of voters by reference to the electoral roll,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>536748</tid>
<number>v</number>the marking with indelible ink of the left forefinger or any other 
finger or limb of the voter and prohibition of the delivery of any 
ballot paper to any person if at the time such person applies for such 
paper he has already such mark so as to prevent personation of voters,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1375482</tid>
<number>vi</number>the manner in which votes are to be given and in particular in 
the case of illiterate voters or of voters under physical or other 
disability,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>377363</tid>
<number>vii</number>the procedure to be followed in respect of challenging votes and 
tendered votes,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1247948</tid>
<number>viii</number>the scrutiny of votes, counting of votes, the declaration of 
the results and the procedure in case of equality of votes or in the 
event of a member being elected to represent more than one ward,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>947837</tid>
<number>ix</number>the custody and disposal of papers relating to elections,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>704782</tid>
<number>x</number>the suspension of polls in case of any interruption by riot, 
violence or any other sufficient cause and the holding of a fresh 
poll,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>658947</tid>
<number>xi</number>the holding of a fresh poll in the case of destruction of, or 
tampering with, ballot boxes before the count,

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1954263</tid>
<number>xii</number>the countermanding of the poll in the case of the death of a 
candidate before the poll;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1028916</tid>
<number>p</number>the fee to be paid on an election petition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1843872</tid>
<number>q</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Director Gurdwara 
Elections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1769121</tid>
<number>r</number>the procedure for the election of pro tempore Chairman under sub- 
section (4) of section 15, and of the President and other office- 
bearers and members of the Executive Board under section 16;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>523</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1759775</tid>
<number>s</number>any other matter in respect of which the Central Government deems 
it necessary to make rules under this section or in respect of which 
this Act makes no provision or makes insufficient provision and 
provision is, in the opinion of the Central Government, necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>658894</tid>
<number>t</number>the manner in which results of election or co- option of members of 
the Committee shall be published, or the orders made under the rules 
shall be widely made known by affixing copies thereof in conspicuous 
public places, by publishing the same by beat of drum or by 
advertisement in local newspapers.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1647955</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under this section the Central Government 
may provide that any contravention thereof shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or 
with both.

</section>

<section><tid>170126</tid>
<number>4</number>All rules made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be, after they are made, before each House of Parliament while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be 
comprised in one session or in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid,] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rules or both Houses agree that the rules should 
not be made, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under those rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1896008</tid>
<number> 40</number> Power of Committee to make regulations.
<section><tid>1682684</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may  
make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or 
the rules made thereunder for carrying out its functions under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1403105</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such regulations; may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely.-

<subsection><tid>1742783</tid>
<number>a</number>date for election

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>993541</tid>
<number>b</number>fees and allowances to which office- bearers and other members of 
the Executive Board or other members of the Committee or of a sub- 
committee shall be entitled for attending meetings or any other work 
of the Executive Board, Committee or sub- committee respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>650295</tid>
<number>c</number>the periods of interval at which meetings of the Executive Board 
shall be hold, the manner in which meetings of the Committee or the 
Executive Board or any sub- committee shall be convened, the quorum for 
the transaction of business thereat and the rules of procedure to be 
followed for transaction of business at meetings of the Committee, the 
Executive Board or any sub- committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1727253</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which a majority decision of the Executive Board 
shall be obtained by circulation to its, office- bearers and members of 
any matter requiring decision;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>524</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1974</year>, s. 6. 
2. Omitted by s. 7, ibid.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1054051</tid>
<number>e</number>the matters in respect of which powers may be exercised or duties 
performed by the President or other office- bearers of the Executive 
Board or by any officer or other employee of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>304305</tid>
<number>f</number>the terms and conditions of service of officers and other em- 
ployees of the Committee including recruitment, transfer, fixation of 
seniority, promotion of, and disciplinary action or punishment 
against, such officers and other employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1301997</tid>
<number>g</number>any other functions or religious or charitable acts which, in 
addition to those specified in section 24, may be performed or done by 
the Committee, and the conditions and restrictions subject to which 
those functions or acts shall be performed or done;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>685297</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which cash or other moneys of the Gurdwara Fund 
shall be deposited or invested;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520495</tid>
<number>i</number>the form in which the budget of the Committee shall be presented;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422752</tid>
<number>j</number>the form in which the accounts of the Committee shall be 
maintained and the publication of such accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614462</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which any regulations or orders made thereunder 
shall be published or widely made known by affixing copies thereof in 
conspicuous public places, by publishing the same by beat of drum or 
by advertisement in local newspapers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1068312</tid>
<number>l</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>36963</tid>
<number> 41</number> Repeal and Saving.
<section><tid>1594307</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the date of the establishment  
of the Committee, the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras (Management) Act, <year>1971</year> (24  
  of <year>1971</year>.) shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1691925</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal,-

<subsection><tid>766073</tid>
<number>a</number>any appointment, notification, order or rule made or issued under 
the said Act shall, in so far as it is not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act, continue in force and be deemed to have been 
made or issued under the provisions of this Act unless and until it is 
superseded by any appointment, notification, order or rule made or 
issued under the said provisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>454332</tid>
<number>b</number>all budget estimates made, all obligations and liabilities in- 
curred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged 
to be done by, with or for the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board shall be 
deemed to have been made, incurred, entered into or' engaged to be 
done by, with or for the Committee under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881792</tid>
<number>c</number>all Gurdwara property, movable and immovable and all interests of 
whatsoever nature and kind therein vested in, belonging or due to, the 
Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board, immediately before such establishment, 
shall, with all rights, powers and privileges of whatsoever 
description, used, enjoyed or possessed by the Board vest in the 
Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>678860</tid>
<number>d</number>all sums of money including rents due to the Board immediately 
before such establishment shall be deemed to be due to the Committee;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>525</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119833</tid>
<number>e</number>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or which might 
have been instituted by or against the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board may 
be continued or instituted by or against the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>172479</tid>
<number>f</number>any will deed or other instrument which contains any bequest, 
gifts or trusts in favour of the Board shall as from such 
establishment, be construed as if the Committee were therein named 
instead of the said Board.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>