<act><title>

The 
Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[the
whole of India] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***].
   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act—
 <section> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>
“foreigner” means a person who is not a citizen of India;]
  <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Power to make rules.—<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
The Central Government may after previous publication, by notification in the
Official Gazette, make rules<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
with respect to foreigners for any or all of the following purposes, that is to
say—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
for requiring any foreigner entering, or being present in, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[India]
to report his presence to a prescribed authority within such time and in such
manner and with such particulars as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
for requiring any foreigner moving from one place to another place in <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[India]
to report, on arrival at such other place, his presence to a prescribed
authority within such time and in such manner and with such particulars as may
be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
for requiring any foreigner who is about to leave <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[India]
to report the date of his intended departure and such other particulars as may
be prescribed to such authority and within such period before departure as may
be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
for requiring any foreigner entering, being present in, or departing
from, 3[India] to produce, on demand
by a prescribed authority, such proof of his identity as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
for requiring any person having the management of any hotel,
boarding-house, sarai or any other premises of like nature to report the
name of any foreigner residing therein or whatever duration, to a prescribed
authority within such time and in such manner and with such particulars as may
be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
for requiring any person having the management or control of any vessel
or aircraft to furnish to a prescribed authority such information as may be
prescribed regarding any foreigner entering, or intending to depart from, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[India],
in such vessel or aircraft, and to furnish to such authority such assistance as
may be necessary or prescribed for giving effect to this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
for providing for such other incidental or supplementary matters as may
appear to the Central Government necessary or expedient for giving effect to
this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rule.]
   












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Burden of proof.—If
any question arises with reference to this Act or any rule made thereunder
whether any person is or is not a foreigner or is or is not a foreigner of a
particular class or description, the onus of proving that such person is not a
foreigner or is not a foreigner of such particular class or description, as the
case may be, shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence
Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), lie upon such person.
   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Penalties.—Any person who
contravenes, or attempts to contravene or fails to comply with, any provision of
any rule made under this Act shall be punished, if a foreigner, with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may
extend to one thousand rupees or with both, or if not a foreigner, with fine
which may extend to five hundred rupees.
   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Power to exempt from application of 
      Act.—The Central Government 
      may, by order, declare that any or all of the provisions of the rules made 
      under this Act shall not apply, or shall apply only with such 
      modifications or subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
      said order, to or in relation to any individual foreigner or any class or 
      description of foreigner:
 Provided that a copy of every such order shall 
      be placed on the table of <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***] <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Parliament] as soon as may be after its 
      promulgation.
    






 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Protection to persons acting under this 
      Act.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding 
      shall lie against, any person for anything which is in good faith done or 
      intended to be done under this Act.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Application of other laws not barred.—The
provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the
provisions of the Foreigners Act, <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[1946]
(31 of 1946) and any other law for the time being in force.
   








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>9</number>
Application of Act to Part B States.—[Rep.
by the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951 (3 of 1951) sec. 3 and Sch. (w.e.f.
1-4-1951)].]
  





 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 37 of 1949, sec. 3, for “all the provinces of India” (w.e.f.
28-4-1949).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
The words “except the State of Hyderabad” ins. by the A.O. 1950 and
omitted by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by Act 11 of 1957, sec. 8, for clause (a) (w.r.e.f. 19-1-1957).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Clause (aa) ins. by the A.O. 1950 and omitted by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3
and Sch (w.e.f.
1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Section 3 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2
and Sch. (w.e.f.
15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
For Registration of Foreigners Rules, 1939, see. Gazette of India,
1939, Pt. I, p. 1059.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by Act 37 of 1949, sec. 4 for “the Provinces of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> The words “Both Houses of” 
      rep. by the A.O. 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by A.O. 1950, for “the 
      Central Legislature”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Subs. by Act 37 of 1949, sec. 5, for “1864”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
Added by Act 37 of 1949, sec. 6.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>