<act><tid>7751</tid>
<title>THE COKING COAL MINES (NATIONALISATION) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 36 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 17th August, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the right, title 
and interest of the owners of the coking coal mines specified in the 
First Schedule, and the right, title and interest of the owners of 
such coke oven plants as are in or about the said coking coal mines 
with a view to reorganising and reconstructing such mines and plants 
for the purpose of protecting, conserving and promoting scientific 
development of the resources of coking coal needed to meet the growing 
requirements of the iron and steel industry and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1218606</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1151097</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Coking Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Act, <year>1972</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1671013</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 30 and 31 shall come into force at 
once and the remaining provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have 
come into force on the 1st day of May, <year>1972</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>744471</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to the policy of the State. It is hereby 
declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State 
towards securing the principles specified in clause (b) of article 39 
of the Constitution.
Explanation.-- In this section," State" has the same meaning as in 
article 12 of the Constitution.



</article>



<article><tid>561815</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1191766</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of May, <year>1972</year>;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>146</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>243895</tid>
<number>b</number>" coke oven plant" means the plant and equipment with 
which the manufacture of hard coke has been, or is 
being, carried on, and includes--

<subsection><tid>1132872</tid>
<number>i</number>all lands, buildings, works, machinery and 
equipment, vehicles, railways, tramways and sidings, 
belonging to, or in, the coke oven plant,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>62347</tid>
<number>ii</number>all workshops belonging to the coke oven 
plant, including buildings, machinery, instruments, 
stores, equipment of such workshops and the lands on 
which such workshops stand,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1201882</tid>
<number>iii</number>all coke in stock or under production, and 
other stores, stocks and instruments, belonging to the 
coke oven plant,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>278232</tid>
<number>iv</number>all power stations belonging to the coke oven 
plant or operated for supplying electricity for the 
purpose of working the coke oven plant or a number of 
coke oven plants,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1720979</tid>
<number>v</number>all lands, buildings and equipment belonging 
to the coke oven plant where the washing of coal is 
carried on,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>627444</tid>
<number>vi</number>all other fixed assets, movable or immovable, 
and current assets belonging to a coke oven plant, 
whether within its premises or outside.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- The expression" current assets" 
does not include,--


<subsubsection><tid>1790798</tid>
<number>a</number>dues representing the sale of coal and coal 
products effected at any time before the appointed day 
and outstanding immediately before the said day;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1255893</tid>
<number>b</number>dues from the Coal Board, established under 
section 4 of the Coal Mines (conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (19 of <year>1952</year>), prior to the 
repeal of the said Act, with respect to any period 
before the appointed day;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>606966</tid>
<number>c</number>dues from sundry debtors, loans and advances 
to other parties and investments, not being investments 
in the coke oven plant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>746394</tid>
<number>d</number>security deposits made by the owners with the 
Coal Controller appointed by the Central Government
<pagefootnote><pagenum>147</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1979</year> s. 2, for the original Explanation 
 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or with the Railways for the fulfilment of contracts or 
with a State Electricity Board for the payment of 
bills;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1255137</tid>
<number>e</number>earnest money deposited by the owners with the 
Railways for obtaining contracts;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>606966</tid>
<number>c</number>" coking coal mine" means a coal mine in which there 
exists one or more seams of coking coal, whether 
exclusively or in addition to any seam of other coal;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>746394</tid>
<number>d</number>" company" means a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and includes a 
foreign company within the meaning of section 591 of 
that Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1255137</tid>
<number>e</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments 
appointed under section 20;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1793061</tid>
<number>f</number>" Custodian" means the Custodian appointed under sub- 
section (2) of section 14, to take over, or carry on, 
the management of a coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1593022</tid>
<number>g</number>" date of assent" means the date on which assent is given 
by the President to this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>860235</tid>
<number>h</number>" Government company" has the meaning assigned to it by 
section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>175797</tid>
<number>i</number>" managing contractor" means the person, or body of 
persons, who, with the previous consent in writing of 
the State Government, has entered into an arrangement, 
contract or understanding, with the owner of a coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant under which the operations 
of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant are 
substantially controlled by such person or body of 
persons;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>947870</tid>
<number>j</number>" mine" means any excavation where any operation for the 
purpose of searching for or obtaining minerals has been 
or is being carried on, and includes--

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1132872</tid>
<number>i</number>all borings and bore holes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>62347</tid>
<number>ii</number>all shafts adjacent to, and belonging to, or 
in, a mine, whether in the course of being sunk or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1201882</tid>
<number>iii</number>all levels and inclined planes in the course 
of being driven;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>278232</tid>
<number>iv</number>all open cast working;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1720979</tid>
<number>v</number>all conveyors or aerial ropeways provided for 
bringing into or removal from a mine of minerals or 
other articles or for the removal of refuse therefrom;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>148</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>627444</tid>
<number>vi</number>all lands, buildings, works, adits, levels, 
planes, machinery and equipment, vehicles, railways, 
tramways and sidings belonging to, or in, or about, a 
mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>316420</tid>
<number>vii</number>all workshops belonging to, or in, a mine, 
including buildings, machinery, instruments, stores, 
equipment of such workshops and the lands on which such 
workshops stand;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1346214</tid>
<number>viii</number>all coal in stock or in transit or under 
production and other stores, stocks and instruments 
belonging to, or in, a mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881065</tid>
<number>ix</number>all power stations belonging to, or in, a 
mine or operated for supplying electricity for the 
purpose of working the mine or a number of mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>28945</tid>
<number>x</number>all lands, buildings and equipment belonging 
to, or in, a mine where the washing of coal or 
manufacture of coke is carried on;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>631785</tid>
<number>xi</number>all other fixed assets, movable or immovable, 
and current assets, belonging to a mine, whether within 
its premises or outside.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- The expression" current assets" 
does not include,--


<subsubsection><tid>54840</tid>
<number>a</number>dues representing the sale of coal and coal 
products effected at any time before the appointed day 
and outstanding immediately before the said day;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1892738</tid>
<number>b</number>dues from the Coal Board, established under 
section 4 of the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (19 of <year>1952</year>), prior to the 
repeal of the said Act, with respect to any period 
before the appointed day;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1081252</tid>
<number>c</number>dues from sundry debtors, loans and advances 
to other parties and investments, not being investments 
in the coking coal mine;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>231089</tid>
<number>d</number>security deposits made by the owners with the 
Coal Controller appointed by the Central Government or 
with the Railways for the fulfilment of contracts or 
with a State Electricity Board for the payment of 
bills;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>149</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year> s. 2, for the original Explanation 
 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1375358</tid>
<number>e</number>earnest money deposited by the owners with the 
Railways for obtaining contracts;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>381696</tid>
<number>k</number>" Mineral Concession Rules" means the rules, for the time 
being in force, made under the Mines and Minerals 
 (Regulation and Development) Act, <year>1957</year> (67 of <year>1957</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1165001</tid>
<number>l</number>" mining company" means a company owning a coking coal 
mine, and in relation to a foreign company within the 
meaning of section 591 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), the undertaking of that company in India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1305864</tid>
<number>m</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>6069</tid>
<number>n</number>" owner",--

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1132872</tid>
<number>i</number>when used in relation to a mine, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of  
  <year>1952</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>62347</tid>
<number>ii</number>when used in relation to a coke oven plant, 
means any person who is the immediate proprietor or 
lessee or occupier of the coke oven plant or any part 
thereof or is a contractor for the working of the coke 
oven plant or any part thereof;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>132452</tid>
<number>o</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1423731</tid>
<number>p</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank included for the time 
being in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (1 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1721805</tid>
<number>q</number>" specified date" means such date as the Central 
Government may, for the purpose of any provision of 
this Act, by notification, specify; and different dates 
may be specified for different provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1688586</tid>
<number>r</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), have the 
meanings, respectively, assigned to them in that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>760582</tid>
<number>s</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined in 
this Act or in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), but defined in 
the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>), shall have the 
meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the Mines 
Act, <year>1952</year>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>150</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Provisions of the Act Specified Date Gazette No. and Date 
------------------------------------------------------ 
Section 17 (3) 1- 9- <year>1972</year> GSR 385 (E) dated 22- 8- <year>1972</year>


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

ACQUISITION OF THE RIGHTS OF OWNERS OF COKING COAL MINES AND COKE OVENPLANTS

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE RIGHTS OF OWNERS OF COKING COAL MINES AND COKE 
OVEN PLANTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>341139</tid>
<number> 4</number> Acquisition of rights in coking coal mines.
<section><tid>1124360</tid>
<number>1</number>On the  
appointed day, the right, title and interest of the owners in relation 
to the coking coal mines specified in the First Schedule shall stand 
transferred to, and shall vest absolutely in, the Central Government, 
free from all incumbrances.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>832131</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If after the appointed day, the Central Government is 
satisfied, whether from any information received by it or otherwise, 
that there has been any error, omission or misdescription in relation 
to the particulars of a coking coal mine included in the First 
Schedule or the name and address of the owner of any such coking coal 
mine, it may, by notification, correct such error, omission or 
misdescription, and on the issue of such notification, the relevant 
entries in the First Schedule shall be, and shall be deemed always to 
have been, corrected accordingly:
Provided that no such correction in relation to the ownership of 
a coking coal mine shall be made where such ownership is in dispute.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>943488</tid>
<number> 5</number> Acquisition of rights of owners of coke oven plants.
<section><tid>1519585</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> On the appointed day, the right, title and interest of the owners of 
each of the coke oven plants specified in the Second Schedule, being 
the coke oven plants which are situated in or about the coking coal 
mines specified in the First Schedule, shall stand transferred to, and 
shall vest absolutely in, the Central Government, free from all 
incumbrances.

</section>

<section><tid>1659539</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] If after the appointed day, the Central Government is 
satisfied, whether from any information received by it or otherwise, 
that there has been any error, omission or misdescription in relation 
to the particulars of a coke oven plant included in the Second
<pagefootnote><pagenum>151</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
3 Renumbered by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
4 Ins. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Schedule or the name and address of the owner of any such coke oven 
plant, it may, by notification, correct such error, omission or 
misdescription, and on the issue of such notification, the relevant 
entries in the Second Schedule shall be, and shall be deemed always to 
have been, corrected accordingly:

Provided that no such correction in relation to the ownership of 
a coke oven plant shall be made where such ownership is in dispute.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476826</tid>
<number> 6</number> Central Government to be the lessee of the State Government.

<section><tid>1059213</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the rights of an owner under any mining lease granted, or  
deemed to have been granted, in relation to a coking coal mine, by a 
State Government or any other person, vest in the Central Government 
under section 4, the Central Government shall, on and from the date of 
such vesting, be deemed to have become the lessee of the State 
Government or such other person, as the case may be, in relation to 
such coking coal mine <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as if a fresh mining lease] in relation to 
such coking coal mine had been granted to the Central Government under 
the Mineral Concession Rules, the period of such lease <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be the 
maximum period] for which such lease could have been granted by the 
State Government or such other person under those Rules and, 
thereupon, all the rights under such mining lease, including surface, 
underground and other rights granted to the lessee shall be deemed to 
have been transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>494065</tid>
<number>2</number>On the expiry of the term of any lease, referred to in sub- 
section (1), such lease shall, if so desired by the Central Government 
be renewed, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, by the lessor for the maximum period for which such 
lease can be renewed under the Mineral Concession Rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>551355</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Central Government to direct vesting rights in a 
Government company.
<section><tid>1562505</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections  
 4 to 6 (both inclusive), the Central Government may, if it is 
satisfied that a Government company is willing to comply, or has 
complied, with such terms and conditions as that Government may think 
fit to impose, direct, by an order in writing, that the right, title 
and interest of an owner in relation to a coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant referred to, respectively, in section 4 or section 5 shall, 
instead of continuing to vest in the Central Government, vest in the 
Government company either on the date of publication of the direction 
or on such earlier or later date (not being a date earlier than the  
  appointed day), as may be specified in the direction.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>152</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Omitted by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>178599</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the right, title and interest of an owner in relation 
to a coking coal mine or coke oven plant vest in a Government company 
under sub- section (1), the Government company shall, on and from the 
date of such vesting, be deemed to have become--

<subsection><tid>861015</tid>
<number>a</number>the lessee in relation to such coking coal mine as if a 
mining lease in relation to such coking coal mine had 
been granted to the Government company under the 
Mineral Concession Rules, the period of such lease 
being the entire period for which such lease could have 
been granted under those Rules;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1684290</tid>
<number>b</number>the owner of the coke oven plant;
and all the rights and liabilities of the Central Government in 
relation to such coking coal mine or coke oven plant shall, on and 
from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have become the rights and 
liabilities, respectively, of the Government company.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1548345</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 6 shall apply to 
a lease which vests in a Government company as they apply to a lease 
vested in the Central Government and, reference therein to the Central 
Government shall be construed as reference to the Government company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>123633</tid>
<number> 8</number> Properties vesting in Central Government to be freed from 
mortgages, etc.
<section><tid>448182</tid>
<number>1</number>All property which vests in the Central Government  
or in a Government company under this Chapter shall, by force of such 
vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, 
charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting it and any 
attachment, injunction or decree or order of any court restricting the 
use of such property in any manner shall be deemed to have been 
withdrawn.

</section>

<section><tid>325014</tid>
<number>2</number>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this 
Act in the Central Government or in a Government company, and every 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in or in relation to 
any such property shall give, within such time and in such manner as 
may be prescribed, an intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, 
charge, lien or other interest.

</section>

<section><tid>298075</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (1) or any other 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation 
to, any such property shall be entitled to claim payment of the 
mortgage money or other dues, in whole or in part, out of the amount 
specified in relation to such property in the First Schedule or the 
Second

<pagefootnote><pagenum>153</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Schedule, as the case may be, but no such mortgage, charge or lien or 
other interest shall be enforceable against any such property of the 
Central Government or the Government company.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1639854</tid>
<number> 9</number> Central Government not to be liable for prior liabilities.
<section><tid>1874897</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every liability of the owner, agent, manager, or managing contractor 
of a coking coal mine or coke oven plant, in relation to any period 
prior to the appointed day, shall be the liability of such owner, 
agent, manager or managing contractor, as the case may be, and shall 
be enforceable against him and not against the Central Government or 
the Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>1628804</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that--

<subsection><tid>1172173</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise provided elsewhere in this Act, no 
claim for wages, bonus, royalty, rate, rent, taxes, 
provident fund, pension, gratuity or any other dues in 
relation to a coking coal mine or coke oven plant in 
respect of any period prior to the appointed day, shall 
be enforceable against the Central Government or the 
Government company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>730118</tid>
<number>b</number>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or 
other authority in relation to any coking coal mine or 
coke oven plant passed after the appointed day, but in 
relation to any matter, claim or dispute which arose 
before that day, shall be enforceable against the 
Central Government or the Government company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>88080</tid>
<number>c</number>no liability for the contravention of any provision of 
law for the time being in force, made before the 
appointed day, shall be enforceable against the Central 
Government or the Government company.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1247389</tid>
<number> 10</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1695668</tid>
<number>1</number>] Payment of amount to owners of coking coal mines. The  
owner of every coking coal mine or group of coking coal mines 
specified in the second column of the First Schedule, shall be given 
by the Central Government, in cash and in the manner specified in 
section 21, for vesting in it, under section 4, the right, title and 
interest of the owner in relation to such coking coal mine or group of 
coking coal mines, an amount equal to the amount specified against it 
in the corresponding entry in the fifth column of the said Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1113035</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
amount specified in the fifth column of the First Schedule against any 
coking coal mine or group of coking coal mines specified in the second 
column of the said Schedule and required to be given by the Central 
Government to its owner under sub- section (1), shall be deemed to 
include, and deemed always to have included, the amount required to be 
paid to such owner in respect of all coal in stock or other assets 
referred to in clause (j) of section 3 on the date immediately before 
the appointed day and no further amount shall be payable to the owner 
in respect of such coal or other assets.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>154</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1992</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1344420</tid>
<number> 11</number> Payment of amount to owners of coke oven plants. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>912661</tid>
<number>1</number>] The  
owner of every coke oven plant specified in the second column of the 
Second Schedule, shall be given by the Central Government, in cash and 
in the manner specified in section 21, for vesting in it, under 
section 5, the right, title and interest of the owner in relation to 
such coke oven plant, an amount equal to the amount specified against 
it in the corresponding entry in the fifth column of the said 
Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>797561</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
amount specified in the fifth column of the Second Schedule against 
any coke oven plant specified in the second column of the said 
Schedule and required to be given by the Central Government to its 
owner under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to include, and deemed 
always to have included, the amount required to be paid to such owner 
in respect of all coke in stock or other assets referred to in clause 
 (b) of section 3 on the date immediately before the appointed day and 
no further amount shall be payable to the owner in respect of such 
coke or other assets.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748324</tid>
<number> 12</number> Payment of further amount.
<section><tid>1282998</tid>
<number>1</number>In consideration of the  
retrospective operation of the provisions of section 4 and section 5, 
there shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner 
of every coking coal mine specified in the First Schedule or the owner 
of every coke oven plant specified in the Second Schedule, an amount 
equal to the amount which would have been, but for the provisions of 
the said section 4 or section 5, as the case may be, payable to such 
owner under the Coking Coal Mines (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year> (64  
  of <year>1971</year>), for the period commencing on the 1st day of May, <year>1972</year>, and 
ending on the date of assent.

</section>

<section><tid>1155781</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the amount specified in sub- section (1), there 
shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner of 
every coking coal mine specified in the First Schedule and the owner 
of every coke oven plant specified in the Second Schedule, simple 
interest at the rate of four per cent. per annum on the amount 
specified against such owner in the corresponding entry in the fifth 
column of the first schedule or the second schedule, as the case 
may be, for the period commencing on the date of assent and ending on 
the date of payment of such amount to the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1383710</tid>
<number>3</number>The amounts referred to in sub- section (1) and sub- section 
 (2) shall be in addition to the amount specified in the First Schedule 
or the Second Schedule, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>586366</tid>
<number> 12A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Workers' dues to be paid out of the amount.
<section><tid>498927</tid>
<number>1</number>Out of  
the amount payable,--

<subsection><tid>24717</tid>
<number>a</number>under section 10 and section 12 to the owner of every 
coking coal mine or group of coking coal mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1200177</tid>
<number>b</number>under section 11 and section 12 to the owner of every 
coke oven plant;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>155</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered by Act 57 of <year>1986</year> s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


there shall be paid to every person employed by such owner, a sum 
equal to the amount of arrears due, on the appointed day, to such 
employee,--


<subsubsection><tid>408932</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to a provident fund, pension fund, gratuity 
fund or any other fund or any other fund established 
for the welfare of such employee; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1582666</tid>
<number>ii</number>as wages.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1054210</tid>
<number>2</number>Every employee to whom the whole or any part of the arrears 
referred to in sub- section (1) is due shall file the proof of his 
claim to the Commissioner within such time, after the commencement of 
the Coking and Non- Coking Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Amendment Act, 
<year>1973</year>, as the Commissioner may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1233197</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of section 23 shall, as far as may be, apply 
to the filing, admission or rejection of the proofs referred to in 
sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>942490</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after the admission or rejection of 
the claims made under sub- section (2), determine the total amount of 
the arrears referred to in sub- section (1), and shall, after such 
determination, deduct, in the first instance, out of the amount paid 
to him under section 21, a sum equal to the total amount of such 
arrears.

</section>

<section><tid>1324996</tid>
<number>5</number>All sums deducted by the Commissioner under sub- section (4) 
shall, in accordance with such rules as may be made under this Act, be 
credited by the Commissioner to the relevant fund or be paid to the 
persons to whom such sums are due, and on such credit or payment, the 
liability of the owner of the coking coal mine or group of coking coal 
mines or coke oven plant, as the case may be, in respect of the 
amounts of arrears due as aforesaid, shall stand discharged.

</section>

<section><tid>364277</tid>
<number>6</number>The deductions made by the Commissioner under sub- section (4) 
shall have priority over all other debts, whether secured or 
unsecured.

</section>

<section><tid>1473337</tid>
<number>7</number>Save as otherwise provided in the foregoing sub- sections, 
every secured debt due from the owner of a coking coal mine or group 
of coking coal mines or coke oven plant, as the case may be, shall 
have priority over all other debts and shall be paid in accordance 
with the rights and interests of the secured creditors.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>156</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>736296</tid>
<number> 13</number> Income derived by the owners of coking coal mines and coke 
oven plants after the appointed day to be refunded to the Central 
Government.
<section><tid>1775667</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in pursuance of any decree, order or injunction  
made by a court, the Central Government or the Custodian appointed 
under the Coking Coal Mines (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year> (64 of  
  <year>1971</year>), was prevented from taking over the management of any coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant, the owner of such coking coal mine or 
coke oven plant shall render, within sixty days from the date of 
assent, to the Central Government or the Government company, as the 
case may be, accounts, in relation to the period commencing on the 
appointed day and ending on the date of assent, with regard to the--

<subsection><tid>1730241</tid>
<number>a</number>assets or stores of the coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant acquired or sold by him during the said period;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1631919</tid>
<number>b</number>coal or coke sold or despatched during the said period;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1645921</tid>
<number>c</number>income derived by him from the coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant during the said period.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>944599</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on examination of the accounts referred to in sub- section 
 (1), any income is found to have been derived by the owner from the 
coking coal mine or coke oven plant during the period referred to in 
that sub- section, such income shall be set off against the amount 
specified in the First Schedule or the Second Schedule, as the case 
may be, against the name of such owner, and the balance of such amount 
shall be paid to him.

</section>

<section><tid>1189706</tid>
<number>3</number>If no account is rendered by the owner of a coking coal mine 
or coke oven plant within the period referred to in sub- section (1) or 
if the Central Government or the Government company has any reason to 
believe that the account rendered by such owner is incorrect or false 
in material particulars, the Central Government or the Government 
Company may refer the matter to the commissioner and thereupon 
the Commissioner shall determine the income derived by the 
owner from the coking coal mine or coke oven plant during the period 
referred to in sub- section (1), and set off such income against the 
amount specified in the First Schedule or the Second Schedule, as the 
case may be, against the name of such owner and pay the balance to 
such owner.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF COKING COAL MINES AND COKE OVEN PLANTS

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF COKING COAL MINES AND COKE OVEN PLANTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1950588</tid>
<number> 14</number> Management, etc., of coking coal mines and coke oven plants.

<section><tid>66218</tid>
<number>1</number>The general superintendence, direction, control and management of  
the affairs and business of a coking coal mine or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>157</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

coke oven plant, the right, title and interest of an owner in relation 
to which have vested in the Central Government under section 4 or 
section 5, as the case may be, shall,--


<subsection><tid>545511</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of coking coal mine or coke oven plant, in 
relation to which a direction has been made by the 
Central Government under sub- section (1) of section 7, 
vest in the Government company specified in such 
direction, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392135</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a coking coal mine or coke oven plant, in 
relation to which no such direction has been made by 
the Central Government, vest in one or more Custodians 
appointed by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (2),
and thereupon the Government company so specified or the Custodian so 
appointed, as the case may be, shall be entitled to exercise all such 
powers and do all such things as the owner of the coking coal mine or 
coke oven plant is authorised to exercise and do.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1832035</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint an individual or a 
Government company as the Custodian of a coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant in relation to which no direction has been made by it under sub- 
section (1) of section 7.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>22746</tid>
<number> 15</number> Duty of persons in charge of management of coking coal mines 
or coke oven plants to deliver all assets, etc.
<section><tid>1471290</tid>
<number>1</number>On the vesting of  
the management of a coking coal mine or coke oven plant in a 
Government company or on the appointment of a Custodian, all persons 
in charge of the management of such coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant immediately before such vesting or appointment, shall be bound 
to deliver to the Government company or Custodian, as the case may be, 
all assets, books of account, registers or other documents in their 
custody relating to the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, and any 
contract, whether express or implied, providing for the management of 
the coking coal mine or coke oven plant made before the appointed day 
between such persons and the owners of such coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant, shall be deemed to have terminated on the date on which 
the management of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant vests in the 
Government company or the Custodian so appointed.

</section>

<section><tid>705205</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may 
deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the Government

<pagefootnote><pagenum>158</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

company or Custodian as to its or his powers and duties and the 
Government company or Custodian may, also if it or he so desires, 
apply to the Central Government at any time for instructions as to the 
manner in which the management of the coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant shall be conducted by it or him or in relation to any other 
matter arising in the course of such management.


</section>

<section><tid>1740387</tid>
<number>3</number>The Custodian shall receive from the funds of the coking coal 
mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, in relation to which he 
or it is the Custodian, such remuneration as the Central Government 
may fix and shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1257484</tid>
<number>16</number>Accounts and audit. The Custodian of every coking coal mine 
or coke oven plant shall maintain the accounts of such mine or plant 
in such manner and under such conditions as may be prescribed.
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF COKING COAL MINES AND COKE OVENPLANTS

CHAPTER V

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF COKING COAL MINES AND 
COKE OVEN PLANTS



</article>



<article><tid>969211</tid>
<number>17</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Liability of officer or other employee of a coking coal 
mine or coke oven plant for transfer to any other coking coal mine or 
coke oven plant. Notwithstanding anything contained in the industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being 
in force, the services of any officer or other employee employed in a 
coking coal mine or coke oven plant shall be liable to be transferred 
to in any other coking coal mine or coke oven plant and such transfer 
shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation 
under this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no 
such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>159</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1125880</tid>
<number> 18</number> Provident fund.
<section><tid>373774</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a coking coal mine or coke oven  
plant has established a provident fund for the benefit of its 
employees, the monies relatable to the employees, whose services have 
become transferred, by or under this Act, to the Central Government or 
a Government company, shall, out of the monies standing, on the 
appointed day, to the credit of such provident fund, stand transferred 
to, and vest in, the Central Government or the Government company, as 
the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>651540</tid>
<number>2</number>The monies which stand transferred, under sub- section (1), to 
the Central Government or a Government company shall be dealt with by 
that Government or company, as the case may be, in such manner as may 
be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>160</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>336451</tid>
<number>19</number>Superannuation, welfare and other funds. Where a 
superannuation, welfare or other fund has been established for the 
benefit of the employees whose services stand transferred to the 
Central Government or a Government company, the coking coal mine or 
coke oven plant, by which such employees were employed, shall 
distribute the amount due to each such employee as if the employee had 
superannuated, or his services with the coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant had terminated, on the day immediately preceding the specified 
date.
CHAP

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS

CHAPTER VI

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS



</article>



<article><tid>591134</tid>
<number> 20</number> Commissioner of Payments to be appointed.
<section><tid>1724722</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose  
of disbursing the amounts payable to the owner of each coking coal 
mine or coke oven plant, the Central Government shall appoint such 
person as it may think fit to be the Commissioner of Payments.

</section>

<section><tid>656725</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Central Government may appoint such other persons as 
it may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons to also 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act, 
and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>86290</tid>
<number>2A</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any 
powers may exercise those powers in the same manner and with the same 
effect as if they have been conferred on that person directly by this 
Act and not by way of authorisation.]

</section>

<section><tid>1840792</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>214377</tid>
<number> 21</number> Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>305180</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified 
date, pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, for payment to the owner of a 
coking coal mine or coke oven plant, a sum equal to the sum specified 
against the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, 
in the First Schedule or the Second Schedule together with the amount 
and interest, if any, referred to in section 12.

</section>

<section><tid>5014</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the sum referred to in sub- section (1), the 
Central Government shall pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, such
<pagefootnote><pagenum>161</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3, for the original sub- section (2) 
 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


amount as may become due to the owner of a coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant in relation to the period during which the management of 
the coking coal mine or coke oven plant remained vested in the Central 
Government <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and simple interest at the rate of four per cent. per 
annum on such amount for the period commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1973</year> and ending on the date of payment of such amount to the 
Commissioner.]


</section>

<section><tid>808352</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commissioner shall open and operate an account in a 
scheduled bank in respect of each coking coal mine or coke oven plant.

</section>

<section><tid>1317789</tid>
<number>4</number>Every amount paid to the Commissioner shall be deposited to 
the credit of the account, referred to in sub- section (3), of the 
coking coal mine or coke oven plant to which the payment relates.

</section>

<section><tid>214359</tid>
<number>5</number>Interest accruing on the amount standing to the credit of the 
account referred to in sub- section (3) shall enure to the benefit of 
the owner of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may 
be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and shall also be payable to the Commissioner in addition to the 
sum referred to in sub- section (1).]

</section>

<section><tid>1555843</tid>
<number>6</number>References in this section to the owner of a coking coal mine 
shall, in relation to a group of coking coal mines specified in the 
First Schedule, be construed as references to the owner of that group 
of coking coal mines.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>631863</tid>
<number> 22</number> Statement of accounts in relation to the period of management 
by the Central Government, etc.
<section><tid>347585</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government or the  
Government company, as the case may be, shall cause the books in 
relation to each coking coal mine or coke oven plant, the management 
of which has vested in it under the Coking Coal Mines (Emergency  
  Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year>, (64 of <year>1971</year>) to be closed and balanced as on 
the 30th day of April, <year>1972</year>, and shall cause a statement of accounts, 
as on that day, to be prepared, within such time, in such form and in 
such manner as may be prescribed, in relation to each such mine or 
plant in respect of the transactions effected by it during the period 
for which the management of such coking coal mine or coke oven plant 
remained vested in it:
Provided that where two or more coking coal mines or coke oven 
plants were owned, before the commencement of this Act, by the same 
owner, a consolidated statement of accounts may be prepared for all 
the coking coal mines or coke oven plants owned by such owner.


</section>

<section><tid>1065727</tid>
<number>2</number>All amounts received by the Central Government or the 
Government company after the closure of such accounts shall, where 
such amounts relate to transactions effected before the appointed day, 
be included in the said statement of accounts in respect of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>162</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


coking coal mine or coke oven plant to which the said receipt relates.


</section>

<section><tid>1134391</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government or the Government company in which the 
right, title and interest of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant 
stands vested shall be entitled to receive, up to the specified date, 
to the exclusion of all other persons, any money, due to the coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, realised after the 
appointed day notwithstanding that the realisations pertain to a 
period prior to the appointed day:
Provided that where such realisations have not been included in 
the statement of accounts as on the 30th day of April, <year>1972</year>, a 
supplementary statement of accounts shall be prepared and furnished, 
at such intervals as may be prescribed, by the Central Government or 
the Government company to the owner of the coking coal mine or the 
coke oven plant, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1671679</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The liabilities of the coking coal mine or the coke over 
plant (not being liabilities arising out of advances made by the  
  Central Government or the Government company), which could not be 
discharged by the appointed day, may be discharged by the Central 
Government or the Government company up to the specified date out of 
the realisations effected before or after the appointed day or out of 
advances or borrowings made up to the specified date and every payment 
so made shall be included in the statement of accounts as on the date 
immediately before the appointed day indicating therein the period in 
relation to which the payments were made and the payments so made 
shall not be called in question in any court:
Provided that the liabilities in relation to the period prior to 
the appointed day, which have not been discharged on or before the 
specified date, shall be the liabilities of the owner of the coking 
coal mine or the coke oven plant, as the case may be.]


</section>

<section><tid>916493</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of each statement of accounts prepared under this 
section shall be delivered by the Central Government or the Government 
company, as the case may be, to the Commissioner and also to the 
owner:
Provided that where the number of owners is more than one, only 
one copy of the statement of accounts shall be given to the owners for 
the benefit of all of them.


</section>

<section><tid>1382852</tid>
<number>6</number>The statement of accounts prepared under this section shall 
be audited by a person who is qualified to be appointed as an auditor 
of a company under section 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>) and the auditor so appointed shall receive, from the funds of 
the coking coal
<pagefootnote><pagenum>163</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, such remuneration as the 
Central Government may fix.


</section>

<section><tid>1612306</tid>
<number>7</number>The audit of the statement of accounts shall be conducted in 
such manner as the Central Government may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1685140</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The statement of accounts audited under sub- section (6) 
shall, unless the contrary is proved, be conclusive proof in respect 
of every matter entered therein.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," statement of 
accounts" means a statement in the form of receipts and payments, and 
does not include any statement that may be prepared as a result of the 
closing and balancing of the books for the preparation of the profit 
and loss account and balance- sheet or any statement prepared in 
accordance with the normal commercial practice.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>131546</tid>
<number> 22A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Validation of certain collections.
<section><tid>1889411</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 3, as amended by section 2 of the Coal 
Mines Nationalisation Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>1978</year>, any money collected 
by the Central Government or the Government company during the period 
commencing on the appointed day and ending with the date specified 
under sub- section (3) of section 22 shall be deemed to have been 
validly collected by the Central Government or the Government company, 
as the case may be, and any such money shall be applied in accordance 
with the provisions of section 22.

</section>

<section><tid>1826106</tid>
<number>2</number>Any money collected as aforesaid shall not be called in 
question in any court of law.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1089245</tid>
<number> 23</number> Claims to be made to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>779889</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person  
having a claim against the owner of a coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant shall prefer such claim before the Commissioner within thirty 
days from the specified date:
Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant 
was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the 
said period of thirty days, he may, on the expiry of the said period 
of thirty days, entertain the claim within a further period of thirty 
days, but not thereafter.


</section>

<section><tid>1919355</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), 
claims in relation to a provident fund, pension fund, gratuity fund or 
any other fund established for the welfare of the persons employed by 
the owner of a coking coal mine or group of coking coal mines or a 
coke oven plant may be filed on behalf of the persons so employed by 
the Coal Mines Provident Fund Commissioner appointed by the Central 
Government under section 3C of the Coal Mines Provident Fund, Family 
Pension and Bonus Schemes Act, <year>1948</year> (46 of <year>1948</year>); <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and claims in 
relation to any other matter may be filed on behalf of all or any of 
the persons so employed or any group of such persons, by any Trade 
Union, registered under the Trade Unions Act,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>164</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
1- 11- <year>1973</year>: vide Notifin. No. G. S. R. 458 (E), dated 28- 9- <year>1973</year>. 
3 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
4 Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>), or, where no such claim has been filed by any 
Trade Union, by the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) appointed by 
the Central Government or any officer subordinate to him;] and the 
claims so made shall be deemed to have been made by the persons having 
a claim against the owner of a coking coal mine or group of coking 
coal mines or a coke oven plant, as the case may be:

Provided that no such claim shall be made by the Coal Mines 
Provident Fund Commissioner <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or the Trade Union or the Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central) or any officer subordinate to him,] in relation 
to a person who has already made a claim under sub- section (1).]


</section>

<section><tid>1872888</tid>
<number>1AA</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where any claim, not being a claim which was time- barred 
on the 17th day of October, <year>1971</year>, was preferred under sub- section (1) 
within the period specified therefor and was rejected merely on the 
ground that such claim was time- barred, such claim shall be deemed not 
to have been rejected and the Commissioner shall restore on his file 
such claim and shall deal with it in the manner specified in this 
section.]

</section>

<section><tid>1011230</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, there shall be paid in priority to all other 
unsecured debts, not being the amounts advanced by the Central 
Government or the Custodian appointed under the Coking Coal Mines 
 (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year> (64 of <year>1971</year>), for the management of 
the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be,--

<subsection><tid>1919560</tid>
<number>a</number>all wages or salary (including wages payable for time or  
piece work and salary earned wholly or in part by way 
  of commission) of any employee, in respect of services 
rendered to the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, as 
the case may be, and any compensation payable to any 
workman under any provisions of Chapter VA of the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>);
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1939252</tid>
<number>c</number>all amounts due in respect of any compensation or 
liability for compensation under the Workmen' s 
Compensation Act, <year>1923</year> (8 of <year>1923</year>) in respect of the 
death or disablement
<pagefootnote><pagenum>165</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Omitted by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of any employee of the coking coal mine or coke oven 
plant unless such mine or plant has, under such a 
contract with insurers as is mentioned in section 15 of 
the said Act, rights capable of being transferred to, 
and vested in, the workmen;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>69638</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> all sums deducted by the employer from the salary or 
wages of any workman or other employee of the coking 
coal mine or group of coking coal mines or coke oven 
plant, as the case may be, for credit to any provident 
fund, or any other fund established for the welfare of 
such workmen or other employees but not deposited to 
the credit of the said fund;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>815807</tid>
<number>e</number>all sums due to the State Government <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> including 
royalty, rent and dead rent].

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>536653</tid>
<number>3</number>The debts specified in sub- section (2) shall rank equally 
among themselves and be paid in full, unless the assets are 
insufficient to meet them, in which case they shall abate in equal 
proportions and be paid accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>525204</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall fix a certain date on or before which 
every claimant shall file the proof of his claim or be excluded from 
the benefit of the disbursements made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>875300</tid>
<number>5</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in 
the English language and one issue of such daily newspaper in the 
regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every 
such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his 
claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the 
advertisement.

</section>

<section><tid>1582508</tid>
<number>6</number>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the time specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from 
the disbursements made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1540377</tid>
<number>7</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary and after giving the owner of the coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, an opportunity of 
refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard, in writing admit or reject the claim in 
whole or in part.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>166</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>913230</tid>
<number>8</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions 
including the place or places at which he will hold his sittings and 
shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act, 
have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of 
the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1537003</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1870933</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other 
material object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1182308</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>393214</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witnesses.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>159083</tid>
<number>9</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter 
XXXV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>. (5 of <year>1898</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1520519</tid>
<number>9A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Commissioner may, on receipt of a claim,--

<subsection><tid>1972879</tid>
<number>a</number>elect to settle the claim himself; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>487997</tid>
<number>b</number>transfer the claim for settlement to a person authorised 
in this behalf under sub- section (2) of section 20; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>752635</tid>
<number>c</number>withdraw the claim from the person referred to in clause 
 (b) and either settle the claim himself or transfer it 
for disposal to any other person who has been 
authorised in this behalf under sub- section (2) of 
section 20.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>396446</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> A claimant or owner who is dissatisfied with the decision 
of the Commissioner may prefer an appeal, within a period of Sixty 
days from the date of the decision,] to the principal civil court of 
original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, as the case may be, is 
situated:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is 
appointed to be the Commissioner, such appeal shall lie to the High 
Court for the State in which the coking coal mine or coke oven plant, 
as the case may be, is situated, and such appeal shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>167</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
3 Added by Act 41 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that High 
Court:]

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that any appeal which has not been preferred 
before the date on which the Coal Mines Nationalisation Laws 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1978</year> (22 of <year>1978</year>), receives the assent of the 
President, shall be preferred within a period of sixty days from such 
date.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>421495</tid>
<number>23A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Application of section 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act. 
The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36  
  of <year>1963</year>), shall, so far as may be, apply to appeals under section 23.]


</article>



<article><tid>1072318</tid>
<number>24</number>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner. Where the total 
amount of the claim admitted by the Commissioner does not exceed the 
total amount of the money credited to the account of a coking coal 
mine or coke oven plant, every such admitted claim shall rank equally 
among themselves and be paid in full, and the balance, if any, shall 
be paid to the owner, but where such amount is insufficient to meet in 
full the total amount of the admitted claims, every such claim shall 
abate in equal proportions and be paid accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>824397</tid>
<number>24A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Interest on admitted claims. Notwithstanding any award, 
decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority, passed 
before the appointed day, in relation to any coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant, where any amount is payable in respect of a claim admitted 
under this Act, the interest payable on such amount for any period 
after the appointed day shall be at such rate not exceeding the rate 
of interest accruing on any amount deposited by the Commissioner under 
section 21.]


</article>



<article><tid>600576</tid>
<number>25</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Recovery of excess payments made by Central Government or 
Custodian. Any amount in excess of payments over receipts in the 
statement of accounts prepared under section 22 shall be deemed to be 
an amount advanced by the Central Government or the Custodian, as the 
case may be, for the management of a coking coal mine or a coke oven 
plant during the period in which the management of such mine or plant 
remained vested in the Central Government and the Central Government 
may make a claim to the Commissioner for such excess payment and such 
claim shall have priority over the claims of all other unsecured 
creditors of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant.
Explanation.-- In this section," Custodian" means the Custodian 
appointed under the Coking Coal Mines (Emergency Provisions) Act, 
<year>1971</year>.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>168</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>151240</tid>
<number> 25A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notice to owners of coking coal mines or coke oven plants 
and managing contractors, etc.
<section><tid>1943835</tid>
<number>1</number>After meeting the liabilities of  
persons whose claims have been admitted under this Act, the 
Commissioner shall notify, in such manner as he may think fit, the 
amount of money available with him and specify in such notification a 
date within which the owners of the coking coal mines or coke oven 
plants, the managing contractors and the owners of any machinery, 
equipment or other property which has vested in the Central Government 
or a Government company under this Act and which does not belong to 
the owners of the coking coal mines or coke oven plants may apply to 
him for payment.

</section>

<section><tid>1184411</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any application is made under sub- section (1), the 
Commissioner shall, after satisfying himself as to the right of the 
applicant to receive the whole or any part of the amount, pay the 
amount to the person concerned and in the event of there being a doubt 
or dispute as to the right of the person to receive the whole or any 
part of the amount, the Commissioner shall deal with the application 
in the manner specified in sub- section (1) of section 26.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>651258</tid>
<number> 26</number> Disputes how to be dealt with.
<section><tid>1675182</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of there  
being a doubt or dispute as to the right of a person to receive the 
whole or any part of the amount referred to in sections 10, 11 and 12, 
the Commissioner shall refer the matter to the court for a decision, 
and shall make the disbursements in accordance with the decision of 
the court.

</section>

<section><tid>444355</tid>
<number>2</number>In relation to a coking coal mine or coke oven plant, the 
operations of which were, immediately before the 17th day of October, 
 <year>1971</year> under the control of a managing contractor, the amount specified 
in the First Schedule against such coking coal mine or in the Second 
Schedule against such coke oven plant shall be apportioned between the 
owner of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant and such managing 
contractor in such proportions as may be agreed upon by or between the 
owner and such managing contractor, and in the event
<pagefootnote><pagenum>169</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of there being no such agreement, in such proportions as may be 
determined by the court.


</section>

<section><tid>266908</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the amount specified in the fifth column of the 
First Schedule is relatable to a group of coking coal mines, the 
Commissioner shall have power to apportion such amount among the 
owners of such group, and in making such apportionment, the 
Commissioner shall have regard to the highest annual production in the 
coking coal mine during the three years immediately preceding the 
appointed day.]
Explanation.-- In this section," court", in relation to a coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant, means the principal civil court of 
original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the coking coal mine or coke oven plant is situated.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1292448</tid>
<number>27</number>Undisbursed or unclaimed amounts to be deposited to the 
general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> which 
remains undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of three years from the 
day on which the last order for disbursement was made] shall be 
transferred by the Commissioner to the general revenue account of the 
Central Government; but a claim to any money so transferred may be 
preferred to the Central Government by the person entitled to such 
payment and shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, 
the order, if any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order 
for the refund of revenue.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>855413</tid>
<number>28</number>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument 
having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, or in any 
decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>186752</tid>
<number> 29</number> Contracts cease to have effect unless ratified by the Central 
Government.
<section><tid>1819729</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract entered into by the owner or occupier  
of any coking coal mine or coke oven plant for any service, sale or 
supply before the appointed day shall, on and from the expiry of one 
hundred and twenty days from the date of assent, cease to have effect 
unless such contract is, before the expiry of that period, ratified, 
in writing, by the Central Government and in ratifying such contract 
the Central Government may make such alterations or modifications 
therein as it may think fit:
Provided that the Central Government shall not omit to ratify a 
contract unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly onerous 
or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the 
interests of the coking coal mine or coke oven plant.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>170</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1972</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 9, for certain words (w. e. f. 29- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>125247</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall not omit to ratify a contract or 
make any alteration or modification therein except after giving to the 
parties to the contract a reasonable opportunity of being heard and 
except after recording in writing its reasons for refusal to ratify 
the contract.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>216637</tid>
<number> 30</number> Penalties. Any person who,--
<section><tid>315785</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control of any 
property forming part of the undertaking of any coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant referred to in the First 
Schedule or the Second Schedule, as the case may be, 
wrongfully withholds such property from the Central 
Government or Government company, or

</section>

<section><tid>386875</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any 
property forming part of the undertaking of any coking 
coal mine or coke oven plant referred to in the First 
Schedule or the Second Schedule, as the case may be, or 
wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central 
Government or any person specified by that Government, 
any document relating to such coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant, which may be in his possession, custody or 
control, or fails to deliver to the Custodian any 
assets, books of account, registers or other documents 
in his custody relating to the coking coal mine or coke 
oven plant in respect of which a Custodian has been 
appointed, or

</section>

<section><tid>1083140</tid>
<number>c</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property of any 
coking coal mine or coke oven plant or prefers any 
claim under this Act in relation to such mine or plant, 
which he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to be 
false or grossly inaccurate,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>503082</tid>
<number> 31</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1310192</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>171</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:

Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>174239</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1612834</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687890</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1700750</tid>
<number>32</number>Mining companies not to be wound up by court. No proceeding 
for the winding up of a mining company, the right, title and interest 
in relation to the coking coal mine or coke oven plant owned by which 
have vested in the Central Government or in a Government company under 
this Act or for the appointment of a receiver in respect of such 
business, shall lie in any court except with the consent of the 
Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1053416</tid>
<number> 33</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>662444</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act may also be exercised by any person or persons as may 
be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1970127</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1731616</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1755045</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1353336</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1092629</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the coking coal mines or coke oven 
plants shall be managed by a Government company or a 
Custodian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292362</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which provident fund monies referred to in 
section 18 shall be dealt with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>858856</tid>
<number>c</number>the form and manner in which the statement of accounts 
referred to in section 22 shall be prepared;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1063583</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter in relation to which such rule is 
required to be, or may be, made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>509864</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1674785</tid>
<number>35</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the date of assent.



</article>



<article><tid>283642</tid>
<number> 36</number> Coking coal mines to which the Act shall not apply. Nothing 
in this Act shall apply to any coking coal mine--
<section><tid>1011727</tid>
<number>a</number>owned or managed by a Government company or corporation 
owned or controlled by Government;

</section>

<section><tid>900942</tid>
<number>b</number>owned or managed by a company engaged in the production 
of iron or steel:
Provided that this section shall not extend to such mine or part 
thereof which, in the opinion of the Central Government, is in excess 
of the requirements for the production of iron and steel by that 
company.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>