<act><title>

THE CARRIAGE BY AIR ACT, 
    1972</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Carriage by Air Act, 1972.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole 
    of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
    force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification is the Official Gazette, 
    appoint.





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> “amended Convention” means the Convention as amended by the Hague 
  Protocol on the 28th day of September, 1955; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> “Convention” means the Convention for the unification of certain rules 
  relating to international carriage by air signed at Warsaw on the 12th day of 
  October, 1929. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> “Montreal Convention” means the Convention for the 
  unification of certain rules for international carriage by air signed at 
  Montreal on the 28th day of May, 1999;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>iv</number> “Annexure” means the Annexure annexed to this Act.] 
</section>
  



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Application of Convention to India. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The rules 
contained in the First Schedule being the provisions of the Convention relating 
to the rights and liabilities of carriers, passengers, consignors, consignees 
and other persons shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, have the force 
of law in India in relation to any carriage by air to which those rules apply, 
irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing the carriage. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> For the purpose of this Act, the High Contracting Parties to 
the Convention and the date of enforcement of the said Convention shall be such 
as are included in Part I of the Annexure.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any reference in the First Schedule to the territory of any High 
Contracting Party to the Convention shall be construed as a reference to all the 
territories in respect of which he is a party. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any reference in the First Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be 
construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of 
this Act, and if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part I of 
the Annexure, any High Contracting Party and on such addition, or as the case 
may be, omission, such High Contracting Party shall be or shall cease to be, a 
High Contracting Party.] 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Application of amended Convention to India. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The 
rules contained in the Second Schedule, being the provisions of the amended 
Convention relating to the rights and liabilities of carriers, passengers, 
consignors, consignees and other persons, shall, subject to the provisions of 
this Act, have the force of law in India in relation to any carriage by air to 
which those rules apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft 
performing the carriage. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> For the purpose of this Act, the High Contracting Parties to 
the amended Convention and the date of enforcement of the said amended 
Convention shall be such as are included in Part II of the Annexure.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of 
this Act, and if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part II of 
the Annexure, any High Contracting Party and on such addition, or, as the case 
may be, omission, such High Contracting Party shall be or shall cease to be, a 
High Contracting Party.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any reference in the Second Schedule to the territory of any High 
Contracting party to the amended convention shall be construed as a reference to 
all the territories in respect of which he is a party. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any reference in the Second Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be 
construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Application of Montreal Convention to India. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> The rules contained in the Third Schedule, being the provisions of 
the Montreal Convention relating to the rights and liabilities of carriers, 
passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, have the force of law in India in relation to any 
carriage by air to which those rules apply, irrespective of the nationality of 
the aircraft performing the carriage. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of this Act, the State Parties to the Montreal Convention 
and the date of enforcement of the said Montreal Convention shall be such as are 
included in Part III of the Annexure. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any reference in the Third Schedule to the territory of any State Party 
to the Montreal Convention shall be construed as a reference to all the 
territories in respect of which he is party. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any reference in the Third Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be 
construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of this Act, and 
if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part III of the Annexure, 
any State Party and on such addition, or, as the case may be, omission, such 
State Party shall be or shall cease to be, a State Party.] 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Liability in case of death. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Fatal Accidents Act, 1855 or any other enactment or rule of law 
in force in any part of India, the rules contained in <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[the First 
Schedule, the Second Schedule and the Third Schedule] shall, in all cases to 
which those rules apply, determine the liability of a carrier in respect of the 
death of a passenger. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The liability shall be enforceable for the benefit of such of the members 
of the passenger's family as sustained damage by reason of his death. 
 Explanation .—In this sub-section, the expression “member of a 
family” means wife or husband, parent, step-parent, gand parent, brother, 
sister, half-brother, half-sister, child, step-child and grand-child: 
 Provided that in deducing any such relationship as aforesaid any illegitimate 
person and any adopted person shall be treated as being or as having been, the 
legitimate child of his mother and reputed father or, as the case may be, of his 
adopters. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An action to enforce the liability may be brought by the personal 
representative of the passenger or by any person for whose benefit the liability 
is under sub-section (2) enforceable, but only one action shall be brought in 
India in respect of the death of any one passenger, and every such action by 
whomsoever brought shall be for the benefit of all such persons so entitled as 
aforesaid as either are domiciled in India or not being domiciled there express 
a desire of take the benefit of the action. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the amount recovered in any 
such action after deducting any costs not recovered from the defendant, shall be 
divided between the persons entitled in such proportion as the Court may direct. 

 </section><section><number>5</number> The Court before which any such action is brought may, at any stage of 
the proceedings make any such order as appears to the Court to be just and
 equitable in view of the provisions, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[the First Schedule or the 
Second Schedule or the Third Schedule], as the case may be, limiting the 
liability of a carrier and of any proceedings which have been or are likely to 
be commenced outside India in respect of the death of the passenger in question. 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Conversion of francs.—Any 
    sum in francs mentioned in rule 22 of the First Schedule or of the Second 
    Schedule, as the case may be, shall, for the purpose of any action against a 
    carrier, be converted into rupees at the rate of exchange prevailing on the 
    date on which the amount of damages to be paid by the carrier is ascertained 
    by the Court.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <title>[6A Conversion of Special Drawing Rights. </title>—Any 
sum in Special Drawing Rights mentioned in rules 21 and 22 of the Third Schedule 
shall, for the purpose of any action against a carrier, be converted into rupees 
at the rate of exchange prevailing on the date on which the amount of damages to 
be paid by the carrier is ascertained by the Court in accordance with the 
provisions of rule 23 of the said Third Schedule.] 

 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Provisions regarding 
    suits against High Contracting Parties who undertake carriage by air.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every High Contracting Party to the Convention or the amended Convention, as 
    the case may be, who has not availed himself of the provisions of the 
    Additional Protocol thereto shall, for the purposes of any suit brought in a 
    Court in India in accordance with the provisions of rule 28 of the First 
    Schedule, or of the Second Schedule, as the case may be, to enforce a claim 
    in respect of carriage undertaken by him, be deemed to have submitted to the 
    jurisdiction of that Court and to be a person for the purposes of the Code 
    of Civil Procedure, 1908.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The High Court may make 
    rules of procedure providing for all matters which may be expedient to 
    enable such suits to be instituted and carried on.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this section 
    shall authorise any Court to attach or sell any property of a High 
    Contracting Party to the Convention or to the amended Convention.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Application of Act to carriage by air which is not international. 
</title>— 
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, apply the rules contained in First Schedule and any provision of 
section 3 or section 5 or section 6 to such carriage by air, not being 
international carriage by air as defined in the First Schedule, as may be 
specified in the notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations 
and modifications, if any, as may be so specified. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
apply the rules contained in the Second Schedule and any provisions of section 4 
or section 5 or section 6 to such carriage by air, not being international 
carriage by air as defined in the Second Schedule, as may be specified in the 
notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations and 
modifications, if any, as may be so specified. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, apply the rules contained in the Third Schedule and any provision of 
section 4A or section 5 or section 6A to such carriage by air, not being 
international carriage by air as defined in the Third Schedule, as may be 
specified in the notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations 
and modifications, if any, as may be so specified.] 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Repeal.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1978 (38 of 1978), sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
26-11-1978).]
  

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE CARRIAGE BY AIR ACT, 
    1972
 



 

 
 


The First Schedule
 

(See section 3)
 



Rules 

    Chapter I 

Scope—Definitions
 


1. 
    (1) These rules apply to all international carriage of persons, luggage or 
    goods performed by aircraft for reward. They apply also to such carriage 
    when performed gratuitously by an air transport undertaking.
 


(2) In these rules, “High Contracting Party” 
    means a High Contracting Party to the Convention.
 


(3) For the purposes of these rules the 
    expression, “international carriage” means any carriage in which according 
    to the contract made by the parties, the place of departure and the place of 
    destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a 
    transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High 
    Contracting Parties, or within the territory of a single High Contracting 
    Party, if there is an agreed stopping place within a territory subject to 
    the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of another Power, even 
    though that Power is not a party to the Convention. A carriage without such 
    an agreed stopping place between territories subject to the sovereignty, 
    suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party is not 
    deemed to be international for the purposes of these rules.
 


(4) A carriage to be performed by several 
    successive air carriers is deeemd, for the purposes of these rules to be one 
    undivided carriage, if it has been regarded by the parties as a single 
    operation, whether it has been agreed upon under the form of a single 
    contract or of a series of contracts, and it does not lose its international 
    character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be 
    performed entirely within a territory subject to the sovereignty, 
    suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party.
 


2. 
    (1) These rules apply to carriage performed by the State or by legally 
    constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down 
    in rule 1.
 


(2) These rules do not apply to carriage 
    performed under the terms of any international postal Convention.t
 



Chapter II 

Documents of Carriage 

Part I 



    Passenger Ticket
 


3. 
    (1) For the carriage of passengers the carrier must deliver a passenger 
    ticket which shall contain the following particulars:—
 


(a)  the place and date of issue;
 


(b)  the place of departure and of 
    destination;
 


(c)  the agreed stopping places, provided 
    that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case 
    of necessity, and that if he exercises that right, the alteration shall not 
    have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character;
 


(d)  the name and address of the carrier 
    or carriers;
 


(e)  a statement that the carriage is 
    subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.
 


(2) The absence, irregularity or loss of the 
    passenger ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the 
    contract of carriage, which shall nonetheless be subject to these rules. 
    Nevertheless, if the carrier accepts a passenger without a passenger ticket 
    having been delivered he shall not be entitled to avail himself of those 
    provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability
 

 
 


Part II 



    Luggage Ticket
 


4. 
    (1) For the carriage of luggage, other than small personal objects of which 
    the passenger takes charge himself, the carrier must deliver a luggage 
    ticket.
 


(2) The luggage ticket shall be made out in 
    duplicate, one part for the passenger and the other part for the carrier.
 


(3) The luggage ticket shall contain the 
    following particulars:—
 


(a)  the place and date of issue;
 


(b)  the place of departure and of 
    destination;
 


(c)  the name and address of the carrier 
    or carriers;
 


(d)  the number of the passenger ticket;
 


(e)  a statement that delivery of the 
    luggage will be made to the bearer of the luggage ticket;
 


(f)  the number and weight of the 
    packages;
 


(g)  the amount of the value declared in 
    accordance with rule 22(2);
 


(h)  a statement that the carriage is 
    subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.
 


(4) The absence, irregularity or loss of the 
    luggage ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract 
    of carriage, which shall nonetheless be subject to these rules. Nevertheless 
    if the carrier accepts luggage without a luggage ticket having been 
    delivered, or if the luggage ticket does not contain the particulars set out 
    at (d), (f) and (h) of sub-rule (3), the carrier shall not be entitled to 
    avail himself of those provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit 
    his liability.t
 

 
 


Part III
 


Air 
    Consignment Note
 

 
 


5. 
    (1) Every carrier of goods has the right to require the consignor to make 
    out and hand over to him a document called an “air consignment note”; every 
    consignor has the right to require the carrier to accept this document.
 


(2) The absence, irregularity or loss of this 
    document  does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of 
    carriage which shall, subject to the provisions of Rule 9, be nonetheless 
    governed by these rules.
 


6. 
    (1) The air consignment note shall be made out by the consignor in three 
    original parts and be handed over with the goods.
 


(2) The first part shall be marked “for the 
    carrier” and shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be 
    marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the 
    carrier and shall accompany the goods. The third part shall be signed by the 
    carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the goods have been 
    accepted.
 


(3) The carrier shall sign an acceptance of 
    the goods.
 


(4) The signature of the carrier may be 
    stamped; that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.
 


(5) If, at the request of the consignor, the 
    carrier makes out the air consignment note, he shall be deemed, subject to 
    proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.
 


7. 
    The carrier of goods has the right to require the consignor to make out 
    separate consignment notes when there is more than one package.
 


8. 
    The air consignment note shall contain the following particulars:—
 


(a)  the place, date of its execution;
 


(b)  the place of departure and of 
    destination;
 


(c)  the agreed stopping places, provided 
    that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case 
    of necessity, and that if he exercises that right the alteration shall not 
    have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character;
 


(d)  the name and address of the 
    consignor;
 


(e)  the name and address of the first 
    carrier;
 


(f)  the name and address of the 
    consignee, if the case so requires;
 


(g)  the nature of the goods;
 


(h)  the number of the packages, the 
    method of packing and the particular marks or numbers upon them;
 


(i)  the weight, the quantity and 
    the volume or dimensions of the goods;
 


(j)  the apparent condition of the goods 
    and of the packing;
 


(k)  the freight, if it has been agreed 
    upon, the date and place of payment, and the person who is to pay it;
 


(l)  if the goods are sent for payment on 
    delivery, the price of the goods, and if the case so requires, the amount of 
    the expenses incurred;
 


(m)  the amount of the value declared in 
    accordance with rule 22(2);
 


(n)  the number of parts of the air 
    consignment note;
 


(o)  the documents handed to the carrier 
    to accompany the air consignment note;
 


(p)  the time fixed for the completion of 
    the carriage and a brief note of the route to be followed, if these matters 
    have been agreed upon;
 


(q)  a statement that the carriage is 
    subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.
 


9. If 
    the carrier accepts goods without an air consignment note having been made 
    out, or if the air consignment note does not contain all the particulars set 
    out in rule 8(a) to (i) inclusive and (q), the carrier shall not be entitled 
    to avail himself of the provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit 
    his liability.
 


10. 
    (1) The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and 
    statements relating to the goods which he inserts in the air consignment 
    note.
 


(2) The consignor will be liable for all 
    damage suffered by the carrier or any other person of the irregularity, 
    incorrectness or incompleteness of the said particulars and statements.
 


11. 
    (1) The air consignment note is prima facie evidence of the 
    conclusion of the contract, of the receipt of the goods and of the 
    conditions of carriage.
 


(2) The statements in the air consignment note 
    relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the goods, as well as 
    those relating to the number of packages, are prima facie evidence of 
    the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and condition of 
    the goods do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far as 
    they both have been, and are stated in the air consignment note to have 
    been, checked by him in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the 
    apparent condition of the goods.
 


12. 
    (1) Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the 
    contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the goods by 
    withdrawing them at the aerodrome of departure or destination, or by 
    stopping them in the course of the journey on any landing or, by calling for 
    them to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the 
    journey to a person other than the consignee named in the air consignment 
    note or by requiring them to be returned to the aerodrome of departure. He 
    must not exercise the right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the 
    carrier or other consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the 
    exercise of this right.
 


(2) If it is impossible to carry out the 
    orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.
 


(3) If the carrier obeys the orders of the 
    consignor for the disposition of the goods without requiring the production 
    of the part of the air consignment note delivered to the latter, he will be 
    liable, without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for 
    any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in 
    possession of that part of the air consignment note.
 


(4) The right conferred on the consignor 
    ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with 
    rule 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the consignment 
    note or the goods, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor 
    resumes his right of disposition.
 


13. 
    (1) Except in the circumstances set out in rule 12, the consignee is 
    entitled, on arrival of the goods at the place of destination, to require 
    the carrier to hand over to him the air consignment note and to deliver the 
    goods to him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the 
    conditions of carriage set out in the air consignment note.
 


(2) Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the 
    duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the goods 
    arrive.
 


(3) If the carrier admits the loss of the 
    goods, or if the goods have not arrived at the expiration of seven days 
    after the date on which they ought to have arrived, the consignee is 
    entitled to put into force against the carrier the rights which flow from 
    the contract of carriage.
 


14. 
    The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights 
    given to them by rules 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting 
    in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries 
    out the obligations imposed by the contract.
 


15. 
    (1) Rules 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor 
    or the consignee, with each other or the mutual relations of third parties 
    whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.
 


(2) The provisions of rules 12, 13 and 14 can 
    only be varied by express provisions in the air consignment note.
 


16. 
    (1) The consignor must furnish such information and attach to the air 
    consignment note such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of 
    customs, octroi or police before the goods can be delivered to the 
    consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned 
    by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or 
    documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier or his 
    agents.
 


(2) The carrier is under no obligation to 
    enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or 
    documents.
 

 
 


Chapter III
 


Liability of the Carrier
 

 
 


17. 
    The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the death or 
    wounding of a passenger or any other bodily injury suffered by a passenger, 
    if the accident which caused the damage so sustained took place on board the 
    aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or 
    disembarking.
 


18. 
    (1) The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the 
    destruction or loss of, or of damage to, any registered luggage or any 
    goods, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place 
    during the carriage by air.
 


(2) The carriage by air within the meaning of 
    sub-rule (1) comprises the period during which the luggage or goods are in 
    charge of the carrier, whether in an aerodrome or on board an aircraft, or, 
    in the case of a landing outside an aerodrome in any place whatsoever.
 


(3) The period of the carriage by air does not 
    extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an 
    aerodrome. If, however, such a carriage takes place in the performance of a 
    contract for carriage by air, for the purpose of loading, delivery or 
    transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to 
    have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by 
    air.
 


19. 
    The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air 
    of passengers, luggage or goods.
 


20. 
    (1) The carrier is not liable if he proves that he and his agents have taken 
    all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for him 
    or them to take such measures.
 


(2) In the carriage of goods and luggage the 
    carrier is not liable if he proves that the damage was occasioned by 
    negligent pilotage or negligence in the handling of the aircraft or in 
    navigation and that, in all other respects, he and his agents have taken all 
    necessary measures to avoid the damage.
 


21. 
    If the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the 
    negligence of the injured person the Court may exonerate the carrier wholly 
    or partly from his liability.
 


22. 
    (1) In the carriage of passengers the liability of the carrier for each 
    passenger is limited to the sum of 1,25,000 francs. Where damages may be 
    awarded in form of periodical payments, the equivalent capital value of the 
    said payments shall not exceed 1,25,000 francs. Nevertheless, by special 
    contract the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of 
    liability.
 


(2) In the carriage of registered luggage and 
    of goods, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 250 francs per 
    kilogramme, unless the consignor has made, at the time when the package was 
    handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of the value at delivery 
    and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the 
    carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless 
    he proves that that sum is greater than the actual value to the consignor at 
    delivery.
 


(3) As regards objects of which the passenger 
    takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to 5,000 francs 
    per passenger.
 


(4) The sums mentioned in this rule shall be 
    deemed to refer to the French franc consisting of sixty-five and a half 
    miligrammes gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred.
 


23. 
    Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a lower 
    limit than that which is laid down in these rules shall be null and void, 
    but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the 
    whole contract which shall remain subject to the provisions of this 
    Schedule.
 


24. 
    (1) In the cases covered by rules 18 and 19 any action for damage, however 
    founded, can only be brought subject to the conditions and limits set out in 
    this Schedule.
 


(2) In the cases covered by rule 17, the 
    provisions of sub-rule (1) also apply, without prejudice to the questions as 
    to who are the person who have the right to bring suit and what are their 
    respective rights.
 


25. 
    (1) The carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of 
    this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability, if the damage is caused 
    by his wilful misconduct or by such default on his part as is in the opinion 
    of the Court equivalent to wilful misconduct.
 


(2)  Similarly the carrier shall not be 
    entitled to avail himself of the said provisions, if the damage is caused as 
    aforesaid by any agent of the carrier acting within the scope of his 
    employment.
 


26. 
    (1) Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of luggage or goods without 
    complaint is prima facie evidence that the same have been delivered 
    in good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage.
 


(2) In the case of damage, the person entitled 
    to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of 
    the damage, and, at the latest, within three days from the date of receipt 
    in the case of luggage and seven days from the date of receipt in the case 
    of goods. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest 
    within fourteen days from the date on which the luggage or goods have been 
    placed at his disposal.
 


(3) Every complaint must be made in writing 
    upon the document of carriage or by separate notice in writing despatched 
    within the times aforesaid.
 


(4) Failing complaint within the times 
    aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of 
    fraud on his part.
 


27. 
    In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in 
    accordance with these rules against those legally representing his estate.
 


28. 
    An action for damages must be brought at the option of the plaintiff either 
    before the Court having jurisdiction whether the carrier is ordinarily 
    resident, or has his principal place of business, or has an establishment by 
    which the contract has been made or before the Court having jurisdiction at 
    the place of destination.
 


29. 
    The right of damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought 
    within two years reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or 
    from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date 
    on which the carriage stopped.
 


30. 
    (1) In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers 
    and falling within the definition set out in sub-rule (4) of rule 1, each 
    carrier who accepts passenger’s luggage or goods is subjected to the rules 
    set out in this Schedule, and is deemed to be one of the contracting parties 
    to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part 
    of the carriage which is performed under his supervision.
 


(2) In the case of carriage of this nature, 
    the passenger or his representative can take action only against the carrier 
    who performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred, 
    save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed 
    liability for the whole journey.
 


(3) As regards luggage or goods, the passenger 
    or consignor will have  a right of action against the first carrier, and the 
    passenger or consginee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of 
    action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against 
    the carrier who performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, 
    damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally 
    liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.
 

 
 


Chapter IV
 


Provisions Relating to Combined Carriage
 

 
 


31. 
    (1) In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by 
    any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Schedule apply only to 
    the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the 
    terms of rule 1.
 


(2) Nothing in this Schedule shall prevent the 
    parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of 
    air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that 
    the provisions of this Schedule are observed as regards the carriage by air.
 

 
 


Chapter V
 


General and Final Provisions
 


32. 
    Any clause contained in the contract and all special agreements entered into 
    before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the 
    rules laid down by this Schedule, whether by deciding the law to be applied, 
    or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. 
    Nevertheless for the carriage of goods arbitration clauses are allowed, 
    subject to these rules, if the arbitration is to take place in the territory 
    of one of the High Contracting Parties within one of the jurisdictions 
    referred to in rule 28.
 


33. 
    Nothing contained in this Schedule shall prevent the carrier either from 
    refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, or from making regulations 
    which do not conflict with the provisions of this Schedule.
 


34. 
    This Schedule does not apply to international carriage by air performed by 
    way of experimental trial by air navigation undertaking with the view to the 
    establishment of a regular line of air nagivation, nor does it apply to 
    carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope 
    of an air carrier’s business.
 


35. 
    The expression “days” when used in these rules means current days, not 
    working days.
 


36. 
    When a High Contracting Party has declared at the time of ratification of or 
    of accession to the Convention that sub-rule (1) of rule 2 of these rules 
    shall not apply to international carriage by air performed directly by the 
    State, its colonies, protectorates or mandated territories or by any other 
    territory under its sovereignty, suzerainty or authority, these rules shall 
    not apply to international carriage by air so performed.
 

 
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE CARRIAGE BY AIR ACT, 
    1972
 



 

 
 


The Second Schedule
 


(See 
    section 4)
 


RULES
 


CHAPTER I
 


SCOPE -DEFINITION
 

 
 


1. 
    (1) These rules apply to all international carriage of persons, baggage or 
    cargo performed by aircraft for reward. They apply equally to gratuitous 
    carriage by aircraft performed by an air transport undertaking.
 


(2) In these rules, “High Contracting Party” 
    means a High Contracting Party to the amended Convention.
 


(3) For the purposes of these rules, the 
    expression “international carriage” means any carriage in which, according 
    to the agreement between the parties, the place of departure and the place 
    of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a 
    transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High 
    Contracting Parties or within the territory of a single High Contracting 
    Party if there is an agreed stopping place within the territory of another 
    State, even if that State is not a High Contracting Party. Carriage between 
    two points within the territory of a single High Contracting Party without 
    an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State is not 
    international carriage for the purposes of these rules.
 


(4) Carriage to be performed by several 
    successive air carriers is deemed, for the purposes of these rules, to be 
    one undivided carriage if it has been regarded by the parties as a single 
    operation, whether it had been agreed upon under the form of a single 
    contract or of a series of contracts and it does not lose its international 
    character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be 
    performed entirely within the territory of the same State.
 


2. 
    (1) These rules apply to carriage performed by the State or by legally 
    constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down 
    in rule 1.
 


(2) These rules shall not apply to carriage of 
    mail and post packages.
 

 
 


Chapter II
 


Documents of Carriage
 


Part I
 



    Passenger Ticket
 

 
 


3. 
    (1) In respect of the carriage of passengers a ticket shall be delivered 
    containing:
 


(a)  an indication of the place of 
    departure and destination;
 


(b)  if the places of departure and 
    destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one 
    or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, 
    an indication of at least one such stopping place;
 


(c)  a notice to the effect that, if the 
    passenger’s journey involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country 
    other than the country of departure, the amended Convention may be 
    applicable and that the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits 
    the liability of carriers for death or personal injury and in respect of 
    loss of, or damage to, baggage.
 


(2) The passenger ticket shall constitute 
    prima facie evidence of the conclusion and conditions of the contract of 
    carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of the passenger ticket does not 
    affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which 
    shall, nonetheless, be subject to these rules. Nevertheless, if with the 
    consent of the carrier, the passenger embarks without a passenger ticket 
    having been delivered, or if the ticket does not include the notice required 
    by sub-rule (1)(c)  of this rule, the carrier shall not be entitled to avail 
    himself of the provisions of rule 22.
 

 
 


Part II
 



    Baggage Check
 

 
 


4. 
    (1) In respect of the carriage of registered baggage, a baggage check shall 
    be delivered, which, unless combined with or incorporated in a passenger 
    ticket which complies with the provisions of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall 
    contain:
 


(a)  an indication of the places of 
    departure and destination;
 


(b)  if the places of departure and 
    destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one 
    or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, 
    an indication of at least one such stopping place;
 


(c)  a notice to the effect that, if the 
    carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than 
    the country of departure, the amended Convention may be applicable and that 
    the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of 
    carriers in respect of loss of, or damage to baggage.
 


(2) The baggage check shall constitute 
    prima facie evidence of the registration of the baggage and of the 
    conditions of the contract of carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of 
    the baggage check does not affect the existence or the validity of the 
    contract of carriage which shall, nonetheless, be subject to these rules. 
    Nevertheless, if the carrier takes charge of the baggage without a baggage 
    check having been delivered or if the baggage check [unless combined with or 
    incorporated in the passenger’s ticket with the provisions of sub-rule 
    (1)(c) of rule 3] does not include the notice required by sub-rule (1)(c) of 
    this rule, he shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 22.
 

 
 


Part III
 


Air 
    Waybill
 

 
 


5. 
    (1) Every carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make 
    out and hand over to him a document called as “air waybill”; every consignor 
    has the right to require the carrier to accept this document.
 


(2) The absence, irregularity or loss of this 
    document does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of 
    carriage which shall, subject to the provisions of rule 9, be nonetheless 
    governed by these rules.
 


6. 
    (1) The air waybill shall be made out by the consignor in the three original 
    parts and be handed over with the cargo.
 


(2) The first part shall be marked “for the 
    carrier”, and shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be 
    marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the 
    carrier and shall accompany the cargo. The third part shall be signed by the 
    carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the cargo has been 
    accepted.
 


(3) The carrier shall sign prior to the 
    loading of the cargo on board the aircraft.
 


(4) The signature of the carrier may be 
    stamped; that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.
 


(5) If, at the request of the consignor, the 
    carrier makes out the air waybill, he shall be deemed, subject to proof to 
    the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.
 


7. 
    The carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out 
    separate waybills when there is more than one package.
 


8. 
    The air waybill shall contain:
 


(a)  an indication of the places of 
    departure and destination;
 


(b)  if the places of departure and 
    destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one 
    or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, 
    an indication of at least one such stopping place;
 


(c)  a notice to the consignor to the 
    effect that, if the carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a 
    country other than the country of departure, the amended Convention may be 
    applicable and that the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits 
    the liability of carriers in respect of loss of, or damage to, cargo.
 


9. 
    If, with the consent of the carrier, cargo is loaded on board the aircraft 
    without an air waybill having been made out, or if the air waybill does not 
    include the notice required by rule 8(c), the carrier shall not be entitled 
    to avail himself of the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 22.
 


10. 
    (1) The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and 
    statements relating to the cargo which he inserts in the air waybill.
 


(2) The consignor shall indemnify the carrier 
    against all damage suffered by him, or by any other person to whom the 
    carrier is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or 
    incompleteness of the particulars and statements furnished by the consignor.
 


11. 
    (1) The air waybill is prima facie evidence of the conclusion of the 
    contract, of the receipt of the cargo and of the conditions of carriage.
 


(2) The statements in the air waybill relating 
    to the weight, dimensions and packing of the cargo, as well as those 
    relating to the number of packages, are prima facie evidence of the 
    facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and conditions of the 
    cargo do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far they both 
    have been, and are stated in the air waybill to have been checked by him in 
    the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent conditions of the 
    cargo.
 


12. 
    (1) Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the 
    contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the cargo by 
    withdrawing it at the aerodrome of departure or destination, or by stopping 
    it in the course of the journey on any landing, or by calling for it to be 
    delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a 
    person other than the consignee named in the air waybill, or by requiring it 
    to be returned to the aerodrome of departure. He must not exercise this 
    right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other 
    consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this 
    right.
 


(2) If it is impossible to carry out the 
    orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.
 


(3) If the carrier obeys the orders of the 
    consignor for the disposition of the cargo without requiring the production 
    of the part of the air waybill delivered to the latter, he will be liable, 
    without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for any 
    damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in 
    possession of that part of the air waybill.
 


(4) The right conferred on the consignor 
    ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with 
    rule 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the waybill or 
    the cargo, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes his 
    right of disposition.
 


13. 
    (1) Except in the circumstances set out in the preceding rule, the consignee 
    is entitled on arrival of the cargo at the place of destination to require 
    the carrier to hand over to him the air waybill and to deliver the cargo to 
    him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of 
    carriage set out in the air way bill.
 


(2) Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the 
    duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the cargo 
    arrives.
 


(3) If the carrier admits the loss of the 
    cargo, or if the cargo has not arrived at the expiration of seven days after 
    the date on which it ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to put 
    into force against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of 
    carriage.
 


14. 
    The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights 
    given to them by rules 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting 
    in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries 
    out the obligations imposed by the contract.
 


15. 
    (1) Rules 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor 
    or the consignee with each other or the mutual relations of third parties 
    whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.
 


(2) The provisions of rules 12, 13 and 14 can 
    only be varied by express provision in the air waybill.
 


(3) Nothing in these rules prevents the issue 
    of a negotiable air waybill.
 


16. 
    (1) The consignor must furnish such information and attach to the air 
    waybill such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, 
    octroi or police before the cargo can be delivered to the consignee. The 
    consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, 
    insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless 
    the damage is due to the fault of the carrier or his servants or agents.
 


(2) The carrier is under no obligation to 
    enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or 
    documents.
 

 
 


Chapter III
 


Liability of the carrier
 

 
 


17. 
    The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the death or 
    wounding of a passenger or any other bodily injury suffered by a passenger 
    if the accident which caused the damage so sustained took place on board the 
    aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or 
    disembarking.
 


18. 
    (1) The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the 
    destruction or loss of, or of damage to, any registered baggage or any 
    cargo, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place 
    during the carriage by air.
 


(2) The carriage by air within the meaning of 
    the preceding sub-rule comprises the period during which the baggage or 
    cargo is in charge of the carrier, whether in an aerodrome or on board an 
    aircraft, or in the case of a landing outside an aerodrome, in any place 
    whatsoever.
 


(3) The period of the carriage by air does not 
    extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an 
    aerodrome. If, however, such a carriage takes place in the performance of a 
    contract for carriage by air for the purpose of loading delivery or 
    transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to 
    have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by 
    air.
 


19. 
    The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air 
    of passengers, baggage or cargo.
 


20. 
    The carrier is not liable if he proves that he and his servants or agents 
    have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was 
    impossible for him or them to take such measures.
 


21. 
    If the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the 
    negligence of the injured person the Court may in accordance with the 
    provisions of its own law exonerate the carrier wholly or partly from his 
    liability.
 


22. 
    (1) In the carriage of persons the liability of the carrier for each 
    passenger is limited to the sum of 2,50,000 francs. Where, in accordance 
    with the law of the Court seized of the case, damages may be awarded in the 
    form of periodical payments the equivalent capital value of the said 
    payments shall not exceed 2,50,000 francs. Nevertheless, by special 
    contract, the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of 
    liability.
 


(2) (a) In the carriage of registered baggage 
    and of cargo, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 250 francs 
    per kilogramme, unless the passenger or consignor has made, at the time when 
    the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of 
    interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the 
    case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not 
    exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that that sum is greater than 
    the passenger’s or consignor’s actual interest in delivery at destination.
 


(b) In the case of loss, damage or delay of 
    part of registered baggage or cargo, or of any object contained therein, the 
    weight to be taken into consideration in determining the amount to which the 
    carrier’s liability is limited shall be only the total weight of the package 
    or packages concerned. Nevertheless, when the loss, damage or delay of a 
    part of the registered baggage or cargo, or of an object contained therein, 
    affects the value of other packages covered by the same baggage check or the 
    same air waybill, the total weight of such package or packages shall also be 
    taken into consideration in determining the limit of liability.
 


(3) As regards objects of which the passenger 
    takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to 5,000 francs 
    per passenger.
 


(4) The limits prescribed in this rule shall 
    not prevent the Court from awarding in accordance with its own law, in 
    addition, the whole or part of the Court costs and of the other expenses of 
    the litigation incurred by the plaintiff. The foregoing provision shall not 
    apply if the amount of the damages awarded, excluded Court costs and other 
    expenses of the litigation, does not exceed the sum which the carrier has 
    offered in writing to the plaintiff within a period of six months from the 
    date of the occurrence causing the damage, or before the commencement of the 
    action, if that is later.
 


(5) The sums mentioned in francs in this rule 
    shall be deemed to refer to a currency unit consisting of sixty-five and a 
    half miligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. These sums may 
    be converted into national currencies in round figures. Convention of the 
    sums into national currencies other than gold shall, in case of judicial 
    proceedings, be made according to the gold value of such currencies at the 
    date of the judgment.
 


23. 
    (1) Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a 
    lower limit than that which is laid down in these rules shall be null and 
    void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of 
    the whole contract, which shall remain subject to the provisions of these 
    rules.
 


(2) Sub-rule (1) of this rule shall not apply 
    to provisions governing loss or damage resulting from the inherent defect, 
    quality or vice of the cargo carried.
 


24. 
    (1) In the cases covered by rules 18 and 19 any action for damages, however 
    founded, can only be brought, subject to the conditions and limits set out 
    in these rules.
 


(2) In the cases covered by rule 17 the 
    provisions of the preceding sub-rule also apply, without prejudice to the 
    questions as to who are the persons who have the right to bring suit and 
    what are their respective rights.
 


25. 
    The limits of liability specified in rule 22 shall not apply if it is proved 
    that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the carrier, his 
    servants or agents, done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with 
    knowledge that damage would probably result; provided that, in the case of 
    such act or omission of a servant or agent, it is also proved that he was 
    acting within the scope of his employment.
 


26. 
    (1) If an action is brought against a servant or agent of the carrier 
    arising out of damage to which these rules relate, such servant or agent, if 
    he proves that he acted within the scope of his employment, shall be 
    entitled to avail himself of the limits of liability which that carrier 
    himself is entitled to invoke under rule 22.
 


(2) The aggregate of the amounts recoverable 
    from the carrier, his servants and agents, in that case, shall not exceed 
    the said limits.
 


(3) The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) of 
    this rule shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an 
    act or omission of the servant or agent done with intent to cause damage or 
    recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result.
 


27. 
    (1) Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of baggage or cargo without 
    complaint is prima facie evidence that the same has been delivered in 
    good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage.
 


(2) In the case of damage, the person entitled 
    to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of 
    the damage, and, at the latest, within seven days from the date of receipt 
    in the case of baggage and fourteen days from the date of receipt in the 
    case of cargo. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest 
    within twenty-one days from the date on which the baggage or cargo have been 
    placed at his disposal.
 


(3) Every complaint must be made in writing 
    upon the document of carriage or by separate notice in writing despatched 
    within the time aforesaid.
 


(4) Failing complaint within the times 
    aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of 
    fraud on his part.
 


28. 
    In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in 
    accordance with the terms of these rules against those legally representing 
    his estate.
 


29. 
    (1) An action for damages must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, 
    in the territory of one of the High Contracting Parties, either before the 
    Court having jurisdiction where the carrier is ordinarily resident, or has 
    his principal place of business, or has an establishment by which the 
    contract has been made or before the Court have jurisdiction at the place of 
    destination.
 


(2) Questions of procedure shall be governed 
    by the law of the Court seized of the case.
 


30. 
    (1) The right to damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought 
    within two years, reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or 
    from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date 
    on which the carriage stopped.
 


(2) The method of calculating the period of 
    limitation shall be determined by the law of the Court seized of the case.
 


31. 
    (1) In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers 
    and falling within the definition set out in sub-rule (3) of rule 1, each 
    carrier who accepts passengers, baggage or cargo is subjected to the rules 
    set out in this Schedule, and is deemed to be one of the contracting parties 
    to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part 
    of the carriage which is performed under his supervision.
 


(2) In the case of carriage of this nature, 
    the passenger or his representative can take action only against the carrier 
    who performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred 
    save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed 
    liability for the whole journey.
 


(3) As regards baggage or cargo, the passenger 
    or consignor will have a right of action against the first carrier, and the 
    passenger or consignee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of 
    action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against 
    the carrier who performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, 
    damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally 
    liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.
 

 
 


Chapter IV
 


Provisions Relating to Combined Carriage
 

 
 


32. 
    (1) In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by 
    any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Schedule apply only to 
    the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the 
    terms of rule (1).
 


(2) Nothing in this Schedule shall prevent the 
    parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of 
    air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that 
    the provisions of the Schedule are observed as regards the carriage by air.
 

 
 


Chapter V
 


General and Final Provisions
 

 
 


33. 
    Any clause contained in the contract and all special agreements entered into 
    before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the 
    rules laid down by this Schedule, whether by deciding the law to be applied, 
    or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. 
    Nevertheless for the carriage of cargo arbitration clauses are allowed, 
    subject to these rules, if the arbitration is to take place within one of 
    the jurisdictions referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 29.
 


34. 
    Nothing contained in this Schedule shall prevent the carrier either from 
    refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, or from making regulations 
    which do not conflict with the provisions of this Schedule.
 


35. 
    The provisions of rules 3 to 9 (inclusive) relating to documents of carriage 
    shall not apply in the case of carriage performed in extraordinary 
    circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business.
 


36. 
    The expression “days” when used in these rules means current days not 
    working days. 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came 
    into force on 15-5-1973, vide S.O. 170(E), dated 23rd March, 1973, 
    published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), dated 26th 
    March, 1973</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 4(a), for sub-section (2) 
(w.e.f. 1-7-2009 ). Sub-section (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 4(b), for sub-section (5) 
(w.e.f. 1-7-2009 ). Sub-section (5), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 5, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 
1-7-2009 ). Sub-section (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
1-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 7(a), for “the First Schedule 
and in the Second Schedule” (w.e.f. 1-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
1-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2009, sec. 9, for sub-section (3) (w.e.f. 
1-7-2009 ). Sub-section (3), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>