<act><tid>137892</tid>
<title>THE MARINE PRODUCTS EXPORT DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 13 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 20th April, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of an Authority for the 
development of the marine products industry under the control of the 
Union and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1379244</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>198592</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Marine Products Export Development Authority Act, <year>1972</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>124766</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>682427</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
Provided that different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>362516</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is 
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
Union should take under its control the marine products industry.


</article>



<article><tid>651719</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1218977</tid>
<number>a</number>" Authority" means the Marine Products Export Development 
Authority established under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1728426</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>10300</tid>
<number>c</number>" conveyance" includes a carrier vessel or a vehicle;

</section>

<section><tid>135746</tid>
<number>d</number>" dealer" means a dealer in any of the marine products;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>368</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The provisions of sections 11 to 19 (both inclusive) shall come 
into force w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1973</year>; vide Notifin. No. G. S. R. 8 (E), dated 10- 
1- <year>1973</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 15.

The provisions of sections other than sections 11 to 19 (both  
  inclusive) shall come into force w. e. f. 12- 7- <year>1972</year>; vide Notifin. No. 
G. S. R. 338 (E), dated 12- 7- <year>1972</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. 
II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 377.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1916634</tid>
<number>e</number>" Director" means the Director of Marine Products Export 
Development appointed under section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>643064</tid>
<number>f</number>" export" and" import" mean respectively taking out of, 
or bringing into, India by land, sea or air;

</section>

<section><tid>331704</tid>
<number>g</number>" fishing vessel" means a ship or boat fitted with 
mechanical means of propulsion which is exclusively 
engaged in sea- fishing for profit;

</section>

<section><tid>1512714</tid>
<number>h</number>" marine products" includes all varieties of fishery 
products known commercially as shrimp, prawn, lobster, 
crab, fish, shell- fish, other aquatic animals or plants 
or part thereof and any other products which the 
Authority may, by notification in the Gazette of India, 
declare to be marine products for the purposes of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>662867</tid>
<number>i</number>" member" means a member of the Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>160391</tid>
<number>j</number>" owner", in relation to any fishing vessel or in 
relation to any processing plant or storage premises 
for marine products or in relation to any conveyance 
used for the transport of marine products, includes--

<subsection><tid>1253992</tid>
<number>i</number>any agent of the owner; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200570</tid>
<number>ii</number>a mortgagee, lessee or other person in 
actual possession of the fishing vessel, 
processing plant, storage premises or conveyance;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>852186</tid>
<number>k</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>751565</tid>
<number>l</number>" processing", in relation to marine products, includes 
the preservation of such products such as canning, 
freezing, drying, salting, smoking, peeling or 
filleting and any other method of processing which the 
Authority may, by notification in the Gazette of India, 
specify in this behalf.
CHAP

MARINE PRODUCTS EXPORT DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY

CHAPTER II

MARINE PRODUCTS EXPORT DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>358707</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and constitution of the Authority.
<section><tid>1886330</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, there shall be 
established for the purposes of this Act, an Authority to be called 
the marine Products Export Development Authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>369</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>526684</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name 
aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power 
to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, 
and to contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>556163</tid>
<number>3</number>The Authority shall consist of the following members, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1284883</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257528</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director of Marine Products Export Development, ex- 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1802720</tid>
<number>c</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be elected 
by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>242685</tid>
<number>d</number>five members to represent respectively the Ministries of 
the Central Government dealing with--

<subsubsection><tid>423625</tid>
<number>i</number>agriculture,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1948058</tid>
<number>ii</number>finance,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>703116</tid>
<number>iii</number>foreign trade,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>710802</tid>
<number>iv</number>industry, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1003194</tid>
<number>v</number>shipping and transport;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1963829</tid>
<number>e</number>such number of other members not exceeding twenty as the 
Central Government may think expedient, to be appointed 
by that Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette from among persons who are in its opinion 
capable of representing--

<subsubsection><tid>772222</tid>
<number>i</number>the Governments of the States or Union 
territories having a sea- coast;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>640971</tid>
<number>ii</number>the interests of owners of fishing 
vessels, processing plants or storage premises for 
marine products and conveyances used for the 
transport of marine products;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>660236</tid>
<number>iii</number>the interests of dealers;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1491836</tid>
<number>iv</number>the interests of persons employed in the 
marine products industry;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1622845</tid>
<number>v</number>the interests of persons employed in 
research institutions engaged in the researches 
connected with the said industry; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1603502</tid>
<number>vi</number>such other persons or class of persons 
who, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
ought to be represented on the Authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>370</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>361691</tid>
<number>4</number>The number of persons to be appointed as members from each of 
the categories specified in clause (e) of sub- section (3), the term of 
office of the members other than the member referred to in clause (b) 
of that sub- section, and the manner of filling vacancies among, and 
the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their functions by 
the members shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>512445</tid>
<number>5</number>Any officer of the Central Government, not being a member of 
the Authority, when deputed by that Government in this behalf, shall 
have the right to attend meetings of the Authority and take part in 
the proceedings thereof but shall not be entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>858768</tid>
<number>6</number>The Authority shall elect from among its members a Vice- 
Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the 
functions of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated 
to him by the Chairman.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1209124</tid>
<number> 5</number> Acts or proceedings of Authority or its Committees not to be 
invalidated. No act or proceeding of the Authority or any Committee 
appointed by it under section 8, shall be invalidated merely by reason 
of--
<section><tid>1560231</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Authority or such Committee; or

</section>

<section><tid>1804359</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Authority or such Committee; or

</section>

<section><tid>1893849</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority or 
such Committee not affecting the merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1033291</tid>
<number>6</number>Salary and allowances of Chairman. The Chairman shall be 
entitled to such salary and allowances and such conditions of service 
in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters as may, 
from time to time, be fixed by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1527380</tid>
<number> 7</number> Executive officers of the Authority and other staff.
<section><tid>683742</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government shall appoint a Director of Marine Products Export 
Development to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the 
Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1190354</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall appoint a Secretary to the 
Authority to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the 
Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1648712</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director and the Secretary to the Authority shall be 
entitled to such salaries and allowances and such conditions of 
service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters 
as may be fixed by the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>371</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1251494</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be 
prescribed, the Authority may appoint such other officers and 
employees as may be necessary for the efficient performance of its 
functions and pay them such salaries and allowances as it may 
determine from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>1027783</tid>
<number>5</number>The Chairman, the Director, the Secretary and other employees 
of the Authority shall not undertake any work unconnected with their 
duties under this Act except with the permission of the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>525155</tid>
<number> 8</number> Committees of the Authority.
<section><tid>801827</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may appoint  
such Committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
duties and performance of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1222826</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall have the power to co- opt as members of 
any Committee appointed under sub- section (1) such other number of 
persons who are not members of the Authority, as it may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>853691</tid>
<number> 9</number> Functions of the Authority.
<section><tid>1127680</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the  
Authority to promote, by such measures as it thinks fit, the 
development under the control of the Central Government of the marine 
products industry with special reference to exports.

</section>

<section><tid>1428889</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub- 
section (1), the measures referred to therein may provide for--

<subsection><tid>268112</tid>
<number>a</number>developing and regulating off- shore and deep- sea fishing 
and undertaking measures for the conservation and 
management of off- shore and deep- sea fisheries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>659680</tid>
<number>b</number>registering fishing vessel, processing plants or storage 
premises for marine products and conveyances used for 
the transport of marine products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1872668</tid>
<number>c</number>fixing of standards and specifications for marine 
products for purposes of export;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1074133</tid>
<number>d</number>rendering of financial or other assistance to owners of 
fishing vessels engaged in off- shore and deep- sea 
fishing and owners of processing plants or storage 
premises for marine products and conveyances used for 
the transport of marine products, and acting as an 
agency for such relief and subsidy schemes as may be 
entrusted to the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>640456</tid>
<number>e</number>carrying out inspection of marine products in any 
fishing vessel, processing plant, storage premises, 
conveyance or other place where such products are kept 
or handled, for the purpose of ensuring the quality of 
such products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535367</tid>
<number>f</number>regulating the export of marine products;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>372</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1487604</tid>
<number>g</number>improving the marketing of marine products outside 
India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>127377</tid>
<number>h</number>registering of exporters of marine products on payment 
of such fees as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>741362</tid>
<number>i</number>collecting statistics from persons engaged in the 
catching of fish or other marine products, owners of 
processing plants or storage premises for marine 
products or conveyances used for the transport of 
marine products, exporters of such products and such 
other persons as may be prescribed on any matter 
relating to the marine products industry and the 
publishing of statistics so collected. or portions 
thereof or extracts therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1022194</tid>
<number>j</number>training in various aspects of the marine products 
industry; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1989721</tid>
<number>k</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>253793</tid>
<number>3</number>The Authority shall perform its functions under this section 
in accordance with and subject to such rules as may be made by the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>554343</tid>
<number> 10</number> Dissolution of the Authority.
<section><tid>1748512</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette and for reasons to be 
specified therein, direct that the Authority shall be dissolved from 
such date and for such period as may be specified in the notification:
Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central 
Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Authority to 
make representations against the proposed dissolution and shall 
consider the representations, if any, of the Authority.


</section>

<section><tid>810563</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Authority is dissolved under the provisions of sub- 
section (1),--

<subsection><tid>483552</tid>
<number>a</number>all members notwithstanding that their term of office 
has not expired, shall, from the date of dissolution, 
vacate their offices as such members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1244642</tid>
<number>b</number>all powers and duties of the Authority shall, during the 
period of dissolution, be exercised and performed by 
such person or persons as the Central Government may 
appoint in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1639012</tid>
<number>c</number>all funds and other property vested in the Authority 
shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the 
Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>648094</tid>
<number>d</number>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the 
Authority shall be reconstituted in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>373</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

REGISTRATION

CHAPTER III

REGISTRATION




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1930388</tid>
<number> 11</number> Registration of fishing vessel, processing plant, etc.
<section><tid>1591222</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every owner of a fishing vessel, processing plant or storage premises 
for marine products or conveyance used for the transport of marine 
products shall, before the expiration of one month from the date on 
which he first became owner of such fishing vessel, processing plant, 
storage premises or conveyance, or before the expiration of three 
months from the date of coming into force of this section, whichever 
is later, apply to the Authority for registration under this Act of 
every such fishing vessel, processing plant, storage premises, or 
conveyance owned by him:
Provided that the Authority may, for sufficient reason, extend 
the time- limit for registration by such period as it thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1135471</tid>
<number>2</number>Registration once made shall continue to be in force until it 
is cancelled by the Authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1357621</tid>
<number>12</number>Application, cancellation, fee payable and other matters 
relating to registration. The form of application for registration 
under section 11 and for the cancellation of such registration, the 
fee payable on such applications, the particulars to be included in 
such applications, the procedure to be followed in granting and 
cancelling registration and the registers to be kept by the Authority 
shall be such as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>773322</tid>
<number> 13</number> Returns to be made by owners.
<section><tid>1658022</tid>
<number>1</number>Every owner referred to in  
sub- section (1) of section 11 shall furnish to the Authority at the 
prescribed time and in the prescribed manner such returns as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1009816</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority may authorise a member or any of its officers 
to inspect any fishing vessel, processing plant, storage premises or 
conveyance at any time to verify the accuracy of any return made under 
this section.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1269155</tid>
<number> 14</number> lmposition of a cess on marine products exported.
<section><tid>462370</tid>
<number>1</number>There  
shall be levied on all marine products which are exported, a cess for 
the purposes of this Act at such rate not exceeding three per cent. ad 
valorem as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, fix.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>374</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1005030</tid>
<number>2</number>The cess levied under sub- section (1) shall be in addition to 
any cess or duty leviable on marine products under any other law for 
the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1568310</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>), and 
the rules and regulations made thereunder, including those relating to 
refunds and exemptions from duty, shall, as far as may be, apply in 
relation to the levy and collection of the cess leviable under sub- 
section (1) as they apply in relation to the levy and collection of a 
duty of customs under that Act or those rules and regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>18404</tid>
<number>15</number>Payment of proceeds of cess to the Authority. The proceeds of 
the cess levied under section 14 shall first be credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of India and the Central Government may, if 
Parliament by appropriation made by law in this behalf so provides, 
pay to the Authority, from time to time from out of such proceeds, 
after deducting the expenses of collection, such sums of money as it 
may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1874803</tid>
<number>16</number>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, pay to the Authority by way of grants or loans such sums 
of money as the Central Government may consider necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>708364</tid>
<number> 17</number> Constitution of the Fund.
<section><tid>67601</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be formed a Fund to  
be called the Marine Products Export Development Fund and there shall 
be credited thereto--

<subsection><tid>460633</tid>
<number>a</number>the proceeds of the cess made over to the Authority by 
the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930464</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees levied and collected in respect of registration 
made under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>390511</tid>
<number>c</number>any other fee that may be levied and collected by the 
Authority under this Act or the rules made thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>889980</tid>
<number>d</number>any grants or loans that may be made by the Central 
Government for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1743303</tid>
<number>e</number>any grants or loans that may be made by any institution 
for the purposes of this Act: and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1701314</tid>
<number>f</number>all sums realised by the Authority in carrying out the 
measures referred to in section 9.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1904012</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>359079</tid>
<number>a</number>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other 
remuneration of the officers and other employees of the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1925548</tid>
<number>b</number>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the 
Authority;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>375</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443975</tid>
<number>c</number>for meeting the cost of the measures referred to in 
section 9; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>871758</tid>
<number>d</number>for repayment of any loans from the Central Government 
or from any institution.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>10667</tid>
<number>18</number>Borrowing powers of the Authority. Subject to such rules as 
may be made in this behalf, the Authority shall have power to borrow 
on the security of the Marine Products Export Development Fund or any 
other asset for carrying out the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>861268</tid>
<number> 19</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1369690</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the profit and loss account and the balance- sheet 
in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>466071</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Authority shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be 
specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such 
audit shall be payable by the Authority to the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General.

</section>

<section><tid>293878</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Authority shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has 
in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>412788</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in 
this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded 
annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the 
same to be laid before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT

CHAPTER V

CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>928372</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to prohibit or control imports and exports of marine 
products.
<section><tid>1490763</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by order published in the  
Official Gazette, make provision for prohibiting, restricting or 
otherwise controlling the import or export of marine products, either 
generally or in specified classes of cases.

</section>

<section><tid>1949532</tid>
<number>2</number>All marine products to which any order under sub- section (1) 
applies, shall be deemed to be goods of which the import or export has 
been prohibited under section 11 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of  
  <year>1962</year>), and all the provisions of that Act shall have effect 
accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>376</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>43102</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person contravenes any order made under sub- section 
 (1) he shall, without prejudice to any confiscation or penalty to 
which he may be liable under the provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> 
 (52 of <year>1962</year>), as applied by sub- section (2), be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or 
with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>884503</tid>
<number>21</number>Directions by Central Government. The Authority shall carry 
out such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the 
Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>232654</tid>
<number> 22</number> Returns and reports.
<section><tid>720104</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall furnish to the  
Central Government, at such time and in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such returns and 
statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing 
programme for the promotion and development of the marine products 
industry, as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.

</section>

<section><tid>146023</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Authority shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial 
year, submit to the Central Government a report in such form and 
before such date, as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account 
of its activities, policy and programmes during the previous financial 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>251272</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be 
laid before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>475946</tid>
<number>23</number>Penalty for making false returns. Any person who being 
required by or under this Act to furnish any return fails to furnish 
such return or furnishes a return containing any particular which is 
false and which he knows to be false or does not believe to be true 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>407997</tid>
<number> 24</number> Penalties for obstructing a member or officer of the 
Authority in the discharge of his duties and for failure to produce 
books and records. Any person who--
<section><tid>1654108</tid>
<number>a</number>obstructs any member authorised by the Chairman in 
writing or any officer or other employee of the 
Authority authorised by it in this behalf or any person 
authorised in this behalf by the Central Government or 
by the Authority, in the exercise of any power 
conferred, or in the discharge of any duty imposed, on 
him by or under this Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>651249</tid>
<number>b</number>having control over or custody of any account book or 
other record, fails to produce such book or record when 
required to do so by or under this Act,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>377</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>195866</tid>
<number>25</number>Other penalties. Whoever contravenes or attempts to 
contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of this Act or 
of any rules made thereunder other than the provisions, punishment for 
the contravention whereof has been provided for in sections 20, 23 and 
24, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
or with both, and in the case of a continuing contravention with an 
additional fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every day during 
which such contravention continues after conviction for the first such 
contravention.


</article>



<article><tid>915041</tid>
<number> 26</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1056884</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all 
due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1892623</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


<subsection><tid>792959</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>440939</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>867550</tid>
<number>27</number>Jurisdiction of court. No court inferior to that of a 
Presidency magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence punishable under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1622371</tid>
<number>28</number>Previous sanction of Central Government. No prosecution for 
any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted except with 
the previous sanction of the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>378</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>864842</tid>
<number>29</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the 
Government, or the Authority or any Committee appointed by it, or any 
member of the Authority or such Committee, or any officer or other 
employee of the Government or of the Authority or any other person 
authorised by the Government or the Authority, for anything which is 
in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules 
made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1738257</tid>
<number>30</number>Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by order 
notified in the Official Gazette, direct that any power exercisable by 
it under this Act (not being the power to make rules under section 33) 
may also be exercised, in such cases and subject to such conditions, 
if any, as may be specified in the order, by such officer or authority 
as may be specified therein.


</article>



<article><tid>892723</tid>
<number> 31</number> Suspension of operation of Act.
<section><tid>412730</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government  
is satisfied that circumstances have arisen rendering it necessary 
that certain of the restrictions imposed by this Act should cease to 
be imposed or if it considers necessary or expedient so to do in the 
public interest, the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, suspend or relax to a specified extent, either 
indefinitely or for such period as may be specified in the 
notification, the operation of all or any of the provisions of this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1641633</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the operation of any provision of this Act has under 
sub- section (1) been suspended or relaxed indefinitely, such 
suspension or relaxation may at any time while this Act remains in 
force be removed by the Central Government by notification in the 
Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1012976</tid>
<number>32</number>Application of other laws not barred. The provisions of this 
Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of 
any other law for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>576218</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1818686</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1185839</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>540733</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of persons to be appointed as members from 
each of the categories specified in clause (e) of sub- 
section (3) of section 4, the term of office and other 
conditions of service of members, the manner of filling 
vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed in 
the discharge of their functions by, such members;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>379</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>233984</tid>
<number>b</number>the circumstances in which and the authority by which a 
member may be removed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>104881</tid>
<number>c</number>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the 
Authority every year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1893422</tid>
<number>d</number>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the 
Authority for the conduct of business and the number of 
members which shall form a quorum at a meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>340356</tid>
<number>e</number>the maintenance by the Authority of records of business 
transacted by the Authority and the submission of 
copies thereof to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1705688</tid>
<number>f</number>the powers of the Authority, its Chairman, the Director 
and Committees of the Authority with respect to the 
incurring of expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5777</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions subject to which the Authority may incur 
expenditure outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>279505</tid>
<number>h</number>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and 
expenditure of the Authority and the authority by which 
the estimates are to be sanctioned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1957153</tid>
<number>i</number>the form and manner in which the accounts should be kept 
by the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1316080</tid>
<number>j</number>the deposit of the funds of the Authority in banks and 
the investment of such funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>376020</tid>
<number>k</number>the conditions subject to which the Authority may 
borrow;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>361977</tid>
<number>l</number>the conditions subject to which and the manner in which 
contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>924186</tid>
<number>m</number>the additional matters in respect of which the Authority 
may undertake measures in the discharge of its 
functions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1863098</tid>
<number>n</number>the remuneration and other allowances payable to the 
person or persons referred to in clause (b) of sub- 
section (2) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>201397</tid>
<number>o</number>the form of, and the particulars to be contained in, any 
returns or reports to be made to the Authority under 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563065</tid>
<number>p</number>the form of, and the manner of making applications for 
registration and for its cancellation by the Authority, 
the fee payable on such applications and the procedure 
to be followed in granting and cancelling registration 
and the conditions governing such registration;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>380</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>407116</tid>
<number>q</number>the collection of any information or statistics in 
respect of marine products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1438428</tid>
<number>r</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed by, 
or provided for by rules under, this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1083446</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>720624</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1319794</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may make  
regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>449825</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>53365</tid>
<number>a</number>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the 
Committees appointed by the Authority and the number of 
members which shall form a quorum at a meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1979615</tid>
<number>b</number>the delegation to the Chairman, members, Director, 
Secretary or other officers of the Authority of any of 
the powers and duties of the Authority under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1375966</tid>
<number>c</number>the travelling and other allowances of members of the 
Authority and of Committees thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1589023</tid>
<number>d</number>the pay and allowances and leave and other conditions of 
service of officers (other than those appointed by the  
  Central Government) and other employees of the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>714373</tid>
<number>e</number>the maintenance of its accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92888</tid>
<number>f</number>the maintenance of the registers and other records of 
the Authority and its various Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>14541</tid>
<number>g</number>the appointment by the Authority of agents to discharge 
on its behalf any of its functions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>949580</tid>
<number>h</number>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments, 
deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the 
Authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>381</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1433947</tid>
<number>3</number>No regulation made by the Authority shall have effect until 
it has been approved by the Central Government and published in the 
Official Gazette, and the Central Government, in confirming a 
regulation, may make any change therein which appears to it to be 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1301794</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, cancel any regulation which it has confirmed and thereupon 
the regulation shall cease to have effect.

</section>

<section><tid>411927</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive session, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>382</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>