<act><tid>929419</tid>
<title>THE IRON ORE MINES MANGANESE ORE MINES AND CHROME ORE MINES 
LABOURWELFARE FUND ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 61 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 10th April, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the financing of activities to promote the 
welfare of persons employed in the iron ore mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, manganese ore 
mines 
and chrome ore mines].

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1319354</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>417469</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1892824</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1698841</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and 
different dates may be appointed for different States:
Provided that the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, apply in the first instance the provisions of this 
Act, only to iron ore mines, or only to manganese ore mines <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, or 
only to chrome ore mines], in a State with effect from such date as may 
be specified in the notification, and if that Government is satisfied 
that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may extend this Act to 
all iron ore mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines] in 
that State with effect from such date as may be specified in the 
notification published in the Official Gazette.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>653524</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1290811</tid>
<number>a</number>" agent" and" owner" have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in clauses (c) and (l) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 2 of the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1712608</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" chrome ore" includes ferro- chrome;]

</section>

<section><tid>1835776</tid>
<number>b</number>" contractor" has the meaning assigned to it in clause 
 (c) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Contract 
Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, <year>1970</year> (37 of  
  <year>1970</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>513770</tid>
<number>c</number>" factory" and" occupier" have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in clauses (m) and (n) of section 2 of 
the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>612731</tid>
<number>d</number>" Fund" means the Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>, Manganese Ore Mines 
and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund formed under 
section 3;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>572</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
3.  1- 9- <year>1978</year>: Vide Notifin. No. G. S. R. 1042, dated 9- 8- <year>1978</year>, Gazette 
of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. <year>1901</year>. 
4. Ins. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
5. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
6. Subs. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1830159</tid>
<number>e</number>" manager" means the manager referred to in section 17 of 
the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>466589</tid>
<number>f</number>" manganese ore" includes ferrogenous manganese ore or 
ferro- manganese ore;

</section>

<section><tid>1568054</tid>
<number>g</number>" metallurgical factory" means--

<subsection><tid>1101265</tid>
<number>i</number>a factory in which iron or steel or manganese 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome] is being processed or manufactured;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>128749</tid>
<number>ii</number>any other factory, being a factory in which 
iron ore or manganese ore <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore] is used for 
any purpose which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
metallurgical factory for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1649387</tid>
<number>h</number>a person is said to be employed in an iron ore mine or 
manganese ore mine <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore mine],--

<subsection><tid>705626</tid>
<number>1</number>if he is employed within the premises or in 
the vicinity of such mine by the owner, agent or 
manager of such mine or by a contractor or any other 
agency exclusively in any one or more of the following, 
namely:--

<subsubsection><tid>62345</tid>
<number>i</number>any iron ore or manganese ore <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome 
ore] mining operation;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1082902</tid>
<number>ii</number>the operation, servicing, maintenance or 
repair of any machinery or any part thereof used 
in or about such mine;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1562196</tid>
<number>iii</number>the loading, unloading or despatch of 
iron ore or manganese ore <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore] or any 
other material connected with the mining of iron 
ore or manganese ore;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1711096</tid>
<number>iv</number>any work in any office, canteen or 
creche situated within the precincts of such mine;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>462302</tid>
<number>v</number>any welfare, health, sanitary or 
conservancy services or any watch and ward duties 
at any place situated within such premises or 
vicinity, not being a place occupied by any 
residential building; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1762126</tid>
<number>2</number>if, in any such area as may be notified by the 
Central Government in the Official Gazette in this 
behalf, he is employed by the owner, agent or manager 
of such mine or by a contractor or any other agency 
exclusively in the loading, unloading or despatch of 
iron ore or manganese ore <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore] or any 
other material connected with the mining of iron ore or 
manganese ore <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore];

<subsubsection><tid>11972</tid>
<number>i</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>573</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>652933</tid>
<number> 3</number> Iron Ore Mines and Manganese Ore Mines Labour Welfare Fund.- 
There shall be formed a Fund, to be called the Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund, and 
there shall be credited thereto--
<section><tid>646770</tid>
<number>a</number>an amount which the Central Government may, after due 
appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, 
provide from and out of the proceeds of duty of customs 
and duty of excise credited under section 5 of the Iron 
Ore Mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines 
Labour Welfare] Cess Act, <year>1976</year> (55 of <year>1976</year>), after 
deducting therefrom, the cost of collection as 
determined by the Central Government under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1499754</tid>
<number>b</number>any income from investment of the amount credited under 
the Act referred to in clause (a) and any other moneys 
received by the Central Government for the purposes of 
this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>857221</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application of Fund.- The Fund shall be applied by the Central 
Government to meet the expenditure incurred in connection with the 
measures which, in the opinion of that Government, are necessary or 
expedient to promote the welfare of persons employed in the iron ore 
mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines], and in 
particular--
<section><tid>295717</tid>
<number>a</number>to defray the cost of measures for the benefit of 
persons employed in the iron ore mines or manganese ore 
mines <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or chrome ore mines] directed towards--

<subsection><tid>578270</tid>
<number>i</number>the provision and improvement of public health 
and sanitation, the prevention of disease and the 
provision and improvement of medical facilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>651228</tid>
<number>ii</number>the provision and improvement of water 
supplies and facilities for washing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1752023</tid>
<number>iii</number>the provision and improvement of educational 
facilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48699</tid>
<number>iv</number>the provision and improvement of housing and 
recreational facilities including standards of living, 
nutrition and amelioration of social conditions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>639199</tid>
<number>v</number>the provision of transport to and from the 
place of work;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>231347</tid>
<number>vi</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the provision of family welfare, including 
family planning education and services;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1690349</tid>
<number>b</number>to grant loan or subsidy to a State Government, a local 
authority or the owner of an iron ore mine or of a 
manganese ore mine <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or of a chrome ore mine], in aid 
of any scheme approved by the Central Government for 
any purpose connected with the welfare of persons 
employed in iron ore mines or manganese ore mines <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or 
chrome ore mines];
<pagefootnote><pagenum>574</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1987</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1502337</tid>
<number>c</number>to pay annually grants- in- aid to such of the owners of 
iron ore mines or manganese ore mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore 
mines] who provide to the satisfaction of the Central 
Government welfare measures of the prescribed standard 
for the benefit of persons employed in their mines, so, 
however, that the amount payable as grants- in- aid to 
such owners shall not exceed--

<subsection><tid>1759474</tid>
<number>i</number>the amount spent by them in the provision of 
welfare measures as determined by the Central 
Government or any person specified by it in this 
behalf, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443985</tid>
<number>ii</number>such amount as may be prescribed,
whichever is less:

Provided that no grant- in- aid shall be payable in respect of 
any welfare measures provided by the owner of an iron 
ore mine or of a manganese ore mine <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of a chrome 
ore mine] where the amount spent thereon determined as 
aforesaid is less than the amount prescribed in this 
behalf;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>971442</tid>
<number>d</number>to meet the allowances, if any, of the members of the 
Advisory Committee and the Central Advisory Committee 
constituted under section 5 and section 6 respectively 
and the salaries and allowances, if any, of persons 
appointed under section 8;

</section>

<section><tid>1409846</tid>
<number>e</number>any other expenditure which the Central Government may 
direct to be defrayed from the Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1512745</tid>
<number> 5</number> Advisory Committees.-
<section><tid>1032025</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,-- 

<subsection><tid>58304</tid>
<number>a</number>constitute for each State which produces iron ore or 
manganese ore <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or chrome ore] an Advisory Committee, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85582</tid>
<number>b</number>where <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any two of or all such ores] are produced in a 
State, constitute, for such State, an Advisory 
Committee in respect of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any one of such ores only, 
or in respect of any two of such ores only, or in 
respect of all such ores],
to advise the Central Government on such matters arising out of the 
administration of this Act as may be referred to it by that 
Government, including matters relating to the application of the Fund.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>771498</tid>
<number>2</number>Each Advisory Committee shall consist of such number of 
persons as may be appointed to it by the Central Government of whom 
one shall be a woman and the members shall be chosen in such manner as 
may be prescribed:
Provided that each Advisory Committee shall include an equal 
number of members representing Government, the owners of iron ore 
mines <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines] and the persons 
employed in the iron ore mines <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and chrome ore 
mines].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>575</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>286959</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman of each Advisory Committee shall be appointed by 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>573849</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall publish in the Official Gazette 
the names of the members of every Advisory Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>695088</tid>
<number> 6</number> Central Advisory Committee.-
<section><tid>1513143</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
constitute a Central Advisory Committee to co- ordinate the work of the 
Advisory Committees constituted under section 5 and to advise the 
Central Government on any matter arising out of the administration of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>27052</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Advisory Committee shall consist of such number 
of persons as may be appointed by the Central Government of whom one 
shall be a woman and the members shall be chosen in such manner as may 
be prescribed:
Provided that the Central Advisory Committee shall include an 
equal number of members representing the Government, the owners of 
iron ore mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines] and the 
persons employed in the iron ore mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, manganese ore mines and 
chrome ore mines].


</section>

<section><tid>1554662</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman of the Central Advisory Committee shall be 
appointed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>922956</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall publish in the Official Gazette 
the names of the members of the Central Advisory Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1196959</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to co- opt, etc.-
<section><tid>1453434</tid>
<number>1</number>The Advisory Committee or the  
Central Advisory Committee may, at any time and for such period as it 
thinks fit, co- opt any person or persons to the Advisory Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1402893</tid>
<number>2</number>A person co- opted under sub- section (1) shall exercise all 
the powers and functions of a member under this Act but shall not be 
entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>588697</tid>
<number>3</number>The Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee may, 
if it considers it necessary or expedient so to do, invite any person 
to attend its meeting and when such person attends any meeting, he 
shall not be entitled to vote thereat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1680902</tid>
<number> 8</number> Appointment of Welfare Commissioners, etc., and their powers.-

<section><tid>1647992</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may appoint as many Welfare Commissioners,  
Welfare Administrators, Inspectors and such other officers and staff 
as it thinks necessary for the purposes of this Act and the Iron Ore 
Mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] 
Cess Act, <year>1976</year> (55 of <year>1976</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1139294</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by general or special order, 
direct a Welfare Commissioner to appoint such staff as is considered 
necessary for the purposes of this Act and the Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Cess Act, 
 <year>1976</year> (55 of <year>1976</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>576</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>802458</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person so appointed shall be deemed to be a public 
servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45  
  of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>658163</tid>
<number>4</number>Any Welfare Commissioner, Welfare Administrator or Inspector 
may,--

<subsection><tid>1201057</tid>
<number>a</number>with such assistance, if any, as he may think fit, enter 
at any reasonable time, any place which he considers it 
necessary to enter for carrying out the purposes of 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518392</tid>
<number>b</number>do within such place anything necessary for the proper 
discharge of his duties; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>947989</tid>
<number>c</number>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>441074</tid>
<number>9</number>Power of Central Government to exempt.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is satisfied 
that there is in force in any State or part therof a law making 
adequate provision for the financing of activities to promote the 
welfare of persons employed in the iron ore mines or manganese ore 
mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or chrome ore mines], it may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that all or any of the provisions of this Act shall 
not apply to such State or part thereof subject to such exceptions and 
modifications as may be specified in the notification.


</article>



<article><tid>138767</tid>
<number>10</number>Annual report of activities financed under the Act.- The 
Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the end of each 
financial year, cause to be published in the Official Gazette a report 
giving an account of its activities financed under this Act during the 
previous financial year, together with a statement of accounts.


</article>



<article><tid>781919</tid>
<number>11</number>Power to call for information.- The Central Government may 
require an occupier of a metallurgical factory or the owner, agent or 
manager of an iron ore mine or of a manganese ore mine <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or of a 
chrome ore mine] to furnish, for the purposes of this Act, such 
statistical and other information in such form and within such period 
as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1965553</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1539399</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette and subject to the condition of 
previous publication, make rules for carrying out the provisions of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>742736</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
fore- going power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>838206</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the Fund may be applied for the 
measures specified in section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205174</tid>
<number>b</number>the conditions governing the grant of loan or subsidy 
under clause (b) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225505</tid>
<number>c</number>the standard of welfare measures to be provided by 
owners of iron ore mines or manganese ore mines <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or 
chrome ore mines] for the purposes of clause (c) of 
section 4;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>577</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>933303</tid>
<number>d</number>the determination of the amount referred to in sub- 
clause (ii) of clause (c) of section 4 and in the 
proviso to that clause;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1448499</tid>
<number>e</number>the composition of the Advisory Committees and the 
Central Advisory Committee constituted under section 5 
and section 6 respectively, the manner in which the 
members thereof shall be chosen, the term of office of 
such members, the allowances, if any, payable to them 
including co- opted members and invitees, and the manner 
in which the said Advisory Committees and the Central 
Advisory Committee shall conduct their business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1217701</tid>
<number>f</number>the recruitment, conditions of service and the duties of 
all persons appointed under section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135097</tid>
<number>g</number>the powers that may be exercised by a Welfare 
Commissioner, Welfare Administrator or an Inspector 
under section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550880</tid>
<number>h</number>the furnishing to the Central Government by the 
occupiers of metallurgical factories and the owners, 
agents or managers of iron ore mines or of manganese 
ore mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of chrome ore mines], of such 
statistical and other information as may be required to 
be furnished, from time to time, by that Government 
under section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>46987</tid>
<number>i</number>the form in which and the period within which 
statistical and other information are to be furnished 
under clause (h);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>137765</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed, 
or provided for, by rules under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1898107</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under clause (h) or clause (i) of sub- 
section (2), the Central Government may direct that a breach thereof 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>174465</tid>
<number>4</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>578</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>