<act><title>


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee 
Rules, 20001</title> 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
these rules may be called the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee Rules, 
2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Gazette of India.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless the context otherwise requires—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  "Act" means 
the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 (39 of 1987);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  "Member" means 
the Members of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee nominated under clause 
(b) of sub-section (2) of section 3A of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  "Secretary" 
means the Secretary of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee appointed uner 
sub-section (3) of section 3A of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  all other 
words and expressions used in these rules but not defined shall have the same 
meaning as assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  
Rules, 2000
 <article>
<number>3</number> The number, 
experience and qualifications of Members of the Supreme Court Legal Services 
Committee under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee shall consist of not more than nine 
Members.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The following shall be 
the ex offico Members of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Attorney 
General of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Additional 
Secretary in the Department of legal Affairs, Ministry of Law, Justice and 
Company Affairs, Government of India or his nominee;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  Additonal 
Secretary in the Department of Expenditure, Ministry of Finance, Government of 
India or his nominee; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Registrar 
General of the Supreme Court of India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Justice of 
India may nominate other Members from amongst those possessing the qualification 
and experience prescribed in sub-rule (4) of the rules.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for nomination as a Member unless he is—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  an eminent 
person in the field of law; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a person of 
repute who is specially interested in the implementation of the Legal Services 
Schemes; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  an eminent 
social worker who is engaged in the upliftment of the weaker sections of the 
society including Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, women, children, rural and 
urban labour.
</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  
Rules, 2000
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> The experience and 
qualifications of Secretary of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee under 
sub-section (3) of section 3A.—A 
person shall not be qualified for appointment as Secretary unless he is—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  an officer of 
the Supreme Court Registry not below the rank of Joint Registrar; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  an officer of 
the rank of Director in the Central Government and possessing a degree in Law.
</section></article> 
 


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  
Rules, 2000
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> The number of 
officers and other employees of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee under 
sub-section (5) of section 3A.—The 
Supreme Court Legal Services Committee shall have such number of officers and 
other employees for rendering secretarial assistance and for its day-do-day 
functions as are set out in the Schedule to these rules or as may be notified by 
the Central Goernment from time to time.
</article> 
 


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  
Rules, 2000
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> The conditions of 
service and the salary and allowances payable to the officers and employees of 
the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section (6) of section 3A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The officers and other employees of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee 
shall be entitled to draw pay and allowances in the scale of pay indicated 
against each post in the Schedule to these rules or at par with the Central 
Government employees holding equivalent posts.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In all matters like 
age of retirement, pay and allowances, benefits and entitlements and 
disciplinary matters, the officers and employees of the Supreme Court Legal 
Services Committee shall be governed by the Central Government rules as are 
applicable to persons holding equivalent posts.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officers and other 
employees of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee shall be entitled to 
such other facilities and benefits as may be notified by the Central Government 
from time to time.
 
Explanation.—The 
words "benefits", "allowances", "entitlements", "facilities" occurring in these 
rules shall be deemed to include, the entitlement to gratuity, provident fund, 
housing, medicial benefits, pension, group insurance, and all other benefits as 
are available to employees of the Central Government holding equivalent posts.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> The uper limit of annual income of a person entitling him to legal services under clause (h) of section 12, if the case is before the Supreme Court. </title>—A person whose annual income from all sources does not exceed 
  <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Rs. 1,25,000 (Rupees one lakh twenty-five thousand)] per annum shall be entitled to legal services under clause (h) of section 12 of the Act. 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> The uper limit of annual income of a person entitling him to legal services under clause (h) of section 12, if the case is before the Supreme Court. </title>—A person whose annual income from all sources does not exceed 
  <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Rs. 1,25,000 (Rupees one lakh twenty-five thousand)] per annum shall be entitled to legal services under clause (h) of section 12 of the Act. 



</article> 
 


The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  
Rules, 2000
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> The experience and 
qualifications of other persons of the Lok Adalats organised by the Supreme 
Court Legal Services Committee specified in sub-section (3) of section 19.—A 
person shall not be qualified to be included in the Lok Adalat unless he is—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  a member of 
the legal profession; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  a person of 
repute who is specially interested in the implementation of the Legal Services 
Schemes and Programmes; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  an eminent 
social worker who is engaged in the upliftment of the weaker sections of the 
society, including Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, women, children, rural 
and urban labour.
</section></article><form>
 




The Supreme Court Legal Services Committee  

Rules, 2000
 

 
 



1[Schedule
 


(See 
rules 5 and 6)
 




Sanctioned Strength of the Staff of the Supreme  

Court Legal Services Committee
 


 


  Sl. No    
  Designation                               Scale of 
  pay                                       No. of Posts
 


   I. Officers
 


     1.        
Secretary                                  Rs. 
14300-400-18300                                1
 


     2.        Legal 
Service Counsel-cum-     Rs. 12000-375-16500                                1
 


                
Consultant                               
 


     3.        
Superintendent                        Rs. 
6500-200-10500                                  1
 



                                                                                 
Total                                         3
 


    II. Establishment
 


     1.        
Assistant                                  Rs. 
5500-175-9000                                    2
 


     2.        Upper 
Division Clerk                 Rs. 
4000-100-6000                                    2
 


     3.        Upper 
Division Clerk-cum-        Rs. 4000-100-6000                                    
1
 


                Accounts
 


     4.        Junior 
Stenographer                 Rs. 
4000-100-6000                                    1
 


     5.        Lower 
Division Clerk                 Rs. 3050-75-3950-80-4590                       4
 


     6.        Daftry                                       
Rs. 2610-60-3150-65-3540                       1
 


     7.        
Peon                                         Rs. 
2550-55-2660-60-3200                       3
 


     8.        Farash                                      
Rs. 2550-55-2660-60-3200                       1
 


              
                                                                        
Total                                   15
 


              
                          Grand Total of Officers and Staff 
:                                    18]
 


 


 
 


—————
 

    
1.    Vide (Corrigendun) G.S.R. 637 (E), dated 25th July, 2000.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 807(E), dated 14th November, 2011, for “Rs. 50,000 (Rupees fifty thousand)” (w.e.f. 14-11-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 807(E), dated 14th November, 2011, for “Rs. 50,000 (Rupees fifty thousand)” (w.e.f. 14-11-2011).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>