<act><tid>1330088</tid>
<title>THE MERCHANT SHIPPING (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 63 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year>, and the Major 
Port Trusts Act, <year>1963</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>865958</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>786357</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Merchant Shipping (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>852829</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.
CHAP

AMENDMENT OF THE MERCHANT SHIPPING ACT, <year>1958</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENT OF THE MERCHANT SHIPPING ACT, <year>1958</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1025813</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 76.- For section 76 of the 
Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as  
  the principal Act), the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 76. Certificates of competency to be held by officers of ships.- (1) 
Every Indian ship, when going to sea from any port or place, shall be 
provided with officers duly certificated under this Act in accordance 
with such manning scales as may be prescribed

Provided that the Central Government may prescribe different manning 
scales for different types of ships.

<section><tid>1914746</tid>
<number>2</number>Every ship, whether at sea or in any port or place, shall engage 
such number of persons and with such qualifications as may be 
prescribed for maintaining watches.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1787704</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 87.- In section 87 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), in clause (b), for the words" by a ship", the words 
" by different types of ships" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>905821</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 95.- In section 95 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1770098</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), for clauses (a) and (b), the following clause 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (a) to issue licence, to regulate and control the recruitment and 
placement service, and to-


</section>

<section><tid>1770098</tid>
<number>i</number>ensure that no fees or other charges for recruitment or placement 
of seafarers are borne directly or indirectly or in whole or in part, 
by the seafarers;

</section>

<section><tid>1405467</tid>
<number>ii</number>ensure that adequate machinery and procedures exist for the 
investigation, if necessary, of complaints concerning the activities 
of recruitment and placement services; and

</section>

<section><tid>1754836</tid>
<number>iii</number>to maintain registers of seamen in respect of the categories of 
seamen;";

</section>

<section><tid>1405467</tid>
<number>ii</number>sub- section (2) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1754836</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (3), for clauses (b) and (c), the following 
clauses shall be substituted, namely:-
" (b) the levy and collection of such fees as may be specified for the 
issue of licences to recruitment and placement services, renewal of 
such licences and services to be rendered by the seamen' s employment 
office;


<subsection><tid>438891</tid>
<number>c</number>the issue of directions by the Central Government to any seamen' s 
employment office or any recruitment and placement service with 
reference to the exercise of any of its powers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>263911</tid>
<number>ca</number>the conditions under which the recruitment and placement service 
to recruit and place seafarers abroad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>901232</tid>
<number>cb</number>the circumstances and conditions under which licence to be 
suspended or withdrawn;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1096178</tid>
<number>cc</number>the conditions under which seafarers' personal data to be 
processed by the recruitment and placement services including the 
collection, storage, combination and communication of such data to 
third parties;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1523123</tid>
<number>iv</number>after sub- section (3), the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>105815</tid>
<number>a</number>" recruitment and placement service" means any person, company, 
institution, agency or other organisation, in the public or private 
sector which is engaged in recruiting seafarers on behalf of employers 
or placing seafarers with employers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1913438</tid>
<number>b</number>" seafarer" means any person who fulfils the conditions to be 
employed or engaged in any capacity on board a sea- going ship other 
than a government ship used for military or non- commercial purposes.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>920931</tid>
<number> 5</number> Substitution of new section for section 97.- For section 97 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 97. Receipt of remuneration, donation, fees, etc., for shipping them 
prohibited.- (1) A person or company or organisation including a union 
purporting to represent the interests of seamen shall not demand or 
receive, either directly or indirectly, from a y seaman or person 
seeking employment as seaman or any person on his behalf, any 
remuneration or donation or fees or compulsory subscription of any 
kind attributable from such seaman or person' s employment as seaman, 
other than the fees authorised by thi Act.

<section><tid>1293405</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the company employing or proposing to 
employ person as seaman to ensure that no money has been demanded or 
received by any person or company or organisation including the union 
remuneration or donation or fees or compulsory subscription of any 
kind attributable to employment of such person as seaman.". 
purporting to represent the interests of seamen b way of any



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1653463</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new section 97A.- After section 97 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 97A. Prohibition against discrimination.- There shall be no 
discrimination between seamen,-

<section><tid>1474403</tid>
<number>a</number>on the ground of their membership or lack of membership in any 
particular union purporting to represent the interests of seamen and 
membership in such union shall not be pre- requisite condition;

</section>

<section><tid>819925</tid>
<number>b</number>on the basis of training institute from where they obtained 
training or place of issue of their continuous discharge certificates, 
for their recruitment and engagement on board any ship.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1535364</tid>
<number>7</number>Substitution of new sub- heading for sub- heading above section 
299.- For the sub- heading" Safety certificates, safety equipment 
certificates, safety radio telegraphy certificates, safety radio 
telephony certificates, exemption certificates, etc." above ection 299 
of the principal Act, the following sub- heading shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" Safety certificates, safety equipment certificates, safety radio 
certificates, exemption certificates, etc.".



</article>



<article><tid>862985</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 299.- In section 299 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1345974</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" radio telegraphy or radio 
telephony installation and radio direction finder", the words" radio 
installation" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1062933</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3), the words" or a pilgrim ship" shall be 
omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1655893</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4) The certificates issued under sub- sections (1) and (2), 
sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 300 and section 301 shall be 
supplemented by a record of equipment in the prescribed form.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1576003</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 299A.- In section 299A of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>838656</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1494786</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" the Central Government", the words" the Central 
Government or any person authorised by it in this behalf" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1510893</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" the Central Government", the words" that 
Government or the authorised person" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1466722</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>379645</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" of the Act and the Central Government", the words 
" and the Central Government or any person authorised by it in this 
behalf" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314775</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" the Central Government", the words" that 
Government or the authorised person" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>673247</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (3) The owner of every ship in respect of which a certificate is 
issued under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) of section 300 or section 301 shall, so long as the 
certificate remains in force, cause the ship to be s rveyed in the 
manner as specified in the Safety Convention or in cases where such 
specified manner is not applicable, in such manner as the rules made 
in this behalf prescribe, as the case may be.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1659262</tid>
<number> 10</number> Substitution of new section for section 300.- For section 300 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 300. Cargo ship safety equipment and cargo ship equipment 
certificates for ships other than passenger ships.- (1) Where in 
respect of an Indian cargo ship the Central Government or any person 
with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder relating 
to life saving and fire appliances applicable to such ship and is 
provided with lights and shapes and the means of making fog and 
distress signals required by the collision regul authorised by it in 
this behalf is satisfied that the ship com lies tions, that Government 
or the authorised person may issue in respect of the ship-

<section><tid>1394055</tid>
<number>a</number>if the ship is of five hundred tons gross or more and performs 
international voyages, a certificate in the prescribed form to be 
called a cargo ship safety equipment certificate;

</section>

<section><tid>212738</tid>
<number>b</number>in other cases, a certificate in the prescribed form to be called 
a cargo ship equipment certificate.

<subsection><tid>674454</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, in respect of a ship referred to in sub- section (1), there 
is in force an exemption certificate granted under section 302 and the 
Central Government or any person authorised by it in this behalf is 
satisfied that the ship complies with all the requirements referred to 
in that sub- section, other than those from which the ship is exempt 
under that certificate, that Government or the authorised person may 
issue a certificate in the prescribed form to be called a qualified 
cargo ship safety equipm nt certificate or a qualified cargo ship 
equipment certificate, as the case may be.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1154013</tid>
<number> 11</number> Substitution of new section for section 301.- For section 301 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 301. Cargo ship safety radio certificate and qualified cargo ship 
safety radio certificate, etc.- The owner or master of any Indian cargo 
ship, which is required by the provisions of section 291 to be 
provided with a radio installation shall, if the Cent al Government or 
any person authorised by it in this behalf is satisfied that the ship 
complies with all the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder relating to radio installation applicable to such ship, 
receive-

<section><tid>26142</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a ship of three hundred tons gross or more, a 
certificate in the prescribed form to be called a cargo ship safety 
radio certificate;

</section>

<section><tid>1629690</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a ship of three hundred tons gross or more but less 
than three thousand tons gross performing voyages only between ports 
or places in India, a certificate in the prescribed form to be called 
a qualified cargo ship safety radio certific te; and

</section>

<section><tid>442058</tid>
<number>c</number>in other cases, a certificate in the prescribed form to be called 
a cargo ship radio certificate.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1780338</tid>
<number> 12</number> Substitution of new section for section 303.- For section 303 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 303. Duration of certificates.- (1) A passenger ship safety 
certificate, a qualified passenger ship safety certificate, a special 
trade passenger ship safety certificate and a special trade passenger 
ship space certificate issued under this Part shall be in force for a 
period of twelve months from the date of its issue or for such shorter 
period as may be specified in the certificate.

<section><tid>1211991</tid>
<number>2</number>A cargo ship safety equipment certificate, a qualified cargo ship 
safety equipment certificate, a cargo ship equipment certificate, a 
qualified cargo ship equipment certificate, a cargo ship safety 
construction certificate, a qualified cargo ship saf ty construction 
certificate, a cargo ship construction certificate, a qualified cargo 
ship construction certificate, a cargo ship safety radio certificate, 
a qualified cargo ship safety radio certificate and a cargo ship radio 
certificate issued under th s Part shall be in force for a period of 
five years from the date of its issue or for such shorter period as 
may be specified in the certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>852728</tid>
<number>3</number>An exemption certificate issued under section 302 shall be in 
force for the period for which the certificate to which it relates 
remains in force or for such shorter period as may be specified in the 
exemption certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>1658202</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding the requirements of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) 
when the survey is completed within three months before the expiry 
date of the existing certificate, the new certificate may be valid 
from the date of completion of the survey,-

<subsection><tid>231018</tid>
<number>a</number>for a passenger ship, a date not exceeding twelve months; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1711199</tid>
<number>b</number>for a cargo ship, a date not exceeding five years,
from the date of expiry of the existing certificate.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>407422</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government or any person authorised by it in this 
behalf may grant an extension of any certificate issued under this 
Part in respect of an Indian ship-

<subsection><tid>977260</tid>
<number>a</number>where the ship is not in a port in which it is to be surveyed, on 
the date when the certificate would, but for the extension, have 
expired, for such period not exceeding three months from the said date 
as may be sufficient to enable the ship to compl te its voyage to the 
port in which it is to be surveyed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1577547</tid>
<number>b</number>where the ship is engaged on a short voyage and whose certificate 
has not been extended under clause (a), for a period up to one month 
from the date when the certificate would have expired:
Provided that any extension granted under clause (a) shall cease to be 
operative upon the ship' s arrival at the port referred to in that 
clause:

Provided further that no extension shall be granted under clause (b) 
in respect of a certificate extended under clause (a).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1881035</tid>
<number>6</number>Where an existing certificate of a ship has been extended under 
sub- section (5) and when survey is completed, the new certificate 
shall be valid up to,-

<subsection><tid>1252756</tid>
<number>a</number>for a passenger ship, a date not exceeding twelve months; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>399477</tid>
<number>b</number>for a cargo ship, a date not exceeding five years, from the date 
of expiry of the existing certificate.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1914727</tid>
<number>7</number>In special circumstances where the Central Government so 
determines, a new certificate, need not be dated from the date of 
expiry of the existing certificate, shall be valid up to,-

<subsection><tid>456649</tid>
<number>a</number>for a passenger ship, a date not exceeding twelve months;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1409095</tid>
<number>b</number>for a cargo ship, a date not exceeding five years, from the date 
of completion of the survey.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>210435</tid>
<number>8</number>Where a certificate referred to in sub- section (2) is issued for a 
period of less than five years, the Central Government or any person 
authorised by it in this behalf may extend the validity of the 
certificate beyond the expiry date to the maximum p riod specified in 
sub- section (2) if appropriate surveys, applicable when a certificate 
is issued for a period of five years, are carried out.

</section>

<section><tid>1595347</tid>
<number>9</number>If a survey has been completed and a new certificate cannot be 
issued or placed on board the ship before the expiry date of the 
existing certificate, the Central Government or any person authorised 
by it in this behalf may endorse the existing certi icate and such 
certificate shall be in force for a further period which shall not 
exceed five months from the expiry date of the existing certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>259589</tid>
<number>10</number>If annual, intermediate or periodical surveys in the manner as 
specified in the Safety Convention or in cases where such specified 
manner is not applicable, in such manner as the rules made in this 
behalf prescribe, as the case may be, are completed before the period 
stipulated therefor, then-

<subsection><tid>1766393</tid>
<number>a</number>the anniversary date mentioned on the relevant certificate shall 
be amended by endorsement to a date which shall not be more than three 
months later than the date on which the survey was completed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1739740</tid>
<number>b</number>the subsequent surveys shall be completed at the stipulated 
intervals using the new anniversary date so endorsed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1304819</tid>
<number>c</number>the expiry date may remain unchanged provided one or more annual, 
intermediate or periodical surveys, as the case may be, are carried 
out so that the maximum stipulated intervals between the surveys are 
not exceeded.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1664173</tid>
<number>11</number>A certificate issued under section 299A, section 300 or section 
 301 shall cease to be valid,-

<subsection><tid>138137</tid>
<number>a</number>if the relevant surveys specified in the Safety Convention or in 
cases where such specified manner is not applicable, in such manner as 
the rules made in this behalf prescribe, as the case may be, are not 
completed within the stipulated period;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>657351</tid>
<number>b</number>if the certificate is not endorsed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>812443</tid>
<number>c</number>if the ship ceases to be an Indian ship.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>446785</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 307.- In section 307 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>151588</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (b), for the words" radio 
telegraphy certificate or a cargo ship safety radio telephony 
certificate", the words" radio certificate" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>901665</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (2A), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2A) No sea- going Indian cargo ship, less than five hundred tons 
gross, shall proceed on a voyage from any port or place in India to 
any port or place in India or to any port or place outside India 
unless there is in force in respect of the ship a cargo ship 
construction certificate issued under section 299A and a cargo ship 
equipment certificate issued under section 300 and,-


<subsection><tid>1351571</tid>
<number>i</number>a cargo ship safety radio certificate if the ship is three hundred 
tons gross or more;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940875</tid>
<number>ii</number>a qualified cargo ship safety radio certificate if the ship is 
operating within ports or places in India and is of three hundred to 
five hundred tons gross; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>757991</tid>
<number>iii</number>a cargo ship radio certificate if the ship is less than three 
hundred tons gross,
issued under section 301.";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1408942</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3),-

<subsection><tid>1118192</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words and figures" equipment certificate 
issued under section 300", the words, figures and letter" safety 
construction certificate or cargo ship construction certificate issued 
under section 299A" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>909381</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), in the opening portion, after the word" a", the 
words" cargo ship equipment certificate or a" shall be inserted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>525675</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (c), for the words" radio telegraphy certificate or a 
cargo ship radio telephony certificate", the words" safety radio 
certificate or a qualified cargo ship safety radio certificate, if the 
ship operates between ports or places in India a d is between five 
hundred to three thousand tons gross," shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>898956</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of section 317.- In section 317 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>85971</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), after the existing proviso, the following 
proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided further that when the survey for the purpose of issue of 
certificate under sub- section (1) of section 316 is completed within 
three months before the expiry date of the existing certificate, the 
new certificate may be valid from the date of com letion of such 
survey to a date not exceeding five years from the date of expiry of 
the existing certificate.";


</section>

<section><tid>197157</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (3), for the portion beginning with the words 
" shall cease'' and ending with the words'' Indian ship", the following 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" shall cease to be valid when-


<subsection><tid>1500492</tid>
<number>a</number>the ship ceases to be an Indian ship;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>668567</tid>
<number>b</number>material alterations such as would necessitate the assignment of 
an increased free board have taken place in the hull or superstructure 
of the ship;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1905837</tid>
<number>c</number>the fittings and appliances for the protection of openings, the 
guard rails, freeing ports, or the means of access to the crew' s 
quarters are not maintained in an effective condition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1622413</tid>
<number>d</number>the structural strength of the ship is lowered to such an extent 
as to render the ship unsafe;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>556904</tid>
<number>e</number>the certificate is not endorsed to prove that the ship has been 
surveyed as required under sub- section (5); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>816412</tid>
<number>f</number>the marking of the deck line and load lines on the ship have not 
been properly maintained";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>57697</tid>
<number>iii</number>sub- section (4) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>70633</tid>
<number>iv</number>in sub- section (5), for the portion beginning with the words 
" once at least in each year" and ending with the words" caused to be 
so surveyed", the following shall be substituted, namely:-
" and the certificate endorsed once at least in each year during the 
period commencing three months before and ending three months after 
the anniversary date of expiry of the certificate for the purpose of 
ensuring that-


<subsection><tid>1137859</tid>
<number>a</number>alterations have not been made to the hull or superstructure which 
would affect the calculations determining the position of the load 
lines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>250173</tid>
<number>b</number>the fittings and the appliances for the protection of openings, 
the guard rails, freeing ports, or the means of access to the crew' s 
quarters are maintained in an effective condition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>816384</tid>
<number>c</number>the free board marks are correctly and permanently marked; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881643</tid>
<number>d</number>the stability information required under section 298 is readily 
available on board";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1584278</tid>
<number>v</number>for sub- sections (6) and (7), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (6) If an annual survey is completed before the period specified in 
sub- section (5) then,-


<subsection><tid>761651</tid>
<number>a</number>the anniversary date mentioned on the certificate shall be amended 
by endorsement to a date which shall not be more than three months 
later than the date on which the survey was completed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1806302</tid>
<number>b</number>the subsequent annual survey required by sub- section (5) shall be 
completed using the new anniversary date;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43944</tid>
<number>c</number>the expiry date of the certificate may remain unchanged provided 
one or more annual survey is carried out so that the maximum interval 
between the surveys specified under sub- section (5) is not exceeded.

<subsubsection><tid>1216003</tid>
<number>7</number>If a certificate under sub- section (1) of section 316 is issued 
for a period of less than five years, the Central Government or any 
person authorised by it in this behalf, may extend the validity of the 
certificate beyond the expiry date to a maximum period specified in 
sub- section (1):
Provided that annual surveys referred to in sub- section (5) are 
carried out as may be appropriate.


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1559599</tid>
<number>7A</number>If a ship at the time when a certificate expires is not in a port 
at which it is to be surveyed, the Central Government or any person 
authorised by it in this behalf may extend the period of validity of 
the certificate, but this extension shall be g anted only for the 
purpose of allowing the ship to complete the voyage to the port in 
which it is to be surveyed and also only in cases where it appears 
proper and reasonable to do so:
Provided that no certificate shall be extended for a period longer 
than three months and the ship to which an extension is granted shall 
not on its arrival at the port in which it is to be surveyed leave 
that port without having a new certificate:

Provided further that when the survey is completed, the new 
certificate shall be valid to a date not exceeding five years from the 
date of expiry of the existing certificate.


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>359526</tid>
<number>7B</number>A certificate, issued to a ship engaged in short voyage which has 
not been extended under sub- section (7A), may be extended by the 
Central Government or any person authorised by it in this behalf for a 
period up to one month from the date of expiry nd when the survey is 
completed, the new certificate shall be valid up to a date not 
exceeding five years from the date of expiry of the existing 
certificate.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>585800</tid>
<number>7C</number>In special circumstances where the Central Government so 
determines a new certificate, need not be dated from the date of 
expiry of the existing certificate, shall be valid up to a date not 
exceeding five years from the date of completion of the su vey.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1320321</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of section 344.- In section 344 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for clause (a), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) the form of any certificate and record of equipment issued under 
this Part;

<section><tid>669262</tid>
<number>aa</number>the manner of surveys required to be made in respect of ships to 
which the manner of surveys specified in the Safety Convention is not 
applicable;".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>698605</tid>
<number> 16</number> Amendment of section 352.- In section 352 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>306637</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (b), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (b)" Convention" means the Convention on Limitation of Liability for 
Maritime Claims, <year>1976</year> as amended from time to time;';


</section>

<section><tid>558006</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (g), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (h)" salvor" means any person rendering services in direct connection 
with salvage operations.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this clause," salvage operations" 
includes-


</section>

<section><tid>306637</tid>
<number>i</number>the raising, removal, destruction or the rendering a ship harmless 
which is sunk, wrecked, stranded or abandoned including anything that 
is or has been on board such ship;

</section>

<section><tid>558006</tid>
<number>ii</number>the removal, destruction or rendering the cargo of a ship 
harmless; and

</section>

<section><tid>1638277</tid>
<number>iii</number>the measures taken to avert or minimise loss to a ship or its 
cargo or both;

</section>

<section><tid>306637</tid>
<number>i</number>" ship owner" means owner, charterer, manager and operator of a 
sea- going ship;

</section>

<section><tid>1060035</tid>
<number>j</number>" Special Drawing Rights" means Special Drawing Rights as 
determined by the International Monetary Fund.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>404112</tid>
<number> 17</number> Substitution of new section for section 352A.- For section 352A of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 352A. Limitation of liability for damages in respect of certain 
claims.- (1) The ship owner, salvor, any person for whose act, neglect 
or default the ship owner or salvor, as the case may be, is 
responsible, and an insurer of liability for claims to the ame extent 
as the assured himself, may limit his liability as provided under 
section 352B in respect of,-

<section><tid>1915118</tid>
<number>a</number>claims arising from loss of life of or personal injury to, or loss 
of or damage to, property (including damage to harbour works, basins  
  and waterways and aids to navigation), occurring on board or in direct 
connection with the operation of the ship o with salvage operations, 
and consequential loss resulting therefrom;

</section>

<section><tid>871246</tid>
<number>b</number>claims arising out of loss resulting from delay in the carriage by 
sea of cargo and passengers or their luggage;

</section>

<section><tid>283254</tid>
<number>c</number>claims arising out of other loss resulting from infringement of 
rights other than contractual rights, occurring in direct connection 
with the operation of the ship or salvage operations;

</section>

<section><tid>81523</tid>
<number>d</number>claims of a person other than the person liable in respect of 
measures taken in order to avert or minimise loss for which the person 
liable may limit his liability in accordance with the provisions of 
the Convention or the rules made in this behalf rescribe, as the case 
may be, and such further loss caused by such measures;

</section>

<section><tid>1263247</tid>
<number>e</number>claims for the loss of life or personal injury to passengers of a 
ship brought by or on behalf of any person,-

<subsection><tid>181525</tid>
<number>i</number>under the contract of passenger carriage; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136069</tid>
<number>ii</number>who, with the consent of the carrier, is accompanying a vehicle 
for live animals which are covered by a contract for the carriage of 
goods, carried in that ship:
Provided that the limits for passengers claim specified in the rules 
made under this Part shall not be applicable to the passengers carried 
in and around the coast of India in respect of whom separate limits 
shall be prescribed.


<subsubsection><tid>723108</tid>
<number>2</number>Claims set out in sub- section (1) shall be subject to limitation 
of liability even if brought by way of recourse or for indemnity under 
a contract or otherwise:
Provided that claims set out in clause (d) of sub- section (1) shall 
not be subject to limitation of liability to the extent that they 
relate to remuneration under a contract with the person liable.


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1422962</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall apply to-

<subsubsubsection><tid>1811384</tid>
<number>a</number>claims for salvage or contribution in general average;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1619943</tid>
<number>b</number>claims for oil pollution damage within the meaning of the 
International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, 
 <year>1992</year> as amended from time to time;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1444219</tid>
<number>c</number>claims by servants of the ship owner or salvor whose duties are 
connected with the ship or the salvage operations, including claims of 
their heirs, dependents or other persons entitled to make such claims, 
if under the law governing the contract of s rvice between the ship 
owner or salvor and such servants of the ship owner or salvor is not 
entitled to limit his liability in respect of such claims, or if he is 
by such law only permitted to limit his liability to an amount greater 
than that provided f r in the provision of the Convention or the rules 
made under this Part prescribe;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1188012</tid>
<number>d</number>claims subject to any International Convention or any law for the 
time being in force in India governing or prohibiting limitation of 
liability for nuclear damage;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>299725</tid>
<number>e</number>claims against the ship owner of a nuclear ship for nuclear 
damage. Explanation 1.- For the purpose of this section, the act of 
involving limitation of liability shall not constitute an admission of 
liability. Explanation 2.- For the purpose of this Part, the liability 
of a ship owner shall include liability in an action brought against 
the ship herself.".



</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362132</tid>
<number>18</number>Substitution of new section for section 352B.- For section 352B of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 352B. Limitation of liability.- The amount to which any person 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 352A may limit his liability 
in accordance with the provisions of the Convention and in cases where 
the provisions of the Convention are not applicab e, the limit shall 
be in accordance with the rules made in this behalf prescribe.".



</article>



<article><tid>1800142</tid>
<number> 19</number> Amendment of section 352C.- In section 352C of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1128032</tid>
<number>a</number>in the marginal heading, the words" against owner" shall be 
omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1018817</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) Where any liability is alleged to have been incurred by a person 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 352A in respect of claims 
arising out of an occurrence, and legal proceedings are instituted in 
respect of claims subject to limitation, then uch person may apply to 
the High Court for the setting up of a limitation Fund for the total 
sum representing the amounts set out in the Convention or the rules 
made in this behalf under this Part applicable to claims for which 
that person may be liable ogether with interest thereon from the date 
of occurrence giving rise to the liability until the date of the 
constitution of the Fund.";


</section>

<section><tid>226120</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (2), for the words beginning with the words" or 
furnish" and ending with the words" or secured", the words" or produce 
a guarantee acceptable or produce a bank guarantee in respect of the 
amount as in the opinion of the High Court is s tisfactory and the 
amount so deposited or guarantee so given" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>641580</tid>
<number>d</number>for sub- sections (5) and (6), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (5) Where the person referred to in sub- section (1) or his insurer 
establishes that he has paid in whole or in part any claims in respect 
of which he can limit his liability under this Part, the High Court 
shall place him in the same position and to the same extent in 
relation to the Fund as the claimant whose claim has been paid and 
allow to acquire by subrogation the rights which the person so 
compensated would have enjoyed under this Part: Provided that the 
right of subrogation provided for in this sub- section may also be 
exercised by persons other than those therein mentioned in respect of 
any amount of compensation which they might have paid to that extent 
if prescribed by the rules made in this behalf under this Part. (6) 
Where the person liable or any other person has established that he 
may at a later date be required to pay in whole or in part, any of the 
claims under this Part, which could be settled from the Fund, the High 
Court may notwithstanding the foregoing rovisions of this section 
order that a sufficient sum may be provisionally set aside for the 
purpose to enable the person to enforce his claim against the Fund at 
a later date in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (5).".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>106914</tid>
<number> 20</number> Amendment of section 352D.- In section 352D of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1664821</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (5), for clause (a), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' (a)" Convention country" means a country in which the Convention on 
Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims, <year>1976</year> as amended from time 
to time is for the time being in force;';


</section>

<section><tid>1631528</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (5), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (6) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) to (4), 
the vessels or other property referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
ordered to be released if the limitation Fund has been constituted,-


<subsection><tid>1242566</tid>
<number>a</number>in the port where the occurrence took place, or, if it took place 
out of port, in the first port of call thereafter;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1065139</tid>
<number>b</number>in the port of disembarkation in respect of claims for loss of 
life or personal injury; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1552716</tid>
<number>c</number>in the port of discharge in respect of damage to cargo.

<subsubsection><tid>1053860</tid>
<number>7</number>The provision of sub- section (6) shall apply only if the claimant 
brings a claim against the limitation Fund before the High Court 
administering the Fund and the Fund is actually available and freely 
transferable in respect of that claim.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1477494</tid>
<number> 21</number> Substitution of new section for section 352E.- For section 352E of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 352E. Scope of application.- (1) The provisions of this Part shall 
apply whenever any person referred to in sub- section (1) of section 
 352A seeks to limit his liability before the Court or seeks to procure 
guarantee given within the Indian jurisdiction but any person referred 
to in sub- section (1) of section 352A who at the time when the 
provisions under this Part are invoked before any Court in India does 
not have his habitual residence in the release of a ship or other 
property or the d scharge of any ndia or does not have his principal 
place of business in India or any ship in relation to which the right 
of limitation is invoked or whose release is sought and which does not 
at the time specified above fly the flag of the State, which is a 
party to he Convention, is wholly excluded from the provisions of this 
Part.

<section><tid>1604486</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this Part shall not be applicable to the 
following vessels unless the Central Government, by notification, 
specify otherwise,-

<subsection><tid>332027</tid>
<number>a</number>ships intended for navigation on or around coast of India and 
registered as coastal vessels under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>300270</tid>
<number>b</number>ships less than three hundred tons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>839628</tid>
<number>c</number>air- cushion vehicles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662354</tid>
<number>d</number>floating platforms constructed for the purpose of exploring or 
exploiting the natural resources of the sea- bed or the subsoil 
thereof.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>944433</tid>
<number>22</number>Insertion of new section 352FA.- After section 352F of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 352FA. Power to make rules.- The Central Government may make rules to 
carry out the purposes of this Part:

Provided that the rules under this Part shall be made having regard to 
the provisions of the Convention.".



</article>



<article><tid>1994752</tid>
<number> 23</number> Substitution of new section for section 352H.- For section 352H of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' 352H. Definitions.- In this Part, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-

<section><tid>388538</tid>
<number>a</number>" incident" means any occurrence, or series of occurrences having 
the same origin, which causes pollution damage or creates a grave and 
imminent threat of causing such damage;

</section>

<section><tid>1599587</tid>
<number>b</number>" Liability Convention" means the International Convention on Civil 
Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, <year>1992</year> as amended from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>376329</tid>
<number>c</number>" oil" means any persistent hydro carbon mineral oil such as crude 
oil, fuel oil, heavy diesel oil, lubricating oil whether carried on 
board a ship as cargo or in the bunker of such ship;

</section>

<section><tid>262869</tid>
<number>d</number>" owner" means-

<subsection><tid>1542407</tid>
<number>i</number>the person registered as owner of the ship;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>316149</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the absence of registration, the person owning the ship; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>900047</tid>
<number>iii</number>in the case of a ship owned by a foreign State, the person 
registered in that State as operator of the ship;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1435044</tid>
<number>e</number>" person" means any individual or partnership or any public or 
private body, whether corporate or not, including a State or any of 
its constituent sub- divisions;

</section>

<section><tid>281643</tid>
<number>f</number>" pollution damage" means-

<subsection><tid>559620</tid>
<number>i</number>loss or damage caused outside the ship by contamination resulting 
from escape or discharge of oil from the ship, wherever such escape or 
discharge occurs, provided that compensation for impairment of the 
environment other than losses or profit from s ch impairment shall be 
limited to costs of reasonable measures of reinstatement actually 
undertaken or to be undertaken;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>261812</tid>
<number>ii</number>the costs of preventive measures and further loss or damage 
caused by such measures;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>110314</tid>
<number>g</number>" preventive measures" means any reasonable measures taken by any 
person after the incident to prevent or minimise pollution damage;

</section>

<section><tid>1027450</tid>
<number>h</number>" ship" means any sea- going vessel and sea borne craft of any type 
whatsoever constructed or adapted for the carriage of oil in bulk as 
cargo, provided that a ship capable of carrying oil and other cargoes 
shall be regarded as a ship only when it is a tually carrying oil in 
bulk as cargo and during any voyage following such carriage unless it 
is proved that it has no residues of such carriage of oil in bulk 
aboard;

</section>

<section><tid>1124754</tid>
<number>i</number>" State of the ship' s registry", in relation to registered or 
unregistered ships, means the State of registration of the ship, or as 
the case may be, the State whose flag the ship is flying;'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1430031</tid>
<number> 24</number> Amendment of section 352-I.- In section 352-I of the principal 
Act,-
<section><tid>1027446</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (4) When any incident involving two or more ships occurs and 
pollution damage results therefrom, the owners of all the ships 
concerned, unless exonerated under sub- section (3), shall be jointly 
separable."; and severally liable for such damage which is not 
reasonabl


</section>

<section><tid>1390835</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (6), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (6) Without prejudice to any right of recourse of the owner against 
third parties, no claim for compensation for pollution damage may be 
made against-


</section>

<section><tid>1027446</tid>
<number>a</number>the servants or agents of the owner or the members of the crew;

</section>

<section><tid>1390835</tid>
<number>b</number>the pilot or any other person who, without being a member of the 
crew, renders services for the ship;

</section>

<section><tid>1204303</tid>
<number>c</number>any charterer (howsoever described, including a bare- boat  
  charterer), manager or operator of the ship;

</section>

<section><tid>1775205</tid>
<number>d</number>any person performing salvage operations with the consent of the 
owner or on the instructions of a competent public authority;

</section>

<section><tid>200329</tid>
<number>e</number>any person taking preventive measures;

</section>

<section><tid>783749</tid>
<number>f</number>all servants or agents of persons mentioned in clauses (c), (d) 
and (e), unless the incident causing such damage occurred as a result 
of their personal act or omission committed or made with the intent to 
cause such damage, or recklessly and with knowledge that such damage 
would probably result.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>973166</tid>
<number> 25</number> Substitution of new section for section 352J.- For section 352J of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 352J. Limitation of liability.- (1) The owner shall be entitled to 
limit his liability under this Part, in respect of any one or more 
incident, as may be prescribed.

<section><tid>646665</tid>
<number>2</number>The owner shall not be entitled to limit his liability if it is 
proved that the incident causing pollution damage occurred as a result 
of his personal act or omission committed or made with the intent to 
cause such damage, or recklessly and with kno ledge that such damage 
would probably result.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>785986</tid>
<number>26</number>Amendment of section 352R.- In section 352R of the principal Act, 
after clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (c) the limits of liability of owner in respect of one or more 
incident of pollution damage or other requirements having regard to 
the provisions of the Liability Convention.".



</article>



<article><tid>1940663</tid>
<number>27</number>Insertion of new Part XC.- After Part XB of the principal Act, the 
following Part shall be inserted, namely:-
' PART XC

INTERNATIONAL OIL POLLUTION COMPENSATION FUND

</article>



<article><tid>750399</tid>
<number> 352S</number> Definitions.- In this Part, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1207857</tid>
<number>a</number>" contributing oil" means crude oil and fuel oil.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause,-


<subsection><tid>1653398</tid>
<number>i</number>" crude oil" means any liquid hydro carbon mixture occurring 
naturally in the earth whether or not treated to render it suitable 
for transportation and includes crude oils from which certain 
distillate fractions have been removed or to which certain d stillate 
fractions have been added;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1924434</tid>
<number>ii</number>" fuel oil" means heavy distillates or residues from crude oil or 
blends of such materials intended for use as a fuel for the production 
of heat or power of a quality equivalent to the' American Society for 
Testing and Materials' Specification for Nu ber Four Fuel Oil 
 (Designation D 396- 69)', or heavier;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>830704</tid>
<number>b</number>" discharge or escape", in relation to pollution damage, means the 
discharge or escape of oil carried by the ship;

</section>

<section><tid>354858</tid>
<number>c</number>" Fund" means the International Oil Pollution Compensation Fund 
established by the Fund Convention;

</section>

<section><tid>1875096</tid>
<number>d</number>" Fund Convention" means the International Convention on the 
Establishment of an International Fund for Compensation for Oil 
Pollution Damage, <year>1992</year> as amended from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>814749</tid>
<number>e</number>" Fund Convention country" means a country in which the Fund 
Convention is for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>610947</tid>
<number>f</number>" guarantor" means any person providing insurance or other 
financial security to cover the owner' s liability;

</section>

<section><tid>329</tid>
<number>g</number>" terminal installation" means any site for the storage of oil in 
bulk which is capable of receiving oil from waterborne transportation, 
including any facility situated off- shore and linked to such site;

</section>

<section><tid>205346</tid>
<number>h</number>" ton", in relation to oil, means a metric ton.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1546192</tid>
<number> 352T</number> Contribution to the Fund.-
<section><tid>1044041</tid>
<number>1</number>Contributions to the Fund, in  
respect of contributing oil carried by sea to ports or terminal 
installations in India, shall be payable in accordance with Articles 
 10 and 12 of the Fund Convention.

</section>

<section><tid>1923598</tid>
<number>2</number>Sub- section (1) shall apply whether or not the contributing oil is 
imported, and notwithstanding that contributions are payable to the 
Fund in respect of carriage of the same contributing oil on a previous 
voyage.

</section>

<section><tid>166320</tid>
<number>3</number>Contributions shall also be payable to the Fund in respect of 
contributing oil when first received in any installation in India 
after having been carried by sea and discharged in a port or terminal 
installation in a country which is not a Fund Conven ion country.

</section>

<section><tid>1115537</tid>
<number>4</number>The person liable to pay contributions to the Fund shall be-

<subsection><tid>1795074</tid>
<number>a</number>in case of contributing oil which is being imported into India, 
the importer; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929078</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the person by whom the oil is received in 
India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>742664</tid>
<number>5</number>A person shall not be liable to pay contributions to the Fund in 
respect of the contributing oil imported or received by him in any 
year if the quantity of contributing oil so imported or received in 
the year does not exceed one hundred and fifty tho sand tonnes or as 
may be specified from time to time in the Fund Convention.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>969062</tid>
<number> 352U</number> Contribution payable by persons to the Fund.-
<section><tid>1041730</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
contributions payable to the Fund by a person for any year shall be,-

<subsection><tid>1072832</tid>
<number>a</number>such amount as may be determined by the Assembly of the Fund under 
Articles 10 and 12 of the Fund Convention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788718</tid>
<number>b</number>in such instalments, becoming due at such dates,
as may be notified and if any amount due from such person remains 
unpaid after the date on which it became due, it shall from that due 
date bear interest at a rate determined by the said Assembly until it 
is paid.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>723542</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may require persons, who are or may be 
liable to pay contributions to the Fund under section 352T, to give 
financial security for payment of contributions to that Government or 
the Fund.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>640976</tid>
<number> 352V</number> Power to call for information.-
<section><tid>1736310</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,  
for the purpose of transmitting to the Fund the names and addresses of 
the persons who under section 352T are liable to make contributions to 
the Fund every year and the quantity of con ributing oil in respect of 
which they are so liable, by notice require any such person to furnish 
such information as may be specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>505240</tid>
<number>2</number>A notice under this section may require a person to give such 
information as may be required to ascertain whether he is liable to 
contribute to the Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1703454</tid>
<number>3</number>A notice under this section may specify the manner in which, and 
the time within which, such notice is to be complied with.

</section>

<section><tid>1794045</tid>
<number>4</number>In proceedings by the Fund against any person to recover any 
amount due under section 352T, particulars contained in any list 
transmitted by the Central Government to the Fund shall, so far as 
those particulars are based on information obtained under this 
section, be admissible as evidence of the facts stated in the list; 
and so far as particulars which are so admissible are based on 
information given by the person against whom the proceedings are 
brought, those particulars shall be presumed to be ac urate until the 
contrary is proved.

</section>

<section><tid>1261519</tid>
<number>5</number>No person shall disclose any information which has been furnished 
to or obtained by him under this section unless the disclosure is 
made,-

<subsection><tid>509650</tid>
<number>a</number>with the consent of the person from whom the information was 
obtained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1817973</tid>
<number>b</number>in connection with the compliance of this section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>853766</tid>
<number>c</number>for the purpose of any legal proceedings arising out of this 
section or of any report of such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>643049</tid>
<number>6</number>A person who,-

<subsection><tid>313998</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses or wilfully neglects to comply with a notice under this 
section; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>629547</tid>
<number>b</number>makes, while furnishing any information in compliance with a 
notice under this section, any statement which he knows to be false in 
a material particular, or recklessly makes any statement which is 
false in a material particular, shall be guilty of an offence 
punishable under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1156116</tid>
<number>352W</number>Liability of the Fund.- Where any person suffering pollution 
damage has been unable to obtain full and adequate compensation for 
the damage under the terms of the Liability Convention on any of the 
grounds specified in Article 4 of the Fund Conventi n, the Fund shall 
be liable for pollution damage in accordance with the provisions of 
the Fund Convention.
</article>



<article><tid>1912821</tid>
<number> 352X</number> Jurisdiction of Courts.-
<section><tid>1105979</tid>
<number>1</number>Any action for a claim against the  
Fund for compensation under section 352W shall be brought before the 
High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>484701</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall have the right to intervene as a party to any legal 
proceedings instituted in the High Court against the owner or his 
guarantor.

</section>

<section><tid>794978</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an action for compensation for pollution damage has been 
brought against the owner or his guarantor before the High Court each 
party to the proceedings may notify the Fund of the proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>1537080</tid>
<number>4</number>Where such notice of proceedings has been given to the Fund, any 
judgment given in the proceedings shall, after it has become final and 
enforceable, become binding upon the Fund in the sense that the facts 
and evidence in that judgment may not be dis uted by the Fund on the 
ground that it has not intervened in the proceedings.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>717194</tid>
<number> 352Y</number> Extinguishment of claims.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
any other law for the time being in force, no action to enforce a 
claim against the Fund under this Part shall be entertained by a High 
Court unless-
<section><tid>1844218</tid>
<number>a</number>the action to enforce is commenced; or

</section>

<section><tid>1821552</tid>
<number>b</number>notice of action to enforce a claim against the owner or his 
guarantor in respect of the same pollution damage is given to the 
Fund,
within three years from the date when the damage occurred:

Provided that in no case an action to enforce a claim shall be brought 
after six years from the date of the incident that caused such damage.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1758552</tid>
<number>352Z</number>Subrogation and right to recourse.- In respect of any sum paid 
by a public authority in India or the Fund, as the case may be, as 
compensation for pollution damage, that authority shall acquire by 
subrogation any rights which the person so compensat d would have 
enjoyed under the Fund Convention.
</article>



<article><tid>1170174</tid>
<number>352ZA</number>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may make such 
rules as may be required to carry out the purposes of the Fund 
Convention.'.
CHAP

AMENDMENT OF THE MAJOR PORT TRUSTS ACT, <year>1963</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT OF THE MAJOR PORT TRUSTS ACT, <year>1963</year>



</article>



<article><tid>902225</tid>
<number>28</number>Amendment of section 116 of Act 38 of <year>1963</year>.- In section 116 of the 
Major Port Trusts Act, <year>1963</year>, for the portion beginning with the words 
" such recovery, by distress and sale," and ending with the words 
" attributable to the order, act or improper omiss on of such 
employee", the words, letters and figures" such recovery in accordance 
with the provisions of Part XA of the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44  
  of <year>1958</year>)" shall be substituted.
-----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>