<act><title>


the Forum of Regulators Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number>     Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Forum of Regulators Rules, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    “Forum” means Forum of Regulators as 
    constituted under rule 3;  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003);  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    words and expressions used herein and 
    not defined, but defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in the said Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of the Forum.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Forum shall consist of the Chairperson of the Central Commission and 
    Chairpersons of the State Commissions. The Chairperson of the Central 
    Commission shall be the Chairperson of the Forum of Regulators.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Secretary to the Central Commission shall be the ex‑officio Secretary 
    to the Forum.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Secretarial 
    assistance to the Forum shall be provided by the Central Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    headquarter of the Forum will be located at New Delhi.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Functions 
    of the Forum.—The Forum shall 
    discharge the following functions, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    analysis of the tariff orders and other 
    orders of Central Commission and State Commissions and compilation of data 
    arising out of the said orders, highlighting, especially the efficiency 
    improvements of the utilities;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    harmonization of regulation in power 
    sector;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    laying of standards of performance of 
    licensees as required under the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    sharing of information among the 
    members of the Forum on various issues of common interest and also of common 
    approach;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    undertaking research work in‑house or 
    through outsourcing on issues relevant to power sector regulation;  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    evolving measures for protection of 
    interest of consumers and promotion of efficiency, economy and competition 
    in power sector; and  
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    such other functions as the Central 
    Government may assign to it, from time to time.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Finances 
    of the Forum.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Commission may take necessary financial contributions from the State 
    Commissions for carrying out the activities of the Forum.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Commission will keep separate accounts for the activities of the Forum.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Meetings 
    of the Forum.—
<section><number>1</number> The Forum shall 
    meet at least twice in a year.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Forum 
    will frame its own rules of business for the conduct of its meetings.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Annual 
    Report.—The Forum of Regulators 
    shall prepare every year, an annual report, giving a summary of its 
    activities during the previous financial year and copies of the report shall 
    be forwarded to the Central Government.  
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>