<act><title>THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS RULES, 
19941 </title> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 19941
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Cable Television Networks Rules, 1994.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 

      1[
<section><number>a</number>  “Act” means the Cable 
Television Networks (Regulation) Act, 1995 (7 of 1995);
 </section><section>
     <number>aa</number>  “Authority” means the Telecom 
Regulatory Authority of India established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of 
the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 1997);
 </section><section>
   <number>aaa</number>  “Broadcaster” means any person 
including an individual, group of persons, public or body corporate, firm or 
any organization or body who or which is providing programing service and 
includes his or her authorized distribution agencies;]
 

2[(aaaa)]   “cable operator” means 
any person who provides cable service through a cable television network or 
otherwise controls or is responsible for the management and operation of a 
cable television networks;
 </section><section>
      <number>b</number> “cable service” means the 
transmission by cables of programmes including re-transmission by cables of any 
broadcast television signals;
 </section><section>
      <number>c</number> “cable television network” means 
any system consisting of a set of closed transmission paths and associated 
signals generation, control and distribution equipment, designed to provide 
cable service for reception by multiple subscribers;
 </section><section>
      <number>d</number> “company” means a company defined 
in section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956;
 </section><section>
      <number>e</number> “form” means form appended to 
these rules;
 
 

1[(ee)  “Multi-System Operator (MSO)” 
means a cable operator who receives a programming service from a broadcaster or 
his authorized agencies and re-transmits the same or transmits his own 
programming service for simultaneous reception either by multiple subscribers 
directly or through one or more Local Cable Operators (LCOs), and includes his 
authorised distribution agencies by whatever name called;
 </section><section>
   <number>eee</number>  “Notified area” means any area 
notified by the Central Government under section 4A of the Act;]
 </section><section>
       <number>f</number> “person” means—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number> an individual who is 
a citizen of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number> an association of 
individuals or body of individuals, whether incorporated or not, whose members 
are citizens of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number> a company in which not 
less than fifty-one per cent. of the paid-up share capital is held by the 
citizens of India;
 </subsection></section><section>
      <number>g</number> “programme” means any television 
broadcast and includes—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number> exhibition of films, 
features, dramas, advertisements and serials through video cassette recorders 
or video cassette players;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number> any audio or visual or 
audio-visual live performance or presentation; and the expression “programming 
service” shall be construed accordingly;
 </subsection></section><section>
      <number>h</number> “registering authority” means the 
registering authority notified under clause (h) of section 2 of the Cable 
Television Networks (Regulation) Ordinance 1994*;
 </section><section>
       <number>i</number> “subscriber” means a person who 
receives the signal of cable television network at a place indicated by him to 
the cable operator, without further transmitting it to any other person.
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for 
registration as a cable television network in India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for registration as a cable television network in India shall 
be made in writing in Form 1 and shall be renewable after every twelve months.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application shall 
be addressed to the Registering Authority and delivered to his office in Form 
1.
 

1[(3) (a) Every 
application for registration or renewal of registration shall be accompanied 
by—
 <subsection>
       <number>i</number>  a fee of rupees five hundred 
only; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ii</number>  the requisite documents 
mentioned in Form 1 and Form 2.
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> Every application for 
issue of duplicate certificate of registration shall be accompanied by—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>i</number>  a fee of rupees two hundred and 
fifty only; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ii</number> the requisite documents 
mentioned in Form 1.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The amount of fee 
shall be deposited in the Head Post Office where the application for 
registration or renewal of registration or issue of duplicate certificate of 
registration is being made.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The amount of the 
fees shall be deposited under the Head ‘Un-Classified Receipts (U.C.R.)’.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Examination of 
applications.—On 
receipt of an application under rule 3 the registering authority shall examine 
the application having regard to the provisions of section 4 of the Ordinance*.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Registration.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
On being satisfied that the applicant fulfils the provisions of the Act, the 
registering authority shall issue a registration certificate in Form 3:
 
Provided that where the 
registering authority is satisfied that the registration cannot be granted to 
the applicant, he shall inform the applicant in Form 4.
 

2[(2) On receipt 
of an application under clause (b), sub-rule (3) of rule 3 for issue of 
duplicate certificate the Registering Authority shall examine the application 
having regard to the provisions of rule 3 and shall issue a duplicate 
Registration Certificate in Form 3A.]
 
 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Programme Code. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No programme should be carried in 
the cable service which— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> offends against good taste or decency; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> contains criticism of friendly countries; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> contains attack on religions or communities or visuals or words 
  contemptuous of religious groups or which promote communal attitudes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> contains anything obscene, defamatory, deliberate, false and suggestive 
  innuendos and half truths; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> is likely to encourage or incite violence or contains anything against 
  maintenance of law and order or which promote anti-national attitudes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> contains anything amounting to contempt of court; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> contains aspersions against the integrity of the President and 
  Judiciary; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> contains anything affecting the integrity of the Nation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> criticises, maligns or slanders any individual in person or certain 
  groups, segments of social, public and moral life of the country; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> encourages superstition or blind belief; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> denigrates women through the depiction in any manner of the figure of a 
  woman, her form or body or any part thereof in such a way as to have the 
  effect of being indecent, or derogatory to women, or is likely to deprave, 
  corrupt or injure the public morality or morals; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> denigrates children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> contains visual or words which reflect a slandering, ironical and 
  snobbish attitude in the portrayal of certain ethnic, linguistic and regional 
  groups; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> contravenes the provisions of the Cinematograph Act, 1952 (37 of 1952); 
  
 </subsection><subsection>[<number>o</number> is not suitable for unrestricted public exhibition]: 
</subsection>
 [Provided that no film or film song or film promo or film trailer 
or music video or music albums or their promos, whether produced in India or 
abroad, shall be carried through cable service unless it has been certified by 
the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) as suitable for unrestricted 
public exhibition in India.] 
 
 [Explanation. —For the purpose of this clause, the 
  expression “unrestricted public exhibition” shall have the same meaning as 
  assigned to it in the Cinematograph Act, 1952 (37 of 1952).] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The cable operator should strive to carry programmes in his cable service 
which project women in a positive, leadership role of sobriety, moral and 
character building qualities. 
 </section><section>[<number>3</number> No cable operator shall carry or include in his cable 
service any programme in respect of which copyright subsists under the 
[Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957)] unless he has been granted a 
licence by owners of copyright under that Act in respect of such programme.] 

 </section><section><number>4</number> Care should be taken to ensure that programmes meant for children do not 
contain any bad language or explicit scenes of violence. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Programmes unsuitable for children must not be carried in the cable 
service at times when the largest numbers of children are viewing. 
 </section><section>[<number>6</number> No cable operator shall carry or include in his cable 
service any television broadcast or channel, which has not been registered by 
the Central Government for being viewed within the territory of India: 
 [Provided that a cable operator may continue to carry or include 
in his cable service any television broadcast or channel, whose application for 
registration to the Central Government was made on or before 11th May, 2006 and 
is under consideration, for a period up to 15th June, 2009 or till such 
registration has been granted or refused, whichever is earlier.] 
 Provided further that channels uplinking from India , in accordance with 
permission for uplinking granted before 2nd December, 2005 , shall be treated as 
“registered” television channels and can be carried or included in the cable 
service.] 
 [***]
 ____________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 729(E), dated 29th September, 1994, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), dated 29th 
September, 1994 and amended vide 
 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 459(E), dated 8-10-1996 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 710(E), dated 8-9-2000 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 282(E), dated 11-5-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 452(E), dated 31-7-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 459(E), dated 2-8-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 469(E), dated 9-8-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 697(E), dated 11-11-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 286(E), dated 11-4-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 482(E), dated 12-7-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 774(E), dated 3-12-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 25(E), dated 10-1-2008 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 104(E), dated 25-2-2008 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 413(E), dated 29-5-2008 .</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 710(E), dated 8th September, 2000 (w.e.f. 
8-9-2000 ). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 459(E), dated 2nd August, 2006 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2006 ). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 710(E), dated 8th September, 2000 (w.e.f. 
8-9-2000 ). 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 26(E), dated 18th January, 2001 . 
 </section></article><article><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 282(E), dated 11th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 11-5-2006 
). 
 </article><article><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 411(E), dated 12th June, 2009 , for first 
proviso (w.e.f. 12-6-2009 ). Earlier the first proviso was substituted by G.S.R. 
413(E), dated 29th May, 2008 (w.e.f. 29-5-2008), by G.S.R. 25(E), dated 10th 
January, 2008 (w.e.f. 10-1-2008), by G.S.R. 774(E), dated 3rd December, 2007 
(w.e.f. 18-12-2007), by G.S.R. 482(E), dated 12th July, 2007 (w.e.f. 12-7-2007), 
by G.S.R. 286(E), dated 11th April, 2007 (w.e.f. 11-4-2007) and G.S.R. 697(E), 
dated 11th November, 2006 (w.e.f. 11-11-2006). The first proviso, before 
substitution by G.S.R. 411(E), stood as under: 
 “Provided that a cable operator may continue to carry or include 
in his cable service any television broadcast or channel, whose application for 
registration to the Central Government was made on or before 11th May, 2006 and 
is under consideration, for a period up to 31st May, 2008 or till such 
registration has been granted or refused, whichever is earlier.”. 
 </article><article><number>8</number> Rescinded by G.S.R. 719(E), dated 13th September, 2000 . 
Earlier rule 6A was inserted by G.S.R. 597(E), dated 20th August, 1999 (w.e.f. 
20-8-1999 ). 
  
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number>Advertising Code. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Advertising carried in the cable 
service shall be so designed as to conform to the laws of the country and should 
not offend morality, decency and religious susceptibilities of the subscribers. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> No advertisement shall be permitted which— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> derides any race, caste, colour, creed and nationality; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> is against any provision of the Constitution of India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> tends to incite people to crime, cause disorder or violence or breach 
  of law or glorifies violence or obscenity in any way; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> presents criminality as desirable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> exploits the national emblem, or any part of the Constitution or the 
  person or personality of a national leader or a State dignitary; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> in its depiction of women violates the Constitutional guarantees to 
  all citizens. In particular, no advertisement shall be permitted which 
  projects a derogatory image of women. Women must not be portrayed in a manner 
  that emphasises passive, submissive qualities and encourages them to play a 
  subordinate, secondary role in the family and society. The cable operator 
  shall ensure that the portrayal of the female form, in the programmes carried 
  in his cable service is tasteful and aesthetic, and is within the well 
  established norms of good taste and decency; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> exploits social evils like dowry, child marriage; 
 </subsection><subsection>[<number>viii</number> promotes directly or indirectly production, sale or 
  consumption of— 
 <subsubsection>[<number>A</number> cigarettes, tobacco products, wine, alcohol, liquor or 
  other intoxicants:] </subsubsection></subsection>
 [Provided that a product that uses a brand name or logo, which is 
also used for cigarettes, tobacco products, wine, alcohol, liquor or other 
intoxicants, may be advertised on cable service subject to the following 
conditions that— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the story board or visual of the advertisement must depict only the 
  product being advertised and not the prohibited products in any form or 
  manner; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the advertisement must not make any direct or indirect reference to 
  the prohibited products; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the advertisement must not contain any nuances or phrases promoting 
  prohibited products; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the advertisement must not use particular colours and layout or 
  presentations associated with prohibited products; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the advertisement must not use situations typical for promotion of 
  prohibited products when advertising the other products: 
 Provided further that— 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the advertiser shall submit an application with a copy of the proposed 
  advertisement along with a certificate by a registered Chartered Accountant 
  that the product carrying the same name as cigarettes, tobacco products, wine, 
  alcohol, liquor or other intoxicants is distributed in reasonable quantity and 
  is available in a substantial number of outlets where other products of the 
  same category are available and the proposed expenditure on such advertising 
  thereon shall not be disproportionate to the actual sales turnover of the 
  product; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> all such advertisements found to be genuine brand extensions by the 
  Ministry of Information and Broadcasting shall be previewed and certified by 
  the Central Board of Film Certification as suitable for unrestricted public 
  exhibition and are in accordance with the provisions contained in sub-clause 
  (i) to (v) of the first proviso, prior to their telecast or transmission or 
  retransmission.] 
 <subsubsection><number>B</number> infant milk substitutes, feeding bottle or infant foods.] 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> No advertisement shall be permitted the objects whereof are wholly or 
mainly of a religious or political nature; advertisements must not be directed 
towards any religious or political end. 
 </section><section>[<number>3A</number> No advertisement shall contain references which hurt 
religious sentiments.] 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The goods or services advertised shall not suffer from any defect or 
deficiency as mentioned in Consumer Protection Act, 1986. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> No advertisement shall contain references which are likely to lead the 
public to infer that the product advertised or any of its ingredients has some 
special or miraculous or super-natural property or quality, which is difficult 
of being proved. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The picture and the audible matter of the advertisement shall not be 
excessively ‘loud'. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> No advertisement which endangers the safety of children or creates in 
them any interest in unhealthy practices or shows them begging or in an 
undignified or indecent manner shall not be carried in the cable service. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Indecent, vulgar, suggestive, repulsive or offensive themes or treatment 
shall be avoided in all advertisements. 
 </section><section>[<number>9</number> No advertisement which violates the Code for self-regulation 
in advertising, as adopted by the Advertising Standard Council of India (ASCI), 
Mumbai for public exhibition in India, from time to time, shall be carried in 
the cable service.] 
 </section><section><number>10</number> All advertisements should be clearly distinguishable from the programme 
and should not in any manner interfere with the programme viz., use of 
lower part of screen to carry captions, static or moving alongside the 
programme. 
 </section><section>[<number>11</number> No programme shall carry advertisements exceeding twelve 
minutes per hour, which may include up to ten minutes per hour of commercial 
advertisements, and up to two minutes per hour of a channel's self-promotional 
programmes.] 
 ______________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 729(E), dated 29th September, 1994, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra.,  Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), dated 29th 
September, 1994 and amended vide 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 459(E), dated 8-10-1996 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 710(E), dated 8-9-2000 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 282(E), dated 11-5-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 452(E), dated 31-7-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 459(E), dated 2-8-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 469(E), dated 9-8-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 697(E), dated 11-11-2006 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 286(E), dated 11-4-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 482(E), dated 12-7-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 774(E), dated 3-12-2007 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 25(E), dated 10-1-2008 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 104(E), dated 25-2-2008 . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 413(E), dated 29-5-2008 . 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 710(E), dated 8th September, 2000 (w.e.f. 
8-9-2000 ). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 104(E), dated 25th February, 2008 (w.e.f. 
25-2-2008 ). Earlier it was amended by G.S.R. 469(E), dated 9th August, 2006 
(w.e.f. 10-8-2006 ). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 138(E), 27th February, 2009 (w.e.f. 27-2-2009 
). 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 710(E), dated 8th September, 2000 (w.e.f. 
8-9-2000 ). 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 459(E), dated 2nd August, 2006 for sub-rule 
(9) (w.e.f. 3-8-2006 ). Sub-rule (9), before substitution, stood as under: 
 ”(9) No advertisement which violates the standards of practice 
for advertising agencies as approved by the Advertising Agencies Association of 
India, Bombay, from time to time, shall be carried in the cable service.” 
 </section></article><article><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st July, 2006 (w.e.f. 
31-7-2006 ). </article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Register.—Each 
cable operator shall maintain a register in Form 5 for each month of the year 
for which the registration is granted.
</article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>9</number> Standard 
interconnection agreements, tariffs and quality of service standards for the 
service providers in the areas notified under section 4A of the Act.—The 
Authority may, on issue of any notification under section 4A of the Act by the 
Central Government, take appropriate decisions on the following aspects and 
duly notify the—
 <section>
      <number>a</number>  standard interconnection 
agreement to be used for entering into commercial agreements for distribution 
in the notified areas, of pay or free-to-air channels among (i) broadcasters 
and multi-system operators; and (ii) multi-system operators and local cable 
operators;
 </section><section>
      <number>b</number>  the maximum limits of security 
deposit and monthly rental for supply, maintenance and servicing of Set Top 
Boxes of prescribed specifications to the subscribers on rental basis by 
multi-system operators in the notified areas;
 </section><section>
      <number>c</number>  tariff for the basic service tier 
along with the minimum number of free-to-air channels to be provided by the 
multi-system operators or local cable operators to the subscribers in the 
notified areas;
 </section><section>
      <number>d</number>  regulations for quality of 
service to be provided by the multi-system operators or local cable operators 
to the subscribers in the notified areas.]
 
 









</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> 
Nature and prices of channels.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every broadcaster shall declare the nature of each of its channels as ‘pay’ or 
‘free-to-air’ channel as well as the maximum retail price of each of its ‘pay’ 
channels to be charged by the multi-system operators or local cable operators 
from the subscribers in each of the notified areas.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every broadcaster 
shall file his declaration of the nature and prices of channels under sub-rule 
(1) before the Authority and the Central Government within fifteen days of the 
date of notification by the Central Government under section 4A of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If in the opinion of 
the Authority, the price declared by the broadcaster in respect of any of its 
pay channels is too high, the Authority may, under section 11 of the Telecom 
Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 1997), fix and declare the 
maximum retail price of such a pay channel or fix a general maximum retail 
price for all pay channels within which the broadcasters may declare their 
individual prices for each pay channel, to be paid by the subscribers in any of 
the notified areas, and such an order of the Authority shall be binding on the 
broadcasters and the multi-system operators and local cable operators.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every broadcaster 
shall enter into interconnection agreements with multi-system operators in the 
notified areas as per the standard interconnection agreement, or with any 
mutually agreed modifications on a non-discriminatory basis, as per the 
regulations or directions or orders of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If a broadcaster 
fails to declare the price of any of its pay channels within the prescribed 
time limit under sub-rule (2) or refuses or fails to comply with the direction 
under sub-rule (3) or refuses or fails to enter into an interconnect agreement 
with a multi­-system operator permitted by the Central Government under 
sub-rule (3) of rule 11 within the time limit as prescribed by the Authority, 
then the Authority may, so as to protect the interests of the subscribers, take 
interim measures to ensure supply of signals.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In the event of 
non-compliance by the broadcaster of the directions issued by the Authority 
under sub-rule (5), the Central Government may, on the recommendations of the 
Authority, suspend the permission granted to the broadcaster under uplinking or 
downlinking guidelines as the case may be, to broadcast that channel in the 
country or any part thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every declaration 
filed by the broadcaster under sub-rule (1) or maximum retail price fixed by 
the Authority under sub-rule (3) shall normally remain valid for a period of 
one year from the date of such declaration or fixation, as the case may be, 
subject to the condition that every broadcaster will be free to revise the 
price of any channel or convert a pay channel to free-to-air or a free-to-air 
channel to a pay channel by giving one month’s notice to the multi-system 
operator and subscribers:
 
Provided that no increase 
in price beyond the individual limit, if any specified by the Authority, shall 
be valid without prior approval of the Authority:
 
Provided further that no 
such price increase shall be valid beyond the general maximum retail price for 
all channels fixed by the Authority.]
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> 
Grant of permission to multi-system operators to provide cable services with 
addressable systems in the notified areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No multi-system operator shall provide cable television network services with 
addressable systems in any one or more notified areas without a valid 
permission from the Central Government under sub-rule (3) of rule 11.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every multi-system 
operator who desires to provide cable television network services with 
addressable systems in any of the notified areas, shall, within thirty days of 
the issue of the notifications under section 4A of the Act by the Central 
Government, apply for permission to the Ministry of Information and 
Broadcasting in Form 6 annexed to these rules, along with processing fee of 
rupees ten thousand.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Ministry of 
Information and Broadcasting in the Government of India shall, within thirty 
days of the receipt of the application, grant, or refuse, permission to the 
applicant to provide addressable systems in the notified areas after 
considering its suitability or otherwise on the basis of information given in 
respect of its existing operational area, actual number of subscribers and 
addresses of its local cable operators in each of the notified areas, 
commercial arrangements with the broadcasters and local cable operators, if 
any, financial strength, management capability, security clearance and 
preparedness to supply and maintain adequate number of Set Top Boxes for its 
subscribers, installation of its subscriber management system and compliance 
with all other quality of service standards as may be specified by the 
Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
Government may lay down such terms and conditions of permission under sub-rule 
(3) as may be deemed necessary and desirable to ensure compliance with the 
provisions of this Act and the regulations, directions and orders made by the 
Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No multi-system 
operator shall continue to provide any cable television network services in the 
notified areas after the date notified therein, without obtaining prior 
permission from the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In the event of a 
multi-system operator who fails or refuses to enter into an interconnection 
agreement with a broadcaster of a pay channel or an adequate number of local 
cable operators in the notified areas or who violate the terms and conditions 
of the permission granted to it under sub-rule (3), within the time limit as 
prescribed by the Authority, the Authority may, so as to protect the interests 
of the subscribers, take interim measures to ensure supply of signals.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In the event of 
violation by a multi-system operator of one or more of the terms and conditions 
of the permission granted under sub-rule (3), the Central Government may 
suspend or revoke such permission for such period and for such notified areas 
as it deems fit:
 
Provided that no such 
order of suspension or revocation shall be made without giving a reasonable 
opportunity to the multi-system operator to explain its position.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> 
Public awareness campaign about Conditional Access System scheme.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-system operator granted permission under sub-rule (3) of rule 11 
shall create public awareness among the subscribers in the notified areas for a 
period of thirty days from the date to be specified by the Authority, either 
through advertisements in the print and electronic media or through other means 
(e.g. leaflets, printing on the reverse of the receipts, personal 
visits, group meetings with subscribers or consumer groups etc.) the salient 
features of the Conditional Access System scheme as approved by the Authority 
for implementation, by the multi-system operator, in the notified areas, and in 
particular the following:—
 <subsection>
      <number>a</number>  A-la-carte subscription rates and 
the periodic intervals at which such subscriptions are payable for receiving 
the various pay channels;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>b</number>  the refundable security deposit 
and the daily or monthly rental payable for the set-top box and its detailed 
specifications such as make, model, technical specifications, user manuals and 
maintenance centers etc.;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>c</number>  the number and names of 
free-to-air channels that the multi-system operator will provide to the 
subscribers and specific placement of each channel in the prime or non-prime 
bands;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>d</number>  the prescribed monthly service 
charge to be paid by each subscriber for receiving the basic service tier fixed 
by the Authority and the number of additional free-to-air channels, if any, 
offered by the Multi-system Operator;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>e</number>  the Quality of Service Standards 
specified by the Authority and the arrangements made by the Multi-System 
Operator to comply with these standards;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>f</number>  the Subscriber Management System 
established by the multi-system operator to demonstrate the functioning of the 
Set Top Boxes and interact with the subscribers to explain the various 
financial, logistic and technical aspects of the system for its smooth 
implementation;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>g</number>  the subsisting arrangements for 
resolution of disputes between the multi-system operator and local cable 
operators and the subscribers in respect of the quality of service standards, 
payments and refunds etc.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority may 
also arrange public awareness activities in the notified areas either directly 
or through authorized officers or consumer organizations etc.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>13</number> 
Supply and installation of Set Top Boxes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every subscriber in the notified areas who desires to receive one or more pay 
channels shall, during the public awareness campaign under rule 12 or within 
fifteen days after its expiry, apply to any one of the multi-system operators 
granted permission under sub-rule (3) of rule 11 either directly or through any 
of his linked local cable operators, to supply and install one or more Set Top 
Boxes in his premises as per the scheme approved by the Authority and deliver 
the requisite channels through the same:
 
Provided that every 
subscriber shall be free to buy a Set Top Box of approved quality from the open 
market, if available and technically compatible with the multi-system 
operator’s system, and no multi-system operator or cable operator shall force 
any subscriber to buy or to take on rent the Set Top Box from him only.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every subscriber in 
the notified areas who desires to receive one or more pay channels, and who 
failed to apply within the period prescribed under sub-rule (1) may at any time 
either buy a Set Top Box of approved quality from the open market, if available 
and technically compatible with the multi-system operator’s system, or apply to 
any one of the multi-system operators granted permission under sub-rule (3) of 
rule 11 either directly or through any of his linked local cable operators, to 
supply and install one or more Set Top Boxes in his premises as per the scheme 
approved by the Authority and deliver the requisite channels through the same 
or through the Set Top Box of approved quality acquired by the applicant on his 
own, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every multi-system 
operator shall procure, supply and install the required number of Set Top Boxes 
of approved quality in the premises of every applicant under sub-rule (1) or 
sub-rule (2) within a period as may be determined by regulation or order by the 
Authority from the date of receipt of such application, and transmit the 
requisite pay channels through the same or through the Set Top Box of approved 
quality acquired by the applicant on his own, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every multi-system 
operator shall set up and operationalise its subscriber management system 
within a time frame as may be determined by regulation or order by the 
Authority, for ensuring efficient and error-free service to the subscribers by 
recording and providing individualized preferences for pay channels, billing 
cycles, refunds etc..
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of the 
failure of any multi-system operator to supply and install a Set Top Box each 
in the premises of one or more applicants under sub-rule (1) or to 
operationalise subscriber management system within the time limit as determined 
by regulation or order by the Authority, then the Authority may, so as to 
protect the interests of the subscribers, take interim measures to ensure 
supply of signals.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>14</number> 
Dispute Resolution Mechanism.—Every 
multi-system operator shall be obliged to maintain the quality of service as 
per the standards, including the arrangements for handling complaints and 
redressal of grievances of the subscribers, as may be determined by regulation 
or order by the Authority. The Authority may look into the efficacy of such 
arrangements and issue necessary directions to the concerned parties for 
compliance.]
 
 












</article> 
 
THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Transition to 
addressable systems.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Immediately on operationalisation of the subscriber management system and the 
installation of the Set Top Boxes under rule 13, every multi-system operator 
shall start transmitting the pay channels in encrypted as well as unencrypted 
form for a period of not less than fifteen days to test out the quality of 
service, remove any technical or operational snags and enable the subscribers 
to become familiar with the operation of addressable systems at their end.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before the start of 
the transition period under sub-rule (1), the Authority may call for progress 
or compliance reports from the service providers in the Forms appended to these 
rules, and at intervals, as may be specified by it to satisfy itself that all 
the multi-system operators permitted under sub-rule (3) of rule 11 have 
completed all the necessary arrangements to switch over to transmission of pay 
channels through addressable systems in the whole of the notified area by the 
date notified by the Central Government under section 4A of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event of 
satisfactory completion of all arrangements, every multi-system operator in the 
notified area shall start transmitting pay channels only through addressable 
systems from the date notified by the Central Government under section 4A of 
the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the event of the 
Authority coming to a conclusion that the arrangements made by the multi-system 
operators are not adequate and the switch over to transmission of pay channels 
through addressable systems is likely to be against the interests of a 
substantial portion of the subscribers in any notified area, the Authority may 
recommend to the Central! Government an extension of the notified date by such 
period as in its opinion is the minimum required for the satisfactory 
completion of the necessary arrangements by the multi-system operators.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of a 
recommendation from the Authority under sub-rule (4), and before the expiry of 
the notified date, the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that it is 
not in public interest to switch over to addressable systems on the notified 
date and that circumstances so warrant to extend the notified date to protect 
the interests of a substantial portion of subscribers in the notified area, 
issue another notification indicating the revised date under section 4A of the 
Act:
 
Provided that the power 
to issue notification in respect of the areas already notified by the 
Government of India in the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting under 
section 4A of the Act vide number S.O. 792(E), dated the 10th July, 2003 
shall be subject to the orders and final outcome of the LPA No. 985/2006 &amp; CMs 
6660/2006 and 6658/2006 pending in the High Court of Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every multi-system 
operator shall complete the remaining arrangements within such extended period 
and start transmitting the pay channels only through addressable systems from 
such revised date as notified under sub-rule (5).
 
 
</section></article><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 



1[FORM 1
 


[See rule 3(1)]
 


(To be submitted in duplicate)
 


Form of 
application for *registration/renewal of  

registration/issue of duplicate certificate of  

registration as a cable operator
 


To
 


The Head Postmaster
 


Head Post Office
 


...............................
 


Application for *registration/renewal of 
registration/issue of duplicate certificate of registration as a cable 
operator.
 


         1. (a) Name of Applicant 
(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of individuals)*
 


             (b) Age/Date of 
establishment/Date of incorporation.
 


         2. (a) Address (Office)
 


 
(b)     Telephone number (if any).
 


         3. (a) Nationality (for individual 
applicants/body of individuals)
 


             (b) By birth/domicile
 


         
4. (a) Amount of fee paid for *registration/renewal/issue of duplicate 
certificate Rs..........
 


             (b)     Name of Head Post 
Office..................................................................
 


              (Attach copy of challan 
vide which the fees have been deposited)
 


         5. Area in which cable television 
network is working/proposed to be set up.
 


         6.  Date from which the cable 
television network is operating/proposed to be set up..............
 


         7. Number of channels being 
provided/proposed to be provided (with names).
 


         8. (a) Whether using Television 
Receive Only (TVRO)                  Yes/No
 


             (b) If Yes, number and size of 
TVRO.............................
 


             (c) 
Location...................................
 


         9. Names of Doordarshan satellite 
channels included in cable service.....................
 


       10. Copy of earlier registration 
certificate enclosed.                    Yes/No
 


              (To be filled in only for 
renewal of registration).
 


       11. (a) State reasons for issue of 
duplicate certificate of registration.......................
 


                  (Attach mutilated or 
defaced original certificate of registration/copy of report made to the police 
in case of theft or loss of the original certificate)
 


             (b) Period validity of the 
original Registration Certificate for which the duplicate Registration 
Certificate is being sought........................
 


              (To be filled in only for 
issue of duplicate Registration Certificate)]
 


       12.  Declaration if Form 2 enclosed. 
                                 Yes/No
 


I/We ................................ the 
applicant(s) *(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of 
individuals) do hereby declare that the above facts are correct in all respect.
 




 
 


 
 



                                                                                                                                Signature of Applicant
 



                                                                                                                           
*(individual/firm/company/
 



                                                                                                                             
association of persons/
 



                                                                                                                                
body of individuals)
 



Place.............................                                                                                            
Name................................
 



Date..............................                                                                                            Address.............................
 


* Score out the word or words which are not 
applicable.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 459(E), dated 8th 
October, 1996 (w.e.f. 8-10-1996).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 


FORM 2
 


[See rule 3(3)]
 


I/We.....................the applicant(s) 
(individual/firm/company/ association of persons/body of individuals)* for 
registration as a cable operator/renewal of registration as a cable operator do 
hereby declare that—
 


         (i) I/We shall ensure that my/our 
cable television network shall run in accordance with the provisions of the 
Cable Television Networks (Regulation) Act, 1995 at all times.
 


        (ii) I/We shall not permit/associate 
any person who is not eligible to run a cable television network under the 
Cable Television Networks (Regulation) Act, 1995 to run/with the running of 
my/our cable television network.
 


        (iii) I/We shall strive to the best 
of my/our ability to provide cable service to the satisfaction of the 
subscriber(s) of my/our cable television network.
 


       (iv) I/We shall strive to the best of 
my/our ability to ensure that my/our cable television network is not used for 
any unlawful purpose.
 


        (v) I/We shall obtain the necessary 
approval/ clearance from the relevant authority for the running of my/our cable 
television network.
 


       (vi) I/We shall abide by any 
direction issued by the Central Government in respect of the running of a cable 
television network within India.
 




 
 



                                                                                                                        
Signature of Applicant
 



                                                                                                                      
(individual/firm/company/
 



                                                                                                                       
association of persons/
 



                                                                                                                          
body of individuals)
 



Place.............................                                                                                           
Name................................
 



Date..............................                                                                                          
Address.............................
 



                                                                                                                    
.........................................
 


* Score out the word or words which are not 
applicable.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 


FORM 3
 


(See rule 5)
 


Government of India
 


Head Post Office
 


REGISTRATION CERTIFICATE NUMBER
 


Shri/Shrimati/M/s........................resident 
of.......................is registered as a cable operator (individual, firm, 
company, association of persons or body of individuals)* for running a cable 
television network at the following address....................... in the 
city/town of.......................for a period of twelve months with effect 
from....................... His Registration Number is.......................
 


2. This Certificate is only valid for the 
premises stated above.
 


3. This Registration Certificate is not 
transferable.
 


4. The Certificate shall remain valid for 
the period indicated above or till the holder carries on the cable service or 
where the surrender of the certificate is accepted by the competent authority.
 



                                                                              
Head Post Master
 



                                                                              
Head Post Office
 



                                                                              
..........................(town/city)
 



Place.............................                                                                      

 



Date..............................                       
 


TO BE DISPLAYED PROMINENTLY ON THE PREMISES 
OF THE CABLE OPERATOR.
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 



1[Form 3A
 


[See rule 5(2)]
 


Government of India 

Head Post Office
 


duplicate 
registration certificate
 


1. Shri/Shrimati/M/s...................resident 
of ................... is registered as a cable operator 
(individual/firm/company/association of persons or body of individuals)* for 
running a cable television network at the following 
address.....................in the city/town of .................... for a 
period of twelve months with effect from.................(date from which the 
original Registration Certificate was valid).
 


His Registration Number 
is.................................................
 


2. This Certificate is valid only for the 
premises stated above.
 


3. This Registration Certificate is not 
transferable.
 


4. The Certificate shall remain valid for 
the period indicated above or till the holder carries on the cable service or 
where the surrender of the certificate is accepted by the competent authority.
 



                                                                              
Head Post Master
 



                                                                              
Head Post Office
 



                                                                              
.........................(town/city)
 



Place.............................                                                          

 



Date..............................                       
 


to be displayed 
prominently on the premises of the cable operator
 


      *Tick whichever is a appropriate]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 459(E), dated 8th 
October, 1996 (w.e.f. 8-10-1996).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 


FORM 4
 


[See proviso to rule 5(1)]
 


To
 


.....................................
 


Sir,
 


Reference to your application 
dated.........................for registration as a cable operator. The 
necessary registration cannot be granted to you for the following reason(s):—
 


         (i) Application is incomplete.
 


        (ii) Registration fee has not been 
tendered.
 


        (iii) Applicant is not a citizen of 
India.
 


       (iv) Less than fifty-one per cent. of 
the paid-up share capital of the applicant company is held by citizens of 
India.
 


Head Post Master
 



                      
Head Post Office
 



Place............................. 
 



Date..............................                       
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 


FORM 5
 


(See rule 8)
 


Form of 
register to be maintained by each cable operator
 


 


    Sl.                   Encrypted 
   channel/                Duration                          Date                  Month                  Year
 


    No.                         programme 
                      from to
 


 


     1                                  2 
                                      3                                  4                         
   5                         6
 


 
 


 


 
 


Signature of Cable Operator
</form><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 



1[Form 6
 


[See rule 11(2)]
 


(To be submitted in duplicate)
 


Form of 
application for grant of permission to multi-system operators to provide cable 
television network services with addressable system in any one or more Notified 
area
 


To
 


The Secretary
 


Ministry of Information &amp; Broadcasting,
 


‘A’ Wing, Shastri Bhawan,
 


New Delhi-110001.
 


                  Subject:—Application 
for grant of permission to multi-system operators to provide cable 
television network services with addressable system in any or more notified 
areas.
 


Sir,       
 


I hereby submit the following details for 
grant of permission.
 


         1. (a) Name of the Applicant 
(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of individuals)**
 


             (b) Age/Date of 
establishment/Date of Incorporation.
 


         2. (a) Nationality (for individual 
applicants/body of individuals) 
 


             (b)     By birth/domicile.
 


         3.  Details of payment of 
Processing Fee.
 


 
4.  Details of Registration as a Cable 
Operator
 


             (a) Name of the Post Office 
with which registered
 


             (b) Registration No./Validity 
up to
 


             (c) Copy of the Registration 
Certificate (enclose).
 


        (5)  Complete Postal Address with 
Telephone/Fax No./E-mail ID
 


             (a) Corporate Office/Head 
Office         
 


             (b) Registered Office
 


             (c) Regional Offices     

 


             (d) Address of Correspondence.
 


         6.  Name of authorized contact 
person, his designation and Telephone/Fax No./E-mail ID.
 


         7.  *Registration detail under 
Companies Act, 1956: Incorporation No. and Date (Attach a copy of Certificate 
of Incorporation and Memorandum and Article of Associations).
 


         8.  *Board of Directors (Attach 
list of Directors along with bio-data of each Director giving date of 
birth, place of birth, parentage, nationality, permanent address, residential 
address, official address, passport No. (if any), qualification, experience, 
etc.
 


         9.  *Attach list of key executives 
including CEO/MD along with defails as in 8 above.
 


       10.  *(i) Authorized Share Capital, 
(ii) Paid-up Share Capital, (iii) Net worth (enclose a copy of the audited 
Balance Sheet and Profit and Loss Account for the immediate preceding year and 
certificate of Net Worth on the basis of these documents by a Chartered 
Accountant).
 


       11.  Details of 
availability/arrangement of funds (sufficient proof to be enclosed).
 


       12.  (i) Present Area of Operation 
(if in more than one city, city-wise details to be given)
 


             (ii) CAS notified Area or Areas 
proposed to be covered by the applicant (if in more than one city, then 
city-wise details should be given).
 


       13.  No. of channels being provided 
in unencrypted form (own/broadcasters) (give names separately for own channels 
and broadcasters’ channels).
 


       14.  Other value added services being 
provided (details along with their copies of licenses).
 


       15.  Total No. of each of local cable 
operators and subscribers covered (attach list of local cable operators with 
their Telephone Nos./Fax Nos./E-mail IDs and the number of subscribers each of 
the cable operators has with him).
 


       16.  Details of past experience/field 
of activity.
 


       17.  Preparedness to supply and 
maintain adequate number of Set Top Boxes for the subscribers and installation 
of subscriber management system (give details to substantiate your claim 
including no. of Set Top Boxes already available/orders placed/network of 
authorized persons/agents to supply find provide after sales service).
 


       18.  Number of Agreements signed with 
broadcasters to supply their channels under CAS scheme (Give names of 
broadcasters and their channels for which agreements signed along with copies 
of agreements to substantiate your claim).
 


       19.  What arrangements have been 
made/proposed to be made to give wide publicity to CAS scheme in each of the 
notified areas, as approved by the Authority. (Give full details)
 


I/We……………………………………., the applicant(s) 
**(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of individuals) do 
hereby declare that the above 

; facts are correct in all respects.
 


I/We hereby undertake to abide by all the 
conditions/directions/orders that the Central Government or the Authority may 
lay down/issue for the smooth implementation and operation of CAS scheme in the 
notified areas.
 


 
 


                                    Signature of Applicant/Authorized person  

**(individual/firm/company/association  

of persons/body of individuals)
 



Place............................                                                                                          Name............................
 



Date............................                                                                                       Address............................
 


 
 


* To be given in case applicant is a 
Company/Firm.
 


** Score out the word or words which are not 
applicable].
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006).
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006, for rule 10 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006). Rule 10, before substitution, stood 
as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006, for rule 11 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006). Rule 11, before substitution, stood 
as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006, for rule 12 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006). Rule 12, before substitution, stood 
as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006, for rule 13 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006). Rule 13, before substitution, stood 
as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 452(E), dated 31st 
July, 2006, for rule 14 (w.e.f. 31-7-2006). Rule 14, before substitution, stood 
as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>