<act><tid>1785689</tid>
<title>THE UNIT TRUST OF INDIA (TRANSFER OF UNDERTAKING AND REPEAL) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to provide for the transfer and vesting of the undertaking 
 (excluding the specified undertaking) of the Unit Trust of India to 
the specified company to be formed and registered under the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year>, and the transfer and vesting of the spe ified undertaking 
of the Unit Trust of India in the Administrator and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto and also to repeal the Unit 
Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1969602</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1951009</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Unit  
Trust of India (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1593401</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day of 
October, <year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1235927</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1608550</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means a person or a body of persons appointed as 
Administrator under section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>911118</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1313381</tid>
<number>c</number>" bank" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (d) of 
section 2 of the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial 
Institutions Act, <year>1993</year> (51 of <year>1993</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1225632</tid>
<number>d</number>" Development Bank" means the Industrial Development Bank of India 
established under the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year> 
 (18 of <year>1964</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>174917</tid>
<number>e</number>" financial institution" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (h) of section 2 of the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and 
Financial Institutions Act, <year>1993</year> (51 of <year>1993</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>772480</tid>
<number>f</number>" Life Insurance Corporation of India" means the Life Insurance 
Corporation of India established under sub- section (1) of section 3 of 
the Life Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1956</year> (31 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1110044</tid>
<number>g</number>" Schedule" means Schedules I and II to this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>260325</tid>
<number>h</number>" specified company" means a company to be formed and registered 
under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) and whose entire capital is 
subscribed by such financial institutions or banks as may be specified 
by the Central Government, by notification i the Official Gazette, for 
the purpose of transfer and vesting of the undertaking;

</section>

<section><tid>1298952</tid>
<number>i</number>" specified undertaking" includes all business, assets, liabilities 
and properties of the Trust representing and relatable to the schemes 
and Development Reserve Fund specified in the Schedule I;

</section>

<section><tid>1494106</tid>
<number>j</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted under the 
State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1461330</tid>
<number>k</number>" Trust" means the Unit Trust of India established under 
sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> (52  
  of <year>1963</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1952878</tid>
<number>l</number>" undertaking" includes all business, assets, liabilities and 
properties of the Trust representing and relatable to the schemes and 
plans specified in the Schedule II;

</section>

<section><tid>1253342</tid>
<number>m</number>" unit" means a unit issued under a unit scheme made under section 
 21 of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> (52 of <year>1963</year>).
CHAP

TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE UNDERTAKING OF TRUST IN THE SPECIFIEDCOMPANY 
AND TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE SPECIFIED UNDERTAKING OF TRUSTIN THE 
ADMINISTRATOR

CHAPTER II

TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE UNDERTAKING OF TRUST IN THE SPECIFIED 
COMPANY AND TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE SPECIFIED UNDERTAKING OF TRUST 
IN THE ADMINISTRATOR




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1512504</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of initial capital.-
<section><tid>1986819</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the initial  
capital of the Trust, contributed by the Development Bank, the Life 
Insurance Corporation, the State Bank and the subsidiary banks and 
other institutions under sections 4 and 4A of the Unit Trust of India 
Act, <year>1963</year> (52 of <year>1963</year>), as it stood immediately before the 
commencement of this Act, shall stand transferred to, and vest in, the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1896909</tid>
<number>2</number>The initial capital contributed by the Development Bank, the Life 
Insurance Corporation, the State Bank and the subsidiary banks and 
other institutions shall be refunded, by the Central Government, to 
such extent as may be determined by it, having re ard to the book 
value, the assets and liabilities of the Trust.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1651224</tid>
<number> 4</number> Undertaking of Trust to vest in specified company and specified 
undertaking of Trust to vest in Administrator.-
<section><tid>1012003</tid>
<number>1</number>On such date as the  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint, there shall be transferred to, and vest in-

<subsection><tid>142781</tid>
<number>a</number>the specified company, the undertaking (excluding the specified  
  undertaking) of the Trust for such consideration and on such terms and 
conditions as may be mutually agreed upon between the Central 
Government and the subscribers to the capital of th specified company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>264452</tid>
<number>b</number>the Administrator, the specified undertaking of the Trust.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1968561</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government, as to whether any 
business, assets, liabilities or properties represent or relate to the 
undertaking or specified undertaking, shall be final:
Provided that any business, asset or property which is not represented 
or related to the undertaking or specified undertaking, shall vest in 
the Central Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1559260</tid>
<number> 5</number> General effect of vesting of undertaking or specified undertaking 
in specified company or Administrator.-
<section><tid>1673857</tid>
<number>1</number>The undertaking of the  
Trust which is transferred to, and which vest in, the specified 
company or the specified undertaking of the Trust, whic is transferred 
to, and vest in, the Administrator, as the case may be, under section 
4, shall be deemed to include all business, assets, rights, powers, 
authorities and privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, 
real and personal, corporeal a d incorporeal, in possession or 
reservation, present or contingent of whatever nature and wheresoever 
situate including lands, buildings, vehicles, cash balances, deposits, 
foreign currencies, disclosed and undisclosed reserves, reserve fund, 
special res rve fund, benevolent reserve fund, any other fund, stocks, 
investments, shares, bonds, debentures, security, management of any 
industrial concern, loans, advances and guarantees given to industrial 
concerns, tenancies, leases and book- debts nd all other rights and 
interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the 
appointed day in the ownership, possession or power of the Trust in 
relation to the undertaking or the specified undertaking, as the case 
may be, within or without India, all books of account, registers, 
records and documents relating thereto and shall also be deemed to 
include all borrowings, liabilities, units issued and obligations of 
whatever kind within or without India then sub isting of the Trust in 
relation to such undertaking or the specified undertaking, as the case 
may be.

</section>

<section><tid>921381</tid>
<number>2</number>All contracts, deeds, bonds, guarantees, powers- of- attorney, other 
instruments (including all units issued and unit schemes formulated by  
  the Trust) and working arrangements subsisting immediately before the 
appointed day and affecting the Trust hall cease to have effect or to 
be enforceable against the Trust and shall be of as full force and 
effect against or in favour of the specified company or the 
Administrator, as the case may be, in which the undertaking or 
specified undertaking has vested by virtue of this Act and enforceable 
as fully and effectually as if instead of the Trust, the specified 
company or the Administrator, as the case may be, had been named 
therein or had been a party thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>402489</tid>
<number>3</number>All unit schemes taken by the Board of the Trust immediately 
before the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been taken 
by the specified company or the Administrator, as the case may be, and 
all the units issued by the Trust under such sc eme shall be deemed to 
be the units issued by the specified company or the Administrator, as 
the case may be, and the income on such units shall be distributed and 
such units shall be redeemed or purchased by them in the same manner 
as would have been do e by the Trust had the undertaking or the 
specified undertaking not been transferred under section 4.

</section>

<section><tid>606108</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding or cause of action pending or existing immediately 
before the appointed day by or against the Trust may, as from the 
appointed day, be continued and enforced by or against the specified 
company or the Administrator, as the case may b, in which the 
undertaking or specified undertaking has vested by virtue of this Act 
as it might have been enforced by or against the Trust if this Act had 
not been enacted and shall cease to be enforceable by or against the 
Trust.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1953831</tid>
<number> 6</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of 
Trust.-
<section><tid>546019</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer or other employee of the Trust (except a   
  trustee of the Board, the Chairman and executive trustee) serving in 
the employment immediately before the appointed day shall b come, as 
from the appointed day, an officer or, as the case may be, other 
employee of the specified company and shall hold his office or service 
therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration, upon the same 
terms and conditions, with the same oblig tions and with the same 
rights and privileges as to leave, leave fare concession, welfare 
scheme, medical benefit scheme, insurance, provident fund, other 
funds, retirement, voluntary retirement, gratuity and other benefits 
as he would have held und r the Trust if its undertaking had not 
vested in the specified company and shall continue to do so as an 
officer or, as the case may be, other employee of the specified 
company or until the expiry of a period of six months from the 
appointed da if such officer or other employee opts not to continue to 
be the officer or other employee of the specified company within such 
period.

</section>

<section><tid>1105691</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator, in consultation with the specified company, may 
requisition, the services of such officers or other employees as it 
may deem fit, on such terms and conditions which may be mutually 
agreed upon between the Administrator and the spec fied company.

</section>

<section><tid>1910620</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an officer or other employee of the Trust opts under 
sub- section (1) not to be in employment or service of the specified 
company, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to have 
resigned.

</section>

<section><tid>221367</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
transfer of the services of any officer or other employee of the Trust 
to the specified company shall not entitl such officer or other 
employee to any compensation under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1937491</tid>
<number>5</number>The officers and other employees who have retired before the 
appointed day from the service of the Trust and are entitled to any 
benefits, rights or privileges shall be entitled to receive the same 
benefits, rights or privileges from the specified co pany.

</section>

<section><tid>1297331</tid>
<number>6</number>The trust of the provident fund or the gratuity fund of the Unit 
Trust of India and any other bodies created for the welfare of 
officers or other employees would continue to discharge their 
functions in the specified company as was being done hithert in the 
Unit Trust of India and any tax exemption granted to the provident 
fund or the gratuity fund would continue to be applied to the 
specified company.

</section>

<section><tid>103465</tid>
<number>7</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or in any other law for the time being in force 
or in the regulations of the Unit Trust of India, the Chairman, the 
trustees, executive trustee or any other pers n entitled to manage the 
whole or substantial part of the business and affairs of the Trust 
shall not be entitled to any compensation against the Trust for the 
loss of office or for the premature termination of any contract of 
management entered into by im with the Trust.
CHAP

APPOINTMENT OF ADMINISTRATOR TO MANAGE THE SPECIFIED UNDERTAKING OFTHE TRUST

CHAPTER III

APPOINTMENT OF ADMINISTRATOR TO MANAGE THE SPECIFIED UNDERTAKING OF 
THE TRUST




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1417302</tid>
<number> 7</number> Appointment of Administrator to manage specified undertaking.-
<section><tid>504059</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, on and from the appointed day, appoint a 
person or a body of persons, as the" Administrator of the specified 
undertaking of the Unit Trust of India" for th purpose of taking over 
the administration thereof and the Administrator shall carry on the 
management of the specified undertaking of the Trust for and on behalf 
of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>912169</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions (including  
directions as to initiating, defending or continuing any legal 
  proceedings before any court, tribunal or other authority) to the 
Administrator as to his powers and functions as that Governme t may 
deem desirable and the Administrator may apply to the Central 
Government at any time for instructions as to the manner in which he 
shall conduct the management of the specified undertaking or in 
relation to any matter arising in the course of such anagement.

</section>

<section><tid>1544804</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and the Schemes made 
thereunder and the control of the Central Government, the 
Administrator shall be entitled, notwithstanding anything contained in 
any other law for the time being in force, to exercise, n relation to 
the management of the specified undertaking, the powers specified 
under section 10 including powers to dispose of any property or assets 
of such specified undertaking whether such powers are derived under 
any law for the time being in force

</section>

<section><tid>1194780</tid>
<number>4</number>Every person having possession, custody or control of any property 
forming part of the specified undertaking of the Trust shall deliver 
forthwith such property to the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>269854</tid>
<number>5</number>Any person who, on the appointed day, has in his possession or 
under his control any books, papers or other documents relating to the 
specified undertaking, including the minutes book containing the 
resolutions of the persons in charge of the managem nt of the 
specified undertaking before the appointed day, the current cheque 
books relating to the specified undertaking, any letters, memoranda, 
notes or other communications between him and the Turst so far they 
relate to the specified undertaking sh ll, notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, be liable to 
account for the books, papers and other documents (including such  
  minutes book, letters, memoranda, notes or other communications) to 
the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>998116</tid>
<number>6</number>Any person in charge of the management of the specified 
undertaking immediately before the appointed day shall, within ten 
days from that day or within such further period as the Central 
complete inventory of all the properties and assets (including  
  particulars of book- debts and investments and belongings) forming part 
of the specified undertaking immediately before the appointed day and 
of all the liabilities and obligations of su Government may allow in 
this behalf, furnish to the Administrat r the h specified undertaking, 
in relation to its administration, subsisting immediately before that 
day, and also of all agreements relating to specified undertaking 
entered into by the Trust in relation to its administration and in 
force immediately before t at day.

</section>

<section><tid>1340707</tid>
<number>7</number>The Administrator shall receive from the funds of the specified 
undertaking such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>15428</tid>
<number> 8</number> Administrator to vacate office.-
<section><tid>889527</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator shall,  
immediately on redemption of all the schemes of the specified 
undertaking and the payment of entire amount to investors, shall 
vacate his office; but nothing in this sub- section shall e construed 
as prohibiting his appointment as a member of the Board of Advisers 
after vacation of his office as such.

</section>

<section><tid>1469451</tid>
<number>2</number>On the vacation of his office, the Administrator shall forthwith 
deliver, to the Central Government or any institution or officer 
specified by it, possession of all assets and properties representing 
and relatable to the specified undertaking which a e in his 
possession, custody and control on the date immediately preceding the 
date on which he vacates his office as the Administrator.
CHAP

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF ADMINISTRATOR

CHAPTER IV

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF ADMINISTRATOR




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1908560</tid>
<number> 9</number> Board of Advisers.-
<section><tid>1449008</tid>
<number>1</number>On such date as the Central Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a Board of Advisers 
to advise and assist the Administrator in carrying on the management 
of the specified undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>675522</tid>
<number>2</number>The composition, term of office of the Advisers, the fees and 
allowances and other conditions of appointment, disqualifications for 
being an Adviser, filling up of casual vacancy in the office of the 
Adviser, the meetings of the Board of Advisers, va ation and 
resignation of office of the Advisers, shall be such as may be 
specified in the Scheme made by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>377463</tid>
<number> 10</number> Powers and functions of Administrator.-
<section><tid>1582413</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act and the Scheme made thereunder, the 
Administrator may, on the advice of the Board of Advisers, transact 
any of the following kinds of business in India in relation to th 
specified undertaking only, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1188402</tid>
<number>a</number>selling and purchasing units of the schemes specified in Schedule 
I;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1147013</tid>
<number>b</number>investing in and acquiring, holding or disposing of securities and 
exercising and enforcing, all powers and rights incidental thereto 
including protection or realisation of such investment and the taking 
over of the administration of any property off red as security for 
such investment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>937704</tid>
<number>c</number>granting of loans and advances upon the security of any movable or 
immovable property or otherwise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>458258</tid>
<number>d</number>accepting, collecting, discounting, re- discounting, purchasing, 
selling or negotiating or otherwise dealing with, any bills of 
exchange, hundies, promissory notes, coupons, drafts, bill of lading, 
railway receipts, warehouse receipts, documents of ti le to goods, 
warrants, certificates, scrips and other mercantile instruments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492466</tid>
<number>e</number>purchasing, selling or issuing participation certificates in 
relation to any loan or advance granted by any public financial 
institution or scheduled bank or such other institution as may be 
specified by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>184355</tid>
<number>f</number>keeping money on deposit with companies or other bodies corporate, 
scheduled banks or such other institutions as may be specified by the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1926547</tid>
<number>g</number>formulating in relation to any unit scheme specified in Schedule 
I,-

<subsubsection><tid>1932710</tid>
<number>i</number>savings and life insurance plan or plans under which a person may 
acquire an interest in units in association with or as the agent of, 
the Life Insurance Corporation of India or the Central Government, but 
not including the life insurance business;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>950585</tid>
<number>ii</number>savings and insurance plan or plans under which a person may 
acquire an interest in units in association with, or as the agent of, 
the General Insurance Corporation but not including the general 
insurance business; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>926040</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other plan or plans, under which a person may acquire an 
interest in units;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866574</tid>
<number>h</number>acquiring immovable property or any interest therein, the 
development (including construction) and sale of such property and the 
rendering of financial and other assistance to any person for the 
acquisition of any immovable property or any interest t erein and for 
the development (including construction) of such property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>752108</tid>
<number>i</number>providing leasing and hire purchase finance to persons, companies, 
and other bodies corporate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>88604</tid>
<number>j</number>providing merchant banking and investment advisory services;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1878049</tid>
<number>k</number>extending investment or fund or port folio management services to 
persons resident outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865389</tid>
<number>l</number>opening of an account or the making of an agency arrangement with 
a bank incorporated outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>350399</tid>
<number>m</number>buying or selling of or entering into such other dealings in, 
foreign exchange, as may be necessary for the discharge of its 
functions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>886030</tid>
<number>n</number>doing any other kind of business connected with mobilisation of 
savings or investments which the Central Government may authorise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>650133</tid>
<number>o</number>generally doing all such acts and things as may be incidental to 
or consequential upon the discharge of its functions under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1723405</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator shall, on and after the appointed day, neither 
formulate any new scheme nor issue any new unit, whether related to 
the undertaking or the specified undertaking or otherwise.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1928963</tid>
<number> 11</number> Maintenance of accounts by Administrator.-
<section><tid>503608</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator  
shall maintain separate accounts of each of the specified undertaking 
asset possession whereof has been taken by him, and shall cause to be 
made therein entries of all receipts and expen iture in respect 
thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1550320</tid>
<number>2</number>The separate accounts under sub- section (1) shall be maintained in 
such form and in such manner as may be specified by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>678172</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall cause the accounts maintained under 
this section to be inspected and audited at such intervals and by such 
persons as may be specified by it.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>470132</tid>
<number>12</number>Concession, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to specified 
undertaking.- With effect from the appointed day, all fiscal and other 
concessions, licences, benefits, privileges and exemptions granted to 
the Trust in connection with the affairs and usiness of the specified 
undertaking of the Trust under any law for the time being in force 
shall be deemed to have been granted in relation to the specified 
undertaking.


</article>



<article><tid>1150910</tid>
<number> 13</number> Tax exemption or benefit to continue to have effect.-
<section><tid>235054</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>) or any other enactment for the time being in force relating to 
tax or income, profits or gains, no income- tax or an other tax shall 
be payable by the Administrator in relation to the specified 
undertaking for a period of five years computed from the appointed day 
in respect of any income, profits or gains derived, or any amount 
received in relation to the specified u dertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>183433</tid>
<number>2</number>The transfer and vesting of the undertaking or the specified 
undertaking in terms of section 4 shall not be construed as a transfer 
within the meaning of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) for the 
purposes of capital gains.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>371891</tid>
<number>14</number>Exemption from stamp duty.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year> (2 of <year>1899</year>), the transfer and vesting of 
the undertaking and the specified undertaking in terms of section 4 
shall not be liable to the payment of any stamp d ty under that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>875327</tid>
<number>15</number>Guarantee to be operative.- Any guarantee given for or in favour 
of the Trust with respect to any loan, lease, finance or other 
assistance shall continue to be operative in relation to the specified 
undertaking managed by the Administrator.


</article>



<article><tid>1497193</tid>
<number>16</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit or other legal 
proceedings shall lie against the Central Government or the 
Administrator, Board of Advisers or any of the officers or other 
employees of the Central Government for any damage caused or likely to 
be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1580400</tid>
<number>17</number>Shares, bonds, debentures and units to be deemed to be approved 
securities.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force, the shares, bonds, debentures and units of 
the specified undertaking shall be deemed to be ap roved securities 
for the purposes of the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>), the 
Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of <year>1938</year>) and the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> 
 (10 of <year>1949</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>665309</tid>
<number>18</number>Substitution in every Act, rule, regulation or notification by 
specified company or Administrator in place of Trust.- In every Act, 
rule, regulation or notification in force on the appointed day, for 
the words" Unit Trust of India", wherever they occu, the words, 
brackets and figures" specified company referred to in the Unit Trust 
of India (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2002</year>" or 
" Administrator of the specified undertaking of the Unit Trust of India 
referred to in the Unit Trust of India (Transfer of Undertaking and  
  Repeal) Act, <year>2002</year>", as the case may be, shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>160868</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power of Central Government to alter Schedules I and II.-
<section><tid>1506627</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, alter 
Schedules I and II.

</section>

<section><tid>859082</tid>
<number>2</number>Every alteration made by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session r in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
alteration, or both Houses agree that the alteratio should not be 
made, the alteration shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously don under that alteration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>757618</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power of Central Government to make Scheme.-
<section><tid>707640</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make a Scheme 
for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1761270</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, the said Scheme may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>941822</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the specified undertaking and schemes and 
assets and investments specified in Schedule I shall be managed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1877884</tid>
<number>b</number>the term of office of the Advisers, the fee and allowances and 
other conditions of appointment of the Advisers, disqualifications for 
being an Adviser, filling up of casual vacancy in the office of 
Adviser, the meetings of Board of Advisers, vacation and resignation 
of office of the Advisers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>301971</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner of payment of consideration for which the undertaking 
shall be transferred to the specified company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1420971</tid>
<number>d</number>the assets representing and relatable to the undertaking and the 
specified undertaking; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>907737</tid>
<number>e</number>such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as may be 
necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1425088</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Scheme made under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the Scheme or both Houses agree that the Scheme should 
not be made, the Scheme shall t in one session or in two or more 
successive se sions, and if, before ereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that Scheme.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>35511</tid>
<number> 21</number> Repeal and saving of Act 52 of <year>1963</year>.-
<section><tid>679862</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day,  
the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> shall stand repealed and the Board 
of trustees referred to in section 10 of the said Act (hereinafter  
  referred to as the repealed Act) shall stand dissol ed.

</section>

<section><tid>400512</tid>
<number>2</number>On the dissolution of the said Board, the person appointed as the 
Chairman of the Board and every other person appointed as the trustee 
and executive trustee and holding office as such immediately before 
such date shall vacate their respective office.

</section>

<section><tid>1403779</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken or 
purported to have been done or taken including any rule, regulation, 
notification, scheme, inspection, order or notice made or issued or 
any appointment, confirmation or declaration ma e or any permission, 
authorisation or exemption granted or any document or instrument 
executed or any direction given under the Act hereby repealed shall, 
in so far as it is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>394773</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> 
 (52 of <year>1963</year>), the Administrator shall, so far as may be, comply with 
the provisions of Chapter VI of the Act so repealed for any of the 
purposes related to the annual accounts and audit f the Trust.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1755449</tid>
<number>22</number>Act to have overriding effect.- The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any enactment other than this Act or in any instrument having 
effect by virtue of any enactment other than this A t.


</article>



<article><tid>1192214</tid>
<number>23</number>Application of other laws not barred.- The provisions of this Act 
shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of the provisions of 
any other law for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1150017</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>56801</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act s appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1113269</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after 
it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1818607</tid>
<number> 25</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1682068</tid>
<number>1</number>The Unit Trust of India (Transfer of   
  Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 5 of <year>2002</year>) is hereby 
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1193036</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Unit Trust of India (Transfer of  
  Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 5 of <year>2002</year>), anything 
done or any action taken under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the correspondi g provisions of this 
Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>