<act><title>THE BUREAU OF ENERGY EFFICIENCY APPOINTMENT AND 
TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL RULES, 
20031</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Bureau of Energy Efficiency Appointment and Terms and Conditions of 
Service of the Director-General Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Energy Conservation Act, 2001 (52 of 2001); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Director General means the Director-General of the Bureau appointed 
  under sub-section (1) of section 9 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Section means a section of the Act; and 
 </section><section><number>d</number> all other words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined 
  in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
  </section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Appointment of Director-General. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government shall appoint a person possessing the qualifications and experience 
laid down in sub-section (1) of section 9 as the Director-General. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The term of the office of Director-General shall be determined from the 
date on which he enters upon his office. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an officer of the Central Government or a State Government is 
appointed as the Director-General, his appointment, till the date he attains the 
age of superannuation, shall be deemed to have been made on deputation and after 
the date of superannuation, till he attains the age of sixty years, his 
appointment shall be deemed to have been made on short-term contract. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where a person working under a public sector undertaking or autonomous or 
statutory organization or from any private company or society or institution is 
appointed as the Director-General, his appointment shall be deemed to have been 
made on short-term contract. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Scale of pay and allowances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Director-General 
shall be entitled to draw a salary in the pay scale of Rs. 22400-525-24500: 
 Provided that where an officer of the Central or State Government is 
appointed as Director-General his pay being drawn from the parent Government 
shall be protected. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The pension and the leave salary contribution in respect of a person (2) 
The pension and the leave salary contribution in respect of a person appointed 
under sub-rule (4) of rule 3 shall be paid by the Bureau to the lending 
Government. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Director-General shall be entitled to dearness allowance appropriate 
to his pay at the rate admissible to a Group A' officer of the corresponding 
status in the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The other terms and conditions of the service of the Director-General for 
which the provisions have not been made in these rules, including entitlement of 
leave salary, leave travel concession, travelling allowance, medical facilities, 
shall be such as are admissible to a Group A' officer of the corresponding 
status in the Central Government. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Resignation and removal of Director-General. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Director-General may relinquish his office by giving in writing under his hand 
to the Central Government a notice of not less than ninety days. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Director-General may be removed from his office by the Central 
Government if he is subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in rule 6: 

 Provided that the Director-General shall, unless he is permitted by the 
Central Government to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold office 
until the expiry of ninety days from the date of receipt of such notice or 
within the said period of ninety days until a person duly appointed as his 
successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of term of office, 
whichever is the earliest. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Grounds for removal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may 
remove from office the Director-General who 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> is, or at any time has been, adjudged as an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> is, or becomes, of unsound mind or is so declared by a competent court; 
  or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as the 
  Director-General; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has been convicted of any offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
  Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
  prejudically his functions as the Director-General; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> has so abused his position as to render his continuation in office 
  detrimental to the public interest. </subsection>(2) The Director-General 
shall not be removed from service under the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 5 
unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Entitlement for staff car. </title>The Director-General shall be 
entitled to the use of staff car in accordance with the instructions issued from 
time to time by the Central Government. 


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>