<act><title>


The Life Insurance Corporation Rules, 19561</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Life Insurance Corporation Rules, 1956. 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules—  
 

2[
<section><number>i</number>    
    “chairman” means chairman appointed by the Central Government under 
    sub-section (1) of section 4;]
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    “section” means a section of the 
    Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    “Tribunal” means the tribunal 
    constituted by the notification of the Government of India in the Ministry 
    of Finance S.R.O. No. 1734, dated the 25th May, 1957].  
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Term of office of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An official member shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    non-official member shall hold office for a period of two years unless a 
    shorter period is specified in the order of appointment.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    outgoing member shall be eligible for re-appointment.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>3A</number> Office of the 
    Chairman.—The office of the Chairman shall be whole-time.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Registration of members.—The 
    Chairman or any member may, by writing under his hand addressed to the 
    Central Government, resign his office, and such resignation shall take 
    effect from the date on which it is accepted by the Central Government,
    

    1[or on the expiry of 
    thirty days from the date of resignation whichever is earlier.]  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Absence from meetings.—Any 
    member who absents himself from three consecutive meetings of the 
    Corporation without leave of the Corporation shall cease to be a member 
    thereof.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Removal of member.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may remove any member, who in the opinion of that 
    Government, has so flagrantly abused in any manner his position as a member 
    as to render his continuance as a member deterimental to the public 
    interest.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    member shall be removed under sub-rule (1) unless he has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of showing cause against his removal.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Casual vacancies among members.—In 
    the event of the occurrence of any vacancy in the office of a member by 
    reason of his death, resignation or removal, or otherwise, the Central 
    Government may appoint another person to act in his place.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Fees of members.—A 
    member not being a whole-time officer of the Corporation or an officer of 
    the Central Government shall be paid fees by the Corporation as follows:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for attending meetings of the 
    Corporation—Rs. 100 for each meeting;  
 

1[(b)    
    for attending meetings of any Committee constituted by the Corporation
    2[Rs. 
    50] for each meeting;]  
 


    3[***]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Travelling and daily allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every non-official member shall be entitled to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    travelling allowances for journey 
    performed by him in connection with the work of the Corporation at the rates 
    admissible to officers of the first grade in service of the Central 
    Government:  
 
Provided that every such member shall, 
    when travelling by rail, be entitled to travel by air-conditioned 
    accommodation if such accommodation is available;  
 

1[(b)    
    daily allowances for halts on duty at the rate of Rs. 30 per day.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    travelling and daily allowances of an official member shall be governed by 
    the rules applicable to him for journeys performed on official duty; and in 
    case such official member is not in the service of the Corporation, the 
    Corporation shall make necessary reimbursement to the authority employing 
    such official.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Apportionment of provident fund, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where all the employees of an insurer whose controlled business is 
    transferred to and vested in the Corporation under section 7 do not become 
    employees of the Corporation under section 11, all the moneys and other 
    assets belonging to the provident fund or superannuation fund or any other 
    like fund referred to in sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be apportioned 
    between the trustees of the fund and the Corporation in the following 
    manner, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the moneys and other assets of 
    any provident fund shall be apportioned in the proportion which the total of 
    the amounts lying to the credit of the persons becoming employees of the 
    Corporation bears to the total of the amounts lying to the credit of the 
    person who do not become employees of the Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the moneys and other assets of 
    any superannuation fund shall be apportioned in the proportion which the 
    liability of the fund in respect of the person becoming employees of the 
    Corporation bears to a similar liability in respect of the persons who do 
    not become employees of the Corporation, such liability to be ascertained on 
    such basis as may be determined by the Corporation and approved by the 
    Central Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the moneys and other assets of 
    any other like fund shall be apportioned in accordance with the principles 
    set out in clause (i) or clause (ii), as the case may be.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of sub-rule (1), shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to 
    the valuation and apportiontment of moneys and other assets belonging to any 
    provident fund or superannuation fund or any other like fund referred to in 
    clause (f) of sub-section (2) of section 10, as they apply in relation to 
    the apportionment and valuation of moneys and other assets belonging to a 
    provident fund, superannuation fund or any other like fund referred to in 
    sub-section (1) of section 8.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this rule the assets of a provident fund, superannuation 
    fund or any other like fund shall be valued at the market rates as on the 
    appointed day.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Transfer of service of existing employees of chief agents.—The 
    provisions of section 12, shall apply only in respect of the employees of a 
    chief agent of an insurer who was, under the terms of his contract with the 
    insurer, require to render the following services to the policy-holders, 
    namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    collection of premium, from the 
    policy-holders in respect of policies secured through his insurance agents 
    in the area for which he was appointed chief agent; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    issuing of final (pukka) 
    receipts for the premiums so collected.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12</number> Reference to the 
    Tribunal, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the amount of compensation offered under sub-section (2) of section 16 
    is not acceptable to an insurer, or where the compensation offered under 
    section 36 is not acceptable to a chief agent or a special agent, the 
    insurer, the chief agent or the special agent, as the case may be, may, for 
    the purpose of having the matter referred to the Tribunal, apply to the 
    Corporation along with the documents specified, if any, in this behalf by 
    the Tribunal in regulations made by it under section 17 (in this rule 
    referred to as the regulation)—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in cases where the compensation 
    was offered before the 1st day of November, 1964, not later than 31st day of 
    January, 1965, or, if the applicant is an insurer to whom compensation is 
    payable under Part B of the First Schedule to the Act, not later than the 
    31st day of April, 1965;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in all other cases within three 
    months from the date on which the compensation is offered or, if the 
    applicant is an insurer to whom compensation is payable under Part B of the 
    First Schedule to the Act, within six months from the date on which the 
    compensation is offered.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Corporation shall within three months of the date of receipt of an 
    application under sub-rule (1) refer the matter to the Tribunal for decision 
    alongwith a written statement and other documents specified, if any, by the 
    Tribunal in the regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) 
    Where an application under sub-rule (1), is made after the expiry of the 
    period specified therefor in that sub-rule, the Corporation shall, 
    notwithstanding expiration of the said period, refer the matter within three 
    months of the date of receipt of the application to the Tribunal for 
    decision along with a written statement and other documents specified, if 
    any, in the regulations.  
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The 
    Tribunal may admit reference made under clause (i) if the applicant 
    satisfies the Tribunal that he had sufficient cause for not making the 
    application to the Corporation within the period specified therefor in 
    sub-rule (1).  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> An 
    application to the Tribunal under section 15, or a reference to the 
    Tribunal, other than reference referred to in sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3), 
    may be made—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in cases where the cause of 
    action arose before the 1st day of November, 1964, not later than 31st day 
    of January, 1965,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in all other cases, within a 
    period of three months from the date on which the cause of action arose:  
 
Provided that 
    the Tribunal may admit an application or a reference other than reference to 
    in sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) after the expiry of the relevant period 
    referred to clause (a) or clause (b) if the persons making the application 
    or reference satisfies the Tribunal that there was sufficient cause for not 
    making it within that period.]
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12A</number> Jurisdiction of 
    Tribunal.—The 
    tribunal may exercise jurisdiction in the whole of India and shall have 
    power to decide or determine all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    any question whether of title or 
    of liability or of any nature whatsoever in relation to the assets and 
    liabilities pertaining to the controlled business of the insurer transferred 
    to and vested in the Corporation;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    any question under section 10 or 
    under any rules made thereunder whether any property is or was held or used 
    by a composite insurer for the purposes of his controlled business;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    every application made under 
    section 15 and all claims outstanding in respect of any transaction which 
    may be the subject-matter of any such application determined in favour of 
    the Corporation;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    all claims for compensation 
    payable under the Act to insurer whose controlled business has been 
    transferred to and vested in the Corporation; and all matters connected with 
    the determination, payment and distribution of such compensation;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    all claims for compensation 
    payable under the Act to chief agents or special agents for contracts 
    terminated under section 36; and all matters connected with the termination, 
    payment and distribution of such compensation;  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    such supplemental, incidental or 
    consequential matters which the Tribunal may deem it expedient or necessary 
    to decide or determine for the purpose of securing that the jurisdiction 
    vested in it under the Act and in respect of matters referred to above is 
    fully and effectively exercised.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Compensation.—The 
    compensation payable under the Act shall be paid in cash.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Employees and Agents Relations Committee.—The 
    representatives of the Corporation on the Employees and Agents Relations 
    Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of section 22 of the Act for 
    each zonal office at the Corporation and the representatives of the 
    employees and agents on such Committee shall be nominated by the 
    Corporation.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Term of office of members of Employees and Agents Relations Committee.—A 
    member of an Employee and Agents Relations Committee shall hold office for a 
    period of two years but shall be eligible for being renominated.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Casual vacancies in Employees and Agents Relations Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any casual vacancy occurs in the office of a member of an Employees and 
    Agents Relations Committee by death or resignation of such member or 
    otherwise, the Corporation shall as soon as may be after the occurrence of 
    the vacancy take immediate steps to fill the vacancy.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every member appointed to fill a casual vacancy of such Committee shall 
    continue in office for the unexpired term of his predecessor.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Report.—The 
    Annual report to be submitted by the Corporation to the Central Government 
    under section 27 of the Act regarding its activities during the previous 
    financial year shall be in such form as the Central Government may, from 
    time to time, direct, and shall inter alia contain particulars in 
    respect of the following matters, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the extent of the new business;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the total amount of business in 
    force;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the total amount of claims;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    nature of investment; and  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    the accounts.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Allocation of paid-up capital of composite insurer.—For 
    the purposes of the Explanation to sub-section (2) of section 7 and 
    of clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 10 of the Act, the part of the 
    paid-up capital, as the case may be, allocated to the controlled business of 
    an insurer shall be determined in the manner following, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    in respect of an insurer entitled 
    to receive compensation under Part A of the First Schedule to the Act, the 
    paid-up capital allocable to the controlled business shall be that 
    proportion of the total paid-up capital of the insurer which the annual 
    average of the profits from the controlled business during the period 
    covered by the relevant actuarial investigation bears to the total of such 
    annual average of profits plus two times the annual average of the profits 
    from other business during that period:  
 
Provided that the paid-up capital 
    allocable to the controlled business shall not in any case exceed a sum of 
    rupees six lakhs;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    in respect of an insurer 
    entitled to compensation under Part B of the First Schedule to the Act, the 
    paid-up capital allocable to the controlled business shall be the excess, if 
    any, of the amount of liabilities of the insurer appertaining to such 
    business in existence on the 19th day of January, 1956, computed as at that 
    date in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 4 of Part B of the First 
    Schedule to the Act over the value of the assets of the insurer appertaining 
    to his controlled business (excluding the paid-up capital allocable to 
    controlled business) in existence on the 19th day of January, 1956, computed 
    as at the date in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 3 of Part B of 
    the First Schedule to the Act.  
 

    Explanation 1.—“Profits 
    from controlled business” means the share of the surplus allocated to the 
    shareholder as disclosed in the abstracts prepared in accordance with Part 
    II of the Fourth Schedule to the Insurance Act in respect of the relevant 
    actuarial investigations.  
 

    Explanation 2.—“Profits 
    from other business” means the total of the profits less losses transferred 
    to “Profit and Loss Account” from the fire, marine and miscellaneous 
    insurance revenue accounts prepared in accordance with Form F of the Third 
    Schedule of the Insurance Act.  
 

    Explanation 3.—“Relevant 
    Actuarial Investigations” means such minimum number of latest actuarial 
    investigations as at dates earlier than the 1st day of January, 1956 (not 
    being less than 2 in any case) would leave the period intervening between 
    the date as at which the actuarial investigation immediately preceding the 
    first of such investigations was made and the date at which the last of such 
    investigations was made and to be not less than four years.  
 

    Explanation 4.—Where 
    an insurer has allocated to shareholders more than 5 per cent. of any such 
    surplus as is referred to in Explanation 1, the insurer shall be deemed to 
    have allocated only 5 per cent. of surplus and where an insurer has not 
    allocated any such surplus to shareholders or has allocated to shareholders 
    less than 5 per cent. of any such surplus, the insurer shall be deemed to 
    have allocated 5 per cent. of the surplus.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Transfer of business of certain composite insurer to the Corporation.—Every 
    transfer by the Administrator under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of section 45 of the Act 
    shall be made in pursuance of an agreement between the Administrator and the 
    Corporation and no such agreement shall be entered into except with the 
    previous approval of the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Vesting of the management of the affairs of the insurer in the persons 
    entitled thereto.—As 
    soon as the transfer in terms of rule 19 is effected, the Administrator 
    shall by notice call upon the persons in charge of the management of the 
    insurer immediately prior to the appointment of the Administrator to take 
    charge of the management of any other kind of business not transferred to 
    and vested in the Corporation and upon such notice being given, such persons 
    shall take the management of that other kind of business.  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>