<act><tid>1546288</tid>
<title>THE ORIGINAL GAS COMPANY</title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1867</year>
[ 1st March, <year>1867</year>.]

An Act to empower the Oriental Gas Company Limited, to 
extend 
their operations to certain places in'[ the Provinces of India].

Preamble.- WHEREAS under or by virtue of Act No. V of <year>1857</year> 
 (to  
  confer certain power on the Oriental Gas Company, Limited), 
certain 
powers exercisable only in Calcutta and its environs were conferred 
on 
the Oriental Gas Company, Limited; and whereas it is expedient 
to 
empower the said Company to extend, with the previous sanction of 
the 
'[ Central Government], their operations to any other place in 
'[ the 
Provinces of India]; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>927813</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Interpretation clause.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1762124</tid>
<number>2</number>Power to extend Act 5 of <year>1857</year>.- The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend the said Act No. 
V of <year>1857</year>, to any place <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the territories which, immediately 
before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were composed in Part A States and Part 
C States]] other than Calcutta and its environs: Provided that, in 
every place to which the said Act shall be so extended, section 3 of 
the same Act shall be read as is after the words' Town of Calcutta', 
the name of the place to which the said act shall be so extended were 
substituted: sanction 7 or the same Act shall be read as if for the 
words and figures' Act xiv or <year>1856</year>', the following- words were 
substituted; (that is to say)' any law for the time being in force to 
provide for the conservancy and improvement of such place:' Section 22 
of the said Act shall be read, as if after the words' Joint Stock 
Companies' Act, <year>1856</year>', the following words were inserted; (that is  
  to say), the Indian Companies' Act, <year>1866</year>, or any other Statute or Act 
for the time being in force relating to Joint Stock Companies'; and as 
if for the expression' Supreme Court of Judicature at Fort William', 
the name of the highest Civil Court of appeal in such place were 
substituted; and as if for the expression the territories of the East 
India Company', the expression the States <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> were substituted.
------------


<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" British India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>, Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" in the Provinces" which has been 
subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" within the territories subject to such 
Govt.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" the 
States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" as defined in this Act" omitted by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>