<act><tid>1619388</tid>
<title>THE TRANSFER OF EVACUEE DEPOSITS ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 26th March, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to provide, in pursuance of an agreement with Pakistan, for the 
transfer to that country of certain deposits belonging to evacuees, 
the reception in India of similar deposits belonging to displaced 
persons, and matters connected therewith.

WHEREAS an agreement has been arrived at with Pakistan for the 
transfer to that country of certain deposits belonging to evacuees, 
the reception in India of similar deposits belonging to displaced 
persons, and matters connected therewith;

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--





<article><tid>1840119</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1712251</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Transfer of Evacuee Deposits Act, <year>1954</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1652975</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India, except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in] 
the States of Assam, West Bengal, Tripura, Manipur and Jammu and 
Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>524827</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of 
February, <year>1954</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>546213</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1093825</tid>
<number>a</number>" Custodian" means a Custodian of Deposits appointed 
under section 3, and includes an Assistant Custodian of 
Deposits;

</section>

<section><tid>957227</tid>
<number>b</number>" deposit" means--

<subsection><tid>1901203</tid>
<number>i</number>any movable property in the custody or under 
the control of any Civil or Revenue Court in respect of 
any proceedings before it; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1349701</tid>
<number>ii</number>any movable property under the 
superintendence or in the custody of a court of wards 
under any law for the time being in force, whether such 
movable property is in the actual custody of the court 
of wards, or in that of some other authority on its 
behalf; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>550379</tid>
<number>iii</number>any movable property in the custody or under 
the control of a manager;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and includes any securities, insurance policies and 
negotiable instruments in the custody or under the 
control of any such Civil or Revenue Court or under the 
superintendence or in the custody of such court of 
wards or in the custody or under the control of such 
manager.

Explanation I.--" Securities" include shares, 
scrips, stocks, bonds, debentures, debenture stocks or 
other marketable securities of a like nature in or of 
any body corporate and also Government securities.

Explanation II.-- Where any deposit in the custody 
or under the control of any Civil or Revenue Court or 
under the superintendence or in the custody of a court 
of wards or in the custody or under the control of the 
manager has vested in the Custodian of Evacuee Property 
as evacuee property, such deposit shall, for the 
purposes of this Act, be deemed to be in the custody or 
under the control of such Civil or Revenue Court or 
under the superintendence or in the custody of the 
court of wards or in the custody or under the control 
of the manager, as the case may be;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1254102</tid>
<number>c</number>" displaced person" means any person who, on account of 
the setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan 
or on account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances in any area now forming part of Pakistan, 
has, on or after the 1st day of March, <year>1947</year>, left, or 
been displaced from, his place of residence in such 
area and who has been subsequently residing in India;

</section>

<section><tid>1129120</tid>
<number>d</number>" evacuee" means any person who, on account of the 
setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan or on 
account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances, has, on or after the 1st day of March, 
<year>1947</year>, left any place in the territories to which this 
Act extends and who is not residing in any place 
forming part of Pakistan;

</section>

<section><tid>127307</tid>
<number>e</number>" manager" means the manager of an encumbered estate 
appointed under any law for the time being in force 
relating to encumbered estates;

</section>

<section><tid>247405</tid>
<number>f</number>" transferable deposit" means a deposit in which an 
evacuee has any right or interest, to the extent of 
that right or interest:

</section>

<section><tid>946538</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>101</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>355380</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appointment of custodian and Assistant Custodians of Deposits.

<section><tid>1613958</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official  
Gazette, appoint a Custodian of Deposits and as many Assistant 
Custodians of Deposits as may be necessary for the purpose of 
discharging the duties imposed upon the Custodian and Assistant 
Custodians by or under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>478434</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Custodian and 
Assistant Custodians of Deposits shall discharge the duties imposed on 
them by or under this Act under the general superintendence and 
control of the Central Government, and the Central Government may, by 
general or special order, provide for the distribution of work among 
them.

</section>

<section><tid>686018</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Assistant 
Custodians of Deposits shall discharge the duties imposed on them by 
or under this Act under the general superintendence and control of the 
Custodian.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1082364</tid>
<number> 4</number> Transfer of deposits in mass migration area.
<section><tid>1332939</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a Civil  
or Revenue Court or a court of wards situated in a mass migration area 
or the manager exercising jurisdiction in any such area is satisfied--

<subsection><tid>980465</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a Civil or Revenue Court other than a 
Civil Court exercising jurisdiction under the Guardians 
and Wards Act, <year>1890</year> (8 of <year>1890</year>) or the manager, that 
all the parties interested in a deposit are Muslims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1703852</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a Civil court exercising jurisdiction 
under the Guardians and Words Act, <year>1890</year> (8 of <year>1890</year>), 
that both the guardian and the minor interested in a 
deposit are Muslims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>721894</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a court of wards having under its 
superintendence or custody a deposit, that the ward is 
a Muslim;
the Civil or Revenue Court or the court of wards or the manager, as 
the case may be, shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of 
this Act, transfer the deposit along with the records relating 
thereto, to such authorized officer or authority in Pakistan as the 
Central Government may, by general or special order, specify in this 
behalf:

Provided that where, in the opinion of any such Civil or Revenue 
Court or the court of wards or the manager, any of the persons 
interested in a deposit is not an evacuee, the deposit shall not be 
transferred to Pakistan under this section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>265378</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Civil or Revenue Court and every court of wards and the 
manager shall, as soon as may be, send to the Custodian in such form 
as may be prescribed particulars of all deposits transferred to 
Pakistan under sub- section (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>102</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" mass migration 
area" means the territories <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> which immediately before the 1st 
November, <year>1956</year>, were] comprised in the following States or areas, 
namely:-


<subsection><tid>1761989</tid>
<number>i</number>the State of Punjab;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1340832</tid>
<number>ii</number>the State of Patiala and East Punjab States Union;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1403751</tid>
<number>iii</number>the State of Ajmer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>446453</tid>
<number>iv</number>the State of Delhi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1295994</tid>
<number>v</number>the State of Himachal Pradesh;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720051</tid>
<number>vi</number>the districts of Alwar, Bharatpur and Bikaner in the 
State or Rajasthan, and the districts of Saharanpur, 
Dehra Dun, Meerut and Muzaffarnagar in the State of 
Uttar Pradesh.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1646979</tid>
<number> 5</number> Procedure for transfer of certain other deposits to Pakistan.

<section><tid>1810920</tid>
<number>1</number>Where either on a request received in this behalf from any such  
officer or authority in Pakistan as may be specified in this behalf by 
the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, or on 
any other information available to him, the Custodian is of opinion 
that there is a transferable deposit to which the provisions of 
section 4 do not apply, he may send for the record relating thereto 
from any Court or other authority and inspect the same.

</section>

<section><tid>1632393</tid>
<number>2</number>If, after making any such inspection as is referred to in 
sub- section (1) and after making such further inquiry into the matter 
as may be prescribed, the Custodian is satisfied that the deposit is a 
transferable deposit within the meaning of this Act, he may, by order, 
direct that the deposit shall be transferred to such authorized 
officer or authority in Pakistan as the Central Government may, by 
general or special order, specify in this behalf, and any Court or 
other authority holding in its custody or under its control any such 
deposit shall comply with the direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1725424</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where in 
respect of any deposit the extent of the right or interest of an 
evacuee in such deposit is not easily ascertainable or, having regard 
to the nature of the deposit, it is in the opinion of the Custodian 
not practicable to separate the right or interest of the evacuee from 
the right or interest of other persons in such deposit, the Custodian 
shall not transfer any part of the deposit to Pakistan.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>460388</tid>
<number> 6</number> Transfer of records relating to transferable deposit.
<section><tid>659860</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a transferable deposit is directed to be transferred to Pakistan 
under the provisions of section 5, the Custodian may send the record 
relating to the deposit, or, if it is expedient so to do, only a 
certified copy of such part of the record as, in the opinion of the 
Custodian, is material to the case to the Government of Pakistan
<pagefootnote><pagenum>103</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or to such officer or authority to whom or to which the deposit has 
been directed to be transferred.


</section>

<section><tid>1062394</tid>
<number>2</number>If a certified copy only is sent in pursuance of sub- section 
 (1), the original record, together with a copy of the order of the 
Custodian under section 5, shall be returned to the Court or other 
authority from which it was obtained.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220471</tid>
<number>7</number>Power of Court or Custodian to convert deposits into money 
before transmission to Pakistan. Where the transfer to Pakistan of any 
article which is a transferable deposit is prohibited under any law 
for the time being in force, it shall be lawful for a Civil or a 
Revenue Court, or the court of wards or the manager or the Custodian, 
as the case may be, to convert such article into money in such manner 
as may be prescribed, and upon such conversion the provisions of this 
Act shall apply to the proceeds thereof as they apply to a 
transferable deposit.


</article>



<article><tid>1507385</tid>
<number>8</number>Cesser of jurisdiction in respect of deposits transferred. 
Upon the transfer of any transferable deposit under section 4 or in 
pursuance of an order of the Custodian under section 5, all Courts and 
authorities in India shall, save as otherwise provided in this Act. 
cease to have or exercise any jurisdiction in relation to the deposit 
so transferred in so far as it relates to the right or interest of any 
evacuee in the deposit.


</article>



<article><tid>530208</tid>
<number> 9</number> Reception in India of deposits transferred from Pakistan.
<section><tid>232159</tid>
<number>1</number> 
It shall be lawful for the Custodian to receive and hold in his 
custody any deposit transferred by any such officer or authority in 
Pakistan as may be specified by the Central Government by general or 
special order as being a deposit belonging to any displaced person in 
India.

</section>

<section><tid>902556</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of any such deposit as it referred to in sub- 
section (1), the Custodian shall cause notice thereof to be given in 
such manner as may be prescribed to all persons who may, in his 
opinion, be interested in the deposit, and after giving a reasonable 
opportunity to such persons to be heard in the matter and after 
inspecting any such record relating to the deposit as may be 
transferred from Pakistan, dispose of the deposit in the manner 
following, that is to say--

<subsection><tid>500499</tid>
<number>a</number>if there is only one claimant entitled to the deposit 
or if all the claimants, where there are more than one, 
appear before the Custodian and there is no dispute as 
to the distribution of the deposit, pay the deposit to 
that claimant or, as the case may be, distribute the 
deposit among the claimants in the manner agreed to by 
them;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>104</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>369578</tid>
<number>b</number>if all the claimants do not appear before the Custodian 
or if all such claimants appear but do not agree as to 
the person or persons entitled to the deposit or to the 
manner of its distribution among them, the Custodian 
shall forward the deposit and the records relating 
thereto to the principal Civil court of original 
jurisdiction within whose jurisdiction all, or the 
largest number of claimants, reside, or where the 
claimants residing within the jurisdiction of two or 
more Courts are equal in number, to the Court which, in 
the opinion of the Custodian, would best serve the 
convenience of claimants.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1604690</tid>
<number>3</number>The Court to which a deposit and any record relating thereto 
are forwarded under sub- section (2) shall proceed to deal with the 
matter as if the deposit had been made in compliance with an order 
made by it in a proceeding before it and, after making such further 
inquiry into the matter as it thinks fit, award the deposit to or 
distribute it among the person or persons who in its opinion is or are 
entitled thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1039658</tid>
<number>4</number>An appeal shall lie from every order passed by any Court 
under sub- section (3) to the Court authorized to hear appeals from the 
decisions of such Court if the amount or value of the subject matter 
of the claim made in the appeal exceeds two thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>25549</tid>
<number>5</number>The disposal of any deposit in accordance with the provisions 
of this section shall discharge the Custodian from any liability to 
any person in respect of the deposit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>63345</tid>
<number> 10</number> Powers of custodian. The Custodian shall have all the powers 
vested in a Civil Court under the Code of civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>) when trying a suit in respect of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>650502</tid>
<number>a</number>discovery and inspection;

</section>

<section><tid>1281644</tid>
<number>b</number>enforcing the attendance of witnesses and requiring the 
deposit of their expenses;

</section>

<section><tid>235638</tid>
<number>c</number>compelling the production of documents;

</section>

<section><tid>1642473</tid>
<number>d</number>examining witnesses on oath;

</section>

<section><tid>1666073</tid>
<number>e</number>reception of evidence on affidavits;

</section>

<section><tid>1510719</tid>
<number>f</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;
and may summon and examine suo motu any person whose evidence appears 
to him to be material; and shall be deemed to be a Civil Court within 
the meaning of section 480 and section 482 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year>. (5 of <year>1898</year>)


<pagefootnote><pagenum>105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- For the purpose of enforcing the attendance of 
witnesses, the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Custodian shall 
be the limits for which he is appointed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>369774</tid>
<number>11</number>Jurisdiction or Civil Courts barred. No Civil Court shall 
have jurisdiction to question the legality of any action taken or of 
any decision given by the Custodian in connection with the transfer of 
any transferable deposit or with the disposal of any deposit received 
from Pakistan as belonging to a displaced person.


</article>



<article><tid>535793</tid>
<number>12</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any Custodian or any other person in respect of anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1507584</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1114742</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>616350</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may--

<subsection><tid>1962516</tid>
<number>a</number>define the terms and conditions of service of the 
Custodian and Assistant Custodians and the local limits 
of their respective jurisdictions and the distribution 
of work among them or the transfer of work from one to 
another of the Custodian and Assistant Custodians;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1762416</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which deposits and records relating 
thereto may be transferred to Pakistan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>363456</tid>
<number>c</number>prescribe the manner in which any inquiry under this 
Act may be held;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>604399</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which a transferable deposit may be 
converted into money under section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>391778</tid>
<number>e</number>specify the persons to whom and the manner in which 
notices of any proceedings under this Act shall be 
given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>977674</tid>
<number>f</number>prescribe the manner in which certified copies of any 
record may be prepared under this Act and the fees, if 
any, which may be levied in respect of such certified 
copies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131495</tid>
<number>g</number>prescribe the form in which any application may be made 
to the Custodian under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>642769</tid>
<number>14</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 6 of <year>1954</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2003</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See Gazette of India, <year>1955</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. S, p.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>