<act><tid>1483303</tid>
<title>THE DELHI HIGH COURT ACT, <year>1966</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1966</year> AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE CONSTITUTION OF A HIGH COURT 
FOR THE UNION TER
[ 5th September, <year>1966</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>557055</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1117450</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Delhi High Court Act, <year>1966</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1746412</tid>
<number>2</number>Section 17 shall come into force on such date 1 as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint; and the remaining provisions of this Act shall come into 
force at once.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>164038</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>418281</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date appointed under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>678484</tid>
<number>b</number>" notified order" means order notified in the Official 
Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>743985</tid>
<number> 3</number> High Court.
<section><tid>901588</tid>
<number>1</number>As from such date 2 as the Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be 
a High Court for the Union territory of Delhi (hereinafter referred to  
  as the High Court of Delhi).

</section>

<section><tid>213064</tid>
<number>2</number>The principal seat of the High Court of Delhi shall be at 
Delhi or at such other place as the President may, by notified order, 
appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>300987</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
Judges and Division Courts of the High Court of Delhi may sit at such 
other place or places other than its principal seat as the Chief 
Justice may, with the approval of the President, appoint.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>70421</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Salaries and allowances of Judges to be expenditure 
charged on Consolidated Fund of India. Expenditure in respect of the 
salaries and allowances of Judges of the High Court of Delhi shall be 
expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of India.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>134</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 5- <year>1967</year>, vide G. S. R. 508, dated 11- 4- <year>1967</year>, Gazette of India, 
Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 563.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 31st October, <year>1966</year>, vide Notification No. S. O. 3273, dated 27- 
10- <year>1966</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 2996.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1969</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1969</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1028712</tid>
<number> 4</number> Exceptions and modifications subject to which the provisions of 
Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution apply to the High Court of 
Delhi.
<section><tid>1899279</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution  
shall, in their application to the High Court of Delhi, have effect 
subject to the following exceptions and modifications, namely:-

<subsection><tid>747855</tid>
<number>a</number>in article 217, the words" the Governor of the State" 
shall be omitted and in relation to appointments to be made 
under sub- section (2), that article shall be construed as if 
the words" and, in the case of appointment of a Judge other 
than the Chief Justice, the Chief Justice of the High Court," 
had also been omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1293993</tid>
<number>b</number>in article 219, the reference to the Governor of the 
State, and in the proviso to clause (3) of article 227, the 
reference to the Governor, shall be construed as a reference 
to the administrator of the Union territory of Delhi

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>717618</tid>
<number>c</number>the provisions of article 225 shall not apply

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>935469</tid>
<number>d</number>in article 229,-

<subsubsection><tid>1365313</tid>
<number>i</number>the references to the Governor of the State shall be 
construed as references to the administrator of the 
Union territory of Delhi;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1210508</tid>
<number>ii</number>the references to the State Public Service Com- 
mission, the Legislature of the State and the Consoli- 
dated Fund of the State shall be construed, 
respectively, as references to the Union Public Service 
Commission, Parliament and the Consolidated Fund of 
India;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>783216</tid>
<number>e</number>the provisions of article 230 shall apply subject to 
the modifications that-

<subsubsection><tid>1226433</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (1) thereof, for the words" High Court in 
both the places where they occur, the words" High Court 
for a Union territory" and for the words" any Union 
territory", the words" any other Union territory" 
shall be substituted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>405861</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (2) thereof, the following clause shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" (2) Where the High Court for a Union territory 
exercises jurisdiction in relation to another Union 
territory, the reference in article 227 to the 
administrator of the Union territory of Delhi 
shall, in relation to any rules, forms or tables 
for subordinate courts in that other Union 
territory, be construed as a reference to the admi- 
nistrator of that other Union territory."


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1982329</tid>
<number>2</number>Between the coming into force of this section and the 
appointed day, the President may, after consultation with the Chief 
Justice of India, appoint the Chief Justice of the High Court of Delhi 
and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>135</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as many other Judges of the said High Court as he thinks fit, and an 
appointments so made shall take effect as from the appointed day.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>2256</tid>
<number> 5</number> Jurisdiction of High Court.
<section><tid>909083</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Court of Delhi  
shall have, in respect of the territories for the time being included 
in the Union territory of Delhi all such original, appellate and other 
jurisdiction as, under the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day, is exercisable in respect of the said territories by 
the High Court of Punjab.

</section>

<section><tid>1943756</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, the High Court of Delhi shall also have in respect of 
the said territories ordinary original civil jurisdiction in every 
suit the value of which exceeds <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> rupees five lakhs].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>669643</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to enrol legal practitioners, etc.
<section><tid>775439</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Court  
of Delhi shall have like powers to approve, admit, enrol, remove and 
suspend legal practitioners, and to make rules with respect to them, 
as are, under the law in force immediately before the appointed day 
exercisable by the High Court of Punjab.

</section>

<section><tid>940691</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of audience in the High Court of Delhi shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles, as, immediately 
before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of 
audience in the High Court of Punjab:
Provided that subject to any rule made or direction given by the 
High Court of Delhi in the exercise of the powers conferred by this 
section, any person who immediately before the appointed day is an 
advocate entitled to practise or an attorney entitled to act in the 
High Court of Punjab shall be recognised as an advocate or an attorney 
entitled to practise or act, as the case may be, in the High Court of 
Delhi.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>613216</tid>
<number>7</number>Practice and procedure in the High Court of Delhi. Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation 
to the High Court of Delhi and accordingly the High Court of Delhi 
shall have all such powers to make rules and orders with respect to 
practice and procedure as are immediately before the appointed day 
exercisable by the High Court of Punjab and shall also have powers to 
make rules and orders with respect to practice and procedure for the 
exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction:
Provided that any rules or orders which are in force immediately 
before the appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the 
High Court of Punjab shall, until varied or revoked by rules or


<pagefootnote><pagenum>136</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1969</year> s. 3, for" twenty- five thousand rupees" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1969</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1980</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1980</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1991</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 9- 11- <year>1992</year>)





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

orders made by the High Court of Delhi, apply with the necessary 
modifications in relation to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Delhi as if made by that High Court.



</article>



<article><tid>1063118</tid>
<number>8</number>Custody of the Seal of the High Court of Delhi. The law in 
force immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody 
of the Seal of the High Court of Punjab shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the Seal of the 
High Court of Delhi.


</article>



<article><tid>804998</tid>
<number>9</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of 
Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with respect to 
the form of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the 
High Court of Delhi.


</article>



<article><tid>1617497</tid>
<number> 10</number> Powers of Judges.
<section><tid>823366</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a single Judge of the High Court  
of Delhi exercises ordinary original civil jurisdiction conferred by 
sub- section (2) of section 5 on that Court, an appeal shall lie from 
the judgment of the single Judge to a Division Court of that High 
Court.

</section>

<section><tid>503805</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to the powers of the 
Chief Justice, single Judges and Division Courts of the High Court of 
Punjab and with respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of 
those powers shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in 
relation to the High Court of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>747268</tid>
<number>11</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Punjab and the Judges and 
Division Courts thereof shall, with the necessary modifications, apply 
in relation to the High Court of Delhi.


</article>



<article><tid>1551630</tid>
<number> 12</number> Transfer of proceedings from the High Court of Punjab to the 
High Court of Delhi.
<section><tid>1587945</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided, the High Court  
of Punjab shall, as from the appointed day, have no jurisdiction in 
respect of the Union territory of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>55838</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Punjab imme- 
diately before the appointed day as are certified, whether before or 
after that day, by the Chief Justice of that High Court having regard 
to the place of accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances 
to be proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High 
Court of Delhi, shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the High Court of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>1175188</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (l) and 
 (2) of this section and in section 5, but save as hereinafter 
provided,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>137</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the High Court of Punjab shall have, and the High Court of Delhi shall 
not have, jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of, appeals 
applications for leave to appeal including leave to appeal to the 
Supreme Court, applications for review and other proceedings where any 
such proceedings seek any relief in respect of any order passe by the 
High Court of Punjab before the appointed day:

Provided that if after any, such proceedings have been 
entertained by the High Court of Punjab, it appears to the Chief 
Justice of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the 
High Court of Delhi, he shall order that they shall be so transferred, 
and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1742469</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court of Punjab-

<subsection><tid>942078</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day, in any proceedings 
transferred to the High Court of Delhi by virtue of sub- 
section (2);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1358551</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High 
Court of Punjab retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- 
section (3),
shall for all purposes have effect, not only as an order of the High 
Court of Punjab, but also as an order made by the High Court of Delhi.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1675640</tid>
<number>13</number>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to 
the High Court of Delhi. Any person who, immediately before the 
appointed day, is an advocate entitled to practise or an attorney 
entitled to act, in the High Court of Punjab, and was authorised to 
appear or to act in any proceedings transferred from that High Court 
to the High Court of Delhi under section 12, shall have the right to 
appear or to act, as the case may be, in the High Court of Delhi in 
relation to those proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>251953</tid>
<number> 14</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 12 and 17,-
<section><tid>629810</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a 
court until that court has disposed of all issues 
between the parties, including any issues with respect 
to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings and 
shall include appeals, applications for leave to appeal 
to the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions 
for revision and petitions for writs;

</section>

<section><tid>718867</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or Division Court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a court or a 
Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>138</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>62125</tid>
<number>15</number>Savings. Save as provided in section 4, nothing in this Act 
shall affect the application to the High Court of Delhi of any 
provisions of the Constitution, and this Act shall have effect subject 
to any provision that may be made on or after the appointed day with 
respect to that High Court by any Legislature or other authority 
having power to make such provision.


</article>



<article><tid>472207</tid>
<number>16</number>Pending proceedings before subordinate courts in Delhi. All 
proceedings pending immediately before the appointed day in any 
subordinate court in the Union territory of Delhi in or in relation to 
any such civil suit as is referred to in sub- section (2) of section 5 
shall on that day stand transferred to the High Court of Delhi which 
shall proceed to try, hear and determine the matter as if it had been 
pending therein.


</article>



<article><tid>284438</tid>
<number> 17</number> Extension of the jurisdiction of the High Court of Delhi.

<section><tid>1239419</tid>
<number>1</number>As from such date 1 as the Central Government may, by notification  
in the Official Gazette, appoint (hereinafter referred to as the  
  prescribed date), the jurisdiction of the High Court of Delhi shall 
extend to the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>866832</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the prescribed date the Court of the Judicial Com- 
missioner for Himachal Pradesh shall cease to function and is hereby 
abolished:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prejudice or 
affect the continued operation of any notice served, injunction 
issued, direction given, or proceedings taken before the prescribed 
date by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh 
abolished by this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>1517223</tid>
<number>3</number>The High Court of Delhi shall have, in respect of the terri- 
tories for the time being included in the Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh,--

<subsection><tid>1921411</tid>
<number>a</number>all such original, appellate and other jurisdiction as under 
the law in force immediately before the prescribed date, is 
exercisable in respect of the said territories by the Court 
of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh; and also

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1502650</tid>
<number>b</number>ordinary original civil jurisdiction in every suit the 
value of which exceeds <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fifty thousand rupees], 
notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>139</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 5- <year>1967</year> vide G. S. R. 508, dated 11- 4- <year>1967</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. 
II, Sec. 3 (i), 563.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1969</year>, s. 4, for" twenty- five thousand rupees" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1969</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1297492</tid>
<number>4</number>All proceedings pending in the Court of the Judicial Commis- 
sioner for Himachal Pradesh before the prescribed date shall stand 
transferred to the High Court of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>104130</tid>
<number>5</number>Any order made before the prescribed date by the Court 
referred to in sub- section (4) shall for all purposes have effect not 
only as an order of that Court but also as an order of the High Court 
of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>851522</tid>
<number>6</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
provisions of sections 6 to 11 and 13 shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply to the High Court of Delhi in the exercise of 
jurisdiction conferred upon it by this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1029287</tid>
<number>7</number>All proceedings pending immediately before the prescribed 
date in any subordinate court in the Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh in or in relation to any such civil suit as is referred to in 
clause (b) of sub- section (3) shall on- that date stand transferred to 
the High Court of Delhi which shall proceed to try, hear and determine 
the matter as if it had been pending therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1551271</tid>
<number> 18</number> Rule of construction.
<section><tid>1084775</tid>
<number>1</number>References in any law in force in  
the Union territory of Delhi to the High Court of Punjab shall, as 
from the appointed day, be construed in relation to that Union 
territory as references to the High Court of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>469537</tid>
<number>2</number>References in any law in force in the Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh to the High Court of Punjab or to the Court of the 
Judicial Commissioner for that territory shall, as from the prescribed 
ate, be construed in relation to that Union territory as references to 
the High Court of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1648498</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Amendment of certain laws.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56 of <year>1974</year>) s. 2 and Sch. 1.


</article>



<article><tid>1105646</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>208304</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises  
in giving effect to the provisions OX this Act, the Central Government 
may, by notified order, make such provision as appears to it to be 
necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>463621</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
following both Houses agree in making any modification in the order or 
both Houses agree that the order should not be made, the order shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annul- 
ment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
done under that order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>425887</tid>
<number>21</number>Power to adapt Laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application of any law in relation to the Union territory of Delhi or 
Himachal Pradesh, the Central Government may, before the expiration of 
two years from the appointed,, day in relation to the Union territory 
of Delhi and before the expiration of two years from the prescribed 
date in relation to the union territory of Himachal Pradesh, by order, 
make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by way of 
repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient to give effect 
to the provisions of this Act and thereupon every such law shall have 
effect subject to the adaptions and modifications so made until 
altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or other 
competent authority.

</article>



 </act>