<act><tid>890027</tid>
<title>THE PERSONAL INJURIES (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 59 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 19th December, <year>1962</year>]

An Act to make provision for the grant of relief in respect of 
certain 
personal injuries sustained during the period of the emergency.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>802825</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1184782</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Personal Injuries (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1962</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1166310</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1707295</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day of 
October, <year>1962</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1494268</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>793267</tid>
<number>1</number>" civil defence organisation" means any organisation 
established for civil defence purposes which is declared by a scheme 
to be a civil defence organisation for the purposes of this Act and 
the scheme;

</section>

<section><tid>582824</tid>
<number>2</number>" civil defence volunteer", in relation to an injury, means a 
person certified, by an officer of a civil defence organisation 
authorised by the Central Government to grant such certificates, to 
have been a member of that organisation at the time when the injury 
was sustained;

</section>

<section><tid>1934535</tid>
<number>3</number>" enemy" means-

<subsection><tid>684074</tid>
<number>i</number>any person or country committing external aggression against 
India;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>440</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1828532</tid>
<number>ii</number>any person belonging to a country committing such aggression;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1633555</tid>
<number>iii</number>such other country as may be declared by the Central Government 
to be assisting the country committing such aggression;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>10713</tid>
<number>iv</number>any person belonging to such other country;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>819411</tid>
<number>4</number>" gainfully occupied person" means a person who is engaged in 
any trade, business, profession, office, employment or vocation and is 
wholly or substantially dependent thereon for a livelihood, or a 
person who, though temporarily unemployed, is normally so engaged and 
dependent;

</section>

<section><tid>1870435</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" period of emergency" means, in relation to the 
Proclamation of Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 of 
the Constitution,-

<subsection><tid>1273725</tid>
<number>i</number>on the 26th day of October, <year>1962</year>, the period beginning with the 
 26th day of October, <year>1962</year>, and ending with the 10th day of January, 
<year>1968</year>, that is to say, the date on which the said Emergency was 
declared, by notification of the Government of India in the Ministry 
of Home Affairs, No. G. S. R. 93, dated the 10th January, <year>1968</year>, to have 
come to an end;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667512</tid>
<number>ii</number>on the 3rd day of December, <year>1971</year>, the period beginning with the 
 3rd day of December, <year>1971</year>, and ending with such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
the date on which the emergency shall come to an end;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1261576</tid>
<number>6</number>" personal injury" means a physical or mental injury or a 
disease whether manifesting itself immediately or subsequently-

<subsection><tid>930022</tid>
<number>a</number>caused by-

<subsubsection><tid>778804</tid>
<number>i</number>the discharge of any missile (including liquid or gas or both), or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>479617</tid>
<number>ii</number>the use of any weapon, explosive or other noxious thing, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>165870</tid>
<number>iii</number>the doing of any other injurious act,
either by the enemy or in combating the enemy or in repelling an 
imagined attack by the enemy; or


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>393505</tid>
<number>b</number>caused by the impact, on any person or property, of any enemy 
aircraft or any aircraft belonging to or held by any person on behalf 
of or for the benefit of the Government of India or any allied power, 
or any part of, or anything dropped from, any such aircraft: or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>441</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 25- 12- <year>1971</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21459</tid>
<number>c</number>caused by any explosion or fire which involves any explosives or 
munitions or other dangerous things, required for the purposes of 
defence against the enemy and which happens or is caused by, through, 
or in connection with the manufacture, storage or transportation of 
any such explosive, munition or other dangerous things;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>783805</tid>
<number>7</number>" personal service injury", in relation to a civil defence 
volunteer, means any physical or mental injury, or a disease whether 
manifesting itself immediately or subsequently, shown to the 
satisfaction of the Central Government or other authority authorised 
to make payments under a scheme, to have arisen out of and in the 
course of the performance by the volunteer of his duties as a member 
of the civil defence Organisation to which he belonged at the time 
when the injury was sustained or the disease was contracted, and 
 (except in the case of a personal injury) not to have arisen out of, 
and in the course of, his employment in any other capacity:
Provided that before being so satisfied, the Central Government 
or other authority authorised to make payments under a scheme shall 
have received from the civil defence Organisation of which the 
volunteer concerned was a member at the time when the injury was 
sustained or the disease was contracted, a report, by an officer of 
the organisation authorised by the Central Government to make such 
reports, about the injury or the disease in question;


</section>

<section><tid>1879866</tid>
<number>8</number>" scheme" means a scheme made under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331136</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to make schemes for relief in respect of personal 
injuries and personal service injuries.
<section><tid>1210550</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
make a scheme or schemes in accordance with the provisions of this Act 
providing for the grant of relief in respect of the following injuries 
sustained during the period of the emergency, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1233790</tid>
<number>a</number>personal injuries sustained by gainfully occupied persons (with  
  such exceptions, if any, as may be specified in the scheme) and by 
persons of such other classes as may be so specified; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1696498</tid>
<number>b</number>personal service injuries sustained by civil defence volunteers.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that different Schemes may be made in relation to 
different periods of emergency.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>486618</tid>
<number>2</number>A scheme may authorise the Central Government or any 
authority authorised by the Central Government to make payments under 
the scheme, in such circumstances and subject to such conditions as 
may be specified in the scheme, to make to or in



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>802825</tid>
<number> 1</number> Added by Act 74 of <year>1971</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 25- 12- <year>1971</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>442</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

respect of persons injured, diseased or disabled due to injuries or 
any disease-

<section><tid>1510493</tid>
<number>a</number>payments by way of temporary allowance, which shall be payable 
only so long as the person injured or diseased is Incapacitated for 
work by the injury or disease and has not received any such payment as 
is mentioned in clause (b);

</section>

<section><tid>844782</tid>
<number>b</number>payments otherwise then by way of temporary allowance, which shall 
be payable only where the injury or disease causes serious and 
prolonged or permanent disablement or death; and

</section>

<section><tid>1925223</tid>
<number>c</number>payments for the purchase of or the grant at the cost of 
Government of artificial limbs or surgical or other appliances and 
payments for medical and surgical treatment.

<subsection><tid>478501</tid>
<number>3</number>A scheme may empower the Central Government to make re- 
gulations for giving effect to the purposes of the scheme.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1953845</tid>
<number>4</number>A scheme may provide that it shall come into operation or 
shall be deemed to have come into operation on such date as may be 
specified therein.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>586640</tid>
<number>5</number>A scheme may be amended or rescinded at any time by the 
Central Government.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013077</tid>
<number>6</number>Any decision of the Central Government or other authority 
empowered to make payments under a scheme as to the making, refusal of 
amount, or as to the continuance or discontinuance, of a payment under 
a scheme may be varied from time to time, by a subsequent decision of 
the Central Government or such authority, as the case may be, but save 
in so far as it is so varied shall be final and conclusive.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>149725</tid>
<number>7</number>Every scheme and every regulation made under a scheme, shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so 
laid or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses, agree in 
making any modification in the scheme or the regulation or both Houses 
agree that the scheme or the regulation should not be made, the scheme 
or the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any suck 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that scheme or the regulation.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1516418</tid>
<number> 4</number> Relief from liability to pay compensation or damages.
<section><tid>613068</tid>
<number>1</number>In  
respect of a personal injury sustained during the period of the 
emergency by any other person, and in respect of a personal service 
injury sustained during that period by a civil defence volunteer, no 
such compensation or damages shall be payable,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>443</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

whether to the person injured or to any other person, as part from 
the provisions of this sub- section-


<subsection><tid>1032575</tid>
<number>a</number>would be payable under-

<subsubsection><tid>1637519</tid>
<number>i</number>the Workmen' s Compensation Act, <year>1923</year>, or (8 of <year>1923</year>).

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1418115</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Employees' State Insurance Act, <year>1948</year>; or (34 of <year>1948</year>).

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>895885</tid>
<number>b</number>would, whether by virtue of any enactment or by virtue of any 
contract or any custom or usage having the force of law, be payable-

<subsubsection><tid>239838</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a personal injury, by any person, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1729370</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a personal service injury sustained by a civil 
defence volunteer, by the employer of the volunteer, or by any person 
who has any responsibility in connection with the volunteer' s duties 
as such or by any other civil defence volunteer, on the ground that 
the injury in question was attributable to some negligence, nuisance 
or breach of duty for which the person by whom the compensation or 
damages would be payable is responsible.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1533552</tid>
<number>2</number>The failure to give a notice or make a claim or commence 
proceedings within the time required by any enactment shall not be a 
bar to the maintenance of proceedings in respect of any personal 
injury or personal service injury, if-

<subsection><tid>1206686</tid>
<number>a</number>an application for a payment under a scheme has been duly made to 
the Central Government or other authority empowered to make payments 
under the scheme in respect of the injury; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1646436</tid>
<number>b</number>the court or other authority before which the proceedings, are 
brought, Is satisfied that the said application was made in the 
reasonable belief that the injury was such that a payment could be 
made under the scheme; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>899404</tid>
<number>c</number>the Central Government or other authority empowered to make 
payments under the scheme certifies that the application was rejected, 
or that payments made in pursuance of the application were 
discontinued, on the ground that the injury was not such an injury; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>14672</tid>
<number>d</number>the proceedings are commenced within one month from the date of 
the said certificate.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>34168</tid>
<number> 5</number> Information as to earnings.
<section><tid>1025964</tid>
<number>1</number>Where it is necessary, in  
order to determine the amount of any payment to be awarded under under 
a scheme in respect of any personal injury or personal service injury, 
to ascertain the earnings of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>444</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the person injured in respect of any period before he sustained the 
personal injury or the personal service injury, the Central Government 
or other authority authorised to make payments under the scheme may, 
by notice in writing, require-


<subsection><tid>536961</tid>
<number>a</number>any person who was an employer of the injured person during that, 
period; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>786137</tid>
<number>b</number>any other person having any knowledge with respect to the 
financial circumstances of the injured person during that period, to 
furnish in accordance with the notice any information in his 
possession relating to those earnings or circumstances, and to produce 
to any person specified in the notice any wage books, records or other 
documents in his possession containing entries with respect to those 
earnings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1212383</tid>
<number>2</number>It any person-

<subsection><tid>66363</tid>
<number>a</number>falls to comply with the requirements of any such notice, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1437929</tid>
<number>b</number>in purported compliance with any such notice, knowingly or 
recklessly makes any untrue statement or untrue representation, or 
produces any document which is false in a material particular or 
calculated to deceive, he shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643651</tid>
<number> 6</number> Medical attention in dispensaries and hospitals.
<section><tid>1225830</tid>
<number>1</number>The person  
managing any dispensary or hospital shall, if so required by the 
Central or a State Government by general or special order,-

<subsection><tid>357399</tid>
<number>a</number>provide at the dispensary or hospital medical and surgical 
treatment for persons who have sustained injuries of the nature 
specified in sub- section (1) of section 3, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1110669</tid>
<number>b</number>keep such records and make such returns relating to the persons 
treated for such injuries as may be required by or under a scheme.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1675462</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person fails to comply, when so required, with the 
provisions of this section, he shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>246853</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty for false statement. Any person who, for the purpose 
of obtaining a payment or grant under a scheme either for himself or 
for any other person, knowingly makes any untrue statement or untrue 
representation shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three months.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>445</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1441498</tid>
<number>8</number>Assignments or charges to be void. Any assignment of, or 
charge on, and any agreement to assign or charge, any payment awarded 
or to be awarded under a scheme shall be void, and, on the insolvency 
of any person to whom such a payment has been awarded, the payment 
shall not pass to any trustee or other person acting on behalf of the 
creditors.

</article>



 </act>