<act><tid>1955466</tid>
<title>THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE (THIRD AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 72 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 28th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1431318</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1261104</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Representation of the People (Third Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>115189</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act 
shall be deemed to have come into force on the 24th August, <year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1916632</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new section 33A.- After section 33 of the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>)  (hereinafter  
  referred to as the principal Act), the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" 33A. Right to information.- (1) A candidate shall, apart from any 
information which he is required to furnish, under this Act or the 
rules made thereunder, in his nomination paper delivered under 
sub- section (1) of section 33, also furnish the informatio as to 
whether-

<section><tid>1609612</tid>
<number>i</number>he is accused of any offence punishable with imprisonment for two 
years or more in a pending case in which a charge has been framed by 
the court of competent jurisdiction;

</section>

<section><tid>1116974</tid>
<number>ii</number>he has been convicted of an offence[ other than any offence 
referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or covered in 
sub- section (3), of section 8] and sentenced to imprisonment for one 
year or more.

<subsection><tid>298464</tid>
<number>2</number>The candidate or his proposer, as the case may be, shall, at the 
time of delivering to the returning officer the nomination paper under 
sub- section (1) of section 33, also deliver to him an affidavit sworn 
specified in sub- section (1). by the candidate in a prescribed form 
verify ng the information

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1848837</tid>
<number>3</number>The returning officer shall, as soon as may be after the 
furnishing of information to him under sub- section (1), display the 
aforesaid information by affixing a copy of the affidavit, delivered 
under sub- section (2), at a conspicuous place at his o fice for the 
information of the electors relating to a constituency for which the 
nomination paper is delivered.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>449886</tid>
<number>3</number>Insertion of new section 33B.- After section 33A of the principal 
Act as so inserted, the following section shall be inserted and shall 
be deemed to have been inserted with effect from the 2nd day of May, 
<year>2002</year>, namely:-
" 33B. Candidate to furnish information only under the Act and the 
rules.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any judgment, decree or 
order of any court or any direction, order or any other instruction 
issued by the Election Commission, no candidate sha l be liable to 
disclose or furnish any such information, in respect of his election, 
which is not required to be disclosed or furnished under this Act or 
the rules made thereunder.".



</article>



<article><tid>1406932</tid>
<number>4</number>Insertion of new Chapter VIIA.- In Part V of the principal Act, 
after Chapter VII, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
' CHAPTER VIIA

DECLARATION OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

</article>



<article><tid>230985</tid>
<number> 75A</number> Declaration of assets and liabilities.-
<section><tid>1894557</tid>
<number>1</number>Every elected  
candidate for a House of Parliament shall, within ninety days from the 
date on which he makes and subscribes an oath or affirmation, 
according to the form set out for the purpose in the Third Schedule to 
the Constitution, for taking his seat in either House of Parliament, 
furnish the information, relating to-

<subsection><tid>125000</tid>
<number>i</number>the movable and immovable property of which he, his spouse and his 
dependant children are jointly or severally owners or beneficiaries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119851</tid>
<number>ii</number>his liabilities to any public financial institution; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1353100</tid>
<number>iii</number>his liabilities to the Central Government or the State 
Government, to the Chairman of the Council of States or the Speaker of 
the House of the People, as the case may be.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1209824</tid>
<number>2</number>The information under sub- section (1) shall be furnished in such 
form and in such manner as may be prescribed in the rules made under 
sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>998125</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman of the Council of States or the Speaker of the House 
of the People, as the case may be, may make rules for the purposes of 
sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1878745</tid>
<number>4</number>The rules made by the Chairman of the Council of States or the 
Speaker of the House of the People, under sub- section (3) shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after they are made, before the Council of 
States or the House of the People, as the case may b, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
or more successive sessions and shall take effect upon the expiry of 
the said period of thirty days unless they are sooner approved with or 
without modifications or disap roved by the Council of States or the 
House of the People and where they are so approved, they shall take 
effect on such approval in the form in which they were laid or in such 
modified form, as the case may be, and where they are so disapproved, 
they sh ll be of no effect.

</section>

<section><tid>630709</tid>
<number>5</number>The Chairman of the Council of States or the Speaker of the House 
of the People, as the case may be, may direct that any wilful 
contravention of the rules made under sub- section (3) by an elected 
candidate for a House of Parliament referred to in ub- section (1) may 
be dealt with in the same manner as a breach of privilege of the 
Council of States or the House of the People, as the case may be.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>737950</tid>
<number>i</number>" immovable property" means the land and includes any building or 
other structure attached to the land or permanently fastened to 
anything which is attached to the land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>644595</tid>
<number>ii</number>" movable property" means any other property which is not the 
immovable property and includes corporeal and incorporeal property of 
every description;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>76434</tid>
<number>iii</number>" public financial institution" means a public financial 
institution within the meaning of section 4A of the Companies Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) and includes bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1633610</tid>
<number>iv</number>" bank" referred to in clause (iii) means-

<subsubsection><tid>157800</tid>
<number>a</number>State Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the State Bank 
of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>512117</tid>
<number>b</number>subsidiary bank having the meaning assigned to it in clause (k) of 
section 2 of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38  
  of <year>1959</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>552261</tid>
<number>c</number>Regional Rural Bank established under section 3 of the Regional 
Rural Banks Act, <year>1976</year> (21 of <year>1976</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>43562</tid>
<number>d</number>corresponding new bank having the meaning assigned to it in clause 
 (da) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>); 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>662395</tid>
<number>e</number>co- operative bank having the meaning assigned to it in clause 
 (cci) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>) as 
modified by sub- clause (i) of clause (c) of section 56 of that Act; 
and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488911</tid>
<number>v</number>" dependant children" means sons and daughters who have no separate 
means of earning and are wholly dependant on the elected candidate 
referred to in sub- section (1) for their livelihood.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>441135</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 125A.- After section 125 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 125A. Penalty for filing false affidavit, etc.- A candidate who 
himself or through his proposer, with intent to be elected in an 
election,-

<section><tid>23187</tid>
<number>i</number>fails to furnish information relating to sub- section (1) of 
section 33A; or

</section>

<section><tid>567272</tid>
<number>ii</number>gives false information which he knows or has reason to believe 
to be false; or

</section>

<section><tid>806454</tid>
<number>iii</number>conceals any information,
in his nomination paper delivered under sub- section (1) of section 33 
or in his affidavit which is required to be delivered under 
sub- section (2) of section 33A, as the case may be, shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to six months, or with fine, or with both.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>138017</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 169.- In section 169 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), clause (a) shall be renumbered as clause (aa) 
thereof, and before clause (aa) as so renumbered, the following clause 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" (a) the form of affidavit under sub- section (2) of section 33A;".



</article>



<article><tid>883646</tid>
<number> 7</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1245610</tid>
<number>1</number>The Representation of the People  
 (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 4 of <year>2002</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1593013</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the principal Act, as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended 
by this Act.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</section>

</article>



 </act>