<act><tid>1022351</tid>
<title>THE COTTON CLOTH ACT, <year>1918</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1918</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 26th September, <year>1918</year>.]

An Act to take powers to provide for the cheap supply of cotton cloth 
to the poorer classes of the community.

WHEREAS it is expedient to take powers for the purpose of 
encouraging or maintaining the supply, at reasonable rates, to the 
poorer classes of the community, of cotton cloth manufactured in this 
country; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1733588</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the Cotton 
Cloth Act. <year>1918</year>.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].]



</article>



<article><tid>1883783</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>898701</tid>
<number>a</number>" Controller" means a Controller appointed under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>204121</tid>
<number>b</number>" cotton cloth" means cotton cloth manufactured in this 
country; and

</section>

<section><tid>1213610</tid>
<number>c</number>" standard cloth" means any kind of cotton cloth which a 
Controller may, from time to time, declare to be 
standard cloth.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1656831</tid>
<number>3</number>Power to appoint Controller. The <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State Government] may, by 
notification <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> in the Official Gazette, appoint one or more persons 
as <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> it] may think fit to be Controllers for the purposes of this 
Act, and shall specify in any such notification the area in which any 
Controller so appointed shall exercise his powers.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been declared to be in force in the Khondmals 
District by the Khondmals Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (4 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and 
Sch,; and in the Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (5  
  of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and Sch. 
2 Added by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year> for" Part B 
States". 
4 The words" G. G. in C." successively amended by the A. O. <year>1937</year> 
and the A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above. 
5 For a notification issued by the G. G. in C. under this section, 
see Gazette of India, <year>1918</year>, Pt. I, p. 1558. 
6 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" he".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>188092</tid>
<number> 4</number> Powers of the Controller.
<section><tid>1287142</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever it appears to a  
Controller that such a course is necessary or expedient, for the 
purpose of encouraging or maintaining the supply of standard cloth, at 
reasonable rates to the poorer classes of the community, he may 
 (subject to this Act and the rules made thereunder and to the control  
  of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government]) make general or special orders regulating 
or giving directions within the area in which he is empowered, with 
respect to the manufacture, transport, distribution and sale or 
purchase of, or other dealings in, cotton cloth.

</section>

<section><tid>1055181</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
orders may be made by a Controller--

<subsection><tid>223657</tid>
<number>a</number>declaring and defining the classes of standard cloth;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>230475</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribing distinctive indications which shall be woven 
into, impressed or otherwise displayed upon, different 
classes of standard cloth;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>553943</tid>
<number>c</number>requiring any person, who ordinarily manufactures cotton 
cloth, to manufacture, or provide for the manufacture 
of, standard cloth in such quantity, of such quality 
and by such date as the Controller may direct; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075519</tid>
<number>d</number>fixing the prices to be paid to the manufacturer for 
standard cloth or for any particular class of standard 
cloth, and providing for the payment thereof on 
delivery:
Provided that in fixing prices the Controller shall have regard 
to the cost of production and to the allowance of a reasonable profit, 
without necessarily taking into consideration the market- price, and if 
the Controller is satisfied that the manufacturer has incurred actual 
loss arising out of forward contracts entered into before the 
commencement of this Act, and that such loss is immediately 
attributable to an order under this Act, he may take such loss into 
account:

Provided further that the Controller may fix different prices in 
the case of different localities or, if special reasons exist, in 
respect of different manufacturers in the same locality.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137230</tid>
<number>5</number>Appointment of Advisory Committees. Where a Controller is 
appointed in exercise of the power conferred by section 3, the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] shall appoint a Committee consisting of such 
number of persons having knowledge of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" G. G. in C." successively amended by the A. O. <year>1937</year> 
and the A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the cotton or cotton cloth trade as <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> it] thinks fit to assist the 
Controller with their advice in the performance of his duties. Before 
a Controller issues any order declaring and defining the classes of 
standard cloth of fixing the prices to be paid to the manufacturer, he 
shall consult the committee, and he may consult the Committee on any 
other matter connected with his duties:

Provided that, if the opinion, of the majority of members of the 
Committee who are present at any meeting is adverse to the issue of 
any order, the Controller shall, if he does not accept the Committee' s 
advice, refer the matter for the decision of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State Government].



</article>



<article><tid>941554</tid>
<number>6</number>Manufacture and delivery of standard cloth. Where, by an order 
made in, the exercise of powers conferred by section 4, the Controller 
has directed a manufacturer to manufacture, or provide for the 
manufacture of, standard cloth and has fixed the price therefor, the 
manufacturer shall deliver the same at such time and place and in such 
manner as the Controller may specify from time to time, and the 
Controller shall pay or cause to be paid to the manufacturer the said 
price, together with the freight, if any, actually paid by the 
manufacturer.


</article>



<article><tid>987086</tid>
<number>7</number>Delegation of powers. Subject to the control of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State 
Government], a Controller may, from time to time by order in writing, 
delegate all or any of his powers subject to such conditions and 
restrictions as may be prescribed therein.


</article>



<article><tid>1108379</tid>
<number>8</number>Penalty for disobedience or orders under section 4. If any 
person acts in contravention of or, without reasonable cause, fails to 
comply with the provisions of any order made under section 4, or 
counterfeits upon any cloth a distinctive indication prescribed by the 
Controller, such person shall be punishable with imprisonment which 
may extend to six months, or with fine or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1895460</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to fix prices of standard cloth.
<section><tid>321341</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government shall, if standard cloth is sold in the State, by order in 
writing which shall be notified in the Official Gazette, fix the price 
at which alone standard cloth or any class of standard cloth shall be 
sold to the public.

</section>

<section><tid>379474</tid>
<number>2</number>Orders may be made fixing different prices for different 
localities or for different methods of sale.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" he". 
2 The words" G. G. in C." successively amended by the A. O. <year>1937</year> 
and the A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>884124</tid>
<number>3</number>Every such order shall be published in such manner as the 
State Government may consider to be best adapted for bringing the 
prices so fixed to the notice of the poorer classes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1769296</tid>
<number> 10</number> Limitation of sale of standard cloth.
<section><tid>1200231</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall  
sell or keep, offer or expose for sale to the public, standard cloth 
otherwise than at such price as may be fixed by the State Government 
and in accordance with the terms and conditions of a licence issued in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1743471</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1), 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six 
months, or with fine or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>561984</tid>
<number>11</number>Grant of licences for sale of standard cloth. A licence for 
the sale of standard cloth shall be granted by such authority, in such 
form and subject to such conditions as the State Government may 
prescribe by rules made under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>999945</tid>
<number> 12</number> Rule- making power.
<section><tid>852806</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may make  
rules--

<subsection><tid>155238</tid>
<number>a</number>prescribing the powers and duties of the Controller,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205241</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribing the manner in which the Controller' s orders 
shall be published or served, as the case may be, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>813605</tid>
<number>c</number>generally giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>964967</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government shall, if standard cloth is sold in the 
State, make rules prescribing the authority by which, the form in 
which and the conditions under which, any licence or class of licences 
for the sale of standard cloth shall be granted.

</section>

<section><tid>171207</tid>
<number>3</number>Rules made under this Act shall be published in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the 
Official Gazette, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and on such publication shall have effect as if 
enacted in this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1316083</tid>
<number>13</number>Protection for acts done under the Act. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1255939</tid>
<number>14</number>Powers to Act to be cumulative. All powers given, by this Act 
shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any other powers 
conferred by or under any enactment, and all such powers may be 
exercised in the same manner and by the same authority as if this Act 
had not been made.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" G. G. in C." successively amended by the A. O. <year>1937</year> 
and the A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above. 
2 The words" the Gazette of India or" omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
3 The words" as the case may be", omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>