<act><tid>310908</tid>
<title>THE INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION (STATUS, IMMUNITIES  
  ANDPRIVILEGES) ACT, <year>1960</year></title>

ACT NO. 32 OF <year>1960</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 9th September, <year>1960</year>.]
An Act to implement the international agreement for the establishment 
and operation of the International Development Association in so far 
as it relates to the status, immunities and privileges of that 
Association, and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--




<article><tid>753296</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>50394</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the International Development Association (Status, Immunities  
  and Privileges) Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1693914</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>448405</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>507528</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>179421</tid>
<number>a</number>" Agreement" means the Agreement for the establishment 
and operation of the international body known as the 
International Development Association;

</section>

<section><tid>292028</tid>
<number>b</number>" Association" means the International Development 
Association established under the Agreement.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>671200</tid>
<number> 3</number> Conferment of status and certain immunities and privileges on 
the Association and conferment of certain immunities and privileges on 
its officers and employees.-
<section><tid>491423</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the  
contrary contained in any other law, the provisions of Article VIII of 
the Agreement set out in the Schedule shall have the force of law in 
India:
Provided that nothing in section 9 thereof shall be construed 
as--


<subsection><tid>1238430</tid>
<number>a</number>entitling the Association to import into India goods 
free of any duty of customs without any restriction on 
their subsequent sale therein; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1999063</tid>
<number>b</number>conferring on the Association any exemption from duties 
or taxes which form part of the price of goods sold; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union torritory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
S. 3 and Schedule.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 15th October, <year>1960</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 2474-A, dt. 11- 10- 
<year>1960</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1960</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 
580-A.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1282828</tid>
<number>c</number>conferring on the Association any exemption from duties 
or taxes which are in fact no more than charges for 
services rendered.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>968499</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity 
with any amendments, duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the 
Agreement set out therein.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>954313</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>374207</tid>
<number>5</number>Notifications under section 3 and rules under section 4 to be 
placed before Parliament.- Every notification issued under sub- section 
 (2) of section 3 and every rule made under section 4 shall be laid as 
soon as may be after it is issued or made before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a period of thirty days which 
may be comprised in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the sessions, immediately 
following the session or the successive sesions aforesaid] both Houses 
agree for making any modification in the notification, or as the case 
may be, in the rule, or both Houses agree that the notification or 
rule should not be issued or made, the notification or rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that notification or rule.

</article>



 </act>