<act><title>THE FATAL ACCIDENT ACT, 1855 </title> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<title><number>1</number> Short title and extent</title>.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Fatal Accidents Act, 1855. 
  (2) It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.]




</section></article> 

 Fatal Accidents Act, 
1855 
   

 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number>] Suit for compensation to the family of a person 
for loss occasioned to it by his death by actionable 
wrong.-Whenever the death of a person shall be caused by 
wrongful act, neglect or default, and the act, neglect or default is such as 
would (if death had not ensued) have entitled the party injured to maintain an 
action and recover damages in respect thereof, the party who would have been 
liable if death had not ensued, shall be liable to an action or suit for 
damages, notwithstanding the death of the person injured and although the death 
shall have been caused under such circumstances as amount in law to felony or 
other crime. 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] Every such action or suit shall be for the 
benefit of the wife, husband, parent and child, if any, of the person whose 
death shall have been so caused, and shall be brought by and in the name of the 
executor, administrator or representative of the person deceased; 
 and in every such action, the court may 
give such damages as it may think proportioned to the loss resulting from such 
death to the parties respectively, for whom and for whose benefit such action 
shall be brought, and the amount so recovered, after deducting all costs and 
expenses, including the costs not recovered from the defendant, shall be divided 
amongst the before-mentioned parties, or any of them, in such shares as the 
court by its judgment or decree shall direct. 








</article> 

 <title></title>
  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Not more than one suit to be brought. </title> -Provided always that not more than one action or suit shall be brought for, and in respect of the same subject-matter of complaint <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***]: 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Plaintiff shall deliver particulars, etc.-The 
    plaint in any such action or suit shall give a full particular of the person 
    or persons for whom, or on whose behalf, such action or suit shall be 
    brought, and of the nature of the claim in respect of which damages shall be 
    sought to be recovered. 
 
  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Interpretation clause</title>. -The following words and expressions are intended to have the meanings hereby assigned to them respectively, so far as such meanings are not excluded by the context or by the nature of the subject-matter; that is to say <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] the word "person" shall apply to bodies politic and corporate; and the word "parent" shall include father and mother <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>and grand-father and grand-mother; and the word "child" shall include son and daughter, and grand-son and grand-daughter and step-son and step-daughter. 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Section 1 re-numbered as section 1A by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch. tc "	3.	Section 1
re-numbered as section 1A by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> The words "And it is enacted 
further that" rep. by Act 10 of 1914, Sch. II. tc
"	4.	The words "And it is enacted further that" rep. by Act 10 of
1914, Sch. II."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> The words "and that every such action shall be brought within twelve calendar months after the death of such deceased person", rep. by Act 9 of 1871. For limitation,  see  now the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Certain words rep. by Act 10 of 1914, Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>Step-father and step-mother are designedly omitted.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>