<act><tid>1818222</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL CRIMINAL COURTS (JURISDICTION) ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <year>1950</year>
[ 10th March, <year>1950</year>.]

An Act to confer upon special criminal Courts, constituted by or under 
certain State laws, jurisdiction to try offences against laws with 
respect to any of the matters enumerated in the Union List,

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>191720</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>758589</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Special Criminal Courts (Jurisdiction) Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1594515</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (the territories  
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
  Part B States.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>360971</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," special Criminal Court" means any 
special Court of criminal jurisdiction constituted by or under any law 
included in the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1247887</tid>
<number>3</number>Jurisdiction of special Criminal Courts to try offences with 
respect to matters in the Union List. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any law for the time being in force, it shall be lawful 
for any special Criminal Court to try offences against laws with 
respect to any of the matters enumerated in List I in the Seventh 
Schedule to the Constitution, if such Court is otherwise competent to 
try such offence under the law constituting it,


</article>



<article><tid>1621714</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to add to Schedule. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, add to the Schedule any other 
State law providing for the trial of offences by special Criminal 
Courts, and any such addition shall take effect as if such law had 
been included in the Schedule by this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1835349</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeal of Ordinance.
<section><tid>926853</tid>
<number>1</number>The Special Criminal Courts  
 (Jurisdiction) Ordinance, <year>1950</year> (7 of <year>1950</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>655414</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken in the exercise of any power conferred by or under the said 
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken in the exercise 
of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act were in 
force on the day on which such thing was done or action was taken.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>682</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part 
B States".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>