<act><title>
THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 19571</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Working Journalists (Conditions of Service) and 
    Miscellaneous Provisions Rules, 1957.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Working Journalists (Conditions of Service) and 
    Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955 (45 of 1955);  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   “authorised medical practitioner” means a registered medical 
    practitioner designated as such under rule 24 and where no such practitioner 
    has been designated, any registered medical practitioner;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>   “average pay” shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Industrial 
    Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947);  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>   “competent officer” means an office designated as such under rule 17;
 


    1[***]  
 </section><section>


    <number>f</number>   “form” means a form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>g</number>   “leave” means earned leave, leave on medical certificate, maternity 
    leave, extraordinary leave, leave not due, casual leave, study leave or 
    quarantine leave;  
 </section><section>


    <number>h</number>   “earned leave” means leave admissible under clause (a) of section 7 of 
    the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>i</number>   “leave on medical certificate” means leave admissible under clause (b) 
    of section 7 of the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>j</number>   “leave not due” means leave which is not due to a working journalist 
    but which may be granted to him in anticipation of its being earned 
    subsequently;  
 </section><section>


    <number>k</number>   “quarantine leave” means leave of absence from duty by reason of the 
    presence of an infectious disease in the family or household of a working 
    journalist;  
 </section><section>


    <number>l</number>   “study leave” means leave granted to a working journalist to enable 
    him to undergo any special course of training which may be of use to him in 
    his journalistic career; and  
 </section><section>


    <number>m</number>   “shifts”: ‘day shift’ means a shift when any hours of work of the 
    shift do not fall between the hours of 11 P.M. and 5 A.M.; ‘night shift’ 
    means a shift when any hours of work fall between the hours of 11 P.M. and 5 
    A.M.  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>3</number> 
    Payment of gratuity.—Gratuity 
    shall be paid to a working journalist or, in the case of his death, his 
    nominee or nominees or, if there is no nomination in force at the time of 
    the death of the working journalist, his family, as soon as possible after 
    it becomes due and in any case not later than three months.]
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> 
    Gratuity due to a deceased working journalist to whom payable.—On 
    death of a working journalist—
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   If a nomination made by him in accordance with Rule 5 subsists, the 
    gratuity shall be paid to his nominee or nominees in accordance with such 
    nomination; and  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   If no nomination subsists or if that nomination relates only to a part 
    of the gratuity, the amount of the gratuity or the part thereof to which the 
    nomination does not relate, as the case may be, shall be paid to his 
    family.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A working journalist shall, as soon as he completes three years of 
    continuous service, or in the case of those who have completed three years 
    of continuous service at the commencement of the Act, as soon as may be 
    after these rules come into force, make a nomination in form A conferring 
    the right to receive any gratuity payable under the Act, in the event of 
    this death before the amount has become payable or, where the amount has 
    become payable, before the payment has been made. 

    1[Where 
    the nominee is a minor, a working journalist shall appoint any person in 
    Form AA to receive the gratuity in the event of working journalist’s death 
    during the minority of the nominee.] 
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A working journalist may, in his nomination distribute the amount that 
    may become due to him amongst his nominees at his own discretion. 
 


    2[***]
 


    3[(3)] 
    A nomination made under sub-rule (1) 

    4[***] 
    may at any time be modified by the working journalist after giving a written 
    notice of his intention to do so in Form B. If the nominee predeceases the 
    working journalist, the interest of the nominee shall revert to the working 
    journalist, who may make a fresh nomination in accordance with these rules. 
 


    3[(4)] 
    A nomination or its modification shall take effect, to the extent it is 
    valid on the date on which it is received by the newspaper establishment.  
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Deductions from gratuity.—The 
    gratuity will be subject to deductions on account of overpayments made to a 
    working journalist by the newspaper establishment liable to pay such 
    gratuity and monies borrowed by the working journalist from such newspaper 
    establishment.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Special provisions regarding editors etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provision of this Chapter shall not apply to editors, or to 
    correspondents, reporters or news-photographers.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), the following 
    provisions shall apply to every correspondent, reporter or news-photographer 
    stationed at the place at which the newspaper (in relation to which any such 
    person is employed) is published, namely:—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>   subject to such agreement as may be arrived at either collectively or 
    individually between the parties concerned, every such correspondent, 
    reporter or news-photographer shall, once he enters upon duty on any day, be 
    deemed to be on duty throughout that day till he finishes all the work 
    assigned to him during that day:  
 


    Provided that if such correspondent, reporter or news-photographer has had 
    at his disposal for rest any interval or intervals for a total period of two 
    hours or less between any two or more assignments of work, he shall not be 
    deemed to be on duty during such period:  
 


    Provided further that where the total period of such interval or intervals 
    exceeds two hours, he shall be deemed to be on duty during the period which 
    is in excess of the said period of two hours;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>   Any period of work in excess of thirty-six hours during any week 
    (which shall be considered as a unit of work for the purposes of this 
    sub-rule) shall be compensated by rest during the succeeding week and shall 
    be given in one or more spells of not less than three hours each:  
 


    Provided that where the aggregate of the excess hours worked falls short of 
    three hours, the duration of rest shall be limited only to such excess.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>8</number> Normal working day.—The 
    number of hours which shall constitute a normal working day for a working 
    journalist exclusive of the time for meals shall not exceed six hours per 
    day in the case of a day shift and five and half hours per day in the case 
    of a night shift and no working journalist shall ordinarily be required or 
    allowed to work for longer than the number of hours constituting a normal 
    working day.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Interval for rest.—Subject 
    to such agreement as may be arrived at between a newspaper establishment and 
    working journalists employed in that establishment, the periods of work for 
    working journalists shall be so fixed that no working journalist shall work 
    for more than four hours in the case of day shift and three hours in the 
    case of night shift before he had had an interval of rest, in the case of 
    day shift for one hour, and in the case of night shift for half an hour.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>10</number> Compensation for overtime work.—When 
    a working journalist works for more than six hours on any day in the case of 
    a day shift and more than five and-half hours in the case of a night shift 
    he shall, in respect of that overtime work, be compensated in the form of 
    hours of rest equal in number to the hours for which he has worked overtime.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> Conditions governing night shifts.—No 
    working journalist shall be employed on a night shift continuously for more 
    than one week at a time or for more than one week in any period of fourteen 
    days:  
 


    Provided that, subject to the previous approval of the State Labour 
    Commissioner or any authority appointed by the State Government in this 
    behalf, the limit prescribed in this rule may be exceeded where special 
    circumstances so require.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Interval preceding change of shift.—In 
    the case of change of shift from night shift to day shift or vice versa, 
    there shall be an interval of not less than twenty-four consecutive hours 
    between the two shifts and in the case of a change from one day shift to 
    another day shift or from one night shift to another night shift there shall 
    be interval of not less than twelve consecutive hours.  
 


    Provided that no such interval may be allowed if such interval either 
    coincides with, or falls within, the interval enjoyed by a working 
    journalist under sub-section (2) of section 6 of the Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> Number of holidays in a year.—A 
    working journalist shall be entitled to ten holidays in a calendar year.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>14</number> Compensatory holidays.—If 
    a working journalist is required to attend on a holiday, a compensatory 
    holiday shall be given to him, within thirty days immediately following the 
    holiday, on a day mutually agreed upon by him and his employer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>15</number> Wages for holidays.—A 
    working journalist shall be entitled to wages on all holidays as if he was 
    on duty.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>16</number> Wages for weekly day of rest.—A 
    working journalist shall be entitled to wages for the weekly day of rest as 
    if he was on duty.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>17</number> Competent Officers.—Every 
    newspaper establishment may designate one or more officers in that 
    establishment as competent officers for the purposes of this Chapter.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>18</number> Application for leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A working journalist who desires to obtain leave of absence shall apply in 
    writing to the competent officer.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Application for leave, other than casual leave, leave on medical 
    certificate and quarantine leave, shall be made not less than one month 
    before the date of commencement of leave, except in urgent or unforeseen 
    circumstances.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>19</number> Recording of reason for refusal or postponement of leave.—If 
    leave is
    refused or postponed, the competent officer shall record the reasons for 
    such refusal or postponement, as the case may be, and send a copy of the 
    order to the working journalist.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>20</number> Affixing of holidays to leave.—Holidays, 
    other than weekly days of rest, shall not be prefixed or suffixed to any 
    leave without the prior sanction of the competent officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>21</number> Holidays intervening, during period of leave.—A 
    holiday, including a weekly rest day, intervening during any leave granted 
    under these rules shall form part of the period of leave.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>22</number> Recall before expiry of leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A newspaper establishment may recall a working journalist on leave if that 
    establishment considers it necessary to do so. In the event of such recall 
    such working journalist shall be entitled to travelling allowance if at the 
    time of recall he is spending his leave at a place other than his 
    headquarters.           
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The traveling allowance which shall be paid to a working journalist 
    under sub-rule (1) shall be determined in accordance with the rules of the 
    newspaper establishment governing traveling allowance for journeys 
    undertaken by working journalists in the course of their duties.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>23</number> 
    Production of medical certificate of fitness before resumption of duty.—A 
    working journalist who has availed himself of leave for reasons of health 
    may, before he resumes duty, be required by his employer to produce a 
    medical certificate of fitness from an authorised medical practitioner, any 
    registered medical practitioner or the medical officer who issued the 
    medical certificate under sub-rule (2) of rules 28.]  
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>23</number> 
    Production of medical certificate of fitness before resumption of duty.—A 
    working journalist who has availed himself of leave for reasons of health 
    may, before he resumes duty, be required by his employer to produce a 
    medical certificate of fitness from an authorised medical practitioner, any 
    registered medical practitioner or the medical officer who issued the 
    medical certificate under sub-rule (2) of rules 28.]  
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number> 
      Designation of authorised medical practitioner.—Every 
      newspaper establishment may designate one or more registered medical 
      practitioner as authorised medical practitioners for the purposes of these 
      rules.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>25</number> Earned leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A working journalist shall be entitled to earned leave on full wages for a 
    period not less than one month for every eleven months spent on duty:  
 


    Provided that he shall cease to earn such leave when the earned leave due 
    amounts to ninety days.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The period spent on duty shall include the weekly days of rest, 
    holidays, casual leave and quarantine leave.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>26</number> Wages during earned leave.—A 
    working journalist on earned leave shall draw wages equal to his average 
    monthly wages earned during the period of twelve complete months spent on 
    duty, or if the period is less than twelve complete months, during the 
    entire such period, immediately preceding the month in which the leave 
    commences.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>27</number> Cash compensation for earned leave not availed of.—
<section><number>1</number>When 
    a working journalist voluntarily relinquishes his post or retires from 
    service on reaching the age of superannuation, he shall be entitled to cash 
    compensation for earned leave not availed of upto a maximum of thirty days:  
 


    Provided that a working journalist who has been refused earned leave due to 
    him shall be entitled to get cash compensation for the earned leave so 
    refused:  
 


    Provided further that in the case of a working journalist who dies while in 
    service and who has not availed himself of the earned leave due to him 
    immediately preceding the date of his death, his heirs shall be entitled to 
    cash compensation for the leave not so availed of.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> When a working journalist’s services are terminated for any reason, 
    whatsoever, other than as punishment inflicted by way of disciplinary 
    action, he shall be entitled to cash compensation for earned leave not 
    availed of upto a maximum of ninety days.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The cash compensation shall not be less than the amount of wages due to 
    a working journalist for the period of leave not availed of, the relevant 
    wage being that which would have been payable to him had he actually 
    proceeded on leave on the day immediately preceding the occurrence of any of 
    the events specified in sub-rules (1) or (2), as the case may be.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>28</number> Leave on medical certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A working journalist shall be entitled to leave on medical certificate on 
    one-half of the wages at the rate of not less than one month for every 
    eighteen months of service:  
 


    Provided that he shall cease to earn such leave when the leave on medical 
    certificate amounts to ninety days.  
 


    1[(2) 
    The medical certificate shall be from an authorised medical practitioner:  
 


    Provided that when a working journalist has proceeded to a place other than 
    his headquarters with the permission of his employer and falls ill, he may 
    produce a medical certificate from any registered medical practitioner:  
 


    Provided further that the employer may, when the registered medical 
    practitioner is not in the service of the Government, arrange at his own 
    expense, the medical examination of the working journalist concerned, by any 
    Government Medical Officer not below the rank of a Civil Assistant Surgeon 
    or any other Medical Officer in Charge of a hospital run by a local 
    authority or a public organisation at that place like the Kasturba Gandhi 
    Trust, Kamladevi Nehru Trust or Tata Memorial Trust.]  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Leave on medical certificate may be taken in continuation with earned 
    leave provided that the total duration of earned leave and leave on medical 
    certificate taken together shall not exceed a hundred and twenty days at any 
    one time.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> A working journalist shall be entitled at his option to convert leave on 
    medical certificate on one-half of the wages to half the amount of leave on 
    full wages.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The ceiling laid down in the provisos to sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (3) 
    on the accummulation and total duration of leave may be relaxed by the 
    competent officer in the cases of working journalists suffering from 
    lingering illness such as tuberculosis.  
 


    2[(6) 
    Leave on medical certificate or converted leave on medical certificate 
    referred to in sub-rules (1) and (4) may be granted to a working journalist 
    at his request notwithstanding that earned leave is due to him.]
 



 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>29</number> Maternity leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A female working journalist who has put in not less than one year's service 
    in the newspaper establishment in which she for the time being employed 
    shall be granted maternity leave on full wages for a period which may extend 
    up to three months from the date of its commencement or six weeks from the 
    date of confinement whichever be earlier.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Leave of any other kind may also be granted in continuation of maternity 
    leave.   
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Maternity leave shall also be granted in cases of mis-carriage, 
    including abortion, subject to the condition that the leave does not exceed 
    six weeks.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>30</number> Quarantine leave.—Quarantine 
    leave on full wages shall be granted by the newspaper establishment on the 
    certificate of the authorised medical practitioner designated as such under 
    rule 24 or where, there is no such authorised medical practitioner by a 
    district public health officer or other Municipal Health Officer of similar 
    status, for a period not exceeding twenty-one days, or, in exceptional 
    circumstances, thirty days. Any leave necessary for quarantine purposes in 
    excess of that period shall be adjusted against any other leave that may be 
    due to the working journalist.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>31</number> Extraordinary leave.—A 
    working journalist who has no leave to his credit may be granted 
    extraordinary leave without wages at the discretion of the newspaper 
    establishment in which such working journalist is employed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>32</number> Leave not due.—A 
    working journalist who has no leave to his credit may be granted at the 
    discretion of the newspaper establishment in which such working journalist 
    is employed leave not due.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>33</number> Study leave.—A 
    working journalist may be granted study leave with or without wages at the 
    discretion of the newspaper establishment in which such working journalist 
    is employed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>34</number> Casual leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A working journalist shall be eligible for casual leave at the discretion of 
    the newspaper establishment for fifteen days in a calendar year:  
 


    Provided that not more than five days’ casual leave shall be taken at any 
    one time and such leave shall not be combined with any other leave.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Casual leave not availed of during a calendar year will not be carried 
    forward to the following year.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>35</number> Wages during casual leave.—A 
    working journalist on casual leave shall be entitled to wages as if he was 
    on duty.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>35A</number> 
      Manner of giving notice under section 12 of the Act.—Notice 
      required to be given under proviso to clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of 
      section 12 of the Act shall be in Form H and shall be published in the 
      Official Gazette and in leading newspapers.]
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>36</number> 
      Application under section 17 of the Act.—An 
      application under section 17 of the Act shall be made in Form C to the 
      Government of the State, where the Central Office or the Branch Office of 
      the newspaper establishment in which the newspaper employee is employed, 
      is situated.]
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>37</number> 
    Maintenance of registers, records and muster-rolls.—Every 
    newspaper establishment shall prepare and maintain the following registers, 
    records and muster-rolls:—  
 <section>


    <number>i</number>   A register of employees in Form D.  
 </section><section>


    <number>ii</number>   Service Registers in respect of all working journalists in Form E.  
 </section><section>


    <number>iii</number>   Leave Registers in respect of all working journalists in Form F.  
 </section><section>


    <number>iv</number>   A muster-roll in Form G:  
 


    Provided that the leave register in Form F and the muster-roll in Form G may 
    not be maintained by the newspaper establishments to which the Minimum Wages 
    Act, 1948 and/or the Shops and Commercial Establishments Act of the State 
    concerned apply and which are required under those Acts or the rules made 
    thereunder to maintain such or similar forms.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number> 
      Effect of rules and agreements inconsistent with these 
      rules.—The 
      provisions of these rules shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
      inconsistent therewith contained in any other rule or agreement or 
      contract of service applicable to a working journalist:  
 Provided 
      that where under any such rule, agreement or contract of service or 
      otherwise, a working journalist is entitled to benefits in respect of any 
      matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would be 
      entitled under these rules, the working journalist shall continue to be 
      entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect of that matter, 
      notwithstanding that he receives benefit in respect of other matters under 
      these rules.  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number> 
      Effect of rules and agreements inconsistent with these 
      rules.—The 
      provisions of these rules shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
      inconsistent therewith contained in any other rule or agreement or 
      contract of service applicable to a working journalist:  
 Provided 
      that where under any such rule, agreement or contract of service or 
      otherwise, a working journalist is entitled to benefits in respect of any 
      matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would be 
      entitled under these rules, the working journalist shall continue to be 
      entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect of that matter, 
      notwithstanding that he receives benefit in respect of other matters under 
      these rules.  
  
 
  </article><form>
 
  
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 1957
 



 


FORM A
 



    NOMINATION FORM FOR PAYMENT OF GRATUITY UNDER SECTION 5 OF  

    THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND  

    MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS ACT, 1955
 




    [See rule 5(1)]
 




    1.  Name (in block letters) 
    ....................................................................................................
 




        Surname (if any) 
    ..............................................................................................................
 




2. Sex
...............................................................................................................................
 




    3. Religion 
    ...........................................................................................................................
 




    4. Occupation 
    ....................................................................................................................
 




    5. Father’s name 
    ...............................................................................................................
 




    6. Husband’s name 
    ..............................................................................................................
 




        (for married women only)
 




    7. Marital Status 
    .................................................................................................................
 




        whether bachelor, spinster, married, widow or widower
 




    8. Date of birth ........................ Day ............. Month 
    ...................... Year ....................
 




    9. Permanent address 
    ........................................................................................................
 




            Village .................... Thana .................. District 
    ....................... State .......................
 




    I hereby nominate the person/s mentioned below to receive the amount of 
    gratuity standing to my credit, in the event of my death before that amount 
    has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid and direct 
    that the said amount shall be distributed among the said persons in the 
    manner shown below against their names:—
 
  
  

 
 
Name and Address of the nominee or 
        nominees
 
Nominee's relation with working journalist
 
Age of nominee
 
Amount of share of gratuity to be paid to 
        each nominee
 
Contingencies of the happening of which 
        the nomination shall become invalid

 
  

 
 
1
 
2
 
3
 
4
 
5

 
  

 
 
 

 

 



 
  


 




    Date...............         
 




    Signature of the working journalist
 

 
 




    Certified that above declaration has been signed by 
    ............................ employed in 
    .............................................................. (the name of 
    the newspaper establishment to be given)   before me after he has read the 
    entries/ the entries have been read over to him by me.
 

 
 




    Dated.......................              
 




    Signature of a responsible officer  

    of the Newspaper establishment
 
  
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (1) Designation ...............................................

 
 

        Dated ...................................
  

 
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (2) Name and address of the newspaper  

        establishment .........................................


 




    Dated.........................
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 1957
 



 


1[FORM 
    AA]
 


FORM 
    FOR PAYMENT OF GRATUITY UNDER SECTION 5 OF THE WORKING  

    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS  

    PROVISIONS ACT, 1955 IN THE CASE OF MINORS
 




    [See rule 5(1)]
 

 
 




    Whereas Shri/Kumari ................................. son/daughter of 
    ................ who has been nominated by me to receive the amount of 
    gratuity standing to my credit, in the event of my death before that amount 
    has become payable, or having become payable has not been paid, is a minor, 
    I hereby appoint Shri/Kumari/Shrimati ............................. 
    son/daughter/wife of ................... to receive the gratuity in the 
    event of my death during the minority of Shri/Kumari 
    .........................................................................................................  
 




    Dated ....................                Signature of Working Journalist  
 




    Certified that the above declaration has been signed by 
    ..................... employed in .............. (the name of the newspaper 
    establishment to be given) before me after he has read the entries/the 
    entries have been read to him by me.  
 




    Dated.................... 
 




    Signature of a responsible officer
 




    of the newspaper establishment
 

 
 
 
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (1) Designation ...............................................

 
 

        Dated ...................................
  

 
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (2) Name and address of the newspaper  

        establishment .........................................

 
 

        Dated.......................]
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 




    -------------------------------
 


     1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 1320, 
    dated 1st August, 1963.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 1957
 



 


FORM B
 



    NOMINATION FORM FOR PAYMENT OF GRATUITY UNDER SECTION 5 OF  

    THE WORKING JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND  

    MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS ACT, 1955
 




    [See rule 5(5)]
 




    I, ..................... hereby cancel the nomination made by me on 
    the.................... regards the disposal in the event of my death of the 
    amount of gratuity standing to my credit and hereby nominate the person/s 
    mentioned below to receive the amount of gratuity standing to my credit, in 
    the event of my death before that amount has become payable, or having 
    become payable has not been paid and direct that the said amount shall be 
    distributed among the said persons in the manner shown below against their 
    names:—
 

 
 
 
  

 
 
Name and Address of the nominee or 
        nominees
 
Nominee's relation with working journalist
 
Age of nominee
 
Amount of share of gratuity to be paid to 
        each nominee
 
Contingencies of the happening of which 
        the nomination shall become invalid

 
  

 
 
1
 
2
 
3
 
4
 
5

 
  

 
 
 

 

 

 
 

 
 

 



 
  

 
  
  
  
  
  


 

 
 




    Dated.....................                
 




    Signature of the working journalist
 




    Certified that the above declaration has been signed before me 
    by..................... employed in 
    ................................................................................................. 

    ................................................................................ 
    (the name of the newspaper establishment to be given).
 

 
 




    Dated.....................                
 




    Signature of a responsible official 
 




    of the newspaper establishment
 

 
 
 
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (1) Designation ...............................................

 
 

        Dated ...................................
  

 
 

        Signature of witness ..................................
 

        (2) Name and address of the newspaper  

        establishment .........................................

 
 

        Dated.......................]
 

 
  
  



 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 1957
 

 
 


1[FORM C
 



    APPLICATION UNDER SUB-SECTION (1) OF SECTION 17 OF THE  

    WORKING JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND  

    MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS ACT, 1955
 




    (See rule 36)
 

 
 




    To
 




    The Secretary to the Government of ............... (here insert the name of 
    the State Government)
 




    Department of.................... (here insert the name of the Department 
    which deals with labour matters)...................... (here insert the name 
    of the place where the headquarters of the State Government are situated).  
 




    Sir,  
 




    I have to state that I Shri/Shrimati/Kumari...................... 
    son/widow/daughter of ................, a working journalist, was entitled 
    to receive from................ (here insert the name and address of the 
    newspaper establishment) a sum of Rs. .................. on account 
    of............................ (here insert gratuity, wages, etc., as the 
    case may be), payable under the Working Journalists (Conditions of service) 
    and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955 (45 of 1955).
 




    I further state that I was appointed by 
    Shri.................................... by an instrument 
    dated...................... to receive the amount of the gratuity on behalf 
    of Shri/Kumari ............................
 




    I further state that I served the said newspaper establishment with a demand 
    notice by registered post on...................... for the said amount which 
    the said newspaper establishment has neither paid nor offered to pay to me 
    even though 15 days have since lapsed. The details of the amount due are 
    mentioned in the statement hereto annexed.  
 




    I request that the said sum may kindly be recovered from the said newspaper 
    establishment under section 17 of the said Act, and paid to me as early as 
    possible.
 

 
 




    *[I have been duly authorised in writing by.................... (here insert 
    the name of the newspaper employee) to make this application and to receive 
    the payment of the aforesaid amount due to him.]
 




    *[I am a member of the family of late...................... (insert the name 
    of the deceased newspaper employee), being his..................... (here 
    insert the relationship) and am entitled to receive the payment of the 
    aforesaid amount due to late........................ (here insert the name 
    of the deceased newspaper employee).]
 




    *To be struck out when the payment is claimed by the newspaper employee 
    himself.
 

 
 




    Station....................               
 




    Signature of the applicant
 




    Date........................                
 




    Address................................
 




    ..............................................
 



 
 



 
 




    -----------------------------
 


     1.   Forms C  to G ins. by 
    G.S.R. 1320, dated 1st August, 1963.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS RULES, 1957
 



 




    1[form 
    h
 




    Form of notice to be given under the proviso to clause (a) of sub-section 
    (2) of section 12 of the Working Journalists and other Newspaper Employees 
    (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955
 




    (See rule 35A)
 

 
 




    Whereas the Central Government by notification No. 
    ............................................ dated 
    ...................................... constituted a board/tribunal for 
    fixing or revising rates of wages of......................................
 




    And whereas the said board/tribunal has made its recommendations;
 




    And whereas the Central Government proposes to make the modifications to the 
    said recommendations;
 




    Now, therefore, in pursuance of the proviso to clause (a) of sub-section (2) 
    of section 12 of the working jounalists and other Newspaper Employees 
    (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955, notice is 
    hereby given to all persons likely to be affected by the following 
    modifications to make their representation in writing within a period of 
    thirty days from the publication of this notice.
 




    Proposed Modifications :]
 





 





 




    ------------------------
 


       1. Form H ins. by G.S.R. 
    899(E), dated 11th November, 1980 (w.e.f. 12-11-1996).          
 




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>