<act><title>

The 
    Voluntary Deposits (Immunities 
    and Exemptions) Act, 1991</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—This Act may be 
    called the Voluntary Deposits (Immunities and Exemptions) Act, 1991. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “deposit” means a voluntary deposit 
    made by any person with the National Housing Bank in accordance with the 
    scheme on or after the commencement of this Act but before the specified 
    date. 
 
        
    Explanation.—For the purposes of this clause, “specified date” means the 
    1st day of December, 1991 or such other later date as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “National Housing Bank” means the 
    National Housing Bank established under section 3 of the National Housing 
    Bank Act, 1987 (53 of 1987);  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “net deposit” means sixty per cent. of 
    the amount of deposit made by any person with the National Housing Bank in 
    accordance with the scheme;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “person” includes—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    an individual,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    a Hindu undivided family,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a company,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a firm,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    an association of person or a body of 
    individuals, whether incorporated or not, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    every artificial juridical person, not 
    falling within any of the preceding sub-clauses,  
 
but does not include a local authority;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>    “scheme” means a scheme formulated by 
    the National Housing Bank under the National Housing Bank Act, 1987 (53 of 
    1987) for the purpose of enabling—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any person to make deposit with that 
    Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    such Bank to credit forty per cent. of 
    the amount of such deposit to a special fund created for financing slum 
    clearance and low cost housing for the poor; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the depositor to utilise the net 
    deposit for any purpose specified by him;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>    all other words and expressions used in 
    this Act but not defined and defined in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 
    1961) shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Immunities.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force,—  
 <subsection>
 <number>a</number>    no person, who has made a deposit 
    with the National Housing Bank in accordance with the scheme, shall be 
    required to disclose, for any purpose whatsoever, the nature and source of 
    the deposit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    no inquiry or investigation shall be 
    commenced against any person under any such law on the ground that he has 
    made the deposit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the fact that a person has made the 
    deposit shall not be taken into account and shall be inadmissible as 
    evidence in any proceedings relating to any offence or the imposition of any 
    penalty under any such law.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    sub-section (1) shall apply in relation to prosecution for any offence 
    punishable under Chapter IX or Chapter XVII of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860), the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 
    1985), the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act, 1987 (28 of 
    1987), the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), or for the 
    purpose of enforcement of any civil liability.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Deposit 
    not to be taken into account in certain cases.—Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the provisions of section 3—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the deposit shall not be taken into 
    account for the purpose of any proceeding under the Income-tax Act, 1961 
    and, in particular the depositor shall not be entitled to claim any set-off 
    or relief in any assessment, re-assessment, appeal, reference or other 
    proceeding under that Act or to re-open any assessment or re-assessment made 
    under that Act on the ground that he has made such deposit;
 
     Explanation.—For the avoidance 
    of doubt, it is hereby declared that the provisions of the Income-tax Act, 
    1961 will apply to any income which accrues or arises or is deemed to accrue 
    or arise to the depositor from the amount of the net deposit;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the deposit shall not form part of the 
    assets of any assessee for the purposes of computing his net wealth under 
    the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 in relation to any assessment year commencing 
    before the 1st day of April, 1992.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Amendment of Act 53 of 1987.—In 
    the National Housing Bank Act, 1987,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in section 14,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in clause (b), after the words 
    “scheduled banks”, the words “or to any authority established by or under 
    any Central, State or Provincial Act and engaged in slum clearance” shall be 
    inserted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    after clause (h), the following clause 
    shall be inserted, namely:—  
 
      “(hh) formulating a scheme for the 
    purpose of accepting deposits referred to in clause (a) of section 2 of the 
    Voluntary Deposits (Immunities and Exemptions) Act, 1991 and crediting forty 
    per cent. of the amount of such deposits to a special fund created under 
    section 37;”;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    in section 15, in sub-section (1), to 
    clause (c), the following proviso shall be added, namely:—  
 
       “Provided that nothing contained in 
    this clause shall apply to deposits accepted under the scheme formulated by 
    the Bank in pursuance of clause (hh) of section 14;”;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    in section 55, in sub-section (5), for 
    the word “regulation”, wherever it occurs, the words “regulation or scheme” 
    shall be substituted.  

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>