<act><tid>544006</tid>
<title>THE CRIMINAL LAW AMENDMENT ACT, <year>1932</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1932</year>
[ 19th December, <year>1932</year>.]

An Act to supplement the criminal law.

WHEREAS it is expedient to supplement the criminal law and to 
that end to amend the Indian Press (Emergency Powers) Act, <year>1931</year> (23  
  of <year>1931</year>), and further to amend <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Indian Criminal Law 
Amendment Act, <year>1908</year> (14 of <year>1908</year>), for the purposes 
hereinafter appearing;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>691844</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent, duration and commencement.
<section><tid>965856</tid>
<number>1</number>This  
Act may be called the Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1932</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1261634</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in Part B States].]
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1932970</tid>
<number>4</number>The whole of the Act except <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> section 7 shall come 
into force at once, and the State Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette direct that <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> section 7 shall come into 
force in any area on such date as may be specified in the 
notification.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>655A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" temporarily" rep. by the Criminal Law Amendment 
Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part 
B States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Sub- section (3), limiting the duration of the Act to three 
years from commencement, rep. by Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 
2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words and figure" section 4 and" rep. by s. 4, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>S. 7 was brought into force in-

Former Province of Bihar and Orissa, from 26th December, <year>1932</year>: 
see B. and O. Gazette, Extraordinary, dated 26th December, <year>1932</year>;

The Delhi Province, from 24th December, <year>1932</year>: see Gazette of India, 
Extraordinary, <year>1932</year>, p. 429;

The City of Bombay, the Bombay Suburban district and the 
districts of Kaira, Ahmednagar, East Khandesh, West Khandesh, 
Ratnagiri and Kanara, from 29th December, <year>1932</year>: see Bombay Gazette, 
Extraordinary, dated 27th December, <year>1932</year>;

Amritsar district, from 31st December, <year>1932</year>: see Punjab Gazette, 
Extraordinary, <year>1932</year>, p. 163;

The districts of Cachar, Goalpara, Kamrup, Darrang, Nowgong, Sib- 
sagar and Lakhimpur, from 7th January, <year>1933</year>: see Assam Gazette, Extra- 
ordinary, dated 7th January, <year>1933</year>;

Ajmer- Merwara, from 30th September, <year>1933</year>: see Gazette of India, 
<year>1933</year>, Pt. II- A, p. 716.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>The words and figure" section 4 or" rep. by the Criminal Law 
Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 4.

Am. in Bombay by Bom. Act 2407 <year>1959</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Extended to Pondicherry (with modifications): ride G. S. R. 200. 
dt. 7- 2- <year>1957</year>, Gaz. of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 230


<pagefootnote><pagenum>655B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Extended to Goa, Daman and Die (with modification): vide G. S. R. 
 863 dt. 2- 6- 66, Gaz. of India, Ex., pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 389.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>656</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

 2 to

Dissuasion from enlistment. Tampering with public Boycotting a publicservant.

 2 to 4.[ Dissuasion from enlistment. Tampering with public 
servants. Boycotting a public servant.] Rep. by the Criminal Law 
Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 2.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>513932</tid>
<number> 5</number> Dissemination of contents of prescribed document.
<section><tid>383588</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Whoever publishes, circulates or repeats in public any passage from a 
newspaper, book or other document copies whereof have been declared to 
be forfeited to Government under any law for the time being in force, 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>640503</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable 
under this section unless the State Government has certified that the 
passage published, circulated or repeated contains, in the opinion of 
the State Government, seditious or other matter of the nature referred 
to in sub- section (1) of section 99A of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>) or sub- section (1) of section 4 of the 
Indian Press (Emergency, Powers) Act, <year>1931</year> (23 of <year>1931</year>),



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252012</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Dissemination of false rumours.] Rep. by the Criminal Law 
Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 2.


</article>



<article><tid>341214</tid>
<number> 7</number> Molesting a person to prejudice of employment or business.

<section><tid>661024</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever- 

<subsection><tid>432789</tid>
<number>a</number>with intent to cause any person to abstain from doing 
or to do any act which such person has a right to do or to 
abstain from doing, obstructs or uses violence to or inti- 
midates such person or any member of his family or person in 
his employ, or loiters at or near a place where such person 
or member or employed person resides or works or carries on 
business or happens to be, or persistently follows him from 
place to place, or interferes with any property owned or used 
by him or deprives him of or hinders him in the use thereof, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>751303</tid>
<number>b</number>loiters or does any similar act at or near the place 
where a person carries on business, in such a way and with 
intent that any person may thereby be deterred from entering 
or approaching or dealing at such place,
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with 
both.

Explanation.- Encouragement of indigenous industries or 
advocacy of temperance, without the commission of any of the acts 
prohibited by this section is not an offence under this section.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>657</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1451060</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable 
under this section except upon a report in writing of facts which 
constitute such offence made by a police- officer not below the rank of 
officer in charge of a police- station.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>616272</tid>
<number>8</number>[ Power to order parent or guardian to pay line imposed on 
young person.] Rep. by the Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 2.


</article>



<article><tid>1031438</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure in offences under the Act. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>),
<section><tid>942041</tid>
<number>i</number>no Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or 
Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>356254</tid>
<number>ii</number>an offence punishable under sections <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or 
 7 shall be cognizable by the police;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and


</section>

<section><tid>1677642</tid>
<number>iv</number>an offence punishable under section 7 shall be non- 
bailable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1428999</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power of State Government to make certain offences 
cognizable and non- bailable.
<section><tid>1497555</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any offence 
punishable under section 186, 188, 189, 190, 228, 295A, 298, 505, 506 
or 507 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), when committed in any 
area specified in the notification shall, notwithstanding anything co- 
ntained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), be 
cognizable, and thereupon the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of  
  <year>1898</year>), shall, while such notification remains in force, be deemed to 
be amended accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>668073</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, in like manner and subject to the 
like conditions, and with the like effect, declare that an offence 
punishable under section 188 or section 506 of the Indian Penal Code 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>). shall be non- bailable.
 11 t

Amendment of s. 16, Act 14 of <year>1908</year>. Amendment of s. 17, Act 14 of <year>1908</year>. 
Insertion of new ss. 17A to 17F in Act 14 of <year>1908</year>. Amendmentof title and 
preamble of Act 23 of <year>1931</year>.

 11 to 14.[ Amendment of s. 16, Act 14 of <year>1908</year>. Amendment of s. 
17, Act 14 of <year>1908</year>. Insertion of new ss. 17A to 17F in Act 14 of 
<year>1908</year>. Amendment of title and preamble of Act 23 of <year>1931</year>.] Rep. by the 
Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>658</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The figures" 2"" 3" and" 6" were rep. by the Criminal Law 
Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 5.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl. (iii) was rep. by s. 5, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For such notifications, as to the former Province of Bihar and 
Orissa, see B. and O. Gazette, Extraordinary, dated 26th December, <year>1932</year> 
; and as to the former Presidency of Bombay, see Bombay Gazette, 
Extraordinary, dated 27th December, <year>1932</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1524345</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Amendment of s. 1, Act 23 of <year>1931</year>.] Rep. by the Criminal 
Law Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 2.


</article>



<article><tid>370670</tid>
<number>16</number>[ Amendment of s. 4, Act 23 of <year>1931</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing 
Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>1546136</tid>
<number>17</number>[ Cessation of effect of s. 62, Ordinance 10 of <year>1932</year>.] Rep. 
by the Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, s. 2.


</article>



<article><tid>1641395</tid>
<number>18</number>Adoption and continuance of action taken under Ordinance 10 
of <year>1932</year>. Anything done or any proceedings commenced in pursuance of 
the provisions of Chapter VI of the Special Powers Ordinance, <year>1932</year> 
 (10 of <year>1932</year>), shall, upon the commencement of this Act, be deemed to 
have been done or to have been commenced in pursuance of the corres- 
ponding provisions of the Indian Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1908</year> (45  
  of <year>1908</year>), as amended by this Act, and shall have effect as if this Act 
was already in force when such thing was done or such proceedings were 
commenced.


</article>



<article><tid>1703485</tid>
<number>19</number>Adoption and continuance of action taken under Act 23 of 
 <year>1931</year> as amended by Ordinance 10 of <year>1932</year>. Anything done or any 
proceedings commenced in pursuance of the provisions of the Indian 
Press (Emergency Powers) Act, <year>1931</year> (23 of <year>1931</year>), as amended by 
section 77 of the Special Powers Ordinance, <year>1932</year> (10 of <year>1932</year>), 
shall, upon the commencement of this Act, be deemed to have been done 
or to have been commenced in pursuance of the corresponding provisions 
of the Indian Press (Emergency Powers) Act, <year>1931</year>, as amended by this 
Act, and shall have effect as if this Act was already in force when 
such thing was done or such proceedings were commenced.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Trial of, and completion of trials of, offences against Ordinance 10of <year>1932</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>1888022</tid>
<number>20</number>[ Trial of, and completion of trials of, offences against 
Ordinance 10 of <year>1932</year>.] Rep. by the Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1935</year>, 
s. 2.

</article>



 </act>