<act><tid>318384</tid>
<title>THE NORTH- EASTERN AREAS (REORGANISATION) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 81 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of the States of Manipur and 
Tripura and to provide for the formation of the State of 
Meghalaya and of the Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal 
Pradesh by reorganisation of the existing State of Assam and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>63714</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the North- Eastern Areas 
 (Reorganisation) Act, <year>1971</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>104367</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>688196</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the administrator of a Union 
territory appointed by the President under article 239 
of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>91005</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>1493212</tid>
<number>c</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>323579</tid>
<number>d</number>" common High Court" means the Gauhati High Court (the  
High Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and 
  Tripura) referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) 
of section 28;

</section>

<section><tid>843210</tid>
<number>e</number>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
appointed by the President under article 324;

</section>

<section><tid>1509596</tid>
<number>f</number>" existing State of Assam" means the State of Assam as 
existing immediately before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>1897103</tid>
<number>g</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1072</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 21- 1- <year>1972</year>: vide Notifin. No. G. S. R. 18 (E) dated in the 6th 
January, <year>1972</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), 
p. 57.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


immediately before the appointed day, the force of law 
in the whole or any part of the existing State of Assam 
or the autonomous State of Meghalaya or the Union 
territory of Manipur or the Union territory of Tripura, 
as the case may be;


</section>

<section><tid>1764827</tid>
<number>h</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or the Legislative Assembly of the existing 
State of Assam, means a person who, immediately before 
the appointed day, is a member of that House or that 
Assembly;

</section>

<section><tid>221574</tid>
<number>i</number>" successor State", in relation to the existing State of 
Assam, means the State of Assam or Meghalaya, and 
includes also the Union in relation to the Union 
territory of Mizoram;

</section>

<section><tid>407519</tid>
<number>j</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury.
PART

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATES OF MANIPUR AND TRIPURA AND FORMATION OFTHE STATE 
OF MEGHALAYA AND OF THE UNION TERRITORIES OF MIZORAM ANDARUNACHAL PRADESH

PART II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATES OF MANIPUR AND TRIPURA AND FORMATION 
OF THE STATE OF MEGHALAYA AND OF THE UNION TERRITORIES OF MIZORAM 
AND ARUNACHAL PRADESH




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>620186</tid>
<number>3</number>Establishment of the State of Manipur. On and from the 
appointed day there shall be established a new State, to be known as 
the State of Manipur, comprising the territories which immediately 
before that day were comprised in the Union territory of Manipur.


</article>



<article><tid>1274464</tid>
<number>4</number>Establishment of the State of Tripura. On and from the 
appointed day there shall be established a new State, to be known as 
the State of Tripura, comprising the territories which immediately 
before that day were comprised in the Union territory of Tripura.


</article>



<article><tid>803119</tid>
<number> 5</number> Formation of the State of Meghalaya. On and from the appointed 
day there shall be formed a new State, to be known as the State of 
Meghalaya, comprising--
<section><tid>1099600</tid>
<number>a</number>the territories which immediately before that day were 
comprised in the autonomous State of Meghalaya formed 
under section 3 of the Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) 
Act, <year>1969</year> (55 of <year>1969</year>); and

</section>

<section><tid>706655</tid>
<number>b</number>so much of the territories comprised within the 
cantonment and municipality of Shillong as did not form 
part of that autonomous State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1073</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and thereupon the said territotries shall cease to form part of the 
existing State of Assam.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>597669</tid>
<number>6</number>Formation of the Union territory of Mizoram. On and from the 
appointed day there shall be formed a new Union territory, to be known 
as the Union territory of Mizoram, comprising the territories which 
immediately before that day were comprised in the Mizo District in the 
existing State of Assam and thereupon the said territories shall cease 
to form part of the existing State of Assam.


</article>



<article><tid>116810</tid>
<number>7</number>Formation of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh. On and 
from the appointed day there shall be formed a new Union territory, to 
be known as the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh, comprising the 
territories which immediately before that day were comprised in the 
tribal areas specified in Part B of the table appended to paragraph 20 
or the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution[ but excluding the areas 
covered by notification No. TAD R 35 50 109, dated the 23rd February, 
 <year>1951</year> issued by the Governor of Assam under the proviso to sub- 
paragraph (3) of the said paragraph 20] and known as the North- East 
Frontier Agency and thereupon the said territories shall cease to form 
part of the existing State of Assam.


</article>



<article><tid>1883273</tid>
<number>8</number>Territories of State of Assam. On and from the appointed day 
the State of Assam shall comprise the territories of the existing 
State of Assam other than those specified in sections 5, 6 and 7.


</article>



<article><tid>849864</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of first Schedule to the constitution. On and from 
the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution,--
<section><tid>854685</tid>
<number>a</number>under the heading" I. THE STATES",--

<subsection><tid>1236552</tid>
<number>i</number>in the paragraph relating to the territories 
of the State of Assam, the following shall be added at 
the end, namely:--
" and the territories specified in sections 5, 
 6 and 7 of the North- Eastern Areas 
 (Reorganisation) Act, <year>1971</year>";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>676603</tid>
<number>ii</number>after entry 18, the following entries shall 
be inserted, namely:--
" 19. Manipur The territory which immediately before the 
commencement of this Constitution was 
being administered as if it were a Chief Com- 
missioner' s Province under the name of 
Manipur.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1074</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1973494</tid>
<number>20</number>Tripura The territory which immediately before 
the commencement of this Constitution was 
being administered as if it were a Chief 
Commissioner' s Province under the name of 
Tripura.
</article>



<article><tid>300551</tid>
<number> 21</number> Meghalaya The territories specified in section 5 of 
the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) 
Act, <year>1971</year>.":
<section><tid>1074678</tid>
<number>b</number>under the heading" II. THE UNION TERRITORIES".--

<subsection><tid>59503</tid>
<number>i</number>entries 2 and 3 shall be omitted and entries 4 to 9 
shall be re- numbered as entries 2 to 7 respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1253744</tid>
<number>ii</number>after entry 7 as so re- numbered, the following 
entries shall be inserted, namely:--
" 8. Mizoram The territories specified in section 6 of 
the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) 
Act, <year>1971</year>.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>849864</tid>
<number>9</number>Arunachal The territories specified in section 7 of 
Pradesh the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) 
Act, <year>1971</year>.".
PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States



</article>



<article><tid>47394</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. On and from 
the appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the 
Table,--
<section><tid>1303435</tid>
<number>a</number>for entries 19 to 22, the following shall be 
substituted, namely:--
" 19. Manipur.. 1 
20. Tripura.. 1 
21. Meghalaya.. 1 
22. Delhi.. 3 
23. Pondicherry.. 1 
24. Mizoram.. 1 
25. Arunachal Pradesh.. 1";


</section>

<section><tid>517198</tid>
<number>b</number>for the figures" 228", the figures" 231" shall be 
substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1075</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>771094</tid>
<number>11</number>Allocation of sitting members representing the existing Union 
territories of Manipur and Tripura. On and from the appointed day the 
sitting members of the Council of States representing the existing 
Union territories of Manipur and Tripura shall be deemed to have been 
duly elected under clause (4) of article 80 to fill the seat allotted 
to each of the States of Manipur and Tripura respectively in that 
Council and the term of office of such sitting members shall remain 
unaltered.


</article>



<article><tid>1166060</tid>
<number>12</number>Election to fill the seats allotted to the State of Meghalaya 
and the Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh. As soon as 
may be after the appointed day steps shall be taken to fill the seats 
in the Council of States allotted to the State of Meghalaya and the 
Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1157890</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 27A of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. On and from the 
appointed day, in section 27A of the Representation of the People Act, 
<year>1950</year>,--
<section><tid>677522</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" For the purpose of 
filling any seat", the words, brackets and figure 
" Subject to the provisions of sub- section (5), for the 
purpose of filling any seat" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>801981</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4), for the words" The electoral college 
for each of the Union territories of Manipur, Tripura 
and Pondicherry", the words" The electoral college for 
the Union territory of Pondicherry" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>787292</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall 
be inserted, namely:--
" (5) The seat allotted in the Council of State to 
each of the Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal 
Pradesh shall be filled by a person nominated by the 
President in this behalf.".

The House of the People




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1820961</tid>
<number> 14</number> Allocation of seats in the existing House of the People.
<section><tid>1800891</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On and from the appointed day and until the dissolution of the 
existing House of the People, the allocation of seats to the States of 
Assam, Manipur, Tripura and Meghalaya and the Union territories of 
Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the People and the 
number of seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and 
for

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1076</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Scheduled Tribes of each State and Union territory shall be as 
specified in the Table below and the First Schedule to the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), shall be deemed 
to have been amended accordingly.

THE TABLE

Number of seats in the existing 
House of the People 
Name of the State Union 
territory Reserved Reserved 
Total for the for the 
Scheduled Scheduled 
Castes Tribes 
 1 2 3 4 
I. STATES: 
1. Assam... 14 1 2 
2. Manipur... 2.. 1 
3. Tripura... 2.. 1 
4. Meghalaya.. 2.. 2 
II. UNION TERRITORIES: 
1. Mizoram.. 1.. 1 
2. Arunachal Pradesh. 1.. 1


</section>

<section><tid>1154470</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day and until the dissolution of 
the existing House of the People, Part A of Schedule II to the 
Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1966</year> 
shall stand amended as directed in the First Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1077</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>30360</tid>
<number> 15</number> Parliamentary constituencies of the States of Manipur and 
Tripura and provision as to sitting members.
<section><tid>1720114</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day and until the dissolution of the existing House of the 
People,--

<subsection><tid>1052706</tid>
<number>a</number>the two parliamentary constituencies of the existing 
Union territory of Manipur shall be deemed to be the 
two parliamentary constituencies of the State of 
Manipur; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728192</tid>
<number>b</number>the two parliamentary constituencies of the existing 
Union territory of Tripura shall be deemed to be the 
two parliamentary constituencies of the State of 
Tripura.
and the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies 
Order, <year>1966</year> shall be construed accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1607624</tid>
<number>2</number>Every sitting member of the House of the People representing 
a parliamentary constituency which on the appointed day, by virtue of 
the provisions of sub- section (1), becomes a parliamentary 
constituency of the State of Manipur or Tripura, as the case may be, 
shall, as from that day, be deemed to have been elected under sub- 
clause (a) of clause (1) of article 81 to the House of the People from 
that constituency.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>337518</tid>
<number> 16</number> Provision as to sitting members representing Cachar and 
Dhubri parliamentary constituencies in the House of the People and the 
election of representative from Diphu parliamentary constituency.
<section><tid>2019</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The sitting member of the House of the People representing the Cachar 
parliamentary constituency which on the appointed day, by virtue of 
the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 14, stands altered shall, 
as from that day, be deemed to have been elected under sub- clause (a) 
of clause (1) of article 81 to the House of the People from that 
constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>872637</tid>
<number>2</number>The sitting member of the House of the People representing 
the Dhubri parliamentary constituency which on the appointed day, by 
virtue of the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 14, stands 
altered shall, as from that day, be deemed to have been elected under 
sub- clause (a) of clause (1) of article 81 to the House of the People 
from that constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>104239</tid>
<number>3</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day election shall be 
held to the House of the People to elect a representative from the 
Diphu parliamentary constituency as if the seat of the member elected 
to the House of the People from that constituency has become vacant 
and the provisions of section 149 of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>) shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to 
such election.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1078</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1664949</tid>
<number> 17</number> Parliamentary constituencies of the State of Meghalaya and 
provision as to sitting member representing the Autonomous Districts 
parliamentary constituency in the House of the People and the election 
of representative from Tura parliamentary constituency.
<section><tid>1502491</tid>
<number>1</number>There  
shall be two parliamentary constituencies in the State of Meghalaya to 
be called the Shillong parliamentary constituency and the Tura 
parliamentary constituency.

</section>

<section><tid>1298336</tid>
<number>2</number>The area falling within the Garo Hills district as it exists 
immediately before the appointed day shall form the Tura parliamentary 
constituency and the remaining area in the State of Meghalaya shall 
form the Shillong parliamentary constituency and the said two 
parliamentary constituencies shall be deemed to have been delimited 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1801663</tid>
<number>3</number>The sitting member of the House of the People representing 
immediately before the appointed day the Autonomous Districts 
parliamentary constituency shall, as from that day, be deemed to have 
been elected under sub- clause (a) of clause (1) of article 81 to the 
House of the People from the Shillong parliamentary constituency.

</section>

<section><tid>458190</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day election shall be 
held to the House of the People to elect a representative from the 
Tura parliamentary constituency as if the seat of the member elected 
to the House of the People from that constituency has become vacant 
and the provisions of section 149 of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>) shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to 
such election.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>606724</tid>
<number>18</number>Parliamentary constituency of the Union territory of Mizoram. 
The whole of the Union territory of Mizoram shall form one 
parliamentary constituency to be called the Mizoram parliamentary 
constituency and as soon as may be after the appointed day election 
shall be held to the House of the People to elect a representative 
from that constituency, as if the seat of the member elected to the 
House of the People from that constituency has become vacant and the 
provisions of section 149 of the Representation of the People Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>) shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to such 
election.


</article>



<article><tid>1697222</tid>
<number>19</number>Provision as to the member to represent Arunachal Pradesh in 
the House of the People. The sitting member nominated to fill the seat 
allotted in the House of the People to the Tribal Areas of Assam 
specified in Part B of the Table appended to paragraph 20 of the Sixth 
Schedule to the Constitution, known as the North- East Frontier Agency, 
shall, on and from the appointed day, be deemed to have been nominated 
to fill the seat allotted to the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh 
in the House of the People.
The Legislative Assemblies



</article>



<article><tid>1973494</tid>
<number> 20</number> Allocation of seats in the Legislative Assemblies.
<section><tid>1918642</tid>
<number>1</number>On and  
from the appointed day, the total number of seats in the Legislative 
Assembly of the State of Assam, to be filled by persons chosen by 
direct election from territorial constituencies, shall be reduced from 
one hundred and twenty- six to one hundred and fourteen; and every 
sitting member of that Legislative Assembly representing a 
constituency which ceases to be a constituency in the State of Assam 
by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1079</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

virtue of the provisions of sub- section (5) shall, as from the 
appointed day, cease to be a member of that Legislative Assembly.


</section>

<section><tid>86294</tid>
<number>2</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Manipur, to be constituted at any time after the appointed 
day, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from 
territorial constituencies shall be sixty, out of which one seat shall 
be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and nineteen seats shall be 
reserved for the Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

<section><tid>834205</tid>
<number>3</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Tripura, to be constituted at any time after the appointed 
day, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from 
territorial constituencies shall be sixty, out of which six seats 
shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and nineteen seats shall be 
reserved for the Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

<section><tid>160931</tid>
<number>4</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Meghalaya, to be constituted at any time after the appointed 
day, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from 
territorial constituencies shall be sixty, out of which fifty seats 
shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes.

</section>

<section><tid>977032</tid>
<number>5</number>On and from the appointed day, Part B of Schedule II to the 
Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1966</year> 
shall stand amended as directed in the First Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>300551</tid>
<number> 21</number> Amendment of Second Schedule to Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.
<section><tid>1827164</tid>
<number>1</number>In the  
Second Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year>,--

<subsection><tid>715732</tid>
<number>i</number>under the heading" I. STATES:",--

<subsubsection><tid>1125377</tid>
<number>a</number>in item 2 relating to Assam, for the figures 
" 126", the figures" 114" shall be substituted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1040942</tid>
<number>b</number>after item 17 and the entries relating 
thereto, the following shall be inserted, namely:--
" 18. Manipur.. 60 1 19 
19. Tripura.. 60 6 19 
20. Meghalaya.. 60.. 50":


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>758381</tid>
<number>ii</number>under the heading" II. UNION TERRITORIES:" items 3 and 
 5 and the entries relating thereto shall be omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1812519</tid>
<number>2</number>The amendment made by clause (i)  (a) of sub- section (1) shall 
have effect on and after the appointed day in relation to the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam and the amendments made by 
clause (i)  (b) and clause (ii) of sub- section (1) shall have effect in 
relation to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1080</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Legislative Assemblies of the States of Manipur, Tripura and 
Meghalaya to be constituted at any time after the appointed day.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>998384</tid>
<number> 22</number> Delimitation of constituencies.
<section><tid>569472</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission  
shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute, whether before or 
after the appointed day, the seats assigned to the Legislative 
Assemblies of the States of Manipur, Tripura and Meghalaya under 
section 20 to single member territorial constituencies and delimit 
them on the basis of the latest census figures having regard to the 
provisions of the Constitution and to the following provisions:--

<subsection><tid>469215</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, so far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas and in delimiting them, 
regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
boundaries of administrative units, facilities of 
communication and public convenience;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1826591</tid>
<number>b</number>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to 
fall only within one parliamentary constituency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>558970</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes shall be distributed in different 
parts of the States and located, as far as practicable, 
in those areas where the proportion of their population 
to the total population is comparatively large; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>285725</tid>
<number>d</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be 
located in those areas where the proportion of their 
population to the total population is the largest.
Explanation.-- In this section" latest census figures" mean the 
census figures with respect to the State concerned ascertainable from 
the latest census of which the finally published figures are 
available.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>254046</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of assisting in the performance of its 
functions under sub- section (1), the Election Commission shall 
associate with itself as associate members,--

<subsection><tid>456716</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of the State of Manipur, all the sitting 
members of the House of the People representing the 
Union territory of Manipur or, as the case may be, the 
State of Manipur under sub- section (2) of section 15, 
and such six persons who were members of the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Manipur 
immediately before its dissolution by order of the 
President published in the Gazette of India, dated 16th 
October, <year>1969</year> with notification No. S. O. 4223, dated
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16th</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



<pagefootnote><pagenum>1081</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

October, <year>1969</year> of the Government of India in the 
Ministry of Home Affairs, as the President may, by 
order, nominate;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1355983</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of the State of Tripura, all the sitting 
members of the House of the People representing the 
Union territory of Tripura or, as the case may be, the 
State of Tripura under sub- section (2) of section 15, 
and such six persons, being members of the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory of Tripura as it 
functioned immediately before the 1st November, <year>1971</year>, 
as the President may, by order, nominate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>965284</tid>
<number>c</number>in respect of the State of Meghalaya, the member of the 
House of the People representing the Autonomous 
Districts parliamentary constituency or, as the case 
may be, the Meghalaya parliamentary constituency under 
section 17, and such of the six members of the 
Legislative Assembly of the autonomous State of 
Meghalaya constituted under section 62 of the Assam 
Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, <year>1969</year> or, as the case 
may be, of the Provisional Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Meghalaya referred to in section 27, as the 
President may, by order, nominate:
Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to 
vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1274408</tid>
<number>3</number>If owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance 
with the provisions of sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1889999</tid>
<number>4</number>A member of any Legislative Assembly nominated under clause 
 (b) or clause (c) of sub- section (2) shall continue to be an associate 
member notwithstanding that he ceases to be a member of such 
Legislative Assembly, otherwise than consequent on the incurring of 
any disqualification.

</section>

<section><tid>1710918</tid>
<number>5</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>1154111</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of 
constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals, 
if any, of any associate member who desires publication 
thereof, in the Official Gazette and in such other 
manner as the Commission may consider fit, together 
with a notice inviting objections and suggestions in 
relation to the proposals and specifying a date on or 
after which the proposals will be further considered by 
it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1739586</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1782</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520373</tid>
<number>c</number>after considering all objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine by one or more orders the 
delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or 
orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and 
upon such publication, the order or orders shall have 
the full force of law and shall not be called in 
question in any court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>601053</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order 
shall be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the concerned State.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>965911</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders 
up- to- date.
<section><tid>688915</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  
notification in the Official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>14292</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistake in any order made under 
section 22 or any error arising therein from 
inadvertent slip or omission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951360</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order or orders are or is 
altered, make such amendment as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for bringing such order up- to- 
date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1007078</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is issued, before the Legislative Assembly of the 
concerned State.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1928020</tid>
<number>24</number>Validation of acts done previous to the commencement of the 
Act. All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement of 
this Act with a view to delimiting the territorial constituencies of 
the States of Manipur, Tripura and Meghalaya for the purpose of 
elections to the Legislative Assemblies of those States shall, in so 
far as they are in conformity with the provisions of sections 22 and 
23, be deemed to have been done or taken under those sections as if 
those sections were in force at the time such things were done or such 
steps were taken.


</article>



<article><tid>109410</tid>
<number> 25</number> Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.
<section><tid>218723</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed any, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year> shall 
stand amended as directed in the Second Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1866321</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Castes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year> shall stand amended as 
directed in the Third Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1492747</tid>
<number> 26</number> Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.
<section><tid>709453</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year> shall 
stand amended as directed in the Fourth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1083</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1247616</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Tribes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year> shall stand amended as 
directed in the Fifth Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>87079</tid>
<number> 27</number> Provision as to Provisional Legislative Assembly of the State 
of Meghalaya and as to Rules of Procedure and Conduct of Business of 
the Legislative Assemblies of the States of Meghalaya, Manipur and 
Tripura.
<section><tid>1942845</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day and until the Legislative  
Assembly of the State of Meghalaya has been duly constituted and 
summoned to meet for the first session under the provisions of the 
Constitution, the Provisional Legislative Assembly of the autonomous 
State of Meghalaya, excluding the members nominated thereto, 
constituted under section 62 of the Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) 
Act, <year>1969</year> (55 of <year>1969</year>) and functioning immediately before the 
appointed day, shall be the Provisional Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Meghalaya and that Assembly shall exercise all the powers and 
perform all the duties conferred by the provisions of the Constitution 
on the Legislative Assembly of that State:
Provided that for the purposes of this sub- section, the member 
representing the autonomous District of United Khasi- Jaintia Hills in 
the said Provisional Legislative Assembly of the autonomous State of 
Meghalaya shall be deemed also to represent the territories specified 
in clause (b) of section 5.


</section>

<section><tid>1132984</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members of the Provisional 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Meghalaya shall, unless the said 
Legislative Assembly is sooner dissolved, expire immediately before 
the first meeting of the Legislative Assembly of the State of 
Meghalaya.

</section>

<section><tid>169989</tid>
<number>3</number>The persons who, immediately before the appointed day, are 
the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the Provisional Legislative 
Assembly of the autonomous State of Meghalaya shall be the Speaker and 
the Deputy Speaker respectively of the Provisional Legislative 
Assembly of the State of Meghalaya.

</section>

<section><tid>1794531</tid>
<number>4</number>The Rules of Procedure and Conduct of Business of the 
Provisional Legislative Assembly of the autonomous State of Meghalaya, 
as in force immediately before the appointed day, shall, until rules 
are made under clause (1) of article 208, be the Rules of Procedure 
and Conduct of Business of the Provisional Legislative Assembly of the 
State of Meghalaya and of the Legislative Assembly of the State of 
Meghalaya duly constituted under the provisions of the Constitution, 
subject to such adaptations as may be made therein by the Speaker of 
the Legislative Assembly, concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>962717</tid>
<number>5</number>The Rules of Procedure and Conduct of Business of the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Manipur, as in force 
immediately before its dissolution by order of the President published 
in the Gazette of India, dated the 16th October, <year>1969</year> with 
notification No. S. O.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1084</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

 4223, dated the 16th October, <year>1969</year> of the Government of India in the 
Ministry of Home Affairs, shall, until rules are made under clause (1) 
of article 208, be the Rules of Procedure and Conduct of Business of 
the Legislative Assembly of the State of Manipur, subject to such 
modifications and adaptations as may be made therein by the Governor 
of that State.


</section>

<section><tid>1924765</tid>
<number>6</number>The Rules of Procedure and Conduct of Business of the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Tripura as in force 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1971</year>, shall, until rules are made 
under clause (1) of article 208, be the Rules of Procedure and Conduct 
of Business of the Legislative Assembly of the State of Tripura, 
subject to such modifications and adaptations as may be made therein 
by the Governor of that State.
PART

HIGH COURT

PART IV

HIGH COURT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>381294</tid>
<number> 28</number> Common High Court for Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and 
Tripura.
<section><tid>1251099</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day,-- 

<subsection><tid>290320</tid>
<number>a</number>the High Court of Assam and Nagaland shall cease to 
function and is hereby abolished;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1523024</tid>
<number>b</number>there shall be a common High Court for the States of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura to be 
called the Gauhati High Court (the High Court of Assam,  
  Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>493789</tid>
<number>c</number>the Judges of the High Court of Assam and Nagaland 
holding office immediately before that day shall, 
unless they have elected otherwise, become on that day 
the Judges of the common High Court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1493266</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in clause (a) of sub- section (1) shall prejudice or 
affect the continued operation of any notice served, injunction 
issued, direction given or proceedings taken before the appointed day 
by the High Court of Assam and Nagaland under the powers then 
conferred upon that Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>822234</tid>
<number>29</number>Jurisdiction of the common High Court. On and from the 
appointed day, the common High Court shall have, in respect of the 
territories comprised in the States of Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, 
Nagaland and Tripura, all such jurisdiction, powers and authority as 
under the law in force immediately before the appointed day,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1085</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

are exercisable in respect of those territories by the High Court of 
Assam and Nagaland or the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Manipur, or the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Tripura, as the 
case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>344677</tid>
<number> 30</number> Abolition of certain Courts.
<section><tid>381920</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed  
day, the Courts of the Judicial Commissioners for Manipur and Tripura 
shall cease to function and are hereby abolished.

</section>

<section><tid>837221</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall prejudice or affect the 
continued operation of any notice served, injunction issued, direction 
given or proceedings taken before the appointed day by any of the 
Courts abolished by that sub- section, under the powers then conferred 
upon that Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>554307</tid>
<number> 31</number> Principal seat and other places of sitting of the common High 
Court.
<section><tid>207328</tid>
<number>1</number>The principal seat of the common High Court shall be at the  
same place at which the principal seat of the High Court of Assam and 
Nagaland is located immediately before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>113098</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may by notified order provide for the 
establishment of a permanent bench or benches of the common High Court 
at one or more places within the territories to which the jurisdiction 
of the High Court extends, other than the principal seat of the High 
Court, and for any matters connected therewith:
Provided that before issuing any order under this sub- section, 
the President shall consult the Chief Justice of the common High Court 
and the Governor of the State in which the bench or benches is or are 
proposed to be established.


</section>

<section><tid>583335</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), the Judges and division courts of the common High Court 
may also sit at such other place or places in the State of Assam, 
Manipur, Meghalaya, Nagaland or Tripura as the Chief Justice may, with 
the approval of the Governor of the State concerned, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1846321</tid>
<number>32</number>Extension of jurisdiction of the common High Court to the 
Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh. On and from the 
appointed day, the jurisdiction of the common High Court shall extend 
to the Union territories of Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1086</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>359538</tid>
<number>33</number>Allocation of expenditure of the common High Court. The 
expenditure in respect of salaries and allowances of the Judges of the 
common High Court shall be allocated amongst the States of Assam, 
Manipur, Meghalaya, Nagaland and Tripura and the Union in such 
proportion as the President may, by order, determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1486115</tid>
<number> 34</number> Special provisions relating to advocates and Bar Council.
<section><tid>250492</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to any rule made or direction given by the common High Court 
in this behalf, any person, who immediately before the appointed day, 
is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Assam and 
Nagaland or in the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Manipur or 
in the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Tripura, shall be 
entitled to practise as an advocate in the common High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>145988</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of audience in the common High Court shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles as, immediately 
before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of 
audience in the High Court of Assam and Nagaland:
Provided that as among the Advocates- General of the States of 
Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Nagaland and Tripura, the right of audience 
shall be determined with reference to their dates of enrolment as 
advocates.


</section>

<section><tid>1656356</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the appointed day, in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25  
  of <year>1961</year>)  (hereafter in this Part referred to as the Advocates Act), 
in section 3,--

<subsection><tid>381703</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),--

<subsubsection><tid>1038878</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (b), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:--
" (b) for the States of Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, 
Nagaland and Tripura and the Union territories of Mizoram 
and Arunachal Pradesh, to be known as the Bar Council of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura.";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1723850</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (e), for the words" Union territories of 
Tripura and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands", the words 
" Union territory of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands" shall 
be substituted;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1937397</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (b), for the words" Bar 
Council of Assam", the words" Bar Council of Assam, 
Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura" shall be 
substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1087</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1693412</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of section 17 of the Advocates Act shall have 
effect in respect of the roll of the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, 
Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura subject to the modifications that,--

<subsection><tid>156501</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (a) of sub- section (1) of the said section 17, the 
following clause shall be substituted, namely:--
" (a) all persons who were entered as advocates,--


<subsubsection><tid>735588</tid>
<number>i</number>on the roll of the Bar Council of Assam and 
Nagaland immediately before the day appointed under clause 
 (b) of section 2 of the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) 
Act, <year>1971</year>;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1251469</tid>
<number>ii</number>on the roll of the Bar Council of West Bengal 
immediately before that day and who, within three months 
from that day, express in such manner as the Bar Council of 
India may, by rules, prescribe their intention in writing to 
practise within the jurisdiction of the Bar Council of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura;";

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>165774</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (a) of sub- section (3) of the said section 17, 
for the words and figures" with his date of enrolment 
under the Indian Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year>," (38 of <year>1926</year>), 
the words" with his seniority on the roll of the Bar 
Council of Assam and Nagaland or, as the case may be, 
the Bar Council of West Bengal" shall be substituted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1000610</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Advocates Act, as 
amended or modified by sub- sections (3) and (4),--

<subsection><tid>1979280</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the first Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, 
Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura under that Act, the 
fifteen members required to be elected under clause (b) 
of sub- section (2) of section 3 of that Act, shall be 
nominated by the Chief Justice of the common High Court 
from amongst the advocates who are entitled as of right 
to practise in that High Court and are ordinarily 
practising within the territories comprised in the 
States of Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Nagaland and 
Tripura and the Union territories of Mizoram and 
Arunachal Pradesh and the term of office of the members 
so nominated shall be one year from the date of the 
first meeting of the Council or until their successors 
are duly elected in accordance with the provisions of 
the said Act, whichever is earlier:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1088</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1929126</tid>
<number>b</number>the names of persons entered on the roll of the Bar 
Council of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and 
Tripura from the roll of the Bar Council of West Bengal 
in accordance with the provisions of clause (a) of sub- 
section (1) of section 17 of the Advocates Act, as 
modified by sub- section (4), shall, as from the date or 
dates on which the names are so entered, stand removed 
from the roll of the Bar Council of West Bengal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1566443</tid>
<number>c</number>any proceedings which were pending or which may be 
instituted against any person before or by the Bar 
Council of Assam and Nagaland or by the Bar Council of 
West Bengal immediately before his name is entered in 
the roll of the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, 
Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura in accordance with the 
provisions of clause (a) of sub- section (1) of section 
 17 of the Advocates Act, as modified by sub- section 
 (4), may, after such entry, be continued or instituted 
before or by the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, 
Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>704985</tid>
<number>d</number>every person who, immediately before his name stands 
removed from the roll of the Bar Council of West Bengal 
in accordance with the provisions of clause (b), is a 
member of the Bar Council of West Bengal, shall cease 
to be a member of that Council as from the date on 
which his name stands so removed from the roll of that 
Bar Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1120345</tid>
<number>e</number>the rules made or deemed to have been made by the Bar 
Council of Assam and Nagaland and in force immediately 
before the date on which the first Bar Council of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura is duly 
constituted in accordance with the provisions of clause 
 (a), shall, subject to such modifications and 
adaptations as may be made therein by the Chairman of 
the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur 
and Tripura, be deemed to be rules made by that Bar 
Council and shall have effect accordingly.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>454079</tid>
<number>6</number> (a) As from the appointed day, the assets and liabilities of 
the Bar Council of Assam and Nagaland shall pass to the Bar Council of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura.

<subsection><tid>1790116</tid>
<number>b</number>The assets and liabilities of the Bar Council of West Bengal 
shall be apportioned between that Bar Council and the Bar Council of 
Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur and Tripura in such manner and 
proportion as may be agreed upon by the Bar Councils and in default of 
agreement with reference to any matter, the matter shall be referred 
to the Chairman of the Bar Council of India and his decision thereon 
shall be final.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1089</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- Expressions used in this section but not defined in 
this Act shall have the meanings assigned to them respectively in the 
Advocates Act.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>58341</tid>
<number>35</number>Practice and procedure in the common High Court. Subject to 
the provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Assam and Nagaland shall, with the necessary modifications, apply 
in relation to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1704493</tid>
<number>36</number>Custody of seal of the common High Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody of 
the seal of the High Court of Assam and Nagaland shall, with the 
necessary modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the seal 
of the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>542833</tid>
<number>37</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of Assam 
and Nagaland shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with 
respect to the form of writs and other processes used, issued or 
awarded by the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>405201</tid>
<number>38</number>Powers of Judges. The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Assam and Nagaland and 
with respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those powers 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the 
common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1479229</tid>
<number>39</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Assam and Nagaland and the Judges 
and division courts thereof shall, with the necessary modifications, 
apply in relation to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>51630</tid>
<number> 40</number> Transfer of proceedings from the High Court of Assam and 
Nagaland and the Courts of the Judicial Commissioners to the common 
High Court.
<section><tid>179156</tid>
<number>1</number>All proceedings pending in the High Court of Assam and  
Nagaland and in the Courts of the Judicial Commissioners for Manipur 
and Tripura immediately before the appointed day shall, from such day, 
stand transferred to the common High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1213603</tid>
<number>2</number>Every proceeding transferred under sub- section (1) shall be 
disposed of by the common High Court as if such proceeding was 
entertained by that High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1855276</tid>
<number>3</number>Any order made before the appointed day by the High Court of 
Assam and Nagaland or by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Manipur or by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Tripura 
shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of that High 
Court or, as the case may be, of that Court but also as an order of 
the common High Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1090</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1038864</tid>
<number> 41</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of section 40,--
<section><tid>364006</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court 
until that court has disposed of all issues between the 
parties, including any issues with respect to the 
taxation of the costs of the proceedings and shall 
include appeals, applications for leave to appeal to 
the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions 
for revision and petitions for writs; and

</section>

<section><tid>108622</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof; and references to an order made by a court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1322902</tid>
<number>42</number>Right to appear or act in proceedings transferred to the 
common High Court. Any person who, immediately before the appointed 
day, is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Assam 
and Nagaland or in the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Manipur 
or in the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Tripura and was 
authorised to appear or to act in any proceedings transferred from the 
said High Court or Courts of the Judicial Commissioners to the common 
High Court under section 40, shall have the right to appear or to act, 
as the case may be, in the common High Court in relation to those 
proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>1648432</tid>
<number>43</number>Savings. Nothing in this Part shall affect the application to 
the common High Court of any provisions of the Constitution, and this 
Part shall have effect subject to any provision that may be made on or 
after the appointed day with respect to that High Court by any 
Legislature or other authority having power to make such provisions.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES



</article>



<article><tid>713723</tid>
<number> 44</number> Authorisation of expenditure pending sanction by 
Legislatures.
<section><tid>617747</tid>
<number>1</number>The President may, at any time before the appointed  
day, authorise by order such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of 
the State of Manipur or of the State of Tripura as he deems necessary 
for a period of not more than six months beginning with the appointed 
day pending the sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative 
Assembly of the State of Manipur or of the State of Tripura, as the 
case may be:
Provided that the Governor of Manipur or of Tripura may, after 
the appointed day, authorise by order such further expenditure as he 
deems necessary from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Manipur or, 
as the case may be, of the State of Tripura for any period not 
extending beyond the said period of six months.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1091</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>784855</tid>
<number>2</number>The President or, as the case may be, the Governor of the 
concerned State shall make separate orders under sub- section (1) in 
respect of periods falling in different financial years.

</section>

<section><tid>1802274</tid>
<number>3</number>The Governor of Assam, exercising the functions as Governor 
in relation to the autonomous State of Meghalaya by virtue of the 
Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, <year>1969</year> (55 of <year>1969</year>), may at any 
time, before the appointed day, authorise by order such expenditure 
from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Meghalaya as he deems 
necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning with the 
appointed day pending the sanction of such expenditure by the 
Legislative Assembly of Meghalaya:
Provided that the Governor of Meghalaya may, after the appointed 
day, authorise such further expenditure as he deems necessary from the 
Consolidated Fund of the State of Meghalaya for any period not 
extending beyond the said period of six months.


</section>

<section><tid>1349376</tid>
<number>4</number>The Governors referred to in sub- section (3) shall make 
separate orders under that sub- section in respect of periods falling 
in different financial years.

</section>

<section><tid>316368</tid>
<number>5</number>The President may, at any time, before or after the appointed 
day authorise by order such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of 
India as he deems necessary for a period of not more than six months 
beginning with the appointed day for the administration of the affairs 
of the Union territory of Mizoram pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>610446</tid>
<number>6</number>The President shall make separate orders under sub- section 
 (5) in respect of periods falling in different financial years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>112249</tid>
<number>45</number>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure to the Union 
territory of Arunachal Pradesh. Any Act passed by Parliament for the 
appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of India to 
meet the expenditure in respect of any part of the financial year 
<year>1971</year>- 72 in, or for the purposes of, the tribal areas of Assam 
specified in Part B of the Table appended to paragraph 20 of the Sixth 
Schedule to the Constitution shall, on and from the appointed day, 
have effect also in relation to the Union territory of Arunachal 
Pradesh and it shall be lawful for the President to spend any amount 
in, or for the purposes of, that Union territory out of the amounts 
authorised by such Act to be expended in, or for the purposes of, the 
said tribal areas.


</article>



<article><tid>970146</tid>
<number> 46</number> Reports relating to the accounts of the Union territories of 
Manipur and Tripura.
<section><tid>1484585</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor-  
General of India referred to in section 49 of the Government of Union 
Territories Act, <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>) relating to the accounts of the 
Union territory of Manipur or of the Union territory of Tripura in 
respect of any period prior to the appointed day shall be submitted to 
the Governor of Manipur or of Tripura, as the case may be, who shall 
cause them to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the State of 
Manipur or of the State of Tripura, as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1092</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1892041</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governor of Manipur or of Tripura, as the case may be, 
may, by order,--

<subsection><tid>198395</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated 
Fund of the Union territory of Manipur or of Tripura on 
any service in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day during the financial year <year>1971</year>- 72 or in 
respect of any earlier financial year in excess of the 
amount granted for that service and for that year as 
disclosed in the reports referred to in sub- section (1) 
to have been duly authorised, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1173151</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising 
out of the said reports.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>9749</tid>
<number> 47</number> Reports relating to the accounts of the autonomous State of 
Meghalaya.
<section><tid>922189</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of  
India relating to the accounts of the autonomous State of Meghalaya in 
respect of any period prior to the appointed day shall be submitted to 
the Governor of Meghalaya who shall cause them to be laid before the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Meghalaya.

</section>

<section><tid>959663</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governor of Meghalya may, by order,--

<subsection><tid>802198</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated 
Fund of the autonomous State of Meghalaya on any 
service in respect of any period prior to the appointed 
day during the financial year <year>1971</year>- 72 or in respect of 
any earlier financial year in excess of the amount 
granted for that service and for that year as disclosed 
in the reports referred to in sub- section (1) to have 
been duly authorised, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1374511</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising 
out of the said reports.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>940480</tid>
<number>48</number>Allowances and privileges of the Governors of Assam, Manipur, 
Meghalaya and Tripura. The allowances and privileges of the Governors 
of Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya and Tripura shall, until provision in 
that behalf is made by Parliament by law under clause (3) of article 
158, be such as the President may, by order, determine.


</article>



<article><tid>754556</tid>
<number>49</number>Distribution of revenues. The President shall, by order, 
determine the grants- in- aid of the revenues of the States of Assam, 
Manipur, Meghalaya and Tripura and the share of each such State in the 
Union duties of excise, estate duty and taxes on income and for that 
purpose amend thereby the relevant provisions of the Union Duties of 
Excise (Distribution) Act, <year>1962</year> (3 of <year>1962</year>), the Additional Duties of 
Excise (Goods of Special Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>), the 
Estate Duty (Distribution) Act, <year>1962</year> (9 of <year>1962</year>) and the Constitution 
 (Distribution of Revenues) Order, <year>1969</year> in such manner as he thinks 
fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1093</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>1392378</tid>
<number> 50</number> Property, assets, rights, liabilities, obligations, etc., of 
the States of Manipur and Tripura.
<section><tid>1134372</tid>
<number>1</number>All such property and assets  
within the Union territory of Manipur or of Tripura as are held 
immediately before the appointed day by the Union for purposes of 
governance of that Union territory shall, on and from that day, pass 
to the State of Manipur or of Tripura, as the case may be, unless the 
purposes for which such property and assets are so held are Union 
purposes:
Provided that the cash balance in the treasuries in the Union 
territory of Manipur or of Tripura before the appointed day shall, as 
from that day, vest in the State of Manipur or of Tripura, as the case 
may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1244393</tid>
<number>2</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations (other than those  
  relatable to, or in connection with, a Union purpose), whether arising 
out of any contract or otherwise, which are, immediately before the 
appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>320905</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights liabilities and obligations of the Central 
Government arising out of, or in connection with, the 
governance of the Union territory of Manipur or of 
Tripura; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>958557</tid>
<number>b</number>the rights, liabilities and obligations of the 
Administrator of the Union territory of Manipur or of 
Tripura in his capacity as such or of the Government of 
the Union territory of Manipur or of Tripura,
shall, on and from the appointed day, be the rights, liabilities and 
obligations of the Government of the State of Manipur or of Tripura, 
as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1772390</tid>
<number>3</number>The right to recover arrears of--

<subsection><tid>1335785</tid>
<number>a</number>any tax or duty being a tax or duty enumerated in the 
state List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>260228</tid>
<number>b</number>any duty referred to in article 268, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1199066</tid>
<number>c</number>any tax under the Central Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year> (74 of  
  <year>1956</year>).
which having fallen due in the Union territory of Manipur or of 
Tripura immediately before the appointed day shall, on and from that 
day, pass to the State of Manipur or of Tripura, as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>701090</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of this section shall not apply to or in 
relation to,--

<subsection><tid>167218</tid>
<number>a</number>any institution, undertaking or project the expenditure 
in relation to which is, immediately before the 
appointed day, met from and out of the Consolidated 
Fund of India;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1094</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064356</tid>
<number>b</number>any property which has been placed by the Union at the 
disposal of the administration of the Union territory 
of Manipur or of Tripura subject to the condition that 
the ownership thereof will continue to vest in the 
Union.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>167218</tid>
<number>a</number>" liability" includes liability in respect of any civil 
deposit, local fund deposit, charitable or other 
endowment, provident fund account, pension or 
actionable wrong;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064356</tid>
<number>b</number>" Union purposes" mean the purposes of Government 
relatable to any of the matters mentioned in the Union 
List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>926592</tid>
<number> 51</number> Assets and liabilities of the State of Meghalaya.
<section><tid>1347371</tid>
<number>1</number>All  
rights, liabilities and obligations whether arising out of any 
contract or otherwise, which are, immediately before the appointed 
day, the rights, liabilities and obligations of the autonomous State 
of Meghalya, including the rights, liabilities and obligations 
apportioned or to be apportioned to the share of the autonomous State 
of Meghalaya by virtue of section 58 of the Assam Reorganisation 
 (Meghalaya) Act, <year>1969</year> (55 of <year>1969</year>), shall, on and from the appointed 
day, be the rights, liabilities and obligations of the State of 
Meghalya.

</section>

<section><tid>1789773</tid>
<number>2</number>All property and assets held by the autonomous State of 
Meghalya immediately before the appointed day, including the property 
and assets apportioned or to be apportioned to the share of the 
autonomous State of Mehgalya by virtue of section 58 of the Assam 
Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, <year>1969</year> (55 of <year>1969</year>) shall, on and from 
that day, pass to the State of Meghalya.

</section>

<section><tid>336395</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) of this 
section and section 52, all rights, liabilities and obligations 
whether arising out of any contract or otherwise, which are, 
immediately before the appointed day, the rights, liabilities and 
obligations of the existing State of Assam and all property and assets 
held by the existing State of Assam immediately before the appointed 
day shall be apportioned between the State of Assam and the State of 
Meghalaya in accordance with the provisions contained in the Sixth 
Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1691388</tid>
<number> 52</number> Assets and liabilities (including public debt) relating to 
the Mizo District.
<section><tid>855162</tid>
<number>1</number>All property and assets within the Mizo  
District which are, immediately before the appointed day, vested in 
the existing State of Assam shall, as from that day, vest in the 
Union.

</section>

<section><tid>419206</tid>
<number>2</number>Unless the Central Government otherwise directs, any stores, 
articles and other goods belonging to the existing State of Assam and 
situated outside the Mizo District immediately before the appointed 
day shall, as from that day, pass to the Union if such stores, 
articles or other goods are held for, or are relatable to, the 
administration of that District.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1095</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1367805</tid>
<number>3</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations of the existing State 
of Assam in relation to the Mizo District shall, as from the appointed 
day, be the rights, liabilities and obligations of the Union.

</section>

<section><tid>601652</tid>
<number>4</number>The liability of the existing State of Assam to the Union in 
respect of the loans taken by that State from the Central Government 
shall be reduced by an amount which bears such proportion to the total 
public debt of that State immediately before the appointed day as the 
total expenditure on all capital works and other capital outlays 
incurred or deemed to have been incurred up to that day by the 
existing State of Assam in the Mizo District bears to the total 
expenditure on all capital works and other capital outlays incurred or 
deemed to have been incurred by the existing State of Assam up to the 
appointed day:
Provided that for the purposes of this sub- section the total 
public debt of the existing State of Assam shall exclude the public 
debt apportioned or apportionable to the autonomous State of Meghalaya 
under section 58 of the Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, <year>1969</year> 
 (55 of <year>1969</year>), and the total expenditure on all capital works and 
other capital outlays incurred or deemed to have been incurred by the 
existing State of Assam shall exclude such outlays incurred or deemed 
to have been incurred for the purposes of the autonomous State under 
the said section.


</section>

<section><tid>575269</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall apply to any amount which may 
be payable by the Union to the existing State of Assam in respect of 
the expenditure incurred by that State in connection with internal 
disturbances in the Mizo District.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS

PART VII

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>815523</tid>
<number> 53</number> Provisions as to certain Corporations.
<section><tid>1661761</tid>
<number>1</number>The following  
bodies corporate constituted for the existing State of Assam, namely:- 
-

<subsection><tid>905122</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Electricity Board constituted under the 
Electricity (Supply) Act, <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>323022</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Warehousing Corporation established under the 
Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year> (58 of <year>1962</year>),
shall, on and from the appointed day, continue to function in those 
areas in respect of which they were functioning immediately before


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1096</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

that day, subject to the provisions of this section and to such 
directions as may, from time to time, be issued by the Central 
Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>586801</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Board or the Corporation may include a 
direction that the Act under which the Board or the Corporation was 
constituted shall, in its application to that Board or Corporation, 
have effect subject to such exceptions and modifications as the 
Central Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1226276</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board or the Corporation referred to in sub- section (1) 
shall cease to function as from, and shall be deemed to be dissolved 
on, the expiry of a period of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> thirty- eight months] from the 
appointed day or such earlier date as the Central Government may, by 
order, appoint; and upon such dissolution, its assets, rights and 
liabilities shall be apportioned between the successor States in such 
manner as may be agreed upon among them within one year of the 
dissolution of the Board or the Corporation, as the case may be, or if 
no agreement is reached, in such manner as the Central Government may, 
by order, determine.

</section>

<section><tid>929741</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of any of the successor States 
from constituting at any time on or after the appointed day, a State 
Electricity Board or a State Warehousing Corporation for that State 
under the provisions of the Act relating to such Board or Corporation; 
and if such a Board or a Corporation is so constituted in any of the 
successor States before the dissolution of the Board or the 
Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>80841</tid>
<number>a</number>provision may be made by order of the Central Government 
enabling the new Board or the new Corporation to take 
over from the existing Board or corporation all or any 
of its undertakings, assets, rights and liabilities in 
that State, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1634777</tid>
<number>b</number>upon the dissolution of the existing Board or 
Corporation,--

<subsubsection><tid>1182667</tid>
<number>i</number>any assets, rights and liabilities which would 
otherwise have passed to that State by or under the 
provisions of sub- section (3) shall pass to the new 
Board or the new Corporation instead of to that State;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1096A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2, for" three years" (w. e. f. 20- 1-  
  <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>311201</tid>
<number>ii</number>any employees who would otherwise have been 
transferred to or re- employed by that State under sub- 
section (3), read with clause (i) of sub- section (5), 
shall be transferred to or re- employed by the new Board 
or the new Corporation instead of to or by that State.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1684737</tid>
<number>5</number>An agreement entered into between the successor States under 
sub- section (3) and an order made by the Central Government under that 
sub- section or under clause (a) of sub- section (4) may provide for the 
transfer or re- employment of any employees of the Board or the 
Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1267558</tid>
<number>i</number>to or by the successor States, in the case of an 
agreement under sub- section (3) or an order made under 
that sub- section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290450</tid>
<number>ii</number>to or by the new Board or the new Corporation 
constituted under sub- section (4), in the case of an 
order made under clause (a) of that sub- section,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1097</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and, subject to the provisions of section 58, also for the terms and 
conditions of service applicable to such employees after such transfer 
or re- employment.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1337659</tid>
<number>54</number>Continuance of arrangements in regard to generation and 
supply of electric power and supply of water. If it appears to the 
Central Government that the arrangement in regard to the generation or 
supply of electric power or the supply of water for any area or in 
regard to the execution of any project for such generation or supply 
has been or is likely to be modified to the disadvantage of that area 
by reason of the fact that it is, by virtue of the provisions of Part 
II, outside the State in which the power stations and other 
installations for the generation and supply of such power, or the 
catchment area, reservoirs and other works for the supply of water, as 
the case may be are located, the Central Government may give such 
directions as it deems fit, to the State Government or other authority 
concerned for the maintenance, so far as practicable, of the previous 
arrangement.


</article>



<article><tid>1623100</tid>
<number> 55</number> Provisions as to Assam State Financial Corporation.
<section><tid>1830167</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Assam State Financial Corporation established under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>) shall, on and from the 
appointed day, continue to function in those areas in respect of which 
it was functioning immediately before that day, subject to the 
provisions of this section and to such directions as may, from time to 
time, be issued by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>502188</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Corporation may include a direction that 
the said Act, in its application to the Corporation, shall have effect 
subject to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in 
the direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1572746</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), the Board of Directors of the Corporation may, with the 
previous approval of the Central Government and shall, if so required 
by the Central Government, convene at any time after the appointed day 
a meeting for the consideration of a scheme for the reconstitution or 
reorganisation or dissolution, as the case may be, of the Corporation, 
including proposals regarding the formation of new Corporations, and 
the transfer thereto of the assets, rights and liabilities of the 
existing Corporation, and if such a scheme is approved at a general 
meeting by a resolution passed by a majority of the shareholders 
present and voting, the scheme shall be submitted to the Central 
Government for its sanction.

</section>

<section><tid>1896104</tid>
<number>4</number>If the scheme is sanctioned by the Central Government either 
without modifications or with modifications which are approved at a 
general meeting, the Central Government shall certify the scheme, and 
upon such certification the scheme shall, notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force, be 
binding on the Corporations affected by the scheme as well as the 
shareholders and creditors thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1098</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1642594</tid>
<number>5</number>If the scheme is not so approved or sanctioned, the Central 
Government may refer the scheme to such Judge of the common High Court 
as may be nominated in this behalf by the Chief Justice thereof, and 
the decision of the Judge in regard to the scheme shall be final and 
shall be binding on the Corporations affected by the scheme as well as 
the shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>244145</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the State of Meghalaya from 
constituting, at any time after the appointed day and with the 
approval of the Central Government, a State Financial Corporation for 
that State under the State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of  
  <year>1951</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>653879</tid>
<number> 56</number> General provisions as to statutory corporations.
<section><tid>1911048</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise expressly provided by the foregoing provisions of this Part, 
where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, State Act or 
Provincial Act for the existing State of Assam or any part thereof 
has, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an inter- State 
body corporate, then, the body corporate shall, on and from the 
appointed day continue to function and operate in those areas in 
respect of which it was functioning and operating immediately before 
that day, subject to such directions as may from time to time be 
issued by the Central Government, until other provision is made by law 
in respect of the said body corporate.

</section>

<section><tid>1873928</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of any such body corporate may include a 
direction that any law by which the said body corporate is governed 
shall, in its application to that body corporate, have effect, subject 
to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in the 
direction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1699850</tid>
<number> 57</number> Temporary provisions as to continuance of certain existing 
road transport permits.
<section><tid>1731855</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
section 63 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year>, (4 of <year>1939</year>.) a permit 
granted by the State or a Regional Transport Authority in the existing 
State of Assam shall, if such permit was, immediately before the 
appointed day, valid and effective in any area therein, be deemed to 
continue to be valid and effective in that area after that day subject 
to the provisions of that Act as for the time being in force in that 
area and it shall not be necessary for any such permit to be 
countersigned by any State or Regional Transport Authority for the 
purpose of validating it for use in such area:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Government or Governments concerned, add to, amend or vary 
the conditions attached to the permit by the authority by which the 
permit was granted.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1099</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>517577</tid>
<number>2</number>No tolls, entrance fees or other charges of a like nature 
shall be levied after the appointed day in respect of any transport 
vehicle for its operations in any of the successor States under any 
such permit, if such vehicle was immediately before that day exempt 
from the payment of any such tolls, entrance fees or other charges for 
its operations within the existing State of Assam:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Government or Governments concerned, authorise the levy of 
any such tolls, entrance fees or other charges, as the case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>730003</tid>
<number> 58</number> Special provision relating to retrenchment compensation in 
certain cases. Where, on account of the reorganisation of the existing 
State of Assam under this Act, any body corporate constituted under a 
Central Act, State Act or Provincial Act, any co- operative society 
registered under any law relating to co- operative societies or any 
commercial or industrial undertaking of that State is reconstituted or 
reorganised in any manner whatsoever or is amalgamated with any other 
body corporate, co- operative society or undertaking, or is dissolved, 
and in consequence of such reconstitution, reorganisation, 
amalgamation or dissolution, any workman employed by such body 
corporate or any such co- operative society or undertaking, is 
transferred to, or re- employed by, any other body corporate, or in any 
other co- operative society or undertaking, then, notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 25F, 25FF or 25FFF of the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), such transfer or re- employment shall 
not entitle him to any compensation under that section:
Provided that--

<section><tid>218351</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service applicable to the 
workman after such transfer or re- employment are not 
less favourable to the workman than those applicable to 
him immediately before the transfer or re- employment; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>36035</tid>
<number>b</number>the employer in relation to the body corporate, the co- 
operative society or the undertaking where the workman 
transferred or re- employed is, by agreement or 
otherwise, legally liable to pay to the workman, in the 
event of his retrenchment, compensation under section 
25F, 25FF or 25FFF of the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), on the basis that his service has 
been continuous and has not been interrupted by the 
transfer or re- employment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>349470</tid>
<number>59</number>Special provisions as to income tax. Where the assets, rights 
and liabilities of any body corporate carrying on business are, under 
the provisions of this Part, transferred to any other bodies corporate 
which after the transfer carry on the same business, the losses or 
profits or gains sustained by the body corporate first mentioned 
which, but for such transfer, would have been allowed to be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1100</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

carried forward and set- off in accordance with the provisions of 
Chapter VI of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) shall be 
apportioned amongst the transferee bodies corporate in accordance with 
the rules to be made by the Central Government in this behalf and, 
upon such apportionment, the share of loss allotted to each transferee 
body corporate shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions 
of Chapter VI of the said Act as if the transferee body corporate had 
itself sustained such loss in a business carried on by it in the years 
in which these losses were sustained.



</article>



<article><tid>991051</tid>
<number> 60</number> Continuance of facilities in certain State institutions.
<section><tid>1045522</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Government of the State of Assam or Meghalaya or, as the case may 
be, the Central Government in relation to the Union territory of 
Mizoram shall, in respect of the institutions specified in the Seventh 
Schedule located in that State or Union territory, continue to provide 
facilities to any other Government aforesaid and the people of the 
States and Union territory aforesaid which shall not, in any respect, 
be less favourable to such Government and people than what were being 
provided to them before the appointed day, for such period and upon 
such terms and conditions (including those relating to any  
  contributions to be made for the provision of such facilities) as may 
be agreed upon between the said Governments before the expiry of a 
period of one year from the appointed day or, if no agreement is 
reached before such expiry, as may be fixed by order of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>980350</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may at any time before the expiry of a 
period of one year from the appointed day, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify in the Seventh Schedule any other 
institution existing on the appointed day in the said States and Union 
territory and on the issue of such notification, the said Schedule 
shall be deemed to be amended by the inclusion of the said institution 
therein.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES

PART VIII

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1908261</tid>
<number> 61</number> Provisions relating to All- India Services.
<section><tid>1921616</tid>
<number>1</number>In this  
section, the expression" joint cadre",--

<subsection><tid>1104489</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to the Indian Administrative Service, has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Indian Administrative 
Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>396882</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to the Indian Police Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Police Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>786636</tid>
<number>c</number>in relation to the Indian Forest Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Forest Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1966</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1101</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>307597</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, there shall be constituted for 
the States of Assam and Meghalaya a joint cadre of the Indian 
Administrative Service, a joint cadre of the Indian Police Service and 
a joint cadre of the Indian Forest Service.

</section>

<section><tid>1483209</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the appointed day, there shall be constituted for 
the States of Manipur and Tripura a joint cadre of the Indian 
Administrative Service, a joint cadre of the Indian Police Service and 
a joint cadre of the Indian Forest Service.

</section>

<section><tid>1613530</tid>
<number>4</number>The initial strength and composition of each of the joint 
cadres referred to in sub- sections (2) and (3) shall be such as the 
Central Government may, by order, determine before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>194917</tid>
<number>5</number>The members of each of the said Services borne on the Assam 
cadre thereof immediately before the appointed day shall be allocated 
to the joint cadre of the same Service constituted under sub- section 
 (2) and to the Union Territories cadre of that Service in such manner 
and with effect from such date or dates as the Central Government may, 
by order, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1124886</tid>
<number>6</number>Such members of each of the said Services borne on the Union 
Territories cadre thereof immediately before the appointed day, as the 
Central Government may, by order, specify, shall be allocated to the 
joint cadre of the same Service constituted under sub- section (3) with 
effect from such date or dates as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1428661</tid>
<number>7</number>Every person who, being a member of a State Civil Service of 
the existing State of Assam, is borne on a Select List for promotion 
to the Assam cadre of an All- India Service immediately before the 
appointed day shall, unless he is deemed to have been allocated to 
the Union under section 64, be deemed to have been included in the 
same order as in that List, in the Select List for promotion to the 
joint cadre of the same Service constituted under sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1273349</tid>
<number>8</number>Every person who, being a person deemed to have been 
allocated under section 62 for service in connection with the affairs 
of the State of Manipur or the State of Tripura, is borne on a Select 
List for promotion to the Union Territories cadre of an All- India 
Service immediately before the appointed day, shall be deemed to have 
been included in the same order as in that List, in the Select List 
for promotion to the joint cadre of the same Service constituted under 
sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>528270</tid>
<number>9</number>Every person who, being a person deemed to have been 
allocated to the Union under section 64, is borne on a Select List for 
promotion to the Assam cadre of an All- India Service immediately 
before the appointed day, shall be deemed to have been included in the 
Select List for promotion to the Union Territories cadre of the same 
Service and his position in the said Select List shall be determined 
by the Central Government in consultation with the Union Public 
Service Commission.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1102</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1872754</tid>
<number>10</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
operation after the appointed day of the All- India Services Act, <year>1951</year> 
 (61 of <year>1951</year>), or the rules or regulations made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>409865</tid>
<number>62</number>Provision relating to Services in Manipur and Tripura. Every 
person who immediately before the appointed day is serving in 
connection with the affairs of the Union under the administrative 
control of the Administrator of the Union territory of Manipur, or the 
Administrator of the Union territory of Tripura (including a person  
who has been placed on deputation by the Administrator concerned with 
  any other authority), shall, unless otherwise directed by an order of 
the Central Government, be deemed to have been allocated for service 
as from that day in connection with the affairs of the State of 
Manipur or, as the case may be, of the State of Tripura:
Provided that no direction shall be issued under this section 
after the expiry of a period of one year from the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>913200</tid>
<number>63</number>Special provisions relating to members of Central Health 
Service. Notwithstanding the provisions of section 62, every member of 
the Central Health Service who immediately before the appointed day is 
holding any post in the Union territory of Manipur or the Union 
territory of Tripura, being a post included in the authorised strength 
of that Service, shall, unless otherwise directed by the Central 
Government, be deemed to be on deputation on and from the appointed 
day, to the Government of the State of Manipur or, as the case may be, 
of the State of Tripura on the same terms and conditions of service as 
are applicable to him under the Central Health Service Rules, <year>1963</year>, 
but without any deputation allowance:
Provided that the period of such deputation shall in no case 
extend beyond a period of three years from the appointed day.

Explanation.-- In this section," Central Health Service" means the 
Central health Service constituted under the Central Health Service 
Rules, <year>1963</year>.



</article>



<article><tid>1250453</tid>
<number> 64</number> Provisions relating to Services in the existing State of 
Assam.
<section><tid>1483347</tid>
<number>1</number>Such persons serving in connection with the affairs of the  
existing State of Assam (including persons borne on any cadre of that  
State and serving under the Government of the autonomous State of 
  Meghalaya or on deputation to any other Government or authority) as 
may be determined at any time before or after the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>175075</tid>
<number>a</number>by agreement between the Government of the existing 
State of Assam and the Government of the autonomous 
State of Meghalaya or between the Government of the 
State of Assam and the Government of the State of 
Meghalaya, as the case may be, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443392</tid>
<number>b</number>in default of any such agreement, by the Central 
Government,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1103</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

may, notwithstanding anything in their terms of appointment or their 
conditions of service,--


<subsubsection><tid>73940</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case referred to in clause (a), by one or more 
orders made by the Government of the existing State of 
Assam or the Government of the State of Assam, as the 
case may be, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1986785</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case referred to in clause (b), by one or more 
orders made by the Central Government,
be required to serve in connection with the affairs of the State of 
Meghalaya and every such person shall accordingly be deemed to have 
been allocated to that State with effect from such date as may be 
specified in the order.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>450394</tid>
<number>2</number>Such persons serving in connection with the affairs of the 
existing State of Assam (including persons borne on any cadre of the  
existing State of Assam and serving under the Government of the 
autonomous State of Meghalaya or on deputation to any other Government 
  or authority), as the Central Government may, at any time before or 
after the appointed day, determine after consultation with the 
Government of the existing State of Assam, as the case may be, may, 
notwithstanding anything in the terms of their appointment or their 
conditions of service, by one or more orders made by the Central 
Government, be required to serve in connection with the administration 
of the Union territory of Mizoram, and every such person shall, 
accordingly, be deemed to have been allocated to the Union with effect 
from such date as may be specified in the order:
Provided that every person borne on any cadre of the existing 
State of Assam and serving in the Mizo District immediately before the 
appointed day shall, unless otherwise directed by the Administrator 
of the Union territory of Mizoram, continue to serve on and from the 
appointed day, in connection with the administration of that Union 
territory until any order is made under this sub- section in respect of 
such person or the expiry of a period of three years from the 
appointed day, whichever is earlier.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932148</tid>
<number>65</number>Provisions relating to Services in the autonomous State of 
Meghalaya. Every person who immediately before the appointed day is 
serving in connection with the affairs of the autonomous State of 
Meghalaya (including a person on deputation from the Government of  
  that autonomous State to any other Government or authority) not being 
a person to whom section 64 applies, shall be deemed to have been 
allocated to serve as from that day in connection with the affairs of 
the State of Meghalaya.


</article>



<article><tid>895025</tid>
<number> 66</number> Other provisions relating to Services.
<section><tid>1716246</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing in this  
section or sections 62 to 65 (both inclusive) shall be deemed to 
affect on or after the appointed day the operation of the provisions 
of Chapter I of Part XIV of the Constitution in relation to 
determination of conditions of service of persons serving in 
connection with

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1104</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the affairs of the State of Manipur, Meghalaya or Tripura or the Union 
territory of Mizoram:

Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately 
before the appointed day in the case of any person deemed to have been 
allocated to the State of Manipur or the State of Tripura under 
section 62 or to the State of Meghalaya under sub- section (1) of 
section 64 or section 65 or to the Union under sub- section (2) of 
section 64 shall not be varied to his disadvantage except with the 
previous approval of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1656187</tid>
<number>2</number>All services prior to the appointed day rendered by a person-

<subsection><tid>100136</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is deemed to have been allocated to any State 
under section 62 or section 64 or section 65, shall be 
deemed to have been rendered in connection with the 
affairs of that State,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940048</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is deemed to have been allocated to the Union in 
connection with the administration of the Union 
territory of Mizoram, shall be deemed to have been 
rendered in connection with the affairs of the Union,
for the purposes of the rules regulating his conditions of service.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>277881</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sections 62, 64 and 65 shall not apply in 
relation to members of any All- India Service.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>89957</tid>
<number> 67</number> Provisions as to continuance of officers in same posts.
<section><tid>1326377</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every person who, immediately before the appointed day is holding or 
discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the 
administration of the Union territory of Manipur or Union territory of 
Tripura, shall continue to hold the same post or office in the State 
of Manipur, or, as the case may be, in the State of Tripura and shall 
be deemed, on and from that day, to have been duly appointed to the 
post or office by the Government of, or other appropriate authority in 
the State concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>118745</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person who immediately before the appointed day is 
holding or discharging the duties of any post or office in connection 
with the affairs of the existing State of Assam and, as from the 
appointed day, such duties become duties in connection with the 
affairs of the State of Meghalaya or administration of the Union 
territory of Mizoram, then, he shall continue to hold the same post or 
office in that State or Union territory and shall be deemed, on and 
from that day, to have been duly appointed to the post or office by 
the Government or Administrator of, or other appropriate authority in, 
that State or Union territory, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>690616</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a person who immediately before the appointed day is 
holding or discharging the duties of any post or office in connection 
with the affairs of the autonomous State of Meghalaya and, as from the 
appointed day, such duties become duties in connection with the 
affairs of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

State of Meghalaya, then, he shall continue to hold the same post or 
office in the State of Meghalaya and shall be deemed, on and from that 
day, to have been duly appointed to the post or office by the 
Government of, or other appropriate authority in, the State of 
Meghalaya.


</section>

<section><tid>1631088</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) or sub- section 
 (3) shall be deemed to prevent a competent authority, on and from the 
appointed day, from passing in relation to any person referred to in 
that sub- section any order affecting his continuance in such post or 
office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1617484</tid>
<number> 68</number> Advisory Committees. The Central Government may, by order, 
establish one or more Advisory Committees for the purpose of assisting 
it in regard to--
<section><tid>1764904</tid>
<number>a</number>the discharge of any of its functions under this Part; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1074686</tid>
<number>b</number>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all 
persons affected by the provisions of this Part and the 
proper consideration of any representations made by 
such persons.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>66328</tid>
<number>69</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. The Central 
Government may give such directions to the State Governments of Assam, 
Manipur, Meghalaya and Tripura and to the Administrator of the Union 
territory of Mizoram as may appear to it to be necessary for the 
purpose of giving effect to the foregoing provisions of this Part and 
the State Governments and the Administrator shall comply with such 
directions.


</article>



<article><tid>1330452</tid>
<number> 70</number> Provisions as to State Public Service Commission.
<section><tid>1664076</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Public Service Commission for the existing State of Assam shall, on 
and from the appointed day, be deemed to be the Public Service 
Commission for the State of Assam.

</section>

<section><tid>1465322</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person holding office immediately before the appointed 
day as Chairman or other member of the Public Service Commission for 
the existing State of Assam shall, as from the appointed day, be the 
Chairman or, as the case may be, the other member of the Public 
Service Commission for the State of Assam.

</section>

<section><tid>861566</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who becomes Chairman or other member of the 
Public Service Commission for the State of Assam on the appointed day 
under sub- section (2) shall--

<subsection><tid>1236701</tid>
<number>a</number>be entitled to receive from the Government of the State 
of Assam conditions of service not less favourable than 
those to which he was entitled under the provisions 
applicable to him immediately before the appointed day; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300116</tid>
<number>b</number>subject to the proviso to clause (2) of article 316, 
hold office or continue to hold office until the 
expiration of his term of office as determined under 
the provisions applicable to him immediately before the 
appointed day.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1106</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART IX

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>587175</tid>
<number> 71</number> Amendment of articles 210, 239A, 244, 244A, 275, 332, 371B 
and Fifth and Sixth Schedules to the Constitution. On and from the 
appointed day--
<section><tid>487160</tid>
<number>a</number>in article 210, in the proviso to clause (2), for the 
words" Legislature of the State of Himachal Pradesh", 
the words" Legislatures of the States of Himachal 
Pradesh, Manipur, Meghalaya and Tripura" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1376546</tid>
<number>b</number>in article 239A, in clause (1), the words" Manipur, 
Tripura," shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1808885</tid>
<number>c</number>in article 244,--

<subsection><tid>1346816</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (1), for the words" the State of 
Assam", the words" the States of Assam and Meghalaya" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1432089</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (2), for the words" the State of 
Assam", the words" the States of Assam and Meghalaya 
and the Union territory of Mizoram" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1556</tid>
<number>d</number>in article 244A, in clause (1), for the word and letter 
" Part A", the word and figure" Part I" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1159577</tid>
<number>e</number>in article 275, in clause (a) of the second proviso to 
clause (1), for the word and letter" Part A", the word 
and figure" Part I" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>455089</tid>
<number>f</number>in article 332,--

<subsection><tid>1154679</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (5), the words" except in the case 
of the constituency comprising the cantonment and 
municipality of shillong" shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1889950</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (6), the words" except from the 
constituency comprising the cantonment and municipality 
of Shillong" shall be omitted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1833765</tid>
<number>g</number>in article 371B, for the word and letter" Part A", the 
word and figure" Part I" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>846465</tid>
<number>h</number>in the Fifth Schedule to the Constitution, in paragraph 
1, for the words" State of Assam", the words" States of 
Assam and Meghalaya" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>885687</tid>
<number>i</number>the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution shall stand 
amended as directed in the Eighth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1107</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1953257</tid>
<number>72</number>Amendment of Act 2 of <year>1934</year>. On and from the appointed day, in 
section 21A of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>, in sub- section 
1, the brakets and words" (including the autonomous State of  
  Meghalaya)" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>578470</tid>
<number>73</number>Amendment of Act 64 of <year>1950</year>. On and from the appointed day, 
in section 47A of the Road Transport Corporations Act, <year>1950</year>, in the 
Explanation to sub- section 1, after clause (ii), the following 
clause shall be inserted, namely:--
" (iii) in relation to the Assam State Road Transport 
Corporation, shall mean the Government of the State of 
Assam or of Meghalaya as formed under the North- Eastern 
Areas (Reorganisation) Act, <year>1971</year>.".



</article>



<article><tid>334991</tid>
<number> 74</number> Amendment of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>. On and from the appointed day, 
in the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>,--
<section><tid>1702311</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (c) of section 15, the following clause shall 
be substituted, namely:--
" (c) the Eastern Zone, comprising the States of 
Bihar, West Bengal and Orissa;";


</section>

<section><tid>1931553</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (1) of section 16, clause (d) shall be 
omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1103233</tid>
<number> 75</number> Amendment of Act 20 of <year>1963</year>. On and from the appointed day, 
in the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year>,--
<section><tid>352798</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (h) of sub- section (1) of section 2, the words 
" Manipur, Tripura," shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>681743</tid>
<number>b</number>in section 44, sub- section (2) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1998585</tid>
<number>c</number>section 52 shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>832719</tid>
<number> 76</number> Amendment of Act 56 of <year>1955</year> and the Tripura (Courts) Order, 
<year>1950</year>. On and from the appointed day,--
<section><tid>1995653</tid>
<number>a</number>the Manipur (Courts) Act, <year>1955</year> shall stand amended as 
directed in the Ninth Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1721863</tid>
<number>b</number>the Tripura (Courts) Order, <year>1950</year> shall stand amended as 
directed in the Tenth Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1896128</tid>
<number>77</number>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of Part II shall 
not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which 
any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or 
applies, and the territorial references in any such law to the 
existing State of Assam or the autonomous State of Meghalaya or the 
Union territory of Manipur or the Union territory of Tripura or the 
North- East Frontier Agency shall, until otherwise provided by a 
competent Legislature or other competent authority, be construed as 
meaning the territories within that State or autonomous State or Union 
territory or Agency immediately before the appointed day.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1108</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>542051</tid>
<number> 78</number> Continuance of existing District Councils and Regional 
Council and members thereof. For the removal of doubt, it is hereby 
declared that all District Councils and the Regional Council 
constituted under the provisions of the Sixth Schedule to the 
Constitution and functioning immediately before the appointed day in 
the respective autonomous districts and in the autonomous region 
shall, as from that day, be deemed to have been constituted under the 
said Schedule as amended by clause (i) of section 71, read with the 
Eighth Schedule and accordingly,--
<section><tid>1040719</tid>
<number>a</number>every such District Council and the Regional Council 
shall, unless sooner dissolved, continue to function in 
the respective autonomous districts and in the 
autonomous region, notwithstanding that any such 
district or region ceases to be comprised in the 
territories of the State of Assam, by virtue of the 
provisions of Part II; and

</section>

<section><tid>740110</tid>
<number>b</number>every member of such District Council or Regional 
Council shall continue to be a member thereof for the 
unexpired term of his office as such.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>676673</tid>
<number> 79</number> Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application of any law in relation to any of the States of Union 
territories formed or established by the provisions of Part II, the 
appropriate Government may, before the expiration of two years from 
the appointed day, by order, make such adaptations and modifications 
of the law, whether by way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary 
or expedient, and thereupon every such law shall have effect subject 
to the adaptations and modifications so made until altered, repealed 
or amended by a competent Legislature or other competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" the appropriate 
Government" means--

<section><tid>1430054</tid>
<number>a</number>as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated in 
the Union List in the Seventh Schedule to the 
Constitution, the Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>960773</tid>
<number>b</number>as respects any other law,--

<subsection><tid>1665353</tid>
<number>i</number>in its application to a State, the State 
Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1732619</tid>
<number>ii</number>in its application to a Union territory, the 
Central Government.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1997722</tid>
<number> 80</number> Power to construe laws.
<section><tid>1351244</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding that no provision  
or insufficient provision has been made under section 79 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya or Tripura or to the Union territory of 
Mizoram or Arunachal Pradesh construe the law in such manner, without 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper in regard to 
the matter before the court, tribunal or authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1109</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1749630</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference to the High Court of Assam or the High Court of 
Assam and Nagaland or to the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Manipur or the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Tripura in any 
law shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed, on and 
from the appointed day, as a reference to the common High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1582844</tid>
<number>81</number>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory 
functions. The Central Government, as respects the Union territory of 
Mizoram or Arunachal Pradesh and the State Government as respects any 
new State established or formed by the provisions of Part Ii may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify the authority, officer 
or person who, as from the appointed day, shall be competent to 
exercise such functions exercisable under any law in force on that day 
as may be mentioned in that notification and such law shall have 
effect accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>714959</tid>
<number> 82</number> Legal proceedings.
<section><tid>120215</tid>
<number>1</number>Where immediately before the appointed  
day the Union is a party to any legal proceedings with respect to any 
property, right or liability and such property, right or liability 
devolves on the State of Manipur or the State of tripura under this 
Act, then, the State of Manipur or, as the case may be, the State of 
Tripura shall be deemed to be substituted for the Union as a party to 
those proceedings and the proceedings may continue accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1182849</tid>
<number>2</number>Where immediately before the appointed day the autonomous 
State of Meghalaya is a party to any legal proceedings with respect to 
any property, right or liability of that State, and such property, 
right or liability devolves on the State of Meghalaya under this Act, 
then, the State of Meghalaya shall be deemed to be substituted for the 
autonomous State of Meghalaya as a party to those proceedings and the 
proceedings may continue accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>673275</tid>
<number>3</number>Where immediately before the appointed day the existing State 
of Assam is a party to any legal proceedings with respect to any 
property, rights or liabilities subject to apportionment under this 
Act, the successor State, which succeeds to, or acquires a share in, 
that property or those rights or liabilities by virtue of any 
provision of this Act, shall be deemed to be substituted for the 
existing State of Assam as a party to those proceedings or added as a 
party therto, as the case may be, and the proceedings may continue 
accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1344456</tid>
<number>83</number>Rights of pleaders to practise in certain cases. Any person 
who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the existing State 
of Assam shall, for a period of one year from that day, continue to be 
entitled to practise in those courts, notwithstanding that the whole 
or any part of the territories within the jurisdiction of those courts 
has been transferred to the State Meghalaya or to a Union territory.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1110</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>864396</tid>
<number> 84</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>986819</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within a State or Union territory shall, if it is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to the territories which as from that day are the 
territories of another State or Union territory, stand transferred 
to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer in that 
other State or Union territory, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1667846</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
common High Court and the decision of that High Court shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>896424</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section.--

<subsection><tid>1830851</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568150</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
a State or a Union territory means--

<subsubsection><tid>541378</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in 
that State or Union territory in which or before whom 
the proceeding would have lain if it had been 
instituted after the appointed day; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1515274</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State or Union territory 
as may be determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of that State or the Central Government, as 
the case may be, or before the appointed day by the 
Government of the existing State of Assam or the 
Government of the autonomous State of Meghalaya or the 
Central Government, as the case may be, to be the 
corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>32145</tid>
<number>85</number>Provisions as to continuance of courts, etc. All courts and 
tribunals and all authorities discharging lawful functions throughout 
the existing State of Assam or the Union territory of Manipur or the 
Union territory of Tripura or any part of such State or Union 
territory immediately before the appointed day shall, unless their 
continuance is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or until 
other provision is made by a competent Legislature or other competent 
authority, continue to exercise their respective functions.


</article>



<article><tid>1394742</tid>
<number>86</number>Effect of provisions of the Act inconsistent with other laws. 
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1111</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>63132</tid>
<number> 87</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>761081</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>11055</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1004978</tid>
<number> 88</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>760402</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1859309</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>