<act><title>
THE
RAILWAY CLAIMS TRIBUNAL
ACT, 1987</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and conmencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint.
   







 



</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section><number>a</number> “application” means
      an application made under section 16;
     	(a)
	“application” means an application made under section 16;"
     

 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “appointed day” means
    the date<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> with effect from
    which the Claims Tribunal is established under section 3;
     	(b) 	“appointed day” means the date3 with effect from which
the Claims Tribunal is established under section 3;"
     

 </section><section><number>c</number> “Bench” means a Bench
    of the Claims Tribunal; 	(c)
	“Bench” means a Bench of the Claims Tribunal;"
     

 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “Chairman” means the
    Chairman of the Claims Tribunal; 	(d)
	“Chairman” means the Chairman of the Claims Tribunal;"
     

 </section><section>
<number>e</number> “Claims Tribunal”
    means the Railway Claims Tribunal established under section 3;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
“Judicial Member” means a Member of the Claims Tribunal appointed as
                such under this Act, and includes the hairma or Vice- Chairman who possesses
                any of the qualifications specified in sub-section (3) of section 5; 	(f)
	“Judicial Member” means a Member of the Claims Tribunal appointed as such
under this Act, and includes the Chairman or Vice-Chairman who possesses any of
the qualifications specified in sub-section (3) of section 5;"
     

 </section><section><number>g</number>
“Member” means a Member (whether Judicial or Technical) of the Claims
    Tribunal,and includes the Chairman and Vice-Chairman;
     	(g)
	“Member” means a Member (whether Judicial or Technical) of the Claims
Tribunal, and includes the Chairman and Vice-Chairman;"
     

 </section><section>
<number>h</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official
    Gazette;  	(h) 	“notification” means a
notification published in the Official Gazette; "
     

 </section><section> <number>i</number>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules;
 </section><section><number>j</number> “Railways Act” means the Indian Railways Act, 1890
    (9 of 1890);
     (j) 	“Railways Act” means the
Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890);"
     
 


 </section><section>
<number>k</number> “rules” means rules
    made under this Act; 	(k)
	“rules” means rules made under this Act;"
     
 


 </section><section><number>l</number> “Technical Member”
    means a Member of the Claims Tribunal who is not a Judicial Member, and includes
    the Chairman or a Vice-Chairman who possesses any of the qualifications
    specified in sub-section (4) of section 5; 	(l) 	“Technical Member” means a Member of the
Claims Tribunal who is not a Judicial Member, and includes the Chairman or a
Vice-Chairman who possesses any of the qualifications specified in sub-section (4)
of section 5;"
     
 


 </section><section><number>m</number>
“Vice-Chairman” means a Vice-Chairman of the Claims Tribunal. 	(m)	“Vice-Chairman”
means a Vice-Chairman of the Claims Tribunal."
     
 

</section>
 Explanation.—References to the
      Vice-Chairman in this Act shall be construed as references to each of the
      Vice-Chairman;
   			Explanation.—References
to the Vice-Chairman in this Act shall be construed as references to each of
the Vice-Chairman;"
   
 


 
 <section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>n</number>
“untoward incident” shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause
    (c) of section 123 of the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989); 	1[(n)	“untoward incident”
shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (c) of section 123 of the
Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989);"
     
 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>o</number>]
words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the
    Railways Act or the rules made thereunder shall have the meanings respectively
    assigned to them in that Act or the said rules.]  2[(o)]
	words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the
Railways Act or the rules made thereunder shall have the meanings respectively
assigned to them in that Act or the said rules.]"
     
 


</section>




</article> 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Establishment of Railway Claims Tribunal.—The
Central Government shall, by notification, establish a Claims Tribunal, to be
known as the Railway Claims Tribunal, to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and
authority conferred on it by or under this Act. 3. Establishment of Railway
Claims Tribunal.—The Central
Government shall, by notification, establish a Claims Tribunal, to be known as
the Railway Claims Tribunal, to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority
conferred on it by or under this Act."

 2[(o)] 	words and
expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Railways Act or
the rules made thereunder shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them
in that Act or the said rules.]"
 
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>4</number>
Composition of Claims Tribunal and Benches thereof.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman, four Vice-Chairmen and such
number of Judicial Members and Technical Members as the Central Government may
deem fit and, subject to the other provisions of this Act, the jurisdiction,
powers and authority of the Claims Tribunal may be exercised by Benches thereof. 4. Composition of Claims
Tribunal and Benches thereof.—(1) The
Claims Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman, four Vice-Chairmen and such number
of Judicial Members and Technical Members as the Central Government may deem
fit and, subject to the other provisions of this Act, the jurisdiction, powers
and authority of the Claims Tribunal may be exercised by Benches thereof."

 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the other provisions of this Act, a Bench shall consist of one
Judicial Member and one Technical Member. (2) Subject to the other
provisions of this Act, a Bench shall consist of one Judicial Member and one
Technical Member."

 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairman— (3) Notwithstanding anything
contained in sub-section (1), the Chairman—"

 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> may,
in addition to discharging the functions of the Judicial Member or the Technical
Member of the Bench to which he is appointed, discharge the functions of the
Judicial Member or, as the case may be, the Technical Member, of any other
Bench; 	(a)	may, in addition to
discharging the functions of the Judicial Member or the Technical Member of the
Bench to which he is appointed, discharge the functions of the Judicial Member
or, as the case may be, the Technical Member, of any other Bench;"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> may
transfer a Vice-Chairman or other Member from one Bench to another Bench; 	(b)	may transfer a Vice-Chairman
or other Member from one Bench to another Bench;"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> may
authorise the Vice-Chairman or the Judicial Member or the Technical Member
appointed to one Bench to discharge also the functions of the Vice-Chairman or,
as the case may be, the Judicial Member or the Technical Member of another
Bench. 	(c)	may authorise the
Vice-Chairman or the Judicial Member or the Technical Member appointed to one
Bench to discharge also the functions of the Vice-Chairman or, as the case may
be, the Judicial Member or the Technical Member of another Bench."
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this section,
it shall be competent for the Chairman or any other Member authorised by the
Chairman in this behalf to function as a Bench consisting of a single Member and
exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Claims Tribunal in
respect of such classes of cases or such matters pertaining to such classes of
cases as the Chairman may, by general or special order, specify: (4) Notwithstanding anything
contained in the foregoing provisions of this section, it shall be competent
for the Chairman or any other Member authorised by the Chairman in this behalf
to function as a Bench consisting of a single Member and exercise the
jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Claims Tribunal in respect of such
classes of cases or such matters pertaining to such classes of cases as the
Chairman may, by general or special order, specify\:"

 


 Provided
that if at any stage of the hearing of any such case or matter, it appears to
the Chairman or such Member that the case or matter is of such a nature that it
ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter may
be transferred by the Chairman or, as the case may be, referred to him for
transfer, to such Bench as the Chairman may deem fit. Provided that if at any stage
of the hearing of any such case or matter, it appears to the Chairman or such
Member that the case or matter is of such a nature that it ought to be heard by
a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter may be transferred by the
Chairman or, as the case may be, referred to him for transfer, to such Bench as
the Chairman may deem fit."

 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Benches shall sit at such
places as the Central Government may, by notification, specify.
</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>5</number>
Qualifications for appointment as Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairman unless he— 5. Qualifications for
appointment as Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member.—(1) A person shall not be qualified for appointment
as the Chairman unless he—"

 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court; or 	(a)	is, or has been, a Judge of
a High Court; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
has, for at least two years, held the office of a Vice-Chairman. 	(b)	has,
for at least two years, held the office of a Vice-Chairman."
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Vice-Chairman unless
he— (2) A person shall not be
qualified for appointment as the Vice-Chairman unless he—"

 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or 	(a)	is,
or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
has been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in
Grade I of that service or any higher post for at least five years; or 	(b)	has
been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in Grade I of
that service or any higher post for at least five years; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
has, for at least five years, held a civil judicial post carrying a scale
of pay which is not less than that of a Joint Secretary to the Government of
India; or 	(c)	has, for at least five
years, held a civil judicial post carrying a scale of pay which is not less
than that of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
has, for at least five years, held a post under a railway administration
carrying a scale of pay which is not less than that of a Joint Secretary to the
Government of India and has adequate knowledge of rules and procedure of, and
experience in, claims and commercial matters relating to railways; or 	(d)	has,
for at least five years, held a post under a railway administration carrying a
scale of pay which is not less than that of a Joint Secretary to the Government
of India and has adequate knowledge of rules and procedure of, and experience
in, claims and commercial matters relating to railways; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
has, for a period of not less than three years, held office as a Judicial
Member or a Technical Member. 	(e)	has, for a period of not
less than three years, held office as a Judicial Member or a Technical
Member."
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Judicial Member unless
he— (3) A person shall not be
qualified for appointment as a Judicial Member unless he—"

 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or 	(a)	is,
or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
has been a Member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in
Grade I of that service for at least three years; or 	(b)	has
been a Member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in Grade I of
that service for at least three years; or"
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
has, for at least three years, held a civil judicial post carrying a
scale of pay which is not less than of a Joint Secretary to the Government of
India. 	(c)	has, for at least three
years, held a civil judicial post carrying a scale of pay which is not less
than of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India."
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Technical Member unless he
has, for at least three years, held a post under a railway administration
carrying a scale of pay which is not less than that of a Joint secretary to the
Government of India and has adequate knowledge of rules and procedure of, and
experience in, claims and commercial matters relating to railways. 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (6), the Chairman, Vice-Chairman and
every other Member shall be appointed by the President. (5) Subject to the provisions
of sub-section (6), the Chairman, Vice-Chairman and every other Member shall be
appointed by the President."

 


(6) No appointment
of a person as the Chairman shall be made except after consultation with the
Chief Justice of India.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Vice-Chairman to act as Chairman or to 
      discharge his functions in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> In the event of the occurrence of any 
      vacancy in the office of the Chairman by reason of his death, resignation 
      or otherwise, such one of the Vice-Chairmen as the Central Government may, 
      by notification, authorise in this behalf, shall act as the Chairman until 
      the date on which a new Chairman, appointed in accordance with the 
      provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy, enters upon his 
      office.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the Chairman is unable to discharge his 
      functions owing to absence, illness or any other cause, such one of the 
      Vice-Chairman as the Central Government may, by notification, authorise in 
      this behalf, shall discharge the functions of the Chairman until the date 
      on which the Chairman resumes his duties.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Term of office.—The Chairman,
Vice-Chairman or other Member shall hold office as such for a term of five years
from the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains,—
 <section><number>a</number>
in the case of the Chairman, the age of sixty-five years; and
 </section><section><number>b</number>
in the case of the Vice-Chairman or any other Member, the age of
sixty-two years,
 whichever
is earlier.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Resignation and removal.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member may, by notice in writing under his hand
addressed to the President, resign his office:
 Provided
that the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member shall, unless he is permitted
by the President to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold office until
the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such notice or until a
person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office or until the
expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman, Vice-Chairman or any other Member shall not be removed from his
office except by an order made by the President on the ground of proved
misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court
in which such Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member had been informed of the
charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect
of those charges.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the
investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or
other Member referred to in sub-section (2).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of service of Chairman,
Vice-Chairman and other Members.—The
salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of
service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the
Chairman, Vice-Chairman and other Members shall be such as may be prescribed:
 Provided
that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of
service of the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member shall be varied to his
disadvantage after his appointment.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Provision as to the holding of offices by Chairman, Vice-Chairman etc., on
ceasing to be such Chairman or Vice-Chairman, etc.—On
ceasing to hold office—
 <section><number>a</number>
the Chairman of the Claims Tribunal shall be ineligible for further
employment either under the Government of India or under the Government of a
State;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
a Vice-Chairman shall, subject to the other provisions of this Act, be
eligible for appointment as the Chairman of the Claims Tribunal, or as the
Chairman, Vice-Chairman or member of any other Tribunal established under any
law for the time being in force, but not for any other employment either under
the Government of India or under the Government of a State;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
a Member (other than the Chairman or Vice-Chairman) shall, subject to the
other provisions of this Act, be eligible for appointment as the Chairman or
Vice-Chairman or as the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or member of any other Tribunal
established under any law for the time being in force, but not for any other
employment either under the Government of India or under the Government of a
State;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member shall not appear, act or
plead before the Claims Tribunal.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section, employment under the Government of India or under
the Government of a State includes employment under any local or other authority
within the territory of India or under the control of the Government of India or
under any corporation or society owned or controlled by the Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Financial and administrative powers of Chairman.—The
Chairman shall exercise such financial and administrative powers over the
Benches as may be vested in him under the rules:
 Provided
that the Chairman shall have authority to delegate such of his financial and
administrative powers as he may think fit to the Vice-Chairman or any other
officer of the Claims Tribunal, subject to the condition that the Vice-Chairman
or such officer shall, while exercising such delegated powers, continue to act
under the direction, control and supervision of the Chairman.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Staff of Claims Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Government shall determine the nature and categories of the officers and
other employees required to assist the Claims Tribunal in the discharge of its
functions and provide the Claims Tribunal with such officers and other employees
as it may think fit.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The officers and other employees of the Claims Tribunal shall discharge their
functions under the general superintendence of the Chairman.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other
employees of the Claims Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Jurisdiction, powers and authority of Claims Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall exercise, on and from the appointed day, all such
jurisdiction, powers and authority as were exercisable immediately before that
day by any civil court or a Claims Commissioner appointed under the provisions
of the Railways Act,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
relating to the responsibility of the railway administrations as carriers
under Chapter VII of the Railways Act in respect of claims for—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>
compensation for loss, destruction, damage, deterioration or non-delivery
of animals or goods entrusted to a railway administration for carriage by
railway;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>
compensation payable under section 82A of the Railways Act
or the rules made thereunder; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
in respect of the claims for refund of fares or part thereof or for
refund of any freight paid in respect of animals or goods entrusted to a railway
administration to be carried by railway. 
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall also exercise, on and from the date of commencement of
the provisions of section 124A of the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989), all such
jurisdiction, powers and authority as were exercisable immediately before that
date by any civil court in respect of claims for compensation now payable by the
railway administration under section 124A of the said Act or the rules made
thereunder.]
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The provisions of the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Railways
Act, 1989 (24 of 1989)] and the rules made thereunder shall, so far as may be,
be applicable to the inquiring into or determining, any claims by the Claims
Tribunal under this Act.
   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Distribution of business amongst Benches.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any Benches are constituted, the Central Government may, from time to
time, by notification, make provisions as to the distribution of the business of
the Claims Tribunal amongst the Benches and specify the matters which may be
dealt with by each Bench.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If any question arises as to whether any matter falls within the purview of the
business allocated to a Bench, the decision of the Chairman shall be final.
 Explanation.—For
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the expression “matters”
includes an application under section 20.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Bar of jurisdiction.—On and from the
appointed day, no court or other authority shall have, or be entitled to,
exercise any jurisdiction, powers or authority in relation to the matters
referred to in <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[sub-sections

<section><number>1</number> and (1A)] of section 13. 


  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Application to Claims Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person seeking any relief in respect of the matters referred to in sub-section
(1) <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[or
sub-section (1A)] of section 13 may make an application to the Claims Tribunal.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every application under sub-section (1) shall be in such form and be accompanied
by such documents or other evidence and by such fee in respect of the filing of
such application and by such other fees for the service or execution of
processes as may be prescribed:
 Provided
that no such fee shall be payable in respect of an application under sub-clause
(ii) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) 1[or,
as the case may be, sub-section (1A)] of section 13.
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>17</number>
Limitation.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall not admit an application for any claim—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
under sub-clause (i) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 13
unless the application is made within three years from the date on which the
goods in question were entrusted to the railway administration for carriage by
railway;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 under sub-clause
(ii) of clause (a) of sub-section (1) <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or,
as the case may be, sub-section (1A)] of section 13 unless the application is
made within one year of occurrence of the accident;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 under clause (b)
of sub-section (1) of section 13 unless the application is made within three
years from the date on which the fare or freight is paid to the railway
administration:
 Provided
that no application for any claim referred to in sub-clause (i) of clause (a) of
sub-section (1) of section 13 shall be preferred to the Claims Tribunal until
the expiration of three months next after the date on which the intimation of
the claim has been preferred under section 78B of the Railways Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), an application may be
entertained after the period specified in sub-section (1) if the applicant
satisfies the Claims Tribunal that he had sufficient cause for not making the
application within such period.
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number>
Procedure and powers of Claims Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the Code of
Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by the principles of
natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this Act and of any
rules, the Claims Tribunal shall have powers to regulate its own procedure
including the fixing of places and times of its enquiry.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Claims Tribunal shall decide every application as expeditiously as possible
and ordinarily every application shall be decided on a perusal of documents,
written representations and affidavits and after hearing such oral arguments as
may be advanced.
  













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
Right to legal representation and presenting officers.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person making an application to the Claims Tribunal may either appear in
person or take the assistance of a legal practitioner of his choice to present
his case before the Claims Tribunal.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A railway administration may authorise one or more legal practitioners or any of
its offcers to act as presenting officers and every person so authorised by it
may present its case with respect to any application before the Claims Tribunal.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Power of Chairman to transfer cases from one Bench to another.—On
the application of any of the parties and after notice to the parties, and after
hearing such of them as he may desire to be heard, or on his own motion without
such notice, the Chairman may transfer any case pending before one Bench, for
disposal, to any other Bench.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Decision to be by majority.—If the
Members of a Bench differ in opinion on any point, they shall state the point or
points on which they differ, and make a reference to the Chairman who shall
either hear the point or points himself or refer the case for hearing on such
point or points by one or more of the other Members and such point or points
shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority of the Members who
have heard the case, including those who first heard it.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Execution of orders of Claims Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number>
An order made by the Claims Tribunal under this Act shall be executable by the
Claims Tribunal as a decree of civil court, and, for this purpose, the Claims
Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Claims Tribunal may
transmit any order made by it to a civil court having local jurisdiction and
such civil court shall execute the order as if it were a decree made by that
court.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>23</number>
Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as provided in
sub-section (2) and notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or in any other law, an appeal shall lie from every
order, not being an interlocutory order, of the Claims Tribunal, to the High
Court having jurisdiction over the place where the Bench is located.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No appeal shall lie from an order passed by the Claims Tribunal with the consent
of the parties.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every appeal under this section shall be perferred within a period of ninety
days from the date of the order appealed against.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number>Transfer
of pending cases.—
<section><number>1</number> Every suit,
claim or other legal proceeding (other than an appeal) pending before any court,
Claims Commissioner or other authority immediately before the appointed day, <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[or,
as the case may be, the date of commencement of the provisions of sub-section
(1A) of Section 13] being a suit, claim or proceeding the cause of action
whereon it is based is such that it would have been, if it had arisen after the
appointed day, <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[or,
as the case may be, the date of commencement of the provisions of sub-section
(1A) of section 13] within the jurisdiction of the Claims Tribunal, shall stand
transferred on <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[that
day or, as the case may be, date] to the Claims Tribunal.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where any suit, claim or other legal proceeding stands transferred from any
court, Claims Commissioner or other authority to the Claims Tribunal under sube-section
(1),—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the court, Claims Commissioner or other authority shall, as soon as may
be after such transfer, forward the records of such suit, claim or other legal
proceeding to the Claims Tribunal;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Claims Tribunal may, on receipt of such records, proceed to deal with
such suit, claim or other legal proceeding, so far as may be, in the same manner
as an application, from the stage which was reached before such transfer or from
any earlier stage or de novo as the Claims Tribunal may deem fit.
   








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number>
Proceedings before Claims Tribunal to be judicial proceedings.—All
proceedings before the Claims Tribunal shall be deemed to be judicial
proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal
Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number>Members
and staff of Claims Tribunal to be public servants.—The
Chairman, Vice-Chairman and other Members and the officers and other employees
of the Claims Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. </title>—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or against the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member, or any other person authorised by the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Act to have overriding effect. —</title>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number> Power to remove 
      difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
      difficulty arises in giving effect to provisions of this Act, the Central 
      Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
      provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to 
      it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 Provided that no such order shall be made after 
      the expiry of a period of three years from the appointed day.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every order made under this section shall, 
      as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of 
      Parliament.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>30</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central
Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this
Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the procedure under sub-section (3) of section 8 for the investigation of
misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairman, Vice-Chairman or other Member;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of
service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the
Chairman, Vice-Chairman and other Members under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the financial and administrative powers which the Chairman may exercise
over the Benches under section 11;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
the salaries and allowances and conditions of service of officers and
other employees of the Claims Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
the form of application , the documents and other evidence to be
accompanied with such application and fee in respect of filing of such
application and fee for the service or execution of processes under sub-section
(2) of section 66;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the rules subject to which the Claims Tribunal shall have powers to
regulate its own procedure under sub-section (1) of section 18 and the
additional matters in which the Claims Tribunal may exercise powers of civil
court under clause (i) of sub-section (3) of that section;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rule.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>30A</number>
Power to make rules retrospectively.—The
power to make rules under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 30 shall
include the power to make such rules or any of them retrospectively from a date
not earlier than the date on which this Act received the assent of the
President, but no such retrospective effect shall be given to any such rule so
as to prejudicially affect the interests of any person to whom such rule may be
applicable.] 


  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>31</number>
Amendment of section 3.—In
section 3 of the Railways Act, after clause (18), the following clause shall be
inserted, namely:— 
 ‘(19)
“Claims Tribunal” means the Railway Claims Tribunal established under
section 3 of the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987.’. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>32</number>
Amendment of section 78A.—In section
78A of the Railways Act, for the word “suit”, the words “application
before the Claims Tribunal” shall be substituted. 


   


  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>33</number>
Substitution of new section for section 80.—For
section 80 of the Railways Act, the following section shall be substituted,
namely:—
 “80.
Application for compensation.—An application to the Claims Tribunal
for compensation for loss of the life of, or personal injury to, a passenger or
for loss, destruction, damage, deterioration or non-delivery of animlas or goods
may be made,—
 <section><number>a</number>
if the passenger was, or the animals or goods were, booked from one
station to another on the railway of the same railway administration, against
that railway administration;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
if the passenger was, or the animals or goods were, booked through over
the railway of two or more railway administrations, against the railway
administration from which the passenger obtained his pass or purchased his
ticket or to which the animals or goods were delivered for carriage, as the case
may be, or against the railway administration on whose railway the destination
station lies, or the loss, injury, destruction, damage or deterioration
occurred.”

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>34</number>
Omission of sections 82B, 82D and 82F.—Sections
82B, 82D and 82F of the Railways Act shall be omitted.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number>
Amendment of section 82C.—In section
82C of the Railways Act,—
 <section><number>a</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words ‘Claims Commissioner”, the words
“Claims Tribunal’’ shall be substituted;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
sub-section (2) and the Explanation thereto shall be omitted.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number>
Amendment of sections 82E, 82G and 82HH.—In
sections 82E, 82G and 82HH of the Railways Act, for the words “Claims
Commissioner”, wherever they occur, the words “Claims Tribunal” shall be
substituted.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>37</number>
Amendment of section 82-I.—In
section 82-I of the Railways Act, for the words, figures and letters “sections
82A to 82HH”, the words, figures and letters “sections 82A, 82C, 82E and 82G
to 82HH” shall be substituted.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number>
Amendment of section 82J.—In section
82J of the Railways Act,—
 <section><number>a</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words, figures and letters “sections 82A to
82H inclusive”, the words, figures and letters “sections 82A, 82C, 82E, 82G
and 82H” shall be substituted;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
in sub-section (2), clause (i) and clauses (iv) to (vi) shall be omitted.

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
8-11-1989, vide S.O. 783(E), dated 5th October, 1989. tc
"	2.	8-11-1989, vide S.O. 783(E), dated 5th October, 1989."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
8-11-1989, vide S.O. 784(E), dated 5th October, 1989. tc
"3.	8-11-1989, vide S.O. 784(E), dated 5th October,
1989."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994). tc "1.	Ins.
by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>Clause
(n) re-lettered as clause (o) by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994). tc "	2.	Clause (n)
re-lettered as clause (o) by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994)."
 
tc
"(3) It shall come into force on such date2 as the Central Government may,
by notification, appoint."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Subs. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 9, for “Railway Act” (w.e.f. 1-8-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 10, for “sub-section (1)” (w.e.f.
1-8-1994). tc "	3.	Subs. by Act 28 of 1994,
sec. 10, for “sub-section (1)” (w.e.f. 1-8-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994). tc
"	1.	Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994). tc
"	2.	Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Ins. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-8-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Subs. by Act 28 of 1994, sec. 13, for “that day” (w.e.f. 1-8-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
Ins. by Act 4 of 1999, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 2-1-1999).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>