<act><tid>978436</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI ACT, <year>1991</year></title>

NO. 1 OF <year>1992</year> 
[ 2nd January, <year>1992</year>.]
An Act to supplement the provisions of the Constitution relating to 
the Legislative Assembly and a Council of Ministers for the National 
Capital Territory of Delhi and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART 
PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>1673559</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>655552</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1950781</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
Provided that different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the 
commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the 
coming into force of that provision.

The Provisions of section 56 of this Act, shall come into force 
on 29. 11. <year>1993</year> vide Notification No. S. O. 910 (E), dated 29. 11. <year>1993</year>.

The provisions of sections 46, 47 and 48 of this Act, shall come 
into force on 25. 11. <year>1993</year> vide Notification No. S. O. 894 (E), dated 
25. 11. <year>1993</year>.

The provisions of sections 4 to 37 (both inclusive), 41 to 45 
 (both inclusive), 49 to 52 (both inclusive), 54 and 55 of this Act, 
shall come into force on 2. 10. <year>1993</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 735 (E) 
dated 30. 9. <year>1993</year>.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 2. <year>1992</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 97 (E), dated 31. 1. <year>1992</year>. 
Gazette of India, Extra ordinary, <year>1992</year>, Part II, Sec. 3 (ii)  (in  
  respect of ss. 2, 3, 38, 39, 40 and 53).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>325970</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>259176</tid>
<number>a</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>739438</tid>
<number>b</number>" assembly constituency" means a constituency provided 
under this Act for the purpose of elections to the Legislative 
Assembly;

</section>

<section><tid>722922</tid>
<number>c</number>" Capital" means the National Capital Territory of Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>420762</tid>
<number>d</number>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
referred to in article 324;

</section>

<section><tid>1379846</tid>
<number>e</number>" Legislative Assembly" means the Legislative Assembly of 
the National Capital Territory of Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>616589</tid>
<number>f</number>" Scheduled Castes", in relation to the Capital, means 
such castes, races or tribes or parts of or groups within such 
castes, races or tribes as are deemed under article 341 to be 
Scheduled Castes in relation to the Capital.
PART 
LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY

PART II

LEGISLALTIVE ASSEMBLY



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1276385</tid>
<number> 3</number> Legislative Assembly and its composition.
<section><tid>766687</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number  
of seats in the Legislative Assembly to be filled by persons chosen by 
direct election from territorial constituencies shall be seventy.

</section>

<section><tid>1898867</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of elections to the Legislative Assembly, the 
Capital shall be divided into single- member assembly constituencies in 
accordance with the provisions of Part III in such manner that the 
population of each of the constituencies shall, so far as practicable, 
be the same throughout the Capital.

</section>

<section><tid>1613854</tid>
<number>3</number>Seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes in the 
Legislative Assembly, and the number of seats so reserved shall bear, 
as nearly as may be, the same proportion to the total number of seats 
in the Assembly as the population of the Scheduled Castes in the 
Capital bears to the total population of the Capital and the 
provisions of article 334 shall apply to such reservation.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" Population" means 
the Population as ascertained in the last preceding census of which 
the relevant figures have been published:

Provided that where such figures have not been published, then 
for the purposes of elections for the constitution of the first 
Legislative Assembly under this Act, the provisional figures of the 
population of the Capital as published in relation to the <year>1991</year> census 
shall be deemed to be the population of the Capital.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>849573</tid>
<number> 4</number> Qualifications for membership of Legislative Assembly. A 
person shall not be qualified to be chosen to fill a seat in the 
Legislative Assembly unless he--
<section><tid>1322985</tid>
<number>a</number>is a citizen of India and makes and subscribes before 
some person authorised in that behalf by the Election Commission 
an oath or affirmation according to the form set out for the 
purpose in the Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1934217</tid>
<number>b</number>is not less than twenty- five years of age; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1431316</tid>
<number>c</number>possesses such other qualifications as may be prescribed 
in that behalf by or under any law made by Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>578680</tid>
<number>5</number>Duration of Legislative Assembly. The Legislative Assembly, 
unless sooner dissolved, shall continue for five years from the date 
appointed for its first meeting and no longer, and the expiration of 
the said period of five years shall operate as a dissolution of the 
Assembly:
Provided that the said period may, while a Proclamation of 
Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 is in operation, be 
extended by the President by order for a period not exceeding one year 
at a time and not extending in any case beyond a period of six months 
after the Proclamation has ceased to operate.


</article>



<article><tid>1441169</tid>
<number> 6</number> Sessions of Legislative Assembly, prorogation and dissolution.

<section><tid>2208</tid>
<number>1</number>The Lieutenant Governor shall, from time to time, summon the  
Legislative Assembly to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit, 
but six months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one 
session and the date appointed for its first sitting in the next 
session.

</section>

<section><tid>63516</tid>
<number>2</number>The Lieutenant Governor may, from time to time,--

<subsection><tid>1643025</tid>
<number>a</number>prorogue the Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312523</tid>
<number>b</number>dissolve the Assembly.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529794</tid>
<number> 7</number> Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>185414</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Legislative Assembly shall, as soon as may be, choose two members of 
the Assembly to be respectively Speaker and Deputy Speaker thereof 
and, so often as the office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker becomes 
vacant, the Assembly shall choose another member to be Speaker or 
Deputy Speaker, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1550044</tid>
<number>2</number>A member holding office as Speaker or Deputy Speaker of the 
Legislative Assembly--

<subsection><tid>25818</tid>
<number>a</number>shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of 
the Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1384430</tid>
<number>b</number>may, at any time by writing under his hand addressed, if 
such member is the Speaker, to the Deputy Speaker, and if such 
member is the Deputy Speaker, to the Speaker, resign his office; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1694504</tid>
<number>c</number>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the 
Assembly passed by a majority of all the then members of the 
Assembly:
Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall 
be moved unless at least fourteen days' notice has been given of the 
intention to move the resolution:

Provided further that whenever the Assembly is dissolved, the 
Speaker shall not vacate his office until immediately before the first 
meeting of the Assembly after the dissolution.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1088624</tid>
<number>3</number>While the office of Speaker is vacant, the duties of the 
office shall be performed by the Deputy Speaker or. if the office of 
Deputy Speaker is also vacant. by such member of the Assembly as may 
be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>551762</tid>
<number>4</number>During the absence of the Speaker from any sitting of the 
Assembly, the Deputy Speaker, or, if he is also absent, such person as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

may be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly, or, if no 
such person is present, such other person as may be determined by the 
Assembly, shall act as Speaker.


</section>

<section><tid>1520502</tid>
<number>5</number>There shall be paid to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of 
the Legislative Assembly such salaries and allowances as may be 
respectively fixed by the Legislative Assembly by law and, until 
provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries and allowances as 
the Lieutenant Governor may, with the approval of the President, by 
order determine.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>174886</tid>
<number> 8</number> Speaker or Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution 
for his removal from office is under consideration.
<section><tid>1507809</tid>
<number>1</number>At any sitting  
of the Legislative Assembly, while any resolution for the removal of 
the Speaker from his office is under consideration, the Speaker, or 
while any resolution for the removal of the Deputy Speaker from his 
office is under consideration, the Deputy Speaker, shall not, though 
he is present, preside and the provisions of sub- section (4) of 
section 7 shall apply in relation to every such sitting as they apply 
in relation to a sitting from which the Speaker or, as the case may 
be, the Deputy Speaker is absent.

</section>

<section><tid>62103</tid>
<number>2</number>The Speaker shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise 
to take part in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly while any 
resolution for his removal from office is under consideration in the 
assembly and shall, notwithstanding anything in section 13, be 
entitled to vote only in the first instance on such resolution or on 
any other matter during such proceedings but not in the case of an 
equality of votes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>465271</tid>
<number> 9</number> Right of Lieutenant Governor to address and send messages to 
Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>350289</tid>
<number>1</number>The Lieutenant Governor may address the  
Legislative Assembly and for that purpose require the attendance of 
members.

</section>

<section><tid>246531</tid>
<number>2</number>The Lieutenant Governor may send messages to the Assembly 
whether with respect to a Bill then pending in the Assembly or 
otherwise, and when a message is so sent, the Assembly shall with all 
convenient despatch consider any matter required by the message to be 
taken into consideration.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>541672</tid>
<number> 10</number> Special address by the Lieutenant Governor.
<section><tid>1921688</tid>
<number>1</number>At the  
commencement of the first session after each general election to the 
Legislative Assembly and at the commencement of the first session of 
each year, the Lieutenant Governor shall address the Legislative 
Assembly and inform it of the causes of its summons.

</section>

<section><tid>1512683</tid>
<number>2</number>Provision shall be made by rules to be made by the Assembly 
regulating its procedure for the allotment of time for discussion of 
the matters referred to in such address.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1421441</tid>
<number>11</number>Rights of Ministers as respects Legislative Assembly. Every 
Minister shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise to take part 
in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly and to speak in, and 
otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, any committee of the 
Legislative Assembly of which he may be named a member, but shall not 
by virtue of this section be entitled to vote.

</article>



<article><tid>766428</tid>
<number>12</number>Oath or affirmation by members. Every member of the 
Legislative Assembly shall, before taking his seat, make and subscribe 
before the Lieutenant Governor, or some person appointed in that 
behalf by him, an oath or affirmation according to the form set out 
for the purpose in the Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>810863</tid>
<number> 13</number> Voting in Assembly, power of Assembly to act notwithstanding 
vacancies and quorum.
<section><tid>332539</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all  
questions at any sitting of the Legislative Assembly shall be 
determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting 
other than the Speaker or person acting as such.

</section>

<section><tid>133215</tid>
<number>2</number>The Speaker or person acting as such shall not vote in the 
first instance. but shall have and exercise a casting vote in the case 
of an equality of votes.

</section>

<section><tid>196973</tid>
<number>3</number>The Legislative Assembly shall have power to act 
notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership thereof, and any 
proceedings in the Legislative Assembly shall be valid notwithstanding 
that it is discovered subsequently that some person who was not 
entitled so to do, sat or voted or otherwise took part in the 
proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>926000</tid>
<number>4</number>The quorum to constitute a meeting of the Legislative 
Assembly shall be one- third of the total number of members of the 
Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>132860</tid>
<number>5</number>If at any time during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly 
there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of the Speaker, or person 
acting as such, either to adjourn the Assembly or to suspend the 
meeting until there is a quorum.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1497066</tid>
<number> 14</number> Vacation of seats.
<section><tid>610352</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be a member both of  
Parliament and of the Legislative Assembly and if a person is chosen a 
member both of Parliament and of such Assembly, then, at the 
expiration of such period as is specified in or under the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>). and the rules 
made by the President under clause (2) of article 101 and clause (2) 
of article 190. that person' s seat in Parliament shall become vacant, 
unless he has previously resigned his seat in the Legislative 
Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>1565422</tid>
<number>2</number>If a member of the Legislative Assembly--

<subsection><tid>401175</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any disqualification mentioned in 
section 15 or section 16 for membership of the Assembly, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507340</tid>
<number>b</number>resigns his seat by writing under his hand addressed to 
the Speaker and his resignation is accepted by the Speaker,
his seat shall thereupon become vacant:

Provided that in the case of any resignation referred to in 
clause (b), if from the information received or otherwise and after 
making such inquiry as he thinks fit, the Speaker is satisfied that 
such resignation is not voluntary or genuine, he shall not accept such 
resignation.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>132402</tid>
<number>3</number>If for a period of sixty days a member of the Legislative 
Assembly is without permission of the Assembly absent from all 
meetings thereof, the Assembly may declare his seat vacant:
Provided that in computing the said period of sixty days, no 
account shall be taken of any period during which the Assembly is 
prorogued or is adjourned for more than four consecutive days.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>243110</tid>
<number> 15</number> Disqualifications for membership.
<section><tid>890801</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be  
disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the 
Legislative Assembly--

<subsection><tid>1936964</tid>
<number>a</number>if he holds any office of profit under the Government of 
India or the Government of any State or the Government of any 
Union territory other than an office declared by law made by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Parliament or by the Legislature of any State or by the 
Legislative Assembly of the Capital or of any other Union 
territory not to disqualify its holder; or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>835930</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is for the time being disqualified for being 
chosen as, and for being, a member of either House of Parliament 
under the provisions of sub- clause (b), sub- clause (c) or sub- 
clause (d) of clause (1) of article 102 or of any law made in 
pursuance of that article.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>815542</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, a person shall not be 
deemed to hold an office of profit under the Government of India or 
the Government of any State or the Government of any Union territory 
by reason only that he is a Minister either for the Union or for such 
State or Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1187993</tid>
<number>3</number>If any question arises as to whether a member of the 
Legislative Assembly has become disqualified for being such a member 
under the provisions of sub- section (1), the question shall be 
referred for the decision of the President and his decision shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>1901509</tid>
<number>4</number>Before giving any decision on any such question, the 
President shall obtain the opinion of the Election Commission and 
shall act according to such opinion.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1022774</tid>
<number> 16</number> Disqualification on ground of defection. The provisions of 
the Tenth Schedule to the Constitution shall, subject to the necessary 
modifications (including modifications for construing references  
therein to the Legislative Assembly of a State, article 188, article 
 194 and article 212 as references, respectively, to the Legislative 
  Assembly, section 12, section 18 and section 37 of this Act), apply to 
and in relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly as they 
apply to and in relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly of 
a State, and accordingly:--
<section><tid>1478</tid>
<number>a</number>the said Tenth Schedule as so modified shall be deemed 
to form part of this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1007342</tid>
<number>b</number>a person shall be disqualified for being a member of the 
Legislative Assembly if he is so disqualified under the said 
Tenth Schedule as so modified.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1741952</tid>
<number>17</number>Penalty for sitting and voting before making oath or 
affirmation or when not qualified or when disqualified. If a person 
sits or votes as a member of the Legislative Assembly before he has 
complied with the requirements of section 12 or when he knows that he 
is not qualified or that he is disqualified for membership thereof, he 
shall be liable in respect of each day on which he so sits or votes to 
a penalty of five hundred rupees to be recovered as a debt due to the 
Union.

</article>



<article><tid>737557</tid>
<number> 18</number> Powers, privileges, etc., of members.
<section><tid>1346389</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act and to the rules and standing orders regulating 
the procedure of the Legislative Assembly, there shall be freedom of 
speech in the Legislative Assembly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>508142</tid>
<number>2</number>No member of the Legislative Assembly shall be liable to any 
proceedings in any court in respect of anything said or any vote given 
by him in the Assembly or any committee thereof and no person shall be 
so liable in respect of the publication by or under the authority of 
such Assembly of any report, paper, votes or proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>1700421</tid>
<number>3</number>In other respects, the powers, privileges and immunities of 
the Legislative Assembly and of the members and the committees thereof 
shall be such as are for the time being enjoyed by the House of the 
People and its members and committees.

</section>

<section><tid>186933</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall apply 
in relation to persons who by virtue of this Act have the right to 
speak in, and otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the 
Legislative Assembly or any committee thereof as they apply in 
relation to members of that Assembly.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1454237</tid>
<number>19</number>Salaries and allowances of members. Members of the 
Legislative Assembly shall be entitled to receive such salaries and 
allowances as may from time to time be determined by the Legislative 
Assembly by law and until provision in that behalf is so made, such 
salaries and allowances as the Lieutenant Governor may, with the 
approval of the President, by order determine.

</article>



<article><tid>654658</tid>
<number>20</number>Exemption of property of the Union from taxation. The 
property of the Union shall, save in so far as Parliament may by law 
otherwise provide, be exempted from all taxes imposed by or under any 
law made by the Legislative Assembly or by or under any other law in 
force in the Capital:
Provided that nothing in this section shall, until Parliament by 
law otherwise provides, prevent any authority within the Capital from 
levying any tax on any property of the Union to which such property 
was immediately before the commencement of the Constitution liable or 
treated as liable, so long as that tax continues to be levied in the 
Capital.


</article>



<article><tid>1215214</tid>
<number> 21</number> Restrictions on laws passed by Legislative Assembly with 
respect to certain matters.
<section><tid>531835</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of article 286, article  
 287 and article 288 shall apply in relation to any law passed by the 
Legislative Assembly with respect to any of the matters referred to in 
those articles as they apply in relation to any law passed by the 
Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.

</section>

<section><tid>558853</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of article 304 shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislative 
Assembly with respect to any of the matters referred to in that 
article as they apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislature 
of a State with respect to those matters.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>573650</tid>
<number> 22</number> Special provisions as to financial bills.
<section><tid>1884153</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill or  
amendment shall not be introduced into, or moved in, the Legislative 
Assembly except on the recommendation of the Lieutenant Governor, if 
such Bill or amendment makes provision for any of the following 
matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>261039</tid>
<number>a</number>the imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or 
regulation of any tax;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>588704</tid>
<number>b</number>the amendment of the law with respect to any financial 
obligations undertaken or to be undertaken by the Government of 
the Capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>52797</tid>
<number>c</number>the appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated fund 
of the Capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1778919</tid>
<number>d</number>the declaring of any expenditure to be expenditure 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Capital or the increasing 
of the amount of any such expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1665298</tid>
<number>e</number>the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Capital or the custody or issue of such money:
Provided that no recommendation shall be required under this 
sub- section for the moving of an amendment making provision for the 
reduction or abolition of any tax.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1819518</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill or amendment shall not be deemed to make provision for 
any of the matters aforesaid by reason only that it provides for the 
imposition of fines or other pecuniary penalties, or for the demand or 
payment of fees for licences or fees for services rendered, or by 
reason that it provides for the imposition, abolition, remission, 
alteration or regulation of any tax by any local authority or body for 
local purposes.

</section>

<section><tid>1549530</tid>
<number>3</number>A Bill which, if enacted and brought into operation, would 
involve expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall 
not be passed by the Legislative Assembly unless the Lieutenant 
Governor has recommended to that Assembly the consideration of the 
Bill.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>598171</tid>
<number> 23</number> Procedure as to lapsing of Bills.
<section><tid>1707428</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill pending in the  
Legislative Assembly shall not lapse by reason of the prorogation of 
the Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>423492</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill which is pending in the Legislative Assembly shall 
lapse on a dissolution of the Assembly.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>128960</tid>
<number> 24</number> Assent to Bills. When a Bill has been passed by the 
Legislative Assembly, it shall be presented to the Lieutenant Governor 
and the Lieutenant Governor shall declare either that he assents to 
the Bill or that he withholds assent therefrom or that he reserves the 
Bill for the consideration of the President:
Provided that the Lieutenant Governor may, as soon as possible 
after the presentation of the Bill to him for assent, return the Bill 
if it is not a Money Bill together with a message requesting that the 
Assembly will reconsider the Bill or any specified provisions thereof, 
and, in particular, will consider the desirability of introducing any 
such amendments as he may recommend in his message and, when a Bill is 
so returned, the Assembly will reconsider the Bill accordingly, and if 
the Bill is passed again with or without amendment and presented to 
the Lieutenant Governor for assent, the Lieutenant Governor shall 
declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he reserves the 
Bill for the consideration of the President:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that the Lieutenant Governor shall not assent 
to, but shall reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill 
which,--

<section><tid>95937</tid>
<number>a</number>in the opinion of the Lieutenant Governor would, if it 
became law, so derogate from the powers of the High Court as to 
endanger the position which that Court is, by the Constitution, 
designed to fill; or

</section>

<section><tid>688610</tid>
<number>b</number>the President may, by order, direct to be reserved for 
his consideration; or

</section>

<section><tid>649876</tid>
<number>c</number>relates to matters referred to in sub- section (5) of 
section 7 or section 19 or section 34 or sub- section (3) of 
section 43.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 25, a 
Bill shall be deemed to be a Money Bill if it contains only provisions 
dealing with all or any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) of 
section 22 or any matter incidental to any of those matters and, in 
either case, there is endorsed thereon the certificate of the Speaker 
of the Legislative Assembly signed by him that it is a Money Bill.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030634</tid>
<number>25</number>Bills reserved for consideration. When a Bill is reserved by 
the Lieutenant Governor for the consideration of the President, the 
President shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he 
withholds assent therefrom:
Provided that where the Bill is not a Money Bill, the President 
may direct the Lieutenant Governor to return the Bill to the 
Legislative Assembly together with such a message as is mentioned in 
the first proviso to section 24 and, when a Bill is so returned, the 
Assembly shall reconsider it accordingly within a period of six months 
from the date of receipt of such message and, if it is again passed by 
the Assembly with or without amendment, it shall be presented again to 
the President for his consideration.


</article>



<article><tid>1620643</tid>
<number>26</number>Requirements as to sanction, etc. No Act of the Legislative 
Assembly, and no provision in any such Act, shall be invalid by reason 
only that some previous sanction or recommendation required by this 
Act was not given, if assent to that Act was given by the Lieutenant 
Governor, or, on being reserved by the Lieutenant Governor for the 
consideration of the President, by the President.

</article>



<article><tid>1795223</tid>
<number> 27</number> Annual financial statement.
<section><tid>869149</tid>
<number>1</number>The Lieutenant Governor shall  
in respect of every financial year cause to be laid before the 
Legislative Assembly, with the previous sanction of the President, a 
statement of the estimated receipts and expenditure of the Capital for 
that year, in this Part referred to as the" annual financial 
statement".

</section>

<section><tid>1088397</tid>
<number>2</number>The estimates of expenditure embodied in the annual financial 
statement shall show separately--

<subsection><tid>1889693</tid>
<number>a</number>the sums required to meet expenditure described by this 
Act as expenditure charged upon the Consolidated Fund of the 
Capital; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1148298</tid>
<number>b</number>the sums required to meet other expenditure proposed to 
be made from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, and shall 
distinguish expenditure on revenue account from other 
expenditure.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1389373</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, the following expenditure shall be expenditure charged 
on the Consolidated Fund of the Capital:--

<subsection><tid>1670621</tid>
<number>a</number>the emoluments and allowances of the Lieutenant Governor 
and other expenditure relating to his office as determined by the 
President by general or special order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1705872</tid>
<number>b</number>the charges payable in respect of loans advanced to the 
Capital from the Consolidated Fund of India including interest, 
sinking fund charges and redemption charges, and other 
expenditure connected therewith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>610314</tid>
<number>c</number>the salaries and allowances of the Speaker and the 
Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1151181</tid>
<number>d</number>expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of 
Judges of the High Court of Delhi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1160330</tid>
<number>e</number>any sums required to satisfy any judgment, decree or 
award of any court of arbitral tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411467</tid>
<number>f</number>any other expenditure declared by the Constitution or by 
law made by Parliament or by the Legislative Assembly to be so 
charged.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>573197</tid>
<number> 28</number> Procedure in Legislative Assembly with respect to estimates.

<section><tid>612859</tid>
<number>1</number>So much of the estimates as relates to expenditure charged upon  
the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall not be submitted to the 
vote of the Legislative Assembly, but nothing in this sub- section 
shall be construed as preventing the discussion in the Legislative 
Assembly of any of those estimates.

</section>

<section><tid>1889661</tid>
<number>2</number>So much of the said estimates as relates to other expenditure 
shall be submitted in the form of demands for grants to the 
Legislative Assembly, and the Legislative Assembly shall have power to 
assent, or to refuse to assent, to any demand, or to assent to any 
demand subject to a reduction of the amount specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1266161</tid>
<number>3</number>No demand for a grant shall be made except on the 
recommendation of the Lieutenant Governor.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>611002</tid>
<number> 29</number> Appropriation Bills.
<section><tid>421360</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the grants  
under section 28 have been made by the Legislative Assembly, there 
shall be introduced a Bill to provide for the appropriation out of the 
Consolidated Fund of the Capital of all moneys required to meet--

<subsection><tid>1516804</tid>
<number>a</number>the grants so made by the Assembly, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>449256</tid>
<number>b</number>the expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the 
Capital but not exceeding in any case the amount shown in the 
statement previously laid before the Assembly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>402957</tid>
<number>2</number>No amendment shall be proposed to any such Bill in the 
Legislative Assembly which will have the effect of varying the amount 
or altering the destination of any grant so made or of varying the 
amount of any expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the 
Capital and the decision of the person presiding as to whether an 
amendment is inadmissible under this sub- section shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1648723</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, no money shall 
be withdrawn from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital except under 
appropriation made by law passed in accordance with provisions of this 
section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>140550</tid>
<number> 30</number> Supplementary, additional or excess grants.
<section><tid>1486220</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Lieutenant Governor shall,--

<subsection><tid>816900</tid>
<number>a</number>if the amount authorised by any law made in accordance 
with the provisions of section 29 to be expended for a particular 
service for the current financial year is found to be 
insufficient for the purposes of that year or when a need has 
arisen during the current financial year for supplementary or 
additional expenditure upon some new service not contemplated in 
the annual financial statement for that year, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>258874</tid>
<number>b</number>if any money has been spent on any service during a 
financial year in excess of the amount granted for that service 
and for that year,
cause to be laid before the Legislative Assembly, with the previous 
sanction of the President, another statement showing the estimated 
amount of that expenditure or cause to be presented to the Legislative 
Assembly with such previous sanction a demand for such excess, as the 
case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>674845</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 27, 28 and 29 shall have effect in 
relation to any such statement and expenditure or demand and also to 
any law to be made authorising the appropriation of moneys out of the 
Consolidated Fund of the Capital to meet such expenditure or the grant 
in respect of such demand as they have effect in relation to the 
annual financial statement and the expenditure mentioned therein or to 
a demand for a grant and the law to be made for the authorisation of 
appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital to 
meet such expenditure or grant.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1633707</tid>
<number> 31</number> Votes on account.
<section><tid>1064787</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything in the  
foregoing provisions of this Part, the Legislative Assembly shall have 
power to make any grant in advance in respect of the estimated 
expenditure for a part of any financial year pending the completion of 
the procedure prescribed in section 28 for the voting of such grant 
and the passing of the law in accordance with the provisions of 
section 29 in relation to that expenditure and the Legislative 
Assembly shall have power to authorise by law the withdrawal of moneys 
from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital for the purposes for which 
the said grant is made.

</section>

<section><tid>284114</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 28 and 29 shall have effect in 
relation to the making of any grant under sub- section (1) or to any 
law to be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

made under that sub- section as they have effect in relation to the 
making of a grant with regard to any expenditure mentioned in the 
annual financial statement and the law to be made for the 
authorisation of appropriation of moneys, out of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Capital to meet such expenditure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1808497</tid>
<number>32</number>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by 
Legislative Assembly. Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part, the Lieutenant Governor may authorise such 
expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital as he deems 
necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning with the 
date of the constitution of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, 
pending the sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative Assembly.

</article>



<article><tid>906175</tid>
<number> 33</number> Rules of procedure.
<section><tid>1621843</tid>
<number>1</number>The Legislative Assembly may make  
rules for regulating, subject to the provisions of this Act, its 
procedure and the conduct of its business:
Provided that the Lieutenant Governor shall, after consultation 
with the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and with the approval of 
the President, make rules--


<subsection><tid>1366874</tid>
<number>a</number>for securing the timely completion of financial 
business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>397707</tid>
<number>b</number>for regulating the procedure of, and the conduct of 
business in, the Legislative Assembly in relation to any 
financial matter or to any Bill for the appropriation of moneys 
out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1168949</tid>
<number>c</number>for prohibiting the discussion of, or the asking of 
questions on, any matter which affects the discharge of the 
functions of the Lieutenant Governor in so far as he is required 
by or under this Act or any law to act in his discretion.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1086763</tid>
<number>2</number>Until rules are made under sub- section (1), the rules of 
procedure and standing orders with respect to the Legislative Assembly 
of the State of Uttar Pradesh in force immediately before the 
commencement of this Act shall have effect in relation to the 
Legislative Assembly subject to such modifications and adaptations as 
may be made therein by the Lieutenant Governor.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13715</tid>
<number> 34</number> Official language or languages of the Capital and language 
or languages to be used, in Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>555192</tid>
<number>1</number>The Legislative  
Assembly may by law adopt any one or more of the languages in use in 
the Capital or Hindi as the official language or languages to be used 
for all or any of the official purposes of the Capital:
Provided that the President may by order direct--


<subsection><tid>1977550</tid>
<number>i</number>that the official language of the Union shall be adopted 
for such of the official purposes of the Capital as may be 
specified in the order;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>920525</tid>
<number>ii</number>that any other language shall also be adopted 
throughout the Capital or such part thereof for such of the 
official purposes of the Capital as may be specified in the 
order, if the President is satisfied that a substantial 
proportion of the population of the Capital desires the use of 
that other language for all or any of such purposes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>680277</tid>
<number>2</number>The business in the Legislative Assembly shall be transacted 
in the official language or languages of the Capital or in Hindi or in 
English:
Provided that the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or person 
acting as such, as the case may be, may permit any member who cannot 
adequately express himself in any of the languages aforesaid to 
address the Assembly in his mother- tongue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1786175</tid>
<number> 35</number> Language to be used for Bills, Acts, etc. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 34, until parliament by law otherwise 
provides, the authoritative texts--
<section><tid>516188</tid>
<number>a</number>of all Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to 
be moved in the Legislative Assembly;

</section>

<section><tid>1336481</tid>
<number>b</number>of all Acts passed by the Legislative Assembly; and

</section>

<section><tid>977479</tid>
<number>c</number>of all orders, rules, regulations and bye- laws issued 
under any law made by the Legislative Assembly,
shall be in the English language:

Provided that where the Legislative Assembly has prescribed any 
language other than the English language for use in Bills introduced 
in, or Acts passed by, the Legislative Assembly or in any order, rule, 
regulation or bye- law issued under any law made by the Legislative 
Assembly, a translation of the same in the English language published 
under the authority, of the Lieutenant Governor in the Official Gazette 
shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in the English 
language.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1360996</tid>
<number>36</number>Restriction on discussion in the Legislative Assembly. No 
discussion shall take place in the Legislative Assembly with respect 
to the conduct of any Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court in 
the discharge of his duties.

</article>



<article><tid>315896</tid>
<number> 37</number> Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Legislative 
Assembly.
<section><tid>825266</tid>
<number>1</number>The validity of any proceedings in the Legislative  
Assembly shall not be called in question on the ground of any alleged 
irregularity of procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>1612157</tid>
<number>2</number>No officer or member of the Legislative Assembly in whom 
powers are vested by or under this Act for regulating procedure or the 
conduct of business, or for maintaining order in the Legislative 
Assembly shall be subject to the jurisdiction of any court in respect 
of the exercise by him of those powers.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART 
DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES

PART III

DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1029636</tid>
<number> 38</number> Election Commission to delimit constituencies.
<section><tid>1252381</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Election Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute 
the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly under section 3 to 
single- member territorial constituencies and delimit them having 
regard to the following provisions, namely:--

<subsection><tid>497666</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
delimited in such manner that the ratio between the population of 
each of such constituencies and the total population of the 
Capital is the same; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162561</tid>
<number>b</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes shall, as far as practicable, be located in 
areas where the proportion of their population to the total 
population is comparatively large.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1414128</tid>
<number>2</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>1932996</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of 
constituencies in the Official Gazette and also in such other 
manner as the Commission may consider fit, together with a notice 
inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the proposals 
and specifying a date on or after which the proposals will be 
further considered by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>123785</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>182191</tid>
<number>c</number>after considering all objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so specified, 
determine by one or more orders the delimitation of 
constituencies and cause such order or orders to be published in 
the Official Gazette; and upon such publication, the order or 
orders shall have the full force of law and shall not be called 
in question in any court.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1815744</tid>
<number> 39</number> Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders 
up- to date. The Election Commission may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette,--
<section><tid>302396</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistakes in any order made under 
section 38 or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or 
omission; and

</section>

<section><tid>1037894</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order are or is altered, make such 
amendments as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for 
bringing such order up- to- date.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>175081</tid>
<number> 40</number> Elections to the Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>401593</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of  
constituting the Legislative Assembly, a general election will be held 
as soon as may be, after the delimitation of all the assembly 
constituencies under section 38.

</section>

<section><tid>1693158</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the Lieutenant Governor 
shall, by one or more notifications published in the Official Gazette, 
call upon all the said assembly constituencies to elect members in 
accordance with the provisions of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>), and of the rules and orders made or issued 
thereunder as applicable under sub- section (3).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1492304</tid>
<number>3</number>The Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>), the rules and 
orders made or issued under the said Acts and all other laws for the 
time being in force relating to elections shall apply with necessary 
modifications (including modifications for construing references  
therein to a State, State Government and Governor as including 
references to the Capital, Government of the Capital and Lieutenant 
  Governor, respectively) to, and in relation to, the general election 
referred to in sub- section (1).
PART 
CERTAIN PROVISIONS RELATING TO LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR AND MINISTERS

PART IV

CERTAIN PROVISIONS RELATING TO LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR AND MINISTERS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1468572</tid>
<number> 41</number> Matters in which Lieutenant Governor to act in his 
discretion.
<section><tid>1292812</tid>
<number>1</number>The Lieutenant Governor shall act in his discretion in  
a matter--

<subsection><tid>284571</tid>
<number>i</number>which falls outside the purview of the powers conferred 
on the Legislative Assembly but in respect of which powers or 
functions are entrusted or delegated to him by the President; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>332527</tid>
<number>ii</number>in which he is required by or under any law to act in 
his discretion or to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial 
functions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>639799</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not 
a matter as respects which the Lieutenant Governor is by or under any 
law required to act in his discretion, the decision of the Lieutenant 
Governor thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1957136</tid>
<number>3</number>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not 
a matter as respects which the Lieutenant Governor is required by any 
law to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions, the decision 
of the Lieutenant Governor thereon shall be final.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1664525</tid>
<number>42</number>Advice by Ministers. The question whether any, and if so 
what, advice was tendered by Ministers to the Lieutenant Governor 
shall not be inquired into in any court.

</article>



<article><tid>1965709</tid>
<number> 43</number> Other provisions as to Ministers.
<section><tid>1181320</tid>
<number>1</number>Before a Minister  
enters upon his office, the Lieutenant Governor shall administer to 
him the oaths of office and of secrecy according to the forms set out 
for the purpose in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1851956</tid>
<number>2</number>A Minister who, for any period of six consecutive months, is 
not a member of the Legislative Assembly shall, at the expiration of 
that period, cease to be a Minister.

</section>

<section><tid>560230</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances of Ministers shall be such as the 
Legislative Assembly may from time to time by law determine, and until 
the Legislative Assembly so determines, shall be determined by the 
Lieutenant Governor with the approval of the President.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>84906</tid>
<number> 44</number> Conduct of business.
<section><tid>1429398</tid>
<number>1</number>The President shall make rules-- 

<subsection><tid>1310777</tid>
<number>a</number>for the allocation of business to the Ministers in so 
far as it is business with respect to which the Lieutenant 
Governor is required to act on the aid and advice of his Council 
of Ministers; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>515094</tid>
<number>b</number>for the more convenient transaction of business with the 
Ministers, including the procedure to be adopted in the case of a 
difference of opinion between the Lieutenant Governor and the 
Council of Ministers or a Minister.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1438699</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all executive action 
of the Lieutenant Governor whether taken on the advice of his 
Ministers or otherwise shall be expressed to be taken in the name of 
the Lieutenant Governor.

</section>

<section><tid>273491</tid>
<number>3</number>Orders and other instruments made and executed in the name of 
the Lieutenant Governor shall be authenticated in such manner as may 
be specified in rules to be made by the Lieutenant Governor and the 
validity of an order or instrument which is so authenticated shall not 
be called in question on the ground that it is not an order or 
instrument made or executed by the Lieutenant Governor.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1911090</tid>
<number> 45</number> Duties of Chief Minister as respects the furnishing of 
information to the Lieutenant Governor, etc. It shall be the duty of 
the Chief Minister--
<section><tid>760231</tid>
<number>a</number>to communicate to the Lieutenant Governor all decisions 
of the Council of Ministers relating to the administration of the 
affairs of the Capital and proposals for legislation;

</section>

<section><tid>1733552</tid>
<number>b</number>to furnish such information relating to the 
administration of the affairs of the Capital and proposals for 
legislation as Lieutenant Governor may call for; and

</section>

<section><tid>1702731</tid>
<number>c</number>if the Lieutenant Governor so requires, to submit for 
the consideration of the Council of Ministers any matter on which 
a decision has been taken by a Minister but which has not been 
considered by the Council.
PART 
MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS

PART V

MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>492347</tid>
<number> 46</number> Consolidated Fund of the Capital.
<section><tid>1581593</tid>
<number>1</number>As from such date as  
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint in this behalf, all revenues received in the Capital by the 
Government of India or the Lieutenant Governor in relation to any 
matter with respect to which the Legislative Assembly has power to 
make laws, and all grants made and all loans advanced to the Capital 
from the Consolidated Fund of India and all moneys received by the 
Capital in repayment of loans shall form one Consolidated Fund to be 
entitled" the Consolidated Fund of the National Capital Territory of 
Delhi" (referred to in this Act as the Consolidated Fund of the  
  Capital).

</section>

<section><tid>1996772</tid>
<number>2</number>No moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall 
be appropriated except in accordance with and for the purposes and in 
the manner provided in this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1755033</tid>
<number>3</number>The custody of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, the 
payment of moneys into such Fund, the withdrawal of moneys therefrom 
and all other matters connected with or ancillary to those matters 
shall be regulated by rules made by the Lieutenant Governor with the 
approval of the President.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>715083</tid>
<number> 47</number> Contingency Fund of the Capital.
<section><tid>559587</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
established a Contingency Fund in the nature of an imprest to be 
entitled" the Contingency Fund of the National Capital Territory of 
Delhi" into which shall be paid from and out of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Capital such sums as may, from time to time, be determined by 
law made by the Legislative Assembly; and the said Fund shall be held 
by the Lieutenant Governor to enable advances to be made by him out of 
such Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1375834</tid>
<number>2</number>No advances shall be made out of the Contingency Fund 
referred to in sub- section (1) except for the purposes of meeting 
unforeseen expenditure pending authorisation of such expenditure by 
the Legislative Assembly under appropriations made by law.

</section>

<section><tid>760286</tid>
<number>3</number>The Lieutenant Governor may make rules regulating all matters 
connected with or ancillary to the custody of, the payment of moneys 
into, and the withdrawal of moneys from, the aforesaid Contingency 
Fund.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>610469</tid>
<number> 48</number> Audit reports. The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India relating to the accounts of the Capital for any 
period subsequent to the date referred to in sub- section
<section><tid>1499550</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 46 shall be submitted to the Lieutenant Governor who shall 
cause them to be laid before the Legislative Assembly.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248727</tid>
<number>49</number>Relation of Lieutenant Governor and his Ministers to 
President. Notwithstanding anything in this Act, the Lieutenant 
Governor and his Council of Ministers shall be under the general 
control of, and comply with such particular directions, if any, as may 
from time to time be given by, the President.

</article>



<article><tid>1176489</tid>
<number> 50</number> Period of order made under article 239AB and approval thereof 
by Parliament.
<section><tid>1726801</tid>
<number>1</number>Every order made by the President under article  
 239AB shall expire at the end of one year from the date of issue of 
the order and the provisions of clauses (2) and (3) of article 356 
shall, so far as may be, apply to such order as they apply to a 
Proclamation issued under clause (1) of article 356.

</section>

<section><tid>641565</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
President may extend the duration of the aforesaid order for a further 
period not exceeding two years from the date of expiry of the order 
under sub- section (1) subject to the condition that every extension of 
the said order for any period beyond the expiration of one year shall 
be approved by resolutions of both Houses of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1668382</tid>
<number>51</number>Authorisation of expenditure by President. Where the 
Legislative Assembly is dissolved or its functioning as such Assembly 
remains suspended, on account of an order made by the President under 
article 239AB, it shall be competent for the President to authorise 
when the House of the People is not in session expenditure from the 
Consolidated Fund of the Capital pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1655250</tid>
<number> 52</number> Contracts and suits. For the removal of doubts it is hereby 
declared that--
<section><tid>291413</tid>
<number>a</number>all contracts in connection with the administration of 
the Capital are contracts made in the exercise of the executive 
power of the Union; and

</section>

<section><tid>1209383</tid>
<number>b</number>all suits and proceedings in connection with the 
administration of the Capital shall be instituted by or against 
the Government of India.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>522806</tid>
<number> 53</number> Power of president to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>588228</tid>
<number>1</number>If any  
difficulty arises in relation to the transition from the provisions of 
any law repealed by this Act or in giving effect to the provisions of 
this Act and in particular in relation to the constitution of the 
Legislative Assembly, the President may by order do anything not 
inconsistent with the provisions of the Constitution or of this Act 
which appear to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order under this sub- section shall be made after 
the expiry of three years from the date of constitution of the first 
Legislative Assembly.


</section>

<section><tid>1233542</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be laid before 
each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1991474</tid>
<number>54</number>Laying of rules before Legislative Assembly. Every rule made 
by the Lieutenant Governor under this Act shall be laid, as soon as it 
is made, before the Legislative Assembly.

</article>



<article><tid>576893</tid>
<number>55</number>Ammendment of section 27A of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. In section 27A 
of the Representation of People Act, <year>1950</year>, for sub- section (3), the 
following sub- section shall be substituted, namely:--
" (3) The electoral college for the Union territory of Delhi 
shall consist of the elected members of the Legislative Assembly 
constituted for that territory under the Government of National 
Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year>."


</article>



<article><tid>672251</tid>
<number>56</number>Repeal of Act 19 of <year>1966</year>. The Delhi Administration Act, <year>1966</year> 
is hereby repealed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>