<act><title>THE ARMED FORCES TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 
20081 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number>Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Armed Forces Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force from the date  of publication in 
the Official Gazette. 
 ___________
 </section></article><article><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
 </article><article><number>2</number> Came into force on 17-9-2008 . 
  
  
  
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number>Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Act means the Armed Forces Tribunal Act, 2007 (55 of 2007); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> agent means a person duly authorised by a party to present an 
  application, written reply, rejoinder or any other document on its behalf 
  before the Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> applicant means a person making an application to the Tribunal 
  under sub-section (2) of section 14 or an appeal under sub-section (2) of 
  section 15 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> application includes Original Application (O.A.), Review Application 
  (R.A.), Transferred Application (T.A.), Miscellaneous Application (M.A.), 
  Application for Transfer (A.T.) and Contempt Application (C.A.), filed before 
  the Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> Code means the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> Court appealed from includes a tribunal or any other judicial body 
  or court martial or authority against the decision of which an appeal is 
  preferred to this Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> Form means the Form set out in the appendices to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> judgment includes decree, order, sentence or determination of any 
  Court, Tribunal, Judge, Judicial Officer or authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> legal practitioner shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in 
  the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961) and includes a Standing Counsel 
  authorised or appointed by the Central Government to accept the service for 
  any Department or Organization of Union of India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> legal representative means a person who in law represents the estate 
  of a serving or deceased person and includes a person or persons in whom the 
  right to receive pensionary, retirement, terminal, disability or other 
  benefits or family pension vests; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number> Officer of the Judge-Advocate General's Department means an officer 
  commissioned into the Judge-Advocate General's Department of the Army or an 
  officer permanently transferred to that Department after qualifying at the 
  Judge-Advocate General's Departmental examination and includes an officer of 
  Judge-Advocate General's Department of Navy and Air Force; 
 <subsubsection><number>xii</number> Pleadings shall include original applications, reply statement, 
  rejoinders and additional applications or statements supplementing the 
  original applications and the reply statements, as may be permitted by the 
  Tribunal; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiii</number> Registrar means Registrar of the Armed Forces Tribunal or its 
  Benches and shall include Registrar-General, Principal, Additional, Joint and 
  Deputy Registrars, authorised to discharge the functions of the Registrar; 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiv</number> Registry means the Registry of the Tribunal or any of its Benches, 
  as the case may be; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xv</number> section means a section of the Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xvi</number> Services means the Army, Navy and Air Force, as applicable; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xvii</number> Standing Counsel means an advocate authorised to act, represent 
  and accept the service for the Army, Navy or Air Force or for the Union of 
  India; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xviii</number> Transferred application means the suit or other proceeding which 
  has been transferred to the Tribunal under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
  of section 34; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xix</number> Vice-Chairperson means a Vice-Chairperson of a Tribunal. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined 
in the Act, the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950), the Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957) and 
the Air Force Act, 1950 (45 of 1950) shall have the same meaning respectively 
assigned to them in those Acts and respective rules made thereunder. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Language of the Tribunal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The language of the 
Tribunal shall be English: 
 Provided that the parties to a proceeding before the Tribunal may file 
documents drawn up in Hindi: 
 Provided further that 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Bench may, in its discretion permit the use of Hindi in the 
  proceedings; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Bench hearing the matter may, in its discretion, direct English 
  translation of pleadings and documents to be filed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> No document in a language other than English intended to be used in any 
proceeding shall be received by the Registrar unless it is accompanied by a 
translation in English certified to be a true translation. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Bench may, in its discretion, make final orders either in Hindi or in 
English: 
 Provided that where a final order is made in Hindi, an authenticated English 
translation thereof shall simultaneously be prepared and kept on record. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Procedure for filing applications. </title>
<section><number>1</number> An application to 
the Tribunal shall be presented in Form I by the applicant in person or by an 
agent or by a duly authorised legal practitioner to the Registrar or any other 
officer authorised in writing by the Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson to receive 
the same or be sent by registered post or by courier with acknowledgment due 
addressed to the Registrar of the Bench concerned. 
 
 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>2</number> (i) The application under sub-rule (1) shall be presented in triplicate 
  in the following two compilations: 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Compilation No 1.  application along with an attested 
      true copy of the impugned order against which the application is filed; 
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Compilation No 2.  all other documents and annexures 
      relied upon by the applicant and referred to in the application in a paper 
      book form. </subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> All the documents filed in the Tribunal shall be accompanied by an 
    index in duplicate containing their details memo of the parties and a list 
    of relevant dates. The amount of application fee affixed or paid on any such 
    documents shall also be indicated in the index. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the number of respondents is more than one, as many extra copies 
  of the application and all other documents and annexures referred thereto in 
  paper-book form as are the number of respondents together with unused file 
  size envelope bearing the full address of each respondent shall be furnished 
  by the applicant: 
 Provided that where the number of respondents is more than five, the 
  Registrar may permit the applicant to file extra copies of the application at 
  the time of issue of notice to the respondents. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The applicant may attach to and present with his application a receipt 
  slip in Form II which shall be signed by the Registrar or the Officer 
  receiving the application on behalf of the Registrar in acknowledgement of the 
  receipt of the application. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rules (1) to (3), the 
  Tribunal may permit more than one person, other than the person serving in the 
  regular Army, Navy or Air Force to join together and file a single application 
  if it is satisfied, having regard to the cause of action and the nature of 
  relief prayed for, that they have a common interest in the matter: 
 Provided that all affected persons are impleaded as parties and they join 
  together to file such an application, when they are likely to be affected by 
  the decision in the case. </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Presentation and scrutiny of applications. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Registrar or the officer authorised under rule 4 shall endorse the date of 
receipt on the application and also on the duplicate copy of the index and 
return the same to the party and in case of an application received by post, he 
shall endorse the date of its receipt and send the duplicate index to the 
applicant concerned. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the application is found to be in order, it shall be 
duly registered and given a serial number. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the application is found to be defective and the defect noticed is 
formal in nature, the Registrar may allow the applicant to rectify the same in 
his presence, and if the said defect is not formal in nature, the Registrar may 
for sufficient cause return the said application for rectification or amendment 
to the party filing the same, and for this purpose may allow the party concerned 
such reasonable time as he may consider necessary. Where an application is 
received by registered post, the applicant shall be informed of the defects, if 
any, and he shall be required to rectify the same within such time as may be 
stipulated by the Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> (i) If the applicant fails to rectify the defect within the time allowed 
under sub-rule (3), the Registrar may by order and for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, decline to register the application and place the matter before the 
Bench for appropriate orders. Such matter may be dealt with and disposed by the 
Bench in chamber. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Any applicant aggrieved by any order made by the Registrar under this 
  rule may, within fifteen days of the making of such order, appeal against it 
  to the Chairperson in case the matter relates to Principal Bench and to the 
  Vice-Chairperson concerned, in the case of any other Bench and such appeal may 
  be dealt with and disposed of in chamber by the Chairperson or the 
  Vice-Chairperson concerned or in their absence by any Member authorised by the 
  Chairperson by special or general order, whose decision thereon shall be 
  final. </subsection>
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Place of filing application. </title>
<section><number>1</number> An application shall ordinarily be filed by the applicant with the Registrar of the Bench within whose jurisdiction 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the applicant is posted for the time being, or was last posted or attached; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where the cause of action, wholly or in part, has arisen: 
</subsection>
 Provided that with the leave of the Chairperson the application may be filed with the Registrar of the Principal Bench and subject to the orders under  
  section 14 or section 15 of the Act, such application shall be heard and disposed of by the Bench which has jurisdiction over the matter. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), a person who has ceased to be in service by reason of his retirement, dismissal, discharge, cashiering, release, removal, resignation or termination of service may, at his option, file an application with the Registrar of the Bench within whose jurisdiction such person is ordinarily residing at the time of filing of the application. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th September, 2008. 
  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number></title><title>Application fee. </title>Every 
application filed with the Registrar shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees two 
hundred and fifty to be remitted either in the form of crossed demand draft on a 
nationalized bank in favour of the Registrar of the concerned Bench and payable 
at the main Branch of that bank at the station where the seat of the said Bench 
is situated, or remitted through a crossed Indian Postal Order drawn in favour 
of the Registrar of the concerned Bench and payable at the post office of the 
station where the said Bench is situate: 
 Provided that where the Tribunal permits a single application to be filed on 
behalf of more than one person, the fee payable shall be rupees five hundred: 

 Provided further that where the Tribunal is satisfied that an applicant is 
unable to pay the prescribed fee on ground of indigence, it may exempt such an 
applicant from the payment of application fee. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number>Contents of application. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every application filed 
under section 14 or section 15 shall be fairly and legibly typed or printed in 
double spacing on one side of thick paper of good quality with an inner margin 
of about three cm width on top and on the left side. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Paragraphs shall be divided into sub-paragraphs and numbered 
consecutively. Each paragraph shall contain, as nearly as may be a, separate 
accounts of events. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Dates of Gregorian Calendar shall also be given where Saka or other dates 
are used. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> At the foot of every application there shall appear the name and 
signature of the applicant or the agent or legal practitioner, if any, who has 
drawn and settled it. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The particulars to be stated in address for service shall as far as 
possible contain the following: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the name of the road, street, lane or municipal or other number of the 
  house; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the name of the town or village; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the post office or postal district together with pin code; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> any other particulars including personal number, rank, appointment 
  held, unit or office or pension payment order (PPO) number necessary to 
  identify the addressee. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every interlineations, erasure or correction in any application shall be 
initialled by the applicant or his agent/legal practitioner presenting it. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> It shall not be necessary to present a separate application to seek an 
interim order or direction if the same is prayed for in original application. 

 </section><section><number>8</number> An applicant may, subsequent to the filing of an application made under 
the Act, may apply for an interim order or direction. Such an application shall, 
as far as possible, be in separate form. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where the applicant seeks condonation of delay, he shall file a separate 
application supported by an affidavit. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number>Documents to be annexed to the application. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
following documents shall be annexed to the application: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> an attested true copy of the order against which the application is 
  filed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> copies of the documents relied upon by the applicant and referred to 
  in the application; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> an index of the documents. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The documents referred to in sub-rule (1) may be attested by a legal 
practitioner or by a Gazetted Officer and each document shall be marked serially 
as Annexures A-1, A-2, A-3 and so on. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an application is filed by an agent, documents authorizing him to 
act as such shall also be appended to the application: 
 Provided that where an application is filed by a legal practitioner, it shall 
be accompanied by a duly executed  Vakalatnama . 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number>Plural remedies. </title>An application shall be based upon a 
single cause of action and may seek one or more relief, provided that they are 
consequential to one another. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number>Service of notices and processes issued by the Tribunal. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Notices to be issued by the Tribunal may be served to the party by 
any of the following modes: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> service by the party itself; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> by hand delivery (dasti) through a process server; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> by registered post or a courier agency with acknowledgment due' or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> through the concerned Head of office of the same Department: 
</subsection>
 Provided that if the Tribunal does not specify the mode of service, notice 
may be sent by registered post with acknowledgment due and the provision of 
 Order V of First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) 
shall apply to such mode of service. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where notice issued by the Tribunal is served by the party himself by 
hand delivery' (dasti), he shall file with the Registry of the 
Tribunal, the acknowledgment, together with an affidavit of service. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) the Tribunal may, 
taking into account the number of respondents and their places of residence or 
work and other circumstances, direct that notice of the application shall be 
served upon the respondents in any other manner, including any manner of 
substituted service, as it appears to the Tribunal just and proper. The Tribunal 
may also, in its discretion, having regard to the nature of the case, direct the 
service of the notice on the Standing Counsel, authorised to accept the service, 
for all the three services Headquarters, Army, Navy and Air Force and the 
Ministry of Defence. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every notice issued by the Tribunal shall unless otherwise ordered, be 
accompanied by a copy of the application and a copy of the impugned order. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every applicant shall pay the following fee for the service or execution 
of processes, in respect of an application where the number of respondents 
exceeds five: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a sum of rupees fifty for each respondent in excess of five 
  respondents; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where the service is in such a manner as the Tribunal may direct under 
  sub-rule (3), such sum, not exceeding the actual charges incurred in effecting 
  the service, as may be determined by the Tribunal. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> The fee for the service or execution of processes under sub-rule (3), 
shall be remitted in the manner prescribed in rule 4 within one week of the date 
of the order determining the fee or within such extended time as the Registrar 
may permit. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rules (1) to (3), if the 
Tribunal is satisfied that it is not reasonably practicable to serve notice of 
application upon all the respondents, it may, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, direct that the application shall be heard notwithstanding that some of 
the respondents have not been served with notice of the application: 
 Provided that no application shall be heard unless 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> notice of the application has been served on the Central Government or 
  the State Government if such Government is a respondent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> notice of the application has been served on the authority which 
  passed the order against which the application has been filed; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Tribunal is satisfied that the interests of the respondents on 
  whom notice of the application has not been served are adequately and 
  sufficiently represented by the other respondents on whom notice of the 
  application has been served. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>8</number> The office of the Department or Ministry receiving notices or documents 
from the Tribunal shall mention name and designation along with office stamp, 
date and time of receipt on the acknowledgment slip before the same are returned 
to the Tribunal. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number>Filing of reply and other documents by the respondents. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Each respondent intending to contest the application, shall file 
in triplicate the reply to the application and the documents relied upon in 
paper-book form with the Registry, within one month of the service of notice of 
the application on him. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the reply filed under sub-rule (1), the respondent shall specifically 
admit, deny or explain the facts stated by the applicant in his application and 
may also state such additional facts as may be found necessary for the just 
decision of the case. It shall be signed and verified as a written statement by 
the respondent or any other person duly authorised by him in writing in the same 
manner as provided for in Order VI, rule 15 of the Code of Civil Procedure 1908 
(5 of 1908). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The documents referred to in sub-rule (2) shall also be filed along with 
the reply and the same shall be marked as R1, R2, R3 and so on. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The respondent shall also serve a copy of the reply along with documents 
as mentioned in sub-rule (2) on the applicant or his legal practitioner, if any, 
and file proof of such service in the Registry. In the case of more than one 
applicant, a copy of the reply shall be sent to each one of them. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Tribunal may allow filing of the reply after the expiry of the 
prescribed period with the leave of the Tribunal, or where appropriate order 
imposition of costs or pass any other order. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Tribunal may permit the parties to amend the pleadings in the same 
manner as provided under Order 6, rule 17 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 
(5 of 1908). 
 </section><section><number>7</number> An officer acquainted with the facts of the case but not below the rank 
of Commissioned Officer or a Group A' Officer or a Desk Officer in any Ministry 
or Department of the Union of India may verify the pleadings and other documents 
to be filed for and on behalf of the Union of India before the Tribunal. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number>Filing of written statements before the Benches expeditiously. 
</title>After the receipt of the notice from the Tribunal the respondents will 
file their statements/reply on the date fixed for hearing to enable the Tribunal 
to dispose of the application filed before it as expeditiously as possible. If 
for any reasons, the service Headquarter or the Department/Ministry is unable to 
file their statements on the date fixed, they will produce through a responsible 
official, the required records/documents before the Tribunal to enable it to 
proceed with the case further on the basis of the records/documents and written 
statements may be filed subsequently. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number>Date and place of hearing to be notified. </title>The Tribunal 
shall notify to the parties the date and the place of hearing of the application 
in such manner as the Chairperson may by general or special order direct. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Calendar of cases. </title>Each Bench shall draw up a calendar 
for the hearing of transferred cases and, as far as possible, hear and decide 
the cases according to the calendar. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number>Action on application for applicant's default. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where 
on the date fixed for hearing of the application or on any other date to which 
such hearing may be adjourned, the applicant does not appear when the 
application is called for hearing, the Tribunal may, in its discretion, either 
dismiss the application for default or hear and decide it on merits. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an application has been dismissed for default and the applicant 
files an application within thirty days from the date of dismissal and satisfies 
the Tribunal that there was sufficient cause for his non-appearance when the 
application was called for hearing, the Tribunal shall make an order setting 
aside the order dismissing the application and restore the same: 
 Provided that, where the case has been disposed of on merits the same shall 
not be reopened except by way of review. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number>Ex parte hearing and disposal of application. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Where on the date fixed for hearing the application or on any 
other date to which such hearing may be adjourned, the applicant appears and the 
respondent does not appear when the application is called for hearing, the 
Tribunal may, in its discretion adjourn the hearing or hear and decide the 
application ex parte. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an application has been heard ex parte against a 
respondent or respondents, such respondent or respondents may apply within 
thirty days from the date of the order to the Tribunal for an order to set aside 
and if such respondent or respondents satisfy the Tribunal that the notice was 
not duly served, or that he or they were prevented by any sufficient cause from 
appearing when the application was called for hearing, the Tribunal shall make 
an order setting aside the ex parte hearing as against him or them upon 
such terms as it thinks fit, and shall appoint a day for proceeding with the 
application: 
 Provided that where the ex parte hearing of the application is of 
such nature that it cannot be set aside as against one respondent only, it may 
be set aside as against all or any of the other respondents also: 
 Provided further that in cases covered by sub-rule (6) of rule 11, the 
Tribunal shall not set aside ex parte hearing of an application merely 
on the ground that such notice was not served upon a respondent or respondents. 

 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number>Application for review. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No application for review 
shall be entertained unless it is filed within thirty days from the date of 
receipt of copy of the order sought to be reviewed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for review shall ordinarily be heard by the same Bench 
which has passed the order, unless the Chairperson may, for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, direct it to be heard by any other Bench. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Unless otherwise ordered by the Bench concerned, an application for 
review shall be disposed of by circulation where the Bench may either dismiss 
the application or direct notice to be issued to the opposite party. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where an application for review of any judgment or order has been 
disposed of, thereafter no application for further review shall lie. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> No application for review shall be entertained unless it is supported by 
a duly sworn affidavit indicating therein the source of knowledge, personal or 
otherwise. The counter-affidavit in review application will also be a duly sworn 
affidavit wherever any averment of fact is disputed. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number>Substitution of legal representatives. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In the case 
of death of a party during the pendency of the proceedings before the Tribunal, 
the legal heir or representatives of the deceased party may apply within ninety 
days of the date of such death for being brought on record as a necessary party. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Where no application is received from the legal heir or representatives 
within the period specified in sub-rule (1), the proceedings against the 
deceased party shall abate: 
 Provided that for good and sufficient reasons the Tribunal, may on an 
application, set aside the order of abatement and substitute the legal heir or 
representatives. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number>Adjournment of hearing. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal may if 
sufficient cause is shown at any stage of proceedings grant time to the parties 
or any of them, and adjourn the hearing of the application. The Tribunal may 
make such order as it deems fit with respect to the costs occasioned by the 
adjournment. All adjournments shall be to a day certain and no application or 
matter shall be adjourned sine die except for reasons recorded in 
writing. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Tribunal shall have the power to decline an adjournment and also to 
limit the time for oral arguments: 
 Provided that where the Tribunal deems it necessary, for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, it may allow oral evidence to be adduced. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number>Order to be signed and dated. </title>Every order of the 
Tribunal shall be in writing and shall be signed by the Member or Members 
constituting the Bench, which pronounced the order. The orders shall be 
pronounced in open Court. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number>Publication of orders. </title>Such of the orders of the 
Tribunal, as are deemed fit for publication in any authoritative report or 
Military Law Journal or the press, may be released for such publication on such 
terms and conditions as the Chairperson may specify by general or special order. 

 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number>Communication of orders to the parties. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every 
interim order, granting or refusing or modifying interim relief and final order 
shall be communicated to the applicant and to the concerned respondent or to 
their legal practitioner either by hand delivery or by post free of cost: 
 Provided that unless ordered otherwise by a Bench, a copy of the final order 
need not be sent to any respondent who has not entered appearance: 
 Provided further that when the applicants or the respondents are represented 
by a legal practitioner, under a single Vakalatnama, only one copy 
shall be supplied to such legal practitioner as named therein. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the applicant or the respondent to any proceeding requires a copy of 
any document or proceeding the same shall be supplied to him on such terms and 
conditions and on payment of such fee as may be fixed by the Chairperson by 
general or special order. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number>Inspection of the records. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Inspection of records of 
a pending or decided case before the Tribunal shall be allowed only under the 
orders of the Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The parties to any case or their legal practitioner may be allowed to 
inspect the record of the case on making an application in writing to the 
Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to such terms and conditions as may be prescribed by the 
Chairperson by a general or special order, a person who is not a party to the 
proceedings, may also be allowed to inspect the record after obtaining the 
permission of the Registrar in writing. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number>Powers of the Tribunal with regard to certain orders and 
directions. </title>Nothing in these rules shall be deemed to limit or 
otherwise affect the inherent powers of the Tribunal to make such orders or give 
such directions as may be necessary or expedient to give effect to its orders or 
to prevent abuse of its process or to secure the ends of justice. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number>Commission for local inquiry and accounts. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Whenever 
it becomes necessary in the course of proceedings before the Tribunal to appoint 
a commission to make a local inquiry or to examine documents or accounts, the 
Chairperson or the Vice-Chairperson may issue orders for such appointments, 
specifying therein 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the precise matter of the inquiry; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the reason asking why the evidence bearing on that matter could not 
  reasonably have been taken in the usual way in the proceedings in the 
  Tribunal. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Commissioners to examine accounts may be selected from persons competent 
in the particular form of accounts. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Tribunal shall exercise great care in selecting persons for 
appointment as commissioners for the purpose of making inquiries. The habitual 
employment of the same person should be avoided. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Tribunal shall for the said purpose, maintain a list of legal 
practitioner's whom the Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson may select, from time to 
time, as fit to be employed in such cases. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The legal practitioner so appointed shall receive a fee of Rs. 800 for 
the first effective hearing and Rs. 500 for every subsequent effective hearing 
in the same or similar matters or for non-effective hearing. In criminal cases 
including murder appeals, the fee shall be Rs. 2000 for preparation of the case, 
Rs. 1200 per effective hearing and Rs. 500 per non-effective hearing. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The certificate for the hearing shall be signed by the Registrar and the 
payment shall be made by the Government on production of the said certificate. 

 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number>Registration of legal practitioner's clerk. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No clerk 
employed by a legal practitioner shall act as such in the Tribunal or be 
permitted to have access to the records and obtain copies of the orders of the 
Bench of the Tribunal in which the legal practitioner ordinarily practice unless 
his name is entered in the Register of Clerks maintained by the said Bench. Such 
clerk shall be known as a Registered Clerk. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall be employed by a legal practitioner as his clerk unless 
such person has been a legal practitioner's clerk for three years, or is a 
qualified petition-writer or has passed the Graduation Examination of a 
recognized University: 
 Provided that no such person shall by employed as a Clerk: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> if he has been declared a tout; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> if he is an undischarged insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> if he has been convicted for an offence involving moral turpitude; or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> if he has been dismissed from the service of Government, unless he can 
  show that his dismissal was not due to conduct showing him unfit to be legal 
  practitioner's clerks, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> if he is an ex-petition-writer, whose licence has been cancelled for 
  corruption or for some other reasons involving dishonesty, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> if he is unfit to be a legal practitioner's clerk for any other 
  sufficient reason. </subsection>
 Explanation .Tout means a person who procures or attempts to 
procure for any consideration from any legal practitioner or from any person 
acting on his behalf, the employment of such legal practitioner in legal 
business, or who, for purposes of such procurement, frequents the precincts of 
the Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A legal practitioner desirous of registering his clerk shall make an 
application to the Registrar in Form III and pay a sum of one hundred rupees as 
one time Tribunal Fee. On such application being allowed by the Registrar, his 
name shall be entered in the Register of Clerks. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, declined to 
register any clerk, who in his opinion suffers from any disqualification 
specified in  rule 27 or is otherwise unsuitable to be registered at such. 

 </section><section><number>5</number> The Registrar may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, cancel the 
registration of any clerk after giving him and his employer an opportunity to 
show cause against such cancellation. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> An appeal may be filed against the order of the Registrar made under 
sub-rules (4) and (5) within 30 days from the date of the order to the 
Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> After registration of the clerk, the Registrar shall direct the issue of 
an identity card to him which shall be non-transferable and shall be produced by 
the holder upon request by an officer or other employees of the Tribunal 
authorised in this behalf. The identity card shall be issued under the signature 
of the Deputy Registrar of the Bench concerned. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> A register of all the clerks registered under sub-rule (2) shall be 
maintained in the office of the Registrar of each Bench. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> A legal practitioner shall have at a time not more than two registered 
clerks unless the Registrar by general or special order otherwise permits. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> Whenever a legal practitioner ceases to employ a registered clerk, he 
shall notify the fact at once to the Registrar by means of a letter enclosing 
therewith the identity card issued to his clerk by the Registry, and on receipt 
of such letter the name of the said registered clerk shall be struck off from 
the register. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> No legal practitioner shall employ as his clerk any person who is 
prohibited in the sub-rule (b) above. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number>Working hours of the Tribunal. </title>The offices of the 
Tribunal except on Saturday, Sundays and other public holidays, shall remain 
open daily from 9.30 A.M. to 5.30 P.M. subject to any general or special order 
made by the Chairperson. Any urgent matter filed before 12 noon shall be put 
before the Bench for hearing on the following working day. In exceptional cases, 
it may be received thereafter for hearing on the same day with the leave of the 
Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson, as the case may be. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Sitting hours of the Tribunal. </title>Unless otherwise ordered 
by the Chairperson by any general or special order or by the Vice-Chairperson 
concerned with the prior approval of the Chairperson, the Tribunal, including 
Vacation Bench shall hold its sitting on all working days from 10.00 A.M. to 
1.00 P.M. and from 2.00 P.M. to 4.30 P.M. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number>Functions of the Registrar. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall have 
the custody of the records of the Tribunal and shall exercise such other 
functions as are assigned to him under these rules or by the Chairperson or the 
Vice-Chairperson of the Bench concerned by separate order. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar may, with the approval of the Chairperson or of the 
Vice-Chairperson of the Bench concerned delegate to the Additional Registrar any 
function or power required by these rules to be performed or exercised by the 
Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the absence of the Registrar, the Additional Registrar or any other 
officer to whom the powers and functions of the Registrar are delegated by the 
Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson, may exercise the powers and functions of the 
Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may if the circumstances so require, or if so directed by 
the Bench, at any time adjourn any matter and lay the same before the concerned 
Bench. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number>Powers and duties of Registrar. </title>The Registrar shall have 
the following powers and duties subject to any general or special order of the 
Chairperson or the Vice-Chairperson of the Bench concerned, namely: 
 
 <section><number>i</number> to receive all applications and other documents including transferred 
  applications; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> to decide all questions arising out of the scrutiny of the 
  applications before they are registered; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> to require any application presented to the Tribunal to be amended in 
  accordance with, the Act and the rules; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> subject to the direction of the respective Benches, to fix the date of 
  first hearing of the applications or other proceedings and issue notices 
  thereof; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> to direct any formal amendment of records; 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> to order grant of copies of documents to parties to the proceedings; 
  
 </section><section><number>vii</number> to grant leave to inspect the records of the Tribunal; 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> to dispose of all matters relating to the service of notices or 
  other processes, applications for the issue of fresh notices and for extending 
  the time for filing such applications and to grant time, not exceeding 30 
  days, for filing a reply or rejoinder if any, and to place the matter before 
  the Bench for appropriate orders after the expiry of the aforesaid period; 

 </section><section><number>ix</number> to requisition records from the custody of any Court, Service 
  Headquarter, office, Department or other authority; 
 </section><section><number>x</number> to receive application within ninety days from the date of death for 
  substitution of legal representatives of the deceased parties during the 
  pendency of the application; 
 </section><section><number>xi</number> to receive and dispose of application for substitution, except where 
  the substitution would involve setting aside an order of abatement; 
 <subsection><number>xii</number> to receive and dispose of application by parties for return of 
  documents. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiii</number> registration of the legal practitioner's clerk. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiv</number> in case of the Principal Bench, to call for information and records 
  and to inspect or cause to be inspected the Registry of the other Benches 
  under general or special orders as may be issued by the Chairperson from time 
  to time. </subsection></section>
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number>Seal and emblem. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The official seal and emblem of the 
Tribunal shall be such as the Chairperson may from time to time direct and shall 
be kept in the custody of the Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to any general or special direction by the Chairperson, the seal 
of the Tribunal shall not be affixed to any order, summons or other process save 
under the authority in writing of the Registrar or the Additional Registrar. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The seal of the Tribunal shall not be affixed to any certified copy 
issued by the Tribunal save under the authority in writing of the Registrar or 
the Additional Registrar. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number>Dress of the Members and staff of the Tribunal. </title>The 
dress for the Members of the Tribunal including Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson 
and the staff shall be such as the Chairperson may specify. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number>Dress of the parties. </title>A legal practitioner or, as the 
case may be, the Presenting Officer shall appear before the Tribunal in his 
professional dress, if any, and if there is no such dress 
 
 <section><number>i</number> if a male, in shirt and trousers with or without tie or in a lounge 
  suit; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> if a female, in a saree or any other customary dress of a sober 
  colour. </section>
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 26(E), dated 17th September, 2008, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. IV, dated 17th 
September, 2008. 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>