<act><tid>1547</tid>
<title>THE HIGH DENOMINATION BANK NOTES (DEMONETISATION) ACT, <year>1978</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1978</year>
[ 30th March, <year>1978</year>.]

An Act to provide in the public interest for the demonetisation 
of certain high denomination bank notes and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS the availability of high denomination bank notes 
facilitates the illicit transfer of money for financing transactions 
which are harmful to the national economy or which are for illegal 
purposes and it is therefore necessary in the public interest to 
demonetise high denomination bank notes;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- ninth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>488089</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1615964</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the High Denomination Bank Notes (Demonetisation) Act, <year>1978</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>482905</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>283208</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 16th day 
of January, <year>1978</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>791557</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1520583</tid>
<number>a</number>" bank" means-

<subsection><tid>1965673</tid>
<number>i</number>a banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 
of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1842546</tid>
<number>ii</number>the State Bank of India constituted under the State 
Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489142</tid>
<number>iii</number>a subsidiary bank as defined in the State Bank of 
India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1905683</tid>
<number>iv</number>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of 
the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of  
  Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>610197</tid>
<number>v</number>a regional rural bank established under sub- section (1) 
of section 3 of the Regional Rural Banks Act, <year>1976</year> (21 of  
  <year>1976</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373211</tid>
<number>vi</number>a co- operative bank as defined in section 2 of the 
Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);
and includes every branch thereof;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1859642</tid>
<number>b</number>" bank notes" means the bank notes issued by the Reserve 
Bank of India under section 22 of the Reserve Bank of India 
Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>105831</tid>
<number>c</number>" distinctive number" in relation to a high denomination 
bank note means the number including the alphabetical and 
numerical prefixes appearing on the face of the note;

</section>

<section><tid>1658721</tid>
<number>d</number>" high denomination bank note" means a bank note of the 
denominational value of one thousand rupees, five thousand 
rupees or ten thousand rupees, issued by the Reserve Bank;

</section>

<section><tid>913915</tid>
<number>e</number>" public sector bank" means a bank referred to in sub- 
clause (ii), (iii) or (iv) of clause (a);

</section>

<section><tid>75871</tid>
<number>f</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of  
  <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1451835</tid>
<number>g</number>" scheduled bank" means a public sector bank or any 
other bank, being a bank included in the Second Schedule to 
the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1866930</tid>
<number>h</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted 
under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>422196</tid>
<number>3</number>High denomination bank notes to cease to be legal tender. 
On the expiry of the 16th day of January, <year>1978</year>, all high 
denomination bank notes shall, notwithstanding anything contained in 
section 26 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>, (2 of <year>1934</year>) cease 
to be legal tender in payment or on account at any place.


</article>



<article><tid>158697</tid>
<number>4</number>Prohibition of transfer and receipt of high denomination bank 
notes. Save as provided by or under this Act, no person shall, after 
the 16th day of January, <year>1978</year>, transfer to the possession of another 
person or receive into his possession from another person any high 
denomination bank- note.


</article>



<article><tid>1833463</tid>
<number> 5</number> Declaration of high denomination bank notes by banks and 
Government treasuries.
<section><tid>1888049</tid>
<number>1</number>Every bank and Government treasury shall  
prepare and send to the Reserve Bank in the manner provided in this 
section a return showing separately under each denominational value 
the total value of high denomination bank notes of that value held by 
it at the close of business on the 16th day of January, <year>1978</year> and 
distinctive numbers of high denomination bank notes of that value:
Provided that a bank or a Government treasury in which the 
currency chest of the Issue Department of the Reserve Bank has been 
established shall also submit a separate return showing separately 
under each denominational value the total value of high denomination 
bank notes held in such currency chest at the close of business on the 
 16th day of January, <year>1978</year> and the distinctive numbers of high 
denomination bank notes of that value.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>119</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1617693</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such return shall be prepared and presented as 
provided in sub- section (3) in triplicate and shall be signed by the 
Manager of the bank or other person in charge of the bank or the 
Government treasury.

</section>

<section><tid>1046779</tid>
<number>3</number>Every return under sub- section (1) shall be presented for 
forwarding to the Reserve Bank to the Manager of the sub- office, 
office or branch of the Reserve Bank at the places specified under 
sub- section (2) of section 7, or to the District Magistrate or to the 
Sub- divisional Magistrate or, if such Manager or Magistrate is not 
available, to the senior- most Revenue or Police Officer available not 
later than 3. 00 P. m. on the 17th day of January, <year>1978</year>:
Provided that if it is not feasible to present the return to any 
such person as aforesaid, it may be presented by handing two copies 
thereof not later than 3. 00 P. m. on the 17th day of January, <year>1978</year> to a 
telegraph office, one copy for despatch by express telegram to the 
Reserve Bank at Bombay at the expense of the bank or the Government 
treasury, as the case may be, and the other copy for return to the 
person presenting it in the manner provided in sub- section (4), and by 
despatching the third copy required by sub- section (2) by registered 
post on the same day to the Reserve Bank at Bombay.


</section>

<section><tid>282098</tid>
<number>4</number>The officer to whom the return is presented shall give back 
to the person presenting it one copy thereof under his signature and 
seal of office in acknowledgement of receipt on which shall also be 
recorded the time and date of receipt, and such officer shall without 
delay forward one copy of the return to the Reserve Bank at Bombay.

</section>

<section><tid>1414602</tid>
<number>5</number>The Manager or other person in charge of every bank or 
Government theasury shall, immediately after the preparation of the 
returns required to be submitted under this section, cause the high 
denomination bank notes mentioned therin to be kept in a separate 
receptacle and seal the same with his seal and of the officers having 
custody of such receptacle.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1632580</tid>
<number> 6</number> Exchange of high denomination bank notes held by banks and 
government treasuries.
<section><tid>113280</tid>
<number>1</number>A bank other than a public sector bank may  
obtain from the Reserve Bank or a public sector bank an equivalent 
amount in exchange for the high denomination bank notes declared by it 
in the return referred to in section 5 by credit to an account 
maintained with the Reserve Bank or a public sector bank or in bank 
notes.

</section>

<section><tid>626338</tid>
<number>2</number>A public sector bank may obtain from the Reserve Bank an 
equivalent amount in exchange for the high denomination bank notes 
declared by it in the return referred to in section 5 or the high 
denomination bank notes received by it in exchange under sub- section 
 (1) by credit to an account with the Reserve Bank or in bank notes.

</section>

<section><tid>1350785</tid>
<number>3</number>A Government treasury may obtain from the Reserve Bank an 
equivalent amount in exchange for the high denomination bank notes

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

declared by it in the return referred to in section 5 in bank notes or 
by credit to Government account.


</section>

<section><tid>1950447</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1), (2) 
and (3), where the return referred to in section 5 is presented in the 
manner provided in the proviso to sub- section (3) of that section, the 
exchange referred to in this section may be effected only by the 
Reserve Bank at Bombay.

</section>

<section><tid>647694</tid>
<number>5</number>Every application for the exchange of high denomination bank 
notes under this section shall be accompanied by the copy of the 
return received under sub- section (4) of section 5 which contains the 
distinctive numbers of such bank notes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1038060</tid>
<number> 7</number> Exchange of high denomination bank notes held by other persons.

<section><tid>666046</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstading anything to the contrary contained in the Reserve  
Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>), any high denomination bank note 
owned by a person other than a bank or Government treasury may be 
exchanged after the 16th day of January, <year>1978</year>, only on tender of the 
note-

<subsection><tid>1109993</tid>
<number>a</number>where the high denomination bank note is owned by an 
individual, by the individual himself; or where the 
individual. is absent from India, by the individual concerned 
or some persons duly authorised by him in this behalf; or 
where the individual is mentally incapacitated from attending 
to his affairs, by his guarian or by any other person 
competent to act on his behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1128296</tid>
<number>b</number>where the high denomination bank note is owned by a 
Hindu undivided family, by the karta, and, where the karta is 
absent from India or is mentally incapacitated from attending 
to his affairs, by any other adult member of his family;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>789365</tid>
<number>c</number>where the high denomination bank note is owned by a 
company, by the managing director thereof, or, where for any 
unavoidable reason such managing director is not able to 
tender the note, or; where there is no managing director, by 
any director thereof

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1385329</tid>
<number>d</number>where the high denomination bank note forms part of the 
assets of a firm, by the managing partner thereof, or, where 
for any unavoidable reason such partner is not able to tender 
the note, or where there is no managing partner as such, by 
any partner thereof not being a minor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>725745</tid>
<number>e</number>where the high denomination bank note is owned by any 
other association of persons, by any member of the associa- 
tion or the principal officer thereof; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>908901</tid>
<number>f</number>where the high denomination bank note is owned by any 
other person, by that person or by some person competent to 
act on his behalf;
and within the time and in the manner provided in this section.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>121</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>261150</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person desiring to tender for exchange a high 
denomination bank note under this section shall prepare in the form 
set out, in the Schedule three copies of a declaration signed by him 
giving in full the particulars required by that form and shalls not 
later than the 19th day of January, <year>1978</year>, deliver such copier, in 
person together with the high denomination bank notes he desires to 
exchange-

<subsection><tid>306668</tid>
<number>a</number>to either of the offices of the Reserve Bank at Bombay 
or to the sub- office, office or branch, as the case may be, 
of that bank at Ahmedabad, Bangalore, Bhubaneshwar, Calcutta, 
Gauhati, Hyderabad, Jaipur, Kanpur, Madras, Nagpur, New Delhi 
and Patna; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>107683</tid>
<number>b</number>to the main office or branch of the State Bank at the 
headquarters of a district; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>123708</tid>
<number>c</number>to any other office of a public sector bank notified in 
this behalf by the Reserve Bank:
Provided that if such person resides in a place not within 
convenient reach of any such office or branch, or if, by reason of 
age, infirmity or illness he is unable to attend thereat, he may 
forward the high denomination bank notes he desires to exchange 
together with three copies of the declaration in respect thereof by 
insured post to the Reserve Bank at Bombay not later than the 19th day 
of January, <year>1978</year>.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>69769</tid>
<number>3</number>Every declaration under this section shall, for the purpose 
of identifying the person making it, be attested by the manager or 
other person in charge of the bank, if any, with which he maintains an 
account, or by a salaried Magistrate or a Justice of the P. ace or a 
police officer not below the rank of an Inspector of Police,

</section>

<section><tid>1813597</tid>
<number>4</number>Unless it appears that the declaration has not been complete 
in all material particulars, the Reserve Bank, the State Bank or any 
bank notified under clause (c) of sub- section (2), as the case may be, 
to which an application for exchange of high denomination bank notes 
is made under this section, shall pay the exchange value of the said 
notes for credit to a properly introduced account of te owner or the 
declarant, as the case may be, with any scheduled bank:
Provided that if the owner or declarant, as the case may be, does 
not have a bank account, the exchange value of the said notes shall be 
paid only on proper identification and until payment is so made, the 
amount shall remain in the custody of the Reserve Bank or the bank, as 
the cas. may be, to which the high denomination bank notes were 
tendered:


</section>

<section><tid>1286677</tid>
<number>5</number>Where it appears that the declaration has not been completed 
in all material particulars, the Reserve Bank, the State Bank or the 
notified bank, as the case may be, to which such application as 
aforesaid is made

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall, unless the declarant is able to supply the omission without 
delay, refuse to accept and pay for the bank notes to which the 
declaration relates, and where it does so refuse, shall return one 
copy of the declaration to the declarant after entering therein the 
date on which it is presented and shall refer the matter to the 
Central Government to which it shall forward a copy of the declaration 
with a brief statement of the reasons for refusing to pay for the bank 
notes.


</section>

<section><tid>987831</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government may require any declarant referred to 
in sub- section (5) to, amplify his declaration to such extent and in 
respect of such particulars as it thinks fit and may, unless the 
declarant is able to fully comply with such requirement, refuse, 
for reasons to be recorded in writing, to sanction the exchange of the 
high denomination bank notes to which the declaration relates.

</section>

<section><tid>486689</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government or any person or authority authorised 
by it in this behalf may, by order in writing and for reasons to be 
recorded therein, extend in any case or class of cases the period 
during which high denomination bank notes may be tendered for exchange 
under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>963822</tid>
<number> 8</number> Exchange of notes after the time limit specified in section 7.

<section><tid>1403433</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, any person who  
fails to apply for exchange of any high denomination bank notes within 
the time provided in that section may tender the notes together with 
the declaration required under that section to the Reserve Bank at any 
of the places specified in clause (a) of sub- section (2) of that 
section, not later than the 24th day of January, <year>1978</year> together with a 
statement explaining the reasons for his failure to apply within the 
said time limit:
Provided that if such person resides in a place not within 
convenient reach of the sub- office, office or branch of the Reserve 
Bank at any of the said places or if, by reason of age, infirmity or 
illness, he is unable to attend thereat, he may forward the high 
denomination bank notes be desires to exchange together with three 
copies of the declaration required under section- 7 by insured post to 
the Reserve Bank at Bombay not later than the 24th day of January, 
<year>1978</year>, along with a statement explaining the reasons for his failure to 
apply within the time specified in section 7.


</section>

<section><tid>1483799</tid>
<number>2</number>The Reserve Bank may if satisfied after making such 
inquiries as it may consider necessary that the reasons for the 
failure to submit the notes for exchange within the time provided in 
section 7 are genuine, pay the value of the notes in the manner 
specified in sub- section (4) of that section.

</section>

<section><tid>1066243</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person aggrieved by the refusal of the reserve Bank to 
pay the value of the notes under sub- section (2) may prefer an appeal 
to the Central Government within fourteen days of the communication of 
such refusal to him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1535177</tid>
<number> 9</number> Closing of banks and Government treasuries.
<section><tid>1498114</tid>
<number>1</number>All banks and  
Government treasuries shall be closed on the 17th day of January, <year>1978</year> 
for the transaction of all business except the preparation and 
presentation or, as the case may be, receipt of the returns referred 
to in section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>1471335</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to tb- section (1), the 17th day 
of January <year>1978</year> shall for the purposes of the Negotiable Instruments 
Act, <year>1881</year> (2 of <year>1881</year>), be deemed to be a public holiday notified 
under that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>875120</tid>
<number> 10</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>1695801</tid>
<number>1</number>If any bank fails to prepare and present within  
the time and in the manner provided by section 5 any return referred 
to in that section, or presents any return under that section which is 
false in any material particular, the manager or other person in 
charge of the bank shall, unless he proves that the failure took place 
or the false return was presented, without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the same, be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, 
or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>81666</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever knowingly makes in any declaration under section 7 
any statement which is false or only partially true or which he does 
not believe to be true or contravences any provision of this Act or 
the rules made thereunder shall, be punishable with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to three years or with fine or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>897816</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer of a scheduled bank who makes payment out of the 
amount, being the exchange value of a high denomination bank note 
credited under sub- section (4) of section 7 to an account maintained 
with such bank shall, unless such account is an account which has been 
opened after proper introduction, be punishable with imprisonment for 
a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1938759</tid>
<number> 11</number> Special provisions relating to offences.
<section><tid>319653</tid>
<number>1</number>No prosecution  
for an offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted except 
with the previous sanction of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1027466</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything in section 29 of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), the court of a Magistrate of the 
first class or the court of a Metropolitan Magistrate trying an 
offence punishable under this Act may impose a fine exceeding five 
thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>592561</tid>
<number>12</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government or any 
officer of the Government or against the Reserve Bank or any public 
sector bank or any officer of such bank for anything done or intended 
to be done in good faith under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>331141</tid>
<number>13</number>Removal of difficulties. If any difficulty arises in giving 
effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make any order, not inconsistent 
with the provisions of this Act, which appears to it to be necessary 
for the purpose of removing the difficulty:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that every such order shall, as soon as may be after it is 
made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</article>



<article><tid>966406</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>535725</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make rules  
for giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1286717</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>162727</tid>
<number>a</number>the custody and disposal of high denomination bank 
notes tendered for exchange under this Act and of the 
declarations in respect thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>691290</tid>
<number>b</number>the time within which applications referred to in sub- 
section (5) of section 6 may be made; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1616341</tid>
<number>c</number>the time within which and the manner in which the State 
Bank and public sector banks notified under clause (c) of 
sub- section (2) of section 7 may claim reimbursement from the 
Reserve Bank of payments made by them in respect of high 
denomination bank notes accepted by them under that section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>85846</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>793756</tid>
<number> 15</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>35802</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Denomination Bank Notes  
 (Demonetisation) Ordinance, <year>1978</year> (1 of <year>1978</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1282303</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>