<act><title>


The Dock Workers (Advisory Committee) 
Rules, 19621</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Dock Workers (Advisory Committee) Rules, 1962.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They extend to all the 
major ports in India.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means 
the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1948 (9 of 1948); 
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> ‘Chairman’ 
means the Chairman of the Dock Workers Advisory Committee;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  ‘Committee’ 
means the Dock Workers Advisory Committee;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  ‘Member’ 
means a member of the Dock Workers Advisory Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Constitution.—The 
Committee shall consist of the following 

1[thirty] members 
to be appointed by the Central Government, namely:—
 <section>
<number>1</number> 

1[Ten] members 
representing the Central Government who shall be—
 

              2(i) 
The secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of 

1[Surface 
Transport], who shall be the Chairman.
 <subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  A 
representative of the Ministry of Labour].
 
 

3[(iiA)  A 
representative of the Ministry of Agriculture;]
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  the 
Chairman, Calcutta Dock Labour Board. 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number>  the 
Chairman, Bombay Dock Labour Board.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number>  Chairman, 
Madras Dock Labour Board.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vi</number>  Chairman, 
Cochin Dock Labour Board.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vii</number>  the 
Chairman, Vizagapatnam Dock Labour Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 

1[Ten] members 
representing the employers of dock workers and shipping companies, who shall be 
appointed in consultation with such association of employers and shipping 
companies as the Central Government may consider appropriate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 

1[Ten] members 
representing the dock workers who shall be appointed in consultation with such 
unions of dock workers as the Central Government may consider appropriate.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Secretary of the 
Committee.—The 
Deputy Secretary in the 

1[Ministry of


2[Surface 
Transport]] of the Government of India or any other officer nominated by that 
Government shall be the Secretary of the Committee and shall be entitled to 
attend and take part in the meetings of the Committee. He shall not have a right 
to vote.
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Functions.—The 
Committee shall advise the Central Government upon such matters arising out of 
the administration of the Act or any scheme made thereunder as the Central 
Government may refer to it for advice.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Term of office of 
members.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
member other than a member representing the Central Government shall hold office 
for a period of three years from the date of the notification appointing him as 
a member and shall be eligible for reappointment:
 
Provided that an outgoing 
member shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is 
notified in the Official Gazette:
 
Provided further that a 
member appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the unexpired 
portion of the term of the person in whose place he is appointed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member representing 
the Central Government may be appointed either by name or by virtue of his 
office. Every such member shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A member other than a 
member representing the Central Government may resign his office by a letter 
under his hand addressed to the Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If a  member proposes 
to proceed out of India, he shall before doing so, intimate to the Chairman, the 
anticipated date of his departure from and of his return to India and, if he 
intends to be absent from India for a period exceeding six months, he shall 
tender his resignation.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A member shall be 
deemed to have vacated his office:
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  if he 
proceeds out of India without complying with the provisions of sub-rule (4);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  if he 
becomes an insolvent;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  if he is 
convicted of any offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
involves moral turpitude;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  if he is 
absent from three consecutive meetings of the Committee without leave of absence 
from the Chairman;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  if, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, a member who was appointed to represent dock 
workers or their employers ceases to be representative of dock workers or their 
employers, as the case may be; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  if, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, it is not desirable that he should continue 
to be a member.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Headquarters.—The 
headquarters of the Committee shall be at such place as may be fixed by the 
Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every matter referred to the Committee for advice shall be considered either at 
a meeting of the Committee, or if the Chairman so directs, by circulation of the 
necessary papers for opinion to every member who is present in India at the 
time:
 
Provided that any member 
may request that the matter be considered at a meeting of the Committee and 
thereupon the Chairman may, and if the request is made by three or more members 
shall, direct that it be so considered.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Committee shall 
meet at such places and the same may be appointed by the Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairman shall 
preside over every meeting of the Committee at which he is present and in his 
absence the members present shall elect one of them to preside over the meeting 
and member so elected shall at that meeting exercise all the powers of the 
Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No business shall be 
transacted at a meeting of the Committee unless at least seven members are 
present:
 
Provided that if at any 
meeting less than seven members are present, the Chairman may adjourn the 
meeting to a date not less than seven days later, informing the members present 
and giving notice to other members that he proposes to dispose of the business 
at the adjourned meeting whether there is the prescribed quorum or not, and it 
shall thereupon be lawful for him to dispose of the business at the adjourned 
meeting irrespective of the number of members attending.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every question at a 
meeting of the Committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of their 
members present voting:
 
Provided that a member 
shall in all cases have the right to have his note of dissent recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every question 
referred to the members for opinion under sub-rule (1) shall, unless the 
Chairman in pursuance of the proviso to that sub-rule reserves it for 
consideration at a meeting, be decided in accordance with the opinion of the 
majority of the members recording opinion within the time allowed for it. 

1[The decision 
taken shall be communicated to the members of the Committee and reported at the 
next meeting of the Committee.]
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In the case of an 
equal division of votes or opinions, as the case may be, the Chairman shall have 
a second or casting vote or opinion.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Notice of meetings 
and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notice shall be given to every member present in India of the time and place 
fixed for each meeting at least fifteen days before the date of such meeting and 
each member shall be furnished with a list of business to be disposed of at the 
meeting:
 
Provided that when an 
emergent meeting is called by the Chairman, it shall not be necessary to give 
more than five days’ notice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No business which is 
not on the list of business shall be considered at a meeting without the 
permission of the Chairman.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Minutes of 
meetings.—The 
minutes of each meeting of the Committee shall be circulated to all members 
present in India as soon as possible after the meeting, shall be read out and 
confirmed at the next meeting of the Committee, shall be signed by the Chairman 
or the member presiding, as the case may be, and shall thereafter be recorded in 
a minute book.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Power to invite 
experts to meetings.—The 
Chairman may invite one or more experts to be present at any meeting and to 
participate in the discussion of any technical matter, but such experts shall 
not be entitled to vote.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Allowances of 
Members.—Every 
non-official member and any expert invited to attend a meeting of the Committee 
under rule 11, shall be entitled to travelling allowance and daily allowance at 
such rates and subject to such terms and conditions as may be specified by the 
Central Government from time to time for payment to non-official delegates 
attending meetings of the conferences and committees convened by that 
Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> The Chairman shall be the Controlling 
Officer in respect of the bills for the allowances admissible under rule 12.
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>