<act><title>
THE
MUSSALMAN WAKF ACT, 1923</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short tittle extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Mussalman Wakf Act, 1923. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in
Part B States].]
 </section><section><number>3</number>
This section shall come into force at once; and
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[State Government]
may, by notification in the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Official
Gazette], direct that the remaining provisions of this Act, or any of them which
it may specify, shall come into force in the 5[State],
or any specified part thereof, on such date as it may appoint in this behalf.
  












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless
there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
“benefit” does not include any benefit which a mutwalli is entitled
to claim solely by reason of his being such mutwalli;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Court” means the Court of the District Judge or, within the limits
of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of a High Court, such Court,
subordinate to the High Court, as the 1[State
Government] may, by notification in the 2[Official
Gazette], designate in this behalf;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“mutwalli” means any person appointed either verbally or under any
deed or instrument by which a wakf has been created or by a Court of competent
jurisdiction to be the mutwalli of a wakf, and includes a naib-mutwalli or other
person appointed by a mutwalli to perform the duties of the mutwalli, and, save
as otherwise provided in this Act, any person who is for the time being
administrating any wakf property;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and 
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“wakf” means the permanent dedication by a person professing the
Mussalman faith of any property for any purpose recognised by the Mussalman law
as religious, pious or charitable, but does not include any wakf, such as is
described in section 3 of the Mussalman Wakf Validating Act, 1913, under which
any benefit is for the time being claimable for himself by the person by whom
the wakf was created or by any of his family or descendants. 
  
 

 State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its application to Bombay
area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,— 
 <subsection>

<number>1</number>
in section 2— 
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>
after clause (b), insert the following clause, namely:— 
 

“(bb)
“Distirct” means a district constituted under section 3 of the Bombay
Civil Courts Act, 1869, and includes the Greater Bombay.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
after clause (e), insert the following clause namely:— 
 

“(ee)
“Wakf Committee” means a committee constituted under section 6L.” 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>2</number>
after section 2 insert the heading “Part II”. 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, secs. 3 and 4 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935) and 17 of 1945,
sec. 9 Sch. E, Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).] 
 

 
  









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Obligation to furnish particulars relating to wakf.—
<section><number>1</number> Within six months
from the commencement of this Act every mutwalli shall furnish to the Court
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the property of the wakf of which
he is the mutwalli is situated or to any one of two or more such Courts, a
statement containing the following particulars, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>
a description of the wakf property sufficient for the identification
thereof;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the gross annual income from such property;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the gross amount of such income which has been collected during the five
years preceding the date on which the statement is furnished, or of the period
which has elapsed since the creation of the wakf, whichever period is shorter;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
the amount of the Government revenue and cesses, and of all rents,
annually payable in respect of the wakf property;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
an estimate of the expenses annually incurred in the realisation of the
income of the wakf property, based on such details as are available of any such
expenses incurred within the period to which the particulars under clause (c)
relate;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the amount set apart under the wakf for—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>
the salary of the mutwalli and allowances to individuals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>
purely religious purposes;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>
charitable purposes;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>
any other purposes; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
any other particulars which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Every such statement shall be accompanied by a copy of the deed or instrument
creating the wakf or, if no such deed or instrument has been executed or a copy
thereof cannot be obtained shall contain full particulars, as far as they are
known to the mutwalli, of the origin, nature and objects of the wakf.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
a wakf is created after the commencement of this Act, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
in the case of a wakf such as is described in section 3 of the Wakf
Validating Act, 1913, the person creating the wakf or any member of his family
or any of his descendants is at the commencement of this Act alive and entitled
to claim any benefit thereunder,
 the
statement referred to in sub-section (1) shall be furnished, in the case
referred to in clause (a), within six months of the date on which the wakf is
created or, if it has been created by a written document, of the date on which
such document is executed, or, in the case referred to in clause (b), within six
months of the date of the death of the person entitled to such benefit as
aforesaid, or of the last survivor of any such persons, as the case may be.
  
 
State
Amendment
 Uttar
Pradesh.—Omit section 3. 
 [Vide
Uttar Pradesh Act 13 of 1936, sec. 70 (w.e.f. 1-7-1941).] 
   

 



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>4</number>
Publication of particulars and requisition of further particulars.—
<section><number>1</number>
When any statement has been furnished under section 3 the Court shall cause
notice of the furnishing thereof to be affixed in some conspicuous place in the
Court-house and to be published in such other manner, if any, as may be
prescribed, and thereafter any person may apply to the Court by a petition in
writing, accompanied by the prescribed fee, for the issue of an order requiring
the mutwalli to furnish further particulars or documents. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
On such application being made, the Court may, after making such inquiry, if
any, as it thinks fit, if it is of opinion that any further particulars or
documents are necessary in order that full information may be obtained regarding
the origin, nature or objects of the wakf or the condition or management of the
wakf property, cause to be served on the mutwalli an order requiring him to
furnish such particulars or documents within such time as the Court may direct
in the order.
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Uttar
Pradesh.—Omit section 4.
 
[Vide
Uttar Pradesh Act, 13 of 1936, sec. 70 (w.e.f. 1-7-1941).]
   


   

 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>5</number>
Statement of accounts.—Within three months after the thirty-first day of
March next following the date on which the statement referred to in section 3
has been furnished and thereafter within three months of the thirty-first day of
March in every year, every mutwalli shall prepare and furnish to the Court to
which such statement was furnished a full and true statement of accounts, in
such form and containing such particulars as may be prescribed, of all moneys
received or expended by him on behalf of the wakf of which he is the mutwalli
during the period of twelve months ending on such thirty-first day of March or,
as the case may be, during that portion of the said period during which the
provisions of this Act have been applicable to the wakf: 
  Provided
that the Court may, if it is satisfied that there is sufficient cause for so
doing, extend the time allowed for the furnishing of any statement of accounts
under this section.
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>6</number>
Audit of account.—Every statement of
accounts shall, before it is furnished to the Court under section 5, be
audited—
 <section><number>a</number>
in the case of a wakf the gross income of which during the year in
question, after deduction of the land-revenue and cesses, if any, payable to the
Government exceeds two thousand rupees, by a person who is the holder of a
certificate granted by the <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[Central
Government] under section 144 of the Indian Companies Act, 1913, or is a member
of any institution or association the members of which have been declared under
that section to be entitled to act as auditors of companies throughout the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[territories
to which this Act applies]; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
in the case of any other wakf, by any person authorised in this behalf by
general or special order of the said Court.
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its appliction to Bombay
area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,— 
 <subsection>

<number>1</number>
after section 6, insert the following parts, namely:— 
 
“Part
III 
 

Powers
of the Court to Call for Particulars 
and Statement of Accounts 
 </subsection></section></article><article>

<number>6A</number> Power of Court to
call upon the mutwalli to submit statement.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything
contained in section 3, it shall be competent to the Court on failure of a
mutwalli to furnish a statement as required under the said section to require
the mutwalli to furnish, within such time as the Court shall fix, a statement
containing all or any of the particulars referred to in the said section,
including a copy of the deed or instrument, if any, creating the wakf.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The provision of section
4 shall apply to a statement furnished under this section as if such statement
had been furnished under section 3.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6B</number> Power of Court to require
statement of accounts at any time.—
<section><number>1</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 5, it shall be competent to the
Court, on failure of a mutwalli to furnish a statement of accounts as required
under the said section, to require the mutwalli to prepare and furnish, within
such time as the Court may fix, a
statement of accounts of the nature described in the said section and for such
period as the Court may think fit.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The provisions of section
6 shall apply to any statement of accounts required to be furnished under this
section as if such statement of accounts were a statement of accounts furnished
under section 5. 
 
Part
IV
 

Powers
of the Court to Enquire 
 </section></article><article>

<number>6C</number> Power of Court to
Enquire.—
<section><number>1</number> The Court may, either on its own motion or upon the
application of any person claiming to have an interest in a wakf, hold an
inquiry in the prescribed manner at any time to ascertain—

 <subsection>

<number>i</number>
 whether a wakf exists;

 <subsubsection>

<number>ia</number>
 whether such wakf is a wakf to which this Act applies;

 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>
whether any property is the property of such wakf and whether the whole
or any substantial portion of the subject-matter of such wakf is situate within
the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court; and

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>
who is the mutwalli of such wakf.

 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> If it comes to the
knowledge of the Court that a suit
has been instituted in any Civil Court in regard to any of the matters mentioned
in sub-section (1), it shall stay the inquiry so far as it relates to, or is
likely to be affected by, the Court’s findings or order in regard to such matters, until
the suit is finally decided in that Court.

 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The Court shall from time
to time ascertain whether such suit has been finally decided and after the final
decision of the suit, it shall proceed with the enquiry in regard to such
matters, if any, as may not have been decided in such suit.

 </section><section>

<number>4</number> On completion of the
enquiry provided for in sub-sections (1) and (3) the Court
shall record its findings as to the matters mentioned in the said sub-sections,
except such matters as may have been decided in the aforesaid suit.

 </section><section>

<number>5</number> Save as provided in this
section, the Court shall not, when acting under this section, try or determine
any question of the title of any person claiming adversely to the wakf.

 
Part
V
 

Registration
of Wakfs, Wakf Accounts and Wakf Administration Funds 
 </section></article><article>

<number>6D</number> Registration of
Wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> The Court shall, after the submission of a statement under
section 3 or section 4 or section 6A and an enquiry, if necessary, held under
section 6C, or merely after an enquiry held under section 6C, record, in such
forms as may be prescribed in a register called the Register of Wakfs, the
following particulars:—

 <subsection>

<number>a</number>
a description of the wakf property sufficient for the identification
thereof;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>
the gross annual income from such property;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>
the gross amount of such income which has been collected during the five
years preceding the date on which the statement is furnished, or during the
period which has elasped since the creation of the wakf, whichever period is
shorter;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>
the amount of the Government revenue and cesses and of all rents annually
payable in respect of the wakf property;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>
an estimate of the expenses annually incurred in the realisation of the
income, of the wakf property, based on such details as are available of any such
expenses incureed within the period to which the particulars under clause (c)
relate;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>
the amount set apart under the wakf for—

 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>
the salary of the mutwalli and allowances to individuals.

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
purely religous purposes;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iii</number>
charitable purposes;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iv</number>
any other purposes;

 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>g</number>
the name of the mutwalli; and

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>h</number>
such other particulars as may be prescribed.

 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Statements, if any,
furnished under sections 3, 4 and 6A shall be filed with the Register of Wakfs.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6E</number> Amendment of
entries in Register of Wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> When any change occurs in any of the
particulars recorded in the Register of Wakfs, the mutwalli shall, within three
months of the occurrence of succh change, report to the Court such, change in
the prescribed form, accompanied by the prescribed fee. The provisions of
sections 3 and 4 shall, so far as may be, apply to any such statement.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> For the purpose of
verifying the correctness of the entries in the Register of Wakfs or
ascertaining any change which may have occurred in such register, the Court may
hold an enquiry in the prescribed manner. The provisions of section 6C shall, so
far as may be, apply to any such inquiry.

 </section><section>

<number>3</number> If the Court, after
receiving a report under sub-section (1) and holding an enquiry, if necessary,
under sub-section (2), or merely after an enquiry held under sub-section (2), is
satisfied that a change has occurred in any of the particulars recorded in the
Register of Wakfs with regard to wakf, it shall amend in the prescribed manner
the entry or entries affected by such change and shall file the report furnished
under sub-section (1) along with the statement, if any, relating to the said
wakf filed under section 3.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6F</number> Entries in the
Register of Wakfs and findings recorded under section 6C to be final subject to
section 6G.—The entries made by the Court in the Register of Wakfs and the
findings recorded under section 6C shall, subject to the provision of section
6G, be final for the purposes of this Act.

 </article><article>

<number>6G</number> Making or
amendment of entries in Register of Wakfs by order of Court.—A Civil Court
of competent jurisdiction deciding any question relating to any wakf may direct
that the Court shall make such entries or amendments of entries in the Register
of Wakfs relating to the said wakf as are consequential upon its decision, and
the Court shall make such entries or amendments of such entries accordingly.

 </article><article>

<number>6H</number> Maintenance of
account and their audit.—
<section><number>1</number> Every mutwalli of a wakf in respect of which
an entry has been recorded in the Register of Wakfs shall keep regular accounts
of all movable and immovable property received, and of all payments and
alienations made and incumbrances created by him on behalf of the wakf of which
he is the mutwall. such accounts
shall be kept in such form and shall contain such particulars as amy be
prescribed.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The account shall be
balanced on the thirty-first day of March in each year and shall be examined and
audited annually or at such other intervals, and in such manner as may be
prescribed and by the persons referred to in section 6.

 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Every auditor acting
under sub-section (2) shall have access to the accounts and to all books,
vouchers and other documents and records in the possession and under the control
of the mutwalli:

 

Provided that, if it is proved to the satisfaction of the Court that the
gross annual income of any particular wakf is less than two hundred rupees, the
Court may by order in writing exempt such wakf from the provisions of this
section.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6-I</number> Annual
contribution from wakfs.—Every wakf shall, for the purpose of meeting the
charges and expenses incidental to the registration, superintendence,
administration and control of wakfs, the maintenance of the Registers of wakfs,
the scrutiny and audit of accounts of wakfs, the institution and defence of
suits and proceedings relating to wakfs, and generally carrying into effect the
purposes of this Act, be liable to pay to the Wakf Administration Fund of the
district concerned annually such contribution, on such date and in such manner
as may be prescribed:

 

Provided that the (Provincial Government) may, by rules made in this
behalf, exempt from the provisions of this section any particular wakf or class
of wakfs.

 </article><article>

<number>6J</number> Wakf
Administration Fund.—For each distirct there shall be created a fund to be
called the Wakf Administration Fund of the district concerned, and there shall
be placed to the credit thereof the following sums, namely:—

 <section>

<number>a</number>
any fee which may be levied under this Act;

 </section><section>

<number>b</number>
contributions under section 6-I;

 </section><section>

<number>c</number> any sums received by the Wakf Administration Fund from private sources; 
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>
any sums alloted by (any Government) or by any local authority to the
Wakf Administration Fund. 
 </section></article><article>

<number>6K</number> Application of
Wakf Administration Fund.—The Wakf Administration Fund of a district shall
be under the control and management of the Court and shall be applicable to the
payment of charges for and expenses incidental to the registration,
superintendence, administration and control of wakfs, the maintenance of the
Register of Wakfs, the scrutiny and audit of accounts of wakfs, the institution
and defence of suits and proceedings relating to wakfs, and generally carrying
into effect the purposes of this Act.

 
Part
VI
 
Supervision
and Control
 </article><article>

<number>6L</number> Constitution and
appointment of Wakf Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be constituted in each
district a Wakf Committee to advise and assist the Court in all matters relating
to the registration, superintendence, administration and control of wakfs.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Committee shall
consist of:—

 <subsection>

<number>a</number>
the members of the Indian and State Legislatures.

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>
two members elected in the prescribed manner by the mutwallis of all
wakfs in the district registered under the Act,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>
two members elected in the prescribed manner by the members of each
District Local Board in the district professing the Mussalman faith from among
their number,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>
one member elected in the prescribed manner by the members professing
Mussalman faith of each municipality in the district constituted under the
Bombay District Municipal Act, 1991, 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>
two members elected in the prescribed manner by the members professing
Mussalman faith of each municipality in the district constituted under the City
of Bombay Municipal Act, 1888, the City of Karachi Municpal Act, 1933, or the
Bombay Municipal Buroughs Act, 1925, and 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>
such other members not exceeding one-fourth of the total number of the
members of the Committee as the State Government may nominate: 
 

Provided that no person who does not ordinarily reside in the district or
does not profess the Mussalman faith shall be eligible to be a member of the
Committee.

 </subsection></section></article><article>

<number>6M</number> Functions of Wakf
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be competent to the Court to refer at any time to
the Wakf Committee or any three or more members thereof, for advice, opinion,
enquiry report or recommendation, within such time as the Court may direct, any
matter relating to the registration, superintendence, administration, and
control of wakfs, and in particular any matter relating to—

 <subsection>

<number>a</number>
the conduct of a mutwalli or a trustee in the administration of a wakf or
his fitness to continue as a mutwalli or a trustee. 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>
the settlement, cancellation or alteration of a scheme for the
administration of a wakf, or 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>
the application of the funds of a wakf or any surplus thereof. 
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> When the Court has
referred any of the matters mentioned in sub-section (1) to a wakf
committee or any members thereof for advice, opinion, enquiry
report or recommendation, and the committee
or the members thereof, as the case may be, have, either unanimously or by a
majority, made their recommendation in relation to the matter referred to them,
the Court may pass orders as it thinks fit after giving due consideration to
such recommendation—

 <subsection>

<number>i</number>
suspending, removing or dismissing a mutwalli or trustee;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>
appointing a new mutwalli or trustee; t
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>
settling, cancelling or altering a scheme for the administration of wakf;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>
directing the application, investment or deposit of the funds of a wakf
for any surplus thereof in a particular manner or to a particular purpose; 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>v</number>
generally for carrying out the purposes of the Act: 
 

Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorise the
Court to pass any order which is inconsistent with the objects and purposes of
the wakf: 

 

Provided further that no order under this section shall be passed to the
prejudice of any mutwalli or trustee without giving such mutwalli or trustee an
opportunity to be heard.

 </subsection></section><section>

<number>3</number> For the performance of
any of the duties under sub-section (2) the Wakf Committee or any members
thereof to whom the Court has referred any matter for advice, opinion, enquiry,
report, or recommendation, the committee
or such members thereof may by order in writing require—

 <subsection>

<number>a</number>
the production of any document necessary for the purpose;

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>
the attendance of any person for the purpose of giving evidence or for
the production of any document referred to in clause (a).

 </subsection></section><section>

<number>4</number> The provisions of
sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 6C shall, so far as may be, apply to any
inquiry under sub-section (1) or (2).

 </section></article><article>

<number>6N</number> Court’s power to
authorise members of Wakf Committee to institute suits, etc.—Notwithstanding
anything contained in section 92 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, it shall
be competent to the Court, after such inquiry as it may think fit, 
<section><number>a</number> to
authorise any one or more of the members of a Wakf Committee to institute or
defend any suit or preceding for the purposes of the protection or recovery of
the property of a wakf or for the application of the property of a wakf to any
public, charitable or religious purpose and (b) to allocate from the Wakf
Administration Fund such sums as may, in the opinion of the Court, be necessary
for the aforesaid purpose.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6-O</number> Inspection of
wakf property, records and accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be competent to the
Court to direct one or more members of the Wakf Committee to undertake the
inspection, in the prescribed manner, of the property, records and accounts of
any wakf and to report to the Court, within such time as the Court may direct,
the result of such inspection.

 </section><section>

<number>2</number> It shall be competent to
the Court to employ upon such terms and conditions as may be prescribed such
persons as may in the opinion of the Court be necessary for carrying out the
purposes of this Act and to pay them such remuneration from the Wakf
Administration Fund as may be prescribed.

 </section></article><article>

<number>6P</number> Court’s power to
order special audit.—It shall be competent to the Court at any time to
order a special audit of the accounts of a wakf by an accountant possessing the
prescribed qualifications and to order the cost of such audit to be paid by the
mutwalli from the income of property of the wakf or out of the Wakf
Administration Fund.

 </article><article>

<number>6Q</number> Publication of
lists of wakfs.—There shall be published annually on such date as the
State Government may determine in the (Official Gazette) and if the State
Government so directs in the principle vernacular of the district in a newspaper
circulating therein a list of wakf and a statement of the sums standing to the
credit of the Wakf Administration Fund under the signature of the Court and in
such form as the State Government may prescribe.

 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935) as amended by Bombay Acts
10 of 1944 and 15 of 1945, Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 5-5-1960)].

 <section>

<number>2</number> after section 6Q inserted
by Bombay Act 18 of 1935 insert the heading “Part VII”. 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).] 
 
  











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>7</number>
Mutwalli entitled to pay cost of audit, etc., from wakf funds.—Notwithstanding
anything contained in the deed or instrument
creating any wakf, every Mutwalli may pay from the income of the wakf
property any expenses properly incurred by him for the purpose  of
enabling him to furnish any particulars, documents or copies under section 3 or
section 4 or in respect of the preparation or audit of the annual accounts for
the purposes of this Act. 
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,
in section 7 after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and
figures “section 6A or section 6B or section 6C or section 6E”.
 
[Vide
Bomabay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]
 
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>8</number>
Verification.—Every statement of
particulars furnished under section 3 or section
4, and every statement of accounts furnished under section 5, shall be written
in the language of the Court to which it is furnished, and shall be verified in
the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the
signing and verification of pleadings. 
  
 
 State
Amendments
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashra/Gujarat,
in section 8,— 
 <section>

<number>a</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 4’ insert the words and figures
“or section 6A or secion 6C or section 6E”; and 
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 5’ insert the words and figures
“or section 6B or section 6C”. 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]

 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—In
section 8, after the word “written”, insert the words “in Urdu or”.

 
[Vide
Bihar and Orissa Act 1 of 1926, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-5-1926).]
 
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>9</number>
Inspection and copies.—Any person
shall, with the permission of the Court and on payment of the prescribed fee, at
any time at which the Court is open, be entitled to inspect in the prescribed
manner, or to obtain a copy of, any statement of particulars or any document
furnished to the Court under section 3 or section 4, or any statement of
accounts furnished to it under section 5, or any audit report made on an audit
under section 6. 
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its application to Bombay
area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,— 
 <section>

<number>i</number>
in section 9,—

 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and figures
“or section 6A or section 6C or section 6E”; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 5’, insert the words and figures
“or section 6B or section 6C”; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 6’, insert the words and figures
“or section 6H or section 6P or any entry in the Register of Wakfs or any
statement, notice, intimation, report, accounts or any document filed under this
Act”. 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).] 
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>ii</number>
after section 9, insert the following section,
namely:— 
 

“9A. Provisions of Code
of Civil Procedure to apply.—(1) The Provisions of the Code of Civil
Procedure, 1908, relating to—

 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the proof of facts by affidavits;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the enforcing of the attendance of any person and his examination on
oath;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the enforcing of the profuction of documents; and

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
the issuing of commissions.

 
shall
apply to all proceedings held by the Court under this Act and provisions
relating to the service of summons shall apply to the service of notices
thereunder.

 <subsubsection>
    <number>2</number>
The provisions of the said Code relating to the execution of decrees shall, so
far as they are applicable, apply to the execution of orders passed by the Court
under this Act.

 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]

 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>

<number>iii</number>
after section 9A inserted by Bombay Act 18 of 1935, insert the heading
“Part III”.

 

[Vide Act 11 of
1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).]
   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>10</number>
Penalties.—Any person who is required
by or under section 3 or section 4 to furnish a statement of particulars or any
document relating to a wakf, or who is required by section 5 to furnish a
statement of accounts, shall, if he, without reasonable cause the burden of
proving which shall be upon him fails to furnish such statement or document, as
the case may be, in due time, or furnishes a statement which he knows or has
reason to believe to be false, misleading or untrue in any material particular,
or, in the case of a statement of accounts furnishes a statement which has not
been audited in the manner required by section 6, be punishable with fine which
may extend to five hundred rupees, or, in the case of a second or subsequent
offence, with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees. 
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In its application to Bombay
area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,— 
 <section>

<number>i</number>
in section 10,—

 <subsection>
 <number>a</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and figures
“or section 6A or section 6C or section 6E”;

 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>b</number>
after the word and figure ‘section 5’, insert the words and figures
“or section 6B or section 6C”;

 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>c</number>
after the word ‘accounts’ where it occurs for the the first time
insert, the words, figure and letter “or who is required by section 6H to keep
regular accounts”;

 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>d</number>
after the word “document” where it occurs for the second time, insert
the words “or to keep regular accounts”;

 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>e</number>
after the word ‘statement’ where it occurs for the fourth time,
insert the words “or keeps accounts”.

 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>ii</number>
after section 10, insert the following sections, namely:— 
 

“10A. Penalty for
non-compliance with any other order.—(1) if any person fails to comply
with any order passed by the Court or by the Wakf Committee or any member
thereof under or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act, such person shall,
if such failure to comply is not punishable under any of the sections of this
Act, be, on conviction, punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand
rupees. 
 <subsection>

<number>2</number> A Criminal Court may, in
passing an order of conviction, for an offence under sub-section (1), specify
the period within which the person convicted shall comply with the provisions of
this Act which may be found to have been contravened by him, and may also
prescribe a daily fine not exceeding Rs. 50 for every day for the period during
which the default continues after the expiry of the period so specified: 
 

Provided that, if the person failing to comply with any direction issued
by such Court satisfies such Court that there is good reason for his failure to
do so and applies for an extension of the period specified under this section,
such Court may, if it thinks fit, extend the period and may remit the whole or
any part of the fine paid or due. 
 </subsection></section></article><article>
 
<number>10B</number> Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No prosecution under this Act
shall be instituted except by or with the previous sanction of the Court given
in the prescribed manner. 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> No Criminal Court
inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or of a Magistrate of the First
Class shall try an offence under this Act. 
 </section></article><article>

<number>10C</number> Prosecution of, and
suits against, persons acting in good faith.—No suit or prosecution or
other proceeding shall be instituted against any person for anything which is in
good faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 
 </article><article>

<number>10D</number> Recovery of sums due
under this Act.—All sums due under this Act shall be recoverable as
arrears of land revenue.” 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]   

  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>11</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[State
Government] may, after previous publication, by notification in the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Official
Gazette], make rules to carry into effect the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the additional particulars to be furnished by mutwallis
under clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the fees to be charged upon applications made to a Court
under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the form in which the statement of accounts referred to
in section 5 shall be furnished, and the particulars which shall be contained
therein;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the powers which may be exercised by auditors for the
purposes of any audit referred to in section 6, and the particulars to be
contained in the reports of such auditors;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the fees respectively chargeable on account of the
allowing of inspections and of the supply of copies under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the safe custody of statements, audit reports and copies
of deeds or instruments furnished to Courts under this Act; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Every rule made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as
may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.] 
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Maharashtra:
Gujarat.—In section 11,— 
 </section><section>
   <number>1</number>
in sub-section (2),—

 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
in clause (a), after the word and figure “section 3”, insert the
words and figures “or under section 6A or section 6C”;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
for clause (b), substitute the following clause, namely:— 
 
“(b)
the manner in which notice to be published under section 4 and the fees
to be charged upon application made to the Court under sub-section (1) of
section 4 or under section 6A or section 6B or section 6C;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
in clause (c), after the word and figure “section 5”, insert the
words and figures “or section 6B or section 6C”;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
in clause (d), after the word and figure “section 6”, insert the
words and figures “or section 6H or section 6P”;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
in clause (e), after the brackets and letter “(e)”, insert the words
“the manner of inspection and”;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
after clause (f), insert the following clauses, namely:—

 
“(f1)
the manner in which subject to the provisions of section 9A an inquiry
shall be held by the Court and the Wakf Committee under section 6C or 6M and the
manner in which the parties shall be represented in such inquiry and the costs
of such inquiry shall be borne;

 <subsubsection>
<number>f2</number>
the manner in which the Register of Wakfs shall be prepared and
maintained under section 6D;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f3</number>
the form in which a change in any of the particulars recorded in the
Register of Wakfs shall be reported and
the amount of fee to accompany such report and the manner in which the inquiry
shall be held and the entries in the Register of Wakfs shall be amended under
section 6E;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f4</number>
the form in which the accounts shall be prepared, kept and furnished, the
particulars to be entered therein, and the manner in which, and interval at
which such accounts shall be audited under section 6H;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f5</number>
the amount of contribution, and the date on which and the manner in which
it shall be paid and exemptions granted under section 6-I;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f6</number>
the appointment and remuneration of auditors appointed under the Act;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f7</number>
the management, custody, investment and disbursement of the Wakf
Administration Fund;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f8</number>
the purpose for which a Wakf Administration Fund shall be applied under
section 6K;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f9</number>
the number of members who shall constitute a Wakf Committee, the period
of office of a Wakf Committee and the manner in which such committee shall hold
its meetings and the procedure to be followed at their meetings;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f10</number>
the manner in which the inspection of the property, records and accounts
of a wakf shall be carried out, the sum which shall be paid in respect of the
costs of the members of the Wakf Committee undertaking such insepction, the
terms and conditions on which persons shall be employed and the remuneration
which shall be paid to such persons, under secion 6-O;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f11</number>
the qualifications of an accountant appointed under section 6P;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f12</number>
the form in which a list of Wakfs shall be published under section 6Q.”


 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
    <number>2</number> after sub-section (2), insert the following sub-section, namely:— 
 



“(3) Rules made under this
section shall be laid before each of the Chambers of the State Legislature at
the session thereof next following and shall be liable to be modified or
rescinded by a resolution in which both the Chambers concur and such rule shall
after notification in the Official Gazette be deemed to have been modified or
rescinded accordingly: 
 

Provided that when in the option of the State Government such
modification or rescission is likely to defeat or frustrate any of the purposes
of this Act, the State Government may by notification, in the Official Gazette,
declare that the modification or rescission shall have no effect and thereupon
the rules shall remain in force as if they had not been modified or
rescinded.” 
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f.
1-5-1960).]
 
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article>  

<number>12</number> Saving.—Nothing
in this Act shall— 
 <section> <number>a</number>
affect any other enactment for the time being in force in the 1[territories
to which this Act applies] providing for the control or supervision of religious
or charitable endowments; or
 </section><section> <number>b</number>
apply in the case of any wakf the property of which—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
is being administered by the Treasurer of Charitable Endowments, the
Administrator General, or the Official Trustee; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
is being administered either by a receiver appointed by any Court of
competent jurisdiction, or under a scheme for the administration of the wakf
which has been settled or approved by any Court of competent jurisdiction or by
any other authority acting under the provisions of any enactment.
   







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>13</number>
Exemption.—The <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[State
Government] may, by notification in the 2[Official
Gazette], exempt from the operation of this Act or of any specified
provision thereof any wakf or wakfs created or administered for the benefit of
any specified section of the Mussalman community.
  






 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for sub-section (2).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by the A.O. (No. 3) 1956, for “Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General in Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Ins. by Act 4 of 2005, sec. 2 and Schedule.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by the
A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of India”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>