<act><tid>1483180</tid>
<title>THE MARKING OF HEAVY PACKAGES ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 39 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 25th June, <year>1951</year>.] BE

An Act to give effect to the International Convention drawn up in 
Geneva on the 30th day of May, <year>1929</year>, for the marking of weight on 
heavy packages transported by sea or inland waterways.





<article><tid>1669223</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1097931</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Marking of Heavy Packages Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>178410</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1162416</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>570367</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1143251</tid>
<number>a</number>" heavy package" means a package or other object weighing 
not less than one metric ton, which is equal to one 
thousand kilogrammes or 2204. 6 standard pounds or 26. 8 
standard maunds;

</section>

<section><tid>1654077</tid>
<number>b</number>" inland waterway" means any canal, river, lake or other 
navigable water in India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1166225</tid>
<number>3</number>Obligation to mark weight on heavy packages. Every person 
consigning a heavy package for transport by sea or inland water- way 
from any place in India shall have marked thereon plainly, durably and 
conspicuously the gross weight of the packages:
Provided that in cases or circumstances specified by rules made 
under this Act where it is difficult to determine the correct weight, 
only the approximate weight may be so marked.



</article>



<article><tid>1562542</tid>
<number> 4</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Inspectors.
<section><tid>1744080</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification  
in the Official Gazette, appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be 
inspectors for the purposes of this Act and assign to each of them one 
or more areas to be specified in the notification, or to two or more 
of them the same area to be so specified.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>384</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st November, <year>1951</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 1461, dated the 
15th September, <year>1951</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1951</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 
1608. 
2. Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2, for ss. 4 and 5.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 
of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1445500</tid>
<number>2</number>Every inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>555091</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of inspectors. Subject to any rules made by the Central 
Government in this behalf, an inspector appointed under sub- section

<section><tid>1477741</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4 may- 

<subsection><tid>683090</tid>
<number>a</number>enter, with such assistants as he considers necessary, 
and inspect any place or vessel and examine any 
packages found therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>974881</tid>
<number>b</number>if, on such examination, any heavy package is found not 
to have been marked in accordance with the provisions 
of section 3, direct that the package shall not be 
transported by sea or inland waterway until it has been 
marked in accordance with those provisions:
Provided that, instead of issuing any direction as aforesaid, the 
inspector may himself cause the package to be marked in accordance 
with the provisions of section 3; and in any such case, the expenses 
incurred by him for such marking shall be recoverable as an arrear of 
land revenue from the person consigning the package for transport.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>349669</tid>
<number> 6</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>436423</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person contravenes-- 

<subsection><tid>847494</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of section 3, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1129970</tid>
<number>b</number>any direction given by an inspector under clause (b) of 
section 5,
he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1157994</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person wilfully obstructs an inspector in the exercise 
of his powers under this Act, he shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to two hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>120070</tid>
<number> 7</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>703153</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the person committing an  
offence under this Act is a company, the company as well as every 
person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>384A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>279272</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or 
other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>858538</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1731414</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1002373</tid>
<number> 8</number> Cognizance of offences.
<section><tid>604691</tid>
<number>1</number>No court inferior to that of a  
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>894077</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act 
except on a complaint in writing made by an inspector within six 
months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have been 
committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>731331</tid>
<number>9</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1456903</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>715939</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules providing for--

<subsection><tid>1115731</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions as to the manner of marking of heavy 
packages, the manner of their packing and the type of 
covering to be used;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1108047</tid>
<number>b</number>the cases or circumstances in which the approximate 
weight of heavy packages instead of their correct 
weight may be marked;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>107575</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, provided 
for by rules.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>733336</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
follow-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>384B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

ing, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



 </act>