<act><tid>488279</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (SURCHARGE ON INCOME- TAX) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>1971</year>]

An Act to provide for the levy of a surcharge on income- tax 
payable in advance by companies during the financial year <year>1971</year>- 72 
under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1702456</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Companies (Surcharge on  
  Income- tax) Act, <year>1971</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1710379</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1525953</tid>
<number>a</number>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43  
  of <year>1961</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1305572</tid>
<number>b</number>all words and expressions used in this Act shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Income- tax 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>2973</tid>
<number> 3</number> Levy of surcharge on income- tax payable by companies during 
<year>1971</year>- 72.
<section><tid>1599994</tid>
<number>1</number>Every company which is liable to pay advance tax under  
section 210 or section 212 of the Income- tax Act during the financial 
year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1971</year>, shall, in addition to 
the advance tax so payable, pay to the credit of the Central Gov- 
ernment on or before the 15th day of March, <year>1972</year>, a further sum, by 
way of surcharge on income- tax, calculated at the rate of two and one- 
half per cent. of the amount specified in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>781937</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount referred to in sub- section (1) shall be-

<subsection><tid>766191</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where advance tax is required to be paid by 
an order under sub- section (1) or sub- section (3) of section 
 210 of the Income- tax Act, the amount specified in such 
order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1441432</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case where advance tax is payable under sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) or sub- 
section (3A) of section 212 of the Income- tax Act on the 
basis of the estimate furnished by the company, the amount of 
advance tax so payable.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>346266</tid>
<number>3</number>Any sum required to be paid by a company as surcharge on 
income- tax under sub- section (1) shall be paid without any notice of 
demand to the company in that behalf from the Income- tax Officer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1312</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>827728</tid>
<number> 4</number> Mode of recovery. If the sum required to be paid under sub- 
section
<section><tid>1173860</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 is not paid on or before the 15th day of  
March, <year>1972</year>, the company shall be deemed to be an assessee in default 
and-

<subsection><tid>1952668</tid>
<number>a</number>the company shall be liable to pay simple interest at 
nine per cent. per annum from the 16th day of March, <year>1972</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>940033</tid>
<number>b</number>all the provisions of sections 221 to 227, section 229, 
section 231 and section 232 of the Income- tax Act and the 
Second and Third Schedules to that Act and any rules made 
thereunder shall, so far as may be, apply as if the said 
provisions were the provisions of this Act and referred to 
surcharge on income- tax and sums imposed by way of penalty 
and interest under this Act instead of to income- tax and sums 
imposed by way of penalty and interest under that Act and as 
if references to subsection (2) of section 220 were 
references to clause (a) of this section.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>323449</tid>
<number>5</number>Credit for surcharge. Any sum paid by or recovered from a 
company as surcharge on income- tax in pursuance of this Act shall be 
treated as a payment of tax under the Income- tax Act in respect of the 
income of the period which would be the previous year for the 
assessment year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1972</year>, and credit 
therefor shall be given to the company for the purposes of assessment 
under section 140A, section 141A, section 143 or section 144 of the 
Income- tax Act.

</article>



 </act>