<act><title>


The Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 
    (Application of Fines) Rules, 19781</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These rules may be called 
    the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Application of Fines) Rules, 1978.  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    ‘Act’ means the Prevention of Cruelty 
    to Animals Act, 1960 (59 to 1960);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Board” means the Animal Welfare Board 
    of India established under the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    ‘fines’ means fines levied under the 
    Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Fines, 
    after deducting cost of collection, to be made over to Board.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Fines levied and realised under the Act shall, subject to any deductions 
    relating to the cost of collection, be made over by the State Government to 
    the Board as soon as may be after due appropriation by law (by State 
    Legislature) in this behalf.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Application of fines made over to Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Fines made over by any State Government to the Board shall be applied 
    exclusively for the following purposes, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the grant of financial assistance to 
    societies dealing with the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals or organisations 
    actively interested in animal welfare work which are for the time being 
    recognised by the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the maintenance of infirmaries, 
    pinjrapoles and veterinary hospitals.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Fines 
    realised in one State and made over to the Board shall be utilised only for 
    the benefit of such societies  or other organisations within the 
    jurisdiction of that State and not otherwise. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Principles to govern application of fines.—In 
    applying the fines for the benefit of societies or other organisations in 
    any State, the Board shall have due regard to the following principles, 
    namely:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    financial assistance shall first be 
    given to societies dealing with the prevention of cruelty to animal’s within 
    the jurisdiction of the State which are for the time being recognised by the 
    Board;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    in granting financial assistance to 
    such societies, due regard shall be had to the amounts they had been 
    receiving from the State Government prior to the coming into force of these 
    rules, and consistently with the amount of fines at its disposal and having 
    regard to the revenues of the Societies concerned, the objects for which 
    assistance is to be given and other relevant matters, the Board shall make 
    every endeavour to ensure that there is no diminution in the amounts such 
    societies had been receiving earlier;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    if after the grant of financial 
    assistance to the societies earlier referred to in this rule, there is any 
    unspent balance, it may be applied by the Board at its discretion for the 
    benefit of any other organisation actively interested in animal welfare work 
    including infirmaries, pinjrapoles and veterinary hospitals.  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>