<act><tid>1423933</tid>
<title>THE KALAKSHETRA FOUNDATION ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

ACT NO. 6 OF <year>1994</year>
[ 4th January, <year>1994</year>.]

An Act to declare Kal a kshett a of Madras to be an institution of 
national importance to provide for the establishment and incorporation 
of a Foundation for its administration, to make provisions for further 
development of Kalakshetra in accordance with the aims and objects for 
which Kalakshetra was founded and for matters connected therewith or 
incide tal. thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1567089</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>315499</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Kalakshetra Foundation Act, <year>1993</year>.-

</section>

<section><tid>71758</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day 
of September, <year>1993</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>624428</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of Kalakshetra as an institution of national 
importance.- Whereas the objects of the institution known as 
Kalakshetra at Adyar, Madras in the State of Tamil Nadu, founded by 
the late Thirumathi Rukmini Devi Atundale, are such as to make the 
Institution one of national importance, it is hereby declared that the 
institution known as Kalakshetra is an institution of national 
importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1529745</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>997373</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Committee" means the Academic Committee 
constituted under section 15;

</section>

<section><tid>1205585</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the date on which the Foundation 
is established under sub- section (1) of section 8;

</section>

<section><tid>1589632</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Trustees" means the Board of Trustees 
managing the affairs of Kalakshetra under the' scheme writ' 
approved by the Madras High Court in petition No. 716 of 
<year>1985</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>844325</tid>
<number>d</number>" constituent units" means the units of Kalakshetra 
specified in the First Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1030590</tid>
<number>e</number>" Director" means the Director appointed under sub- 
section (1) less of section 19,

</section>

<section><tid>1981668</tid>
<number>f</number>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee consti- 
tuted under sub- section (1) of section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>788968</tid>
<number>g</number>" Foundation" means the Kalakshetra Foundation 
established under sub- section (1) of section 8;

</section>

<section><tid>1349311</tid>
<number>h</number>" Fund" means the Fund of the Foundation referred to in 
section 22;

</section>

<section><tid>654442</tid>
<number>i</number>" Governing Board means the Governing Board constituted 
under section 11;

</section>

<section><tid>740824</tid>
<number>j</number>" Kalakshetra", means the institution known as, Kalakshetra 
founded by the late Thirumathi Rukmini Devi Arundale, situated 
at Adyar, Madras, and includes its constituent units;

</section>

<section><tid>618407</tid>
<number>k</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>585188</tid>
<number>l</number>" Member" means a Member of the Governing Board and in- 
cludes the Chairperson thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1718877</tid>
<number>m</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>268035</tid>
<number>n</number>" regulations" means regulations made under section 32;

</section>

<section><tid>757461</tid>
<number>o</number>" Schedule" means a Schedule annexed to this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1525252</tid>
<number>p</number>" State Government" means the Government of Tamil Nadu..

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE ASSETS AND PROPERTIES OF KALAKSHETRA

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE ASSETS AND PROPERTIES OF KALAKSHETRA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>665080</tid>
<number>4</number>Transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government of the 
assets and properties of Kalakshetra.- On the commencement of this Act 
the right, title, and interest in relation to the assets and 
properties of Kalakshetra specified in the Second Schedule and vested 
in the Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever capacity, 
shall Stand transferred to, and vest in, the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>449871</tid>
<number> 5</number> General effect of vesting.-
<section><tid>1369301</tid>
<number>1</number>The right, title and  
interest vested in the Central Government under section 4 shall be 
deemed to include all the assets, rights, leaseholds, powers, 
authorities, licences and privileges; all property (movable and  
  immovable) including lands and buildings; musical instruments; 
equipments used in teaching, training and staging of performing arts; 
tools and facilities used in arts and crafts; costumes and 
decorative items; books; stationery, furniture and other equipments 
used in libraries and laboratories; works of art and artefacts; 
stores, automobiles and other vehicles; workshops; cash balances, 
funds including reserve funds, investments and all other rights and 
interests arising out of such assets and properties as were 
immediately before the commencement of this Act in the possession 
ownership, power or control of the Board of Trustees or any other 
body, in whatever capacity, and all books of account, registers, maps, 
plans and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1294043</tid>
<number>2</number>All assets and properties as aforesaid which have vested in 
the Central Government under section 4 shall, by force of such 
vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, 
charge, lien and all other encumbrances affecting them or of any 
attachment, injunction, decree or order of any court or other 
authority restricting the use of such assets or properties in any 
manner, or appointing any receiver in respect of the whole or any part 
of such assets and properties shall be deemed to have been withdrawn.

</section>

<section><tid>1683563</tid>
<number>3</number>Any licence, permission, authority, concession, facility, 
privilege, affiliation or any other instrument of similar nature 
granted to the Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever 
capacity, in relation to the assets and properties of Kalakshetra or 
any of its constituent units which has vested in the Central 
Government under section 4, at any time before the commencement of 
this Act and in force immediately before such commencement, shall 
continue to be in force on and after such commencement in accordance 
with its tenor in relation to, and for purposes of, such assets and 
properties, or where the direction under section 6 has been issued, 
the Foundation shall be deemed to be substituted in such licence, 
permission, authority, concession, facility, privilege affiliation or 
other instrument, as if it had been granted to the Foundation and the 
Foundation shall hold it for the remainder of the period for which the 
Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever capacity, would have 
held it under the terms thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>575996</tid>
<number>4</number>If, on the commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal or 
other proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any assets or pro- 
perties which have vested in the Central Government under section 4, 
instituted or preferred by the Board of Trustees is, pending, the same 
shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially 
affected by reason of such transfer and vesting, or of anything 
contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted or enforced, by the Central Government or where 
the right, title and interest in relation to such assets and 
properties are directed under section 6 to vest in the Foundation, by 
the Foundation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>20282</tid>
<number> 6</number> Central Government to direct vesting of assets and 
properties in the Foundation.-
<section><tid>1100859</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained  
in sections 4 and 5, the Central Government shall direct, by 
notification, that the right, title and interest in relation to the 
assets and properties of Kalakshetra, which had vested in it under 
section 4, shall vest in the Foundation on such date, not being a date 
earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, as may be specified 
in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1278465</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the date of vesting of the right, title and 
interest in relation to the assets, and properties of Kalakshetra in 
the Foundation under sub- section (1)

<subsection><tid>1290180</tid>
<number>a</number>the Foundation shall be deemed to have become the owner 
of the assets and properties; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>118097</tid>
<number>b</number>the rights and liabilities of the Central Government, 
in relation to such assets and properties shall be deemed to 
have become the rights and liabilities respectively of the 
Foundation.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315732</tid>
<number> 7</number> Duty of persons to deliver and to account for assets, 
properties, etc.-
<section><tid>116795</tid>
<number>1</number>On the vesting in the Central Government of the  
assets and properties of Kalakshetra, all persons in charge of the 
management of the said assets and properties immediately before the 
date of such vesting, shall be bound to deliver to the Central 
Government or to the Foundation or to such person or body of persons 
as the Central Government or the Foundation may specify in this 
behalf, all assets, properties, books of account, registers or other, 
documents in their custody relating to the assets and properties of 
Kalakshetra.

</section>

<section><tid>1893184</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person who has, in his possession or control any 
assets, properties, books, documents or other papers relating to 
Kalakshetra which have vested in the Central Government or the 
Foundation under this Act, and which belong to, Kalakshetra or would 
have so belonged if Kalakshetra had not vested in the Central 
Government or the Foundation, shall be liable to account for the said 
assets, properties, books, documents and other papers to the 
Central Government or the Foundation, as the case may be, and 
shall deliver them up to the Central Government or the Foundation 
or to such person or body of persons as the Central Government or 
the Foundation may specify in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>126786</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall take or cause to be taken all 
necessary steps for securing possession of assets and properties of 
Kalakshetra which have vested in it under section 4.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

KALAKSHETRA FOUNDATION

CHAPTER III

KALAKSHETRA FOUNDATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1429505</tid>
<number> 8</number> Establishment and incorporation of foundation.-
<section><tid>520366</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, 
appoint in this behalf there shall be established a Foundation to be 
called the Kalakshetra Foundation.

</section>

<section><tid>1850298</tid>
<number>2</number>The Foundation shall be a body corporate by the name afore- 
said, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to ac- 
quire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and 
to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>793417</tid>
<number>3</number>The office of the Foundation shall be located at 
Thiruvanmiyur, Madras.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>113653</tid>
<number> 9</number> The object of foundation.- The objects of the Foundation shall 
be,-
<section><tid>1730288</tid>
<number>i</number>to emphasise the essential unity of all true arts;

</section>

<section><tid>1370016</tid>
<number>ii</number>to work for the recognition of the arts as vital to the 
individual, national and international growth;

</section>

<section><tid>153344</tid>
<number>iii</number>to maintain the highest traditions of art and culture 
in their pristine purity and in conformity with traditions;

</section>

<section><tid>1802647</tid>
<number>iv</number>to arrange for the training, research, study, teaching 
and development of art and science, music, dance- drama, fine 
arts, and Bharat- Natyam; and

</section>

<section><tid>1816322</tid>
<number>v</number>to ensure that the principles of" education without 
fear" and" art without vulgarity" are adhered to in the 
activities of the Foundation and not to permit any deviation 
from these high ideals.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>660434</tid>
<number> 10</number> Authorities of the Foundation.-
<section><tid>811251</tid>
<number>1</number>The Foundation shall  
consist of the following, authorities, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1412156</tid>
<number>a</number>the Governing Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1338227</tid>
<number>b</number>the Academic Committee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330752</tid>
<number>c</number>the Finance Committee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>405724</tid>
<number>2</number>In the discharge of functions and exercise of powers under 
this Act, the authorities referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
guided by the objects specified in section 9.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>67042</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Governing Board.- The Governing Board shall consist of-
<section><tid>1756947</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairperson, who shall be a person of high eminence in 
public life, to be appointed by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1751887</tid>
<number>b</number>not more than twelve Members to be nominated by the 
Central Government from amongst persons who-

<subsection><tid>1692776</tid>
<number>i</number>have rendered valuable service to Kalakshetra;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443606</tid>
<number>ii</number>have been connected with, or have knowledge of 
art, culture, folk arts and crafts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1586762</tid>
<number>iii</number>are eminent artistes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>366717</tid>
<number>iv</number>are patrons of art and culture;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1288606</tid>
<number>c</number>two persons, possessing one or more of the 
qualifications referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (ii) of 
clause (b), to be nominated by the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1330478</tid>
<number>d</number>two officers of the Central Government, not below the 
rank of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that 
Government, to represent the Ministry of the Central 
Government dealing with culture, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>1099384</tid>
<number>e</number>one officer of the State Government, not below the rank 
of Joint Secretary, to be nominated by that Government, to 
represent the Department of Education of that Government, ex- 
officio; and

</section>

<section><tid>1392423</tid>
<number>f</number>the Director, ex officio.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1077447</tid>
<number> 12</number> Terms of office of Members.-
<section><tid>1380853</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of the  
Members shall be five years from the date of constitution of the 
Governing Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1277774</tid>
<number>2</number>If a casual Vacancy occurs in the office of a Member 
nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) of section 11, whether by 
reason of his death, resignation or inability to discharge his func- 
tions owing to illness or other incapacity, such vacancy shall be 
filled by making fresh nomination and the Member so nominated shall 
hold office for the remainder of the term of office of the Member in 
whose place he is so nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>1711506</tid>
<number>3</number>An outgoing, Member shall be eligible for renomination,

</section>

<section><tid>255967</tid>
<number>4</number>A Member may resign his office by writing under his hand 
addressed to the Central Government but shall continue in office until 
his resignation is accepted by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>422667</tid>
<number>5</number>The Members nominated under clauses (b) and (c) of section 
11, shall be entitled to such allowances as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13082</tid>
<number> 13</number> Meetings of Governing Board.-
<section><tid>1389688</tid>
<number>1</number>The Governing Board shall  
meet, at least twice in a year at Madras at such time as may be fixed 
by the Chairperson of the Governing Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1444293</tid>
<number>2</number>All decisions at the meeting of the Governing Board shall be 
taken by majority of the Members present and voting:
Provided that in the case of equality of votes the Chairperson of 
the Governing Board shall have a casting vote.


</section>

<section><tid>1348559</tid>
<number>3</number>The Governing Board shall observe such procedure in regard 
to the transaction of its business at its meetings (including the  
  quorum at its meetings) as may be specified by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1979406</tid>
<number>4</number>No act or proceeding of the Governing Board shall be invalid 
merely by reason of-

<subsection><tid>325276</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the 
Governing Board; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>246771</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a 
Member of the Governing Board; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>376868</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Governing 
Board not affecting the merits of the case.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>416161</tid>
<number> 14</number> Governing Board to be the supreme authority of Foundation. 
-
<section><tid>1131863</tid>
<number>1</number>The Governing Board shall be the supreme authority of the  
Foundation and the general superintendence, direction and management 
of the affairs of the Foundation shall vest in the Governing Board.

</section>

<section><tid>839766</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governing Board shall exercise such powers and discharge 
such functions as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242474</tid>
<number> 15</number> Academic Committee.-
<section><tid>141211</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Committee shall  
consist of-

<subsection><tid>1510972</tid>
<number>a</number>the Director;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1083286</tid>
<number>b</number>the Heads of the constituent units;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682360</tid>
<number>c</number>three distinguished persons in the field of art and 
culture including dance, music, folk arts and crafts, to be 
culture including dance, music, folk arts and crafts, to be

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1267299</tid>
<number>d</number>one person to be nominated by the State Government, re- 
presenting the Department of Education of that Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1649764</tid>
<number>2</number>The tenure of office and other terms and conditions of the 
members of the Academic Committee shall be such as may be specified by 
regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>483792</tid>
<number>3</number>The Academic Committee shall observe such procedure in 
regard to the transaction of its business at its meetings (including  
  the quorum at the meetings) as may be specified by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>388340</tid>
<number>16</number>Powers and functions of Academic Committee.- The Academic 
Committee shall be responsible for the maintenance of standards of 
education, training and examination conducted by the constituent units 
and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other functions 
as may be assigned to it, from time to time, by the Governing Board.


</article>



<article><tid>228561</tid>
<number> 17</number> Finance Committee.-
<section><tid>1376982</tid>
<number>1</number>The Finance committee shall consist  
of-

<subsection><tid>175370</tid>
<number>a</number>the Financial Adviser to the Government of India or his 
nominee in the Ministry of the Central Government dealing 
with culture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1067976</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer of the Central Government, not below the 
rank of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>139729</tid>
<number>c</number>an officer of the State Government not below the rank 
of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that Government, 
representing the Department of Finance of that Government; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1266233</tid>
<number>d</number>the Director.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1665299</tid>
<number>2</number>The Finance committee shall observe such procedure in regard 
to the transaction of the business at its meetings as may be specified 
by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1104652</tid>
<number> 18</number> Powers and functions of Finance Committee.- The Finance 
Committee shall-
<section><tid>1193594</tid>
<number>i</number>scrutinise the annual statement of accounts and budget 
estimates of the Foundation prepared by the Director and make 
recommendations to the Governing Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1923806</tid>
<number>ii</number>prescribe the limits of the recurring and non- recurring 
expenditure of the Foundation for each financial year;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1272174</tid>
<number>iii</number>review the financial position of the Foundation from 
time to time and have an internal audit conducted; and

</section>

<section><tid>755456</tid>
<number>iv</number>perform such other functions as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>77592</tid>
<number> 19</number> Appointment and duties of Director.-
<section><tid>1372962</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, by notification, appoint a Direct- or who shall be 
the principal executive officer of the Foundation and who shall be 
responsible for the proper administration of the affairs of the 
Foundation and its day- to- day management and shall exercise such other 
powers and perform such other duties as may be assigned to him by the 
Governing Board.

</section>

<section><tid>32485</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director shall prepare the annual statement of accounts 
and budget estimates of the Foundation for scrutiny by the Finance 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>641236</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director shall be a whole time employee of the 
Foundation and shall be entitled to such salary and allowances out of 
the Fund and shall be subject to such conditions of service in respect 
of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters, as may be 
prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1817230</tid>
<number>20</number>Transfer of service of existing employees.- On and from the 
appointed day, every officer or other employee, employed immediately 
before the appointed day in connection with the affairs of 
Kalakshetra shall become an officer or other employee of the 
Foundation and shall hold office by the same tenure and remuneration 
and on the same terms and conditions as to pension, gratuity and other 
matters as he would have held under the Board of Trustees or any 
other body, in whatever, capacity, if this Act had not been passed and 
shall continue to do so, unless and until his employment in the 
Foundation is terminated or until his tenure, remuneration and other 
terms and conditions are duly altered by the Foundation:
Provided that the tenure, remuneration and other terms and condi- 
tions of service of any such officer or employee shall not be altered 
to his disadvantage without the previous approval of Central 
Government.

CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT



</article>



<article><tid>1830689</tid>
<number>21</number>Grants by Central Government to the Foundation.- For the 
purpose of enabling the Foundation to discharge its functions 
efficiently under this Act, the Central Government may, after due 
appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the 
Foundation in each financial year, such sums of money, on such terms 
and conditions as that Government may determine, by way of grant, loan 
or otherwise.


</article>



<article><tid>363485</tid>
<number> 22</number> Fund of the Foundation.-
<section><tid>1550031</tid>
<number>1</number>The Foundation shall have its  
own Fund; and all sums which may, from time to time, be paid to it by 
the Central Government and all receipts of the Foundation (including  
any sum to which the State Government or any other authority or person 
  may pay to the Foundation) shall be credited to the Fund and all 
payments by the Foundation shall be made therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>913094</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in, such 
banks or invested in such manner as may, subject to the approval of 
the Central Government, be decided by the Governing Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1609631</tid>
<number>3</number>The Foundation may spend such sums as it may think fit for 
performing its functions under this Act, and such sums shall be 
treated as expenditure payable out of the Fund of the Foundation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1419619</tid>
<number>23</number>Budget.- The Foundation shall prepare, in such form and at 
such time each year, as may be prescribed, the budget in respect of 
the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and 
expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1243000</tid>
<number> 24</number> Accounts and audit of the Foundation.-
<section><tid>221081</tid>
<number>1</number>The Foundation  
shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare 
an annual statement of accounts including the balance sheet in such 
form as may be approved by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India.

</section>

<section><tid>1200093</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Foundation shall be audited by the Comp- 
troller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by 
him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Foundation 
to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1748783</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Foundation shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts, 
and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and 
to inspect the office of the Foundation.

</section>

<section><tid>1945032</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Foundation as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General India or any person appointed by him 
in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1784482</tid>
<number> 25</number> Duty to furnish returns, annual reports, etc.-
<section><tid>842001</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Foundation shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in 
such form and in such manner, as may be prescribed, or as the Central 
Government may direct, such returns and statements and such 
particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme for the 
promotion and development of the objects of the Foundation, as the 
Central Government may, from time to time, direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1992231</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Foundation shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial 
year, submit to the Central Government an annual report in such form 
and before such date as may be prescribed, giving a true and full 
account of its activities and programmes during the previous year.

</section>

<section><tid>1193092</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be 
laid, as soon as may be, after it is received, before each House of 
Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1093698</tid>
<number>26</number>Prior approval of the Central Government for alienation of 
property.- The Foundation shall not, except with the previous approval 
of the Central Government, sell or otherwise dispose of any property 
vested in the Foundation.


</article>



<article><tid>334793</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power of Central Government to give directions to the 
Foundation.-
<section><tid>824613</tid>
<number>1</number>the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that  
it is necessary so to do in the public interest, issue, for reasons to 
be recorded and communicated to the Foundation, such directions as it 
thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1073191</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, 
such directions may include directions requiring the Foundation-

<subsection><tid>446890</tid>
<number>a</number>to make or amend any regulation within such period as 
may be specified in the direction; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>505773</tid>
<number>b</number>to give priority to the work undertaken or to be 
undertaken by the Foundation in such manner as the Central 
Government may think fit to specify in this behalf.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1168552</tid>
<number>3</number>Any direction issued under this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force or in the memorandum or regulations of the Kalakshetra Society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>590882</tid>
<number> 28</number> Dissolution of the Foundation.-
<section><tid>740447</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by notification and for reasons to be specified therein, 
dissolve, the Foundation from such date and for such period as may be 
specified in the notification:
Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central 
Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Foundation to 
make representation against the proposed dissolution.


</section>

<section><tid>1748733</tid>
<number>2</number>When the, Foundation is dissolved under sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1149280</tid>
<number>a</number>all members of the Governing Board, Academic Committee 
and the Finance Committee, notwithstanding that the terms of 
their office had not expired, shall, from the date of 
dissolution, vacate their offices as such members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1686400</tid>
<number>b</number>all powers and duties of the Governing Board, Academic 
Committee and the Finance Committee shall, during the period 
of dissolution, be exercised and performed by such person or 
persons as the Central Government may appoint in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>946702</tid>
<number>c</number>all properties and assets vested in the Foundation 
shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the Central 
Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>783647</tid>
<number>d</number>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the 
Foundation shall be reconstituted in accordance with the, 
provisions of this Act



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>341570</tid>
<number>29</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer of that Government or the Foundation or 
Member or Director or any officer of the Foundation for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1603292</tid>
<number>30</number>Indemnity.- Every Member of the Governing Board, Academic 
Committee and the Finance Committee and the Director of the Foundation 
shall be indemnified by the Foundation against all losses and expenses 
incurred by them in relation to the discharge of their duties, except 
such as are caused by their wilful act or default.


</article>



<article><tid>286751</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1096779</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1205028</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>132681</tid>
<number>a</number>the allowances to the Members under sub- section (5) of 
section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>270207</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers which the Governing Board shall exercise and 
the functions which it shall discharge under sub- section (2) 
of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1995738</tid>
<number>c</number>functions to be performed by the Finance Committee, 
under clause (iv) of section 18;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1719870</tid>
<number>d</number>the salary and allowances and other terms and 
conditions of service of the Director under sub- section 
 (3) of section 19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985830</tid>
<number>e</number>the form and the manner in which the budget is to be 
prepared by the Governing Board under section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>49368</tid>
<number>f</number>the form and the manner in which, and the time at which, 
the returns, statements and the annual report shall be 
prepared under section 25;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1390331</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688584</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make regulations.-
<section><tid>1228159</tid>
<number>1</number>The Foundation may make  
thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its functions under this 
Act:

</section>

<section><tid>793942</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1377580</tid>
<number>a</number>the management of the properties and funds, affairs and 
works of the Foundation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1809095</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure in regard to transaction of business of the 
regard to transaction of business of the Governing Board 
Academic Committee (including quorum at their meetings) the 
transaction of business of the Finance Committee under sub- 
section (3) of section 13, sub- section (3) of section 15 and 
sub- section (2) of section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1441206</tid>
<number>c</number>creation or abolition of posts and the procedure for 
appointment of the professional, administrative and 
ministerial staff;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1815145</tid>
<number>d</number>the tenure of office and other terms and conditions of 
the members of the Academic Committee under sub- section (2) 
of section 15; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1718662</tid>
<number>e</number>the maintenance of accounts, registers and other 
records of the Foundation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>368833</tid>
<number>3</number>No regulation made by the Foundation shall have effect until 
it has been approved by the Central Government and published in the 
Official Gazette, and the Central Government, in approving the regula- 
tion, may make changes therein which appear to it to be necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>268877</tid>
<number>33</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.- Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be, compri- 
sed in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, be- 
fore the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation, should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.


</article>



<article><tid>979982</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1109927</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises  
in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years, from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1899920</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid a soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>631215</tid>
<number> 35</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>143207</tid>
<number>1</number>The Kalakshetra Foundation Ordinance,  
 <year>1993</year> (Ord. 31 of <year>1993</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1645251</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed, shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>