<act><tid>949048</tid>
<title>THE WEST GODAVARI DISTRICT (ASSIMILATION OF LAWS ON FEDERAL  
  SUBJECTS) ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1949</year> 
[ 14th April, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to assimilate certain laws in force in different parts of the 
West Godavari District of the Province of Madras.

WHEREAS by virtue of the Madras Partially Excluded Area (Cesser) 
Order, <year>1948</year>, made under section 91 of the Government of India Act, 
<year>1935</year>, the area comprised in the villages specified in Article 2 of the 
said Order ceased, as from the 1st day of July, <year>1948</year>, to be part of a 
partially excluded area in the West Godavari district of the Province 
of Madras;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient that the laws in force in the said 
area with respect to the matters enumerated in List I in the Seventh 
Schedule to the Government of India Act, <year>1935</year>, (25 and 26 Geo. 5, c.  
  2.) should be assimilated to the laws in force with respect to the 
said matters in the rest of the said district;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--




<article><tid>1425718</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1634026</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
West Godavari District (Assimilation of Laws on Federal Subjects) Act, 
<year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1737394</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>294568</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation. In this Act--
<section><tid>1897992</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date appointed under sub- 
section (2) of section 1 for the coming into force of 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>907876</tid>
<number>b</number>" Eluru Taluk" means the taluk of that name in the West 
Godavari district of the State of Madras;

</section>

<section><tid>96778</tid>
<number>c</number>" law" means any Act, Ordinance, Regulation, rule, order 
or bye- law, relating to any of the matters enumerated 
in List I in the Seventh Schedule to the Government of 
India Act, <year>1935</year> (25 and 26 Geo. 5, c. 2); and

</section>

<section><tid>60292</tid>
<number>d</number>" scheduled area" means the area comprised in the 
villages which are specified in the Schedule to this 
Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>684597</tid>
<number> 3</number> Assimilation of laws.
<section><tid>942303</tid>
<number>1</number>All laws which immediately before  
the appointed day extend to, or are in force in, the Eluru Taluk, but 
not in the scheduled
<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ist July, <year>1949</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1949</year>, Extraordinary, p. 1085.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


area, shall, as from that day, extend to, or as the case may be, come 
into force in, the scheduled area.


</section>

<section><tid>1252398</tid>
<number>2</number>All laws which immediately before the appointed day are in 
force in the scheduled area, but not in the Eluru Taluk, shall on that 
day cease to be in force in the scheduled area, except as respects 
things done or omitted to be done before that day.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1224156</tid>
<number>4</number>Provision for removal of difficulties. If any difficulty 
arises in relation to the transition from the laws mentioned in sub- 
section (2) of section 3 to the laws mentioned in sub- section 1 
thereof, the Central Government may, by order notified in the Official 
Gazette, make such provision as it considers necessary for the removal 
of such difficulty.

</article>



 </act>