<act><title>

The 
    Indian Tolls (Army and Air Force) Act, 1901 </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Indian Tolls <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[(Army 
    and Air Force)] Act, 1901.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on the first day of April, 1901.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context.—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the expression “authorised followers” 
    means persons other than officers, soldiers or airmen, who are employed by, 
    or air in the service of, the Forces or Corps concerned, or are in the 
    service of any officer, soldier or airman of such Forces or Corps;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “carriage” means a vehicle for carriage 
    or haulage other than one specially constructed for use on rails;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “ferry” includes every bridge and other 
    thing which is a ferry within the meaning of any enactment authorising the 
    levy of tolls on ferries, but does not include any ferry or other thing 
    which is included in the definition of “railway” in section 3 of the Indian 
    Railways Act, 1890);
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>    
    the expression “the regular forces” means “the regular Army” as defined in 
    clause (xxi) of section 3 of the Army Act, 1950, and includes the “Air 
    Force” as defined in clause (iv) of section 4 of the Air Force Act, 1950.]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “horse” including a mule and any beast 
    of whatever description which is used for burden or draught or for carrying 
    persons;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    the expression “Irregular Corps” means 
    any force (other than <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[the Regular Forces or] <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[the 
    Territorial Army or the National Cadet Corps]) raised and maintained in 
    India under the authority of the Central Government, <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***] or 
    any other force may be notified in this behalf by order published in the 
    Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    the expression “Indian Reserve Forces” 
    means the forces constituted by the Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888 and 
    includes officers belonging to the Army in India Reserve of Officers or to 
    the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Regular Reserve of Officers and members of <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***] 
    the Indian Air Force Volunteer Reserve when subject to military or air force 
    law, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “landing-place” includes a pier, wharf, 
    quay, jetty and a stage, whether fixed or floating;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “public authority” means the 
    Central Government <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***] or a State Government or a local 
    authority; and, so far as regards tolls levied by a railway company under 
    section 4 of the Indian Guaranteed Railways Act, 1879<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>
or section 51 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890, 
    includes such a railway company; and
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “tolls” includes duties, dues, rates, 
    fees and charges, but does not include customs duties levied under the 
    Indian Tariff Act, 1934, octroi duties or town duties on the import of 
    goods, or fares paid for the conveyance of passengers on a tramway.]
 
 
  













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Exemptions from tolls.—The 
    following persons and property, namely:—
 <section>
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>    
    all officers, soldiers and airmen of—
9[(a) 
    all officers, soldiers and airmen of—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[the Regular Forces.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any Irregular Corps, <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[***]
 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    all members of <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[the 
    Territorial Army or of the National Cadet Corps] when on duty or when 
    proceeding to or returning from duty.]
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    all officers, soldiers and airmen of 
    the Indian Reserve Forces when proceeding from their place of residence on 
    being called out for service, training, or muster or when proceeding back to 
    their place of residence after such service, training or muster, ing 
    from their place of residence on being called out for service, training, or 
    muster or when proceeding back to their place of residence after such 
    service, training or muster," 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    all authorized followers of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[the Regular Forces.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>ii</number> 
    the Territorial Army or the National Cadet Corps.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any Irregular Corps, <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***]
 
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>    all members of the families of 
    officers, soldiers, airmen or authorized followers of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[the Regular Forces,] or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any Irregular Corps. 
 
     when accompanying any 
    body of troops, or any officer, soldier, airman or authorized follower 
    thereof on duty or on the march. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>    all prisoners under military or air 
    force escort, 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    the carriages, horses and baggage, and 
    the persons (if any) employed in driving the carriages or in carrying the 
    baggage, of any persons exempted under any of the foregoing clauses, when 
    such carriages, horses, baggage, or persons accompanying the persons so 
    exempted under the circumstances mentioned in those clauses respectively,]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>h</number>]    
    all carriages and horses belonging to government or employed <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[in 
    the Indian] military <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[for air force] service and all persons in 
    charge of or accompanying the same, when conveying any such persons as 
    hereinbefore in this section mentioned or when conveying baggage or stores, 
    or when returning, unladen from conveying such persons, baggage or stores;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>i</number>]    
    all carriages and horses when moving under the orders of military <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[or 
    air-force] authority for the purpose of being employed <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[in the 
    Indian military] <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[or air force] service;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>j</number>]    
    all animals accompanying any body of troops which are intended to be 
    slaughtered for food or kept for any purpose connected with the provisioning 
    of such troops, and
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>k</number>]    
    all persons in charge of any carriage, horse or animal exempted under any of 
    the foregoing clauses when accompanying the same under the circumstances 
    mentioned in those clauses respectively.
 
shall be exempted from payment of any tolls—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> on embarking or disembarking, or on being 
    shipped or landed, from or upon any landing place, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> in 
    passing along or over any turnpike or other road or bridge, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> on being 
    carried by means of any ferry, 
 
otherwise demandable by virtue of any Act, 
    Ordinance, Regulation, order or direction of any legislature or other public 
    authority in <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[India]:
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall exempt any boats, barges or other vessels 
    employed in conveying the said persons or property along any canal from 
    payment of tolls in like manner as other boats, barges and vessels. 
 
<footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[Explanation.—The 
    persons or property exempted under clauses (d), (e), (g) and (j) shall be 
    deemed to accompany the Forces, troops, persons or property concerned, when 
    the move of the former is the direct result of, or is connected with the 
    move of the latter, irrespective of the interval of space and time between 
    the two moves].
 
 


















 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Tolls on 
    vessel transporting troops and baggage, etc., of troops embarked or 
    disembarked.—
<section><number>1</number> No tolls shall 
    be leviable by any local authority in respect of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any vessel employed by <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[the 
    Central Government] solely for the transport of troops, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the horses, baggage or other effects of 
    the any troops embarking or disembarking at any port, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    carriages belonging to Government or 
    employed <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[in the Indian] military <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[or air force] 
    service embarking or disembarking at any port.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    respect of all such vessel or troops, their families, their horses, baggage, 
    and their effects, or any such carriages as aforesaid, the local authority 
    concerned shall, in addition to its duties in the embarking and disembarking 
    of the same, perform and supply all such reasonable services and 
    accommodation as may, from time to time, be required by <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[the 
    Central Government], and shall receive payment for all such services and 
    accommodation on such terms and for such periods as may, from time to time, 
    be determined by <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[the Central Government] in consultation with 
    such local authority.
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Penalty.—Any 
    person who demands and receives any toll in contravention of the provisions 
    of section 3 or section 4 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
    fifty rupees.
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any owner or lessee, or any Company, railway administration or local 
    authority claims compensation for any loss alleged to have been incurred to 
    the operation of this Act, the claim shall be submitted to the 
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receiving any such claim, the <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Central Government] <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[***] 
    shall pass such order thereon as justice requires, and shall give all 
    necessary directions for the purpose of ascertaining the facts of the case 
    and of assessing the compensation, if any, to be paid.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[***] 
    may make rules to carry out the purposes and objects of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    the Central Government <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[***] 
    may make rules providing for the form of passes to be given to persons or 
    bodies of persons or in respect of property entitled to exemption from the 
    payment of tolls under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The power 
    to make rules under this section is subject to the condition of the rules 
    made after previous publication.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    rules made under this section shall be published in the Official Gazette
    <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[***] and, on such publication, shall have effect as if enacted 
    by this Act.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government under this section shall be laid, 
    as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament, while it 
    is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
    one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
    of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modification form or be of no effect, as the case 
    may be; so however, that any such modification or a annulment shall be 
    without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
    rule.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Repeals.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10 of 1914), sec. 3 and Sch. II.]
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Indian Tolls (Army and Air Force) Act, 1901 
 

 
 

 
 


 
 




    The Schedule.—Enactments 
    repealed.—[Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10 of 1914), 
    sec. 3 and Sch. II.]
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1942, sec. 2, for the brackets and word “(Army)” (w.e.f. 30-3-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by A.L.O., 1950, 
    for the former sub-section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   The words “except Part B 
    States” omitted by the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951 (3 of 1951, sec. 3 and 
    Sch. (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 15 of 1942, 
    sec. 3, for section 2 (w.e.f. 30-3-1942).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for the former clause (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by A.L.O., 1950. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by A.L.O., 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for “the Auxiliary Force (India) or the Indian Territorial 
    Force” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   The words “or of the Crown 
    Representative” omitted by A.C.A.O., 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for “Indian Regular Reserve of Officers” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   The words “the Royal Air 
    Force Volunteer Reserve and” omitted by A.L.O., 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   The words “or the Federal 
    Railway Authority” omitted by the A.C.A.O., 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   (1879) 42 and 43 Vict., C. 
    41. In its application to India, this Act is repealed by Act 57 of 1960, 
    (w.e.f. 26-12-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Clauses (a) to (g) were 
    subs. by Act 14 of 1942, sec. 4, for the original clauses (a) to (h).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by A.L.O., 1950, for 
    “His Majesty’s Regular Forces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  The word “or” in sub-clause 
    (ii) and the whole of sub-clause (iii) omitted by 2 A.L.O., 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 
    3 and Sch., for “the Auxiliary Force (India) or of the Indian Territorial 
    Force” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for the former sub-clause (ii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   The word “or” in sub-clause 
    (iii) and the whole of sub-clause (iv) omitted by 2 A.L.O., 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   The original clauses (i), 
    (j), (k) and (l) were lettered (h), (i), (j) and (k) respectively by Act 14 
    of 1942, sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by A.L.O., 1950, for 
    “in his Majesty”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Ins. by Act 10 of 1927, 
    sec. 2 and Sch. 1.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   The original clauses (i), 
    (j), (k) and (l) were lettered (h), (i), (j) and (k) respectively by Act 14 
    of 1942, sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Ins. by Act 10 of 1927, 
    sec. 2 and Sch. 1.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs.  by A.L.O., 1950, 
    for “in his Majesty”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs.  by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch., for “a Part A or Part C State” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Added by Act 14 of 1942, 
    sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> 
 Subs. 
    by A.O., 1937, for “the Government”.   tc 
    " 6. Subs. by A.O., 1937, for “the Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> 
 
    Subs.  by A.L.O., 1950, for “in His Majesty’s”.   tc 
    " 7. Subs.  by A.L.O., 1950, for “in His Majesty’s”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> 
 Ins. by Act 10 of 
    1927, sec. 2 and Sch. 1.   tc 
    "2. Ins. by Act 10 of 1927, sec. 2 and Sch. 1."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> 
 Subs.  by A.O. 1937, for 
    “Local Government”. tc " 1. Subs.  by A.O. 1937, for 
    “Local Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs.  by A.O. 1937, 
    for “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   The words “subject to 
    the control of the Governor-General in Council” omitted by A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   The words “and the Local 
    Government with the previous sanction of the Governor General in Council” 
    omitted by A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   The words “or in the 
    local Official Gazette” omitted by A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Ins. by Act 20 of 
    1983, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>