<act><title>
The
Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called [the Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It shall extend to the whole of India.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless
there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 “entry” means entry by water, land or air;
 
 
“passport” means a passport for the time being in force issued or renewed by
the prescribed authority and satisfying the conditions prescribed relating to
the class of passports to which it belongs; and
 
 
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article><number>3</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central
Government may make rules requiring that person entering India shall be in
possession of passports, and for all matters ancillary or incidental to that
purpose.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such rules may—
 <subsection><number>a</number> prohibit
the entry into India or any part thereof of any person who has not in his
possession a passport issued to him;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> prescribe
the authorities by whom passports must have been issued or renewed, and
conditions with which they must comply, for the purposes of this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> provide
for the exemption, either absolutely or on any condition, of any person or class
of persons from any provision of such rules.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Rules made under this section may provide that any contravention thereof or of
any order issued under the authority of any such rule shall be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[punishable
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five year, or with fine which
may extend to fifty thousand rupees, or with both].
 </section><section><number>4</number>
All rules made under this section shall be published in the Official Gazette,
and shall thereupon have effect as if enacted in this Act.
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>5</number>
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be so, however, that any modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rule].
   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> Punishment for subsequent 
offences.—Whoever 
having been convicted of an offence under any rule or order made under this Act 
is again convicted of an offence under this Act shall be punishable with double 
the penalty provided for the later offence.] 


 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article>
<number>4</number> Power to arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any officer of police, not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector, and any officer of 
the Customs Department empowered by a general or special order of the Central 
Government in this behalf may arrest without warrant any person who has 
contravened or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has 
contravened any rule or order made under section 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every officer making an arrest under this section shall, without unnecessary 
delay, take or send the person arrested before a Magistrate having jurisdiction 
in the case or to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police station, and the 
provisions of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[section 57 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], shall, so far as may be, apply in the case of any 
such arrest.
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article></article><article>
<number>5</number> Power of removal.—The 
Central Government may, by general or special order, direct the removal of any 
person from India who, in contravention of any rule made under section 3 
prohibiting entry into India without passport, has entered therein, and 
thereupon any officer of the Government shall have all reasonable powers 
necessary to enforce such directions.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article></article><article><number>6</number> Application of Act to acceeding 
      States.—[Omitted by Act 3 of 
      1951.]
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 47 of
2000, sec. 2, for the words “punishable with imprisonment for a term which may
extend to three months or with fine, or with both”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 4 of
1986, sec. 2 and Schedule.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 47 of 
2000, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 47 of 
2000, sec. 4 for “section 61 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (V of 
1898)”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>