<act><tid>678206</tid>
<title>THE MAULANA AZAD NATIONAL URDU UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 2 OF <year>1997</year>
[ 8TH January, <year>1997</year>.]

An Act to establish and incorporate a University at the national level 
mainly to promote and develop Urdu language and to impart vacational 
and technical education in Urdu medium through conventional teaching 
and distance education system and to provide for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1267716</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1751709</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Maulana Azad National Urdu University Act, <year>1996</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>125233</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>170981</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, and the Statutes made hereunder, unless 
the context otherwise requires,--
<section><tid>433195</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1202251</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff' means such categories of staff as are designated 
as academic staff by the Ordinances:

</section>

<section><tid>1876569</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>303905</tid>
<number>d</number>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- Chancellor" means, 
respectively, the Chancellor, Vice- Chancellor and Pro- ViceChancellor 
of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1385722</tid>
<number>e</number>" Court" means the Court of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1924201</tid>
<number>f</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies; and includes a Centre 
of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>1132695</tid>
<number>g</number>" distance education system" means the system of imparting 
education through any means of communication such as broadcasting, 
telecasting, correspondence courses, seminars, contact programmes or 
the combination of ay two or more of such means;

</section>

<section><tid>1656936</tid>
<number>h</number>" employ" means any person appointed by the University and includes 
teachers and other staff of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1914629</tid>
<number>i</number>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1641627</tid>
<number>j</number>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>152339</tid>
<number>k</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life for the 
students of the University, or of an Institution, maintained by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>996110</tid>
<number>l</number>" institution" means an academic institution maintained by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1512927</tid>
<number>m</number>" Recognised Institution" means an institution of higher learning 
recognised by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>119837</tid>
<number>n</number>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any authority of the 
University under this Act for the time being force:

</section>

<section><tid>828248</tid>
<number>o</number>" School" means a school of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>80747</tid>
<number>p</number>" Statutes" and" Ordinances" means, respectively, the Statutes and 
Ordinances of the University for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>10052</tid>
<number>q</number>" Teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers, Lectures 
and such other persons as may be appointed for imparting instruction 
or conducting research in the University or in any Institution 
maintained by the University and who are designated as teachers by the 
Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>836351</tid>
<number>r</number>" University" means the Maulana Azad National Urdu University 
established and incorporated as a University under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>632486</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of the University.-
<section><tid>194515</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a  
University by the name of" Maulana Azad National Urdu University".

</section>

<section><tid>1425503</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Hyderabad.

</section>

<section><tid>1509021</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the first 
members of the Courts, the Executive Council and the Academic Council 
and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or members, so 
long as they continue to hold such office or membership and hereby 
constituted a body corporate by the name of" Maulana Azad National 
Urdu University".

</section>

<section><tid>786625</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common seal 
and shall sue and be sued by the said name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1950361</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects of University.- The objects of the University shall be to 
promote and develop Urdu language; to impart education and training 
in vocational and technical subjects through the medium of Urdu; to 
provide wider access to people desirous of pursuing programmes of 
higher education and training in Urdu medium through teaching on the 
Campus as well as a distance and to provide focus on women education.


</article>



<article><tid>1119261</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of the University.- The University shall have the following 
powers, namely:-
<section><tid>931548</tid>
<number>i</number>to provide for instructions and research in such branches of 
learning as are relevant for furtherance of the objects of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>1169352</tid>
<number>ii</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University may 
determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or other 
academic distinctions on the basis of examinations, evaluation or any 
other method of testing, on persons, and to withdraw any such 
diplomas, certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions for 
goods and sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>459408</tid>
<number>iii</number>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies, training and 
extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>799067</tid>
<number>iv</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the manner 
prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>279541</tid>
<number>v</number>to institute Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships and other 
teaching or academic positions, required by the University and to 
appoint persons to such Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships or 
other teaching or academic positions;

</section>

<section><tid>426363</tid>
<number>vi</number>to appoint persons working in any other University or 
organisation as teacher or the University for a specific period;

</section>

<section><tid>915428</tid>
<number>vii</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts and to 
make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1164544</tid>
<number>viii</number>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any other 
University or authority or institution of higher learning in such 
manner and for such purposes as the University may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1689771</tid>
<number>ix</number>to establish, with the prior approval of the Central Government, 
such centres and specialised laboratories, within or outside India, as 
are, in the opinion of the University necessary for the furtherance of 
its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>568036</tid>
<number>x</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, studentships, 
medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>198828</tid>
<number>xi</number>to establish and maintain Institutions and Halls;

<subsection><tid>1307781</tid>
<number>xii</number>to make provision for research and advisory services and for 
that purpose to enter into such arrangements with other institutions, 
industrial or other organisations as the University may deem 
necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1186874</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to organise and conduct refresher courses, workshops, seminars 
and other programmes for teachers, evaluators and other academic 
staff;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>417056</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to make special arrangements in respect of the residence, 
discipline and teaching of women students as the University may 
consider desirable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>178297</tid>
<number>xv</number>to appoint, on contract or otherwise, visiting Professors, 
Emeritus Professors, Consultants, Scholars and such other persons who 
may contribute to the advancement of the objects of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475202</tid>
<number>xvi</number>to confer autonomous status on a Department in accordance with 
the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>155355</tid>
<number>xvii</number>to determine standards of admission to the University which may 
include examination, evaluation or any other method of testing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1981145</tid>
<number>xviii</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>928477</tid>
<number>xix</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the University 
and to make arrangements for promoting their health and general 
welfare;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1750788</tid>
<number>xx</number>to lay down conditions of service of all categories of employees 
including their code of conduct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1229593</tid>
<number>xxi</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students and the 
employees and to take such disciplinary measures in this regard as may 
be deemed by the University to be necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1678653</tid>
<number>xxii</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and general 
welfare of the employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>103684</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to acqhire, 
hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or immovable, 
including trust and endowment properties for the purposes of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>453239</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, on the 
security of the property of the University, money for the purposes of 
the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1974664</tid>
<number>xxv</number>to organise suitable distance education programmes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1993375</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>to establish maintain or recognise Study Centres for the 
delivery of the distance education system in the manner laid down by 
the Ordinances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>790773</tid>
<number>xxvii</number>to provide for the preparation of instructional materials 
including films, cassettes, tapes, video cassettes and other software 
in collaboration with various Open Universities and other Institutions 
dealing with the distance education system;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>596719</tid>
<number>xxviii</number>to devise and implement suitable schemes for providing a base 
for promotion and dissemination of Urdu and to bring about the 
essential continuity in education with special reference to the 
delivery system in distance education consistent with the objectives 
of the University; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682451</tid>
<number>xxix</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be necessary, 
incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or any of its 
objects.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1425128</tid>
<number>6</number>Jurisdiction.- The jurisdiction of the University shall extend to 
the whole of India.


</article>



<article><tid>212071</tid>
<number>7</number>University open to all classes, castes and creeds.- The University 
shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever caste, creed, 
race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the University to adopr 
or impose on any person any test whatsoever of religious belief or 
profession in order to entitle him to be appointed as a teacher of the 
University or to hold any other office therein or to be admitted as a 
student in the University or to graduate thereat or to enjoy or 
exercise any privilege thereof:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent the 
University from making special provisions for the employment or 
admission of women, physically handicapped or of persons belonging to 
the weaker sections of the society and, in particular, of the 
Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes.



</article>



<article><tid>988548</tid>
<number> 8</number> The Visitor.-
<section><tid>4567</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>962885</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more persons to 
review the work and progress of the University, including Institution 
managed by it, and to submit a report thereon; and upon receipt of 
that report the Visitor may, after obtaining the views of the 
Executive Council thereon through the Vice- Chancellor, take such 
action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in respect 
of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the University 
shall be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>1984650</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be made 
by such person or persons as he may direct of the University, its 
buildings, laboratories and equipment and of any Institution 
maintained by the University and also of the examinations, teaching 
and other work conducted or done by the University and to cause an 
inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter connected 
with the administration or finances of the University or Institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>1960097</tid>
<number>4</number>The Visitor shall, in every matter referred to in sub- section (3), 
give notice of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be 
made to the University and the University shall have the right to make 
such representations to the Visitor, as it may consider necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1665450</tid>
<number>5</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or 
inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>989985</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by the 
Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a representative 
who shall have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection 
or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>37242</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in respect 
of the University or any Institution maintained by it, address the 
Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or 
inquiry together with such views and advice with regard to the action 
to be taken thereon, as the Visitor may be pleased to offer, and on 
receipt of address made by the Visitor, the Vice- Chancellor shall 
communicate to the Executive Council, the views of the Visitor with 
such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken 
thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>200335</tid>
<number>8</number>The Executive Council shall communicate, through the 
Vice- Chancellor, to the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to 
take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>1461950</tid>
<number>9</number>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable time, 
take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, after 
considering any explanation furnished or representation made by the 
Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and the 
Executive Council shall comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>881947</tid>
<number>10</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this section, 
the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of the 
University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon the 
Registrar to show cause why such an order should not be made, and, if 
any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the 
same.


</section>

<section><tid>657716</tid>
<number>11</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>822864</tid>
<number> 9</number> Officers of the University.- The Following shall be the officers of 
the University:-
<section><tid>146756</tid>
<number>1</number>the Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1202751</tid>
<number>2</number>the Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>166062</tid>
<number>3</number>the Pro- Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>602253</tid>
<number>4</number>the Deans of Schools;

</section>

<section><tid>1562551</tid>
<number>5</number>the Registrar;

</section>

<section><tid>50872</tid>
<number>6</number>the Finance Officer;

</section>

<section><tid>1988241</tid>
<number>7</number>the Librarian; and

</section>

<section><tid>896685</tid>
<number>8</number>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes to be 
officers of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>31129</tid>
<number> 10</number> The Chancellor.-
<section><tid>414259</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the  
Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>52171</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>1698222</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocation of 
the University held for conferring degrees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1157365</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Vice- Chancellor.-
<section><tid>552626</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed  
by the Visitor in such manner and on such terms and conditions of 
service as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1424185</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and academic 
officer of the University and shall exercise general supervision and 
control over the affairs of the University and give effect to the 
decisions of all the authorities of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1200683</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate action 
is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such matters:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of the opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University who 
is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the 
Executive Councilo within three months from the date on which decision 
on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Executive 
Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the 
Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>1919953</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of the opinion that any decision of 
any authority of the University is beyond the powers of the authority 
conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the 
Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of the 
University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision 
within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to 
review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken 
by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1278567</tid>
<number>5</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1045177</tid>
<number>12</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellor.- The Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be 
appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1947142</tid>
<number>13</number>The Deans of Schools.- Every Dean of a School shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>776834</tid>
<number> 14</number> The Registrar.-
<section><tid>1844968</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>28568</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such manner as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1184506</tid>
<number>15</number>The Finance Officer.- The Finance Officer shall be appointed in 
such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as 
may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1538783</tid>
<number>16</number>The Librarian.- The Librarian shall be appointed in such manner 
and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>631635</tid>
<number>17</number>Other officers.- The manner of appointment and powers and duties 
of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1303108</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University.- The following shall be the 
authorities of the University:-
<section><tid>985221</tid>
<number>1</number>the Court;

</section>

<section><tid>556187</tid>
<number>2</number>the Executive Council;

</section>

<section><tid>44816</tid>
<number>3</number>the Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1166592</tid>
<number>4</number>the Board of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>1430694</tid>
<number>5</number>the Finance Committee; and

</section>

<section><tid>1060872</tid>
<number>6</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be 
the authorities of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49072</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Court.-
<section><tid>1787206</tid>
<number>1</number>The constitution of the Court and the term of  
office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>144699</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have the 
following powers and functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>308858</tid>
<number>a</number>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and programmes of 
the University and to suggest measures for the improvement and 
development of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>71191</tid>
<number>b</number>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which may be 
referred to it for advice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1733200</tid>
<number>c</number>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>683157</tid>
<number> 20</number> The Executive Council.-
<section><tid>120018</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall be the  
principal executive body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>968955</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office of 
its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>355965</tid>
<number> 21</number> The Academic Council.-
<section><tid>1197397</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, co- ordinate 
and exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the 
University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>782547</tid>
<number>22</number>The Board of Studies.- The constitution, powers and functions of 
the Board of Studies shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1357060</tid>
<number>23</number>The Finance Committee.- The constitution, powers and functions of 
the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1246672</tid>
<number>24</number>Other authorities of the University.- The constitution, powers and 
functions of other authorities, as may be declared by the Statutes to 
be the authorities of the University, shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>20045</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to make Statutes.- Subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-
<section><tid>88168</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of the authorities, and 
other bodies of the University, as may be constituted from time to 
time;

</section>

<section><tid>478411</tid>
<number>b</number>appointment and continuance in office of the members of the said 
authorities and bodies, filling up of vacancies of members and all 
other matters relating to those authorities and other bodies for which 
it may be necessary or desirable to provide;

</section>

<section><tid>1275575</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of the 
University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>983724</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff and other 
employees of the University, their emoluments and other conditions of 
service;

</section>

<section><tid>265269</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff working in any other 
University or organisation for specific period for undertaking a joint 
project;

</section>

<section><tid>1767108</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including provision for 
pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner of termination of 
service and disciplinary action;

</section>

<section><tid>1453643</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing the seniority of service of the employees 
of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1652192</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute between 
employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1625609</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by any employee 
or student against the action of any officer or authority of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>50932</tid>
<number>j</number>the conferment of autonomous status on an Institution or a 
Department;

</section>

<section><tid>457166</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment and abolition of Schools, Departments, Centres, 
Halls and Institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>581060</tid>
<number>l</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1271486</tid>
<number>m</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions;

</section>

<section><tid>877220</tid>
<number>n</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, studentships, medals 
and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1649138</tid>
<number>o</number>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or officers of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>431225</tid>
<number>p</number>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and students; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1055465</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be or may be provided 
for by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1471188</tid>
<number> 26</number> Statutes how to be made.-
<section><tid>1112000</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set out  
in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>517684</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
sub- section (1):
Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or repeal 
any Statutes affecting the status, powers or constitution of any 
authority of the University until such authority has been given an 
opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed 
changes and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the 
Executive Council:

Provided further that the Executive Council shall not consider to 
make, amend or repeal any statute relating to the matters provided 
under clauses (j) and (k) of section 25 except with the prior approval 
of the Visitor.


</section>

<section><tid>827084</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any amendment or 
repeal of a Statute shall require the assent of the Visitor who may 
assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the Executive Council 
for re- consideration in the light of observations, if any, made by 
him.

</section>

<section><tid>165541</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>689456</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections, 
the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or repeal the 
Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period of three 
years immediately after the commencement of this Act:
Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period of 
three years, make, within one year from the date of such expiry, such 
detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed 
Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.


</section>

<section><tid>76946</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections, 
the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in the 
Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the 
Executive Council is unable to implement such direction within sixty 
days of its receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reaons, if 
any, communicated by the Executive Council for its inability to comply 
with such direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>542764</tid>
<number> 27</number> Powers to make Ordinance.-
<section><tid>926277</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>414875</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their enrolment as 
such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>951544</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, diplomas and 
certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1020358</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8382</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic 
distinctions, qualifications for the same and the means to be taken 
relating to the granting and obtaining of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193419</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the University and 
for admission to the examinations, degrees and diplomas of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>337366</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions for awards of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>937999</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of office and 
manner of appointment and the duties of examining bodies, examiners 
and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>255522</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1514056</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for the 
residence, discipline and teaching of women students and prescribing 
of special courses of studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075101</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointments and emoluments of employees other than those for 
whom provision has been made in the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>367743</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of Studies, 
Special Centres, Specialised Laboratories and other Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1423415</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities, Institutions and other agencies including learned bodies 
or associations in India or abroad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>920381</tid>
<number>m</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other body which is 
considered necessary for improving the academic life of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1729063</tid>
<number>n</number>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers and other 
academic staff as are not prescribed by the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743579</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of Institutions established by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1991842</tid>
<number>p</number>setting up of a machinery for redressal of grievances of 
employees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1562709</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may be 
provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1412887</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor with the 
previous approval of the Central Government and the Ordinances so made 
may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by the Executive 
Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>893988</tid>
<number>28</number>Regulations.- The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees, if 
any, appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances, in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>205840</tid>
<number> 29</number> Annual report.-
<section><tid>100368</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall be  
prepared under the direction of the Executive Council which shall 
include, among other matters, the steps taken by the University 
towards the fulfilment of its objects and shall be submitted to the 
Visitor on or before such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1928902</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the annual report, as prepared under sub- section (1), 
shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall, as 
soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>109289</tid>
<number> 30</number> Annual accounts.-
<section><tid>1831334</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of the  
University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive 
Council and shall, once at least every year and at intervals of not 
more than fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India or by such persons as he may authorise in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>681634</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
thereon shall be submitted to the Visitor along with the observations, 
if any, of the Executive Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1135878</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts shall 
be brought to the notice of the Executive Council and the views of the 
Executive Council, if any, on such observation shall be submitted to 
the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>925696</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report as 
submitted to the Visitor shall also be submitted to the Central 
Government who shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1242018</tid>
<number>5</number>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before both 
Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Gazette of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>292460</tid>
<number> 31</number> Conditions of service of employees.-
<section><tid>504990</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee of the  
University shall be appointed under a written contract which shall be 
lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be furnished to 
the employee concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1808314</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the University and 
any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to a 
Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the 
Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee and an umpire 
appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>625387</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final and no suit shall lie 
in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1887168</tid>
<number>4</number>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2) shall be 
deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this 
section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1747677</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>807323</tid>
<number> 32</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases against 
students.-
<section><tid>395053</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination whose name  
has been removed from the rolls of the University by the orders or 
resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or Examination 
Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred from 
appearing at the examination of the University for more than one year, 
may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or copy of 
such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and the 
Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of the 
Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>301283</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by the 
University against a student shall, at the request of such student, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions of 
sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 31 shall, as far sa may 
be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1637764</tid>
<number>33</number>Right to appeal.- Every employee or student of the University of 
Institution maintained by the University shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, have a right to appeal within such 
time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council 
against the decision of any officer or authority of the University or 
of Institution, as the case may be, and thereupon, the Executive 
Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision appealed against.


</article>



<article><tid>1963330</tid>
<number> 34</number> Provident and pension funds.-
<section><tid>523497</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall constitute  
for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension funds or 
provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>61024</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so constituted, 
the Central Government may declare that the provision of the Provident 
Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such fund, as if it were 
a Government provident fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>207866</tid>
<number>35</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies.- If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>217436</tid>
<number>36</number>Constitution of Committees.- Where any authority of the University 
is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint Committees, such 
Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist of the members 
of the authority concerned and of such other person, if any, as the 
authority in each case may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>467745</tid>
<number>37</number>Filling of casual vacancies.- All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person or 
body who appoints, elects or co- opts the member whose place has become 
vacant and any person appointed, elected or co- opted to a casual 
vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for the residue of 
the term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a 
member.


</article>



<article><tid>1180810</tid>
<number>38</number>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not invalidated 
by vacancies.- No act or proceedings of any authority or other body of 
the University shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of a 
vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>1103488</tid>
<number>39</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit or other legal 
proceedings shall lie against any officer or other employee of the 
University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>1890935</tid>
<number>40</number>Mode of proof of University records.- A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, 
proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the 
register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and 
transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced, 
have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) or in any other law for 
the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1543222</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1323920</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisionss, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as 
appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1926051</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242034</tid>
<number> 42</number> Transitional provisions.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act and the Statutes,-
<section><tid>440588</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Chancellor shall be appointed by the Visitor and the 
said officer shall hold office for a term of five years;

</section>

<section><tid>589574</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the Visitor and 
the said officer shall hold offive for a term of five years;

</section>

<section><tid>818937</tid>
<number>c</number>the first Registrar and the First Finance Officer shall be 
appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall hold 
office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1494343</tid>
<number>d</number>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall consist of 
not more than thirty members and eleven members, respectively, who 
shall be nominated by the Visitor and they shall hold office for a 
term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1541646</tid>
<number>f</number>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more than 
twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and shall 
hold office for a term of three years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or 
nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in 
whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held that office, 
if such vacancy had not occurred.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>136227</tid>
<number> 43</number> Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the 
Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.-
<section><tid>887783</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Statute,  
Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the 
Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1489858</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation or both Houses agree that the Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation should not be made, the Statute, Ordinance or Regulation 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification 
or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that Statute, Ordinance or Regulation.

</section>

<section><tid>372219</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinance 
or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be 
given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudically 
affect the interests of any person to whom such Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation may be applicable.




</section>

</article>



 </act>