<act><tid>606026</tid>
<title>THE VICE- PRESIDENT' S PENSION (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 23rd May, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Vice- President' s Pension Act, <year>1997</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1316202</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1980154</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Vice- President' s Pension (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1266070</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1210626</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Vice- President' s 
Pension Act, <year>1997</year> (30 of <year>1997</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), after sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (1A) The spouse of a person who dies-

<section><tid>1918756</tid>
<number>a</number>while holding the office of Vice- President, or

</section>

<section><tid>264829</tid>
<number>b</number>after ceasing to hold office as Vice- President either by the 
expiration of his term of office or by resignation of his office, 
shall be paid a family pension at the rate of fifty per cent. of 
pension as is admissible to a retiring Vice- President, for the 
remainder of her life.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>20334</tid>
<number> 3</number> Insertion of new section 3A.- After section 3 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 3A. Free accommodation to spouse of Vice- President.- Subject to any 
rules that may be made in this behalf, the spouse of a person who 
dies-

<section><tid>898485</tid>
<number>a</number>while holding the office of Vice- President, or

</section>

<section><tid>76562</tid>
<number>b</number>after ceasing to hold office as Vice- President either by the 
expiration of his term of office or by resignation of his office, 
shall be entitled to the use of unfurnished residence without payment 
of licence fee, for the remainder of her life.".
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>