<act><title>


The Prevention of Cruelty to Draught and Pack 
    Animals Rules, 19651</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Draught and Pack Animals 
    Rules, 1965.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force in any State on such date as the State Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 




 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “large bullock” or “large buffalo” 
    respectively means a bullock or buffalo the weight of which exceeds 350 
    kilograms; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “medium bullock” or “medium buffalo” 
    respectively means a bullock or buffalo the weight of which exceeds 250 
    kilograms, but does not exceed 350 kilograms; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “small bullock” or “small buffalo” 
    respectively means a bullock or buffalo the weight of which does not exceed 
    250 kilograms; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “street” includes any way, road, lane, 
    square, alley or passage, whether a thoroughfare or not, over which the 
    public have a right of way; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “vehicle” means a wheeled conveyance of 
    any description which is capable of being used as such on any street. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-rule (1), the weight of an 
    animal shall be determined by applying any of the following formulae, 
    namely:—
 

 
             
    Length × Girth in cms.
 

                -------------------------    =    Weight of 
    animal of kgs.
 
         
                
    10838                                                                

 

                            or
 
             
    9 lengths in cms. × Girth in mcs



</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Maximum loads for 
    draught animals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall cause any animal specified in column 1 of the table below to 
    draw a vehicle of the kind described in the corresponding entry in column 2 
    thereof if it carries a load in excess of the weight specified in the 
    corresponding entry in column 3 thereof.
  
 

    Table
 
 
 

 

 

 


 
 

 
  
 
  
 
  

 
 

 
 
        Small bullock or small buffalo
 
 
        two wheeled vehicle — 
 
  

 
 

 
  
 
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> if fitted with ball bearings
 
 
— 1000 Kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 750 Kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> if not fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 500 Kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
  
 
  

 
 

 
 
        Medium bullock or medium buffalo
 
 
        two wheeled vehicle— 
 
  

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number> if fitted with ball bearings
 
 
— 1400 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 1050 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> if not fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 700 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
  
 
 
 

 
 

 
 
        Large bullock or large buffalo
 
 
        two wheeled vehicle— 
 
 
 

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number> if fitted with ball bearings
 
 
— 1800 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 1350 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> if not fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 900 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
  
 
 
 

 
 

 
 
        Horse or mule
 
 
        two wheeled vehicle— 
 
 
 

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number> if fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 750 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if not fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 500 kilograms

 
 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

 
 

 
 
        Pony
 
 
        two wheeled vehicle— 
 
 
 

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number> if fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 600 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if not fitted with pneumatic tyres
 
 
— 400 kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
  
 
 
 

 
 

 
 
        Camel
 
 
        two-wheeled vehicle
 
 
— 1000 Kilograms

 
 

 
  
 
  
 
  


  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the vehicle to be drawn is a four-wheeled vehicle, weight 
    specified in column 3 of the said table shall, in each case, be read as 
    being one and a quarter times and, if the four-wheeled vehicle is one fitted 
    with pneumatic tyres, as being one and a half times, as much as the weight 
    so specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   Where the vehicle, whether two-wheeled or four wheeled is to be 
    drawn by two animals of either species referred to in each of the entries in 
    column 1 of the said table, the weight specified in the corresponding entry 
    in column 3 thereof shall be read as being twice, and, if the vehicle is one 
    fitted with pneumatic tyres, as being two and a half times as much as the 
    weight so specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>  Where the route by which a vehicle is to be drawn involves an 
    ascent for not less than one kilometre and the gradient is more than three 
    metres in a distance of thirty metres, the weight specified in column 3 of 
    the said table shall, in each case, be read as being one-half of what is so 
    specified.
 
Explanation 1.—The weights specified in this rule shall be inclusive of 
    the weight of the vehicle.
 
Explanation 2.—In calculating any weight for the purpose of this rule, 
    fractions shall be disregarded.
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>4</number>
Maximum load for certain pack animals.—No
person shall cause any animal specified in column 1 of the table below to carry
any load in excess of the weight specified in the corresponding entry in column
2 thereof.
 


 TABLE
 
 
 
 
   



 
 1 



 
 2 




 
 
 1 



 
 Small
        bullock or buffalo
 



 
 100
        kilograms
 




 
 
 2 



 
 Medium
        bullock or buffalo
 



 
 150
        kilograms
 




 
 
 3 



 
 Large
        bullock or buffalo
 



 
 175
        kilograms
 




 
 
 4 



 
 Pony
 



 
 70
        kilograms
 




 
 
 5 



 
 Mule
 



 
 200
        kilograms
 




 
 
 6 



 
 Donkey
 



 
 50
        kilograms
 




 
 
 7 



 
 Camel
 



 
 250
        kilograms
 






 
 


</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Maximum 
    number of passengers for animal drawn vehicles.—No 
    person in charge of any vehicle drawn by any animal referred to in column 1 
    of the table under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 3 shall allow more than four 
    persons, excluding the driver and children below 6 years of age, to ride on 
    the vehicle.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> General 
    conditions for use of draught and pack animals.—No 
    person shall use or cause to be used any animal for drawing any vehicle or 
    carrying any load—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    for more than nine hours in a day in 
    the aggregate; 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    for more than five hours continuously 
    without a break or rest for the animal; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    in any area where the 
    temperature exceeds 37ºC 
    (99ºF) 
    during the period between 12 noon and 3.00 p.m. 
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Animals 
    to be disengaged after work.—No 
    person shall continue to keep or cause to be kept in harness any animal used 
    for the purpose of drawing vehicles, after it is no longer needed for such 
    purpose. 
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Use of 
    spiked bits prohibited.—No person 
    shall, for the purpose of driving or riding an animal or causing it to draw 
    any vehicle or for otherwise controlling it, use any spiked stick or bit, 
    harness or yoke with spikes, knobs or projections or any other sharp tackle 
    or equipment which causes or is likely to cause bruises, swellings, 
    abrasions or severe pain to the animal. 
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Saddling 
    of horses.—No person shall cause 
    a horse to be saddled in such a way that the harness rests directly on the 
    animal’s withers without there being sufficient clearance between the arch 
    or the saddle and the withers.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Certificates regarding unladen weight of vehicles, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of these rules, the Board may authorise any organisation 
    established for the purpose of preventing cruelty to animals or for 
    promoting their welfare to issue to the owner of any vehicle which may be 
    brought before it for examination, a certificate as to its unladen weight, 
    and any certificate so issued may be accepted as evidence of the weight of 
    such vehicle. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing 
    contained in this rule shall be construed as being in derogation of any 
    right conferred by any law for the time being in force authorising any local 
    authority to determine the unladen weight of any vehicle and to grant the 
    necessary certificate or stamp the vehicle in this behalf.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Powers 
    of police officers and other authorised persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any police officer above the rank of a constable or any other person 
    authorised in this behalf by the State Government or by the Board by general 
    or special order has reason to believe that an offence against rule 3 or 4, 
    has been or is being committed in respect of any animal referred to therein, 
    he may, in any case where a weighbridge is available within a reasonable 
    distance, require the owner or other person in charge of such animal to take 
    the animal or the vehicle or both to the weighbridge for the purpose of 
    determining the weight of the load which the animal has been or is drawing 
    or carrying. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    owner or other person in charge of the aforesaid animal refuses to comply 
    with the demand of the police officer or other person as so authorised, it 
    shall be lawful for such police officer or other person to take the animal 
    or the vehicle or both to the weighbridge for the purpose aforesaid. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> As soon as 
    any weight is determined under this rule, the owner or other person in 
    charge of the said animal shall be given a statement in writing signed by 
    the police officer or the person authorised as aforesaid, as the case may 
    be, as to the weight so determined and any other information relevant for 
    the purpose. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>12</number> 
Application of rules where local bye-laws etc. exist.—If there is in force in any area to which these rules 
extend, any rule, regulation or bye-law made under any law for the time being in 
force by any local authority in respect of any of the matters for which 
provision is made in these rules, such rule, regulation or bye-law shall, to the 
extent to which— 
 <section><number>a</number>    it contains 
provisions less irksome to the animal than those contained in these rules, 
prevail; 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    it contains 
provisions more irksome to the animal than those contained in these rules, be of 
no effect.</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>