<act><tid>775547</tid>
<title>THE INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION (STATUS, IMMUNITIES  
  ANDPRIVILEGES) ACT, <year>1958</year></title>

ACT NO. 42 OF <year>1958</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 17th October, <year>1958</year>.]

An Act to implement the international agreement for the establishment 
and operation of the International Finance Corporation in so far as it 
relates to the status, immunities and privileges of that Corporation, 
and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1301023</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1413247</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
International Finance Corporation (Status, Immunities and Privileges) 
Act, <year>1958</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>143785</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1736303</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1706569</tid>
<number>a</number>" Agreement" means the Agreement for the establishment 
and operation of the international body known as the 
International Finance Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>792211</tid>
<number>b</number>" Corporation" means the International Finance 
Corporation established under the Agreement.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>456979</tid>
<number> 3</number> Conferment of status and certain immunities and privileges on 
the Corporation and conferment of certain immunities and privileges on 
its officers and employees.-
<section><tid>1168115</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the  
contrary contained in any other law, the provisions of the Agreement 
set out in the Schedule shall have the force of law in India:
Provided that nothing in Section 9 of Article VI of the Agreement 
shall be construed as--


<subsection><tid>873971</tid>
<number>a</number>entitling the Corporation to import into India goods 
free of any duty of customs without any restriction on 
their subsequent sale therein; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1288065</tid>
<number>b</number>conferring on the Corporation any exemption from duties 
or taxes which form part of the price of goods sold; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1863503</tid>
<number>c</number>conferring on the Corporation any exemption from duties 
or taxes which are in fact no more than charges for 
services rendered.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>282191</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity with

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
s. 3 and Schedule.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

any amendments duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the 
Agreement set out therein:

Provided that any notification issued under this sub- section 
shall be laid for not less than thirty days before each House of 
Parliament as soon as may be after it is issued and shall be subject 
to such modifications as Parliament may make during the session in 
which it is so laid or the session immediately following.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>550175</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>980083</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>579755</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>