<act><tid>67961</tid>
<title>THE PUBLIC EMPLOYMENT (REQUIREMENT AS TO RESIDENCE) ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>1957</year>
[ 7th December, <year>1957</year>.]

An Act to make in pursuance of clause (3) of article 16 of the 
Constitution special provisions for requirement as to residence in 
regard to certain classes of public employment in certain areas and to 
repeal existing laws prescribing any such requirement.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1330927</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1019962</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the  
Public Employment (Requirement as to Residence) Act, <year>1957</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>952294</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1392987</tid>
<number>2</number>Repeal of existing laws prescribing requirements as to 
residence. Upon the commencement of this Act, any law then in force in 
any State or Union territory by virtue of clause (b) of article 35 of 
the Constitution prescribing, in regard to a class or classes of 
employment or appointment to an office under the Government of, or any 
local or other authority within, that State or Union territory, any 
requirement as to residence therein prior to such employment or 
appointment shall cease to have effect and is hereby repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>1928846</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>761920</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to make rules in respect of certain classes of public  
employment in certain areas. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules prescribing, in 
regard to appointments to-

<subsection><tid>413622</tid>
<number>a</number>any subordinate service or post under the State 
Government of Andhra Pradesh, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517114</tid>
<number>b</number>any subordinate service, or post under the control of the 
Administrator of Himachal Pradesh, Manipur or Tripura, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656026</tid>
<number>c</number>any service or post under a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> local or other authority] 
 (other than a cantonment board) within the Telangana

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 21st March, <year>1959</year>; vide Notification No. G.- S. R. 323, dt. 21- 3- 
<year>1959</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 392.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>subs. by Act I of <year>1969</year>, s. 2, for" local authority".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

area of Andhra Pradesh or within the Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh, Manipur or Tripura,

any requirement as to residence within' the Telangana area or the said 
Union territory, as the case may be, prior to such appointment.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>882383</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section,-

<subsection><tid>799696</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Himachal Pradesh" includes the territories 
specified in sub- section (1) of section 5 of the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>;] (31 of <year>1966</year>).

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1179628</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>]" subordinate service or post" means any service or post 
appointments to which are not notified in the Official 
Gazette but includes any service of tehsildars;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1375299</tid>
<number>b</number>" Telangana area" comprises all the territories specified in 
sub- section (1) of section 3 of the States 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>. (37 of <year>1956</year>).



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>525414</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Parliamentary scrutiny of rules. Every rule made under this 
Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive 
sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so 
laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in 
such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</article>



<article><tid>1732828</tid>
<number>5</number>Duration of Section 3 and rules. Section 3 and all rules made 
thereunder shall cease to have effect on the expiration of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> fifteen 
years] from the commencement of this Act, but such cesser shall not 
affect the validity of any appointment previously made in pursuance of 
the said rules.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1969</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl. (a) relettered by s. 2, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1969</year>, s. 3, for" ten years".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>