<act><tid>1809244</tid>
<title>THE BETWA RIVER BOARD ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 63 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 10th April, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of a Board for the creation of 
a reservoir at Rajghat by construction, on behalf of the Governments 
of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh, of a dam on the Betwa river at 
Rajghat and for the regulation of such reservoir.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1248620</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>236092</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Betwa River Board Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1968718</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, after consultation with the Governments of Madhya 
Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1962512</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is 
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
Central Government should take under its control the regulation and 
development of the inter- State Betwa River and River Valley to the 
extent hereinafter provided.


</article>



<article><tid>353207</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1691386</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Betwa River Board established under 
section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>675715</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>115406</tid>
<number>c</number>" Executive Committee" means the Executive Committee 
constituted under section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>1215598</tid>
<number>d</number>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the 
Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>242292</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the 
Central Government under section 22;

</section>

<section><tid>1761529</tid>
<number>f</number>" Rajghat Dam" means the Dam described in the Schedule;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 25. 10. <year>1976</year>: Vide Notifn. No G. S. R. 1518, dated 14. 10. <year>1976</year>


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>313627</tid>
<number>g</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rani Laxmibai Sagar] means the reservoir created by 
the construction of the Rajghat Dam;

</section>

<section><tid>1208570</tid>
<number>h</number>" regulations" means regulations made by the Board under 
section 23;

</section>

<section><tid>1092407</tid>
<number>i</number>" rules" means rules made by the Central Government 
under section 22.
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE BOARD

CHAPTER II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>154031</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and incorporation of the Betwa River Board.
<section><tid>741526</tid>
<number>1</number> 
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there 
shall be established for the purposes of this Act, a board to be 
called the Betwa River Board.

</section>

<section><tid>852761</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, 
both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the said name 
sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>99723</tid>
<number>3</number>The Union Minister in charge of Irrigation shall be the 
Chairman of the Board and the other members of the Board shall be the 
following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1937087</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> where the same Union Minister is not in charge of both 
Irrigation and Power, the Union Minister in charge of 
Power or such Minister or Deputy Minister in the Union 
Ministry or Department in charge of Power as may be 
specified in this behalf by the Union Minister in 
charge of Power;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>464427</tid>
<number>b</number>the Chief Ministers of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar 
Pradesh; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>369720</tid>
<number>c</number>the Ministers of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar pradesh in 
charge of Finance, Irrigation and Power]:
Provided that when a proclamation made under article 356 of the 
Constitution is in force in relation to the State of Madhya Pradesh or 
Uttar Pradesh, the Central Government may appoint three persons to 
represent such State on the Board and the persons so appointed shall 
vacate their offices upon the revocation or cesser of operation of 
such proclamation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1993</year>, S. 2 
2. Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 2 for the original clauses.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1745540</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board may permit any officer of the Central Government or 
the Government of Madhya Pradesh or Uttar Pradesh to attend any of its 
meetings and take part in the proceedings but such officer shall not 
be entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1124732</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board may associate with itself, in such manner and for 
such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any person whose 
assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any of the 
provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the right 
to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to the purpose 
for which he has been associated, but shall not be entitled to vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746846</tid>
<number> 5</number> Executive committee.
<section><tid>1771659</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Executive 
Committee consisting of officers of that government and officers of 
the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>323492</tid>
<number>2</number>The composition of the Executive Committee shall be such as 
may be prescribed:
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1672825</tid>
<number>a</number>an officer of the Central government shall be the 
Chairman of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1967239</tid>
<number>b</number>the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh 
shall have equal representation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>765511</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the general superintendence and control of the 
Board, the management of the affairs of the Board shall vest in the 
Executive Committee and the Chairman and other members of the 
Committee shall assist the Board in such manner as the Board may 
require.

</section>

<section><tid>1860243</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the rules, and to the directions of the Board, the 
Executive Committee may exercise any power and do any act or thing 
which may be exercised or done by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>710648</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure to be followed by the Executive committee and 
all other matters relating to the Executive Committee shall be as such 
as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1069164</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Board or 
the Executive Committee. No act or proceeding of the Board or the 
Executive Committee shall be invalidated by reason of-
<section><tid>1632420</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in the Board or the Executive Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>354756</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the composition of, or in any appointment 
to, the Board or the Executive Committee;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1797091</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board or the 
Executive Committee not affecting the merits of the 
case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>860502</tid>
<number> 7</number> Chief Engineer and Financial Adviser.
<section><tid>1230268</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, after consultation with the Governments of Madhya 
Pradesh, and Uttar Pradesh, appoint an Engineer (to be the Chief  
Engineer of the Board and to be known as the Chief Engineer, Rajghat 
  Dam Project), and a Financial Adviser, and a Secretary, to the Board 
from amongst the officers of the Government of Madhya Pradesh and 
Uttar Pradesh:
Provided that the Central Government shall, so far as 
practicable, ensure that officers from the same State do not hold the 
posts of Chief Engineer and Secretary at the same time:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that the Central Government may, with the 
concurrence of the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh, 
appoint an officer of the Central government as the Financial 
Adviser].


</section>

<section><tid>159094</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the general superintendence and control of the 
Board and the Executive Committee, the Chief Engineer of the Board 
appointed under sub- section (1) shall be the Chief Executive Officer 
of the Board and shall exercise and discharge-

<subsection><tid>1147916</tid>
<number>a</number>such powers and duties as may be prescribed or as may 
be delegated to him by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>349650</tid>
<number>b</number>such other powers and duties as may be determined by 
regulations.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1567974</tid>
<number>3</number>The Financial Adviser appointed under sub- section (1) shall 
be the Chief Accounts Officer of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>166778</tid>
<number>4</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Chief Engineer of 
the Board, and of the Financial Adviser, and the Secretary, to the 
Board shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1901737</tid>
<number> 8</number> Other officers and employees of the Board.
<section><tid>260552</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
rules, the Board may appoint such officers and employees as it may 
deem necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions:
Provided that the Board shall, as far as practicable, utilise the 
services of the officers and employees offered by the Governments of 
Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh in such a manner that equal 
representation is given to the two States.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>217</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>512150</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions of service of the officers and 
employees of the Board shall be such as may be determined by 
regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>908409</tid>
<number>9</number>Advisory Committees. Subject to the rules, the Board may from 
time to time, constitute one or more Advisory Committees to assist the 
Board and the Executive Committee in the efficient discharge of their 
functions.
CHAP

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE BOARD

CHAPTER III

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE BOARD



</article>



<article><tid>1366204</tid>
<number> 10</number> Functions of the Board. Subject to the other provisions of 
this Act and the rules, the Board may, if satisfied that the 
Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh have complied with or 
arranged to comply with the conditions specified in section 11,--
<section><tid>43607</tid>
<number>a</number>carry out surveys and investigations in the Betwa 
Inter- State river valley and prepare a comprehensive 
project report for the construction of Rajghat Dam and 
appurtenant works <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and for the generation of power at 
Rajghat Dam, including the construction of a power 
house (hereinafter referred to as the Rajghat Power  
  House) near the dam and appurtenant works] and finalise 
the same after consulting the Governments of Madhya 
Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh and taking into account the 
suggestions if any made by those Governments;

</section>

<section><tid>669698</tid>
<number>b</number>prepare detailed reports and estimates in respect of 
the Project and allocate the cost among the Governments 
of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>1765425</tid>
<number>c</number>draw up standards and specifications for implementation 
of the project and for the maintenance thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>247351</tid>
<number>d</number>construct the Rajghat Dam <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and the Rajghat Power 
House] and the common carrier from the dam to irrigate 
areas in Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>875823</tid>
<number>e</number>lay down rules of operation and management of Rajghat 
Dam;

</section>

<section><tid>1959018</tid>
<number>f</number>perform any other function which is supplemental, 
incidental, or consequential to all or any of the 
functions specified in clauses (a) to (e).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>218</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>111107</tid>
<number> 11</number> Conditions subject to which the Board may exercise its 
functions.
<section><tid>756396</tid>
<number>1</number>The exercise by the Board of the functions specified in  
section 10 shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1386637</tid>
<number>i</number>that the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar 
Pradesh shall at all times make, to the satisfaction of 
the Board, suitable provisions as to the moneys, land 
facilities and electrical power for construction and 
all other things required by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>858591</tid>
<number>ii</number>that the liability for the entire expenditure on the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rajghat Dam and Rajghat Power House including 
appurtenant works and on the generation of power at 
Rajghat Dam] and all other expenditure incurred by the 
Board in the discharge of its functions shall be shared 
by the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh 
in such proportion as may be specified by the Board:
Provided that the Board may specify different proportions 
for different works or matters having regard to the benefits 
which may accrue to the States and other relevant factors;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1933934</tid>
<number>iii</number>that the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar 
Pradesh shall extend full co- operation to the Board and 
shall in particular make available to the Board the 
land and electric power required by it for construction 
purposes as expeditiously as possible.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>709481</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of clause (ii) of sub- section (1), the 
expenditure on the Rajghat Dam shall include the expenditure incurred 
by the Government of Uttar Pradesh on the Rajghat Dam Project before 
the establishment of the Board and the Board shall determine the 
amount of expenditure so incurred by the Government of Uttar Pradesh 
and the extent to which it shall be reimbursed by the Government of 
Madhya Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>900478</tid>
<number> 12</number> Powers of the Board.
<section><tid>187909</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act and the rules, the Board shall have the power to do anything which 
may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of carrying out its 
functions under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>219</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 5, for" Rajghat Dam including 
appurtenant works".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>974631</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provision, such power shall include the powers-

<subsection><tid>891232</tid>
<number>a</number>to acquire, hold and dispose of such properties both 
movable and immovable as the Board deems necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000780</tid>
<number>b</number>to publish statistics or other information relating to 
the various aspects of flood control and drainage in 
the Betwa River Valley <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, the regulation of[ Rani 
Laxmibai Sagar] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and the generation of power at 
Rajghat Dam];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1934416</tid>
<number>c</number>to require the Governments of Uttar Pradesh and Madhya 
Pradesh to furnish such information as the Board may 
require in the discharge of its functions.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1136640</tid>
<number> 13</number> Betwa River Board Fund.
<section><tid>1402433</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be constituted a Fund  
to be called the Betwa River Board Fund and there shall be credited 
thereto the sums paid to the Board by the Governments of Madhya 
Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh and all other sums received by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1918224</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be applied-

<subsection><tid>1661980</tid>
<number>a</number>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other 
remuneration of the officers and other employees of the 
Board and other administrative expenses of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221487</tid>
<number>b</number>for meeting the expenditure on surveys and 
investigations undertaken by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>244934</tid>
<number>c</number>for meeting the cost of construction of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Rajghat 
Dam, the Rajghat Power House and appurtenant works];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>676828</tid>
<number>d</number>for meeting the other expenses of the Board in the 
discharge of its functions under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>777289</tid>
<number>14</number>Budget. The Board shall prepare in such form and at such time 
each year as may be prescribed its budget for the next financial year 
showing the estimated expenditure, the amount of expenditure which the 
State Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh have
<pagefootnote><pagenum>220</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 6 for" and the regulation of Rajghat 
Reservoir". 
2. Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1993</year>, s. 3. 
3. Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1977</year>, s. 7, for" Rajghat Dam and appurtenant 
works".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


undertaken to provide for and forward the same to the Central 
Government and the said State Governments.



</article>



<article><tid>247501</tid>
<number> 15</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1863088</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall prepare in such form and  
at such time each year as may be prescribed its annual report giving a 
full account of its activities during the previous year and forward 
copies thereof to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1045914</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall forward copies of its annual reports to the 
Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>721688</tid>
<number>16</number>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Board shall be 
maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>596727</tid>
<number>17</number>Directions by Central Government. In the discharge of its 
functions, the Board shall be guided by such directions and 
instructions on questions of policy as may be given to it by the 
Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>36661</tid>
<number>18</number>Disputes between the Board and the State Governments. If any 
dispute arises between the Board and the Government of Madhya Pradesh 
or Uttar Pradesh or both regarding any matter covered by this Act or 
touching or arising out of it, it shall be referred to the Central 
government and the decision of the Central Government shall be final 
and binding on the Board and the said Governments.


</article>



<article><tid>1133682</tid>
<number>19</number>Power to enter. Subject to any rules made in this behalf, any 
officer of the Board generally or specially authorised by the Board in 
this behalf may, at all reasonable times, enter upon any land or 
premises and there do such things as may be reasonably necessary for 
the purpose of lawfully carrying out any works or of making any 
surveys, examination or investigation, preliminary or incidental to 
the exercise of any power or the performance of any function by the 
Board under this Act:
Provided that no person shall enter into any building or upon any 
enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling house, unless with the 
consent of the occupier thereof, without previously giving such 
occupier at least seven days' notice in writing of his intention to do 
so.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>221</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>213243</tid>
<number>20</number>Members. officers and employees of the Board to be public 
servants. All members of the Board and the Executive Committee and all 
officers and employees of the Board shall be deemed, when acting or 
purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act to 
be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1722196</tid>
<number> 21</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>81046</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central 
Government or the government of Madhya Pradesh or Uttar Pradesh or any 
members of the Board or the Executive Committee or any officer or 
employee of the Board for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1244374</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the 
Board for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything in good 
faith done or purported to be done under this Act or the rules or 
regulations and, in particular, it shall not be the responsibility of 
the Board to provide for relief measures necessitated by floods or by 
breaches and failure of works.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1615260</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>559014</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1864592</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>384064</tid>
<number>a</number>the composition of, and the procedure to be followed, 
by the Executive Committee and all other matters 
relating to the Executive Committee under sub- sections 
 (2) and (5) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130787</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers and duties which may be exercised or 
discharged by the Chief Engineer of the Board, under 
clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378512</tid>
<number>c</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Chief 
Engineer of, and the financial Adviser and the 
Secretary to, the Board, under sub- section (4) of 
section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>16233</tid>
<number>d</number>appointment of officers and employees of the Board, 
under sub- section (1) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1401608</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which and the time at which the budget and 
annual report of the board shall be prepared, under 
section 14, and sub- section (1) of section 15;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>222</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865399</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which the accounts of the Board shall be 
maintained and audited, under section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>844225</tid>
<number>g</number>the form and manner in which disputes may be referred 
under section 18 to the Central Government and the 
procedure to be followed by the Central Government for 
the settlement of such disputes.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1165111</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1054014</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, with the  
previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and 
the rules, for enabling it to discharge its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>859140</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>373754</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which and the purposes for which the 
Board may associate with itself any persons, under sub- 
section (5) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>522070</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which 
may be discharged by the Chief Engineer of the Board, 
under sub- section (2)  (b) of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>210368</tid>
<number>c</number>the terms and conditions of service of the officers 
 (other than the Chief Engineer of the Board, Financial  
  Adviser and Secretary to the Board) and other employees 
of the Board, under sub- section (2) of section 8.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1077567</tid>
<number>24</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive session and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or successive 
sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree that the rule or regulation, as 
the case may be, should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>223</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>