<act><tid>560085</tid>
<title>THE BERAR LAWS ACT, <year>1941</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1941</year>
[ 17th March, <year>1941</year>.]

An Act to extend certain Acts to Berar.

WHEREAS by orders made under the Indian (Foreign Jurisdiction) 
Order in Council, <year>1902</year>, the provisions of certain Acts <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> have from 
time to time been applied to, and are now, by virtue of such 
application, in force in, Berar;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient that those and certain other Acts 
should be extended to, and be, by virtue of such extension, in force 
in, Berar;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>111891</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commncement.
<section><tid>1578674</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Berar Laws Act, <year>1941</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1783280</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> date as the central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1360173</tid>
<number> 2</number> Extension of certain Acts to Berar.
<section><tid>211374</tid>
<number>1</number>The Acts specified in  
the First Schedule and so much of any Act specified in the Second 
Schedule as relates to matters with respect to which the Central 
Legislature has power to make laws are hereby extended to, and shall 
be in force in, Berar; and in any enactment so extended, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
notwithstanding anything contained in clause (7) of section 3 of the 
General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>.), any reference to the States 
shall be construed as a reference to the States and Berar.

</section>

<section><tid>1617439</tid>
<number>2</number>The Acts specified in the Third Schedule shall be amended in 
the manner set forth in the second column of that Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1480554</tid>
<number>3</number>Cesser of application of certain Acts to Berar. The 
application, if any, to Berar, made by order under the Indian (Foreign  
  Jurisdiction) Order in Council, <year>1902</year>, of the Acts specified in the 
First Schedule, of so much of any Act specified in the second Schedule 
as relates to matters with respect to which the Central Legislature 
has power to make laws, and of the Indian Cotton Cess Act, <year>1923</year> (14 of  
  <year>1923</year>), shall cease to have effect:
Provided that all appointments delegation, notifications, orders, 
bye- laws, rules and regulations, which have been made or issued under, 
or in pursuance of, any provision of any of the said Acts as applied 
to Berar by order under the said Order in Council, and which are in 
force at the commecement of this Act, shall be deemed to have been 
made or issued under or in pursuance of the corresponding provision of 
that Act as now extended to, and in force in, Berar.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>102</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" in force in the Provinces" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2. The 1st August, <year>1941</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1941</year>, Pt. I, p. 966. 
3. Certain words omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>486675</tid>
<number>4</number>Removal of doubt. For the removal of doubt it is hereby 
declared that the Acts specified in the Fourth Schedule have ceased to 
have effect and are repealed in Berar.

</article>



 </act>