<act><tid>1313591</tid>
<title>THE JUNAGADH ADMINISTRATION (PROPERTY) ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 13th April, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the vesting of certain property belonging to the 
State of Junagadh in the Administrator appointed by the Central 
Government.

WHEREAS on or about the 9th day of November <year>1947</year> the 
administration of the State of Junagadh was handed over to the Central 
Government;

AND WHEREAS it is necessary to provide for the vesting of certain 
property belonging to the said State in the Administrator thereof, and 
for certain incidental matters;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>932005</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Junagadh 
Administration (Property) Act, <year>1948</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>542380</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act" Administrator" means the person 
appointed by the Central Government to be the Administrator of the 
State of Junagadh.


</article>



<article><tid>833809</tid>
<number> 3</number> Vesting and disposal of property and powers of Administrator.

<section><tid>361066</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being  
in force, the property described in the Schedule, whether in the name 
of His Highness the Nawab of Junagadh, or the Dewan or the Private 
Secretary to His Highness the Nawab of Junagadh, or the Manager and 
Engineer- in- Chief, Junagadh State Railway, or the Chief Accounts 
Officer, Junagadh State, or any other person whatsoever or in the name 
of more than one of them, shall be deemed on and from the 9th day of 
November <year>1947</year> to have vested in the Administrator, and the 
Administrator shall, as from that date, hold and be entitled to and 
have the power to deal with and dispose of the said property as such 
Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1489135</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provisions, the Administrator shall have the power to-

<subsection><tid>1843480</tid>
<number>a</number>receive and give full and effectual discharge for or in 
respect of the bank deposits, securities and shares 
described in the Schedule;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>892441</tid>
<number>b</number>sell, transfer or otherwise dispose of or deal with 
such property.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>63744</tid>
<number>4</number>Issue of duplicate securities. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any law for the time being in force, the Reserve Bank of 
India shall issue to the Administrator duplicate securities in his 
name in lieu of the securities specified in Part II of the Schedule as 
if the securities so specified had been lost, and such duplicate 
securities shall have the same effect as if they had been issued under 
section 11 of the Public Debts (Central Government) Act, <year>1944</year> (18 of  
  <year>1944</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>457135</tid>
<number>5</number>Transfers otherwise than by Administrator void. Any transfer 
of, or dealing with, any of the property described in the Schedule 
after the 8th day of November <year>1947</year>, otherwise than by the 
Administrator, shall be, and shall always be deemed to have been, void 
and of no effect.


</article>



<article><tid>418156</tid>
<number> 6</number> Bar of jurisdiction.
<section><tid>1154531</tid>
<number>1</number>No Court shall have jurisdiction to  
entertain any suit or other proceeding in respect of any of the 
property described in the Schedule or to enforce any liability in 
respect thereof, otherwise than at the instance of the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1996959</tid>
<number>2</number>Any claim in respect of such property by any person other 
than the Administrator may be submitted to the Central Government, 
whose decision in the matter shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585998</tid>
<number>7</number>Protection of action taken under this Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government, the Reserve Bank of India, any bank or company named in 
Parts I and III of the Schedule or any person for anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the 
provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1182405</tid>
<number>8</number>Power of the Central Government to add to the Schedule. The 
Central Government may from time to time add to the items of property 
included in the Schedule by notification in the Official gazette and 
on such notification such property shall be deemed to have been always 
included in the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1148514</tid>
<number> 9</number> Repeal of Ordinance No. 30 of <year>1947</year>.
<section><tid>1434302</tid>
<number>1</number>The Junagadh  
Administration (Property) Ordinance, <year>1947</year>, is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>780586</tid>
<number>2</number>Anything done or any action taken in exercise of any power 
conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall, so far as it is not 
inconsistent with this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken in 
exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act 
had commenced on the 24th day of December, <year>1947</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>