<act><title>THE TELECOMMUNICATION INTERCONNECTION (PORT CHARGES) REGULATION, 20011</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> This regulation shall be called the Telecommunication Interconnection (Port Charges) Regulation, 2001. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> These regulations pertains to the Port charges payable by the Interconnection Seeker to the Interconnection Provider for terminating the interconnection links on the Network Interface of the Interconnection Provider. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> In this Regulation, a "Port" means a place of termination on a Switch/distribution frame to provide a point of access or interconnection for ingress and egress of traffic between the two Interconnecting Networks. The bandwidth of the Port shall be 2.048 Magabits per second. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> The Regulation shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from date of notification in Official Gazette. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> This Regulation shall regulate Port charges as detailed herein including those in Schedule I. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> </title> Unless the context otherwise requires, all the definitions as provided under section II and the regulations under section(s) III and IV of "the Telecommunication Interconnection (Charges &amp; Revenue Sharing) Regulation 2001" notified on 14-12-2001, will be applicable to this Regulation. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> Port charges on or after the 1st April, 2007. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Every interconnection seeker shall, on or after the 1st day of April, 2007, make his demand, for every Point of Interconnection for the total number of Ports required by him on or after the said date to the interconnection provider. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every interconnection seeker shall make demand under sub-regulation (1) on the basis of traffic projection (in Erlangs) on half yearly basis. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every interconnection provider shall charge, on or after the 1st day of April, 2007, the Port charges in accordance with the Port charges specified in Schedule II to these regulations and raise the demand note or the invoice, as the case may be, for the Ports demanded on or after the said date by the interconnection seeker under sub-regulations (1) and (2). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case where interconnection provider does not allot and provide all the Ports on the date, or, within such period, as requested by the interconnection seeker and in accordance with the demand made by him under sub-regulations (1) and (2), the Port charges for the Ports allotted and provided shall be calculated on the basis of the total number of Ports so demanded (taking into account the Ports allotted and provided and also the remaining ports not allotted and provided by the interconnection provider as per his demand) and charges for the Ports so allotted and provided shall be calculated on the basis of the total Ports so, demanded based on traffic projections (in Erlangs) and the charges for the Ports shall be calculated in accordance with the charges specified against the slabs in Schedule II to these regulations. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> In case where interconnection seeker does not take all the Ports in accordance with the demand made by him under sub-regulations (1) and (2), the Port charges for the Ports allotted and provided shall be calculated on the basis of the total number of Ports so actually taken by him, and, the Ports not taken by him as per his demand shall be ignored for determining the slab for calculating the Port Charges and the charges for the Ports shall be calculated on the basis of actual Ports taken by him and not on the basis of Ports demanded by him under sub-regulations (1) and (2), in accordance with the charges specified against the Port slabs in Schedule II to these regulations. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Port charges for every Port demanded, allotted and provided before the 1st day of April 2007 shall be charged before the said date in accordance with the Port charges specified in Schedule I to these regulations and the interconnection provider shall accordingly raise the demand note or the invoice, as the case may be, for such Ports demanded, allotted and provided. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Port charges for every Port demanded, allotted and provided before the 1st day of April, 2007 shall be charged on or after the said date in accordance with the Port charges specified in Schedule II to these regulations and the interconnection provider shall raise the demand note or the invoice, as the case may be, for such Ports provided by him before the aforesaid date accordingly. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The slab for calculation of Port charges under sub-regulation (7) shall continue to be with reference to the slabs specified in the Schedule I to these regulations, which were taken into account for determining the Port charges before the 1st day of April, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Nothing contained in the Schedule II to these regulations shall apply in case the interconnection provider and the interconnection seeker mutually agree to charge and pay charges lower than those specified in the Schedule II to these regulations.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Reporting Requirement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> All Service Providers shall comply with the Reporting Requirement in respect of Port charges specified under this Regulation, as also all subsequent changes. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> Where a Port charge below the ceiling notified herein is to be implemented, the Service Provider may implement the proposed Port charges after the mandatory notice period of 45 working days, unless the Authority within such period directs otherwise. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Port charges whenever implemented as per Schedule I herein, shall be reported to the Authority within 45 days of their implementation. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> When an Interconnection Provider informs the Interconnection Seeker that it cannot provide the Ports as sought for by the latter, the Interconnection Seeker within 45 days of being so informed, may approach the Authority for seeking its intervention. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> No service provider shall alter any Port charge, or any part thereof, without complying with the Reporting Requirement. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Review. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> The Authority may, from time to time, review and modify Port charges. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> The Authority may also at any time, on reference from any affected party, and for good and sufficient reasons, review and modify the Port charges. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Explanatory Memorandum. </title>-This Regulation contains at Annexe A , an Explanatory Memorandum to provide the background and reasons for issuing this Regulation. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Interpretation. </title>-In case of dispute regarding interpretation of any of the provisions of this Regulation, the decision of the Authority shall be final and binding. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Notification No. 409-10/2006-FN, dated 2nd February, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-4-2007).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>