<act> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 19881
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport 
Services) Rules, 1988.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> These rules shall be 
applicable to the employees in all States and Union Territories except those 
States and Union Territories where, unpaid wages of the employee are required to 
be deposited by the employer with an authority under the provisions of any law 
for the time being in force in such State or Union Territories.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Payment of Wages 
Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Chief Labour Commissioner 
(Central)” means an officer appointed as such by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “employed person” or “employee” 
means a person employed in an air transport service to whom the Act applies;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “employer” means the owner of an 
air transport service and includes a contractor, agent, manager or any other 
person responsible under section 3 of the Act for payment of wages and includes 
in the case of a deceased employer, his legal representatives;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “family” means,—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  in case of a male 
employee, his wife or wives and children, whether married or unmarried, his 
dependent parents and widows and children of his deceased sons;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  in case of a female 
employee, her husband, her children, whether married or unmarried, her dependent 
parents, her husband’s dependent parents, and widows and children of her 
deceased sons;
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  words and expressions used in 
these rules and not defined herein shall have the same meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person who is already in employment on the date of commencement of the Payment 
of Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Service) Rules, 1988, ordinarily within six 
months from such date, and a person who has been employed after the date of the 
commencement of the said rules, ordinarily within three months from the day he 
is employed, shall nominate a person conferring on him the right to receive all 
amounts payable to him as wages, if such amounts could not or cannot be paid on 
account of his death before the payment or on account of his whereabouts not 
being known such nomination shall be in Form I and submitted in duplicate by the 
employed persons by personal service, after taking proper receipt thereof or by 
sending through registered post with acknowledgement due to the employer:
 
Provided that the 
nomination shall be accepted by the employer even after the expiry of the 
specified period if filed with reasonable grounds for delay and no nomination so 
accepted shall be invalid mainly because it was filed after the expiry of the 
specified period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Within thirty days 
from the receipt of the nomination under sub-rule (1), the employer shall get 
the service particulars of the employed person as mentiond in the form of 
nomination, verified with reference to records of the air transport services and 
a duly attested copy of the Form I by the employer shall be given to the 
employed person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, at the time of 
making a nomination an employed person has a family, the nomination shall not be 
in favour of a person other than the members of such family.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If at the time of 
making the nomination, the employed person has no family, the nomination may be 
made in favour of any person but as soon as the employed person subsequently 
acquires a family, such nomination shall become invalid forthwith and the 
employed person shall, within thirty days of acquiring a family, submit a fresh 
nomination in duplicate in Form II to the employer and thereafter the provisions 
of sub-rule (2) shall apply mutatis mutandis, as it was made under 
sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the nominee 
predeceases an employed person, the interest of the nominee shall revert to the 
employed person who shall within a period of thirty days from the death of the 
nominee make a fresh nomination in the manner hereinafter provided for.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A notice of 
modification of a nomination including cases where a nominee pre-deceases an 
employed person shall be submitted in duplicate in Form III to the employer in 
the manner specified in sub-rule (1) and thereafter the provisions of sub-rule 
(2) shall apply mutatis mutandis, as if it was under sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The employed person 
shall not nominate a person who is a minor.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A nomination or a 
fresh nomination or notice of modification of nomination shall be signed by the 
employed person or if illiterate, bears his thumb impression in the presence of 
two witnesses who shall also sign a declaration to that effect in the 
nomination, fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> A nomination or a 
fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination shall take effect 
from the date of receipt thereof by the employer.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Register of 
nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall record and file all nominations, fresh nominations and 
notices of modification of nominations, as the case may be in the register of 
nominations which shall be maintained chronologically by him in Form IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The register of 
nominations shall be maintained by the employer up-to-date and kept permanently 
at the workspot or where the employer experiences difficulty in keeping them at 
the workspot, at any other suitable place as may be approved by the prescribed 
authority in this behalf.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Prescribed authority.—The 
Chief Executives of the Air India, Indian Airlines and Vayudoot shall be the 
prescribed authority with whom the amounts payable to employed persons as wages 
required to be deposited under clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 25A of 
the Act and who shall deal with the amount so deposited in the manner prescribed 
in rule 7.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Deposit of amounts of 
undisbursed wages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where all amounts payable as wages to a person employed in an establishment in 
relation to air transport services remain undisbursed because either no 
nomination has been made by the employed person or for any reasons such amounts 
could not be paid to the nominee of the employed person until the expiry of 
three years from the date the same had become payable, all such amounts shall be 
deposited by the employer with the prescribed authority within fifteen days from 
the said period of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amounts referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be deposited by the employer through crossed demand 
draft obtained from any scheduled bank in India drawn in favour of the 
prescribed authority, and such demand draft shall be submitted by the employer 
to the prescribed authority together with relevant details in Form V by 
registered post.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Manner of dealing with 
the amounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The amount deposited with the prescribed authority under rule 6 shall remain 
with the prescribed authority for four years and be invested in the Central or 
State Government securities or deposited in some nationalised banks.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prescribed 
authority shall as soon as possible exhibit the above fact at least for fifteen 
days on the notice board of the establishment and shall also publish in any two 
newspapers of the languages commonly understood in the area of the establishment 
in which undisbursed wages were earned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority shall release the money to the nominee or to that person whose claim 
to this money has been allowed by any competent authority/court.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The amount deposited 
under sub-rule (1) shall, after a lapse of four years from the date of such 
deposit be applied by the prescribed authority to meet the expenditure incurred 
in connection with the measures which are necessary or expedient in his opinion 
to promote the welfare of persons employed in air transport service and in 
particular to defray the cost of following measures for the benefit of such 
persons:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  for improving the educational 
facilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  for improving family welfare 
including family planning;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  for improving vocational 
training, rehabilitation of disabled and handicapped persons; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  for improving transport 
facilities.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The expenditure 
incurred in connection with the measures referred to in sub-rule (4) either by 
an employer in relation to air transport services or by their trade union 
registered under the Trade Unions Act, 1926 (16 of 1926) may be reimbursed to 
the person concerned by the prescribed authority either wholly or partly at his 
discretion, if he is satisfied that the expenditure has actually been incurred 
for the bona fide purpose as specified in the said sub-rule (4).
  
</section></article><form>
 

The Payment 
of Undisbursed Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1988
 


 
 


Form III
 


[See sub-rule (6) of rule 3]
 


Modification of Nomination
 


To
 


(Give here name and address of employer 
together with name and full address of the establishment).
 


I, ..........................(Name in full 
here), whose particulars are given below hereby give notice that the nomination 
filed by me on.............. and recorded under your reference 
number..................date shall stand modified in the following manner:—
 


(Here give details of the modification 
intended).
 


Statement
 


   1.  Name of the employed person in 
full                                           :
 


   2.  
Sex                                                                                              
:
 


   3.  
Religion                                                                                        
:
 


   4.  Whether 
unmarried/married/widow/widower                              :
 


   5.  Department/Branch/Section where 
employed                             :
 


   6.  Post held with ticket number or serial 
number, if any                  :
 


   7.  Date of 
appointment                                                                    :
 


   8.  Present 
address                                                                          
:
 


   9.  Permanent 
address                                                                    

 


        
Village                                                                                          
:
 


        Thana                                                                                          
:
 


        
Sub-division                                                                                 
:
 


        Post 
Office                                                                                   
:
 


        
District                                                                                         
:
 


        
State                                                                                            
:
 


 
 



Place.............................                                                           
Signature/Thumb-impression
 



Date.............................                                                            
of the employed person
 


 
 


Declaration by 
witnesses
 


Modification of nomination signed/thumb-impressioned 
before me:
 


      Name in Full and full 
address:                                      Signature of witnesses:
 


      
1.                                                                                 
1.         
 


      
2.                                                                                 
2.
 


Place............................
 


Date.............................
 


Certificate by the 
Employer
 


Certified that the above nominations have 
been recorded and entired into in the register of nominations in Form IV at 
serial number.............
 



Place.............................                                      
Signature of the Employer/Officer authorised
 



Date.............................                                       
Designation
 



                                                                           Name 
and address of the mine or 
 



                                                                           
rubber stamp thereof.
 


 
 


Acknowledgement of 
the employed person
 


Received the duplicate copy of the nomination 
in Form III filed by me on............... duly certified by the employer.
 



Place..........................                                                     
Signature of the employed person
 


Date...........................
 


Note.—Strike 
out the words not applicable.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>