<act><tid>735927</tid>
<title>THE PUBLIC DEBT ACT, <year>1944</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <year>1944</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 22nd November, <year>1944</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Government 
Securities <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and to the management by the Reserve Bank of 
India of the public debt of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Government].

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating 
to Government securities <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and to the management by the Reserve 
Bank of India of the public debt of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Government];





<article><tid>622861</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1345442</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Public Debt <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Act, <year>1944</year>.
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.


</section>

<section><tid>616816</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date' as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1015667</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Securities to which this Act applies. This Act applies to 
Government securities created and issued Whether before or after the 
commencement of this Act by the Central Government or a State 
Government <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>.]


</article>



<article><tid>1933261</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in 
the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1855512</tid>
<number>1</number>" the Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India;

</section>

<section><tid>37745</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>" the Government" in relation to any Government 
security means the Central or State Government issuing the 
security;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar 
Haveli. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>. s. 2 and Sch. I.

This Act came into force in Pondicherry on 1- 10- <year>1963</year>: vide Reg. 
7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 1.

Extended to the whole of the Union Teritory of Lakshadweep 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>). vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" issued by the Central Government" omitted by Act 
6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f 1- 4- <year>1949</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2, for" the Union and the Part A 
States" (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words and brackets" (Central Government)" omitted by Act 6 
of <year>1949</year> S. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1949</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Sub- section (2) omitted by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 15- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number> 1st May, <year>1946</year> see Gazette of India, <year>1946</year>, Pt. 1, p. 575.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Certain words omitted by Act 44 of <year>1972</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1972</year>). 
9 Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1949</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>864529</tid>
<number>2</number>" Government security" means-

<subsection><tid>335724</tid>
<number>a</number>a security, created and issued, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by the Government] 
for the purpose of raising a public loan, and having one of 
the following forms, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>588798</tid>
<number>i</number>stock transferable by registration in the books of the 
Bank; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>292917</tid>
<number>ii</number>a promissory note payable to order; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>163772</tid>
<number>iii</number>a bearer bond payable to bearer; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1439831</tid>
<number>iv</number>a form prescribed in this behalf;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921471</tid>
<number>b</number>any other security created and issued by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the 
Government] in such form and for such of the purposes of this 
Act as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1985194</tid>
<number>3</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act:

</section>

<section><tid>1910605</tid>
<number>4</number>" promissory note" includes a treasury bill.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1162788</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of Government securities. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>873458</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of section 5, a transfer of a Government security shall be 
made only in the manner prescribed for the making of transfers of 
securities of the class to which it belongs, and no transfer of a 
Government security which-

<subsection><tid>1799867</tid>
<number>i</number>is made after the 30th April, <year>1946</year>, in the case of a 
security issued by the Central Government,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>25264</tid>
<number>ii</number>is made after the 31st March, <year>1949</year>, in the case of a 
security issued by the Government of a Part A State,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>746941</tid>
<number>iii</number>is made after the 14th October, <year>1956</year>, in the case of 
a security issued by the Government of a Part B State other 
than Jammu and Kashmir, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>523374</tid>
<number>iv</number>is made on or after the 1st day of November, <year>1956</year>, 
in the case of a security issued on or after that day by the 
Government of any State other than Jammu and Kashmir, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>636314</tid>
<number>v</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> is made on or after the 1st day of September, <year>1972</year>, 
in the case of a security issued on or after that day by the 
Government of the State of Jammu and Kashmir,]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5, for" whether before or after the 
commencement of this Act, by the Central Government or a State 
Government" (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" the Central Government or a State 
Government" (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The word" and" omitted by Act 44 of <year>1972</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1972</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

shall be valid if-] 
 (a) it does not purport to convey the full title to the 
security, or


<subsubsection><tid>968917</tid>
<number>b</number>it is of such a nature as to affect the manner in which 
the security was expressed by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] to be held,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1949</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>724355</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section shall affect any order made by the 
Bank under this Act, or any order made by a Court upon the Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>868360</tid>
<number>4</number>Transferor of Government securities not liable for amount 
thereof. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Negotiable Instru- 
ments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>), a person shall not, by reason only of 
his having transferred a Government security, be liable to pay any 
money due either as principal or as interest thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1393701</tid>
<number> 5</number> Holding of Government securities by holders of public offices.

<section><tid>1825858</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of any public office to which <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, declare this subsection to 
apply, a Government security in the form of stock or of a promissory 
note may be held in the name of the office.

</section>

<section><tid>629808</tid>
<number>2</number>When a Government security is so held, it shall be deemed to 
be transferred without any or further endorsement or transfer deed 
from each holder of the office to the succeeding holder of the office 
on and from the date on which the latter takes charge of the office.

</section>

<section><tid>1759194</tid>
<number>3</number>When the holder of the office transfers to a party not being 
his successor in office a Government security so held, the transfer 
shall be made by the signature of the holder of the office and the 
name of the office in the manner and subject to the conditions laid 
down in section 3.

</section>

<section><tid>7410</tid>
<number>4</number>This section applies as well to an office of which there are 
two or more joint holders as to an office of which there is a single 
holder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>356655</tid>
<number> 6</number> Notice of trust not receivable.
<section><tid>1853199</tid>
<number>1</number>No notice of any trust in  
respect of any Government security shall be receivable by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Government], nor shall <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] be bound by any such notice 
even though expressly given, nor shall <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] be regarded 
as a trustee in respect of any Government security.

</section>

<section><tid>541889</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Bank may, as an act of grace and without any liability to the Bank or 
to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government], record in its books such directions by the 
holder of stock for the payment of interest on, or of the maturity 
value of, or the transfer of, or such other matters relating to, the 
stock as the Bank thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>296852</tid>
<number>7</number>Persons whose title to a Government security of a deceased sole 
holder may be recognised by the Bank. Subject to the provisions of 
section 9 the executors or administrators of a deceased sole holder of 
a Government security and the holder of a succession certificate 
issued under Part X of the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>), 
shall be the only persons who may be recognise by the Bank as having 
any title to the Government security:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that nothing in this section shall bar the recognition 
by the Bank of the manager or the sole surviving male member of a 
Hindu undivided family governed by the Mitakshara Law as having a 
title to a Government security, when the security appears to the Bank 
to stand in the name of a deceased member of the family and an 
application is made by such manager or sole surviving member for 
recognition of his title and is supported by a certificate signed by 
such authority and after such inquiry as may be prescribed to the 
effect that the deceased belonged to a Hindu undivided family governed 
by the Mitakshara Law, that the Government security formed Dart of the 
joint property of the family, and that the applicant is the managing 
or sole surviving male member of the family.

Explanation.- The expression" Hindu undivided family governed by 
the Mitakshara Law" shall, for the purposes of this section, be 
deemed to include a Malabar tarwad.



</article>



<article><tid>346009</tid>
<number> 8</number> Right of survivors of joint holders of several payees. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 45 of the Indian 
Contract Act, <year>1872</year> (9 of <year>1872</year>),-
<section><tid>1517990</tid>
<number>a</number>When a Government security is held by two or more persons 
jointly and either or any of them dies, the title to the 
security shall vest in the survivor or survivors of those 
persons, and

</section>

<section><tid>1231034</tid>
<number>b</number>when a Government security is payable to two or more 
Persons severally and either or any of them dies, the 
security shall be payable to the survivor or survivors of 
those persons or to the representative of the deceased or to 
any of them:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect any 
claim which any representative of a deceased person may have against 
the survivors or survivors under or in respect of any security to 
which this section applies.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section I[ a body 
incorporated or deemed to be incorporated under the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>] (1 of <year>1956</year>), or the I Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of  
  <year>1912</year>), or any other enactment for the time 2 being in force whether 
whether or without <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India], relating to the incorporation of 
associations of individuals, shall be deemed to die when it is 
dissolved.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>21566</tid>
<number>9</number>Summary procedure on death of holder of Government securities 
not exceeding five thousand rupees face value. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 7, if within six months of the death of 
a person who was the holder of a

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for" a body incorporated under 
the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year>" (w. e. f. 15th October, <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Government security or securities the face value of which does not in 
the aggregate exceed five thousand rupees, probate of his will or 
letters of administration of his estate or a succession certificate 
issued under Part X of the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>), is 
not produced to the Bank, or proof to the satisfaction of the Bank that 
proceedings have been instituted to obtain one of these is not 
furnished, the Bank may determine who is the person entitled to the 
security or securities, or to administer the estate of the deceased 
and may make an order vesting the security or securities in the person 
so determined.



</article>



<article><tid>352066</tid>
<number>10</number>Government securities not exceeding five thousand rupees face 
value belonging to minor or in same person. When a Government security 
or securities belong to a minor or a person who is insane and 
incapable of managing his affairs and the face value of the security 
or securities does not in the aggregate exceed five thousand rupees, 
the Bank may make such order as it thinks fit for the vesting of such 
security or securities in such person as it considers represents the 
minor or insane person.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>221906</tid>
<number> 11</number> Issue of duplicate securities and of new securities and of new 
securities on conversion, consolidation, sub- division or renewal.
<section><tid>510797</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If the person entitled to a Government security applies to the Bank 
alleging that the security has been lost, stolen or destroyed, or has 
been defaced or mutilated, the Bank may, on proof to its satisfaction 
of the loss, theft, destruction, defacement or mutilation of the 
security, subject to such conditions and on payment of such fees as 
may be prescribed, order the issue of a duplicate security payable to 
the applicant.

</section>

<section><tid>694680</tid>
<number>2</number>If the person entitled to a Government security applies to 
the Bank to have the security converted into a security of another 
form, or into a security issued in connection with another loan or to 
have it consolidated with other like securities, or to have it sub- 
divided, or to have it renewed, the Bank may, subject to such 
conditions and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, cancel 
the security and order the issue of a new security or securities.

</section>

<section><tid>162537</tid>
<number>3</number>The person to whom a duplicate security or a new security is 
issued under this section shall be deemed for the purposes of section 
 19 to have been recognised by the Bank as the holder of the security; 
and a duplicate security or new security so issued to any person shall 
be deemed to constitute a new contract between <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] and 
such person and all persons deriving title thereafter through him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>841634</tid>
<number> 12</number> Summary determination by the Bank of title to Government 
security in case of dispute.
<section><tid>542670</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Bank is of opinion that a  
doubt exists as to the title to a Government security, it may proceed 
to determine the person who shall for the purposes of the Bank be 
deemed to be the person entitled thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1202694</tid>
<number>2</number>The Bank shall give notice in writing to each claimant of 
whom it has knowledge stating the names of all other claimants and the 
time when and the officer of the Bank by whom the determination of the 
Bank will be made.

</section>

<section><tid>769720</tid>
<number>3</number>The Bank shall give notice in writing to each claimant of the 
result of the determination so made.

</section>

<section><tid>1147205</tid>
<number>4</number>On the expiry of six months from the issue of the notices 
referred to in sub- section (3), the Bank may make an order vesting in 
the person, found by the Bank to be entitled to the security, the 
security and any unpaid interest thereon.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1604873</tid>
<number>13</number>Law applicable in regard to Government securities. 
Notwithstanding that as a matter of convenience <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] may 
have arranged for payments on a Government

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

security to be made elsewhere than in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], the rights of all 
persons in relation to Government securities shall be determined in 
connection with all such questions as are dealt with by this Act by 
the law and in the Courts of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India].



</article>



<article><tid>596372</tid>
<number> 14</number> Recording of evidence.
<section><tid>970075</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of making any order  
which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank may request a 
District Magistrate <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> to record or to have recorded the whole or 
any part of such evidence as any person whose evidence the Bank 
requires may produce. A District Magistrate so requested may himself 
record, or may direct any Magistrate of the first class subordinate to 
him or any Magistrate of the second class subordinate to him and 
empowered in this behalf by general or special order of the State 
Government to record the evidence, and shall forward a copy thereof to 
the Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1683201</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of making a vesting order under this Act the 
Bank may direct one of its officers to record the evidence of any 
person whose evidence the Bank requires or may receive evidence upon 
affidavit.

</section>

<section><tid>11019</tid>
<number>3</number>A Magistrate or an officer of the Bank acting in pursuance 
of this section may administer an oath to any witness examined by him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 8, for" Part A States and Part C 
States" (w. e. f. 15th October, <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for" those States" (w. e. f. 15th October,  
  <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" or in a Part B State the Political Agent" omitted 
by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 15th October, <year>1956</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1701285</tid>
<number>15</number>Postponement of payments and registration of transfers pending 
the making of a vesting order. Where the Bank contemplates making an 
order under this Act to vest a Government security in any person, the 
Bank may suspend payment of interest on or the maturity value of the 
security or postpone the making of any order under section 11 or the 
registration of any transfer of the security until the vesting order 
has been made.


</article>



<article><tid>707392</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power of Bank to require bonds.
<section><tid>940010</tid>
<number>1</number>Before making any order  
which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank may require the 
person in whose favour the order is to be made to execute a bond with 
one or more sureties in such form as may be prescribed or to furnish 
security not exceeding twice the value of the subject- matter of the 
order, to be held at the disposal of the Bank, to pay to the Bank or 
any person to whom the Bank may assign the bond or security in 
furtherance of sub- section (2) the amount thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1325139</tid>
<number>2</number>A Court before which a claim in respect of the subject- 
matter of any such order is established may order the bond or 
security to be assigned to the successful claimant who shall thereupon 
be entitled to enforce the bond or realise the security to the extent 
of such claim.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1482417</tid>
<number>17</number>Publication of notices in Official Gazette. Any notice 
required to be given by the Bank under this Act may be served by post, 
but every such notice shall also be published by the Bank in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ the 
Gazette of India or the Official Gazette of the State, according as 
the notice relates to a security, issued by the Central Government or 
a State Government], and on such publication shall be deemed to have 
been delivered to all persons for whom it is intended.


</article>



<article><tid>771957</tid>
<number>18</number>Scope of vesting order. An order made by the Bank under this 
Act may confer the full title to a Government security or may confer a 
title only to the accrued and accruing interest on the security 
pending a further order vesting the full title.


</article>



<article><tid>995192</tid>
<number>19</number>Legal effect of orders made by the Bank. No recognition by the 
Bank of a person as the holder of a Government security, and no order 
made by the Bank under this Act shall be called in question by any 
Court so far as such recognition or order affects the relations of 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Government] or the Bank with the person recognised by the Bank 
as the holder of a Government security or with any person claiming an 
interest in such security: and any such recognition by the Bank of any 
person or any order by the Bank vesting a Government security in any 
person shall operate to confer on that person a title to the security 
subject only to a personal

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 7, for" the Official Gazette" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for" the Central Government" (w. e. f. 1st  
  April, <year>1949</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

liability to the rightful owner of the security for money had and 
received on his account.



</article>



<article><tid>1944143</tid>
<number> 20</number> Stay of proceedings on order of Court. Where the Bank 
contemplates making with reference to any Government security any 
order which it is empowered to make under this Act, and before the 
order is made the Bank receives from a Court in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] an order to 
stay the making of such order, the Bank shall either-
<section><tid>1804678</tid>
<number>a</number>hold the security together with any interest unpaid or 
accruing thereon until the further orders of the Court are 
received, or

</section>

<section><tid>1655621</tid>
<number>b</number>apply to the Court to have the security transferred to 
the official Trustees appointed for the State in which such 
Court is situated, pending the disposal of the proceedings 
before the Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>753076</tid>
<number>21</number>Cancellation by the Bank of vesting proceedings. Where the 
Bank contemplates making an order under this Act vesting a Government 
security in any person the Bank may, at any time before the order is 
made, cancel any proceedings already taken for that purpose and may, 
on such cancellation, proceed anew to the making of such order.


</article>



<article><tid>622327</tid>
<number>22</number>Discharge in respect of interest on Government securities. 
Save as otherwise expressly provided in the terms of a Government 
security, no person shall be entitled to claim interest on such 
security in respect of any period which has elapsed after the earliest 
date on which demand could have been made for the payment of the 
amount due on such security.


</article>



<article><tid>593894</tid>
<number>23</number>Discharge in respect of bearer bonds. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Government] shall 
be discharged from all liability on a bearer bond or on any interest 
coupon of such a bond on payment to the holder of such bond or coupon 
on presentation on or after the date when it becomes due of the amount 
expressed therein, unless before such payment an order of a Court in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ India] has been served on <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Government] restraining it from 
making payment.


</article>



<article><tid>1509234</tid>
<number>24</number>Period of limitation of Central Government' s liability in 
respect of interest. Where no shorter period of limitation is fixed by 
any law for the time being in force, the liability of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the 
Government] in respect

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 10, for" a Part A State or a Part C 
State" (w. e. f. 15th October, <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for The Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 11, for the States" (w. e. f. 15th  
  October, <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 6 of' <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April,. <year>1949</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

of any interest payment due on a Government security shall terminate 
on the expiry of six years from the date on which the amount due by 
way of interest became payable.



</article>



<article><tid>516159</tid>
<number>25</number>Inspection of documents. No person shall be entitled to 
inspect, or to receive information derived from any Government 
security in the possession or custody of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] or from any 
book, register, or other document kept or maintained by or on behalf 
of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government] in relation to Government securities or any 
Government security, save in such circumstances and manner and subject 
to such conditions as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1004179</tid>
<number>26</number>The Bank and its Officers to be deemed public officers. For 
the purposes of section 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of  
  <year>1872</year>), the provisions of Part IV of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, 
 (5 of <year>1908</year>), relating to suits by or against public officers in their 
official capacity, and the provisions of rule 27 of Order V, and rule 
 52 of Order XXI of the said Code, the Bank and any officer of the Bank 
acting in his capacity as such shall be deemed to be a public officer.


</article>



<article><tid>1545759</tid>
<number> 27</number> Penalty.
<section><tid>323434</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person, for the purpose of obtaining for  
himself or for any other person any title to a Government security, 
makes to any authority under this Act in any application made under 
this Act or in the course of any inquiry undertaken in pursuance of 
this Act any statement which is false and which he either knows to be 
false or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>761671</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court shall take cognisance of any offence under sub- 
section (1) except on the complaint of the Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1760677</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1632479</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, subject  
to the condition of previous publication, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>537059</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power such rules may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1527042</tid>
<number>a</number>the forms in which Government securities may be issued;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For the Public Debt (Central Government) Rules, <year>1946</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1946</year>, Pt. I, p. 575.

For the Public Debt (Compensation Bonds) Rules, <year>1954</year> see Gazette 
of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. II, s. 3, p. 2060.

For the Public Debt (Annuity Certificates) Rules, <year>1954</year>, see, 
ibid., p. 2148.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>311961</tid>
<number>b</number>the form of the obligations referred to in clause (iv) 
of sub- clause (a) of clause (2) of section 2;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>448839</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions subject to which Government securities 
may be issued to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rulers of former Indian States];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866343</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which different forms of Government 
securities may be transferred;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1227569</tid>
<number>e</number>the holding of Government securities in the form of 
stock by the holders of offices other than public offices, 
and the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
Government securities so held may be transferred;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>779245</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which payment of interest in respect of 
Government securities is to be made and acknowledged;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>115944</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions governing the grant of duplicate, 
renewed, converted, consolidated and sub- divided Government 
securities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344390</tid>
<number>h</number>the fees to be paid in respect of the issue of 
duplicate Government securities and of the renewal, 
conversion, consolidation and sub- division of Government 
securities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1602690</tid>
<number>i</number>the form in which receipt of a Government security 
delivered for discharge, renewal, conversion, consolidation 
or sub- division is to be acknowledged;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1241145</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner of attestation of documents relating to 
Government securities in the form of stock;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921192</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which any document relating to a 
Government security or any endorsement on a promissory note 
issued by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Government] may, on the demand of a person 
who from any cause is unable to write, be executed on his 
behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>291192</tid>
<number>l</number>the form of the bonds referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 16.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>888575</tid>
<number>m</number>the circumstance and the manner in which and the condi- 
tions subject to which inspection of Government securities, 
books, registers and other documents may be allowed or 
information therefrom may be given under section 25;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1656363</tid>
<number>n</number>the procedure to be followed in making vesting orders;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 12, for" rulers of Part B States" 
 (w. e. f. 15th October, <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 6 of <year>1949</year>, s. 6, for" the Central Government" 
 (w. e. f. 1st April, <year>1949</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>873958</tid>
<number>o</number>the authority by whom the certificate referred to in 
the proviso to section 7 is to be granted and the manner of 
making the inquiry therein mentioned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1435815</tid>
<number>p</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the form in which and the persons in whose favour 
nominations may be made under section 9B, the manner in which 
and the conditions and restrictions subject to which such 
nominations may be made, the registration, variation or can- 
cellation of such nominations and the fees that may be levied 
for such registration, variation or cancellation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>341595</tid>
<number>q</number>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the 
purposes of sub- section (4) of section 9B.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>355683</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1396800</tid>
<number>29</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Certain laws not to apply to Government securities. The 
Indian securities Act, <year>1920</year> (10 of <year>1920</year>), and any law corresponding to 
that law in force in any Part B State immediately before the commence- 
ment of the Public Debt (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year> (57 of <year>1956</year>), shall 
cease to apply to Government securities to which this Act applies and 
to all matters for which provision is made by this Act:
Provided that any such corresponding law shall continue to apply 
to or in relation to any securities created and issued by the 
Government of Hyderabad, Saurashtra or Travancore- Cochin on or before 
the 31st day of March, <year>1953</year>, for such period not exceeding one year 
from the commencement of the Public Debt (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year> (57 of  
  <year>1956</year>), as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify.]



</article>



<article><tid>79916</tid>
<number>30</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Construction of reference to laws not in force before 1st 
April, <year>1951</year> in Part B States. Any reference in this Act to any law 
which did not extend to any Part B State or any part of such State 
before the commencement of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1959</year>. s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1960</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1972</year>. s. 4, sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 13, ibid.. for the original s. 29 (w. e. f. 15- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 14, ibid. (w, e. f. 15- 10- <year>1956</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

the Part B States (Laws) Act, <year>1951</year> (3 of <year>1951</year>), shall wherever neces- 
sary, be construed as including a reference to the corresponding law, 
if any, in force in that State, or, as the case may be, any part 
thereof, before the said date.]



</article>



<article><tid>1496748</tid>
<number>31</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Construction of references to laws not in force in jammu and 
Kashmir. Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in 
the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, wherever necessary, be construed 
as including a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in 
that State.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1972</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1972</year>),

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>