<act><title>


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006</title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Assam Rifles Act, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall come into 
force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  “active 
duty”, in relation to a person subject to this Act, means any duty as a member 
of the Force during the period in which such person is attached to, or forms 
part of, a unit of the Force—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  which 
is engaged in operations against an enemy or an insurgent or a terrorist or any 
person in arms against the Union, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  which 
is operating at a picket or engaged on patrol or other guard duty along the 
borders of India,
 
                   and 
includes duty by such person during any period declared by the Central 
Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, as a period of active duty 
with reference to any area in which or under any provision of this Act or for 
the purposes of any other law for the time being in force, any person or class 
of persons subject to this Act may be serving;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  “Assam Rifles 
Court” means a Court referred to in section 86;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  “battalion” 
means a unit of the Force constituted as battalion by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  “Chief Law 
Officer” and “Law Officer” mean, respectively, the Chief Law Officer and a Law 
Officer of the Force appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  “civil 
offence” means an offence which is triable by a criminal court;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  “civil 
prison” means any jail or place used for the detention of any criminal prisoner 
under the Prisons Act, 1894 (9 of 1894), or under any other law for the time 
being in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  “Commandant”, 
when used in any provision of this Act with reference to any unit of the Force, 
means the officer whose duty it is under the rules or regulations or in the 
absence of such rules or regulations, by custom of the service, to discharge 
with respect to that unit, the functions of a Commandant in regard to matters of 
the description referred to in that provision;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  “criminal 
court” means a court of ordinary criminal justice in any part of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  “deputation” 
means a period for which the services of a person belonging to any department of 
the Central Government are placed at the disposal of the Director-General;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  
“Director-General” and “Additional Director-General” mean, the Director-General 
and Additional Director-General of the Force appointed under sub-sections (1) 
and (2) of section 5, respectively;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  “enemy” 
includes all armed mutineers, armed rebels, armed rioters, pirates, terrorists 
and any person in arms against whom it is the duty of any person subject to this 
Act to take action;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>l</number>  “enrolled 
person” means an under-officer or other person enrolled under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  “Force” means 
the Assam Rifles;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>n</number>  “Force 
custody” means the arrest or confinement of a member of the Force according to 
rules and includes any military custody of such member under the Army Act, 1950 
(46 of 1950);
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>o</number>  
“Inspector-General” and “Deputy Inspector-General” mean, respectively, the 
Inspector-General and the Deputy Inspector-General of the Force appointed under 
sub-section (2) of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>p</number>  “member of 
the Force” means an officer, a subordinate officer, an under-officer or other 
enrolled person and includes the persons on deputation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>q</number>  
“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>r</number>  “offence” 
means any act or omission punishable under this Act and includes a civil 
offence;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>s</number>  “officer” 
means a person appointed or in pay as an officer of the Force; but does not 
include a subordinate officer or an under-officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>t</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>u</number>  “regulations” 
means the regulations made by the Central Government under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number>  “rule” means 
a rule made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>w</number>  “subordinate 
officer” means a person appointed or in pay as a Subedar-Major, a Subedar or a 
Naib Subedar of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>x</number>  “superior 
officer”, when used in relation to a person subject to this Act, means—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  any 
member of the Force or a person on deputation to whose command such person is 
for the time being subject in accordance with the rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  any 
officer of higher rank or class or of a higher grade in the same class,
 
              and includes 
when such person is not an officer, a subordinate officer or an under-officer of 
higher rank, class or grade;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>y</number>  “terrorist” 
means any person who, with intent to overawe the Government as by law 
established or to strike terror in the people or any section of the people or to 
alienate any section of the people or to adversely affect the harmony amongst 
different sections of the people, does any act or thing by using bombs, dynamite 
or other explosive substances or inflammable substances or fire-arms or other 
lethal weapons or poisons or noxious gases or other chemicals or any other 
substances (whether biological or otherwise) of a hazardous nature in such a 
manner, as to cause or is likely to cause death of, or injury to, any person or 
persons, or damage to, or destruction of, property or disruption of any supplies 
or services essential to the life of the community;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>z</number>  
“under-officer” means a Warrant Officer, Havildar, Naik and Lance Naik of the 
Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>za</number>  “unit” means 
any—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  
battalion; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  
regiment; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  
training institution; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iv</number>  Head 
Quarters of Deputy Inspector-General; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>v</number>  Head 
Quarters of Inspector-General; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>vi</number>  Head 
Quarters of Director-General,
 
of the Force and includes 
any other formation of the Force specified, by notification, by the Central 
Government.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Penal Code shall have 
the meanings assigned to them in that Code (45 of 1860).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In this Act, reference 
to any law not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall be construed as 
references to the corresponding law in force in that State.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Persons subject to this 
Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
following persons (whether on deputation or otherwise employed) shall be subject 
to this Act, wherever they may be, namely:—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  officers and subordinate officers; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  under-officers and other persons enrolled under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Members of the Force in 
existence at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been appointed 
or, as the case may be, enrolled as such under this Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), any person who is employed in the Force on 
deputation from the regular Army as defined under clause (xxi) of section 3 of 
the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950) shall not be subject to this Act and shall, 
during the period of such deputation, be deemed to be subject to the Army Act, 
1950 (46 of 1950):
 Provided that such person in 
regard to his duties and discipline shall be deemed to be under the command of 
the member of the Force under whose command such person for the time being is 
placed:
 Provided further that, in case of 
such person, for the purposes of his duties and discipline, the expression 
“active duty” defined in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 2 shall be 
deemed to be the “active service” as defined in clause (i) of section 3 of the 
Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950) for taking any action against him under the 
provisions of the said Army Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any person who is not subject 
to this Act is posted for any service with the members of the Force or engaged 
to accompany with or to provide any service in any manner to the members of the 
Force in such—
 <subsection>         
<number>i</number>  camp;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  line of march;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>iii</number>  frontier post;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>iv</number>  active duty; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>v</number>  counter insurgency operations,
 as may be specified, by 
notification, by the Central Government in this behalf shall be deemed to be a 
member of the Force, till he is so posted or engaged in such corresponding rank 
as may be determined, by notification, by the Central Government for the 
purposes of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Every person subject 
to this Act shall remain so subject until retired, discharged, released, removed 
or dismissed from the Force in accordance with the provisions of this Act and 
the rules.</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Constitution of 
Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be an armed force of the Union called the Assam Rifles for ensuring 
the security of the borders of India, to carry out counter insurgency operations 
in the specified areas and to act in aid of civil authorities for the 
maintenance of law and order and the matters connected therewith.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Force shall be reconstituted in such manner as may 
be prescribed and the conditions of service of the members of the Force shall be 
such as may be prescribed.


</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Control, direction, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
general superintendence, direction and control of the Force shall vest in, and 
be exercised by, the Central Government and subject thereto and to the 
provisions of this Act and the rules and regulations, the command and 
supervision of the Force shall vest in an officer to be appointed by the Central 
Government as the Director-General of the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director-General 
shall, in the discharge of his duties under this Act, be assisted by such number 
of Additional Director-General, Inspectors-General, Deputy Inspectors-General, 
Commandants and other officers as may be appointed by the Central Government.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Enrolment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The persons to be enrolled to the Force, the mode of enrolment and the procedure 
for enrolment shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act and the rules and regulations, every person who 
has, for a continuous period of three months, been in receipt of pay as a person 
enrolled under this Act and borne on the rolls of the Force shall be deemed to 
have been duly enrolled.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person who is not a 
citizen of India shall, except by the consent of the Central Government 
signified in writing, be enrolled in the Force.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Liability for 
service outside India.—Every 
member of the Force shall be liable to serve in any part of India as well as 
outside India.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Resignation and 
withdrawal from the post.—No 
member of the Force shall be at liberty—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  to resign his 
appointment during the term of his engagement; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  to withdraw 
himself from all or any of the duties of his appointment,
 
except with the previous 
permission in writing of the prescribed authority.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>9</number> Tenure of service under the 
Act.—Every person 
subject to this Act shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
President.</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Termination of 
service by Central Government.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act and the rules and regulations, the Central 
Government may dismiss or remove from the service any person subject to this 
Act.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Dismissal, removal 
or reduction by Director-General and by other officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director-General, Additional Director-General or any Inspector-General may 
dismiss or remove from service or reduce to a lower grade or rank or the ranks 
any person subject to this Act other than an officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An officer not below 
the rank of Deputy Inspector-General may dismiss or remove from the service any 
person under his command other than an officer or a subordinate officer of such 
rank or the ranks as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any such officer as is 
mentioned in sub-section (2) may reduce to a lower grade or rank or the ranks 
any person under his command except an officer or a subordinate officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The exercise of any 
power under this section shall be subject to the provisions of this Act and the 
rules and regulations.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Certificate of 
termination of service.—A 
subordinate officer or an under-officer or other enrolled person who is retired, 
discharged, released, removed or dismissed from service shall be furnished by 
the officer, to whose command he is subject, with a certificate in the language 
which is the mother-tongue of such person and also in Hindi and English language 
setting forth—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the authority 
terminating his service;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the cause for 
such termination; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the full 
period of his service in the Force.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Restrictions on 
right to form association, freedom of speech, etc.— 

<section><number>1</number> No person subject to this Act shall, without the previous sanction in 
writing of the Central Government or of the prescribed authority,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  be a member 
of, or be associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political 
association or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political 
associations, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  be a member 
of, or be associated in any way with, any society, institution, association or 
organisation that is not recognised as part of the Force or is not of a purely 
social, recreational or religious nature; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  communicate 
with the press or publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other 
document except where such communication or publication is in the bona fide 
discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific 
character or is of a prescribed nature.
 
Explanation.—If 
any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or 
organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under 
clause (b) of this sub-section, the decision of the Central Government thereon 
shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No person subject to 
this Act shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any 
demonstration organised by any body or persons for any political purposes or for 
such other purposes as may be prescribed.


</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Authorised 
deduction only to be made from pay.—The 
pay of every person subject to this Act due to him as such under any rules or 
regulations for the time being in force shall be paid without any deduction 
other than the deductions authorised by or under this Act or any other Act.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Remedy of aggrieved 
persons other than officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to this Act other than an officer who deems himself wronged 
by any officer or subordinate officer may complain to the officer under whose 
command or orders he is serving.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the officer 
complained against is the officer to whom any complaint should, under 
sub-section (1), be preferred, the aggrieved person may complain to such 
officer’s next superior officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every officer 
receiving any such complaint shall make as complete an investigation into it as 
may be possible for giving full redress to the complainant; or when necessary, 
refer the complaint to superior authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every such complaint 
shall be preferred in such manner as may, from time to time, be specified by the 
Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central Government 
may revise any decision by the Director-General under sub-section (2), but, 
subject thereto, the decision of the Director-General shall be final.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Remedy of aggrieved 
officers.—Any 
officer who deems himself wronged by his Commandant or any superior officer and 
who on due application made to his Commandant or such superior officer does not 
receive the redress to which he considers himself entitled, may complain to the 
Central Government in such manner as may, from time to time, be specified by the 
Director-General.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Immunity from 
attachment.—Neither 
the arms, clothes, equipment, accoutrements or necessaries of any person subject 
to this Act, nor any animal used by him for the discharge of his duty shall be 
seized, nor shall, the pay and allowances of any such person or any part 
thereof, be attached, by direction of any civil or revenue court or any revenue 
officer in satisfaction of any decree or order enforceable against him.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Immunity from 
arrest for debt.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person subject to this Act shall, so long as he belongs to the Force, be 
liable to be arrested for debt under any process issued by, or by the authority 
of, any civil or revenue court or revenue officer, except with the prior consent 
of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Judge of any such 
court or the said officer may examine into any complaint made by such person or 
his superior officer of the arrest of such person contrary to the provisions of 
this section and may, by warrant under his hand, discharge the person, and award 
reasonable costs to the complainant, who may recover those costs in like manner 
as he might have recovered costs awarded to him by a decree against the person 
obtaining the process.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the recovery of 
such costs no court-fee shall be payable by the complainant.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Immunity of persons 
attending Assam Rifles Court from arrest.— 

<section><number>1</number> No Presiding Officer or member of an Assam Rifles Court, no Law Officer, no 
party to any proceeding before an Assam Rifles Court, or his legal practitioner 
or agent and no witness acting in obedience to a summons to attend an Assam 
Rifles Court shall, while proceeding to, attending or returning from, an Assam 
Rifles Court, be liable to arrest under civil or revenue process.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such person is 
arrested under any such process, he may be discharged by order of the Assam 
Rifles Court.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Savings of rights 
and privileges under other laws.—The 
rights and privileges specified in the preceding section of this Chapter shall 
be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other rights and privileges 
conferred on persons subject to this Act generally by any other law for the time 
being in force.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Offences in 
relation to the enemy and punishable with death.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  shamefully 
abandons or delivers up any post, place or guard, committed to his charge or 
which it is his duty to defend; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  intentionally 
uses any means to compel or induce any person subject to this Act or to army, 
naval, air force law or any member of other armed forces to abstain from acting 
against the enemy or to discourage such person from acting against the enemy; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  in the 
presence of enemy, shamefully casts away his arms, ammunition, tools or 
equipment or misbehaves in such manner as to show cowardice; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  treacherously 
holds correspondence with, or communicates intelligence to, the enemy or any 
person in arms against the Union; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  directly or 
indirectly assists the enemy with money, arms, ammunition, stores or supplies or 
in any other manner whatsoever; or
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  in time of 
active operation against the enemy intentionally occasions a false alarm in 
action, camp, quarters or spreads or causes to be spread reports calculated to 
create alarm or despondency; or
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  in time of 
action leaves his Commandant or other superior officer or his post, guard, 
picket, patrol or party without being regularly relieved or without leave; or
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  having been 
captured by the enemy or made a prisoner of war, voluntarily serves with or aids 
the enemy; or
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  knowingly 
harbours or protects an enemy not being a prisoner; or
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  being a 
sentry in time of active operation against the enemy or alarm, sleeps upon his 
post or is intoxicated; or
 </section><section>
        <number>k</number>  knowingly 
does any act calculated to imperil the success of the Force or the army, naval, 
air forces of India or any other armed forces of the Central Government 
co-operating therewith or any part of such forces,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer death or such less punishment as is in 
this Act mentioned.


</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Offences in 
relation to the enemy and not punishable with death.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  is taken 
prisoner or captured by the enemy, by want of due precaution or through 
disobedience of orders, or wilful neglect of duty, or having been taken prisoner 
or so captured fails to rejoin his service when able to do so; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  without due 
authority holds correspondence with, or communicates intelligence to, the enemy 
or any person in league with the enemy or having come by the knowledge of any 
such correspondence or communication, wilfully omits to discover it immediately 
to his Commandant or other superior officer,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to fourteen years or such less punishment as in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>23</number> Offences punishable more 
severely on active duty than at other times.—Any person subject to this Act 
who commits any of the following offences, that is to say,—
 <section>        
<number>a</number>  forces a safeguard or forces or uses criminal force to a sentry; 
or
 </section><section>        
<number>b</number>  breaks into any house or other place in search of plunder; 
or
 </section><section>        
<number>c</number>  being a sentry, sleeps upon his post or is intoxicated; or
 </section><section>        
<number>d</number>  without orders from his superior officer, leaves his guard, picket, 
patrol or posts; or
 </section><section>        
<number>e</number>  intentionally or through neglect occasions a false alarm in camp or 
quarters, or spreads or causes to be spread reports calculated to create 
unnecessary alarm or despondency; or
 </section><section>         
<number>f</number>  makes known the parole, watchword or countersign to any person not 
entitled to receive it; or
 </section><section>        
<number>g</number>  knowingly gives a parole, watchword or countersign different from what 
he received, 
 shall, on conviction by an Assam 
Rifles Court,
 <subsection>             
<number>A</number>  if he commits any such offence when on active duty, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>B</number>  if he commits any such offence when not on active duty, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Mutiny.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  begins, 
incites, causes or conspires with any other person to cause any mutiny in the 
Force or in the army, naval or air forces of India or any forces co-operating 
therewith; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  joins in any 
such mutiny; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  being present 
at any such mutiny, does not use his utmost endeavours to suppress the same; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  knowing or 
having reason to believe in the existence of any such mutiny, or of any 
intention to mutiny or of any such conspiracy, does not, without delay, give 
information thereof to his Commandant or other superior officer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  endeavours to 
seduce any person in the Force or in the army, naval or air forces of India or 
any forces cooperating therewith from his duty or allegiance to the Union,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer death or such less punishment as is in 
this Act mentioned.


</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Desertion and 
aiding desertion.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to this Act who deserts or attempts to desert the service 
shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  if he commits 
the offence when on active duty or when under orders for active duty, be liable 
to suffer death or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if he commits 
the offence under any other circumstances, be liable to suffer imprisonment for 
a term which may extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
this Act who knowingly harbours any such deserter shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person subject to 
this Act who, being cognizant of any desertion or attempt at desertion of a 
person subject to this Act, does not forthwith give notice to his own or some 
other superior officer, or take any steps in his power to cause such person to 
be apprehended, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Absence without 
leave.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  absents 
himself without leave; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  without 
sufficient cause, overstays leave granted to him; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  being on 
leave of absence and having received information from the appropriate authority 
that any battalion or part thereof or any other unit of the Force, to which he 
belongs, has been ordered on active duty, fails, without sufficient cause, to 
rejoin without delay; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  without 
sufficient cause, fails to appear at the time fixed at the parade or place 
appointed for exercise or duty; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  when on 
parade, or on the line of march, without sufficient cause or without leave from 
his superior officer, quits the parade or line of march; or
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  when in camp 
or elsewhere, is found beyond any limits fixed, or in any place prohibited, by 
any general, local or other order, without a pass or written leave from his 
superior officer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  without leave 
from his superior officer or without due cause, absents himself from any school 
when duly ordered to attend there,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Striking or 
threatening superior officers.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  uses criminal 
force to or assaults his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  uses 
threatening language to such officer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  uses 
insubordinate language to such officer,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court,—
 <subsection>
        <number>A</number>  if such 
officer is at the time in the execution of his office or, if the offence is 
committed on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>B</number>  in other 
cases, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years 
or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned:
 
Provided that in the case 
of an offence specified in clause (c), the imprisonment shall not exceed five 
years.
</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Disobedience to 
superior officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to this Act who disobeys, in such manner as to show a wilful 
defiance of authority, any lawful command given personally by his superior 
officer in the execution of his office whether the same is given orally, or in 
writing or by signal or otherwise, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles 
Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen 
years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
this Act who disobeys any lawful command given by his superior officer shall, on 
conviction by an Assam Rifles Court,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  if he commits 
such offence when on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  if he commits 
such offence when not on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.
</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>29</number> Insubordination and 
obstruction.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  being 
concerned in any quarrel, affray or disorder, refuses to obey any officer, 
though of inferior rank, who orders him into arrest, or uses criminal force to 
or assaults any such officer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  uses criminal 
force to, or assaults any person, whether subject to this Act or not, in whose 
custody he is lawfully placed, and whether he is or is not his superior officer; 
or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  resists an 
escort whose duty it is to apprehend him or to have him in charge; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  breaks out of 
barracks, camp or quarters; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  neglects to 
obey any general, local or other order; or
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  impedes the 
Force Police referred to in section 85 or any person lawfully acting on its 
behalf, or when called upon, refuses to assist in the execution of his duty a 
Force Police or any person lawfully acting on his behalf,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend, in the case of the offences specified in clauses (d) and (e), to two 
years, and in the case of the offences specified in the other clauses, to ten 
years, or in either case such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>30</number> Fraudulent 
enrolment.—Any 
person subject to this Act who knowingly attempts to get enrolled or enrolls any 
other person who does not fulfil the conditions enabling him to be enrolled, 
shall, on conviction by the Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this 
Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>31</number> False answers on 
enrolment.—Any 
person having become subject to this Act who is discovered to have made at the 
time of enrolment a wilfully false answer to any question set-forth in the 
prescribed form of enrolment which has been put to him by the enrolling officer 
before whom he appears for the purpose of being enrolled, shall, on conviction 
by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>32</number> Unbecoming conduct.—Any 
officer, subordinate officer or an under-officer who behaves in a manner 
unbecoming his position and the character expected of him shall, on conviction 
by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to be dismissed or to suffer such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>33</number> Certain forms of 
disgraceful conduct.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  is guilty of 
any disgraceful conduct of a cruel, indecent or unnatural kind; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  malingers, or 
feigns or produces disease or infirmity in himself or intentionally delays his 
cure or aggravates his disease or infirmity; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  with intent 
to render himself or any other person unfit for service, voluntarily causes hurt 
to himself or that person,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>34</number> Ill-treating a 
subordinate.—Any 
officer, subordinate officer or an under-officer who uses criminal force to or 
otherwise ill-treats any person subject to this Act, being his subordinate in 
rank or position, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to 
suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Intoxication.—Any 
person subject to this Act who is found in a state of intoxication whether on 
duty or not, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>36</number> Permitting escape 
of person in custody.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  when in 
command of guard, picket, patrol or post, releases without proper authority, 
whether wilfully or without reasonable excuse, any person committed to his 
charge, or refuses to receive any prisoner or person so committed, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  wilfully or 
without reasonable excuse allows to escape any person who is committed to his 
charge, or whom it is his duty to keep or guard,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable, if he has acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in this 
Act mentioned; and if he has not acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to two years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>37</number> Irregularity in 
connection with arrest or confinement.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  unnecessarily 
detains a person in arrest or confinement without bringing him to trial, or 
fails to bring his case before the proper authority for investigation; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  having 
committed a person to Force custody fails without reasonable cause to deliver at 
the time of such committal, or as soon as practicable, and in any case within 
forty-eight hours thereafter, to the officer or other person into whose custody 
the person arrested is committed, an account in writing signed by himself of the 
offence with which the person so committed is charged,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>38</number> Escape from 
custody.—Any 
person subject to this Act who, being in lawful custody, escapes or attempts to 
escape, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>39</number> Offences in respect 
of property.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  commits theft of any property belonging to the Government, or to any 
Force mess, band or institution, or to any person subject to this Act; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  dishonestly misappropriates or converts to his own use any such 
property; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  commits criminal breach of trust in respect of any such property; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  dishonestly receives or retains any such property in respect of which 
any of the offences under clauses (a), (b) and (c) has been committed, knowing 
or having reason to believe the commission of such offence; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  wilfully destroys or injures any property of the Government entrusted 
to him; or
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  does any other thing with intent to defraud, or to cause wrongful gain 
to one person or wrongful loss to another person,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>40</number> Extortion and 
corruption.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  commits 
extortion; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  without 
proper authority extracts from any person money, provisions or service,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>41</number> Making away with 
equipment.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  makes away 
with, or is concerned in making away with any arms, ammunition, equipment, 
instruments, tools, clothing or any other thing being the property of the 
Government issued to him for his use or entrusted to him; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  loses by 
neglect anything mentioned in clause (a); or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  sells, pawns, 
destroys or defaces any medal or decoration granted to him, 
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
extend, in the case of the offences specified in clause (a), to ten years, and 
in the case of the offences specified in the other clauses, to five years, or in 
either case such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>42</number> Injury to property.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  destroys or 
injures any property mentioned in clause (a) of section 41 or any property 
belonging to any Force mess, band or institution, or to any person subject to 
this Act; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  commits any 
act which causes damage to, or destruction of, any property of the Government by 
fire; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  kills, 
injures, makes away with, ill-treats or loses any animal entrusted to him,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable, if he has acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in this 
Act mentioned; and if he has acted without reasonable excuse, to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>43</number> False accusations.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  makes a false 
accusation against any person subject to this Act, knowing or having reason to 
believe such accusation to be false; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in making 
complaint against any person subject to this Act, makes any statement affecting 
the character of such person, knowing or having reason to believe such statement 
to be false, or knowingly and wilfully suppresses any material facts,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>44</number> Falsifying official 
document and false declarations.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  in any 
report, return, list, certificate, book or other document made or signed by him, 
or of the contents of which it is his duty to ascertain the accuracy, knowingly 
makes, or is privy to the making of, any false or fraudulent statement; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in any 
document of the description mentioned in clause (a), knowingly makes, or is 
privy to the making of, any omission, with intent to defraud; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  knowingly and 
with intent to injure any person or knowingly and with intent to defraud, 
suppresses, defaces, alters or makes away with any document which it is his duty 
to preserve or produce; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  where it is 
his official duty to make a declaration respecting any matter, knowingly makes a 
false declaration; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  obtains for 
himself, or for any other person, any pension, allowances or other advantage or 
privilege by a statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes 
to be false or does not believe to be true, or by making or using false entry in 
any book or record, or by making any document containing a false statement, or 
by omitting to make a true entry or document containing a true statement,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>45</number> Signing in blank 
and failure to report.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  when signing 
any document relating to pay, arms, ammunition, equipment, clothing, supplies or 
stores, or any property of the Government fraudulently leaves in blank any 
material part for which his signature is a voucher; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  refuses or by 
culpable neglect omits to make or send a report or return which it is his duty 
to make or send,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years or such less punishment as in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>46</number> Offences relating 
to Assam Rifles Court.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  being duly 
summoned or ordered to attend as a witness before an Assam Rifles Court, 
wilfully or without reasonable excuse, makes default in attending; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  refuses to 
take an oath or make an affirmation legally required by an Assam Rifles Court to 
be taken or made; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  refuses to 
produce or deliver any document in his power or control legally required by an 
Assam Rifles Court to be produced or delivered by him; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  refuses, when 
a witness, to answer any question which he is by law bound to answer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  is guilty of 
contempt of the Assam Rifles Court by using insulting or threatening language, 
or by causing any interruption or disturbance in the proceedings of such Court,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>47</number> False evidence.—Any 
person subject to this Act who, having been duly sworn or affirmed before any 
Assam Rifles Court or other court competent under this Act to administer an oath 
or affirmation, makes any statement which is false, and which he either knows or 
believes to be false or does not believe to be true, shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>48</number> Unlawful detention 
of pay.—Any 
officer, subordinate officer or an under-officer who, having received the pay of 
a person subject to this Act, unlawfully detains or refuses to pay the same when 
due, shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>49</number> Violation of good 
order and discipline.—Any 
person subject to this Act who is guilty of any act or omission which, though 
not specified in this Act, is prejudicial to good order and discipline of the 
Force shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less punishment 
as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>50</number> Miscellaneous 
offences.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that is to 
say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  being in 
command at any post or on the march, and receiving a complaint that anyone under 
his command has beaten or otherwise mal-treated or oppressed any person, or has 
disturbed any fair or market, or committed any riot or trespass, fails to have 
due reparation made to the injured person or to report the case to the proper 
authority; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  by defiling 
any place of worship, or otherwise, intentionally insults the religion, or 
wounds the religious feelings of any person; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  attempts to 
commit suicide, and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of such 
offence; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  being below 
the rank of subordinate officer, when off duty, appears without proper 
authority, in or about camp, or when going to, or returning from, any town or 
bazaar, carrying a rifle, sword or other offensive weapons; or
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  directly or 
indirectly accepts or obtains, or agrees to accept, or attempts to obtain, for 
himself or for any other person, any gratification as a motive or reward for 
procuring the enrolment of any person, or leave of absence, promotion or any 
other advantage or indulgence for any person in the service; or
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  commits any 
offence against the property or person of any inhabitant of, or resident in, the 
country in which he is serving,
 
shall, on conviction by an 
Assam Rifles Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>51</number> Attempt.—Any 
person subject to this Act who attempts to commit any of the offences specified 
in sections 21 to 50 (both inclusive) and in such attempt does any act towards 
the commission of the offence shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, 
where no express provision is made by this Act for the punishment of such 
attempt, be liable,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if the 
offence attempted to be committed is punishable with death, to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  if the 
offence attempted to be committed is punishable with imprisonment to suffer 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one-half of the longest term 
provided for that offence or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>52</number> Abetment of 
offences that have been committed.—Any 
person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
specified in sections 21 to 50 (both inclusive) shall, on conviction by an Assam 
Rifles Court, if the Act abetted is committed in consequence of the abetment and 
no express provision is made by this Act for the punishment of such abetment, be 
liable to suffer the punishment provided for that offence or such less 
punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>53</number> Abetment of 
offences punishable with death and not committed.—Any 
person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
punishable with death under sections 21, 24 and clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of 
section 25 shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, if that offence be not 
committed in consequence of the abetment, and no express provision is made by 
this Act for the punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in 
this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>54</number> Abetment of 
offences punishable with imprisonment and not committed.—Any 
person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
specified in sections 21 to 50 (both inclusive) and punishable with imprisonment 
shall, on conviction by an Assam Rifles Court, if that offence, be not committed 
in consequence of the abetment, and no express provision is made by this Act for 
the punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to one-half of the longest term provided for that offence or 
such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>55</number> Civil offences.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 56, any person subject to this Act who at any place 
in, or beyond, India commits any civil offence shall be deemed to be guilty of 
an offence against this Act and, if charged therewith under this section, shall 
be liable to be tried by an Assam Rifles Court and, on conviction, be punishable 
as follows, that is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if the 
offence is one which would be punishable under any law in force in India with 
death, he shall be liable to suffer any punishment assigned for the offence, by 
the aforesaid law and such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in any other 
case, he shall be liable to suffer any punishment assigned for the offence by 
the law in force in India, or imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven 
years, or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>56</number> Civil offences not 
triable by an Assam Rifles Court.—A 
person subject to this Act who commits an offence of murder or of culpable 
homicide not amounting to murder against, or of rape in relation to, a person 
not subject to this Act shall not be deemed to be guilty of an offence against 
this Act and shall not be tried by an Assam Rifles Court, unless he commits any 
of the said offences,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  while on 
active duty; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  at any place 
outside India; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  at any place 
specified by the Central Government, by notification in this behalf.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>57</number> Punishment 
awardable by Assam Rifles Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Punishments may be inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons subject 
to this Act and convicted by the Assam Rifles Courts, according to the scale 
following, that is to say,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  death;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  imprisonment 
which may be for the term of life or any other lesser term but excluding 
imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months in Force custody;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  dismissal 
from the service;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  compulsory 
retirement from service;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  imprisonment 
for a term not exceeding three months in Force custody except in case of 
officers and subordinate officers;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  reduction to 
the ranks or to a lower rank or grade or place in the list of their rank in the 
case of an under-officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority of rank and forfeiture of all or any part of the service for the 
purpose of promotion;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  forfeiture of 
service for the purpose of increased pay, pension or any other prescribed 
purpose;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  fine;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand except in the case of persons below the rank of an 
under-officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  forfeiture of 
pay and allowances for a period not exceeding three months for an offence 
committed on active duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>l</number>  forfeiture 
in the case of person sentenced to dismissal from the service of all arrears of 
pay and allowances and other public money due to him at the time of such 
dismissal;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  stoppage of 
pay and allowances until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence for 
which he is convicted is made good.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the 
punishments specified in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be inferior in 
degree to every punishment preceding it in the above scale.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>58</number> Alternative 
punishments awardable by Assam Rifles Courts.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, an Assam Rifles Court may, on convicting a person 
subject to this Act of any of the offences specified in sections 21 to 54 (both 
inclusive) award either the particular punishment with which the offence is 
stated in the said sections to be punishable or, in lieu thereof, any of the 
punishments lower in the scale set out in section 57 regard being had to the 
nature and degree of the offence.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>59</number> Combination of 
punishments.—A 
sentence of an Assam Rifles Court may award in addition to, or without any one 
other punishment, the punishment specified in clause (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 57, and any one more of the punishments specified in clauses (f) to (m) 
(both inclusive) of that sub-section.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>60</number> Retention in the Force of a 
person convicted on active duty.—When on active duty, any enrolled 
person has been sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court to dismissal or to 
imprisonment whether combined with dismissal or not, the prescribed officer may 
direct that such person may be retained to serve in the ranks, and such service 
shall be reckoned as part of his term of imprisonment, if 
any.</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>61</number> Punishments 
otherwise than by Assam Rifles Courts.—Punishments 
may also be inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons subject to 
this Act without the intervention of an Assam Rifles Court in the manner stated 
in sections 62, 64, 65 and 66.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>62</number> Minor punishments.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 63, a Commandant or such other officer as is, with 
the consent of the Central Government, specified by the Director-General may, in 
the prescribed manner, proceed against a person subject to this Act, otherwise 
than as an officer or a subordinate officer or a Warrant Officer, who is charged 
with an offence under this Act and award such person to the extent prescribed, 
one or more of the following punishments, that is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  imprisonment 
in Force custody up to twenty-eight days;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  detention up 
to twenty-eight days;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  confinement 
to the lines up to twenty-eight days;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  extra guards 
or duties;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  deprivation 
of any special position or special emoluments or any acting rank or reduction to 
a lower grade of pay;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  forfeiture 
of good service and good conduct pay;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  fine up to 
fourteen days’ pay in any one month;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  deductions 
from his pay and allowances of any sum required to make good such compensation 
for any expense, loss, damage or destruction caused by him to the Central 
Government, or any building or property as may be awarded by his Commandant.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>63</number> Limit of 
punishments under section 62.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of an award of two or more of the punishments specified in clauses 

<subsection><number>a</number>, (b), (c) and (d) of section 62, the punishments specified in clause (c) or 
clause (d) shall take effect only at the end of the punishment specified in 
clause (a) or clause (b).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When two or more of 
the punishments specified in the said clauses (a), (b) and (c) are awarded to a 
person conjointly, or when already undergoing one or more of the said 
punishments, the whole extent of the punishments shall not exceed in the 
aggregate forty-two days.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The punishments 
specified in the said clauses (a), (b) and (c) shall not be awarded to any 
person who is of the rank of an under-officer or was at the time of committing 
the offence for which he is punished, of such rank.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The punishment 
specified in clause (g) of section 62 shall not be awarded to any person below 
the rank of an under-officer.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>64</number> Punishment of 
officers below the rank of Deputy Commandant, subordinate officers and Warrant 
Officer by Deputy Inspectors-General and others.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An officer not below the rank of the Deputy Inspector-General or such other 
officer as is, with the consent of the Central Government, specified by the 
Director-General may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against an officer below 
the rank of a Deputy Commandant and of any rank of subordinate officer and of 
the rank of Warrant Officer who is charged with an offence under this Act and 
award one or more of the following punishments, that is say,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority, or in the case of any of them whose promotion depends upon the length 
of service, forfeiture of service for the purpose of promotion for a period not 
exceeding twelve months, but subject to the right of the accused previous to the 
award to elect to be tried by an Assam Rifles Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  stoppage of 
pay and allowances until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence of 
which he is convicted is made good.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In every case in which 
punishment has been awarded under sub-section (1), certified true copies of the 
proceedings shall be forwarded, in the prescribed manner, by the officer 
awarding the punishment to the prescribed superior authority who may, if the 
punishment awarded, appears to him to be illegal, unjust or excessive, cancel, 
vary or remit the punishment and make such other direction as may be appropriate 
in the circumstances of the case.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>65</number> Punishment of 
officers below the rank of a Commandant, subordinate officers and Warrant 
Officer by the Inspectors-General and others.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An officer not below the rank of the Inspector-General or such other officer as 
is, with the consent of the Central Government, specified by the 
Director-General may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against an officer below 
the rank of a Commandant and any subordinate officer and a Warrant Officer who 
is charged with an offence under this Act and award one or more of the following 
punishments, that is to say,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority, or in the case of any of them whose promotion depends upon the length 
of service, forfeiture of service for the purpose of promotion for a period not 
exceeding twelve months, but subject to the right of the accused previous to the 
award to elect to be tried by an Assam Rifles Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  stoppage of 
pay and allowances until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence of 
which he is convicted is made good.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In every case in which 
punishment has been awarded under sub-section (1), certified true copies of the 
proceedings shall be forwarded, in the prescribed manner, by the officer 
awarding the punishment to the prescribed superior authority who may, if the 
punishment awarded appears to him to be illegal, unjust or excessive, cancel, 
vary or remit the punishment and make such other direction as may be appropriate 
in the circumstances of the case.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>66</number> Punishment of 
subordinate officers and Warrant Officer by Commandant, etc.—A 
Commandant or such other officer as is, with the consent of the Central 
Government, specified by the Director-General may, in the prescribed manner, 
proceed against any subordinate officer or a Warrant Officer who is charged with 
an offence under this Act and award one or more of the following punishments, 
that is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  stoppage of 
pay and allowances until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence of 
which he is convicted is made good:
 
Provided that the 
punishment mentioned under clause (a) shall only be awarded by an officer not 
below the rank of Commandant authorised by the Director-General to award such 
punishment.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>67</number> Collective fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever any weapon or part of a weapon, or ammunition, forming part of the 
equipment of a unit of the Force, is lost or stolen, an officer not below the 
rank of the Commandant of a battalion may, after making such inquiry as he 
thinks fit and subject to the rules and regulations, impose a collective fine 
upon the subordinate officers, under-officer and men of such unit, or upon so 
many of them as, in his judgment, should be held responsible for such loss or 
theft.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such fine shall be 
assessed as a percentage on the pay of the individuals on whom it falls.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>68</number> Deductions from pay 
and allowances of officers.—The 
following penal deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of an 
officer, that is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  all pay and 
allowances due to an officer for every day he absents himself without leave, 
unless a satisfactory explanation has been given to his commanding officer and 
has been approved by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  all pay and 
allowances for every day while he is in custody or under suspension from duty on 
a charge for an offence for which he is afterwards convicted by a criminal court 
or an Assam Rifles Court or by an officer exercising authority under section 64 
or section 65;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  any sum 
required to make good the pay of any person subject to this Act which he has 
unlawfully retained or unlawfully refused to pay;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  any sum 
required to make good compensation for any expenses, loss, damage or destruction 
occasioned by the commission of an offence as may be determined by an Assam 
Rifles Court by whom he is convicted of such offence, or by an officer 
exercising authority under section 64 or section 65;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  all pay and 
allowances ordered by an Assam Rifles Court to be forfeited or stopped;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  any sum 
required to pay a fine awarded by a criminal court or an Assam Rifles Court;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  any sum 
required to make good any loss, damage or destruction of public or regimental 
property which, after due investigation, appears to the Central Government to 
have been occasioned by the wrongful act or negligence on the part of the 
officer;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  all pay and 
allowances forfeited by order of the Central Government if the officer is found 
by a Court of inquiry constituted by the Director General in this behalf, to 
have deserted to the enemy, or while in enemy hands, to have served with, or 
under the orders of, the enemy, or in any manner to have aided the enemy, or to 
have allowed himself to be taken prisoner by the enemy through want of due 
precaution or through disobedience of orders or wilful neglect of duty, or 
having been taken prisoner by the enemy, to have failed to rejoin his service 
when it was possible to do so;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  any sum 
required by order of the Central Government to be paid for the maintenance of 
his wife or his legitimate or illegitimate child or towards the cost of any 
relief given by the said Government to the said wife or child.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>69</number> Deductions from pay 
and allowances of persons other than officers.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 72, the following penal deductions may be made from 
the pay and allowances of a person subject to this Act other than an officer, 
that is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  all pay and 
allowances for every day of absence either on desertion or without leave, or as 
a prisoner of war unless a satisfactory explanation has been given and accepted 
by his Commandant, and for every day of imprisonment awarded by a criminal 
court, an Assam Rifles Court or an officer exercising authority under section 
62;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  all pay and 
allowances for every day while he is in custody on a charge for an offence of 
which he is afterwards convicted by a criminal court or an Assam Rifles Court, 
or on a charge of absence without leave for which he is afterwards awarded 
imprisonment by an officer exercising authority under section 62;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  all pay and 
allowances for every day on which he is in hospital on account of sickness 
certified by the medical officer attending on him to have been caused by an 
offence under this Act committed by him;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  for every day 
on which he is in hospital on account of sickness certified by the medical 
officer attending on him to have been caused by his own misconduct or 
imprudence, such sum as may be specified by the order of the Central Government 
or such officer as may be specified by that Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  all pay and 
allowances ordered by an Assam Rifles Court or by an officer exercising 
authority under any of the sections 62, 64, 65 and 66 to be forfeited or 
stopped;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  all pay and 
allowances for every day between his being recovered from the enemy and his 
dismissal from the service in consequence of his conduct when being taken 
prisoner by, or while in the hands of the enemy;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  any sum 
required to make good such compensation for any expenses, loss, damage or 
destruction caused by him to the Central Government or to any building or 
property as may be awarded by his Commandant;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  any sum 
required to pay a fine awarded by a criminal court, an Assam Rifles Court or an 
officer exercising authority under any of the sections 62 and 67;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  any sum 
required by order of the Central Government or any prescribed officer to be paid 
for the maintenance of his wife or his legitimate or illegitimate child or 
towards the cost of any relief given by the said Government to the said wife or 
child.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>70</number> Computation of time 
of absence of custody.—For 
the purpose of clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of section 69,—
 </section><section>
        <number>a</number>  no person 
shall be treated as absent or in custody for a day unless the absence or custody 
has lasted, whether wholly in one day, or partly in one day and partly in 
another, for six consecutive hours or upwards;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  any absence 
or custody for less than a day may be reckoned as absence or custody for a day 
if such absence or custody prevented the absentee from fulfilling any duty which 
was thereby thrown upon some other person;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  absence or 
custody for twelve consecutive hours or upward may be reckoned as absence or 
custody for the whole of each day during any portion of which the person was 
absent or in custody;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  a period of 
absence or imprisonment, which commences before, and ends after, midnight may be 
reckoned as a day.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>71</number> Pay and allowances 
during trial.—In 
case of any person subject to this Act who is in custody or under suspension 
from duty on a charge for an offence, the prescribed officer may direct that the 
whole or any part of the pay and allowances of such person shall be withheld, 
pending the result of his trial on the charge against him, in order to give 
effect to the provisions of clause (b) of section 68 and section 69.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>72</number> Limit of certain 
deductions.—The 
total deductions from the pay and allowances of a person made under clauses (e), 
(g) to 
<section><number>i</number> of section 69 shall not, except where he is sentenced to dismissal or 
removal, exceed in any one month one-half of his pay and allowances of that 
month.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>73</number> Deduction from 
public money due to a person.—Any 
sum authorised by this Act to be deducted from the pay and allowances of any 
person may, without prejudice to any other mode of recovering the same, be 
deducted from any public money due to him other than a pension.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>74</number> Pay and allowances 
of prisoner of war during inquiry into his conduct.—Where 
the conduct of any person subject to this Act when being taken prisoner by, or 
while in the hands of the enemy, is to be inquired into under this Act or any 
other law, the Director-General or any officer authorised by him may order that 
the whole or any part of the pay and allowances of such person shall be withheld 
pending the result of such inquiry.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>75</number> Remission of 
deductions.—Any 
deduction from pay and allowances authorised by this Act may be remitted in such 
manner and to such extent and by such authority, as may, from time to time, be 
prescribed.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>76</number> Provision for 
dependents of prisoner of war from remitted deductions.—In 
the case of all persons subject to this Act, being prisoners of war, whose pay 
and allowances have been forfeited under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of section 69, but in 
respect of whom a remission has been made under section 75, it shall be lawful 
for proper provision to be made by the prescribed authorities out of such pay 
and allowances for any dependents of such persons, and any such remission shall 
in that case be deemed to apply only to the balance thereafter remaining of such 
pay and allowances.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>77</number> Provision for 
dependents of prisoner of war from his pay and allowances.—It 
shall be lawful for proper provision to be made by the prescribed authorities 
for any dependents of any person subject to this Act who is prisoner of war or 
is missing, out of his pay and allowances.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>78</number> Period during which 
a person is deemed to be a prisoner of war.—For 
the purposes of sections 76 and 77, a person shall be deemed to continue to be 
prisoner of war until the conclusion of any inquiry into his conduct such as is 
referred to in section 74 and if he is dismissed or removed from the service in 
consequence of such conduct, until the date of such dismissal or removal.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>79</number> Custody of 
offenders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to this Act who is charged with an offence may be taken into 
Force custody under the order of any superior officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), an officer may order into Force custody 
any other officer, though such other officer may be of a higher rank, engaged in 
a quarrel, affray or disorder.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>80</number> Duty of Commandant 
in regard to detention.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of every Commandant to take care that a person under his 
command when charged with an offence is not detained in custody for more than 
forty-eight hours after the committal of such person into custody is reported to 
him, without the charge being investigated, unless investigation within that 
period seems to him to be impracticable having regard to the public service.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The case of every 
person being detained in custody beyond a period of forty-eight hours, and 
reason thereof, shall be reported by the Commandant to the Deputy 
Inspector-General under whom he is serving or such other officer to whom an 
application may be made to convene an Assam Rifles Court for the trial of the 
person charged.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In reckoning the 
period of forty-eight hours specified in sub-section (1), Sundays and other 
public holidays shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Central Government may make rules providing for the 
manner in which and the period for which any person subject to this Act may be 
taken into and detained in Force custody, pending the trial by any competent 
authority for any offence committed by him.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>81</number> Interval between 
committal and trial.—In 
every case where any such person as is mentioned in section 79 and as not on 
active duty, remains in such custody for a longer period than eight days, 
without his trial by an Assam Rifles Court being ordered to be convened, a 
special report giving reasons for the delay shall be made by his Commandant in 
the manner prescribed, and a similar report shall be forwarded at intervals of 
every eight days until an Assam Rifles Court is convened or such person is 
released from custody.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>82</number> Arrest by civil 
authorities.—Whenever 
any person subject to this Act who is accused of an offence under this Act, is 
within the jurisdiction of any magistrate or police officer, such magistrate or 
police officer shall aid in the apprehension and delivery to Force custody of 
such person upon receipt of a written application to that effect signed by his 
Commandant or an officer authorised by the Commandant in that behalf.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>83</number> Capture of 
deserters.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever any person subject to this Act deserts, the Commandant of the unit to 
which he belongs, shall give information of the desertion to such civil 
authorities as, in his opinion, may be able to afford assistance towards the 
capture of the deserter; and such authorities shall thereupon take steps for the 
apprehension of the said deserter in like manner as if he were a person for 
whose apprehension a warrant had been issued by a magistrate and shall deliver 
the deserter, when apprehended, into Force custody.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any police officer may 
arrest without warrant any person reasonably believed to be subject to this Act, 
and to be a deserter or to be travelling without authority, and shall bring him 
without delay before the nearest magistrate, to be dealt with according to law.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>84</number> Inquiry into 
absence without leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any person subject to this Act has been absent from his duty without due 
authority for a period of thirty days, a court of inquiry shall, as soon as 
practicable, be assembled and such court shall, on oath or affirmation 
administered in the prescribed manner, inquire respecting the absence of the 
person, and the deficiency, if any, in the property of the Government entrusted 
to his care, or in any arms, ammunition, equipment, instruments, clothing or 
necessaries; and if satisfied of the fact of such absence without due authority 
or other sufficient cause, the court shall declare such absence and the period 
thereof and the said deficiency, if any, and the Commandant of the unit to which 
the person belongs shall make a record thereof in the prescribed manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person declared 
absent does not afterwards surrender or is not apprehended, he shall, for the 
purpose of this Act, be deemed to be a deserter.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>85</number> Force Police 
Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director-General or any prescribed officer may appoint persons (in this Act 
referred to as Force Police) for discharging the functions specified in 
sub-sections (2) and (3).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The duties of a person 
appointed under sub-section (1), are to take charge of persons confined for any 
offence, to preserve good order and discipline and to prevent breaches of the 
same by persons serving in, or attached to, the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 79, a person appointed under sub-section (1) may, 
at any time, arrest and detain for trial, any person subject to this Act who 
commits, or is charged with, an offence, and may also carry into effect any 
punishment to be inflicted in pursuance of a sentence awarded by an Assam Rifles 
Court or by an officer exercising authority under section 62 but shall not 
inflict any punishment on his own authority:
 
Provided that no officer 
shall be arrested or detained otherwise than on the order of another officer.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>86</number> Kinds of Assam 
Rifles Courts.—For 
the purposes of this Act there shall be three kinds of Assam Rifles Courts, that 
is to say,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  General Assam 
Rifles Courts;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  Petty Assam 
Rifles Courts; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  Summary Assam 
Rifles Courts.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>87</number> Power to convene a 
General Assam Rifles Court.—A 
General Assam Rifles Court may be convened by the Central Government or the 
Director-General or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant of the 
Director-General.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>88</number> Power to convene a 
Petty Assam Rifles Court.—A 
Petty Assam Rifles Court may be convened by an officer having power to convene a 
General Assam Rifles Court or by an officer empowered in this behalf by warrant 
of any such officer.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>89</number> Contents of 
warrants issued under sections 87 and 88.—A 
warrant issued under section 87 or section 88, may contain such restrictions, 
reservations or conditions as the officer issuing it may think fit.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>90</number> Composition of 
General Assam Rifles Court.—A 
General Assam Rifles Court shall consist of not less than five officers, each of 
whom has held the post of Assistant Commandant for not less than three whole 
years and of whom not less than four are of a rank not below that of a confirmed 
Assistant Commandant.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this section and section 91, “Assistant Commandant” includes any 
post of a higher rank and any post declared by the Central Government, by 
notification to be an equivalent post as also any post higher in rank than the 
post so declared.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>91</number> Composition of a 
Petty Assam Rifles Court.—A 
Petty Assam Rifles Court shall consist of not less than three officers, each of 
whom has held the post of Assistant Commandant for not less than two whole 
years.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>92</number> Summary Assam 
Rifles Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Summary Assam Rifles Court may be held by the Commandant of any unit of the 
Force and he alone shall constitute the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The proceedings shall 
be attended throughout by two other persons who shall be officers or subordinate 
officers or one of either, and who shall not as such, be sworn or affirmed.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>93</number> Dissolution of an 
Assam Rifles Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If an Assam Rifles Court after the commencement of a trial is reduced below the 
minimum number of officers required by this Act, it shall be dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on account of the 
illness of the Law Officer or of the accused before the finding, it is 
impossible to continue the trial, an Assam Rifles Court shall be dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officer who 
convened an Assam Rifles Court may dissolve the same if it appears to him that 
the exigencies of the service or necessities of discipline render it impossible 
or inexpedient to continue the said Assam Rifles Court.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an Assam Rifles 
Court is dissolved under this section, the accused may be tried again.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>94</number> Power of General 
Assam Rifles Court.—A 
General Assam Rifles Court shall have the power to try any person subject to 
this Act for any offence punishable thereunder and to pass any sentence 
authorised thereby.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>95</number> Power of a Petty 
Assam Rifles Court.—A 
Petty Assam Rifles Court shall have power to try any person subject to this Act 
other than an officer or a subordinate officer for any offence made punishable 
thereunder and to pass any sentence authorised by this Act other than a sentence 
of death or imprisonment for a term exceeding two years.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>96</number> Power of a Summary 
Assam Rifles Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), a Summary Assam Rifles Court may 
try any offence punishable under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When there is no grave 
reason for immediate action and reference can, without detriment to discipline, 
be made to the officer empowered to convene a Petty Assam Rifles Court for the 
trial of the alleged offender, an officer holding a Summary Assam Rifles Court 
shall not try without such reference any offence punishable under any of the 
sections 21, 24 and 55 or any offence against the officer holding the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A Summary Assam Rifles 
Court may try any person subject to this Act and under the command of the 
officer holding the Court, except an officer or a subordinate officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Summary Assam Rifles 
Court may pass any sentence which may be passed under this Act except the 
sentence of death or of imprisonment for a term exceeding the limit specified in 
sub-section (5).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The limit referred to 
in sub-section (4) shall be—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  one year, if 
the officer holding the Assam Rifles Court has held either the post of 
Commandant or a post declared by the Central Government, by notification, to be 
equivalent thereto for a period of not less than three years or holds a post of 
higher rank than either of the said posts; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  three months, 
in any other case.
</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>97</number> Prohibition of 
second trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any person subject to this Act has been acquitted or convicted of an 
offence by an Assam Rifles Court or by a criminal court or has been dealt with 
under section 62 or section 64 or section 65 or section 66, he shall not be 
liable to be tried again for the same offence by an Assam Rifles Court or dealt 
with under the said sections.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When any person, 
subject to this Act has been acquitted or convicted of an offence by an Assam 
Rifles Court or has been dealt with under section 62 or section 64 or section 65 
or section 66, he shall not be liable to be tried again by a criminal court for 
the same offence or on the same facts.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>98</number> Period of 
limitation for trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except as provided by sub-section (2), no trial by an Assam Rifles Court of any 
person subject to this Act for any offence shall be commenced after the 
expiration of a period of three years and such period shall commence—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  on the date 
of the offence; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  where the 
commission of the offence was not known to the person aggrieved by the offence 
or to the authority competent to initiate action, from the first day on which 
such offence comes to the knowledge of such person or authority, whichever is 
earlier; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  where it is 
not known by whom the offence was committed, from the first day on which the 
identity of the offender is known to the person aggrieved by the offence or to 
the authority competent to initiate action, whichever is earlier:
 
Provided that in computing 
any period under this section, the period during which the proceedings of 
investigation has been stayed by any court in such offence by injunction or 
order, the period of the continuance of the injunction or order, the day on 
which it was issued or made, and the day on which it was withdrawn, shall be 
excluded.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
sub-section (1) shall not apply to a trial for an offence of desertion or for 
any of the offences mentioned in section 24 or an offence under section 30.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In computation of the 
period of three years under sub-section (1), any time spent by such person in 
evading arrest after the commission of the offence, shall be excluded.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>99</number> Trial, etc., of 
offender who ceases to be subject to this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act had been committed by any person while subject 
to this Act and he had ceased to be so subject, he may be taken into and kept in 
Force custody and tried and punished for such offence as if he continued to be 
so subject.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such person shall 
be tried for an offence, unless his trial commences within a period of three 
years after he had ceased to be subject to this Act; and in computing such 
period, the time during which such person has avoided arrest by absconding or 
concealing himself or where the institution of the proceeding in respect of the 
offence has been stayed by an injunction or order, the period of the continuance 
of the injunction or order, the day on which it was issued or made, and the day 
on which it was withdrawn, shall be excluded:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall apply to the trial of any such person for an 
offence of desertion or for any of the offences mentioned in section 24 or shall 
affect the jurisdiction of a criminal court to try an offence triable by such 
court as well as by an Assam Rifles Court.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>100</number> Application of this Act 
during term of sentence.—
<section><number>1</number> When a person subject to this 
Act is sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court to imprisonment, this Act shall apply 
to him during the term of his sentence, though he is dismissed from the Force or 
has otherwise ceased to be subject to this Act, and he may be kept, removed, 
imprisoned and punished as if he continued to be subject to this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a person subject to this 
Act is sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court to death, this Act shall apply to him 
till the sentence is carried out.</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>101</number> Place of trial.—Any 
person subject to this Act who commits any offence against it may be tried and 
punished for such offence in any place whatever.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>102</number> Choice between 
criminal court and Assam Rifles Court.—When 
a criminal court and an Assam Rifles Court each have jurisdiction in respect of 
an offence, it shall be in the discretion of the Director-General, or the 
Inspector-General or the Deputy Inspector-General within whose command the 
accused person is serving or such other officer as may be prescribed, to decide 
before which court proceedings shall be instituted, and, if that officer, 
decides that they shall be instituted before an Assam Rifles Court, to direct 
that the accused person shall be detained in Force custody.


</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>103</number> Power of criminal 
court to require delivery of offender.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a criminal court having jurisdiction is of opinion that proceedings shall 
be instituted before itself in respect of any alleged offence, it may, by 
written notice, require the officer referred to in section 102 at his option, 
either to deliver over the offender to the nearest Magistrate to be proceeded 
against according to law, or to postpone proceedings, pending a reference to the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In every such case the 
said officer shall either deliver over the offender in compliance with the 
requisition, or shall forthwith refer the question as to the court before which 
the proceedings are to be instituted, for the determination of the Central 
Government whose order upon such reference shall be final.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>104</number> Presiding officer.—At 
every General Assam Rifles Court or Petty Assam Rifles Court, the senior member 
shall be the presiding officer.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>105</number> Law Officer.—Every 
General Assam Rifles Court shall, and every Petty Assam Rifles Court may, be 
attended by a Law Officer, or if no such officer is available, an officer 
approved by the Chief Law Officer or a Law Officer.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>106</number> Challenges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At all trials by a General Assam Rifles Court or by a Petty Assam Rifles Court, 
as soon as the Court is assembled, the names of the presiding officer and 
members shall be read over to the accused, who shall thereupon be asked whether 
he objects to being tried by any officer sitting on the court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the accused objects 
to such officer, his objection and also the reply thereto of the officer 
objected to, shall be heard and recorded, and the remaining officers of the 
court shall, in the absence of the challenged officer, decide on the objection.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the objection is 
allowed by one-half or more of the votes of the officers entitled to vote, the 
objection shall be allowed, and the member objected to shall retire, and his 
vacancy may be filled in the prescribed manner, by another officer subject to 
the same right of the accused to object.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When no challenge is 
made, or when a challenge has been made and disallowed, or the place of every 
officer successfully challenged has been filled by another officer to whom no 
objection is made or allowed, the court shall proceed with the trial.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>107</number> Oath of member, 
Law Officer and witness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An oath or affirmation in the prescribed manner shall be administered to every 
member of an Assam Rifles Court and to the Law Officer or, as the case may be, 
the officer approved under section 105 before the commencement of the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person giving 
evidence before an Assam Rifles Court shall be examined after being duly sworn 
or affirmed in the prescribed form.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of 
sub-section (2) shall not apply where the witness is a child under twelve years 
of age and the Assam Rifles Court is of opinion that though the witness 
understands the duty of speaking the truth, he does not understand the nature of 
an oath or affirmation.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>108</number> Voting by members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), every decision of an 
Assam Rifles Court shall be passed by a majority of votes; and where there is an 
equality of votes on either the finding or the sentence, the decision shall be 
in favour of the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No sentence of death 
shall be passed by a General Assam Rifles Court without the concurrence of at 
least two-thirds of the members of the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In matters, other than 
a challenge or the finding or sentence, the presiding officer shall have a 
casting vote.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>109</number> General rule as to 
evidence.—The 
Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) shall, subject to the provisions of this 
Act, apply to all proceedings before an Assam Rifles Court.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>110</number> Judicial notice.—An 
Assam Rifles Court may take judicial notice of any matter within the general 
knowledge of the members as officers of the Force.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>111</number> Summoning of 
witness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The convening officer, the presiding officer of an Assam Rifles Court or court 
of inquiry or the Law Officer or, as the case may be, the officer approved under 
section 105 or the Commandant of the accused person may, by summons under his 
hand, require the attendance, at a time and place to be mentioned in the 
summons, of any person either to give evidence or to produce any document or 
other thing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of a 
witness, who is subject to this Act, the summons shall be sent to his Commandant 
and such officer shall serve it upon him accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of any 
other witness, the summons shall be sent to the Magistrate within whose 
jurisdiction he may be, or resides, and such Magistrate shall give effect to the 
summons as if the witness were required in the court of such Magistrate.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>112</number> Documents exempted 
from production.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Nothing in section 111 shall be deemed to affect the operation of sections 123 
and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or to apply to any letter, 
postcard, telegram or other document in the custody of the postal or telegraph 
authorities.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any document in 
such custody is, in the opinion of any Chief Judicial Magistrate, Chief 
Metropolitan Magistrate, Court of Session or High Court, wanted for the purpose 
of any Assam Rifles Court, such Magistrate or Court may require the postal or 
telegraph authorities, as the case may be, to deliver such document to such 
person as such Magistrate, or Court may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any such document 
is, in the opinion of any other Magistrate or of any Commissioner of Police or 
District Superintendent of Police, wanted for any such purpose, he may require 
the postal or telegraph authorities, as the case may be, to cause such search to 
be made for, and to detain such document pending the orders of any such Chief 
Judicial Magistrate, Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or Court of Session or High 
Court.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>113</number> Commission for 
examination of witness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever, in the course of a trial by an Assam Rifles Court, it appears to the 
Court that the examination of a witness is necessary for the ends of justice, 
and that the attendance of such witness cannot be procured without an amount of 
delay, expense or inconvenience which, in the circumstances of the case, would 
be unreasonable, such court may address the Chief Law Officer in order that a 
commission to take the evidence of such witness may be issued.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Law Officer 
may then, if he thinks necessary, issue a commission to any Chief Judicial 
Magistrate or Judicial Magistrate of the first class, within the local limits of 
whose jurisdiction such witness resides, to take the evidence of such witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Judicial 
Magistrate or Judicial Magistrate of the first class to whom the commission is 
issued, or, if he is the Chief Judicial Magistrate, he or such Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class as he appoints in this behalf, shall summon the 
witness before him and shall take down his evidence in the same manner, and may 
for this purpose exercise the same powers, as in the trials of warrant-cases 
under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the witness 
resides in a tribal area or in any place outside India, the commission may be 
issued in the manner specified in sub-heading “B-Commissions for the 
examination of witnesses” of Chapter XXIII of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>114</number> Examination of 
witness on commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The prosecutor and the accused person in any case in which a commission is 
issued under section 113 may respectively forward any interrogatories in writing 
which the court may think relevant to the issue, and the Chief Judicial 
Magistrate or the Judicial Magistrate of the first class executing the 
commission shall examine the witness upon such interrogatories.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor and the 
accused person may appear before such Chief Judicial Magistrate or the Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class by counsel or, except in the case of an accused 
person in custody, in person, and may examine, cross-examine and re-examine, as 
the case may be, the said witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After a commission 
issued under section 113 has been duly executed, it shall be returned, together 
with the deposition of the witness examined thereunder to the Chief Law Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of a 
commission, and deposition returned under sub- section (3), the Chief Law 
Officer shall forward the same to the court at whose instance the commission was 
issued or, if such court has been dissolved, to any other court convened for the 
trial of the accused person and the commission, the return thereto and the 
deposition shall be open to inspection by the prosecutor and the accused person, 
and may, subject to all just exceptions, be read in evidence in the case by 
either the prosecutor or the accused, and shall form part of the proceedings of 
the court.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In every case in which 
a commission is issued under section 113, the trial may be adjourned for 
specified time reasonably sufficient for the execution and return of the 
commission.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>115</number> Conviction of 
offences not charged.—A 
person charged before an Assam Rifles Court—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  with 
desertion may be found guilty of attempting to desert or of being absent without 
leave;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  with 
attempting to desert may be found guilty of being absent without leave;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  with using 
criminal force may be found guilty of assault;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  with using 
threatening language may be found guilty of using insubordinate language;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  with any one 
of the offences specified in clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of section 39 may be 
found guilty of any other of these offences with which he might have been 
charged;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  with an 
offence punishable under section 55 may be found guilty of any other offence of 
which he might have been found guilty, if the provisions of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), were applicable;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  with any 
offence under this Act may, on failure of proof of an offence having been 
committed in circumstances involving a more severe punishment, be found guilty 
of the same offence as having been committed in circumstances involving a less 
severe punishment;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  with any 
offence under this Act may be found guilty of having attempted or abetted the 
commission of that offence, although the attempt or abetment is not separately 
charged.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>116</number> Presumption as to 
signatures.—In 
any proceeding under this Act, any application certificate, warrant, reply or 
other document purporting to be signed by an officer in the service of the 
Government shall, on production, be presumed to have been duly signed by the 
person by whom and in the character in which it purports to have been signed, 
until the contrary is shown.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>117</number> Enrolment paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any enrolment paper purporting to be signed by an enrolling officer shall, in 
proceedings under this Act, be evidence of the person enrolled having given the 
answers to questions which he is therein represented as having given.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The enrolment of such 
person may be proved by the production of the original or a copy of his 
enrolment paper purporting to be certified to be a true copy by the officer 
having the custody of enrolment paper.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>118</number> Presumption as to 
certain documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A letter, return or other document respecting the service of any person in, or 
the dismissal, removal or discharge of any person from, any unit of the Force, 
or respecting the circumstances of any person not having served in, or belonged 
to any unit of the Force, if purporting to be signed by or on behalf of the 
Central Government or the Director-General, or by any prescribed officer, shall 
be the evidence of facts stated in such letter, return or other document.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An Assam Rifles list 
or Gazette purporting to be published by authority shall be evidence of the 
status and rank of the officers, subordinate officers therein mentioned, and of 
any appointment held by them and of the battalion, unit, or branch of the Force 
to which they belong.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a record is made 
in any battalion book in pursuance of this Act or of any rules or otherwise in 
the discharge of official duties, and purporting to be signed by the Commandant 
or by the officer whose duty it is to make such record, such record shall be 
evidence of the facts therein stated.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A copy of any record 
in any battalion book purporting to be certified to be a true copy by the 
officer having custody of such book shall be evidence of such record.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any person 
subject to this Act is being tried on a charge of desertion or of absence 
without leave, and such person has surrendered himself into the custody of any 
officer or other person subject to this Act, or any unit of the Force, or has 
been apprehended by such officer or person, a certificate purporting to be 
signed by such officer or by the Commandant of the unit to which such person 
belongs, as the case may be, and stating the fact, date and place of such 
surrender or apprehension, and the manner in which he was dressed, shall be the 
evidence of the matters so stated.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where any person 
subject to this Act is being tried on a charge of desertion or of absence 
without leave and such person has surrendered himself into the custody of, or 
has been apprehended by, a police officer not below the rank of an officer in 
charge of a police station, a certificate purporting to be signed by such police 
officer and stating the facts, the date and place of such surrender or 
apprehension, and the manner in which he was dressed shall be evidence of the 
matters so stated.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any document 
purporting to be the report under the hand of a Government scientific expert, 
upon any matter or thing duly submitted to him for examination or analysis and 
report in the course of any proceeding under this Act, may be used as evidence 
in any inquiry, trial or other proceeding under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Assam Rifles Court 
may, if it thinks fit, summon and examine the expert referred to in sub-section 
(7) as to the subject-matter of his report.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where any such expert 
is summoned by an Assam Rifles Court and he is unable to attend personally, he 
may, unless the Court has expressly directed him to appear personally, depute 
any responsible officer working with him to attend the Court, if such deputed 
officer is conversant with the facts of the case and can satisfactorily depose 
in the Court on his behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The provisions of 
sub-sections (7), (8) and (9) shall apply to such Government scientific experts 
as specified in sub-section (4) of section 293 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>119</number> Reference by 
accused to Government officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If at any trial for desertion or absence without leave, overstaying leave or not 
rejoining when warned for service, the accused person states in his defence any 
sufficient or reasonable excuse for his unauthorised absence, and refers in 
support thereof to any officer in the service of the Government, or if it 
appears that any such officer is likely to prove or disprove the said statement 
in the defence, the Court shall address such officer and adjourn the proceedings 
until his reply is received.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The written reply of 
any officer so referred to shall, if signed by him, be received in evidence and 
have the same effect as if made on oath before the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Court is 
dissolved before the receipt of such reply or if the Court omits to comply with 
the provisions of this section, the convening officer may, at his discretion, 
annul the proceedings and order a fresh trial.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>120</number> Evidence of previous 
convictions and general character.—
<section><number>1</number> When any person subject to 
this Act has been convicted by an Assam Rifles Court of any offence, such Assam 
Rifles Court may inquire into, and receive, and record evidence of any previous 
convictions of such person, either by an Assam Rifles Court or by a criminal 
court, or any previous award of punishment under section 62 or section 64 or 
section 65 or section 66, and may further inquire into and record the general 
character of such person and such other matters as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Evidence received under this 
section may be either oral, or in the shape of entries in, or certified extracts 
from, books of an Assam Rifles Court, or other official records; and it shall 
not be necessary to give notice before trial to the person tried that evidence 
as to his previous convictions or character will be received.
 </section><section><number>3</number> At a Summary Assam Rifles 
Court, the officer holding the trial may, if he thinks fit, record any previous 
convictions against the offender, his general character, and such other matters 
as may be prescribed, as of his own knowledge, instead of requiring them to be 
proved under the foregoing provisions of this section.</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>121</number> Lunacy of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever, in the course of a trial by an Assam Rifles Court, it appears to the 
Court that the person charged is by reason of unsoundness of mind incapable of 
making his defence, or that he committed the act alleged but was by reason of 
unsoundness of mind incapable of knowing the nature of the act or knowing that 
it was wrong or contrary to law, the Court shall record a finding accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
of the Court, or, in the case of a Summary Assam Rifles Court, the officer 
holding the trial, shall forthwith report the case to the confirming officer, or 
to the authority empowered to deal with its findings under section 137, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The confirming officer 
to whom the case is reported under sub-section (2) may, if he does not confirm 
the finding, take steps to have the accused person tried by the same or another 
Assam Rifles Court for the offence with which he was charged.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The authority to whom 
the finding of a Summary Assam Rifles Court is reported under sub-section (2), 
and a confirming officer confirming the finding in any case so reported to him 
shall order the accused person to be kept in custody in the prescribed manner 
and shall report the case for the orders of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of a report 
under sub-section (4), the Central Government may order the accused person to be 
detained in a lunatic asylum or other suitable place of safe custody.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>122</number> Subsequent fitness 
of lunatic accused for trial.—Where 
any accused person, having been found by reason of unsoundness of mind to be 
incapable of making his defence, is in custody or under detention under section 
121, any officer prescribed in this behalf, may,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if such 
person is in custody under sub-section (4) of section 121, on the report of a 
medical officer that he is capable of making his defence, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  if such 
person is detained in a jail under sub-section (5) of section 121 on a 
certificate of the Inspector-General of Prisons, and if such person is detained 
in a lunatic asylum under the said sub-section, on a certificate of any two or 
more of the visitors of such asylum and if he is detained in any other place 
under that sub-section, on a certificate of the prescribed authority, that he is 
capable of making his defence,
 
take steps to have such 
person tried by the same or another Assam Rifles Court for the offence with 
which he was originally charged or, if the offence is a civil offence, by a 
criminal court.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>123</number> Transmission to 
Central Government of orders under section 122.—A 
copy of every order made by an officer under section 122 for the trial of the 
accused shall forthwith be sent to the Central Government.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>124</number> Release of lunatic 
accused.—Where 
any person is in custody under sub-section (4) of section 121 or under detention 
under sub-section (5) of that section,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if such 
person is in custody under the said sub-section (4), on the report of a medical 
officer, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  if such 
person is detained under the said sub-section (5), on a certificate from any of 
the authorities mentioned in clause (b) of section 122 that in the judgment of 
such officer or authority such person may be released without danger of his 
doing injury to himself or to any other person,
 
the Central Government may 
order that such person be released or detained in custody, or transferred to a 
public lunatic asylum if he has not already been to such an asylum.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>125</number> Delivery of 
lunatic accused to relatives.—Where 
any relative or friend of any person who is in custody under sub-section (4) of 
section 121 or under detention under sub-section (5) of that section desires 
that he should be delivered to his care and custody, the Central Government may, 
upon application by such relative or friend and, on his giving security to the 
satisfaction of that Government that the person delivered shall be properly 
taken care of, and, prevented from doing injury to himself or to any other 
person, and be produced for the inspection of such officer, and at such times 
and places, as the Central Government may direct, order such person to be 
delivered to such relative or friend.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>126</number> Order for custody 
and disposal of property pending trial.—When 
any property regarding which any offence appears to have been committed, or 
which appears to have been used for the commission of any offence, is produced 
before an Assam Rifles Court during a trial, the Court may make such order as it 
thinks fit for the proper custody of such property pending the conclusion of the 
trial, and if the property is subject to speedy or natural decay may, after 
recording such evidence as it thinks necessary, order it to be sold otherwise 
disposed of.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>127</number> Order of disposal 
of property regarding which offence is committed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the conclusion of a trial before any Assam Rifles Court, the Court or the 
officer confirming the finding or sentence of such Assam Rifles Court, or any 
authority superior to such officer, or, in the case of Summary Assam Rifles 
Court whose finding or sentence does not require confirmation, an officer not 
below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General within whose command the trial was 
held, may make such order as it or he thinks fit for the disposal by destruction 
confiscation, delivery to any person claiming to be entitled to possession 
thereof, or otherwise, of any property or document produced before the Court or 
in its custody, or regarding which any offence appears to have been committed or 
which has been committed or which has been used for the commission of any 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any order has 
been made under sub-section (1) in respect of property regarding which an 
offence appears to have been committed, a copy of such order signed and 
certified by the authority making the same may, whether the trial was held 
within India or not, be sent to a Magistrate within whose jurisdiction such 
property for the time being is situated, and such Magistrate shall thereupon 
cause the order to be carried into effect as if it were an order passed by him 
under the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In this section the 
term “property” includes, in the case of property regarding which an offence 
appears to have been committed, not only such property as has been originally in 
the possession or under the control of any person, but also any property into or 
for which the same may have been converted or exchanged, and anything acquired 
by such conversion or exchange whether immediately or otherwise.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>128</number> Powers of Assam 
Rifles Court in relation to proceedings under this Act.—Any 
trial by an Assam Rifles Court under the provisions of this Act shall be deemed 
to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Assam Rifles Court shall be deemed to be 
the Court within the meaning of sections 345 and 346 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>129</number> Finding and 
sentence not valid unless confirmed.—No 
finding or sentence of a General Assam Rifles Court or a Petty Assam Rifles 
Court shall be valid except so far as it may be confirmed as provided by this 
Act.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>130</number> Power to confirm 
finding and sentence of General Assam Rifles Court.—The 
findings and sentences of General Assam Rifles Courts may be confirmed by the 
Central Government or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant of the 
Central Government.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>131</number> Power to confirm 
finding and sentence of Petty Assam Rifles Court.—The 
findings and sentences of Petty Assam Rifles Courts may be confirmed by an 
officer having power to convene a General Assam Rifles Court or by any officer 
empowered in this behalf by warrant of such officer.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>132</number> Limitation of 
powers of confirming authority.—A 
warrant issued under section 130 or section 131 may contain such restrictions, 
reservations or conditions as the authority issuing it may think fit.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>133</number> Power of 
confirming authority to mitigate, remit or commute sentences.—Subject 
to such restrictions, reservations or conditions, as may be contained in any 
warrant issued under section 130 or section 131, a confirming authority may, 
when confirming the sentence of an Assam Rifles Court, mitigate or remit the 
punishment thereby awarded, or commute that punishment for any punishment or 
punishment lower in the scale laid down in section 57.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>134</number> Confirming of 
findings and sentences on board a ship.—When 
any person subject to this Act is tried and sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court 
while on board a ship, the finding and sentence so far as not confirmed and 
executed on board the ship, may be confirmed and executed in like manner as if 
such person had been tried at the port of disembarkation.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>135</number> Revision of 
finding or sentence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any finding or sentence of an Assam Rifles Court which requires confirmation may 
be once revised by order of the confirming authority and on such revision, the 
Court, if so directed by the confirming authority, may take additional evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court, on 
revision, shall consist of the same officers as were present when the original 
decision was passed unless any of those officers are unavoidably absent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case of such 
unavoidable absence the cause thereof shall be duly certified in the 
proceedings, and the Court shall proceed with the revision:
 
Provided that, if a 
General Assam Rifles Court, still consists of five officers, or, if a Petty 
Assam Rifles Court, of three officers.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>136</number> Finding and 
sentence of a Summary Assam Rifles Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2), the finding and sentence of a 
Summary Assam Rifles Court shall not require to be confirmed, but may be carried 
out forthwith.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the officer holding 
the trial is of the rank of Deputy Commandant or of a rank declared under clause 
(a) of sub-section (5) of section 96 as equivalent thereto or of a lower rank 
and has held such rank for less than five years, he shall not, except on active 
duty, carry into effect any sentence, until it has received the approval of an 
officer not below the rank of a Deputy Inspector-General.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>137</number> Transmission of 
proceedings of Summary Assam Rifles Court.—The 
proceedings of every Summary Assam Rifles Court shall, without delay, be 
forwarded to the officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General within 
whose command the trial was held, or to the prescribed officer, and such officer 
or the Director-General or any officer empowered by him in this behalf may, for 
reasons based on the merits of the case, but not on merely technical grounds, 
set aside the proceedings, or reduce the sentence to any other sentence which 
the court might have passed.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>138</number> Alteration of 
finding or sentence in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a finding of guilty by an Assam Rifles Court, which has been confirmed or 
which does not require confirmation, is found for any reason to be invalid or 
cannot be supported by the evidence, the authority which would have had power 
under section 150 to commute the punishment awarded by the sentence, if the 
finding had been valid may substitute a new finding and pass a sentence for the 
offence specified or involved in such finding:
 
Provided that no such 
substitution shall be made unless such finding could have been validly made by 
the Assam Rifles Court on the charge and unless it appears that the Assam Rifles 
Court must have been satisfied of the facts establishing the said offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a sentence 
passed by an Assam Rifles Court which has been confirmed, or which does not 
require confirmation, not being a sentence passed in pursuance of a new finding 
substituted under sub-section (1) is found for any reason to be invalid, the 
authority referred to in sub-section (1) may pass a valid sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The punishment awarded 
by a sentence passed under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall not be 
higher in the scale of punishment than, or in excess of, the punishment awarded 
by, the sentence for which a new sentence is substituted under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any finding 
substituted, or any sentence passed, under this section shall, for the purpose 
of this Act and the rules, have effect as if it were a finding or sentence, as 
the case may be, of an Assam Rifles Court.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>139</number> Remedy against 
order, finding or sentence of Assam Rifles Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to this Act who considers himself aggrieved by any order 
passed by any Assam Rifles Court may present a petition to the officer or 
authority empowered to confirm any finding or sentence of an Assam Rifles Court 
and the confirming authority may take such steps as may be considered necessary 
to satisfy itself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of the order 
passed or as to the regularity of any proceeding to which the order relates.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
this Act who considers himself aggrieved by a finding or sentence of any Assam 
Rifles Court which has been confirmed may present a petition to the Central 
Government, the Director-General or any prescribed officer superior in command 
to the one who confirmed such finding or sentence, and the Central Government, 
the Director-General or the prescribed officer, as the case may be, may pass 
such order thereon as it or he thinks fit.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>140</number> Annulment of 
proceedings.—The 
Central Government, the Director-General or any prescribed officer may annul the 
proceeding of any Assam Rifles Court on the ground that they are illegal or 
unjust.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>141</number> Form of sentence 
of death.—In 
awarding a sentence of death, an Assam Rifles Court shall in its discretion 
direct that the offender shall suffer death by being hanged by the neck until he 
be dead, or shall suffer death by being shot to death.


</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>142</number> Commencement of 
sentence of imprisonment.—Whenever 
any person is sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court under this Act to imprisonment, 
the term of his sentence shall, whether it has been revised or not, be reckoned 
to commence on the day in which the original proceedings were signed by the 
presiding officer, or in the case of a Summary Assam Rifles Court, by the Court:
 
Provided that when a 
person subject to this Act is sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court to a term of 
imprisonment, not being an imprisonment in default of payment of fine, the 
period spent by him in civil or Force custody during investigation, inquiry or 
trial of the same case, and before the date of order such sentence shall be set 
off against the term of imprisonment imposed upon him and the liability of such 
person or officer to undergo imprisonment on such order of sentence shall be 
restricted to the remainder, if any, of the term of imprisonment imposed upon 
him.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>143</number> Execution of 
sentence of imprisonment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever any sentence of imprisonment is passed under this Act by an Assam 
Rifles Court or whenever any sentence of death is commuted to imprisonment, the 
confirming officer or in case of a Summary Assam Rifles Court, the officer 
holding the Court or such other officer as may be prescribed, shall, save as 
otherwise provided in sub-sections (3) and (4), direct that the sentence shall 
be carried out by confinement in a civil prison.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a direction has 
been made under sub-section (1), the Commandant of the person under sentence or 
such other officer as may be prescribed shall forward a warrant in the 
prescribed form to the officer incharge of the prison in which such person is to 
be confined and shall arrange for his dispatch to such prison with the warrant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of a 
sentence of imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months and passed 
under this Act by an Assam Rifles Court the appropriate officer under 
sub-section (1) may direct that the sentence shall be carried out by confinement 
in force custody instead of in a civil prison.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On active duty, a 
sentence of imprisonment may be carried out by confinement in such place as the 
Deputy Inspector-General within whose command the person sentenced is serving or 
any prescribed officer may from time to time appoint.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>144</number> Temporary custody 
of offender.—Where 
a sentence of imprisonment is directed to be undergone in a civil prison, the 
offender may be kept in Force custody or in any other fit place till such time 
as it is possible to send him to a civil prison.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>145</number> Execution of 
sentence of imprisonment in special case.—Whenever, 
in the opinion of an officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General 
within whose command the trial is held, any sentence or portion of a sentence of 
imprisonment cannot for special reasons, conveniently be carried out in Force 
custody in accordance with the provisions of section 143, such officer may 
direct that such sentence or portion of sentence shall be carried out by 
confinement in any civil prison or other fit place.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>146</number> Conveyance of 
prisoner from place to place.—A 
person under sentence of imprisonment may, during his conveyance from place to 
place, or when on board ship, aircraft or otherwise, be subjected to such 
restraint as is necessary for his safe conduct and removal.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>147</number> Communication of 
certain orders to prison officers.—When 
an order is duly made under this Act setting aside or varying any sentence, 
order or warrant under which any person is confined in a civil prison, a warrant 
in accordance with such order shall be forwarded by the officer making the order 
or his staff officer or such other person as may be prescribed, to the officer 
in charge of the prison in which such person is confined.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>148</number> Execution of 
sentence of fine.—When 
a sentence of fine is imposed by an Assam Rifles Court under section 55, a copy 
of such sentence signed and certified by the confirming officer, or where no 
confirmation is required by the officer holding the trial may be sent to any 
Magistrate in India and such Magistrate shall thereupon cause the fine to be 
recovered in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
1973 (2 of 1974), as if it were a sentence of fine imposed by such Magistrate.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>149</number> Informality or 
error in order or warrant.—Whenever 
any person is sentenced to imprisonment under this Act and is undergoing the 
sentence in any place or manner in which he might be confined under a lawful 
order or warrant in pursuance of this Act, the confinement of such person shall 
not be deemed to be illegal only by reason of informality or error in, or as 
respects the order, warrant or other document, or the authority by which, or in 
pursuance whereof such person was brought into, or is confined in any such 
place, and any such order, warrant or document may be amended accordingly.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>150</number> Pardon and 
remission.—When 
any person subject to this Act has been convicted by an Assam Rifles Court of 
any offence, the Central Government or the Director-General, or in the case of a 
sentence which he could have confirmed or which did not require confirmation, an 
officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General within whose command such 
person at the time of conviction was serving or the prescribed officer may,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  either with 
or without conditions which the person sentenced accepts, pardon the person or 
remit the whole or any part of the punishment awarded; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  mitigate the 
punishment awarded; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  commute such 
punishment for any less punishment or punishments mentioned in this Act; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  either with 
or without conditions which the person sentenced accepts, release the person on 
parole.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>151</number> Cancellation of 
conditional pardon, release on parole or remission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any condition on which a person has been pardoned or released on parole or a 
punishment has been remitted is, in the opinion of the authority which granted 
the pardon, release or remission, not fulfilled, such authority may cancel the 
pardon, release or remission and thereupon the sentence of the Court shall be 
carried into effect as if such pardon, release or remession had not been 
granted.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person whose 
sentence of imprisonment is carried into effect under the provisions of 
sub-section (1) shall undergo only the unexpired portion of his sentence.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>152</number> Suspension of 
sentence of imprisonment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a person subject to this Act is sentenced by an Assam Rifles Court to 
imprisonment, the Central Government, the Director-General or any officer 
empowered to convene General Assam Rifles Court may suspend the sentence whether 
or not the offender has already been committed to prison or to Force custody.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The authority or 
officer specified in sub-section (1) may, in the case of an offender so 
sentenced direct that until the order of such authority or officer have been 
obtained, the offender shall not be committed to prison or to Force custody.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The powers conferred 
by sub-sections (1) and (2) may be exercised in the case of any such sentence 
which has been confirmed, reduced or commuted.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>153</number> Orders pending 
suspension.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where sentence referred to in section 152 is imposed by an Assam Rifles Court 
other than Summary Assam Rifles Court, the confirming officer may, when 
confirming the sentence, direct that the offender be not committed to prison or 
to Force custody until the orders of the authority or officer specified in 
section 152 have been obtained.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a sentence of 
imprisonment is imposed by a Summary Assam Rifles Court, the officer holding the 
trial or the officer authorised to approve the sentence under sub-section (2) of 
section 136 may make the direction referred to in sub-section (1).
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>154</number> Release on 
suspension.—Where 
a sentence is suspended under section 152, the offender shall forthwith be 
released from custody.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>155</number> Computation of 
period of suspension.—Any 
period during which the sentence is under suspension shall be reckoned as part 
of the term of such sentence.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>156</number> Order after 
suspension.—The 
authority or officer specified in section 152 may, at any time while a sentence 
is suspended, order—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  that the 
offender be committed to undergo the unexpired portion of the sentence; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  that the 
sentence be remitted.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>157</number> Reconsideration of 
case after suspension.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a sentence has been suspended, the case may at any time, and shall at 
intervals of not more than four months, be reconsidered by the authority or 
officer specified in section 152 or by any officer not below the rank of a 
Deputy Inspector-General duly authorised by the authority or officer specified 
in section 152.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where on such 
reconsideration by the officer so authorised it appears to him that the conduct 
of offender since his conviction has been such as to justify a remission of the 
sentence, he shall refer the matter to the authority or officer specified in 
section 150.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>158</number> Fresh sentence 
after suspension.—Where 
an offender, while a sentence on him is suspended under this Act, is sentenced 
for any other offence then,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  if the 
further sentence is also suspended under this Act, the two sentences shall run 
concurrently;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  if the 
further sentence is for a period of three months or more and is not suspended 
under this Act, the offender shall be so committed to prison or to Force custody 
for the unexpired portion of the previous sentence, but both sentences shall run 
concurrently; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  if the 
further sentence is for a period of less than three months and is not suspended 
under this Act the offender shall be so committed on that sentence only, and the 
previous sentence shall, subject to any order which may be passed under section 
156 or section 157, continue to be suspended.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>159</number> Scope of power of 
suspension.—The 
powers conferred by sections 152 and 156 shall be in addition to, and not in 
derogation of, the power of mitigation, remission and commutation.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>160</number> Effect of 
suspension and remission on dismissal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where in addition to any other sentence the punishment of dismissal or removal 
has been awarded by an Assam Rifles Court, and such sentence is suspended under 
section 152, then, such dismissal or removal shall not take effect until so 
ordered by the authority or officer specified in section 152.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such other sentence 
is remitted under section 156, the punishment of dismissal or removal shall also 
be remitted.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>161</number> Disposal of 
property of the members of the Force.—The 
Central Government or any other authority empowered in this behalf by that 
Government may, by a general or special order, make provisions for the disposal 
of the private or regimental property of any person subject to this Act or any 
other dues including provident fund of that person, who dies or deserts, or is 
ascertained to be of unsound mind or while on active duty is officially reported 
as missing.


</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>162</number> Powers and duties 
conferable and imposable on members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by general or special order published in the 
Official Gazette, direct that, subject to such conditions and limitations, and 
within the local limits of such area adjoining the border of India, as may be 
specified in the order, any member of the Force may,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  for the 
purpose of prevention of any offence punishable under the Passport (Entry into 
India) Act, 1920 (34 of 1920), the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (16 of 
1939), the Central Excise Act, 1944 (1 of 1944), the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 
1946), the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962), the Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967) 
or the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999) or of any cognizable 
offence punishable under any other Central Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  for the 
purpose of apprehending any person who has committed any offence referred to in 
clause (a),
 
exercise or discharge such 
of the powers or duties under that Act or any other Central Act as may be 
specified in the said order, being the powers and duties which, in the opinion 
of the Central Government, an officer of the corresponding or lower rank is by 
that or such other Act empowered to exercise or discharge for the said purposes.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, confer or 
impose, with the concurrence of the State Government concerned, any of the 
powers or duties which may be exercised or discharged under a State Act by a 
police officer upon a member of the Force who, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, holds a corresponding or higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the order or both Houses agree that the order should not be made, the order 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as 
the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that order.
</section></article> 
 The 
Assam Rifles Act, 2006
  
 <article><number>163</number> Protection for acts of 
members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> The provision of section 125 
of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) shall apply to such members of the 
Force who exercise or discharge any power or duty under sub-section (1) of 
section 162 or on whom any power is conferred or duty is imposed under 
sub-section (2) of that section in the same manner as it apply to a police 
officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In any suit or proceeding 
against any member of the Force for any act done by him in pursuance of a 
warrant or order of a competent authority, it shall be lawful for him to plead, 
that such act was done by him under the authority of such warrant or 
order.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any such plea may be proved by 
the production of the warrant or order directing the act, and if it is so proved 
the member of the Force shall thereupon be discharged from liability in respect 
of the act so done by him, notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of the 
authority which issued such warrant or order.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any orther law for the time being in force, any legal proceeding 
(whether civil or criminal) which may lawfully be brought against any member of 
the Force for anything done or intended to be done under the powers conferred 
by, or in pursuance of, any provision of this Act or the rules, shall be 
commenced within three months after the act complained of was committed and not 
otherwise, and notice in writing of such proceedings and of the cause thereof 
shall be given to the defendant or his superior officer at least one month 
before the commencement of such proceedings.</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>164</number> Power of Central 
Government to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no order 
shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from the 
commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>165</number> Power to make 
rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification, make rules for the purposes of carrying 
out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the manner of 
re-constitution of the Force and the conditions of service of the members of the 
Force under sub-section (2) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the mode of 
enrolment and the procedure for enrolment under sub-section (1) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the authority 
whose previous permission in writing is required for resigning from appointment 
or withdrawing from all or any of the duties under section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  rank or ranks 
of an officer or a subordinate officer referred to under sub-section (2) of 
section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the authority 
who shall give previous sanction in writing under sub-section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  nature of 
communication or publication under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  other 
purposes of meeting or demonstration under sub-section (2) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  form of 
enrolement under section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  any other 
purpose under clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 57;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  the officer 
who may direct that an enrolled person who has been sentenced to dismissal or 
imprisonment whether combined with dismissal or not may be retained to serve in 
the ranks under section 60;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  the manner of 
proceedings against a person and the extent of awarding punishment under section 
62;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>l</number>  the manner 
of proceeding against an officer below the rank of a Deputy Commandant and of 
the rank of subordinate officer and of the rank of a Warrant Officer under 
sub-section (1) of section 64;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the manner of 
forwarding certified true copies of the proceedings and the superior authority 
to whom such copies shall be forwarded under sub-section (2) of section 64;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>n</number>  the manner of 
proceeding against an officer below the rank of Commandant and of any rank of 
subordinate officer and of the rank of Warrant Officer under sub-section (1) of 
section 65;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>o</number>  the manner of 
proceeding against any subordinate officer or a Warrant Officer under section 
66;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>p</number>  the officer 
by whose order any sum is required to be paid, for the maintenance of wife or 
legitimate or illegitimate child of a person subject to this Act other than an 
officer, under clause (i) of section 69;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>q</number>  the officer 
who may direct that the whole or any part of the pay and allowances of person 
subject to this Act shall be withheld under section 71;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>r</number>  the manner 
and the extent of remission of deductions from pay and allowances authorised by 
this Act and the authority by which such remission shall be made under section 
75;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>s</number>  the 
authorities by whom proper provisions to be made out of the pay and allowances 
of all persons subject to this Act, being prisoners of war, for the dependents 
of such person under section 76;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>t</number>  the 
authorities who shall make proper provision out of the pay and allowances of any 
person subject to this Act, who is prisoner of war or is missing under section 
77;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>u</number>  the manner in 
which and the period for which any person subject to this Act may be taken into 
and detained in Force custody under sub-section (4) of section 80;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number>  the manner of 
making special report giving reasons for delay under section 81;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>w</number>  the authority 
to appoint, and the manner of appointment of, a court of inquiry; the manner of 
administering oath or affirmation by such court of inquiry and the manner of 
making record under sub-section (1) of section 84;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>x</number>  the officer 
who may appoint Force Police under sub-section (1) of section 85;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>y</number>  the other 
officer having the discretion to decide before which court the proceeding shall 
be instituted under section 102;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>z</number>  the manner of 
filling up the vacancy of member by another officer under sub-section (3) of 
section 106;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>za</number>  the manner 
for administering oath or affirmation to every member of an Assam Rifles Court 
and to the Law Officer, or, as the case may be, the officer approved under 
section 105 before the commencement of the trial under sub-section (1) of 
section 107;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zb</number>  the form for 
being duly sworn or affirmed under sub-section (2) of section 107;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zc</number>  the officer 
by whom the letter, return or other documents purported to be signed shall be 
the evidence of the facts stated in such letter, return or other document under 
sub-section (1) of section 118;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zd</number>  the other 
matters to be further inquired and recorded under sub-section (1) of section 
120;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ze</number>  the other 
matters to be recorded under sub-section (3) of section 120;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zf</number>  the manner of 
keeping in custody of the accused person under sub-section (4) of section 121;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zg</number>  the officer 
who may take steps to have certain persons tried under section 122;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zh</number>  the authority 
for issuing certificate in case of detention in any other place under clause (b) 
of section 122;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>zi</number>  the officer 
to whom the proceedings of every Summary Assam Rifles Courts shall be forwarded 
under section 137;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zj</number>  the officer 
superior in command, to the one who confirmed the findings or sentence referred 
to in sub-section (2) of section 139, to whom petition may be presented under 
that sub-section;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zk</number>  the officer 
who may annul the proceeding of any Assam Rifles Court under section 140;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>zl</number>  the other 
officer who shall direct that sentence shall be carried out by the confinement 
in a civil prison under sub-section (1) of section 143;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>zm</number>  the officer 
who shall forward a warrant and the form of such warrant under sub-section (2) 
of section 143;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zn</number>  the officer 
who may from time to time appoint the place for confinement under sub-section 
(4) of section 143;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zo</number>  the other 
person by whom the warrant shall be forwarded to the officer in charge of the 
prison under section 147;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zp</number>  the officer 
who may pardon or exercise other powers as specified under clauses (a) to (c) of 
section 150;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>zq</number>  any other 
matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision 
is to be, or may be, made by rules.
</subsection></section></article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>166</number> Power to make 
regulations.—The 
Director-General may make regulations for all or any of the purposes of this Act 
other than those specified in section 165, subject to approval of the Central 
Government.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>167</number> Rules and 
regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
rule or regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
</article> 
 


The Assam Rifles Act, 2006
 

 <article>
<number>168</number> Repeal and 
savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Assam Rifles Act, 1941 (5 of 1941) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the Assam 
Rifles in existence at the commencement of this Act and constituted under this 
Act so repealed shall be deemed to be reconstituted under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  members of 
the Assam Rifles in existence at the commencement of this Act and appointed 
under the Act so repealed shall be deemed to have been appointed or, as the case 
may be, enrolled as such under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  any appeal, 
application, trial, inquiry or investigation pending immediately before the 
commencement of this Act shall be disposed of, continued, held or made, as the 
case may be, in accordance with the provisions of the Assam Rifles Act, 1941 (5 
of 1941), as if this Act had not come into force;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  anything done 
or any action taken before the commencement of this Act, in relation to any 
person appointed or enrolled, shall be valid and as effective in law as if such 
thing or action was done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.
 
 

</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>