<act><title>The
Small Industries Development Bank of India  (Appeal to the Central
Government) Rules, 20031</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—(1)
These rules may be called the Small Industries Development Bank of India (Appeal
to the Central Government) Rules, 2003.
 


 <section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.   




</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Small Industries Development Bank of India Act, 1989 (39 of
1989); 
 
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
“authorised representative” means—  
 
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
in relation to an appellant, a person duly authorised by the appellant to
present an appeal on his behalf to the Central Government; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
in relation to the Board, a person duly appointed by the Board by resolution as
authorised representative to appear, plead and act on behalf of the Board in any
appeal under these rules; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
in relation to any other party to the appeal, a person duly authorised by such
party to appear, plead and act on his behalf; 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>c</number>
“Board” means the Board of Directors of the Small Industries Bank
constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
“Small Industries Bank” means the Small Industries Development Bank of India
established under section 3 of the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
“Form” means the Form appended to these rules; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
“party” means a person who files an appeal before the Central
Government and the respondent; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>g</number>
“rules” means the rules made under the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>h</number>
other expressions, which are not defined here, shall have the meaning
respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
 

</section></article> 

   


 <article>  

<number>3</number> Form
of Appeal.—Every appeal under sub-section (3) of section 20D of the
Act shall be preferred by any person aggrieved by an Order of refusal of the
Board made under sub-section (2) of section 20D to the Central Government in the
Form.

</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>4</number>
Time within which appeal is to be preferred.—
<section><number>1</number> An appeal shall be
preferred by the aggrieved person within a period of thirty days from the date
of communication to him of the order of refusal of the Board made under
sub-section (2) of section 20D of the Act.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
When the appeal is preferred after the expiry of the period of thirty days
specified in sub-rule (1), it shall be accompanied by an application supported
by an affidavit setting forth the facts on which the appellant relies to satisfy
the Central Government that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the
appeal within the said period of thirty days:
 


 Provided
that if the Central Government is satisfied that the appellant had sufficient
cause for not preferring the appeal within the aforesaid period, it may, for
reasons to be recorded in writing, admit the appeal after the expiry of the
aforesaid period but before the expiry of forty five days from the date of
communication to him of the order of refusal of the Board.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>5</number>
Payment of fees.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 500.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The amount of fees shall be deposited through a Bank Draft drawn in favour of
Pay &amp; Accounts Officer (Banking) and deposited with the State Bank of India,
Parliament Street, New Delhi under the Major head—
 


 “0070”—Other
administrative services”
 


 “502”—Service
and Service Fees”.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>6</number>
Contents of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every appeal filed under rule 3 shall be written in English or Hindi and shall
set forth concisely under distinct heads, the grounds of appeal which shall be
numbered consecutively.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every appeal shall be filed in the Form in duplicate and shall be accompanied by
a certified copy of the order of refusal of the Board appealed against,
affidavit and other documents to support the grounds of appeal.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>7</number>
Right to representation.—
<section><number>1</number>
An appellant and every other party to the appeal may appear before the Central
Government in person or through their authorized representatives.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Board shall be represented before the Central Government through its
authorised representative.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Authorisation empowering a person to act as an authorised representative shall
be filed with the Central Government before the commencement of the hearing of
the appeal.

  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>8</number>
Procedure for filing appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> An
appeal shall be preferred either by the appellant in person or his autho­rised
representative to the Central Government and the same shall be addressed to the
Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Economic Affairs, Ministry
of Finance and Company Affairs, New Delhi by registered post.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
An appeal under sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been preferred to the
Central Government on the date on which it is received in the office of the
Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Economic Affairs, Ministry
of Finance and Company Affairs, New Delhi.

  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>9</number>
Furnishing of information or documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, before considering the appeal, require any party to
the appeal, to furnish such further information and documents as it considers
necessary. 


 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> The parties shall furnish such information
and documents within thirty days of such order or such further period as may be
granted by the Central Government.

  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>10</number>
Date and place of hearing of appeal to be communicated.—The
Central Government shall communicate, before considering the appeal, to the
parties concerned, the date and place of the hearing of the appeal and shall
also send a notice of the appeal to the Board either before or with such
communication.

</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>11</number>
Hearing of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number>
On the days fixed or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the
appellant shall be heard in support of the appeal. The Central Government shall
then, if necessary, hear the authorised representative of the Board and any
other party to the appeal and in such case the appellant shall be entitled to
reply.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
In case the appellant does not appear in person or through an authorised
representative when the appeal is called for hearing, Central Government may
dismiss the appeal for default:
 


 Provided
that if such appellant or such authorised representative on an application
satisfy the Central Government that there was sufficient cause for his
non-appearance, when the appeal was called for hearing, the Central Government
may make an order setting aside the ex-parte dismissal and restore the
appeal.

  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>12</number>
Orders by the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may after considering the appeal and making such further
enquiry as it considers necessary, either dismiss the appeal; or
 


 <subsection><number>a</number> pass an order directing that the transfer of shares shall be
registered by the Board and the Board shall comply with such order within thirty
days of the receipt of the order; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> pass an order directing the rectification of the register of
shareholders of the Small Industries Bank; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> in its discretion, pass such other orders as it may be deem fit and
just.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The order passed under sub-rule (1) above, shall be in writing, signed and dated
and shall be communicated to the concerned parties.

  
</section></article><form>
 

  


 

 
 

FORM  


 

Small
Industries Development Bank of India 


 

(Appeal
to the Central Government) 


 

(See
rule 3) 


 

Form of Appeal 


 

From: 


 

(Mention
the name and address of the appellant here)  


 

To, 


 

  
     The Secretary to the Government of India, 


 

       
Department of Economic Affairs, 


 

       
Ministry of Finance.New Delhi.  


 

Sir, 


 

The
Appellant named above, begs to prefer this appeal under sub-section (3) of
section 20D of the Small Industries Development Bank of India Act, 1989 (39 of
1989), against Order of refusal of the Board of Small Industries Bank passed
under the said Act, on the following facts and grounds. 


 

FACTS 


 

(Mention
briefly the facts of the case here. Enclose certified copy of the order of
refusal by the Board, an affidavit and, copies of other relevant documents, if
any). 


 

GROUNDS 


 

(Mention
here the grounds on which the appeal is made) 


 

Prayer 


 

In
the light of what is stated above, the appellant prays that he/she/it may be
granted the following relief. 


 

Relief
Sought 


 

(specify the
relief sought) 


 

The
amounts of Rs. ………………as fees for this appeal has been deposited vide
challan No. …………….. dated………….. with……………..
branch of the State Bank of India. 


 

(Signature
of the Appellant or 

his authorised representative) 


 

  


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>