<act><tid>1759043</tid>
<title>THE ORPHANAGES AND OTHER CHARITABLE HOMES (SUPERVISION AND CONTROL) 
ACT, <year>1960</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1960</year> 
[ 9th April, <year>1960</year>.]
An Act to provide for the supervision and control of orphanages, homes 
for neglected women or children and other like institutions and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>1202481</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1973686</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Orphanages and other Charitable Homes (Supervision and  
  Control) Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1775325</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>1473502</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force in a State on such date as the 
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>181272</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>593182</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Board of Control established under 
section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>88964</tid>
<number>b</number>" certificate" means the certificate of recognition 
granted under section 15;

</section>

<section><tid>1497528</tid>
<number>c</number>" child" means a boy or girl who has not completed the 
age of eighteen years;

</section>

<section><tid>1672914</tid>
<number>d</number>" home" means an institution, whether called an 
orphanage, a home for neglected women or children, a widows' 
home, or by any other name, maintained or intended to be 
maintained for the reception, care, protection and welfare 
of women or children;

</section>

<section><tid>1749835</tid>
<number>e</number>" manager" means a member of the managing committee 
appointed as such by the committee under section 20;

</section>

<section><tid>750226</tid>
<number>f</number>" managing committee" means the committee of manage- 
ment referred to in section 20;

</section>

<section><tid>1589699</tid>
<number>g</number>" recognised home" means a home in respect of which a 
certificate has been granted;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>744</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1539027</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1363831</tid>
<number>i</number>" woman" means a female who has completed the age of 
eighteen years.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>147444</tid>
<number> 3</number> Act not to apply to certain institutions. Nothing in this 
Act shall apply to-
<section><tid>873931</tid>
<number>a</number>any hostel or boarding house attached to, or controlled 
or recognised by, an educational institution; or

</section>

<section><tid>536915</tid>
<number>b</number>any protective home established under the Suppression 
of Immoral Traffic in Women and Girls Act, <year>1956</year> (104 of  
  <year>1956</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>228413</tid>
<number>c</number>any reformatory, certified or other school, or any home 
or workhouse, governed by any enactment for the time being in 
force.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297354</tid>
<number>4</number>Effect of Act on instruments governing recognised homes. 
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any instrument governing a 
recognised home.
CHAP 
THE BOARD OF CONTROL AND ITS POWERS AND FUNCTIONS

CHAPTER II

THE BOARD OF CONTROL AND ITS POWERS AND FUNCTIONS


</article>



<article><tid>1921619</tid>
<number> 5</number> Board of Control, its constitution, etc.
<section><tid>845757</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a 
Board of Control for the supervision and control of homes in the 
State.

</section>

<section><tid>53423</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1824208</tid>
<number>a</number>three members of the State Legislature to be elected by 
the members thereof; provided that where the State 
Legislature consist of two Houses, two members shall be 
elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly from among 
themselves and one member shall be elected by the members of 
the Legislative Council from among themselves;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1601121</tid>
<number>b</number>five members of the managing committees in the State, 
to be elected by such committees from among themselves, 
each such committee having one vote only for this purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1223236</tid>
<number>c</number>the officer in charge of social welfare work in the 
State, to be nominated by the State Government;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>745</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1002250</tid>
<number>d</number>six members to be nominated by the State Government, of 
whom not more than one shall be a member of Parliament from 
the State and not less than three shall be women.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>967915</tid>
<number>3</number>If for any reason the officer referred to in clause (c) of 
subsection (2) is unable to attend any meeting of the Board, he may 
depute any officer subordinate to him to attend such meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>185796</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairman of the Board shall be elected by the members of 
the Board from among themselves:
Provided that at the time of the first constitution of the Board, 
one of the members of the Board shall be nominated by the State 
Government to be its Chairman.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>960322</tid>
<number> 6</number> Term of office and casual vacancies.
<section><tid>1485020</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise  
provided in this section, the term of office of a member of the Board 
shall be five years from the date of his election or nomination or 
until his successor has been duly elected or nominated, whichever is 
longer:
Provided that the term of office of a member elected under clause 
 (a) or clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 5, or of a member of 
Parliament nominated under clause (d) of sub- section (2) of section 5, 
shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of the House 
of the State Legislature which elected him, the managing committee or 
Parliament, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>392167</tid>
<number>2</number>A member may at any time resign his office by giving notice 
in writing to the State Government and on such resignation being 
notified in the Official Gazette by that Government, the seat of such 
member shall become vacant.

</section>

<section><tid>1631171</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy in the Board shall be filled by fresh 
election or nomination, as the case may be; and the term of office of 
a member elected or nominated to fill such vacancy shall be the 
remainder of the term of the member in whose place he is elected or 
nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>1052629</tid>
<number>4</number>Members of the Board shall be eligible for re- election or 
re- nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>1140474</tid>
<number>5</number>No act done or proceeding taken by the Board shall be 
questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or 
defect in the constitution of, the Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>746</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>867296</tid>
<number> 7</number> Functions of the Board.
<section><tid>303089</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the  
Board to supervise and control generally all matters relating to the 
management of homes in accordance with the provisions of this Act; 
and exercise such other powers and perform such other functions as may 
be prescribed by or under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>739892</tid>
<number>2</number>In the performance of its functions under this Act, the Board 
shall be bound by such directions as the State Government may give to 
it.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>853101</tid>
<number>8</number>Power of the Board to give directions to manager of a 
recognised home. Subject to the directions, if any given under sub- 
section (2) of section 7, the Board may, from time to time, give such 
general or special directions to the manager of a recognised home as 
it thinks fit for the efficient management of the home and the manager 
shall comply with such directions.

</article>



<article><tid>1024294</tid>
<number>9</number>Power of inspection. Any member of the Board, or any officer 
of the Board authorised in writing by it in this behalf, by general or 
special order, may enter at all reasonable times any home for the 
purpose of ascertaining whether the provisions of this Act or of any 
rules, regulations, directions or orders thereunder are being complied 
with and may require the production, for his inspection, of any 
document, book, register or record kept therein and ask for any 
information relating to the working of the home:
Provided that no such member or officer shall enter any home or 
part thereof where there are females, except in the presence of two 
respectable women of the locality.


</article>



<article><tid>635444</tid>
<number> 10</number> Funds of the Board. The funds of the Board shall consist 
of--
<section><tid>694671</tid>
<number>a</number>contributions, subscriptions, donations or bequests 
made to it by any person; and

</section>

<section><tid>1604741</tid>
<number>b</number>grants made to it by the State Government or any local 
or other public body.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>509897</tid>
<number>11</number>Staff of the Board. Subject to such rules as may be made by 
the State Government in this behalf, the Board may, for the purpose of 
enabling it to perform efficiently its functions or exercise its 
powers under this Act, appoint such officers or other employees as it 
may think fit and determine their functions and conditions of service.

</article>



<article><tid>552679</tid>
<number>12</number>Delegation of powers. Subject to the control of the State 
Government, the Board may, by general or special order in writing and 
subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be 
specified therein, delegate

<pagefootnote><pagenum>747</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to the Chairman or any other member or any officer thereof such of its 
powers and functions under this Act, as it may deem necessary, for the 
efficient carrying on of its administration.

CHAP 
RECOGNITION OF HOMES

CHAPTER III

RECOGNITION OF HOMES


</article>



<article><tid>781348</tid>
<number>13</number>Homes not to be run without certificate. After the 
commencement of this Act, no person shall maintain or conduct any 
home except under, and in accordance with, the conditions of a 
certificate of recognition granted under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1781662</tid>
<number>14</number>Application for certificate. Every person desiring to 
maintain or conduct a home shall make an application for a certificate 
of recognition to the Board in such form and containing such 
particulars as may be prescribed:
Provided that a person maintaining or conducting a home at the 
commencement of this Act shall be allowed a period of three months 
from such commencement to make an application for such certificate.


</article>



<article><tid>431508</tid>
<number> 15</number> Grant or refusal of certificate.
<section><tid>1678632</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of an  
application under section 14, the Board after making such inquiry as 
it considers necessary, may, by order in writing, either grant a 
certificate or refuse to grant it.

</section>

<section><tid>986423</tid>
<number>2</number>No order refusing to grant a certificate shall be made until 
an opportunity is given to the applicant to be heard in the matter and 
where a certificate is refused, the grounds for such refusal shall be 
communicated to the applicant in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>604516</tid>
<number>3</number>No fee shall be charged for the grant of a certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>1614690</tid>
<number>4</number>A certificate shall not be transferable.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>356051</tid>
<number> 16</number> Contents of certificate.
<section><tid>1571275</tid>
<number>1</number>The certificate shall specify- 

<subsection><tid>438192</tid>
<number>a</number>the name and location of the recognised home;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492616</tid>
<number>b</number>the name of the manager thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>825246</tid>
<number>c</number>the nature of the home, whether for women generally or 
for widows or for children generally or for orphans or for one 
or more of these classes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>816828</tid>
<number>d</number>the number of inmates to be taken by the home;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>451548</tid>
<number>e</number>the minimum standards regarding boarding, lodging, 
clothing, sanitation, health and hygiene which, having regard

<pagefootnote><pagenum>748</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to the conditions of the locality in which the recognised 
home is situated and its resources, should be complied with 
in the home;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1466195</tid>
<number>f</number>the standard of education or training to be provided 
for the inmates of the home, in case the education or train- 
ing of its inmates is undertaken; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158214</tid>
<number>g</number>such other conditions and particulars as may be 
prescribed:
Provided that there shall be deemed to be included in the certi- 
ficate granted in respect of a home for females a condition to the 
effect that the person in charge thereof, whether called 
superintendent or by any other name, shall ordinarily be a woman.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>882986</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall not, ordinarily, permit any recognised home to 
admit as inmates, persons of different sexes, but may do so for 
reasons to be recorded and subject to such conditions and limitations 
as may appear to it to be in the public interest.

</section>

<section><tid>1265886</tid>
<number>3</number>Without the previous written consent of the Board, no recog- 
nised home shall-

<subsection><tid>1907111</tid>
<number>a</number>change its name or location as specified in the 
certificate in respect of it; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>28699</tid>
<number>b</number>alter the purpose of any service specified therein.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315467</tid>
<number> 17</number> 
<section><tid>1503058</tid>
<number>1</number>Revocation of certificate. The Board may, without  
prejudice to any other penalty to which a person to whom a certificate 
has been granted may be liable under this Act, revoke the certificate-

<subsection><tid>1330347</tid>
<number>a</number>if it is satisfied that the home is not being conducted 
in accordance with the conditions laid down in the certi- 
ficate; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>552746</tid>
<number>b</number>the management of the home is being persistently 
carried on in an unsatisfactory manner or is being carried on 
in a manner highly prejudicial to the moral and physical 
well- being of the inmates; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1472545</tid>
<number>c</number>the home has, in the opinion of the Board, otherwise 
rendered itself unsuitable for that purpose:
Provided that no order of revocation shall be made under this 
sub- section until an opportunity is given to the person to show cause 
why the certificate should not be revoked;

and in every case of revocation. the grounds therefor shall be com- 
municated to the person in the prescribed manner.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>749</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1519483</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a certificate in respect of a home is revoked under 
subsection (1), such home shall cease to function-

<subsection><tid>1497619</tid>
<number>a</number>where an appeal has not been preferred under section 18 
against the order of revocation, immediately on the 
expiration of the period prescribed for such appeal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950774</tid>
<number>b</number>where such appeal has been preferred, but the order of 
revocation is upheld, from the date of the appellate order.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>481793</tid>
<number>3</number>On any home ceasing to function under sub- section (2), the 
Board may direct that any woman or child who is an inmate of such home 
shall be-

<subsection><tid>585492</tid>
<number>a</number>restored to the custody of her or his parent, husband 
or lawful guardian, as the case may be, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1396042</tid>
<number>b</number>transferred to another recognised home, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>734158</tid>
<number>c</number>entrusted to the care of any other fit person:
Provided that no woman shall be entrusted to the care of any 
person other than a woman.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739824</tid>
<number>18</number>Appeals. Any person aggrieved by an order of the Board 
refusing to grant a certificate or revoking a certificate may, in 
such manner land within such period as may be prescribed, prefer an 
appeal to the State Government or to such authority as may be 
specified by it against such refusal or revocation:
Provided that the State Government or the authority so specified, 
as the case may be, may admit an appeal after the expiry of the period 
so prescribed, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time.


</article>



<article><tid>1703200</tid>
<number> 19</number> 
<section><tid>1797809</tid>
<number>1</number>Surrender of certificate and its effect. The manager of  
a home, if specially authorised in this behalf by resolution of the 
managing committee, may, on giving six months' notice in writing to 
the Board of his intention so to do, apply for the withdrawal of the 
certificate granted in respect of that home and on the expiration of 
the said period from the date of notice, the certificate shall, unless 
before that time the notice is withdrawn, cease to have effect; and 
the home shall cease to function.

</section>

<section><tid>1797802</tid>
<number>2</number>No woman or child shall be received into any such home after 
the date of such notice; but nothing in this section shall be 
construed to affect the obligation of the manager to comply with, all

<pagefootnote><pagenum>750</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the requirements of this Act and the rules, regulations, directions 
and orders thereunder until the certificate ceases to take effect 
under sub- section (1).

CHAP 
MANAGEMENT OF RECOGNISED HOMES

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT OF RECOGNISED HOMES



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966487</tid>
<number> 20</number> Managing committee.
<section><tid>1370893</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a managing committee  
in charge of the management of every recognised home and the members 
of the managing committee shall appoint a member thereof to be the 
manager of such home for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>731292</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution, powers and functions of the managing com- 
mittee and the term of office of the members thereof shall be such 
as may be provided in the constitution pertaining to such home.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>672643</tid>
<number>21</number>Duty of manager. It shall be the duty of the manager to 
comply with all the requirements of this Act and the rules, 
regulations, directions and orders thereunder in respect of every 
woman or child admitted into the recognised home until the woman is 
rehabilitated or the child completes the age of eighteen years or 
until the certificate ceases to have effect.

</article>



<article><tid>1493310</tid>
<number> 22</number> Discharge of inmates of home.
<section><tid>845493</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
regulations, if any, made by the Board, if the managing committee of a 
home is satisfied that an inmate of the home has become fit to earn 
his or her livelihood or is otherwise fit to be discharged from the 
home, the manager may discharge such inmate.

</section>

<section><tid>816454</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), no 
female inmate of a home shall be discharged or given in marriage or 
entrusted to the care of any other person unless such female has made 
a declaration before the Board or an officer specified by it in this 
behalf that she consents to such discharge, marriage or entrustment, 
as the case may be, and, if the inmate to be given in marriage is a 
minor, unless the Board or officer, as the case may be, has, after 
recording the reasons in writing, given its or his approval thereto.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>938906</tid>
<number>23</number>Reports regarding deaths of inmates. The manager shall, 
immediately after the occurrence of any death among the inmates of the 
home, send a written report thereof to the Board explaining the cause 
of death to the best of his knowledge.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>751</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP 
MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS


</article>



<article><tid>1085848</tid>
<number>24</number>Penalties. Any person who fails to comply with any of the 
provisions of this Act or of any rule, regulation, direction or order 
thereunder or any of the conditions of a certificate shall be 
punishable in the case of a first offence with imprisonment which may 
extend to three months or with fine which may extend to two hundred 
and fifty rupees or with both, and in the case. of a second or 
subsequent offence, with imprisonment which may extend to six months 
or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.

</article>



<article><tid>1513301</tid>
<number>25</number>Sanction for prosecutions. No prosecution under this Act 
shall be instituted except with the previous sanction of the District 
Magistrate or the Chief Presidency Magistrate, as the case may be.

</article>



<article><tid>1361845</tid>
<number>26</number>Persons performing functions under Act to be public 
servants. The members of the Board and every person empowered by the 
Board to exercise any of its powers under this Act shall be deemed to 
be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>),

</article>



<article><tid>1885645</tid>
<number>27</number>Protection of acts done in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person who performs 
any function under this Act for anything done or intended to be done 
in good faith under this Act or any rule, regulation direction or 
order thereunder.

</article>



<article><tid>958325</tid>
<number> 28</number> 
<section><tid>1693191</tid>
<number>1</number>Power of State Government to exempt homes. If, after  
consultation with the Board, the State, Government is satisfied that 
the circumstances in relation to any class of homes or any home are 
such that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, and for reasons to be specified 
therein, exempt, subject to such conditions, restrictions or 
limitations, if any, as it may think fit to impose, such class of 
homes or home, as the case may be, from the operation of all or any of 
the provisions of this Act or of any rule or regulation made there- 
under.

</section>

<section><tid>1282895</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification issued under this section granting an 
exemption shall be reviewed in consultation with the Board at 
intervals not exceeding two years, but nothing herein contained shall 
affect the power of the State Government to amend, vary or rescind any 
such notification at any time in consultation with the Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>752</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>842016</tid>
<number> 29</number> 
<section><tid>276116</tid>
<number>1</number>Power of State Government to make rules. The State  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>895650</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1219360</tid>
<number>a</number>all matters relating to, or in connection with, 
elections, to the Board under clause (b) of sub- section (2) 
of section 5 and the election of the Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1549917</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and 
the procedure to be followed in removing a member who is or 
becomes subject to any disqualification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1043</tid>
<number>c</number>the funds of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>144057</tid>
<number>d</number>the travelling and other allowances to be drawn by 
members of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1328289</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of staff for enabling the Board to 
perform its functions efficiently under this Act and their 
recruitment and conditions of service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>106745</tid>
<number>f</number>the calling of returns and other information by the 
State Government from the Board and the managing committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>953377</tid>
<number>g</number>the form in which an application for certificate of 
recognition may be made, the particulars to be contained in 
such application and the form in which, and the conditions 
subject to which, such certificate may be granted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1678434</tid>
<number>h</number>the maintenance of registers and accounts by the Board 
and the audit of its accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1017147</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1914614</tid>
<number>3</number>All rules made under this Act shall, as soon as may be after 
they are made, be laid before the State Legislature.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1593717</tid>
<number> 30</number> Power of the Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>1780673</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may,  
with the previous approval of the State Government, by notification in 
the, Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act 
and the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to perform its functions 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>851150</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all. or any of 
the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1984292</tid>
<number>a</number>the time and place of the meetings of the Board, the 
procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction of 
business at such meetings and the quorum necessary for the 
transaction of business at such meetings;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>753</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300657</tid>
<number>b</number>the maintenance of the minutes of meetings of the Board 
and the transmission of copies thereof to the State 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1180014</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment of sub- committees and local committees 
and of persons by the Board for the purpose of assisting it 
in performing its functions under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1558899</tid>
<number>d</number>the supervision and control of the management of 
recognised homes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1763805</tid>
<number>e</number>the inspection of homes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>58117</tid>
<number>f</number>the calling of returns and other information by the 
Board from managing committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1313090</tid>
<number>g</number>the reception, care, treatment, maintenance, 
protection, training, welfare, instruction, control and 
discipline of inmates in recognised homes.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1638269</tid>
<number>h</number>visits to, and communication with, inmates of 
recognised homes and the grant of permission to such inmates 
to absent themselves for short periods;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1705589</tid>
<number>i</number>the discharge of inmates from recognised homes, their 
transfer from one recognised home to another and the reports 
to be sent by managers to the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>674069</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in 
the opinion of the Board, necessary for the efficient super- 
vision and control of homes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1584428</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend, vary or rescind any regulation which it has approved; 
and thereupon the regulation shall have effect accordingly, but 
without prejudice to the exercise of the powers of the Board under 
sub- section (1).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1278525</tid>
<number> 31</number> Repeals and savings.
<section><tid>329151</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the date of the coming  
into force in any State of this Act, the Women' s and Children' s 
Institutions (Licensing) Act, <year>1956</year> (105 of <year>1956</year>), or any other Act 
corresponding to this Act in force in that State immediately before 
such commencement, shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1851915</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken (including any direction given, any register or rule or order  
  made or any restriction imposed) under the aid Act shall, in so far 
as such thing or action is not inconsistent with the provisions of 
this Act be deemed to have been done or taken under the provisions 
aforesaid, as if they were in force when such thing was done or such 
action was taken, and shall continue in force accordingly until super- 
seded by anything done or any action taken under this Act.
PART 
PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1202481</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Bombay Reorganisation 
Act, <year>1960</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>181272</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>593182</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of May, <year>1960</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>88964</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1497528</tid>
<number>c</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1672914</tid>
<number>d</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having, immediately before the appointed 
day, the force of law in the whole or in any part of 
the State of Bombay;

</section>

<section><tid>1749835</tid>
<number>e</number>" notified order" means an order published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>750226</tid>
<number>f</number>" population ratio", in relation to the States of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat, means the ratio of 66. 31 to 
33. 69;

</section>

<section><tid>1589699</tid>
<number>g</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of the State of 
Bombay, means a person who, immediately before the 
appointed day, is a member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>1539027</tid>
<number>h</number>" transferred territory" means the territories which, as 
from the appointed day, are the territories of the 
State of Gujarat;

</section>

<section><tid>1363831</tid>
<number>i</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>578</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1400190</tid>
<number>j</number>any reference to a district, taluka, village or other 
territorial division of the State of Bombay shall be 
construed as a reference to the area comprised within 
that territorial division as recognised for land 
revenue purposes on the 1st day of December, <year>1959</year>.
PART 
REORGANISATION OF BOMBAY STATE

PART II

REORGANISATION OF BOMBAY STATE



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>147444</tid>
<number> 3</number> Formation of Gujarat State.
<section><tid>1447707</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day,  
there shall be formed a new State to be known as the State of Gujarat 
comprising the following territories of the State of Bombay, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1172845</tid>
<number>a</number>Banaskantha, Mehsana, Sabarkantha, Ahmedabad, Kaira, 
Panch- mahals, Baroda, Broach, Surat, Dangs, Amreli, 
Surendranagar, Rajkot, Jamnagar, Junagadh, Bhavnagar 
and Kutch districts; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1052103</tid>
<number>b</number>the villages in Umbergaon taluka of Thana district, the 
villages in Nawapur and Nandurbar talukas of West 
Khandesh district and the villages in Akkalkuwa and 
Taloda talukas of West Khandesh district, respectively 
specified in Parts I, II and III of the First Schedule;
and thereupon, the said territories shall cease to form part of the 
State of Bombay, and the residuary State of Bombay shall be known as 
the State of Maharashtra.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>531241</tid>
<number>2</number>The villages in Umbergaon taluka specified in Part I of the 
First Schedule shall form a separate taluka of the same name and be 
included in Surat district, and the remaining villages in the said 
taluka shall be included in, and form part of, Dahanu taluka of Thana 
district; and the villages specified in Parts II and III of the First 
Schedule shall respectively be included in, and form part of, Songadh 
taluka of Surat district and Sagbara taluka of Broach district.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297354</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of the first Schedule to the Constitution. As from 
the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under 
the heading" 1. THE STATES",--
<section><tid>76236</tid>
<number>a</number>for entry 4, the following entry shall be substituted, 
namely:--
" 4. Gujarat.. The territories referred to in sub- section 
 (1) of section 3 of the Bombay 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1960</year>.";


<pagefootnote><pagenum>579</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1509191</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 7, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 8. Maharashtra. The territories specified in sub- section 
 (1) of section 8 of the States 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>, but excluding 
the territories referred to in sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the Bombay 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1960</year>"; and


</section>

<section><tid>650278</tid>
<number>c</number>entries 8 to 14 shall be renumbered as entries 9 to 15 
respectively.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1921619</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving powers of State Government. Nothing in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part shall be deemed to affect the power of the 
State Government to alter, after the appointed day, the name, extent 
or boundaries of any district, taluka or village in the State.
PART 
REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States


</article>



<article><tid>960322</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. As from 
the appointed day, there shall be allotted 19 seats to the State of 
Maharashtra, and 11 seats to the State of Gujarat, in the Council of 
States, and in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the Table,- 
-
<section><tid>1408395</tid>
<number>a</number>for entry 4, the following entry shall be substituted, 
namely:--
" 4. Gujarat.... 11";


</section>

<section><tid>1500776</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 7, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 8. Maharashtra.. 19";


</section>

<section><tid>1246234</tid>
<number>c</number>entries 8 to 18 shall be renumbered as entries 9 to 19 
respectively; and

</section>

<section><tid>1312006</tid>
<number>d</number>for the figures" 221" the figures" 224" shall be 
substituted.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>867296</tid>
<number> 7</number> Allocation of sitting members.
<section><tid>303089</tid>
<number>1</number>The twelve sitting members  
of the Council of States representing the State of Bombay, whose names 
are specified in Part I of the Second Schedule, and such six of the 
nine sitting members

<pagefootnote><pagenum>580</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

elected to represent that State at the biennial elections held for the 
purpose of filling the vacancies existing on the 3rd day of April, 
<year>1960</year>, as the Chairman of the Council of States shall by order specify 
shall, as from the appointed day, be deemed to have been duly elected 
to fill eighteen of the nineteen seats allotted to the State of 
Maharashtra.


</section>

<section><tid>739892</tid>
<number>2</number>The five sitting members of the Council of States 
representing the State of Bombay, whose names are specified in Part II 
of the Second Schedule, and the remaining three of the nine members 
elected at the said biennial elections shall, as from the appointed 
day, be deemed to have been duly elected to fill eight of the eleven 
seats allotted to the State of Gujarat.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>853101</tid>
<number>8</number>Bye- elections to fill vacancies. As soon as may be after the 
appointed day, bye- elections shall be held to fill the additional 
seats allotted to the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat as well as the 
existing casual vacancy in the seats allotted to the State of Gujarat.

</article>



<article><tid>1024294</tid>
<number> 9</number> Term of office,
<section><tid>1763596</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of the sitting members  
and of the member chosen to fill the casual vacancy shall remain 
unaltered.

</section>

<section><tid>795311</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the member elected to fill the one 
additional seat allotted to the State of Maharashtra shall expire on 
the 2nd day of April, <year>1966</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>678009</tid>
<number>3</number>Out of the two members elected to fill the two additional 
seats allotted to the State of Gujarat, the term of office of that 
member who, at the counting of votes, is last declared elected, or if 
an equality of votes is found to exist, the term of office of such one 
of them as the returning officer shall decide by lot, shall expire on 
the 2nd day of April, <year>1964</year> and the term of office of the other member 
shall expire on the 2nd day of April, <year>1966</year>.
The House of the People



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635444</tid>
<number> 10</number> Representation in the House of the People. As from the 
appointed day, there shall be allotted 44 seats to the State of 
Maharashtra, and 22 seats to the State of Gujarat, in the House of the 
People, and in the First Schedule to the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>).--
<section><tid>694671</tid>
<number>a</number>for entry 4, the following entry shall be substituted, 
namely:--
" 4. Gujarat... 22";


<pagefootnote><pagenum>581</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1604741</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 7, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 8. Maharashtra.. 44"; and


</section>

<section><tid>1144372</tid>
<number>c</number>entries 8 to 22 shall be renumbered as entries 9 to 23 
respectively.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>509897</tid>
<number>11</number>Delimitation of Parliamentary Constituencies. As from the 
appointed day, the First Schedule to the Delimitation of Parliamentary 
and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, shall stand amended as 
directed in the Third Schedule to this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>552679</tid>
<number>12</number>Provision as to sitting members. Every sitting member of the 
House of the People representing a constituency which, on the 
appointed day, by virtue of the provisions of section 11, stands 
allotted, with or without alteration of boundaries, to the State of 
Maharashtra or to the State of Gujarat, shall be deemed to have been 
elected to the House of the People by that constituency as so 
allotted.
The Legislative Assemblies


</article>



<article><tid>781348</tid>
<number> 13</number> Strength of Legislative Assemblies. As from the appointed 
day, the total number of seats to be filled by persons chosen by 
direct election in the Legislative Assemblies of Maharashtra and 
Gujarat shall be 264 and 132 respectively, and in the Second Schedule 
to the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>).--
<section><tid>1807611</tid>
<number>a</number>for entry 4, the following entry shall be substituted, 
namely:--
" 4. Gujarat... 132";


</section>

<section><tid>1779314</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 7, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 8. Maharashtra.. 264"; and


</section>

<section><tid>970280</tid>
<number>c</number>entries 8 to 13 shall be renumbered as entries 9 to 14 
respectively.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1781662</tid>
<number>14</number>Delimitation of assembly constituencies. As from the 
appointed day, the Second Schedule to the Delimitation of 
Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, shall stand 
amended as directed in the Fourth Schedule to this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>431508</tid>
<number> 15</number> Allocation of members.
<section><tid>1678632</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sitting member of the  
Legislative Assembly of Bombay representing a constituency which on 
the appointed day by virtue of the provisions of section 14 stands 
transferred, whether with

<pagefootnote><pagenum>582</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or without alteration of boundaries, to the State of Gujarat shall, as 
from that day, cease to be a member of the Legislative Assembly of 
Bombay and shall be deemed to have been elected to the Legislative 
Assembly of Gujarat by that constituency as so transferred.


</section>

<section><tid>986423</tid>
<number>2</number>All other sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of 
Bombay shall become members of the Legislative Assembly of Maharashtra 
and any such sitting member representing a constituency the extent or 
the name and extent of which are altered by virtue of the provisions 
of section 14 shall be deemed to have been elected to the Legislative 
Assembly of Maharashtra by that Constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>604516</tid>
<number>3</number>The sitting member of the Legislative Assembly of Bombay 
nominated to that Assembly under article 333 to represent the Anglo- 
Indian community shall be deemed to have been nominated to represent 
the said community in the Legislative Assembly of Maharashtra under 
that article.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>356051</tid>
<number> 16</number> Duration of Legislative Assemblies. The period of five years 
referred to in clause
<section><tid>1571275</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 172 of the Constitution shall, in  
the case of the Legislative Assembly of Maharashtra or Gujarat, be 
deemed to have commenced on the date on which it actually commenced in 
the case of the Legislative Assembly of Bombay.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315467</tid>
<number> 17</number> Speakers and Deputy Speakers.
<section><tid>1503058</tid>
<number>1</number>The persons who immediately  
before the appointed day are the Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the 
Legislative Assembly of Bombay shall be the Speaker and Deputy Speaker 
respectively of the Legislative Assembly of Maharashtra.

</section>

<section><tid>1519483</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Legislative 
Assembly of Gujarat shall choose two members of that Assembly to be 
respectively Speaker and Deputy Speaker thereof and until they are so 
chosen, the duties of the office of Speaker shall be performed by such 
member of the Assembly as the Governor may appoint for the purpose.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739824</tid>
<number> 18</number> Rules of procedure. The rules as to procedure and conduct of 
business in force immediately before the appointed day with respect to 
the Legislative Assembly of Bombay shall, until rules are made under 
clause
<section><tid>1650236</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 208, have effect in relation to the Legislative  
Assembly of Maharashtra or of Gujarat, subject to such modifications 
and adaptations as may be made therein by the Speaker thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>583</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1703200</tid>
<number> 19</number> Special provisions in relation to Gujarat Legislative 
Assembly.
<section><tid>1797809</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of  
Gujarat to be filled by persons chosen by direct election on the 
expiration of the duration of that Assembly under section 16 or on its 
dissolution shall be increased from 132 to 154; and accordingly, as 
from the date of such expiration or dissolution, in the Second 
Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), 
in entry 4, for the figures" 132", the figures" 154" shall be 
substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1797802</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of sub- 
section (1), the Election Commission shall determine in the manner 
hereinafter provided--

<subsection><tid>928504</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of seats to be reserved for the scheduled 
castes and the scheduled tribes of the State in the 
Legislative Assembly, having regard to the relevant 
provisions of the Constitution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1915980</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the assembly constituencies into which the State 
shall be divided, the extent of each of such 
constituencies and in which of them seats shall be 
reserved for the scheduled castes or for the scheduled 
tribes; and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>945995</tid>
<number>c</number>the adjustments in the boundaries and description of the 
extent of the parliamentary constituencies in the State 
that may be necessary or expedient.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1656128</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In determining the matters referred to in clauses (b) and 
 (c) of sub- section (2), the Election Commission shall have regard to 
the following provisions, namely:--

<subsection><tid>178564</tid>
<number>a</number>all the constituencies shall be single- member 
constituencies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>84861</tid>
<number>b</number>all the constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas and in delimiting them 
regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
boundaries of administrative units, facilities of 
communication and public convenience; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444060</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved either for 
the scheduled castes or for the scheduled tribes shall, 
as far as practicable, be located in the areas in which 
the population of the scheduled castes or, as the case 
may be, of the scheduled tribes is most concentrated, 
but in regard to scheduled castes, care should be taken 
to distribute the reserved seats in different areas of 
the State.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>584</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1961</year>, s. 6, for cl. (b) 
2. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for sub- section (3).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>835035</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of assisting the Election Commission in the 
performance of its functions under sub- section (2), the Commission 
shall associate with itself such five persons as the Central 
Government shall by order specify, being persons who are members 
either of the Legislative Assembly of the State or of the House of the 
People representing the State:
Provided that none of the said associate members shall have a 
right to vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.


</section>

<section><tid>1546253</tid>
<number>5</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>1662888</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals in regard to matters mentioned in 
sub- section (2) in the Official Gazette of the State 
together with a notice specifying the date on or after 
which the proposals will be further considered by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>762504</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified, and 
for the purpose of such consideration, hold one or more 
public sittings at such place or places as it thinks 
fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>427255</tid>
<number>c</number>make an order revising to such extent as may be 
necessary or expedient the Schedules to the 
Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly 
Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, in so far as they relate to 
the State; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1769348</tid>
<number>d</number>send authenticated copies of the order to the Central 
Government and to the State Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1419861</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be after the said order is received by the 
Central Government or the State Government, it shall be laid before 
the House of the People or, as the case may be, the Legislative 
Assembly of the State.

</section>

<section><tid>1693436</tid>
<number>7</number>An order made by the Election Commission under this section 
shall have the full force of law and shall not be called in question 
in any court.
The Legislative Council



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966487</tid>
<number>20</number>Amendment of article 168 of the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in article 168 of the Constitution, in sub- clause (a) 
of clause 1, the word" Bombay" shall be omitted, and after the word 
" Madras", the word" Maharashtra" shall be inserted.

</article>



<article><tid>672643</tid>
<number> 21</number> Legislative Council of Maharashtra. As from the appointed 
day, there shall be 78 seats in the Legislative Council of 
Maharashtra, and in the Third Schedule to the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>).--

<pagefootnote><pagenum>584A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>1894911</tid>
<number>a</number>the entry No. 3 relating to Bombay shall be omitted and 
the existing entries 4 and 5 shall be renumbered as 
entries 3 and 4 respectively;

</section>

<section><tid>918880</tid>
<number>b</number>after the entry relating to Madras, the following entry 
shall be inserted, namely:--
" 5. Maharashtra. 78 22 7 7 30 12.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1493310</tid>
<number>22</number>Council constituencies. As from the appointed day, the 
Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Bombay) Order, <year>1951</year> shall 
stand amended as directed in the Fifth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>585</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>938906</tid>
<number> 23</number> Provision as to certain sitting members.
<section><tid>832628</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed  
day--

<subsection><tid>261592</tid>
<number>a</number>the sitting members of the Legislative Council of Bombay 
specified in the Sixth Schedule shall cease to be 
members of that Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>780707</tid>
<number>b</number>all other sitting members of that Council shall become 
members of the Legislative Council of Maharashtra and 
any such sitting member representing a council 
constituency the extent of which is altered by virtue 
of the provisions of section 22 shall be deemed to have 
been elected to the Legislative Council of Maharashtra 
by that constituency as so altered.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1788568</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members referred to in clause (b) 
of sub- section (1) shall remain unaltered.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1085848</tid>
<number> 24</number> Special provision as to biennial elections.
<section><tid>7943</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 16 of the Representation 
of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>), no notification under that 
section shall be published before the appointed day for holding 
biennial elections to fill the seats of members of the Legislative 
Council of Bombay, retiring on the expiration of their term of office 
on the 24th day of April, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>537840</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members of the said Council elected 
to fill the vacancies at the said biennial elections shall expire on 
the 24th day of April, <year>1960</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1513301</tid>
<number> 25</number> Chairman and Deputy Chairman.
<section><tid>679394</tid>
<number>1</number>The person who immediately  
before the appointed day is the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative 
Council of Bombay shall be the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative 
Council of Maharashtra.

</section>

<section><tid>1751880</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the completion of the biennial 
elections referred to in section 24, the Legislative Council of 
Maharashtra shall choose one of its members to be the Chairman 
thereof.
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1361845</tid>
<number>26</number>Amendment of the Scheduled Castes Order. As from the 
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Seventh Schedule.

</article>



<article><tid>1885645</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of the Scheduled Tribes Order. As from the 
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Eighth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>586</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART 
HIGH COURTS

PART IV

HIGH COURTS


</article>



<article><tid>958325</tid>
<number> 28</number> High Court for Gujarat.
<section><tid>1693191</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day, there  
shall be a separate High Court for the State of Gujarat (hereinafter  
  referred to as" the High Court of Gujarat") and the High Court of 
Bombay shall become the High Court for the State of Maharashtra 
 (hereinafter referred to as the High Court at Bombay).

</section>

<section><tid>1282895</tid>
<number>2</number>The principal seat of the High Court of Gujarat shall be at 
such place as the President may, by notified order, appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>400489</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Gujarat may sit at 
such other place or places in the State of Gujarat other than its 
principal seat as the Chief Justice may, with the approval of the 
Governor of Gujarat, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>842016</tid>
<number> 29</number> Judges of Gujarat High Court.
<section><tid>276116</tid>
<number>1</number>Such of the Judges of the  
High Court of Bombay holding office immediately before the appointed 
day as may be determined by the President shall on that day cease to 
be Judges of the High Court at Bombay and become Judges of the High 
Court of Gujarat.

</section>

<section><tid>895650</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons who by virtue of sub- section (1) become Judges of 
the High Court of Gujarat shall, except in the case where any such 
person is appointed to be the Chief Justice of that High Court, rank 
in that Court according to the priority of their respective 
appointments as Judges of the High Court of Bombay.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1593717</tid>
<number>30</number>Jurisdiction of Gujarat High Court. The High Court of Gujarat 
shall have, in respect of any part of the territories included in the 
State of Gujarat, all such jurisdiction, powers and authority as, 
under the law in force immediately before the appointed day, are 
exercisable in respect of that part of the said territories by the 
High Court of Bombay.

</article>



<article><tid>1278525</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to enrol advocates, etc.
<section><tid>329151</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Court of Gujarat  
shall have the like powers to approve, admit, enrol, remove and 
suspend advocates and attorneys, and to make rules with respect to 
advocates and attorneys, as are, under the law in force immediately 
before the appointed day, exercisable by the High Court of Bombay.

</section>

<section><tid>1851915</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of audience in the High Court of Gujarat shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles as, immediately

<pagefootnote><pagenum>587</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of 
audience in the High Court of Bombay:

Provided that, subject to any rule made or direction given by the 
High Court of Gujarat in exercise of the powers conferred by this 
section, any person who immediately before the appointed day is an 
advocate entitled to practise, or an attorney entitled to act, in the 
High Court of Bombay shall be recognised as an advocate or an attorney 
entitled to practise or to act, as the case may be, in the High Court 
of Gujarat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>432801</tid>
<number>32</number>Practice and procedure in Gujarat High Court. Subject to the 
provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Bombay shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation 
to the High Court of Gujarat, and accordingly, the High Court of 
Gujarat shall have all such powers to make rules and orders with 
respect to practice and procedure as are immediately before the 
appointed day exercisable by the High Court of Bombay:
Provided that any rules or orders which are in force immediately 
before the appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the 
High Court of Bombay shall, until varied or revoked by rules or orders 
made by the High Court of Gujarat, apply with the necessary 
modifications in relation to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Gujarat as if made by that Court.


</article>



<article><tid>277267</tid>
<number>33</number>Custody of seal of Gujarat High Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custoday of 
the seal of the High Court of Bombay shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply with respect to the custoday of the seal of the 
High Courd of Gujarat.

</article>



<article><tid>725165</tid>
<number>34</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of 
Bombay shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with respect to 
the form of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the 
High Court of Gujarat.

</article>



<article><tid>1994789</tid>
<number>35</number>Power of Judges. The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day relating to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Bombay and with 
respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those powers 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the High 
Court of Gujarat.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>588</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1100431</tid>
<number>36</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Bombay and the Judges and 
division courts thereof shall, with the necessary modifications, apply 
in relation to the High Court of Gujarat.

</article>



<article><tid>856628</tid>
<number> 37</number> Transfer of proceedings from Bombay High Court to Gujarat 
High Court.
<section><tid>1741501</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided, the High Court at  
Bombay shall, as from the appointed day, have no jurisdiction in 
respect of the transferred territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1920633</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Bombay 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified, whether before 
or after that day, by the Chief Justice of that High Court, having 
regard to the place of accrual of the cause of action and other 
circumstances, to be proceedings which ought to be heard and decided 
by the High Court of Gujarat shall, as soon as may be after such 
certification, be transferred to the High Court of Gujarat.

</section>

<section><tid>750770</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2) of this section or in section 30, but save as hereinafter 
provided, the High Court at Bombay shall have, and the High Court of 
Gujarat shall not have, jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of 
appeals, applications for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, 
applications for review and other proceedings where any such 
proceedings seek any relief in respect of any order passed by the High 
Court of Bombay before the appointed day:
Provided that if after any such proceedings have been entertained 
by the High Court at Bombay, it appears to the Chief Justice of that 
High Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court of 
Gujarat, he shall order that they shall be so transferred, and such 
proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>287479</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court of Bombay--

<subsection><tid>599372</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day, in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court of Gujarat by virtue of sub- section 
 (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>620308</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
at Bombay retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section 
 (3),
shall for all purposes have effect, not only as an order of the High 
Court at Bombay, but also as an order made by the High Court of 
Gujarat.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>589</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>42038</tid>
<number>38</number>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to 
Gujarat High Court. Any person, who, immediately before the appointed 
day, is an advocate entitled to practise, or an attorney entitled to 
act, in the High Court of Bombay and was authorised to appear or to 
act in any proceedings transferred from that High Court to the High 
Court of Gujarat under section 37, shall have the right to appear or 
to act, as the case may be, in the High Court of Gujarat in relation 
to those proceedings.

</article>



<article><tid>1315240</tid>
<number> 39</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of section 37--
<section><tid>410879</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court 
until that court has disposed of all issues between the 
parties, including any issues with respect to the 
taxation of the costs of the proceedings and shall 
include appeals, applications for leave to appeal to 
the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions 
for revision and petitions for writs;

</section>

<section><tid>390689</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgement or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1407835</tid>
<number>40</number>Savings. Nothing in this Part shall affect the application to 
the High Court of Gujarat of any provisions of the Constitution, and 
this Part shall have effect subject to any provision that may be made 
on or after the appointed day with respect to that High Court by any 
Legislature or other authority having power to make such provision.

</article>



<article><tid>173002</tid>
<number>41</number>Permanent Bench of Bombay High Court at Nagpur. Without 
prejudice to the provisions of section 51 of the States Reorganisation 
Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>), such Judges of the High Court at Bombay, 
being not less than three in number, as the Chief Justice may from 
time to time nominate, shall sit at Nagpur in order to exercise the 
jurisdiction and power for the time being vested in that High Court in 
respect of cases arising in the districts of Buldana, Akola, Amravati, 
Yeotmal, Wardha, Nagpur, Bhandara, Chanda and Rajura:
Provided that the Chief Justice may, in his discretion, order 
that any case arising in any such district shall be heard at Bombay.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>590</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART 
AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE


</article>



<article><tid>721265</tid>
<number>42</number>Authorisation of expenditure of Gujarat State. The Governor 
of Bombay may, at any time before the appointed day, authorise such 
expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Gujarat as he 
deems necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning 
with the appointed day pending the sanction of such expenditure by the 
Legislature of the State of Gujarat:
Provided that the Governor of Gujarat may, after the appointed 
day, authorise such further expenditure as he deems necessary from the 
Consolidated Fund of the State of Gujarat for any period not extending 
beyond the said period of six months.


</article>



<article><tid>597996</tid>
<number> 43</number> Reports relating to accounts of Bombay State.
<section><tid>521762</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports  
of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India referred to in clause 
 (2) of article 151 relating to the accounts of the State of Bombay in 
respect of any period prior to the appointed day shall be submitted to 
the Governor of each of the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat who 
shall cause them to be laid before the Legislature of the State.

</section>

<section><tid>1569184</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may by order--

<subsection><tid>463587</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated 
Fund of Bombay on any service in respect of any period 
prior to the appointed day during the financial year 
<year>1960</year>- 61 or in respect of any earlier financial year in 
excess of the amount granted for that service and for 
that year as disclosed in the reports referred to in 
sub- section (1) to have been duly authorised, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1501997</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising 
out of the said reports.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429838</tid>
<number>44</number>Allowances and privileges of Governor of Gujarat. The 
allowances and privileges of the Governor of Gujarat shall, until 
provision in that behalf is made by Parliament by law under clause (3) 
of article 158, be such as the President may, by order, determine.

</article>



<article><tid>719438</tid>
<number> 45</number> Distribution of revenues.
<section><tid>1095638</tid>
<number>1</number>Section 3 of the Union Duties  
of Excise (Distribution) Act, <year>1957</year> (55 of <year>1957</year>), sections 3 and 5 of 
the Estate Duty and Tax on Railway Passenger Fares (Distribution) Act, 
 <year>1957</year> (57 of <year>1957</year>), section 4 of, and the Second Schedule to, the 
Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> 
 (58 of <year>1957</year>), and paragraph 3 of the Constitution (Distribution of  
  Revenues) No. 2 Order, <year>1957</year>, shall have effect subject to such 
modifications as are specified in the Ninth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>591</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>997355</tid>
<number>2</number>The total amount payable to the State of Maharashtra under 
the enactments and Order referred to in sub- section (1) in respect of 
the part of the financial year <year>1960</year>- 61 beginning with the appointed 
day and in respect of the financial year <year>1961</year>- 62 shall be reduced by a 
sum of 602 lakhs of rupees and 614 lakhs of rupees, respectively and 
the total amount payable to the State of Gujarat, under those 
enactments and Order in respect of each of those periods shall be 
correspondingly increased.
PART 
APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>581737</tid>
<number>46</number>Application of Part. The provisions of this Part shall apply 
in relation to the apportionment of the assets and liabilities of the 
State of Bombay immediately before the appointed day.

</article>



<article><tid>1817661</tid>
<number> 47</number> Land and goods.
<section><tid>124462</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this  
Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods belonging to 
the State of Bombay shall,--

<subsection><tid>1356325</tid>
<number>a</number>if within the transferred territory, pass to the State 
of Gujarat; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1214983</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, remain the property of the State of 
Maharashtra:
Provided that where the Central Government is of opinion that any 
goods or class of goods should be distributed otherwise than according 
to the situation of the goods, the Central Government may issue such 
directions as it thinks fit for a just and equitable distribution of 
the goods and the goods shall remain the property of the State of 
Maharashtra or, as the case may be, pass to the State of Gujarat, 
accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>610900</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such stores of the State of Bombay as are referred to in 
the Tenth Schedule shall be divided between the States of Maharashtra 
and Gujarat in the manner specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>440002</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable 
property of every kind and any rights in or over such property, and 
the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes and currency 
notes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>592</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1466770</tid>
<number>48</number>Treasury and bank balances. The total of the cash balances in 
all treasuries of the State of Bombay and the credit balances of that 
State with the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India and the 
State Bank of Saurashtra immediately before the appointed day shall be 
divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat according to the 
population ratio:
Provided that for the purposes of such division, there shall be 
no transfer of cash balances from any treasury to any other treasury 
and the apportionment shall be effected by adjusting the credit 
balances of the two States in the books of the Reserve Bank of India 
on the appointed day:

Provided further that if the State of Gujarat has no account on 
the appointed day with the Reserve Bank of India, the adjustment shall 
be made in such manner as the Central Government may, by order, 
direct.


</article>



<article><tid>455115</tid>
<number>49</number>Arrears of taxes. The right to recover arrears of any tax or 
duty on property, including arrears of land revenue, shall belong to 
the State in which the property is situated, and the right to recover 
arrears of any other tax or duty shall belong to the State in whose 
territories the place of assessment of that tax or duty is included on 
the appointed day:
Provided that any sum recovered after the appointed day in 
respect of any arrears of tax accruing during the period between the 
 1st day of January, <year>1960</year>, and the 30th day of April, <year>1960</year> (both days  
  inclusive) under the Central Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year> (74 of <year>1956</year>), or the 
Bombay Sales Tax Act, <year>1959</year> (Bom. Act LI of <year>1959</year>), shall, after 
deducting the cost of collection thereof, be divided between the 
States of Maharashtra and Gujarat according to the population ratio.


</article>



<article><tid>1891103</tid>
<number> 50</number> Right to recover loans and advances.
<section><tid>1021284</tid>
<number>1</number>The right of the  
State of Bombay to recover any loans or advances made before the 
appointed day to any local body, society, agriculturist or other 
person in an area within that State shall belong to the State in which 
that area is included on that day.

</section>

<section><tid>765868</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of the State of Bombay to recover any loans or 
advances made before the appointed day to any person or institution 
outside that State shall belong to the State of Maharashtra:
Provided that any sum recovered in respect of any such loan or 
advance shall be divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat 
according to the population ratio.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>593</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1617827</tid>
<number> 51</number> Credits in certain funds.
<section><tid>81190</tid>
<number>1</number>Out of the investments of the  
State of Bombay made before the appointed day in the cash balance 
investment account of the State, such securities of the value of ten 
crores of rupees, as the Central Government may by order specify, 
shall pass to the State of Gujarat in connection with the construction 
of a capital for that State; and the remaining investments in the said 
account shall be divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat 
according to the population ratio.

</section>

<section><tid>676218</tid>
<number>2</number>The investments of the State of Bombay immediately before the 
appointed day in the State Famine Relief Fund, the State Road Fund, 
the Fund for Development Schemes, the Insurance Fund, the Bombay State 
Milk Fund, the Securities Adjustment Reserve Fund and any other 
general fund and the sums at the credit of that State in the Central 
Road Fund shall be divided between the States of Maharashtra and 
Gujarat according to the population ratio.

</section>

<section><tid>1509845</tid>
<number>3</number>The investments of the State of Bombay immediately before the 
appointed day in the Dangs District Reserve Fund, the Port Reserve 
Fund, the Port Development Fund and the Anand Institute Fund shall 
pass to the State of Gujarat and the investments in any other special 
fund the objects of which are confined to a local area shall belong to 
the State in which that area is included on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1909792</tid>
<number>4</number>The investments of the State of Bombay immediately before the 
appointed day in any private commercial or industrial undertaking, in 
so far as such investments have not been made or are deemed not to 
have been made from the cash balance investment account, shall pass to 
the State in which the principal seat of business of the undertaking 
is located.

</section>

<section><tid>1781381</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, 
State Act or Provincial Act for the State of Bombay or any part 
thereof has, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an inter- 
State body corporate, the investments in, or loans or advances to, any 
such body corporate by the State of Bombay made before the appointed 
day shall, save as otherwise expressly provided by or under this Act, 
be divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat in the same 
proportion in which the assets of the body corporate are divided under 
the provisions of Part VII.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1403141</tid>
<number> 52</number> Special Revenue Reserve Fund in Gujarat.
<section><tid>708413</tid>
<number>1</number>Out of the  
investments in the cash balance investment account which remain with 
the State of Maharashtra after giving effect to the provisions of 
section 51, such securities of the value of 
1, 420 lakhs of rupees as the Central Government may by order specify 
shall stand transferred to the State of Gujarat.

</section>

<section><tid>1091812</tid>
<number>2</number>There shall be constituted in the State of Gujarat a Fund to 
be called the Special Revenue Reserve Fund consisting of the 
securities transferred to that State under sub- section (1) and such 
other securities belonging to the State of Gujarat of the value of 
1, 419 lakhs of rupees as the Central Government may by order specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1778398</tid>
<number>3</number>From and out of the fund constituted under sub- section (2), 
there shall be transferred as receipts in the revenue account of the 
State of Gujarat in each of the financial years specified in column 1 
of the following Table a sum set out against that year in column 2 
thereof, and in the financial year <year>1969</year>- 70, the balance, if any, 
remaining in that fund:--
TABLE

Financial year Amount in lakhs 
of rupees. 
 1 2 
<year>1962</year>- 63......... 612 
<year>1963</year>- 64......... 585 
<year>1964</year>- 65......... 561 
<year>1965</year>- 66......... 526 
<year>1966</year>- 67......... 433 
<year>1967</year>- 68......... 340 
<year>1968</year>- 69......... 209.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1912739</tid>
<number> 53</number> Assets and liabilities of State undertakings.
<section><tid>651675</tid>
<number>1</number>The assets  
and liabilities relating to any commercial or industrial undertaking 
of the State of Bombay shall pass to the State in which the 
undertaking is located.

</section>

<section><tid>1797799</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a depreciation reserve fund is maintained by the State 
of Bombay for any such commercial or industrial undertaking, the 
securities held in respect of investments made from that fund shall 
pass to the State in which the undertaking is located.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1422201</tid>
<number> 54</number> Public debt.
<section><tid>1420794</tid>
<number>1</number>The public debt of the State of Bombay  
attributable to loans raised by the issue of Government securities and 
outstanding

<pagefootnote><pagenum>595</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

with the public immediately before the appointed day shall, as from 
that day, be the debt of the State of Maharashtra:

Provided that--


<subsection><tid>740851</tid>
<number>a</number>the State of Gujarat shall be liable to pay to the State 
of Maharashtra its share of the sums due from time to 
time for the servicing and repayment of the debt; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1138109</tid>
<number>b</number>for the purpose of determining the said share, the debt 
shall be deemed to be divided between the States of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat as if it were a debt referred 
to in sub- section (2) or sub- section (3), as the case 
may be.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>498670</tid>
<number>2</number>The public debt of the State of Bombay attributable to loans 
taken from the Central Government, the National Co- operative 
Development and Warehousing Board or the Khadi and Village Industries 
Commission or from any other source for the express purpose of re- 
lending the same to a specific institution and outstanding immediately 
before the appointed day shall,--

<subsection><tid>180136</tid>
<number>a</number>if re- lent to any local body, body corporate or other 
institution in any local area, be the debt of the State 
in which the local area is included on the appointed 
day; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>357052</tid>
<number>b</number>if re- lent to the Bombay State Electricity Board, the 
Bombay State Road Transport Corporation, or the Bombay 
Housing Board or any other institution which becomes an 
inter- State institution on the appointed day, be 
divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat 
in the same proportion in which the assets of such body 
corporate or institution are divided under the 
provisions of Part VII.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1474651</tid>
<number>3</number>The remaining public debt of the State of Bombay attributable 
to loans taken from the Central Government, the Reserve Bank of India 
or any other body corporate and outstanding immediately before the 
appointed day shall be divided between the States of Maharashtra and 
Gujarat in proportion to the total expenditure on all capital works 
and other capital outlays incurred or deemed to have been incurred up 
to the appointed day in the territories included respectively in each 
of those States:
Provided that for the purposes of such division, only the 
expenditure on assets for which capital accounts have been kept shall 
be taken into account.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>596</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- Where any expenditure on capital works or other 
capital outlays cannot be allocated between the territories included 
in the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat, such expenditure shall, for 
the purposes of this sub- section, be deemed to have been incurred in 
those territories according to the population ratio.


</section>

<section><tid>511456</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a sinking fund or a depreciation fund is maintained by 
the State of Bombay for repayment of any loan raised by it, the 
securities held in respect of investments made from that fund shall be 
divided between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat in the same 
proportion in which the total public debt is divided between the two 
States under this section.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section, the fund in 
the public account of the State of Bombay known as the Debt Redemption 
and Avoidance Fund shall be deemed to be a sinking fund.


</section>

<section><tid>1522928</tid>
<number>5</number>The share of the State of Gujarat in the liability on account 
of public debt apportioned under sub- section (3) shall be reduced by 
1, 419 lakhs of rupees and the share of the State of Maharashtra in 
such liability shall be correspondingly increased.

</section>

<section><tid>694347</tid>
<number>6</number>In this section, the expression" Government security" means a 
security created and issued by a State Government for the purpose of 
raising a public loan and having any of the forms specified in, or 
prescribed under, clause (2) of section 2 of the Public Debt Act, <year>1944</year> 
 (18 of <year>1944</year>).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1748700</tid>
<number> 55</number> Floating Debt.
<section><tid>1596112</tid>
<number>1</number>The liability of the State of Bombay in  
respect of any floating debt of a Merged State shall be the liability 
of the State in whose territories the area of the Merged State is 
included on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>953011</tid>
<number>2</number>The liability of the State of Bombay in respect of any other 
floating loan to provide short- term finance to any commercial 
undertaking shall be the liability of the State in whose territories 
the undertaking is located.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1521735</tid>
<number>56</number>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of the 
State of Bombay to refund any tax or duty on property, including land 
revenue, collected in excess shall be the liability of the State in 
which the property is situated, and the liability of the State of 
Bombay to refund any other tax or duty

<pagefootnote><pagenum>597</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

collected in excess shall be the liability of the State in whose 
territories the place of assessment of that tax or duty is included:

Provided that the liability to refund any amount after the 
appointed day on account of any excess collected in respect of any tax 
accruing during the period between the 1st day of January, <year>1960</year>, and 
the 30th day of April, <year>1960</year> (both days inclusive) under the Central 
Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year> (74 of <year>1956</year>.), or the Bombay Sales Tax Act, <year>1959</year>, 
 (Bom. Act LI of <year>1959</year>), shall be shared between the two States of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat according to the population ratio.


</article>



<article><tid>1351238</tid>
<number> 57</number> Deposits, etc.
<section><tid>342561</tid>
<number>1</number>The liability of the State of Bombay in  
respect of any civil deposit or local fund deposit shall, as from the 
appointed day, be the liability of the State in whose area the deposit 
has been made.

</section>

<section><tid>1674789</tid>
<number>2</number>The liability of the State of Bombay in respect of any 
charitable or other endowment shall, as from the appointed day, be the 
liability of the State in whose area the institution entitled to the 
benefit of the endowment is located or of the State to which the 
objects of the endowment, under the terms thereof, are confined.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>428035</tid>
<number>58</number>Provident fund. The liability of the State of Bombay in 
respect of the provident fund account of a Government servant in 
service on the appointed day shall, as from that day, be the liability 
of the State to which that Government servant is permanently allotted.

</article>



<article><tid>1356857</tid>
<number>59</number>Pensions. The liability of the State of Bombay in respect of 
pensions shall pass to, or be apportioned between, the States of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat in accordance with the provisions contained in 
the Eleventh Schedule.

</article>



<article><tid>1269003</tid>
<number> 60</number> Contracts.
<section><tid>559227</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, before the appointed day, the State of  
Bombay has made any contract in the exercise of its executive power 
for any purposes of the State, that contract shall be deemed to have 
been made in the exercise of the executive power,--

<subsection><tid>943980</tid>
<number>a</number>if such purposes are, as from that day, exclusively 
purposes of either the State of Maharashtra or the 
State of Gujarat, of that State; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>404071</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, of the State of Maharashtra;
and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue, 
under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they would have 
been rights or liabilities of the State of Bombay, be rights or


<pagefootnote><pagenum>598</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

liabilities of the State of Maharashtra or the State of Gujarat, as 
the case may be:

Provided that in any such case as is referred to in clause (b), 
the initial allocation of rights and liabilities made by this sub- 
section shall be subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed 
upon between the State of Maharashtra and the State of Gujarat or, in 
default of such agreement, as the Central Government may by order 
direct.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1217624</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be 
included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any 
contract--

<subsection><tid>386433</tid>
<number>a</number>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any 
court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the 
contract; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1068389</tid>
<number>b</number>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in 
connection with any such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>392611</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall have effect subject to the other 
provisions of this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities 
in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations; and 
bank balances and securities shall, notwithstanding that they partake 
of the nature of contractual rights, be dealt with under those 
provisions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1801252</tid>
<number> 61</number> Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately 
before the appointed day, the State of Bombay is subject to any 
liability in respect of any actionable wrong other than breach of 
contract, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>1420399</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cause of action arose wholly within the 
territories which, as from that day, are the 
territories of the State of Maharashtra or the State of 
Gujarat, be a liability of that State; and

</section>

<section><tid>681922</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be initially a liability of the State 
of Maharashtra, but subject to such financial 
adjustment as may be agreed upon between the States of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat or, in default of such 
agreement, as the Central Government may by order 
direct.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>299484</tid>
<number> 62</number> Liability as guarantor. Where, immediately before the 
appointed day, the State of Bombay is liable as guarantor in respect 
of any liability of a registered co- operative society or other person, 
that liability shall,--
<section><tid>1497611</tid>
<number>a</number>if the area of operations of such society or person is 
limited to the territories which, as from that day, are 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>599</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

territories of the State of Maharashtra or of the State 
of Gujarat, be a liability of that State; and


</section>

<section><tid>864490</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be initially a liability of the State 
of Maharashtra, subject to such financial adjustment as 
may be agreed upon between the States of Maharashtra 
and Gujarat or, in default of such agreement, as the 
Central Government may by order direct.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1595320</tid>
<number>63</number>Items in suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately 
found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any 
of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in 
accordance with that provision.

</article>



<article><tid>1449381</tid>
<number>64</number>Residuary provision. The benefit or burden of any asset or 
liability of the State of Bombay not dealt with in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part shall pass to the State of Maharashtra in the 
first instance, subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed 
upon between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat before the 1st day 
of April, <year>1961</year> or, in default of such agreement, as the Central 
Government may by order direct.

</article>



<article><tid>20068</tid>
<number>65</number>Apportionment of assets or liabilities by agreement. Where 
the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat agree that the benefit or burden 
of any particular asset or liability should be apportioned between 
them in a manner other than that provided for in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part, then, notwithstanding anything contained 
therein, the benefit or burden of that asset or liability shall be 
apportioned in the manner agreed upon.

</article>



<article><tid>389825</tid>
<number>66</number>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment 
in certain cases. Where, by virtue of any of the provisions of this 
Part, any of the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat becomes entitled to 
any property or obtains any benefits or becomes subject to any 
liability, and the Central Government, on a reference made within a 
period of three years from the appointed day by either of the States, 
is of opinion that it is just and equitable that that property or 
those benefits should be transferred to, or shared with, the other 
State or that a contribution towards that liability should be made by 
the other State, the said property or benefits shall be allocated in 
such manner between the two States, or the other State shall make to 
the State subject to the liability such contribution in respect 
thereof, as the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
two State Governments, by order determine.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>600</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1701382</tid>
<number>67</number>Certain expenditure to be charged on Consolidated Fund. All 
sums payable either by the State of Maharashtra or by the State of 
Gujarat to the other State or by the Central Government to either of 
those States, by virtue of the provisions of this Act, shall be 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the State by which such sums are 
payable or, as the case may be, the Consolidated Fund of India.
PART 
PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS.

PART VII

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS.


</article>



<article><tid>1235696</tid>
<number> 68</number> Provisions as to Bombay State Electricity Board and State 
Warehousing Corporation.
<section><tid>70548</tid>
<number>1</number>The following bodies corporate  
constituted for the State of Bombay, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1539790</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Electricity Board constituted under the 
Electricity Supply Act, <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>.); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>910274</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Warehousing Corporation established under the 
Agricultural Produce (Development and Warehousing) 
Corporations Act, <year>1956</year> (28 of <year>1956</year>),
shall, as from the appointed day, continue to function in those areas 
in respect of which they were functioning immediately before that day, 
subject to the provisions of this section and to such directions as 
may, from time to time, be issued by the Central Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>69145</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Board or the Corporation shall include a 
direction that the Act under which the Board or the Corporation was 
constituted shall, in its application to that Board or Corporation, 
have effect subject to such exceptions and modifications as the 
Central Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1794940</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board or the Corporation referred to in sub- section (1) 
shall cease to function as from, and shall be deemed to be dissolved 
on, the 1st day of October, <year>1960</year>, or such earlier date as the Central 
Government may, by order, appoint; and upon such dissolution, its 
assets, rights and liabilities shall be apportioned between the State 
of Maharashtra and the State of Gujarat in such manner as may be 
agreed upon between them within one year of the dissolution of the 
Board or the Corporation, as the case may be, or if no agreement is 
reached, in such manner as the Central Government may by order 
determine.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>601</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1614583</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the State of Maharashtra or, 
as the case may be, the Government of the State of Gujarat from 
constituting, at any time on or after the appointed day, a State 
Electricity Board or a State Warehousing Corporation for that State 
under the provisions of the Act relating to such Board or Corporation; 
and if such a Board or Corporation; and if such a Board or Corporation 
is so constituted in either of the States before the dissolution of 
the Board or the Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>254035</tid>
<number>a</number>provision may be made by order of the Central Government 
enabling the new Board or the new Corporation to take 
over from the existing Board or Corporation all or any 
of its undertakings, assets, rights and liabilities in 
that State, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1962693</tid>
<number>b</number>upon the dissolution of the existing Board or 
Corporation, any assets, rights and liabilities which 
would otherwise have passed to that State by or under 
the provisions of sub- section (3) shall pass to the new 
Board or the new Corporation instead of to that State.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>336663</tid>
<number>69</number>Continuance of arrangements in regard to generation and 
supply of electric power and supply of water. If it appears to the 
Central Government that the arrangement in regard to the generation or 
supply of electric power or the supply of water for any area or in 
regard to the execution of any project for such generation or supply 
has been or is likely to be modified to the disadvantage of that area 
by reason of the fact that it is, by virtue of the provisions of Part 
II, outside the State in which the power stations and other 
installations for the generation and supply of such power, or the 
catchment area, reservoirs and other works for the supply of water, as 
the case may be, are located, the Central Government may give such 
directions as it deems proper to the State Government or other 
authority concerned for the maintenance, so far as practicable, of the 
previous arrangement.

</article>



<article><tid>1095749</tid>
<number> 70</number> Provisions as to Bombay State Financial Corporation.
<section><tid>1483036</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Bombay State Financial Corporation established under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>) shall, as from the 
appointed day, continue to function in those areas in respect of which 
it was functioning immediately before that day, subject to the 
provisions of this section and to such directions as may, from time to 
time, be issued by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>175224</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Corporation shall include a direction 
that the said Act, in its application to the Corporation, shall have

<pagefootnote><pagenum>602</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

effect subject to such exceptions and modifications as may be 
specified in the direction.


</section>

<section><tid>226834</tid>
<number>3</number>A general meeting of the Corporation shall be convened, in 
accordance with the rules to be made in this behalf by the Central 
Government, by the Board thereof before the 31st day of July, <year>1960</year>, or 
within such further time as the Central Government may allow for the 
consideration of a scheme for the reconstitution or reorganisation or 
dissolution, as the case may be, of the Corporation, including 
proposals regarding the formation of new corporations, and the 
transfer thereto of the assets, rights and liabilities of the existing 
Corporation, and if such a scheme is approved at the general meeting 
by a resolution passed by a majority of the shareholders present and 
voting, the scheme shall be submitted to the Central Government for 
its sanction.

</section>

<section><tid>659968</tid>
<number>4</number>If the scheme is sanctioned by the Central Government either 
without modifications or with modifications which are approved at a 
general meeting, the Central Government shall certify the scheme, and 
upon such certification, the scheme shall, notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force, be 
binding on the corporations affected by the scheme as well as the 
shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1586677</tid>
<number>5</number>If the scheme is not so approved or sanctioned, the Central 
Government may refer the scheme to such Judge of the High Court at 
Bombay as may be nominated in this behalf by the Chief Justice 
thereof, and the decision of the Judge in regard to the scheme shall 
be final and shall be binding on the corporations affected by the 
scheme as well as the shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>852558</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the State of Gujarat from 
constituting, at any time on or after the appointed day, a State 
Financial Corporation for that State under the State Financial 
Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1816806</tid>
<number> 71</number> Amendment of Act 64 of <year>1950</year>. In the Road Transport 
Corporations Act, <year>1950</year>,--
<section><tid>195229</tid>
<number>1</number>in section 47A,--

<subsection><tid>325105</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),--

<subsubsection><tid>1586507</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words, letters and figures," the 
whole or any part of a State in respect of which a 
Corporation was, immediately before the 1st day of 
November, <year>1956</year>," the words" or any other enactment 
relating to reorganisation of States, the whole or 
any part of a

<pagefootnote><pagenum>603</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

State in respect of which a Corporation was, 
immediately before the day on which the 
reorganisation takes place," shall be substituted;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>645004</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the Explanation, for clause (i), the 
following clause shall be substituted, namely:--
" (i) in relation to the Bombay State Road 
Transport Corporation, shall mean the Government 
of the State of Maharashtra or of Gujarat as 
formed under the Bombay Reorganisation Act, 
<year>1960</year>;";


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378147</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3), in clause (f), after the words and 
figures" the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", the 
words" or any other enactment relating to 
reorganisation of States" shall be inserted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>771198</tid>
<number>2</number>after section 47A, the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" 48. Transitional provision relating to Bombay State 
Road Transport Corporation. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 47A, it shall be lawful for the 
Government of the State of Bombay to frame a scheme under 
sub- section (1) thereof and forward the same to the 
Central Government before the 1st day of May, <year>1960</year>, and 
in such a case, the power conferred on the Central 
Government to make an order under sub- section (2) 
thereof may be exercised before that day but no order so 
made shall take effect till that day.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>861134</tid>
<number> 72</number> Special provision for Bar Council of Gujarat.
<section><tid>1483459</tid>
<number>1</number>In the  
Indian Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year> (38 of <year>1926</year>),--

<subsection><tid>874560</tid>
<number>a</number>in section 4,--

<subsubsection><tid>69033</tid>
<number>i</number>to sub- section (2), the following Explanation shall 
be added, namely:--
" Explanation.-- For the purpose of election to 
the Bar Council for the High Court of Gujarat, the 
period of ten years aforesaid shall be computed 
after taking into account the period for which the 
person concerned was entitled as of right to 
practise in the High Court of Bombay or of 
Saurashtra or in the Judicial Commissioner' s Court 
of Kutch before the 1st day of May, <year>1960</year>.";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>897927</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the proviso to sub- section (4), the following 
proviso shall be substituted, namely:--
" Provided that the Advocates- General of West 
Bengal, Madras, Maharashtra and Gujarat shall be


<pagefootnote><pagenum>604</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Chairman ex- officio, respectively, of the Bar 
Councils constituted for the High Courts of those 
States.";


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>474783</tid>
<number>b</number>after section 5, the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" 5A. Ad hoc Bar Council for Gujarat High 
Court. Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Act, the Chief Justice of the High Court of Gujarat 
shall nominate the members of the first Bar Council 
under this Act for the High Court of Gujarat and 
the members so nominated shall remain in office for 
a period of twelve months.".


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>534431</tid>
<number>2</number>The assets and liabilities of the Bar Council for the High 
Court of Bombay shall be divided between the Bar Councils for the High 
Court at Bombay and the High Court of Gujarat in such manner as may be 
agreed upon, and in default of such agreement, as may be directed by 
the Attorney- General for India.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>197484</tid>
<number> 73</number> Amendment of Act 6 of <year>1942</year>. In the Multi- unit Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1942</year>, after section 5B, the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:--
Transitional provision relating to certain multi- unit co- operative 
societies.

" 5C. Transitional provision relating to certain multi- unit 
co- operative societies. (1) Where, in respect of any co- operative 
society specified in the Twelfth Schedule <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, which under the 
provisions of sub- section (1) of section 5A becomes a multi- unit 
co- operative society, the Board of Directors unanimously adopts 
any scheme for the reconstitution, reorganisation or dissolution 
of the society, including proposals for the formation of new co- 
operative societies and the transfer thereto of the assets and 
liabilities and employees of that society and the State 
Government of Bombay certifies the scheme at any time before the 
 1st day of May, <year>1960</year>, then notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) or sub- section (4) of the said 
section or any other law, regulation or bye- law for the time 
being in force in relation to that society, the scheme so 
certified shall be binding on all societies affected by the 
scheme, as well as the shareholders, creditors and employees of 
all such societies, subject to such financial adjustments as may 
be directed in this behalf under sub- section (3), but no such 
scheme shall be given effect to before the said day.

<section><tid>759153</tid>
<number>2</number>When a scheme in respect of a co- operative society is so 
certified, the Central Registrar shall place the scheme at a meeting, 
held in such manner as may be prescribed by rules made under this
<pagefootnote><pagenum>605</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Twelfth Schedule refers to the Twelfth Schedule to the Bombay 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1960</year> (11 of <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Act, of all the persons who, immediately before the date of 
certification of the scheme, were members of the society and the 
scheme may be approved by a resolution passed by a majority of the 
members present and voting at the said meeting.


</section>

<section><tid>92097</tid>
<number>3</number>If the scheme is not so approved or is approved with 
modifications, the Central Registrar may refer the scheme to such 
Judge of the High Court at Bombay as may be nominated in this behalf 
by the Chief Justice thereof and the Judge may direct such financial 
adjustments to be made among the societies affected as he deems 
necessary, and the scheme shall be deemed to be approved subject to 
those financial adjustments.

</section>

<section><tid>28345</tid>
<number>4</number>If in consequence of the directions given under sub- section 
 (3), a society becomes liable to pay any sum of money, the State 
within whose area the society is located shall be liable as guarantor 
in respect of the payment of such money.".


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1164317</tid>
<number> 74</number> General provision as to statutory corporations.
<section><tid>1465216</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise expressly provided by the foregoing provisions of this Part, 
where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, State Act or 
Provincial Act for the State of Bombay or any part thereof has, by 
virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an inter- State body 
corporate, then, the body corporate shall, as from the appointed day, 
continue to function and operate in those areas in respect of which it 
was functioning and operating immediately before that day, subject to 
such directions as may from time to time be issued by the Central 
Government, until other provision is made by law in respect of the 
said body corporate.

</section>

<section><tid>1616931</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of any such body corporate shall include a 
direction that any law by which the said body corporate is governed 
shall, in its application to that body corporate, have effect subject 
to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in the 
direction.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>262103</tid>
<number>75</number>Amendment of Act 38 of <year>1957</year>. In the Inter- State Corporations 
Act, <year>1957</year>, in the preamble, in section 2, in clause (f) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 4 and in section 5, after the words and figures" the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", wherever they occur, the words" or 
of any other enactment relating to reorganisation of States" shall be 
inserted.

</article>



<article><tid>228309</tid>
<number> 76</number> Temporary provisions as to continuance of certain existing 
road transport permits.
<section><tid>1083128</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
section 63 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year> (4 of <year>1939</year>), a permit 
granted by the State Transport Authority of Bombay or any Regional 
Transport Authority in that

<pagefootnote><pagenum>606</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

State shall, if such permit was, immediately before the appointed day, 
valid and effective in any area in the transferred territory, be 
deemed to continue to be valid and effective in that area after that 
day subject to the provisions of that Act as for the time being in 
force in that area; and it shall not be necessary for any such permit 
to be countersigned by the State Transport Authority of Gujarat or any 
Regional Transport Authority therein for the purpose of validating it 
for use in such area:

Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Governments of Maharashtra and Gujarat, add to, amend or 
vary the conditions attached to the permit by the Authority by which 
the permit was granted.


</section>

<section><tid>251606</tid>
<number>2</number>No tolls, entrance fees or other charges of a like nature 
shall be levied after the appointed day in respect of any transport 
vehicle for its operations in the State of Gujarat under any such 
permit, if such vehicle was, immediately before that day, exempt from 
the payment of any such toll, entrance fees or other charges for its 
operations in the transferred territory:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Governments of Maharashtra and Gujarat, authorise the levy 
of any such toll, entrance fees or other charges, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>455193</tid>
<number> 77</number> Special provision relating to retrenchment compensation in 
certain cases. Where on account of the reorganisation of the State of 
Bombay under this Act, any body corporate constituted under a Central 
Act, State Act or Provincial Act, any co- operative society registered 
under any law relating to co- operative societies or any commercial or 
industrial undertaking of that State is reconstituted or reorganised 
in any manner whatsoever or is amalgamated with any other body 
corporate, co- operative society or undertaking, or is dissolved, and 
in consequence of such reconstitution, reorganisation, amalgamation or 
dissolution, any workman employed by such body corporate or in any 
such co- operative society or undertaking, is transferred to, or re- 
employed by any other body corporate, or in any other co- operative 
society or undertaking, then notwithstanding anything contained in 
section 25F of the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), such 
transfer or re- employment shall not entitle him to any compensation 
under that section:
Provided that--

<section><tid>1001882</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service applicable to the 
workman after such transfer or re- employment are not 
less

<pagefootnote><pagenum>607</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

favourable to the workman than those applicable to him 
immediately before the transfer or re- employment;


</section>

<section><tid>1826738</tid>
<number>b</number>the employer in relation to the body corporate, the co- 
operative society or the undertaking where the workman 
is transferred or re- employed is, by agreement or 
otherwise, legally liable to pay to the workman, in the 
event of his retrenchment, compensation under section 
 25F of the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), 
on the basis that his service has been continuous and 
has not been interrupted by the transfer or re- 
employment.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>267102</tid>
<number>78</number>Special provision as to income- tax. Where the assets, rights 
and liabilities of any body corporate carrying on any business are, 
under the provisions of this Part, transferred to any other bodies 
corporate which after the transfer carry on the same business, the 
losses of profits or gains sustained by the body corporate first 
mentioned which, but for such transfer, would have been allowed to be 
carried forward and set off in accordance with the provisions of 
section 24 of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), shall be 
apportioned amongst the transferee bodies corporate in accordance with 
the rules to be made by the Central Government in this behalf and, 
upon such apportionment, the share of loss allotted to each transferee 
body corporate shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions 
of section 24 of the said Act, as if the transferee body corporate had 
itself sustained such loss in a business carried on by it in the years 
in which these losses were sustained.

</article>



<article><tid>1961208</tid>
<number> 79</number> Continuance of facilities in certain State institutions.
<section><tid>1399734</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Government of the State of Maharashtra or, as the case may be, the 
Government of the State of Gujarat shall, in respect of the 
institutions specified in the Thirteenth Schedule located in that 
State, continue to provide facilities to the people of the other State 
which shall not, in any respect, be less favourable to such people 
than what were being provided to them before the appointed day, for 
such period and upon such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon 
between the two State Governments before the 1st day of October, <year>1960</year> 
or, if no agreement is reached by the said date, as may be fixed by 
order of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>383530</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, at any time before the 1st day of 
October, <year>1960</year>, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in the 
Thirteenth Schedule any other institution existing on the appointed 
day in the State of Maharashtra or of Gujarat, and on the issue of 
such notification, the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended by the 
inclusion of the said institution therein.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>608</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART 
PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES

PART VIII

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1279560</tid>
<number> 80</number> Provisions relating to All- India Services.
<section><tid>57226</tid>
<number>1</number>In this  
section, the expression" State cadre"--

<subsection><tid>252515</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to the Indian Administrative Service, has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Indian Administrative 
Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1604298</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to the Indian Police Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Police Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>918952</tid>
<number>2</number>In place of the cadres of the Indian Administrative Service 
and the Indian Police Service existing in the State of Bombay 
immediately before the appointed day, there shall, as from that day, 
be two separate cadres, one for the State of Maharashtra and the other 
for the State of Gujarat, in respect of each of these services.

</section>

<section><tid>786131</tid>
<number>3</number>The initial strength and composition of each of the State 
cadres shall be such as the Central Government may by order determine 
before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>486555</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of each of the said services borne on those 
cadres for the State of Bombay immediately before the appointed day 
shall be allocated to the State cadres of the same service for each of 
the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat in such manner and with effect 
from such date or dates as the Central Government may, by order, 
specify.

</section>

<section><tid>776469</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
operation, after the appointed day, of the All- India Services Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (61 of <year>1951</year>), or the rules made thereunder in relation to the 
State cadres of the said services constituted under sub- section (2) 
and in relation to the members of those services borne on the said 
cadres.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1792637</tid>
<number> 81</number> Provisions relating to other services.
<section><tid>754021</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who,  
immediately before the appointed day, is serving in connection with 
the affairs of the State of Bombay shall, as from that day, 
provisionally continue to serve in connection with the affairs of the 
State of Maharashtra, unless he is required, by general or special 
order of the Central Government, to serve provisionally in connection 
with the affairs of the State of Gujarat.

</section>

<section><tid>218115</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Central 
Government shall, by general or special order, determine the State to 
which every person provisionally allotted to the State of Maharashtra 
or Gujarat, shall be finally allotted for service and the date with 
effect from which such allotment shall take effect or be deemed to 
have taken effect.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>609</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1578845</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who is finally allotted under the provisions of 
sub- section (2) to the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat shall, if he is 
not already serving therein, be made available for serving in that 
State from such date as may be agreed upon between the two State 
Governments or, in default of such agreement, as may be determined by 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1887077</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may by order establish one or more 
Advisory Committees for the purpose of assisting it in regard to--

<subsection><tid>1698347</tid>
<number>a</number>the division and integration of the services among the 
States of Maharashtra and Gujarat; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>129374</tid>
<number>b</number>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all 
persons affected by the provisions of this section and 
the proper consideration of any representations made by 
such persons.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1658081</tid>
<number>5</number>The foregoing provisions of this section shall not apply in 
relation to any person to whom the provisions of section 80 apply.

</section>

<section><tid>105752</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect, after the 
appointed day, the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part 
XIV of the Constitution in relation to the determination of the 
conditions of service of persons serving in connection with the 
affairs of the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat:
Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately 
before the appointed day to the case of any person provisionally or 
finally allotted to the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat under this 
section shall not be varied to his disadvantage except with the 
previous approval of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>381628</tid>
<number>82</number>Provisions as to continuance of officers in same post. Every 
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is holding or 
discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the 
affairs of the State of Bombay in any area which on that day falls 
within the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat shall continue to hold the 
same post or office in that State and shall be deemed, as from that 
day, to have been duly appointed to the post or office by the 
Government of, or other appropriate authority in, that State:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
a competent authority, after the appointed day, from passing, in 
relation to such person, any order affecting his continuance in such 
post or office.


</article>



<article><tid>1344908</tid>
<number>83</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. The Central 
Government may give such directions to the State Governments of 
Maharashtra and Gujarat as may appear to it to be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>610</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

necessary for the purpose of giving effect to the foregoing provisions 
of this Part and the State Government shall comply with such 
directions.


</article>



<article><tid>568673</tid>
<number> 84</number> Provisions as to Bombay Public Service Commission.
<section><tid>562823</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Public Service Commission for the State of Bombay shall, as from the 
appointed day, become the Public Service Commission for the State of 
Maharashtra.

</section>

<section><tid>1502787</tid>
<number>2</number>The report of the Bombay Public Service Commission as to the 
work done by the Commission in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day shall be presented under clause (2) of article 323 to 
the Governors of Maharashtra and Gujarat, and the Governor of 
Maharashtra shall, on receipt of such report, cause a copy thereof 
together with a memorandum explaining, as far as possible, as respects 
the cases, if any, where the advice of the Commission was not 
accepted, the reasons for such non- acceptance to be laid before the 
Legislature of the State of Maharashtra and it shall not be necessary 
to cause such report or any such memorandum to be laid before the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Gujarat.
PART 
LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART IX

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>468602</tid>
<number> 85</number> Amendment of article 371 of the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in article 371 of the Constitution, in clause (2)--
<section><tid>1627358</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" the State of Bombay" the words" the State 
of Maharashtra or Gujarat" shall be substituted; and

</section>

<section><tid>628947</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" the rest of Maharashtra", the words" and 
the rest of Maharashtra or, as the case may be," shall 
be substituted.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1402818</tid>
<number> 86</number> Amendment of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>. In section 15 of the States 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>--
<section><tid>440917</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (d), for the words" Bombay and Mysore", the 
words" Gujarat and Maharashtra" shall be substituted; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>944316</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (e), for the words" Madras and Kerala", the 
words" Madras, Mysore and Kerala" shall be substituted.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1600999</tid>
<number>87</number>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of Part II shall 
not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which 
any law in force immediately

<pagefootnote><pagenum>611</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

before the appointed day extends or applies, and territorial 
references in any such law to the State of Bombay shall, until 
otherwise provided by a competent Legislature or other competent 
authority, be construed as meaning the territories within that State 
immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>514207</tid>
<number>88</number>Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application in relation to the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat of any 
law made before the appointed day, the appropriate Government may, 
before the expiration of one year from that day, by order, make such 
adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by way of repeal or 
amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and thereupon every such 
law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so 
made until altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or 
other competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated 
in the Union List, the Central Government, and as respects any other 
law, the State Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1331259</tid>
<number>89</number>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made under section 88 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority, required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Maharashtra or Gujarat, construe the law in such manner, without 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper in regard to 
the matter before the court, tribunal or authority.

</article>



<article><tid>1177598</tid>
<number>90</number>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory 
functions. The Government of the State of Gujarat, as respects the 
transferred territory may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify the authority, officer or person who, on or after the 
appointed day, shall be competent to exercise such functions 
exercisable under any law in force on that day as may be mentioned in 
that notification and such law shall have effect accordingly.

</article>



<article><tid>524589</tid>
<number>91</number>Legal proceedings. Where immediately before the appointed 
day, the State of Bombay is a party to any legal proceedings with 
respect to any property, rights or liabilities subject to 
apportionment between the States of Maharashtra and Gujarat under this 
Act, the State of Maharashtra or Gujarat which succeeds to, or 
acquires a share in, that property or those rights or liabilities by 
virtue of any provision

<pagefootnote><pagenum>612</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of this Act shall be deemed to be substituted for the State of Bombay 
as a party to those proceedings, and the proceedings may continue 
accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>12580</tid>
<number> 92</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1511957</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within the State of Maharashtra shall, if it is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to the transferred territory, stand transferred 
to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer in the 
State of Gujarat.

</section>

<section><tid>1520711</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
High Court at Bombay and the decision of that High Court shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>1819928</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section--

<subsection><tid>1652581</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>347872</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
the State of Gujarat means--

<subsubsection><tid>357481</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in which, or before whom, the proceeding would 
have lain if it had been instituted after the 
appointed day; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1741781</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority, or officer in that State, as may be 
determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of that State, or before the appointed 
day by the Government of Bombay, to be the 
corresponding court, tribunal, authority or 
officer.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>900988</tid>
<number>93</number>Right of pleaders to practise in certain cases. Any person 
who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the State of Bombay 
shall, for a period of one year from that day, continue to be entitled 
to practise in those courts, notwithstanding that the whole or any 
part of the territories within the jurisdiction of those courts has 
been transferred to the State of Gujarat.

</article>



<article><tid>1465195</tid>
<number>94</number>Effect of provisions of the Act inconsistent with other laws. 
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.

</article>



<article><tid>908478</tid>
<number>95</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with

<pagefootnote><pagenum>613</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

such provisions which appears to him to be necessary or expedient for 
the purpose of removing the difficulties.


</article>



<article><tid>144411</tid>
<number> 96</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>776894</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>909478</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two more successive sessions and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid"], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modifications or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>