<act><title>


The Judges (PROTECTION) Act, 1985</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—(l) This Act may 
    be called The Judges (Protection) Act, 1985.
 <section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In this Act, “Judge” 
    means not only every person who is officially designated as Judge, but also 
    every person—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    who is empowered by law to give in any 
    legal proceeding a definitive judgment, or a judgment which, if not appealed 
    against, would be definitive, or a judgment which, if confirmed by some 
    other authority, would be definitive; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    who is one of a body of persons which 
    body of persons is empowered by law to give such a judgment as is referred 
    to in Clause (a).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Additional protection to Judges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force and subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), no Court shall 
    entertain or continue any civil or criminal proceeding against any person 
    who is or was a Judge for any act, thing or word committed, done or spoken 
    by him when, or in the course of, acting or purporting to act in the 
    discharge of his official or judicial duty or function.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    sub-section (1) shall debar or affect in any manner the power of the Central 
    Government or the State Government or the Supreme Court of India or any High 
    Court or any other authority under any law for the time being in force to 
    take such action (whether by way of civil, criminal, or departmental 
    proceedings or otherwise) against any person who is or was a Judge.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Saving.—The 
    provision of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the 
    provisions of any other law for the time being in force providing for 
    protection of Judges.
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>