<act><title>

THE 
    SPECIAL MARRIAGE ACT, 1954</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Special Marriage Act, 1954. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir, and 
    applies also to citizens of India domiciled in the territories to which this 
    Act extends who are 

    1[in the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir]. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date2
    as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 

1[***]  
 <section>
<number>b</number>   “degrees of prohibited 
    relationship”—a man and any of the persons mentioned in Part I of the First 
    Schedule and a woman and any of the persons mentioned in Part II of the said 
    Schedule are within the degrees of prohibited relationship;  
 
Explanation I.—Relationship 
    includes,—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   relationship by half or uterine 
    blood as well as by full blood;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   illegitimate blood relationship as 
    well as legitimate;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   relationship by adoption as well 
    as by blood;  
 
and all terms of relationship in this 
    Act shall be construed accordingly.  
 
Explanation II.—”Full 
    blood” and “half blood”—two persons are said to be related to each other by 
    full blood when they are descended from a common ancestor by the same wife 
    and by half blood when they are descended from a common ancestor but by 
    different wives.  
 
Explanation III.—”Uterine 
    blood”—two persons are said to be related to each other by uterine blood 
    when they are descended from a common ancestress but by different husbands.  
 
Explanation IV.—In 
    Explanations II and III, “ancestor” includes the father and “ancestress” the 
    mother;  
 

2[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “district” in relation to a 
    Marriage Officer, means the area for which he is appointed as such under 
    sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 3;  
 

3[(e)   
    “district court” means, in any area for which there is a city civil court, 
    that court, and in any other area, the principal civil court of original 
    jurisdiction, and includes any other civil court which may be specified by 
    the State Government by notification in the Official Gazette as having 
    jurisdiction in respect of the matters dealt with in this Act;]  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;  
 

4[(g) 
      “State Government”, in relation to a Union Territory, means the 
    administrator thereto.]  
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Marriage Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purposes of this Act, the State Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, appoint one or more Marriage Officers for the whole or 
    any part of the State.  
 


    1[(2) For the purposes 
    of this Act, in its application to citizens of India domiciled in the 
    territories to which this Act extends who are in the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify such officers of the Central Government as it may think fit 
    to be the Marriage Officers for the State or any part thereof.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Conditions relating to solemnization of special marriages.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force relating to 
    the solemnization of marriages, a marriage between any two persons may be 
    solemnized under this Act, if at the time of the marriage the following 
    conditions are fulfilled, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   neither party has a spouse living;  
 

1[(b) 
      neither party—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   is incapable of giving a valid 
    consent to it in consequence of unsoundness of mind; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   though capable of giving a valid 
    consent, has been suffering from mental disorder of such a kind or to such 
    an extent as to be unfit for marriage and the procreation of children; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   has been subject to recurrent 
    attacks of insanity 
2[***];]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>   the male has completed the age of 
    twenty-one years and the female the age of eighteen years;  
 

3[(d) 
      the parties are not within the degrees of prohibited relationship:  
 
Provided that where a custom governing 
    at least one of the parties permits of a marriage between them, such 
    marriage may be solemnized, notwithstanding that they are within the degrees 
    of prohibited relationship; and]  
 

4(e)   
    where the marriage is solemnized in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, both 
    parties are citizens of India domiciled in the territories to which this Act 
    extends].  
 


    5[Explanation.—In 
    this section, “custom”, in relation to a person belonging to any tribe, 
    community, group or family, means any rule which the State Government may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf as 
    applicable to members of that tribe, community, group or family:  
 
Provided 
    that no such notification shall be issued in relation to the members of any 
    tribe, community, group or family, unless the State Government is satisfied—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   that such rule has been 
    continuously and uniformly observed for a long time among those members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   that such rule is certain and not 
    unreasonable or opposed to public policy; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   that such rule, if applicable 
    only to a family, has not been discontinued by the family.]  
 










 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Notice of intended marriage.—When 
    a marriage is intended to be solemnized under this Act, the parties to the 
    marriage shall give notice thereof in writing in the form specified in the 
    Second Schedule to the Marriage Officer of the district in which at least 
    one of the parties to the marriage has resided for a period of not less than 
    thirty days immediately preceding the date on which such notice is given.  
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Marriage Notice Book and publication.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Marriage Officer shall keep all notices given under section 5 with the 
    records of his office and shall also forthwith enter a true copy of every 
    such notice in a book prescribed for that purpose, to be called the Marriage 
    Notice Book, and such book shall be open for inspection at all reasonable 
    times, without fee, by any person desirous of inspecting the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Marriage Officer shall cause every such notice to be published by affixing a 
    copy thereof to some conspicuous place in his office.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where either of the parties to an intended marriage is not permanently 
    residing within the local limits of the district of the Marriage Officer to 
    whom the notice has been given under section 5, the Marriage Officer shall 
    also cause a copy of such notice to be transmitted to the Marriage Officer 
    of the district within whose limits such party is permanently residing, and 
    that Marriage Officer shall thereupon cause a copy thereof to be affixed to 
    some conspicuous place in his office.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Objection to marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person may, before the expiration of thirty days from the date on which 
    any such notice has been published under sub-section (2) of section 6, 
    object to the marriage on the ground that it would contravene one or more of 
    the conditions specified in section 4.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    After the expiration of thirty days from the date on which notice of an 
    intended marriage has been published under sub-section (2) of section 6, the 
    marriage may be solemnized, unless it has been previously objected to under 
    sub-section (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    nature of the objection shall be recorded in writing by the Marriage Officer 
    in the Marriage Notice Book, be read over and explained if necessary, to the 
    person making the objection and shall be signed by him or on his behalf.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Procedure on receipt of objection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If an objection is made under section 7 to an intended marriage, the 
    Marriage Officer shall not solemnize the marriage until he has inquired into 
    the matter of the objection and is satisfied that it ought not to prevent 
    the solemnization of the marriage or the objection is withdrawn by the 
    person making it; but the Marriage Officer shall not take more than thirty 
    days from the date of the objection for the purpose of inquiring into the 
    matter of the objection and arriving at a decision.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the Marriage Officer upholds the objection and refuses to solemnize the 
    marriage, either party to the intended marriage may, within a period of 
    thirty days from the date of such refusal, prefer an appeal to the district 
    court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the Marriage Officer has 
    his office, and the decision of the district court on such appeal shall be 
    final, and the Marriage Officer shall act in conformity with the decision of 
    the court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Powers of Marriage Officers in respect of inquiries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of any inquiry under section 8, the Marriage Officer shall 
    have all the powers vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), when trying a suit in respect of the following 
    matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   summoning and enforcing the 
    attendance of witnesses and examining them on oath;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   discovery and inspection;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   compelling the production of 
    documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   reception of evidence of 
    affidavits; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   issuing commissions for the 
    examination of witnesses;  
 
and any proceeding before the Marriage Officer 
    shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 
    193 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of enforcing the attendance of any person to give evidence, the 
    local limits of the jurisdiction of the Marriage Officer shall be the local 
    limits of his district.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    it appears to the Marriage Officer that the objection made to an intended 
    marriage is not reasonable and has not been made in good faith he may impose 
    on the person objecting costs by way of compensation not exceeding one 
    thousand rupees and award the whole or any part thereof, to the parties to 
    the intended marriage, and any order for costs so made may be executed in 
    the same manner as a decree passed by the district court within the local 
    limits of whose jurisdiction the Marriage Officer has his office.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Procedure on receipt of objection by Marriage Officer abroad.—Where 
    an objection is made under section 7 to a Marriage Officer 

    1[in the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir in respect of an intended marriage in the State], and the 
    Marriage Officer, after making such inquiry into the matter as he thinks 
    fit, entertains a doubt in respect thereof, he shall not solemnize the 
    marriage but shall transmit the record with such statement respecting the 
    matter as he thinks fit to the Central Government, and the Central 
    Government, after making such inquiry into the matter and after obtaining 
    such advice as it thinks fit, shall give its decision thereon in writing to 
    the Marriage Officer who shall act in conformity with the decision of the 
    Central Government.  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Declaration by parties and witnesses.—Before 
    the marriage is solemnized the parties and three witnesses shall, in the 
    presence of the Marriage Officer, sign a declaration in the form specified 
    in the Third Schedule to this Act, and the declaration shall be 
    countersigned by the Marriage Officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Place and form of solemnization.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The marriage may be solemnized at the office of the Marriage Officer, or at 
    such other place within a reasonable distance therefrom as the parties may 
    desire, and upon such conditions and the payment of such additional fees as 
    may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    marriage may be solemnized in any form which the parties may choose to 
    adopt:  
 
Provided 
    that it shall not be complete and binding on the parties unless each party 
    says to the other in the presence of the Marriage Officer and the three 
    witnesses and in any language understood by the parties,—“I, (A), take the 
    (B), to be my lawful wife (or husband).”  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Certificate of marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the marriage has been solemnized, the Marriage Officer shall enter a 
    certificate thereof in the form specified in the Fourth Schedule in a book 
    to be kept by him for that purpose and to be called the Marriage Certificate 
    Book and such certificate shall be signed by the parties to the marriage and 
    the three witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On a 
    certificate being entered in the Marriage Certificate Book by the Marriage 
    Officer, the Certificate shall be deemed to be conclusive evidence of the 
    fact that a marriage under this Act has been solemnized and that all 
    formalities respecting the signatures of witnesses have been complied with.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    New notice when marriage not solemnized within three months.—Whenever 
    a marriage is not solemnized within three calendar months from the date on 
    which notice thereof has been given to the Marriage Officer as required by 
    section 5, or where an appeal has been filed under sub-section (2) of 
    section 8, within three months from the date of the decision of the district 
    court on such appeal or, where the record of a case has been transmitted to 
    the Central Government under section 10, within three months from the date 
    of decision of the Central Government, the notice and all other proceedings 
    arising therefrom shall be deemed to have lapsed, and no Marriage Officer 
    shall solemnize the marriage until a new notice has been given in the manner 
    laid down in this Act.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Registration of marriages celebrated in other forms.—Any 
    marriage celebrated, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, 
    other than a marriage solemnized under the 

    1Special Marriage Act, 
    1872 (III of 1872) or under this Act, may be registered under this Chapter 
    by a Marriage Officer in the territories to which this Act extends if the 
    following conditions are fulfilled, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   a ceremony of marriage has been 
    performed between the parties and they have been living together as husband 
    and wife ever since;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   neither party has at the time of 
    registration more than one spouse living;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   neither party is an idiot or a 
    lunatic at the time of registration;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   the parties have completed the age 
    of twenty-one years at the time of registration;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   the parties are not within the 
    degrees of prohibited relationship:
 
Provided that in the case of a marriage 
    celebrated before the commencement of this Act, this condition shall be 
    subject to any law, custom or usage having the force of law governing each 
    of them which permits of a marriage between the two; and
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   the parties have been residing 
    within the district of the Marriage Officer for a period of not less than 
    thirty days immediately preceding the date on which the application is made 
    to him for registration of the marriage.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Procedure for registration.—Upon 
    receipt of an application signed by both the parties to the marriage for the 
    registration of their marriage under this Chapter the Marriage Officer shall 
    give public notice thereof in such manner as may be prescribed and after 
    allowing a period of thirty days for objections and after hearing any 
    objection received within that period, shall, if satisfied that all the 
    conditions mentioned in section 15 are fulfilled, enter a certificate of the 
    marriage in the Marriage Certificate Book in the form specified in the Fifth 
    Schedule, and such certificate shall be signed by the parties to the 
    marriage and by three witnesses.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Appeals from orders under section 16.—Any 
    person aggrieved by any order of a Marriage Officer refusing to register a 
    marriage under this Chapter may, within thirty days from the date of the 
    order, appeal against that order to the district court within the local 
    limits of whose jurisdiction the Marriage Officer has his office, and the 
    decision of the district court on such appeal shall be final, and the 
    Marriage Officer to whom the application was made shall act in conformity 
    with such decision.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Effect of registration of marriage under this Chapter.—Subject 
    to the provisions contained in sub-section (2) of section 24, where a 
    certificate of marriage has been finally entered in the Marriage Certificate 
    Book under this Chapter, the marriage shall, as from the date of such entry, 
    be deemed to be a marriage solemnized under this Act, and all children born 
    after the date of the ceremony of marriage (whose names shall also be 
    entered in the Marriage Certificate Book) shall in all respects be deemed to 
    be and always to have been the legitimate children of their parents:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this section shall be construed as conferring upon 
    any such children any rights in or to the property of any person other than 
    their parents in any case where, but for the passing of this Act, such 
    children would have been incapable of possessing or acquiring any such 
    rights by reason of their not being the legitimate children of their 
    parents.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Effect of marriage on member of undivided family.—The 
    marriage solemnized under this Act of any member of an undivided family who 
    professes the Hindu, Buddhist, Sikh or Jaina religions shall be deemed to 
    effect his severance from such family.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number> Rights and disabilities not affected by 
      Act.—Subject to the provisions of section 19, any person whose marriage 
      is solemnized under this Act shall have the same rights and shall be 
      subject to the same disabilities in regard to the right of succession to 
      any property as a person to whom the Caste Disabilities Removal Act, 1850 
      (21 of 1850), applies.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number> Succession to property of parties married under 
      Act.—Notwithstanding any restrictions contained in the Indian 
      Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), with respect to its application to 
      members of certain communities, succession to the property of any person 
      whose marriage is solemnized under this Act and to the property of the 
      issue of such marriage shall be regulated by the provisions of the said 
      Act and for the purposes of this Act shall have effect as if Chapter III 
      of Part V (Special Rules for Parsi section that Intestate) had been 
      omitted therefrom.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>21A</number> Special 
    provision in certain cases.—Where the marriage is solemnized under this 
    Act of any person who professes the Hindu, Buddhist, Sikh or Jaina religion 
    with a person who professes the Hindu, Buddhist, Sikh or Jaina religion, 
    section 19 and section 21 shall not apply and so much of section 20 as 
    creates a disability shall also not apply.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Restitution of conjugal rights.—When 
    either the husband or the wife has, without reasonable excuse, withdrawn 
    from the society of the other, the aggrieved party may apply by petition to 
    the district court for restitution of conjugal rights, and the court, on 
    being satisfied of the truth of the statements made in such petition, and 
    that there is no legal ground why the application should not be granted, may 
    decree restitution of conjugal rights accordingly.
 


    1[Explanation.—Where 
    a question arises whether there has been reasonable excuse for withdrawal 
    from the society, the burden of proving reasonable excuse shall be on the 
    person who has withdrawn from the society.] 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Judicial separation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A petition for judicial separation may be presented to the district court 
    either by the husband or the wife,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   on any of the grounds specified
    1[in 
    sub-section (1)] 
2[and 
    sub-section (1-A)] of section 27 on which a petition for divorce might have 
    been presented; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   on the ground of failure to comply 
    with a decree for restitution of conjugal rights,
 
and the court, on being satisfied of the truth 
    of the statements made in such petition and that there is no legal ground 
    why the application should not be granted, may decree judicial separation 
    accordingly.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the court grants a decree for judicial separation, it shall be no 
    longer obligatory for the petitioner to cohabit with the respondent, but the 
    court may, on the application by petition of either party and on being 
    satisfied of the truth of the statements made in such petition, rescind the 
    decree if it considers it just and reasonable to do so.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Void marriages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any marriage solemnized under this Act shall be null and void 

    1[and may, on a 
    petition presented by either party thereto against the other party, be so 
    declared] by a decree of nullity if—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any of the conditions specified in 
    clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of section 4 has not been fulfilled; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the respondent was impotent at 
    the time of the marriage and at the time of the institution of the suit.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing contained in this section shall apply to any marriage deemed to be 
    solemnized under this Act within the meaning of section 18, but the 
    registration of any such marriage under Chapter III may be declared to be of 
    no effect if the registration was in contravention of any of the conditions 
    specified in clauses (a) to (e) of section 15:  
 
Provided 
    that no such declaration shall be made in any case where an appeal has been 
    preferred under section 17 and the decision of the district court has become 
    final.  
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Voidable marriages.—Any 
    marriage solemnized under this Act shall be voidable and may be annulled by 
    a decree of nullity if,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   the marriage has not been 
    consummated owing to the wilful refusal of the respondent to consummate the 
    marriage; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   the respondent was at the time of 
    the marriage pregnant by some person other than the petitioner; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   the consent of either party to 
    the marriage was obtained by coercion or fraud, as defined in the Indian 
    Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872):  
 
Provided 
    that, in the case specified in clause (ii), the court shall not grant a 
    decree unless it is satisfied,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the petitioner was at the 
    time of the marriage ignorant of the facts alleged;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that proceedings were instituted 
    within a year from the date of the marriage; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that marital intercourse with the 
    consent of the petitioner has not taken place since the discovery by the 
    petitioner of the existence of the grounds for a decree:  
 
Provided 
    further that in the case specified in clause (iii), the court shall not 
    grant a decree if,—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>   proceedings have not been 
    instituted within one year after the coercion had ceased or, as the case may 
    be, the fraud had been discovered; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the petitioner has with his or her 
    free consent lived with the other party to the marriage as husband and wife 
    after the coercion had ceased or, as the case may be, the fraud had been 
    discovered.  
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>26</number> Legitimacy of 
    children of void and voidable marriages.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding that a 
    marriage is null and void under section 24, any child of such marriage who 
    would have been legitimate if the marriage had been valid, shall be 
    legitimate, whether such child is born before or after the commencement of 
    the Marriage Laws (Amendment) Act, 1976 (68 of 1976), and whether or not a 
    decree of nullity is granted in respect of that marriage under this Act and 
    whether or not the marriage is held to be void otherwise than on a petition 
    under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a decree of nullity is granted in respect of a voidable marriage under 
    section 25, any child begotten or conceived before the decree is made, who 
    would have been the legitimate child of the parties to the marriage if at 
    the date of the decree it has been dissolved instead of being annulled, 
    shall be deemed to be their legitimate child notwithstanding the decree of 
    nullity.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be construed 
    as conferring upon any child of a marriage which is null and void or which 
    is annulled by a decree of nullity under section 25, any rights in or to the 
    property of any person, other than the parents, in any case where, but for 
    the passing of this Act, such child would have been incapable of possessing 
    or acquiring any such rights by reason of not his being the legitimate child 
    of his parents.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Divorce.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and to the rules made thereunder, a 
    petition for divorce may be presented to the district court either by the 
    husband or the wife on the ground that the respondent—  
 

2[(a)   
    has, after the solemnization of the marriage, had voluntary sexual 
    intercourse with any person other than his or her spouse; or 
 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>   has deserted the petitioner for a 
    continuous period of not less than two years immediately preceding the 
    presentation of the petition; or]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   is undergoing a sentence of 
    imprisonment for seven years or more for an offence as defined in the Indian 
    Penal Code (45 of 1860);  
 

3[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   has since the solemnization of the 
    marriage treated the petitioner with cruelty; or  
 

4[(e)   
    has been incurably of unsound mind, or has been suffering continuously or 
    intermittently from mental disorder of such a kind and to such an extent 
    that the petitioner cannot reasonably be expected to live with the 
    respondent.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this clause,—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>   the expression “mental disorder” 
    means mental illness, arrested or incomplete development of mind, 
    psychopathic disorder or any other disorder or disability of mind and 
    includes schizophrenia;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the expression “psychopathic 
    disorder” means a persistent disorder or disability of mind (whether or not 
    including sub-normality of intelligence) which results in abnormally 
    aggressive or seriously irresponsible conduct on the part of the respondent, 
    and whether or not it requires or is susceptible to medical treatment; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   has been suffering from venereal 
    disease in a communicable form]; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   has 
5[***] 
    been suffering from leprosy, the disease not having been contacted from the 
    petitioner; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   has not been heard of as being 
    alive for a period of seven years or more by those persons who would 
    naturally have heard of the respondent if the respondent had been alive;
    6[***]  
 


    7[Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section, the expression “desertion” means desertion of the 
    petitioner by the other party to the marriage without reasonable cause and 
    without the consent or against the wish of such party, and includes the 
    wilful neglect of the petitioner by the other party to the marriage, and its 
    grammatical variations and cognate expressions shall be construed 
    accordingly;]  
 


    8[***]  
 


    9[***]  
 


    7[(1A) A wife may also 
    present a petition for divorce to the district court on the ground,—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   that her husband has, since the 
    solemnization of the marriage, been guilty of rape, sodomy or bestiality;  
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   that in a suit under section 18 
    of the Hindu Adoptions and Maintenance Act, 1956 (78 of 1956), or in a 
    proceeding under section 125 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
    1974) (or under the corresponding section 488 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898) (5 of 1898), a decree or order, as the case may be, has 
    been passed against the husband awarding maintenance to the wife 
    notwithstanding that she was living apart and that since the passing of such 
    decree or order, cohabitation between the parties has not been resumed for 
    one year or upwards.]  
 


    10[(2) Subject to the 
    provisions of this Act and to the rules made thereunder, either party to a 
    marriage, whether solemnized before or after the commencement of the Special 
    Marriage (Amendment) Act, 1970 (29 of 1970), may present a petition for 
    divorce to the district court on the ground—  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   that there has been no resumption 
    of cohabitation as between the parties to the marriage for a period of one 
    year or upwards after the passing of a decree for judicial separation in a 
    proceeding to which they were parties; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   that there has been no 
    restitution of conjugal rights as between the parties to the marriage for a 
    period of one year or upwards after the passing of a decree for restitution 
    of conjugal rights in a proceeding to which they were parties.]  
 













 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>27A</number> Alternative 
    relief in divorce proceedings.—In any proceeding under this Act, on a 
    petition for dissolution of marriage by a decree of divorce, except insofar 
    as the petition is founded on the ground mentioned in clause (h) of 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 27, the court may, if it considers it just so to 
    do having regard to the circumstances of the case, pass instead a decree for 
    judicial separation.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Divorce by mutual consent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and to the rules made thereunder, a 
    petition for divorce may be presented to the district court by both the 
    parties together on the ground that they have been living separately for a 
    period of one year or more, that they have not been able to live together 
    and that they have mutually agreed that the marriage should be dissolved.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
    

    1[On the motion of 
    both the parties made not earlier than six months after the date of the 
    presentation of the petition referred to in sub-section (1) and not later 
    than eighteen months] after the said date, if the petition is not withdrawn 
    in the meantime, the district court shall, on being satisfied, after hearing 
    the parties and after making such inquiry as it thinks fit, that a marriage 
    has been solemnized under this Act, and that the averments in the petition 
    are true, pass a decree declaring the marriage to be dissolved with effect 
    from the date of the decree.  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Restriction on petitions for divorce during first one year after marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No petition for divorce shall be presented to the district court 


    1[unless at the date 
    of the presentation of the petition one year has passed] since the date of 
    entering the certificate of marriage in the Marriage Certificate Book:  
 
Provided 
    that the district court may, upon application being made to it, allow a 
    petition to be presented 

    2[before one year has 
    passed] on the ground that the case is one of exceptional hardship suffered 
    by the petitioner or of exceptional depravity on the part of the respondent, 
    but if it appears to the district court at the hearing of the petition that 
    the petitioner obtained leave to present the petition by any 
    misrepresentation or concealment of the nature of the case, the district 
    court may, if it pronounces a decree, do so subject to the condition that 
    the decree shall not have effect until after the 

    3[expiry of one year] 
    from the date of the marriage or may dismiss the petition, without prejudice 
    to any petition, which may be brought after the 

    4[expiration of the 
    said one year] upon the same, or substantially the same, facts as those 
    proved in support of the petition so dismissed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    disposing of any application under this section for leave to present a 
    petition for divorce before the 

    5[expiration of one 
    year] from the date of the marriage, the district court shall have regard to 
    the interests of any children of the marriage, and to the question whether 
    there is a reasonable probability of a reconciliation between the parties 
    before the expiration of the 

    6[said one year].  
 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Re-marriage of divorced persons.—Where 
    a marriage has been dissolved by a decree of divorce; and either there is no 
    right of appeal against the decree or if there is such a right of appeal, 
    the time for appealing has expired without an appeal having been presented, 
    or an appeal has been presented but has been dismissed, 

    1[***] either party to 
    the marriage may marry again.  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Court to which petition should be made.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every petition under Chapter V or Chapter VI shall be presented to the 
    district court within the local limits of whose original civil jurisdiction—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the marriage was solemnized; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the respondent, at the time of 
    the presentation of the petition resides; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the parties to the marriage last 
    resided together; or  
 

2[(iiia)   
    in case the wife is the petitioner, where she is residing on the date of 
    presentation of the petition; or]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the petitioner is residing at the 
    time of the presentation of the petition, in a case where the respondent is, 
    at that time residing outside the territories to which this Act extends, or 
    has not been heard of as being alive for a period of seven years by those 
    who would naturally have heard of him if he were alive.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to any jurisdiction exercisable by the court under 
    sub-section (1), the district court may, by virtue of this sub-section, 
    entertain a petition by a wife domiciled in the territories to which this 
    Act extends for nullity of marriage or for divorce if she is resident in the 
    said territories and has been ordinarily resident therein for a period of 
    three years immediately preceding the presentation of the petition and the 
    husband is not resident in the said territories.  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Contents and verification of petitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every petition under Chapter V or Chapter VI shall state, as distinctly as 
    the nature of the case permits the facts on which the claim to relief is 
    founded, and shall also state that there is no collusion between the 
    petitioner and the other party to the marriage.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    statements contained in every such petition shall be verified by the 
    petitioner or some other competent person in the manner required by law for 
    the verification of plaints, and may, at the hearing, be referred to as 
    evidence.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>33</number> Proceedings 
    to be in camera and may not be printed or published.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every proceeding under this Act shall be conducted in camera and it 
    shall not be lawful for any person to print or publish any matter in 
    relation to any such proceeding except a judgment of the High Court or of 
    the Supreme Court printed or published with the previous permission of the 
    Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any person prints or publishes any matter in contravention of the provisions 
    contained in sub-section (1), he shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to one thousand rupees.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Duty of court in passing decrees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any proceeding under Chapter V or Chapter VI, whether defended or not, if 
    the court is satisfied that,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any of the grounds for granting 
    relief exists; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
1[where 
    the petition is founded on the ground specified in clause (a) of sub-section 
    (1) of section 27, the petitioner has not in any manner been accessory to or 
    connived at or condoned the act of sexual intercourse referred to therein], 
    or, where the ground of the petition is cruelty, the petitioner has not in 
    any manner condoned the cruelty; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   when divorce is sought on the 
    ground of mutual consent, such consent has not been obtained by force, fraud 
    or undue influence; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the petition is not presented or 
    prosecuted in collusion with the respondent; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   there has not been any unnecessary 
    or improper delay in instituting the proceedings; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   there is no other legal ground why 
    the relief should not be granted; then, and in such a case, but not 
    otherwise, the court shall decree such relief accordingly.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Before proceeding to grant any relief under this Act it shall be the duty of 
    the court in the first instance, in every case where it is possible so to do 
    consistently with the nature and circumstances of the case, to make every 
    endeavour to bring about a reconciliation between the parties:
 


    2[Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall apply to any proceeding wherein 
    relief is sought on any of the grounds specified in clause (c), clause (e), 
    clause (f), clause (g) and clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 27.]
 


    2[(3) For the purpose 
    of aiding the court in bringing about such reconciliation, the court may, if 
    the parties so desire or if the court thinks it just and proper so to do, 
    adjourn the proceedings for a reasonable period not exceeding fifteen days 
    and refer the matter to any person named by the parties in this behalf or to 
    any person nominated by the court if the parties fail to name any person, 
    with directions to report to the court as to whether reconciliation can be 
    and has been, effected and the court shall in disposing of the proceeding 
    have due regard to the report.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    every case where a marriage is dissolved by a decree of divorce, the court 
    passing the decree shall give a copy thereof free of cost to each of the 
    parties.]  
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>35</number> Relief for 
    respondent in divorce and other proceedings.—In any proceeding for 
    divorce or judicial separation or restitution of conjugal rights, the 
    respondent may not only oppose the relief sought on the ground of 
    petitioner’s adultery, cruelty or desertion, but also make a counter-claim 
    for any relief under this Act on that ground, and if the petitioner’s 
    adultery, cruelty or desertion is proved, court may give to the respondent 
    any relief under this Act to which he or she would have been entitled if he 
    or she had presented a petition seeking such relief on that ground.]  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Alimony pendente lite.—Where 
    in any proceeding under Chapter V or Chapter VI it appears to the district 
    court that the wife has no independent income sufficient for her support and 
    the necessary expenses of the proceeding, it may, on the application of the 
    wife, order the husband to pay to her the expenses of the proceeding, and 
    weekly or monthly during the proceeding such sum as having regard to the 
    husband’s income, it may seem to the court to be reasonable.  
 


    1[Provided that the 
    application for the payment of the expenses of the proceeding and such 
    weekly or monthly sum during the proceeding under Chapter V or Chapter VI, 
    shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty days from the date of 
    service of notice on the husband.]  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Permanent alimony and maintenance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any court exercising jurisdiction under Chapter V or Chapter VI may, at the 
    time of passing any decree or at any time subsequent to the decree, on 
    application made to it for the purpose, order that the husband shall secure 
    to the wife for her maintenance and support, if necessary, by a charge on 
    the husband’s property such gross sum or such monthly or periodical payment 
    of money for a term not exceeding her life, as, having regard to her own 
    property, if any, her husband’s property and ability 

    1[the conduct of the 
    parties and other circumstances of the case], it may seem to the court to be 
    just.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the district court is satisfied that there is a change in the circumstances 
    of either party at any time after it has made an order under sub-section 
    (1), it may, at the instance of either party, vary, modify or rescind any 
    such order in such manner as it may seem to the court to be just.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the district court is satisfied that the wife in whose favour an order has 
    been made under this section has re-married or is not leading a chaste life,
    

    2[it may, at the 
    instance of the husband vary, modify or rescind any such order and in such 
    manner as the court may deem just.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Custody of children.—In 
    any proceeding under Chapter V or Chapter VI the district court may, from 
    time to time, pass such interim orders and make such provisions in the 
    decree as it may seem to it to be just and proper with respect to the 
    custody, maintenance and education of minor children, consistently with 
    their wishes wherever possible, and may, after the decree, upon application 
    by petition for the purpose, make, revoke, suspend or vary, from time to 
    time, all such orders and provisions with respect to the custody, 
    maintenance and education of such children as might have been made by such 
    decree or interim orders in case the proceeding for obtaining such decree 
    were still pending.  
 


    1[Provided that the 
    application with respect to the maintenance and education of the minor 
    children, during the proceeding, under Chapter V or Chapter VI, shall, as 
    far as possible, be disposed of within sixty days from the date of service 
    of notice on the respondent.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> Appeals from 
    decrees and orders.—
<section><number>1</number> All decrees made by the court in any proceeding 
    under Chapter V or Chapter VI shall, subject to the provisions of 
    sub-section (3), be appealable as decrees of the court made in the exercise 
    of its original civil jurisdiction, and such appeal shall lie to the court 
    to which appeals ordinarily lie from the decisions of the court given in the 
    exercise of its original civil jurisdiction. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Orders made by the court in any proceeding under this Act, under section 37 
    or section 38 shall, subject to the provisions of sub-section (3), be 
    appealable if they are not interim orders, and every such appeal shall lie 
    to the court to which appeals ordinarily lie from the decisions of the court 
    given in the exercise of its original jurisdiction.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    There shall be no appeal under this section on the subject of costs only.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a 

    2[period of ninety 
    days] from the date of the decree or order.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>39A</number> 
    Enforcement of decrees and orders.—All 
    decrees and orders made by the court in any proceeding under Chapter V or 
    Chapter VI shall be enforced in the like manner as the decrees and orders of 
    the court made in the exercise of its original civil jurisdiction for the 
    time being are enforced.]  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>40</number> Application of Act 5 of 1908.—Subject to the other provisions 
      contained in this Act, and to such rules as the High Court may make in 
      this behalf, all proceedings under this Act shall be regulated, as far as 
      may be, by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>


    1[<number>40A</number> Power to 
    transfer petitions in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> Where—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a petition under this Act has been 
    presented to the district court having jurisdiction, by a party to the 
    marriage praying for a decree for judicial separation under section 23 or 
    for a decree of divorce under section 27, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   another petition under this Act 
    has been presented thereafter by the other party to the marriage praying for 
    decree for judicial separation under section 23, or for decree of divorce 
    under section 27 on any ground whether in the same district court, or in a 
    different district court, in the same State orin a different State, the 
    petition shall be dealt with as specified in sub-section (2).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In a 
    case where sub-section (1) applies,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if the petitions are presented to 
    the same district court, both the petitions shall be tried and heard 
    together by that district court;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if the petitions are presented to 
    different district courts, the petitions presented later shall be 
    transferred to the district court in which the earlier petition was 
    presented and both the petitions shall be heard and disposed of together by 
    the district court in which the earlier petition was presented.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In a 
    case where clause (b) of sub-section (2) applies, the court or the 
    Government, as the case may be, competent under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908 (5 of 1908), to transfer any suit or proceeding from the district court 
    in which the later petition has been presented to the district court in 
    which the earlier petition is pending, shall exercise its powers to transfer 
    such later petition as if it had been empowered so to do under the said 
    Code.]
 

 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>40B</number> Special provisions relating to trial and disposal 
      of petitions under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The trial of a petition under 
      this Act shall, so far as is practicable consistently with the interests 
      of justice in respect of the trial, be continued from day to day, until 
      its conclusions, unless the court finds the adjournment of the trial 
      beyond the following day to be necessary for reasons to be 
      recorded. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every petition under this Act shall be tried as expeditiously 
      as possible and endeavour shall be made to conclude the trial within six 
      months from the date of service of notice of the petition on the 
      respondent.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal under this Act shall be heard as expeditiously as 
      possible, and endeavour shall be made to conclude the hearing within three 
      months from the date of service of notice of appeal on the 
      respondent.]
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>40C</number> 
    Documentary evidence.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any enactment to the contrary, no document shall be 
    inadmissible in evidence in any proceeding at the trial of a petition under 
    this Act on the ground that it is not duly stamped or registered.] 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Power of High Court to make rules regulating procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The High Court shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such 
    rules consistent with the provisions contained in this Act and the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), as it may consider expedient for the 
    purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of Chapters V, VI and VII.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    provision, such rules shall provide for,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the impleading by the petitioner 
    of the adulterer as a co-respondent on a petition for divorce on the ground 
    of adultery, and the circumstances in which the petitioner may be execused 
    from doing so;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the awarding of damages against 
    any such co-espondent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the intervention in any proceeding 
    under Chapter V or Chapter VI by any person not already a party thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the form and contents of petitions 
    for nullity of marriage or for divorce and the payment of costs incurred by 
    parties to such petitions; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   any other matter for which no 
    provision or no sufficient provision is made in this Act, and for which 
    provision is made in the Indian Divorce Act, 1869 (4 of 1869).  
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Saving.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall affect the validity of any marriage not 
    solemnized under its provisions; nor shall this Act be deemed directly or 
    indirectly to affect the validity of any mode of contracting marriage.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>43</number> Penalty on married person marrying again under this 
      Act.—Save 
      as otherwise provided in Chapter III, every person who, being at the time 
      married, procures, a marriage of himself or herself to be solemnized under 
      this Act shall be deemed to have committed an offence under section 494 or 
      section 495 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860), as the case may 
      be, and the marriage so solemnized shall be void.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Punishment of bigamy.—Every 
    person whose marriage is solemnized under this Act and who, during the 
    lifetime of his or her wife or husband, contracts any other marriage shall 
    be subject to the penalties provided in section 494 and section 495 of the 
    Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860), for the offence of marrying again 
    during the lifetime of a husband or wife, and the marriage so contracted 
    shall be void.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Penalty for signing false declaration or certificate.—Every 
    person making, signing or attesting any declaration or certificate required 
    by or under this Act containing a statement which is false and which he 
    either knows or believes to be false or does not believe to be true shall be 
    guilty of the offence described in section 199 of the Indian Penal Code, 
    1860 (45 of 1860).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>46</number> Penalty for wrongful action of Marriage 
      Officer.—Any Marriage Officer who knowingly and wilfully solemnizes a 
      marriage under this Act,—  
 <section><number>1</number>   without 
      publishing a notice regarding such marriage as required by section 5, 
      or  
 </section><section><number>2</number>   within 
      thirty days of the publication of the notice of such marriage, or  
 </section><section><number>3</number>   in 
      contravention of any other provision in this Act,  
 shall be punishable with simple 
      imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which 
      may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Marriage Certificate Book to be open to inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Marriage Certificate Book kept under this Act shall at all reasonable 
    times be open for inspection and shall be admissible as evidence of the 
    statements therein contained.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Certified extracts from the Marriage Certificate Book shall, on application, 
    be given by the Marriage Officer to the applicant on payment by him of the 
    prescribed fee.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Transmission of copies of entries in marriage records.—Every 
    Marriage Officer in a State shall send to Registrar-General of Births, 
    Deaths and Marriages of that State at such intervals and in such form as may 
    be prescribed, a true copy of all entries made by him in the Marriage 
    Certificate Book since the last of such intervals, and, in the case of 
    Marriage Officers outside the territories to which this Act extends, the 
    true copy shall be sent to such authority as the Central Governmnt may 
    specify in this behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Correction of errors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any Marriage Officer who discovers any error in the form or substance of any 
    entry in the Marriage Certificate Book may, within one month next after the 
    discovery of such error, in the presence of the persons married or, in case 
    of their death or absence, in the presence of two other credible witnesses, 
    correct the error by entry in the margin without any alteration of the 
    original entry and shall sign the marginal entry and add thereto the date of 
    such correction and the Marriage Officer shall make the like marginal entry 
    in the certificate thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every correction made under this section shall be attested by the witnesses 
    in whose presence it was made.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a copy of any entry has already been sent under section 48 to the 
    Registrar-General or other authority the Marriage Officer shall make and 
    send in like manner a separate certificate of the original erroneous entry 
    and of the marginal corrections therein made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government, in the case of 

    1[***] officers of the 
    Central Government, and the State Government, in all other cases, may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
    purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the duties and powers of Marriage 
    Officers and the areas in which they may exercise jurisdiction;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the manner in which a Marriage 
    Officer may hold inquiries under this Act and the procedure therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the form and manner in which any 
    books required by or under this Act shall be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the fees that may be levied for 
    the performance of any duty imposed upon a Marriage Officer under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the manner in which public notice 
    shall be given under section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the form in which, and the 
    intervals within which, copies of entries in the Marriage Certificate Book 
    shall be sent in pursuance of section 48;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   any other matter which may be or 
    requires to be prescribed.
 


    2[(3) Every rule made 
    by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
    after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, 
    for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
    in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every rule made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as it is made before the State Legislature.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Repeals and Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Special Marriage Act, 1872 (3 of 1872), and any law corresponding to the 
    Special Marriage Act, 1872 (3 of 1872), in force in any Part B State 
    immediately before the commencement of this Act are hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    all marriages duly solemnized under the Special Marriage Act, 1872 (3 of 
    1872), or any such corresponding law shall be deemed to have been solemnized 
    under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    all suits and proceedings in causes and matters matrimonial which, when this 
    Act comes into operation, are pending in any court, shall be dealt with and 
    decided by such court, so far as may be, as if they had been originally 
    instituted therein under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (2) shall be without prejudice to the provisions 
    contained in section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), which 
    shall also apply to the repeal of the corresponding law as if such 
    corresponding law had been an enactment.  
 
 
 
 
 
 

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
    SPECIAL MARRIAGE ACT, 1954
 

 
 


 
 


THE FIRST SCHEDULE
 


[See section 2(b) “Degrees of 
    prohibited relationship”]
 


PART I
 


1.     Mother.
 


2.     Father’s widow (step-mother).
 


3.     Mother’s mother.
 


4.     Mother’s father’s widow (step 
    grand-mother).
 


5.     Mother’s mother’s mother.
 


6.     Mother’s mother’s father’s widow (step 
    great grand-mother).
 


7.     Mother’s father’s mother.
 


8.     Mother’s father’s father’s widow (step 
    great grand-mother).
 


9.     Father’s mother.
 


10.   Father’s father’s widow (step-grand 
    mother).
 


11.   Father’s mother’s mother.
 


12.   Father’s mother’s father’s widow (step 
    great grand-mother).
 


13.   Father’s father’s mother.
 


14.   Father’s father’s father’s widow (step 
    great grand-mother).
 


15.   Daughter.
 


16.   Son’s widow.
 


17.   Daughter’s daughter.
 


18.   Daughter’s son’s widow.
 


19.   Son’s daughter.
 


20.   Son’s son’s widow.
 


21.   Daughter’s daughter’s daughter.
 


22.   Daughter’s daughter’s son’s widow.
 


23.   Daughter’s son’s daughter.
 


24.   Daughter’s son’s son’s widow.
 


25.   Son’s daughter’s daughter.
 


26.   Son’s daughter’s son’s widow.
 


27.   Son’s son’s daughter.
 


28.   Son’s son’s son’s widow.
 


29.   Sister.
 


30.   Sister’s daughter.
 


31.   Brother’s daughter.
 


32.   Mother’s sister.
 


33.   Father’s sister.
 


34.   Father’s brother’s daughter.
 


35.   Father’s sister’s daughter.
 


36.   Mother’s sister’s daughter.
 


37.   Mother’s brother’s daughter.
 


Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    Part, the expression “widow” includes a divorced wife.
 

 
 


PART II
 


1.     Father.
 


2.     Mother’s husband (step-father).
 


3.     Father’s father.
 


4.     Father’s mother’s husband (step 
    grand-father).
 


5.     Father’s father’s father.
 


6.     Father’s father’s mother’s husband 
    (step great grand-father).
 


7.     Father’s mother’s father.
 


8.     Father’s mother’s mother’s husband 
    (step great grand-father).
 


9.     Mother’s father.
 


10.   Mother’s mother’s husband (step 
    grand-father).
 


11.   Mother’s father’s father.
 


12.   Mother’s father’s mother’s husband (step 
    great grand-father).
 


13.   Mother’s mother’s father.
 


14.   Mother’s mother’s mother’s husband (step 
    great grand-father).
 


15.   Son.
 


16.   Daughter’s husband.
 


17.   Son’s son.
 


18.   Son’s daughter’s husband.
 


19.   Daughter’s son.
 


20.   Daughter’s daughter’s husband.
 


21.   Son’s son’s son.
 


22.   Son’s son’s daughter’s husband.
 


23.   Son’s daughter’s son.
 


24.   Son’s daughter’s daughter’s husband.
 


25.   Daughter’s son’s son.
 


26.   Daughter’s son’s daughter’s husband.
 


27.   Daughter’s daughter’s son.
 


28.   Daughter’s daughter’s daughter’s 
    husband.
 


29.   Brother.
 


30.   Brother’s son.
 


31.   Sister’s son.
 


32.   Mother’s brother.
 


33.   Father’s brother.
 


34.   Father’s brother’s son.
 


35.   Father’s sister’s son.
 


36.   Mother’s sister’s son.
 


37.   Mother’s brother’s son.
 


Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    part, the expression “husband” includes a divorced husband.
 


 
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
    SPECIAL MARRIAGE ACT, 1954
 

 
 


 
 


THE THIRD SCHEDULE
 


(See section 11)
 



    Declaration to be made by the Bridegroom
 

 
 




    I, A.B., hereby declare as follows:— tc 
    "I, 
    A.B., hereby declare as follows\:—" 
 


1.   I am at the present time unmarried (or a 
    widower or a divorcee, as the case may be).
 


2.   I have completed .....years of age.
 


3.   I am not related to C.D. (the bride) 
    within the degrees of prohibited relationship.
 


4.   I am aware that, if any statement in this 
    declaration is false, and if in making such statement I either know or 
    believe it to be false or do not believe it to be true, I am liable to 
    imprisonment and also to fine.
 




    (Sd.) A.B. the (Bridegroom)
 

 
 




    DECLARATION TO BE MADE BY THE BRIDE
 

 
 




    I, C.D., hereby declare as follows:— tc 
    "I, 
    C.D., hereby declare as follows\:—" 
 


1.   I am at the present time unmarried (or a 
    widow or a divorcee, as the case may be).
 


2.   I have completed ....years of age.
 


3.   I am not related to A.B. (the bridegroom) 
    within the degree of prohibited relationship.
 


4.   I am aware that, if any statement in this 
    declaration is false, and if in making such statement I either know or 
    believe it to be false or do not believe it to be true, I am liable to 
    imprisonment and also to fine.
 




    (Sd.) C.D. (the Bride)
 

 
 


Signed in our presence by the above-named A.B. 
    and C.D. So far as we are aware there is no lawful impediment to the 
    marriage.
 




    (Sd.) G.H.
 




    (Sd.) I.J.  Three witnesses
 




    (Sd.) K.L.
 




            Countersigned E.F.,
 




Marriage Officer
 


Dated the............... day 
    of...............20.....
 


 
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by Act 
      68 of 1976, sec. 38 (w.e.f. 27-5-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 68 
    of 1976, sec. 38 (w.e.f. 27-5-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   The words 
    “diplomatic and consular officers and other” omitted by Act 33 of 1969, sec. 
    29 (w.e.f. 31-8-1969).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>