<act> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Arms Rules, 1962.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 1st 
October, 1962.
 



</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  "Act" means the Arms Act, 1959 
(54 of 1959);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  "appellate authority" means the 
appellate authority referred to in rule 5;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  "authority" or "officer" means, 
except where otherwise specifically provided in these rules, the District 
Magistrate or such other Officer as may, from time to time, be notified in the 
Official Gazette by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  "company" has the same meaning 
as that assigned to it in the Explanation under section 33;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  "dealer" means a person who, by 
way of trade or business, manufacturers, converts, repairs, proves, tests, 
sells, exports, imports, or transfers or keeps, for sale, repair or test arms 
or ammunition;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  "District Magistrate", 
includes—
 
 

1[***]
 <subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in relation to any 
district or part thereof, an Additional District Magistrate or any other 
officer specially empowered in this behalf by the Government of the State 
concerned;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  in relation to a Union 
territory, any officer specially empowered by the Central Government in this 
behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>iv</number>  in relation to the tribal 
areas of Assam, specified in Part B of the Table appended to paragraph 29 of 
the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution, a Political Officer; and
 
 

2[(v)  in relation to the suburbs of 
Calcutta, as defined by notification issued from time to time by the Government 
of West Bengal in their Official Gazette under the Calcutta Suburban Police 
Act, 1866 (Bengal Act II of 1866), the Commissioner of Police, Calcutta, and a 
Deputy Commissioner of Police, Calcutta, nominated by the State Government in 
this behalf;]
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>g</number>  "Form" means a Form as set out 
in Schedule III;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  "port" includes an airport;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  "Schedule" means a Schedule 
appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>j</number>  "section" means a section of 
the Act;
 
 

3[(k)  "Sub-divisional Magistrate" 
includes Additional Sub-divisional Magistrate, Sub-divisional Officer and 
Additional Sub-divisional Officer.]
 
 






</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Classification of arms 
or ammunition.—For 
the purposes of the Act and these rules, "arms" or “ammunition” shall be of the 
categories specified in columns 2 and 3 respectively of Schedule I and 
references to any category of arms or ammunition in these rules shall be 
construed accordingly.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Licensing authority 
and forms of licences.—Licences 
under Chapter II of the Act may be granted or renewed for such purposes, by 
such authorities, in such Forms and to be valid for such period and in such 
areas as are specified in Schedule II, subject to such conditions as are 
specified in that Schedule and in the licence:
 

1[Provided that 
the licences granted or renewed by a licensing authority may be signed by such 
officer subordinate to that authority as may be specially empowered in this 
behalf by the State Government.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number>
Reasons to be communicated to the appellate authority in certain cases.— 
Where a licensing authority is of opinion that it will not be in the public 
interest to furnish reasons for the refusal, renewal, variation of conditions, 
revocation or suspension, of a licence, to the applicant, the recorded reasons 
therefor and the facts of the case shall be communicated by him to appellate 
authority.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number>
Direction and control over licensing authorities.—All licensing 
authorities shall work under the direction and control of their respective 
appellate authorities.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Restriction in 
granting licences for acquisition, possessing or carrying of arms or ammunition 
of category I.—
<section><number>a</number> 
No licence shall be granted for acquisition, possession or carrying of arms or 
ammunition of categories I (b), I (c) and I (d) unless they have been lawfully 
imported into India or are being imported into India with the sanction of the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A licence for 
acquisition, possessing or carrying of ammunition of categories I (b) and I (c) 
shall be granted only if the licensing authority is satisfied that the 
ammunition is to be sued with rifles or muskets which are lawfully possessed 
for sporting purposes or with pistols or revolvers which have been lawfully 
imported into India; and the amount of ammunition which the licensee may 
possess during each period of 12 months immediately succeeding the date of 
grant of licence shall be entered in the licence.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Copies of licence of 
categories I and II to be sent to certain authorities.—A 
copy of every licence granted for arms or ammunition of categories I
<section><number>a</number>, I(b), 
I (c), I (d) and II, shall forthwith be sent—
 </section><section>
       <number>a</number>  to the District Magistrate of 
the place in which the arms or ammunition are to be kept, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to the State Government if such 
place is in the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number>
possession of arms or ammunition 
for certain purposes to include use thereof.—Possession 
of the following arms or ammunition for the purposes mentioned against each 
includes use thereof, for such purposes only provided that such use does not 
involve manufacture of any arms or ammunition (including explosive and 
fire-works):—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  arms, for theatrical 
performance, cinematograph production or signalling for starting races or 
athletic meets;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  ingredients of ammunition, for
bona fide industrial, agricultural or medicinal purposes.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Restriction may be 
imposed by Central Government.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
Any licence having effect outside the State in which it is granted, shall be 
subject to any restrictions which may be imposed by a general or special order 
of the Central Government.
 

2[(2) Save where 
he is specially authorised in this behalf by the District Magistrate concerned, 
the licensee shall not carry any arms covered by the licence within the campus 
or precincts of any educational institution.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Of retainer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the owner of any arms or ammunition licensed in Form III applies for 
permitting his agent, relative or employee to possess or carry any of the arms 
or ammunition covered by the licence for sport, protection or display, on his 
behalf, whether in attendance only or not and in circumstances different from 
those mentioned in the proviso to section 3, such agent, relative or employee 
may, if the licensing authority considers it fit, be shown as a retainer by 
entering his name and other particulars in column 6 of the owner’s licence in 
Form III.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A licence in Form III 
granted to a company for the protection of its premises or property shall be in 
the name of a member, agent or other representative of the company, who shall 
be responsible for the custody of the weapon. The name of a servant or any 
other employee entrusted with weapon for guarding the premises or property of 
the company shall be entered as a retainer in the appropriate column of the 
licence. The licensing authority shall issue to the licensee a permit in Form 
IIIB for each of such retainers shown in the licencee. The permit shall remain 
in the personal custody of representative of the company and shall be made over 
to the retainers when they are entrusted with the weapon covered by the licence:
 

1[Provided that 
the licensing authority shall obtain a report from the Police about the 
antecedents of the retainer and take into consideration such report before 
admitting him as retainer.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A licence in Form 
IIIA for possessing and carrying of arms or ammunition may be granted to a 
person nominated to be his retainer by a person exempted from licensing 
requirements:
 
Provided that the 
retainer shall have no right, independent of the person so exempted, to use the 
arms or ammunition covered by the licence, and the licence shall cease to be in 
force on the day on which the person so exempted has ceased to be an exemptee, 
or the retainer has ceased to be in the service of the exemptee:
 

2[Provided further 
that the licensing authority shall obtain a report from the Police about the 
antecedents of the retainer and take into consideration such report before 
admitting him as a retainer.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Licences for 
protection of crops and cattle.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a licence is granted in Form V, any member of the family of the licensee 
or a servant employed by the licensee to watch the crops or cattle and residing 
with him, may, in the discretion of the licensing authority, be allowed to 
carry any of the arms or ammunition covered by the licence to protect crops or 
cattle against wild animals in the area specified in the licence by entering 
his name and particulars in column 2 thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, after the end 
of any harvest season, the State Government considers it expedient that for the 
protection of wildlife in any area, any arms or ammunition licensed in Form V 
should be deposited in a police station or with a licensed dealer, it may, by 
order require any licensee to deposit such arms or ammunition for such period 
as the arms or ammunition are not required for the protection of crops or 
cattle and as may be specified therein, and thereupon the licensee should be 
bound to comply with such order.
</section></article> 
 THE ARMS RULES, 1962
  
 <article><number>15</number> Licences for target 
practice.—Where 
a licence in Form VI has been granted in the name of any military mess, club or 
association it shall be lawful for any member of such mess, club or association 
to use the fire-arms or ammunition covered by such licence for the purpose of 
the mess, club or association in accordance with the conditions of the 
licensee.</article> 
 THE ARMS RULES, 1962
  
 <article><number>16</number> Age limit for training and 
target practice.—Any person below the age of 
sixteen years but not below the age of twelve years may be allowed to use a 
fire-arm for the purposes of training in the use of such fire-arm in the 
immediate presence, or under the direct supervision and guidance, of an adult 
instructor or the licensee:
 Provided that no person below 
the age of sixteen years shall be allowed to carry any fire-arm requiring a 
licence, in a public place, except in the immediate presence and supervision of 
the person who is lawfully entitled to carry such fire-arm.
 Explanation.—For the purpose of this rule, 
an "adult" means a person who has completed the age of twenty-one 
years.</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Traveller’s 
(temporary) licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of rule 8, a licence in Form VIII may be granted to 
any bona fide traveller, proceeding from the place of his arrival in 
India to his place of destination in India, for the possession and carrying of 
arms or ammunition for the duration of the journey, by the licensing authority 
at the place of arrival.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of every such 
licence shall be forthwith sent to the District Magistrate having jurisdiction 
over the place of destination of the licensee; such authority shall satisfy 
himself, when necessary, that the licensee has complied with condition 7 
entered on the Form of the licence.
</section></article> 
 THE ARMS RULES, 1962
  
 <article><number>18</number> Application of section 4 of 
the Act.—In any 
area specified in the notification issued by the Central Government under 
section 4, licence for acquisition, possession or carrying in that area of arms 
of such class or description as may be specified in that notification, may also 
be granted or renewed as provided in Schedule II, subject to such conditions as 
are specified in that Schedule and in the licence.</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Arms other than 
fire-arms.—Unless 
the Central or State Government by notification in the Official Gazette so 
directs, no licence shall be required for the manufacture, sale, possession for 
sale, or test, of arms of category V except in the areas notified under section 
4.
</article> 
 THE ARMS RULES, 1962
  
 <article><number>20</number> Manufacture, conversion, 
shortening, repair, test, sale, etc., of arms or ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> The licensing authority 
while granting a licence in Form IX shall show clearly in the licence 
Form—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  the categories and description of the arms or ammunition covered by 
the licence;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  the transactions permitted in respect of the different categories of 
arms or ammunition, and
 omit 
any transactions or categories of arms or ammunition, not covered by the 
licence.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A copy of every licence 
granted in Form IX by an authority other than the District Magistrate of the 
place of business, factory or shop of the licensee shall forthwith be sent to 
that District Magistrate.</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Conversion, repair, 
test, sale, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a licence is granted in Form IX or Form XI for conversion or repair, but 
not manufacture, of any category of fire-arms or ammunition, it entitles the 
licensee to fabricate components or parts, for the purpose of conversion or 
repair of such fire-arms or ammunition but not to manufacture such components 
or parts to be utilised for assembling into complete fire-arms or ammunition of 
any category which he is allowed to manufacture.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a)
a licence in Form XI shall not 
entitle the dealer to shorten a fire-arm or to convert an imitation fire-arm, 
into a fire-arm, unless he has a licence in Form IX showing specifically that 
he is permitted to shorten a fire-arm or convert an imitation fire-arm into a 
fire-arm
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Under no 
circumstances shall a dealer shorten the barrel of a rifle or smooth-bore gun 
so that the resultant length becomes less than 20 inches.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The details of the 
cases in which barrels are shortened and imitation fire-arms are converted into 
fire-arms shall be reported every month to the District Magistrate, in such 
form, if any, as may be required.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A dealer having a 
licence in Form XI, Form XII or Form XIII to 

1[repair or test] 
or to sell fire-arms or ammunition shall not take the fire-arms or ammunition 
for testing to a testing range or other place, unless specifically permitted to 
do so by his licence, and he shall carry out tests only in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as are laid down therein.
 

2[(4) Where a 
licence is granted in Form IX or Form XI for conversion of ammunition, it shall 
not entitle the licensee to convert blank cartridges or any ammunitions having 
no projectile into single/multiple projectile ammunition or to load or reload 
any ammunition.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Proof-testing of 
fire-arms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Proof-testing of fire-arms manufactured by a licensed dealer shall be carried 
out only in accordance with the regulations which may be framed by the Central 
Government or framed by such authorities as the Central Government may specify 
in this behalf and approved by that Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No dealer shall sell 
a fire-arm which has not been duly proof-tested.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Licensing authorities 
to furnish information to the District Magistrate.—A 
copy of every licence granted in any Form by any authority other than a 
District Magistrate shall be sent forthwith to the District Magistrate having 
jurisdiction over the area in which the place of business or residence of the 
licensee is situated.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Sale or keeping for 
sale certain arms and ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government or, in the States of 

1[Tamil Nadu], 
Andhra Pradesh or Kerala, the Board of Revenue, may, by licence granted by it 
in Form XI or Form XII, authorise selected dealers to sell or keep for sale a 
specified amount of ammunition of category I (c).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A dealer possessing a 
licence in Form IX, Form XI, or Form XII shall not sell or transfer any arms or 
ammunition of category I (b) or I (c) to any person, unless the acquisition or 
possession of such arms or ammunition is expressly permitted in his licence or 
in his certificate of exemption.
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE ARMS RULES, 1962
  
 <article><number>26</number> Records of transactions in 
arms and ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> Every dealer shall maintain 
such registers as may be prescribed by the Central Government to show receipts, 
disposals, balance of stock in hand and daily sales of arms or ammunition of 
different categories and provide such other information as may be 
required.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every entry of transactions 
in such registers shall be made before the close of business hours on the same 
day and in the case of a sale or transfer the dealer shall, at the time of the 
transaction, require the purchaser or transferee, if not known to him, to 
furnish particulars sufficient for identification, and shall immediately enter 
the said particulars in the registers.</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Inspection of 
premises, stock and record.—Every 
Magistrate and police-officer not below the rank of Inspector, or if the 
Central Government so directs, of Sub-Inspector, 

1[acting within 
the local limits of his authority, or any officer of the Central Government 
specially empowered in this behalf may]—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  enter and inspect the premises 
in which arms or ammunition are manufactured or in which arms or ammunition are 
kept by a manufacturer or dealer in such arms or ammunition; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  examine the stock and accounts 
of receipts and disposals of arms and ammunition or any other register or 
document.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Restrictions upon 
import or export for re-import of arms or ammunition.—A 
licence shall not be granted for the import or export for re-import of any arms 
or ammunition through the medium of post office.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Import by sea or air.—Arms 
or ammunition shall be deemed to have been brought into India by a person when 
such arms or ammunition are imported though an agent and are either—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  consigned to such person 
direct, or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  consigned to the said agent, 
if the agent possess, a certificate from the said person that the arms or 
ammunition are bona fide his property and the agent only clears the arms 
or ammunition from the customs house and forwards the same.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Vessels entering the 
territorial waters of India.—Arms 
or ammunition carried by a vessel entering the territorial waters of India or 
leaving such waters, shall be deemed to be imported or exported as the case may 
be, irrespective of whether the vessel carrying the arms or ammunition does not 
berth.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Import by land or 
river of arms and ammuniton.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a licence is granted in Form XVI and the articles are consigned to an 
area not on the frontier of India, a copy of the licence shall forthwith be 
sent by the authority granting it to the Government of the State concerned or 
the District Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area in which they cross 
such frontier; and the State Government/District Magistrate may in its/his 
discretion require the licensee to produce the arms or ammunition for its/his 
inspection before allowing the same to be taken out.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where arms or 
ammunition are imported by rail, a copy of the licence shall forthwith be sent 
by the authority granting it to the railway authorities at the place to which 
such arms or ammunition are consigned.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Bringing of arms or 
ammunition into India by bona fide tourists.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence, valid for a period of six months from the date of the endorsement 
referred to in sub-rule (1A), may be granted in Form III to bona fide 
tourists referred to in clause (b) of the provisio to sub-section (1) of 
section 10, so far as practicable, six months prior to the expected date of 
arrival of the tourist in India:
 
Provided that the 
validity of the licence so granted shall commence only from the date of 
endorsement of the said licence and that the arms and ammunition covered by the 
licence shall not be used till the date of endorsement of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>1A</number> When a licence is 
granted in Form III to a bona fide tourist, under sub-rule (1), the 
licence, together with the passport/visa of the tourist, shall be presented to 
the licensing authority as soon as may be after the disembarkment of the 
tourist and the latter shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  after obtaining the undertaking 
referred to in sub-rule (2), endorse the licence making it valid for a period 
of six months from the date of the endorsement; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  make an entry in the 
passport/visa giving full particulars of all the arms and ammunition for which 
the licence has been granted.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The licensing 
authority shall obtain an undertaking in writing from the licensee that he 
shall not sell or transfer the arms or ammunition to any one in India without 
the prior permission of the District Magistrate having jurisdiction over the 
place where such sale or transfer is to be made, and where the arms or 
ammunition are sold or transferred he shall inform the customs authority and 
pay the duty, if any.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The passport checking 
authority or any other officer empowered by the District Magistrate in this 
behalf at the port or other place of departure from India shall verify that the 
arms entered in the passport/visa are being taken out of India by the licensee 
and recover the licence and forward the same to the authority who issued it 
with the remarks that the arms have been duly re-exported or lawfully sold or 
transferred in India, as the case may be.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Of exports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The authority granting a licence in Form XVII for export by sea or air of arms 
or ammunition from customs ports to ports in foreign territory or
commonwealth shall send a copy 
of such licence to the agent or master of the vessel or to the air carrier by 
which the arms or ammunition covered by the licence are intended to taken out 
of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The weapons of the 
following description shall not be allowed to be exported namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  weapons falling within the 
definition of "antiquity" under the Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947 (31 
of 1947)*;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  weapons of current and popular 
bores for which ammunition is available in the country; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  automatic weapons and weapons 
which are in use by the police or the armed forces of the Union.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application for 
the grant of a licence in Form XVII or Form XVIII for export of fire-arms shall 
be accompanied by a certificate from the Director-General of Archaeology of the 
Central Government to the effect that the arms intended to be exported do not 
fall within the definition of "antiquity" under the Antiquities (Export 
Control) Act, 1947 (31 of 1947)*. If the application is made to the Central 
Government, it shall be accompanied by a further certificate from the licensing 
authority of the place from where the weapons are intended to be exported 
certifying that the weapons do not belong to any of descriptions mentioned in 
sub-rule (2).
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Export by land or 
river of arms and ammunition.—When 
a licence for export of arms or ammunition by land or river is granted in Form 
XVIII a copy of the licence shall forthwith be sent by the licensing authority—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  where the arms or ammunition are 
exported by rail, to the District Magistrate of the place from which the 
consignment is to be despatched or, in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, to the 
State Government, and such authority shall forthwith send a copy to the railway 
authorities at the station from which the consignment is to be despatched;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  where the arms or ammunition are 
exported by road or river, to the District Magistrate having jurisdiction over 
the area out of which they are to cross the frontier of India; and such 
Magistrate may, in his discretion, require the licensee to produce the arms or 
ammunition for his inspection before allowing them to leave the area.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Export and re-import 
of arms and ammunition by sea or air.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence in Form XIX may be granted for export of arms or ammunition by sea or 
air from one place in India and re-import into another place in India—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  by the Central Government or any 
other officer specially empowered by it, if—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  the arms or ammunition are 
taken by sea or by an International Air Service or across intervening territory 
not forming part of India, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the arms or ammunition 
form part of the estate of a deceased or insane person who was or is subject to 
the Indian Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957), or whose estate is dealt with under the 
Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private Property) Act, 1950 (4 of 1950), where 
such arms or ammunition are to be sent to the wife, widow, legal representative 
or next-of-kin of such deceased or insane person; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  by the licensing authority—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  for import, at the place 
of destination, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  for export, at the place 
of despatch subject to the previous consent of the licensing authority at the 
place of destination as required under rule 50,
 if 
the arms or ammunition are carried by sea or by an internal air service.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule, "India" 
includes any of ex-French settlements in India.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of every 
licence granted under sub-rule (1) shall forthwith be sent by the authority 
granting it to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the licensing 
authority/authorities of the place of despatch/destination of the articles as 
the case may be; or if the place of despatch/destination is in any of the 
ex-French settlements in India, to the Secretary, General Administration 
Department, Government of Pondicherry; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where the place of despatch/destination 
of the articles is other than a port—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  to the licensing authority 
at the port of export/re-import; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  if the route includes 
transport by rail, to the railway authorities at the station from which the 
consignment is to be despatched.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Arms or ammunition to 
be delivered to Commissioner of Customs in certain cases.—Where 
a vessel or aircraft bound for a port other than a port in India calls at any 
port in India in the course of its voyage, and remains there for a periods 
exceeding forty-eight hours, any arms or ammunition in the possession of any 
passenger not exempted from liability to take out a licence in respect of such 
possession shall be delivered by him to the Commissioner of Customs to be 
detained until the departure by sea or air, as the case may be, of such 
passenger, and it shall not be necessary for such passenger to take out any 
licence in respect of the arms or ammunition so delivered and detained.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Prohibition of 
transport of arms and ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as herein otherwise provided, no person shall transport over India or any 
part thereof any fire-arms or ammunition or any arms of category V, except 
under and in accordance with the conditions of a licence granted under these 
rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in sub-rule 
(1) or in section 12 shall be deemed to apply to arms or ammunition—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  transported personally or as 
personal luggage, in reasonable quantities for his own use, by a person 
lawfully entitled to possess or carry such arms or ammunition;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  transported by a person licensed 
to manufacture such articles, for proof testing, in a case or package legibly 
addressed to a Government establishment or an establishment approved in this 
behalf by the Central Government, or re-transported by such establishment to 
such person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  of category V, transported 
through an area where the Central Government has, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, applied section 4, or from such area where section 4 does not 
apply, provided that the weapons are properly packed and labelled, showing 
clearly the description of these articles and the name and address of the 
consignee;         
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  transported by a licensed dealer 
for export or after import, in accordance with a licence for their export or 
import—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  from the place of despatch 
to the port or other place of export, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  from the port of other 
place of import to the place of destination, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  by transhipment in the 
port of import for re-export by sea or air;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  transported—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  by a person lawfully 
entitled to possess such articles, in reasonable quantities for his own use 
from the premises of a licensed dealer, or for purposes of examination or 
repair or test to or from any such premises, or to the address of any other 
person lawfully entitled to possess such articles; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  by a licensed dealer in a 
case or package legibly addressed to a person lawfully entitled to possess such 
articles, in compliance with an order given by such person for the supply of 
such articles, in reasonable quantities, for his own use or carrying out 
necessary repairs thereto;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  being chlorates, transported 
for bona fide industrial, agricultural or medical purposes:
 
Provided that—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number>  transport of arms or ammunition 
under clause (d), clause (e) or clause (f) shall be subject to obtaining a 
certificate of no objection from the licensing authority at the destination of 
the articles as provided for in rule 50;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number>  transport of arms or 
ammunition personally for any of the purposes stated in sub-clause (i) of 
clause (e) without using them through any area outside the area of validity of 
his possession licence, shall be subject to his obtaining a permit from the 
licensing authority at the starting place of transport; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number>  prior intimation of the 
transport of arms of category V under clause (c) or of chlorates under clause 
(f) shall be given to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police-station or a 
Magistrate having jurisdiction over the place of despatch.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The officer or 
Magistrate receiving prior intimation under clause (iii) of the proviso to 
sub-rule (2) shall immediately inform the District Magistrate and, if the 
articles are transported by rail, the superintendent of railway police having 
jurisdiction—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  over the place of destination 
in the case of transport of chlorate, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  over the place of entry into 
the area where section 4 applies, in the case of transport of arms of category 
V.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, ‘transport’ includes movement or arms or ammunition 
across any part of the country, but does not include movement of arms or 
ammunition by a licensed dealer from a warehouse, godown or any other similar 
place to his factory, shop or other places of business within the same village, 
town or city.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Transport of arms or 
ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A copy of licence granted in Form XX for transport of arms or ammunition beyond 
the local limits of the jurisdiction of the authority granting it shall 
forthwith be sent to the District Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area 
where the place to which the articles are consigned is situated, or if such 
place is in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, to the Government of the State.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of every such 
licence granted by a District Magistrate for transport within the limits of his 
jurisdiction shall forthwith be sent to the
subordinate Magistrate (if any) 
having jurisdiction over the place to which the arms or ammunition are 
consigned. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where arms or 
ammunition are transported by rail, a copy of such licence or a copy of the no 
objection certificate referred to in rule 50 shall be attached to the way-bill 
or invoice, as the case may be, and telegraphic advice of every such 
consignment shall be sent by the railway authorities from the forwarding to the 
receiving station.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A licence of the 
transport of arms or ammunition shall not, save for special reasons to be 
recorded by the authority granting it, be granted for a period longer than 
twice the time likely to be occupied in the journey to the place of destination 
by the route indicated in the licence:
 
Provided that the licence 
for a longer period, not exceeding a quarter of a year at one time, may be 
granted in connection with industrial purposes for transporting ingredients of 
munition in instalments from the godown to the factory of the licensee situated 
within the same district but not in the same locality. A licensee transporting 
any ingredients of ammunition under such licence shall give prior ammunition to 
the nearest Magistrate/officer-incharge of the police station; and he shall 
make necessary entries promptly in stock registers maintained for the purpose 
at both godown and the factory.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Licence for import, 
transport and re-export of arms and ammunition.—Where 
under the authority of a licence for import, transport and re-export of arms or 
ammunition granted in Form XIX, the arms or ammunition are to be—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  transported across Indian 
territory entirely by rail, a copy of the licence shall forthwith be sent by 
the authority granting it, to the licensing authority and to the railway 
authority at the places from which the consignment is to be despatched;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  transported across Indian 
territory and re-exported by land or river, a copy of the licence shall 
forthwith be sent by the authority granting it to the District Magistrate 
having jurisdiction over the area out of which the consignment is to cross the 
frontier of India.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Scrutiny by 
authorities of consignments containing arms and ammunition.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> (i) Where a package or case containing arms or ammunition is brought for 
export or transport, to a railway authority or shipping agent or a master of 
vessel or air carrier, the latter shall, before receiving the articles for 
despatch or despatching them, verify that they are accompanied by the original 
licence in the case of export or an attested copy of the licence in the case of 
transport or of export for re-import.
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Where a consignment 
is received after import, or transport, by an authority at a port checking 
import or by a railway authority, such authority shall require the production 
of the original licence before delivering the consignment.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where arms or 
ammunition consigned to an area not on the frontier of India are imported, or 
where a consignment of arms or ammunition is exported, by land or river, the 
District Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area in India into or out of 
which it crosses the frontier of India or an officer appointed by him in this 
behalf shall require the licensee to produce original licence and may, in his 
discretion, require the licence ot produce the arms or ammunition for his 
inspection before allowing the articles to leave the area.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The aforesaid 
authority shall satisfy himself—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number>  that the licence accompanying 
the consignment or produce by the licensee is identical in substance with the 
copy sent to him; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number>  that the arms or ammunition 
correspond with the description given in such licence.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where in any case 
referred to in sub-rule (1)—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the original licence is not 
produced by the consignee or the original or attested copy of the licence does 
not accompany the case or package, as the case may be, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the licence is not identical in 
substance with the copy sent to the authority, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the arms or ammunition do no 
correspond with the description given in such licence,
 
the authority shall not receive the articles for despatch or allow the articles 
to proceed further or deliver the consignment, as the case may be, and shall, 
in case he is not a Magistrate, forthwith inform the nearest Magistrate.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Production and 
delivery of licence or import/export/transport.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The consignee of arms or ammunition imported/transported under a licence or his 
agent in the case of arms or ammunition exported under a licence shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  produce the licence, where the 
consignment in the course of import crosses the frontiers of India 
by land or river, within six days of such crossing, before the District 
Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area into which the consignment so 
crosses or before such other officer as the District Magistrate may appoint in 
that behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  deliver that licence within six 
days of the arrival of the consignment—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  at the destination, in the 
case of such consignment has been imported or transported to a place in India, 
or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in the area of which such 
consignment, being exported/transported across Indian territory for re-export, 
is to cross the frontier of India and before it so crosses,
 to 
the district
magistrate having jurisdiction 
over the area in which the destination or place of crossing as the case may be, 
is situated, or such other officer as the District Magistrate/State Government 
may appoint in that behalf.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every officer, to 
whom a licence is produced or delivered under sub-rule (1), shall satisfy 
himself that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the arms or ammunition 
correspond with the description given in the licence, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  any deficiency is properly 
accounted for.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the officer to 
whom a licence is delivered under sub-rule (1) is an officer other than the
district
magistrate, the licence shall be 
forwarded by such other officer to the 
district magistrate.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Import, transport and 
export of arms and ammunition for the Government of Nepal or the King of Nepal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where arms or ammunition are imported into India for despatch to the Government 
of Nepal or His Majesty the King of Nepal, the customs authorities at the port 
of disembarkation, or the licensing authority in other places, shall check the 
consignment against the list of arms or ammunition received from the Central 
Government; the package shall be sealed thereafter in the presence of a Customs 
Examiner or any other authority appointed for the purpose by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Where arms or 
ammunition imported into, or acquired in India are to be despatched to Nepal 
for the Government of Nepal, or His Majesty the King of Nepal, they shall be 
accompanied by a certificate from the Commissioner of Customs or the licensing 
authority of the area concerned to that effect; the certificate shall also 
contain a description of the marks on each package or case sufficient to enable 
it to be readily identified and a general statement of the contents of such 
package or case.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> On receipt of 
requisition from the clearing agents or the firm concerned, as the case may be, 
the district
magistrate shall arrange for 
necessary escort up to the railway station.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The railway 
authorities shall not receive for despatch any package or case containing arms 
or ammunition unless accompanied by a certificate as required under clause (a).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in any case—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the list referred to in 
sub-rule (1) is received from the Central Government, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the arms or ammunition 
imported into, or intended to be despatched from India do not correspond with 
the description given in such list, 
 
the authorities concerned shall not allow the consignment to be despatched to 
Nepal and shall forthwith inform the Central Government.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Transport of arms 
from any place in Nepal to any other place in Nepal through Indian territory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in rules 8 and 28, the Ambassador of India 
in Nepal, on application made by or on behalf of His Majesty the King of Nepal, 
of the Government of Nepal and subject to confirmation by the Central 
Government, may grant a licence in Form XXI for the import into, possession in, 
transport across, or export out of, India from any place in the territory of 
Nepal to any other place in that territory across the frontiers of India, of 
arms or ammunition of categories I and II or any other category, by His Majesty 
the King of Nepal, personal accompanying him, his brothers, the Prime Minister 
of Nepal and Nepal Government’s Troops or Police, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where under the 
authority of a licence granted under sub-rule (1), arms or ammunition are to 
pass across Indian 
territory—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if entirely by rail, a copy of 
the licence shall forthwith be sent by the Ambassador to the
district
magistrate having jurisdiction 
over the areas through which the arms or ammunition shall pass across the 
frontiers of India and also to the railway authorities of the place in Indian 
territory through which the consignment shall pass;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if by road or river, a copy of 
the licence shall forthwith be sent to the
district
magistrates having jurisdiction 
over the areas through which the arms or ammunition shall pass across the 
frontiers of India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government, or the Ambassador with the approval of the Central Government may 
make any order regulating the safe transit to Nepal 
across the frontiers of India of the arms or ammunition mentioned in this rule.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Transit licences for
bona fide travellers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a licence is granted in Form XXII, the licensing authority shall endorse 
the passport/visa of the tourist to that effect.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of every 
licence granted in Form XXII shall forthwith be sent to such officer of the 
Government of the State in which the place of his departure from India is 
situated as may be specially empowered in this behalf by the State Government 
or the Administrator or Lieutenant-Governor or Chief Commissioner of Union 
territory, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The licensee 
shall not, while in India, sell or transfer any arms or ammunition covered by 
his licence without prior permission of the licensing authority of the place 
where such sale or transfer is to be effected. He shall produce the arms or 
ammunition or the permission of the licensing authority, as the case may be, at 
the time of leaving India and return his licence to the passport checking 
authority, or other authority empowered by the
district
magistrate in this behalf, at 
the port or other place of departure from India;
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The passport checking 
authority or other authority to whom the licence is returned by the licensee, 
shall forward the same to the authority who issued it, with the remarks that 
the arms or ammunition have been duly exported, or sold or transferred with the 
permission of the authority concerned as required under clause (a).
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Licensee to keep in 
custody arms and ammunition.—The 
licensee in Form XIV shall not accept for custody arms or ammunition without 
satisfying himself that there is no mala fide intention on the part of 
the depositor or any person on whose behalf the deposit is being made. The 
dealer shall either inform the nearest police station and the
district
magistrate personally, or 
despatch information to the officer-in-charge of the police station and the
district
magistrate by registered post on 
the day of deposit or return or disposal, as the case may be, of such arms or 
ammunition.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Deposit of arms and 
ammunition under section 21.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a licensing authority decides to suspend or revoke a licence or to refuse 
to renew it he shall while communicating his decision in writing to the 
licensee, inform him that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  under section 21(1) he is 
required to deposit within such time as may be specified in the order 
suspending, revoking or refusing to renew the licence, the arms or ammunition 
covered by the licence, either with the officer-in-charge of the nearest police 
station or with a dealer holding a licence in Form XIV, or in case he is a 
member of the armed forces of the Union, in the unit armoury;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  subject to the proviso to 
section 21(2), during the period prescribed under sub-rule (4), he or, in the 
case of his death, his legal representative is entitled to sell or otherwise 
dispose of the arms or ammunition to any person lawfully entitled to possess 
the same and to receive the sale proceeds, if any; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  if the arms or ammunition have 
not been disposed of or their possession by the licensee or his legal 
representative, as the case may be, has not become lawful within the prescribed 
period they shall,     subject to the proviso to section 21(3), be forfeited to 
Government by order of the District Magistrate.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any arm or 
ammunition is deposited by an owner under section 21(1), in a police station or 
unit armoury, or with a dealer holding a licence in Form XIV, the 
officer-in-charge of police station or unit armoury or the licensed dealer, as 
the case may be, shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  attach to each article 
deposited, a card showing the following:—
 
              Deposit under section 21(1)—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  Description (No. etc.) of 
the article           .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  Particulars of licence of 
exemption (if any)  .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  Name and address of 
depositor                 .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  Serial No. in register and 
date of deposit     .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  Date due for 
forfeiture/disposal                 .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vi</number>  
....................................................      ..................

 
                  Signature of depositor.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vii</number>  
...................................................       ..................

 
                  Signature of dealer/or 
officer-in-charge       
of police station/unit armoury.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  issue to the depositor a receipt 
containing the same details as in (a); and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  immediately send a copy of the 
receipt of the authority who granted the licence or renewed it last.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number>(a)(i) Any arms or 
ammunition deposited in a unit armoury under section 21(1) may, unless returned 
or disposed of earlier, be transferred, after the expiry of a period of 30 days 
after such deposit to the nearest police station.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> any arms or 
ammunition deposited in a police station under section 21(1) which have not 
been returned or disposed of within 30 days of the deposit and the arms or 
ammunition transferred under clause (i) may be transferred for sake of better 
maintenance or safety to a police armoury in the district/taluqua 
headquarters or such other place as may be specified by the
district
magistrate, in accordance with 
such instructions as may be issued by the State Government for the purpose:
 
Provided that the
district
magistrate may, when he 
considers it desirable, extend the said period of 30 days.
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> Intimation of such 
transfer shall be given to the depositor of the article and to the licensing 
authority who granted or last renewed the licence for the article.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The period within 
which a depositor or his legal representative may exercise his rights under 
sub-section (2) of section 21 shall be—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  six months from the date of 
deposit, if the arms or ammunition are deposited as a consequence or 
contravention by its, owner of any provision of the Act or these rules or any 
condition of the licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  one year—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number> from the date of deposit, 
if the arms or ammunition are deposited as a consequence of its possess on 
becoming unlawful under section 21(1) otherwise than as under clause (a); or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  it is already in deposit, 
from the date of communication to the owner, of the order revoking, suspending, 
or refusing to renew the licence, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  from the date of 
notification issued under section 4:
 
          Provided that any period under 
clause (a) or (b) shall be reckoned—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  where an appeal is 
preferred by the owner under section 18 from the date of the final order of the 
appellate authority;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where the arms or 
ammunition is the subject of a legal suit or dispute or is owned or inherited 
by a person who has not completed the age of sixteen years—from the date of 
termination of the dispute or of completion by that person of the age of 
sixteen years; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  where the owner of the 
arms or ammunition is on active service outside India—from the date of his 
return to India: 
 

                1[Provided further 
that—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  when the arms and 
ammunition is owned by a person who is considered by the licensing authority to 
be unfit, for the time being to carry the arms or ammunition for any reason, or 
in any other suitable case, the District Magistrate or the Commissioner of 
Police, in relation to any metropolitan area, may extend the period prescribed 
under clause (a) or clause (b) for a period upto six months; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the State Government may 
by special or general order extend the period beyond six months:]
 

1[Provided further 
that when the arms or ammunition is owned by a person who is considered by the 
licensing authority to be unfit, for the time being, to carry the arms or 
ammunition for any reason, the period prescribed under clause (a) may be 
extended suitably by the District Magistrate, or the Commissioner of Police in 
relation to any metropolitan area.]
 

2[(c) 

3[two years] if 
the fire-arms are deposited as consequence of proviso to sub-section (2) of 
section 3.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> (a) Any arms or 
ammunition not returned or disposed of before the expiry of the period 
prescribed under sub-rule (4) shall be notified to the
district
magistrate; and subject to the 
provisos of sub-rule (4) and the proviso to the section 21(3) transferred to 
the district malkhana or such other places as required by order of the District 
Magistrate, for the purpose of forfeiture under section 21(3).
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The
district
magistrate shall, before making 
an order of forfeiture after the expiry of the prescribed period serve a notice 
as required under section 21(4) in the like manner as for service of summons 
under the code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)4:
 
Provided that, in the 
case of the depositor being a member of the armed forces of the Union, the 
notice shall served personally through the Commanding Officer of such member.

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Charges for 
maintaining in good condition articles deposited may be levied at such rates as 
may be fixed from time to time by the State Government. 
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Deposit of arms and 
ammunition for safe custody otherwise than under section 21.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> A person lawfully possessing arms or ammunition may deposit them for safe 
custody with a dealer holding a licence in Form XIV or in a police station or, 
if he is a member of the armed forces of Union, in a unit armoury.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Before accepting the 
arms or ammunition for deposit otherwise than under section 21(1), the dealer 
or officer-in-charge of police station or unit armoury shall satisfy himself 
that they are possessed under a valid licence issued under the Act and these 
rules or under exemption from the need for such licence.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Members of the armed 
forces of the
Union may be allowed to keep their arms or ammunition in safe custody in a unit 
armoury only during the tenure of their service.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the arms or 
ammunition have been deposited under sub-rule (1), the dealer or the 
officer-in-charge of the police station or unit armoury shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  attach to each article deposited 
a card, easily distinguishable from that described in rule 46(2)(a) showing the 
following—
 
              Deposit for safe custody:—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  Description (No. etc.) of 
article                 .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  Name and address of 
depositor                 .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  Particulars of licence/exemption                
.................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  Serial No. in register and 
date of deposit    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  Date of expiry of licence                          
.................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vi</number>  Date up to which 
deposited                      .................. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vii</number>  
..................................................
 
                  Signature of depositor
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>viii</number>  
..................................................
 
                  Signature of dealer or 
officer-in-charge       
of police station/unit armoury.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  issue to the depositor a receipt 
containing the particulars as in clause (a); and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  on the same day send a copy of 
the receipt to the authority who granted the licence or renewed it last.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) In the event of 
failure to get the licence renewed, the arms or ammunition shall continue to be 
possessed by the dealer on the authority of his licence in Form XIV or by the 
officer-in-charge of the police station or unit armoury; but, if the licence is 
not renewed for a period of 3 years after its expiry, the dealer or the 
officer-in-charge of the police station or unit armoury shall bring this to the 
notice of the district
magistrate for such action as he 
may consider necessary.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> the articles shall in 
no case be returned to the owner unless the licence to possess them is renewed 
or a new licence is obtained.
 

1[(4) The 
depositor may be charged a fee for the custody of the articles deposited at the 
following rates:—
 <subsubsection>
         <number>1</number>  For each fire-arm—Fifty rupees 
per year or portion thereof.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>2</number>  For every other weapon or 
package of ammunition—Rs. 25 per year or portion thereof.
 
Any extra charges for 
maintenance of the articles in good condition may be levied at such rates as 
may be fixed from time to time by the State Government.]
 
 




</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Records and returns 
of the articles deposited.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The dealer or the officer-in-charge of the police station or unit armoury shall 
maintain such registers as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the entries 
in the registers relating to the quarters ending on the last day of March, 
June, September and December each year, certified as true copy under the 
signature of the dealer or officer-in-charge of the police station or unit 
armoury, as the case may be, shall be forwarded to the
district
magistrate as early as possible 
after the expiry of each quarter.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensed dealer 
or the officer-in-charge of the police station or unit armoury or of any other 
place specified under rule 46(3)(a)(i) where the arms or ammunition are kept, 
shall submit to the district
magistrate by the 11th December 
each year a report showing the particulars of arms or ammunition in their 
custody which have, or will become liable to forfeiture by the end of that 
year.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Arms and ammunition deposited in a police-station or with a dealer and 
transferred to the district malkhana and the register maintained for the 
purpose shall be inspected periodically by the District Magistrate or other 
officer appointed by the State Government in this behalf in accordance with 
such procedure as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The arms or 
ammunition deposited in a unit armoury and the register maintained for this 
purpose shall be inspected periodically by the officer commanding the unit or 
any other officer empowered by him in accordance with the procedure prescribed 
by the Government of the State, where the unit is for the time being located.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Previous consent in 
certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence having effect beyond the local limits of the authority of the officer 
granting it shall not be granted for the transport or export or re-import of 
any arms or ammunition to a place, without ascertaining that there is no 
objection to the grant of such licence on the part of—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the
district
magistrate having jurisdiction 
over the area in which such place is situated; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the Government of the State of Jammu and Kashmir, 
if such place is in that State; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  the Secretary, General 
Administration Department, Government of Pondicherry, if such place is in any 
of the ex-French settlements in India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
sub-rule (1), either—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  a certificate of ‘no objection’ 
may be obtained by the applicant for the licence; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  an enquiry may be made by the 
authority to whom application for grant of such licence is made.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Application for 
licence.—Every 
application for the grant of a licence under these rules—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  shall be submitted in Form A;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  may be presented by the 
applicant in person or sent through the medium of post office or otherwise, to 
the licensing authority, as far as possible having jurisdiction in respect of 
the place where he ordinarily resides or has his occupation;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  shall contain all such 
information as is necessary for the consideration        of the application, 
and in particular—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  where the application is 
for the licence for the acquisition, possession and carrying of arms and 
ammunition for crop-protection, shall specify details of the land and 
cultivation requiring protection and area which the arms or ammunition are 
required to be carried;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where the application is 
for a licence for import by land or river or for export or for transport or for 
export, and re-import, or for import, transport and re-export of arms or 
ammunition, shall specify the place or destination, the route, the time likely 
to be occupied in the journey and the quantity, description and price of each 
kind of arms or ammunition in respect of which the licence is required and the 
purpose for which they are intended;
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>d</number>  where the grant of licence 
requires a certificate of no objection from some other authority as provided in 
rule 50, shall state whether such certificate has been obtained and, if so, 
shall be supported by evidence thereof;
 
 

1[(e)  where an application is for 
the grant of licence in Form II, Form III, Form IIIA, Form IV, Form V or Form 
VI from a person other than a bona fide tourist as defined in section 10 
(1) (b) of the Act it shall be accompanied by two passport size copies of the 
latest        photograph of the applicant:]
 
          Provided that—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  an application by a member 
of the armed forces of the Union shall be made through his Commanding Officer 
to the licensing authority having jurisdiction in respect of the place to which 
he is for the time being posted; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the licensing authority 
may, in accordance with any instructions issued by the State Government in 
respect of all or any class of fire-arms, require the personal attendance of 
the applicant before granting or renewing the licence applied for.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>51A</number> The 
applicant shall not suppress any factual information or furnish any false or 
wrong information in the application form.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Form of licence.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence in Form II, Form III, Form IIIA, Form IV, Form V or Form VI, if 
granted for more than a year, to a person other than bona fide tourist 
as defined in section 10(1)(b) of the Act, shall be in book-form and shall 
contain the latest photograph of the licensee.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a licence is 
granted in Form II, Form III, Form IIIA, Form IV, Form V or Form VI for the 
possession of arms to be acquired by the licensee subsequent to the grant of 
the licence, the authority granting the licence shall at the time of granting 
the same, direct that within a period specified by him in this behalf, which he 
may from time to time extend, the arms covered by the licence shall be acquired 
and that the licence or the arms or both shall be produced for his inspection 
and if within the period so specified or extended the licensee fails to acquire 
the arms and to produced the licence or the arms or both, as the case may be, 
the licence shall cease to be in force:
 
Provided that, if during 
the period so specified or extended, the licensee wishes to acquire and possess 
any weapon or weapons of a different description and the licensing authority 
has no objection to allow the acquisition and possession of such weapon or 
weapons, he may amend the licence accordingly:
 

2[Provided further 
that—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  where the licensing authority 
is the State Government, the licensee residing at any place within the State in 
which the license was issued may produce the licence or the arms or both for 
inspection, before the state 
Government or any authority which the State Government may, by a general or 
special order, specify in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  where the licensing authority 
is the State Government, the licensee may, if he changes his place of residence 
from one State to another State, produce the licence or arms or both for 
inspection before the Government of the second mentioned State or any authority 
which that Government may, by a general or special order, specify in        
this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  where the licensing authority 
is other than the State Government, the licensee may if he changes his place of 
residence, produce the licence or arms or both for inspection before the 
licensing authority of the place of his new residence to which the licensee may 
have shifted after the grant of licence,
 
within the period so specified, or extended and the authority other than the 
licensing authority who inspected the arms as well as the licensee shall 
intimate the fact of such inspection to the authority who issued the licence.]
  






</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Variation of 
conditions of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On application from a licence-holder, a licensing authority may extend the area 
of validity specified in his licence, if he is satisfied about the need of such 
extension, subject to the condition that the licensing authority has the power 
to grant a licence in relation to the area to which extension is sought.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
on application from a company 
holding a licence in Form II or Form III, for a change in the name of the 
member, agent or other representative of the company in whose name the licence 
has been granted or of a retainer included in the licence the necessary 
amendment may be made by the licensing authority.
</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Renewal of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence may, at its expiration and subject to the same condition (if any) 
as to the grant thereof, be renewed by the authority mentioned in Schedule II 
as renewing authority:
 

1[Provided that 
the licence so renewed may be signed in the appropriate column of the licence 
by such officer as may be specially empowered in this behalf by the State 
Government under rule 4.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The authority issuing 
a licence shall ordinarily be responsible for watching all future renewals of 
the licence. Where a licence is renewed by an authority other than the 
authority who granted it, the former shall forthwith inform the latter of the 
fact of renewal and the period for which such renewal is valid. The applicant 
for the renewal of a licence under this rule shall always be required to state 
his permanent residence, and, if he notifies a change in his permanent 
residence to the district in which the renewal is sought, the licensing 
authority of such district shall hence-forward become responsible for watching 
all future renewals of his licence and shall inform the original issuing 
authority accordingly. The procedure shall be repeated on each subsequent 
occasion of renewal of the licence, the necessary intimation being sent by the 
renewing authority to the original issuing authority or to the authority who 
last renewed the licence on a permanent change of residence, as the case may 
be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An application for 
renewal of a licence for arms or ammunition deposited under sub-rule (1) of 
rule 47 may be made by the depositor, or where it is not practicable to make 
the application direct, through the dealer or any other person authorised by 
him in this behalf while the arms or ammunition continue to be so deposited.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The licensing 
authority may consider an application for renewal of a licence, if the period 
between the date of its expiry and the date of application is not, in his 
opinion, unduly long with due regard to the circumstances of the case, and all 
renewal fee for the intervening period are paid; otherwise the application may 
be treated as one for grant of a fresh licence.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> 

1[Appeal against 
the order of a licensing authority or an authority suspending or revoking a 
licence under section 17(6)].—In 
any case in which an authority issues an order—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  refusing to grant or renew a 
licence or to give an objection certificate for such grant or renewal, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  varying any condition of a 
licence or suspending or revoking a licence under sub-section (1), or 
sub-section (3), or sub-section (6) of section 17, the person aggrieved by such 
order may, within thirty days from the date of issue of the order, and subject 
to the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 18, prefer an appeal against that 
order to the concerned appellate authority.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Procedure to be 
followed by the appellate authority.—On 
receipt of an appeal the appellate authority may call for the records of the 
case from the authority who passed the order appealed against and after giving 
the appellant a reasonable opportunity of being heard, pass final orders.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Fee payable for 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[(a) Every 
licence granted or renewed under these rules shall, save as herein otherwise 
expressly provided, be chargeable with the fee (if any) specified in Schedule 
IV.]
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In any case where fee 
is prescribed for a year, free for a fraction of a year shall be the same as 
for a whole year.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a licensee 
submits his application for renewal of his licence after the expiry of the 
period for which the licence was granted, the licensing authority may, if he 
decides to renew the licence, at his discretion levy—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  full fee as for initial grant of 
the licence, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he is satisfied that the 
delay is not justifiable, or excusable, nor serious enough to warrant 
revocation of the licence or prosecution of the licensee, a late fee not 
exceeding the amount of the licence fee is charged, or 

1[Rs. 100] in other cases.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government may, by general or special order and for reasons to be recorded in 
writing and subject to such conditions, if any, as it may specify in the order, 
grant exemption from, or reduction of, the fee payable in respect of any 
licence:
 
Provided that it shall be 
a condition of every exemption from payment of the fee chargeable in respect of 
the grant or renewal of any licence, in Form III that if application for 
renewal of such licence is not made within one month of the date on which the 
licence expires, the licensing authority may, unless the applicant satisfies 
the licensing authority that he had sufficient cause for not making the 
application within that period, levy renewal fee at the rate specified in the 
Form.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No separate fee shall 
be chargeable from retainers.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No fee shall be 
chargeable in respect of the grant or renewal of a licence in Form XV by a 
State Government or the Board of Revenue (in the State of Andhra Pradesh, 
Kerala or 

2[Tamil Nadu]) for 
the import of sulphur in reasonable quantities, if the State Government or the 
Board of Revenue is satisfied that the sulphur is required in good faith for 
medicinal, industrial or agricultural purposes (other than for manufacturing 
arms, ammunition or explosives).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any political 
representative authorised to grant licences in Form XVIII may remit the fee 
payable in respect of the grant or renewal of any such licence in the case of 
arms or ammunition exported for personal use, or in the case of ammunition 
exported for use for blasting purposes (whether on a public work or not) of the 
Government of any territory or place outside India.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> (i) No fee shall be 
chargeable for the grant of a licence for export and re-import of any arms or 
ammunition in a case or package legibly addressed to a person lawfully entitled 
to possess such articles, in compliance with a requisition made by a such 
person for the supply of such articles in reasonable quantities for his own use 
or after carrying out necessary repairs thereto.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Where any arms or 
ammunition are imported under a licence into any customs port in India and 
re-exported thence for re-import into any other customs port in India under 
rule 35 the necessary licence for such re-export and re-import under the said 
rule shall be chargeable with a fee of rupee one only.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> No fee shall be 
chargeable in respect of—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  a change of description of the 
weapon entered in a licence granted for its acquisition under proviso to rule 
52 (2) but if the licence fee in respect of the weapon so changed is higher 
than that for the original      weapon, the difference of such fee may be 
charged;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  an endorsement under rule 12 
of a licence granted in the State of Pondicherry or endorsement to extend or 
change the area of validity of a licence under sub-rule (1) of rule 53;    

 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  a change of name, under rule 
53 (2), of member, agent or other representative of the company or retainer; or

 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  a grant of consent or 
permit/certificate or endorsement or any other document under these rules, 
except as otherwise expressly provided.





</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Fee payable for 
copies and duplicates.—Where 
a licence granted or renewed under these rules in lost or accidentally 
destroyed, the authority empowered to grant such licence may grant a duplicate—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  where the original licence was 
granted without the payment of any fee, on payment of a fee of 

1[Rs. 50]; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in any other case on payment of 
a fee of 

1[Rs. 100] or the fee with which the 
original licence was chargeable; whichever is less.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Fee payable on a 
petition for appeal made under section 18
<section><number>1</number>.—Every 
petition for appeal under section 18 (1) shall be accompanied by a fee of—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  

1[Rs. 100], if the fee for the 
licence in relation to which the appeal is preferred is 

1[Rs. 50] or more; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  

1[Rs. 50] in any other case.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Collection of fees.—All 
fees payable shall be paid in cash either in person or, at the option of the 
person concerned, by a money order/postal order, at the time of application.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Dealers to maintain 
registers, etc. in certain cases.—Where 
no licence is required for the manufacture, sale, import, export or transport 
of any category or description of arms or ammunition by or through a dealer, 
the dealer may be asked to register his name and address and place of business 
in such manner and at such place as the Central Government may prescribe and 
the dealer shall maintain such register and furnish such information to the 
Central Government as it may require in respect of the arms or ammunition so 
manufactured, sold, imported, exported, or transported.
</article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Production of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  holds a licence granted or 
renewed or pass, permit or certificate granted under these rules, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  is acting under colour of such 
licence, pass, permit or certificate, shall forthwith produce such licence, 
pass, permit or certificate upon demand by any
magistrate or any police officer 
of a rank not below that of an officer-in-charge of a police station.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> While granting or 
renewing a licence, no authority shall impose a condition inconsistent with 
sub-rule (1).
 

1[(3) If a person 
who holds a licence in Form II changes his place of residence, permanently or 
temporarily for more than thirty consecutive days, and carries with him the 
weapon concerned by the licence, to a place other than indicated in column 2 of 
the licence, he shall 

2[within thirty 
days of such change], send intimation about such change to the licensing 
authority of the place or his new residence as well as to the authority which 
granted the licence or last renewed it, as the case may be, and shall on demand 
forthwith produce the licence and the weapon to the first mentioned authority 
for making necessary entry in the licence to indicate these in the particulars 
of the new residence of the licensee.]
 

3[(4) The licensee 
shall intimate within a period of thirty days in regard to change of residence 
to the licensing authority of the new place of his residence and produce his 
licence before the licensing authority of the new place for appropriate 
endorsement. On such change of residence and after such endorsement on the 
licence, the said licence shall be deemed to have been transferred to the 
jurisdiction of the licensing authority and renewing authority of the new place 
of residence and such authority shall be the licensing authority and the 
renewing authority in relation to the said licence for purposes of provisions 
of the Arms Act, 1959 and the Arms Rules, 1962.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Production of arms.—The 
authority by whom any licence in Form II, Form III, Form IV, Form V or Form VI 
has been granted or renewed may, for the purposes of satisfying itself that any 
arm covered by such licence are still in the possession of the licensee, at any 
time while the licence is in force by order in writing, require the licensee—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to produce the arms at such time 
and place for inspection of such officer as may be specified in the order; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  at the option of the licensee to 
produce a certificate from—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  a
magistrate or the 
officer-in-charge of the nearest police station in whose jurisdiction the 
licensee resides or has his occupation, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  if he is a Government 
servant, a gazetted officer to whom he is subordinate,
 to 
the effect that he has seen the arms in the possession of the licensee and that 
they correspond to the description given in the licence.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE ARMS RULES, 1962
 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Indian Arms Rules, 1951, are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken (including any exemption, exclusion 
or withdrawal made, fee imposed, levied, remitted or reduced or power 
conferred) or deemed to have been done or taken under the said rules, shall, so 
far as it is consistent with these rules, be deemed to have been done or taken 
under the corresponding provisions of these rules.
 
 
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>