<act><title>


The Central Wakf Council Rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Central Wakf Council Rules, 1998. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” 
    means the Wakf Act, 1995 (43 of 1995);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Council;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “Council” means the Central Wakf Council established under section 9 of the 
    Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Fund” 
    means the Central Wakf Fund formed under sub-section (2) of section 10 of 
    the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “Member” 
    means a member of the Council;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   
    “Secretary” means the Secretary of the Council.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Register of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council 
    shall maintain a roll of members indicating their name, occupation and 
    address and every member shall sign the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The member of the Council shall intimate 
    the change of his address, if any, to the Secretary of the Council who shall 
    cause to make the entry in the roll of members.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Term of office, resignation and removal 
    of members.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in these rules, every member 
    shall hold office for a term of five years from the date on which he assumed 
    such office and shall be eligible for re appointment.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member may resign his office by writing 
    under his hand addressed to the Central Government and such resignation 
    shall take effect from the date on which it is accepted by the Central 
    Government or on the expiry of thirty days from the date of resignation, 
    whichever is earlier.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government may remove a member 
    from the Council if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   becomes 
    an undischarged insolvent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   is, in 
    the opinion of the Central Government, unfit to continue in office by reason 
    of infirmity of mind or body;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   gets 
    convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which in the opinion 
    of the Central Government involves moral turpitude;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   is 
    without obtaining leave of absence from the Chairperson of the Council, 
    absent from three consecutive meetings of the Council;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   in the 
    opinion of the Central Government, has so abused the position of member as 
    to render that person’s continuance in the office detrimental to the 
    purposes of the Act.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Filling of casual vacancies.—In the 
    event of occurrence of any vacancy in the office of a member by reason of 
    his death, resignation, removal or otherwise, the Central Government may 
    appoint another person in his place and the person appointed to fill the 
    vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the 
    member in whose place he was so appointed.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Committees of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Council may appoint, from amongst its members, such number of Committees as 
    the Council deems necessary but not exceeding four, and assign to them such 
    functions, duties and powers as it may consider necessary for the purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The members of the Committee shall hold 
    office for such period as may be specified by the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A member shall cease to be a member of a 
    Committee if he ceases to be a member of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Committee of the Council may meet 
    frequently depending upon the exigencies of work.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The recommendations or decisions of the 
    Committee shall be placed before the Council for its approval:  
 
Provided that when the Council is not holding 
    its meetings the recommendations or decisions shall be placed before the 
    Chairperson by the Secretary of the Council and the Chairperson shall inform 
    the Council of the recommendations or decisions taken in view thereof to the 
    Council as soon as the Council meets:  
 
Provided further that if the Committee is 
    unable to meet for reasons beyond its control, the Secretary of the Council 
    may submit the matter falling within purview of such Committee directly to 
    the Chairperson for directions:  
 
Provided also that all decisions taken by the 
    Chairperson either on the recommendations of a Committee or otherwise shall 
    be ratified forthwith by the Council.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Secretary to the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
    shall be a Secretary to the Council, who shall be a Muslim, appointed by the 
    Chairperson on such terms and conditions as may be fixed by the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Secretary shall be the Chief Executive 
    Officer of the Council and shall exercise powers of control, supervision and 
    management over the office and staff of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Secretary shall give effect to the 
    decisions of, and carry out the instructions that may, from time to time, be 
    given by the Council or the Chairperson:  
 
Provided that when Council is in the process 
    of reconstitution or unable to meet for reasons beyond its control, the 
    Secretary may seek the orders or approval of the Chairperson on an urgent 
    matter:  
 
Provided further that all such orders or 
    approval of the Chairperson shall be placed before the Council for its 
    decision, as soon as the Council meets.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Secretary shall ensure that all the 
    records of the Council are properly maintained and kept in safe custody.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Secretary shall be responsible for the 
    presentation of the annual statement of accounts of the Council duly 
    authenticated in the proper form to the auditor appointed by the Central 
    Government for this purpose.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meeting of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
    shall ordinarily be two meetings of the Council every year which may be 
    increased to five, if necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An extraordinary meeting of the Council 
    may be convened by the Secretary, if the Chairperson so desires, or if a 
    requisition in that behalf is presented to the Chairperson by at least one 
    third members of the Council and such requisition shall set out matters for 
    consideration in the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The date and venue of the meeting shall be 
    such as may be decided by the Chairperson.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An ordinary meeting of the Council may be 
    called by giving not less than one month’s notice in writing and an 
    extraordinary meeting by giving not less than one week’s notice in writing:  
 
Provided that an extraordinary meeting may be 
    called by giving shorter notice if the urgency of the business to be 
    transacted, so requires.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Procedure at meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> An agenda 
    for every meeting of the Council shall be prepared by the Secretary with the 
    approval of the Chairperson and shall be circulated to the members.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The quorum necessary for the transaction 
    of business at a meeting of the Council shall be one-third of the total 
    number of members.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a meeting has been adjourned for 
    lack of quorum, the business which would have been brought before the 
    original meeting if there had been quorum present thereat, shall be brought 
    before, and may be transacted at an adjourned meeting whether there is 
    quorum present or not.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson or in his absence such 
    other member present as is decided by the Council shall preside at every 
    meeting of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All matters brought before any meeting of 
    the Council shall be decided by the majority of the votes of the members 
    present and voting.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chairperson or the person presiding 
    over a meeting shall have and exercise a second or a casting vote in all 
    cases of equality of votes.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> It shall be open to any member to raise 
    any matter not included in the agenda with permission of the Chairperson.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The minutes of the meeting shall be 
    recorded by the Secretary and circulated to the members, as early as 
    possible, after approval by the Chairperson.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> At the next meeting of the Council, the 
    approved minutes of the previous meeting shall be read and confirmed.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Invitees to the Council meeting.—The 
    Chairperson of the Council may invite any person or persons to attend any 
    meeting of the Council but such persons shall have no right to vote.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Travelling and daily allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every member, not being an officer of the Government, performing journeys to 
    attend meeting of the Council or in connection with any work relating to the 
    Council shall be entitled to travel, at his discretion, by air or by rail in 
    first class or in second class AC coach wherever available.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such member shall be entitled to the 
    following travelling and daily allowances, namely:—  
 
Travelling Allowance:  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   By Air  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   One standard air fare;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   Incidental expenses subject to a 
    maximum of rupees fifty.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   By Rail  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   First Class/II A.C. Coach rail fare, as 
    the case may be;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   Incidental expenses subject to a 
    maximum of rupees fifty.  
 
 Note:—In case of air journeys 
    involving overnight halt (either due to non- availability of connective 
    service or due to the cancellation of connective service) at intermediary 
    stations, for which the Airlines does not provide, at its expense, any 
    facility for boarding or lodging to the touring member, he shall be entitled 
    in respect of such overnight halt, one-half of the daily allowance 
    admissible to him in addition to the incidental expenses.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>II</number>   While 
    performing journeys by air, he shall purchase return ticket, wherever it is 
    available, when it is expected that the return journey can be performed 
    before the expiry of the period for which the return ticket is available.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>III</number>   In 
    respect of journeys by road from residence to the air booking office or 
    railway station and from these points to the place where a meeting of the 
    Council is being held, he shall also be entitled to a road mileage at rupees 
    eight per kilometre.  
 
Daily Allowance:  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>   For each 
    day of the meeting, he shall be entitled to a daily allowance of rupees five 
    hundred per day.  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>   In 
    addition to the daily allowance for the days of the meeting, he shall be 
    entitled to full day allowance for the day preceding and the day following 
    the day of the meeting if—  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   he arrives in the forenoon of the day 
    immediately preceding the day of the meeting or on an earlier day;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   he departs in the afternoon of the day 
    following the day of the meeting or on a later day:  
 
Provided that 
    he shall be entitled to only one-half of the daily allowance for the day 
    preceding the day of the meeting and the day following the day of the 
    meeting if—  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   he arrives in the afternoon of the day 
    preceding the day of the meeting; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   he departs in the forenoon of the day 
    following the day of the meeting.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> When a person attends any meeting of the 
    Council or its Committee as an invitee, he may be paid travelling allowance 
    and daily allowance at the rates admissible to a member of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A claim of the member travelling by his 
    own transport shall be restricted to rail fare by II Class AC coach by the 
    shortest route.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-rules (1), (2) and (3), if a member of the Council, is a Member of 
    Parliament, or a State Legislature, he shall not be entitled to any 
    remuneration other than the allowances, defined in clause (a) of Section 2 
    of the Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959 (10 of 1959), 
    or, as the case may be, other than the allowances, if any, which a member of 
    the Legislature of the State may, under any law for the time being in force 
    in the State relating to the prevention of disqualification for Membership 
    of the State Legislature, receive without incurring such disqualification.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Travelling and daily allowances to 
    members who are officers of Government.—
<section><number>1</number> Every member, being an 
    officer of the Government, shall be entitled to such travelling allowance 
    and daily allowance as are admissible under the rules applicable to him for 
    journeys performed on official duty.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any travelling or daily allowance is 
    paid to a member being an officer of the Government, the Council shall make 
    necessary arrangements for the reimbursement of the amount so paid to the 
    authority employing such officer.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Staff of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Council shall, from time to time, and on the recommendation of the 
    Secretary, create such posts as are necessary for the efficient performance 
    of the functions of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) the Chairperson shall make 
    appointments to the posts in the category of Upper Division Clerk or its 
    equivalent and above.  
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The Secretary shall make appointments to 
    the posts in the category of Lower Division Clerk or its equivalent and 
    below.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> The appointing authority of the 
    employees of the Council shall be the disciplinary authority and shall be 
    competent to impose all kinds of punishments including dismissal as per the 
    Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965, as 
    amended from time to time.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> In case of disciplinary proceedings 
    against the employees of the Council, where the disciplinary authority is 
    the Chairperson, the Council shall be the appellate authority and where the 
    disciplinary authority is the Secretary, the Chairperson shall be the 
    appellate authority.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Except as otherwise provided by the 
    Council, with the prior concurrence of the Central Government, the scale of 
    pay, leave, conduct rules, and other terms and conditions of service for the 
    various categories of posts shall be the same as may for the time being in 
    force be applicable to the officers and servants, holding posts of 
    corresponding scale of pay under the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Control of the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Secretary shall receive all payments to the fund and pass receipts on behalf 
    of the Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All monies received by the Council shall 
    be deposited in the name and with the approval of the Council in the State 
    Bank of India or any other nationalised bank as per instructions and 
    guidelines of the Ministry of Finance issued in this regard from time to 
    time:  
 
Provided that for the purpose of disbursement 
    of salary to the staff of the Council, an account of the Council shall also 
    be opened in a branch of a nationalised bank in the vicinity of the 
    Council’s office.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Power to sanction expenditure by 
    Chairperson and Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions made in the 
    budget in this regard—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   The 
    Chairperson may sanction a recurring expenditure up Rs 10,000 (Rupees ten 
    thousand only) and a non-recurring expenditure of Rs. 50,000 (Rupees fifty 
    thousand only) on an item per annum.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   The 
    secretary may sanction a recurring expenditure up to Rs 4000 (Four thousand 
    rupees only) and a non-recurring expenditure up to Rs. 8000 (Eight thousand 
    rupees only) on an item per annum.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Secretary or in his absence an officer 
    subordinate to him, if so authorised, may draw cheques for the sanctioned 
    expenditure.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officer, so authorised by the 
    Secretary, may supervise the maintenance of all registers in the Council’s 
    office and certify the entries made therein.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Annual Statement of Accounts.—The 
    Council shall maintain accounts and other records and cause its books of 
    accounts to be balanced on the last working day of the month of March in 
    each financial year and the annual statement of accounts shall be as set out 
    in the Form appended to these rules.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Powers of the Secretary in respect of 
    staff and contingent expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> The Secretary shall, in respect of 
    all the staff of the Council under his control and supervision, have the 
    power to sanction,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    Increment;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Leave;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   
    Allowances and advances as admissible to the Government employees.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Secretary shall have the power to 
    sanction,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    expenditure up to Rs. 2000 (two thousand rupees only) for repairs of 
    furniture, typewriter, bicycle, clock, water-cooler, electric heater, which 
    are on the stock register of the Council office and an expenditure up to Rs 
    500 (five hundred rupees only) if any of the aforesaid article needs 
    servicing;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    expenditure up to Rs 2000 (two thousand rupees only) for arranging, 
    entertainment such as dinner, lunch or at home for members and invitees of 
    the Council or its Committees.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Additional qualifications for 
    appointment to a post in the Council.—In addition to the qualifications 
    required of a person under the rules for the time being in force in the 
    Central Government for appointment to the posts sanctioned for the Council, 
    under rule 13, a candidate shall preferably have a working knowledge of 
    Urdu. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Exemption from recruitment through 
    Employment Exchange.—Where persons having the requisite qualifications 
    are not available through Employment Exchanges for appointment to the posts 
    in the Council, then direct recruitment of the staff of the Council from 
    outside may be made.  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>