<act><title>


The Personal Injuries (Compensation Insurance) Rules, 19721</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
extent.—These 
rules may be called the Person­al Injuries (Compensation Insurance) Rules, 1972.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless context otherwise re­quires,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  “Act “ means 
the Personal Injuries (Compensation In­surance) Act, 1963 (37 of 1963);
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  “Scheme” 
means the Personal Injuries (Compensation Insurance) Scheme, 1972;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  “Form” means 
a Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  “quarter” 
means a period of three months, commencing on the first day of April, July, 
October or January.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Ascertainment of 
wages bill.—The 
wages bill of an employer shall be computed by aggregating the gross cash wages 
including overtime wages and allowances of all workmen employed by him but shall 
exclude all that part of gross cash wages and allowances of individual employees 
which exceed five hundred rupees per month and bonus paid on profits.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Form of policy.—Every 
policy of insurance referred to in sub-section (2) of section 8 of the Act shall 
be in Form X.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Quarterly advance 
payment.—The 
period for the purpose of clause (h) of sub-section (5) of section 8 of the Act 
shall be a quarter.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Date by which policy 
is to be taken.—An 
application for taking out a policy of insurance shall be made—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  if the 
employer had been 
1[an] employer for 
the com­plete quarter ending the 31st December, 1971, then on or after the 10th 
June, 1972, and not later than the 

2[31st December], 
1972.
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  in all other 
cases, within one month of the employer’s having become an employer for one 
complete quarter.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Form and manner of 
accounts.—An 
account of all sums received into and paid out of the Fund shall be prepared in 
Form Y and shall be published annually in the Official Gazette.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Period of appeal.—An 
appeal under sub-section (3) of section 15 of the Act shall be made within 
ninety days of the determina­tion made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of that section.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Recovery.—The 
Claims Officer may, on default by an employer, recover an arrear of land revenue 
any amount payable by the employer and for this purpose the Claims Officer shall 
be deemed to be a public officer within the meaning of section 5 of the Revenue 
Recovery Act, 1890 (1 of 1890).
 



</article><form>
 




The Personal Injuries (Compensation Insurance) Rules, 1972
 





 




FORM X
 


(See
rule 4)
 



POLICY OF INSURANCE AGAINST LIABILITIES INSURANCE UNDER THE PERSONAL INJURIES 
(COMPENSATION INSURANCE) ACT, 1963
 


Policy No................
 


This policy and the 
specification hereto (which forms an integral part of this Policy) shall be read 
together as one contract and the words and expressions to which specific 
meanings have been attached in the Specification shall bear those meanings 
wherever they may appear.
 



The Specification
 


The 
President                                                                 The 
President of India
 


The Government 
Agent                                                   
..............................................
 


The Insured 
Name                                                          
..............................................
 


Business 
Address                                                           
..............................................
 


Trade or 
business                                                           
..............................................
 


Name and address of all 
premises                                  
..............................................
 


or establishment where 
employees                                
.............................................
 


covered by the Act normally 
work                                   
..............................................
 


Date of commencement of 
Insurance                             
..............................................
 


Advance against premium Rs. 
................................... paid into the.............. Treasury/Reserve 
Bank of India/State Bank of India at.................................on 
the.....................day of...........................................
 


Whereas the Insured has 
made and forwarded to the Government Agent a signed application for insurance, 
which application the Insured has agreed shall be the basis of this Policy and 
has paid the advance premium named above, and
 


Whereas the Insured has 
agreed that all the declarations, which he may be making from time to time 
hereafter, in relation to this policy shall also be the basis of this policy.
 


Now, this policy witnesseth 
that in consideration of the premises and on condition that there shall be duly 
paid to the President subsequent instalments of advance premium as the insured 
may be required to pay in terms of Notification made under sub-clause (2) of 
clause 8 of the Personal Injuries (Compensation Insurance) Scheme, 1972, and on 
condition that after the period of the present emergency there shall be paid to 
the President within such time and in lump sum or in such instalments as may be 
noti­fied, the final adjustment of premium as may be required in terms of 
Notification under the Personal Injuries (Compensation In­surance) Act, 1963. 
The President agrees (subject to the provisions contained in the Personal 
Injuries Compensation Insurance) Act, 1963, and the scheme and rules made 
thereunder in respect of the present emer­gency which provisions shall so far as 
the nature of them respec­tively will permit be deemed to be conditions 
precedent to the right of the Insured to recover hereunder that if during the 
present emergency any employee to whom the said Act applies shall sustain any 
personal injury for which the Insured is liable to pay compensation under the 
said Act, then the President will indemnify the Insured against all sums for 
which the Insured shall be so liable.
 


And it is hereby declared 
that the policy shall be subject to the conditions and privileges printed on the 
back hereof.
 


In witness whereof, I being 
duly authorised in that behalf have hereto set my hand for and on behalf of the 
President.
 


Signed for and on behalf of 
the 
 


President, the.........day 
of............
 



Conditions
 


1. Every notice or 
communication to be given or made under this policy shall be delivered in 
writing to the Government Agent.
 


2. The observance and 
fulfilment of the terms and conditions of this policy so far as they relate to 
anything to be done or not to be done by the insured and the truth of the 
statements and answers in the Application Form and in all the declaration in 
relation to the policy shall be conditions precedent to any lia­bility of the 
President to make any payment under this policy.
 


3. On the happening of any 
occurrence which may give rise to a claim for payment of compensation under the 
Act, the insured shall forthwith furnish details of the occurrence including the 
name of any worker injured or killed, as the case may be, and the name of such 
workers’ father to the Government Agent.
 


4. If the claim be in any 
respect fraudulent or if any fraudulent means or devices be used by the Insured 
or anyone acting on his behalf to obtain any benefit under this policy, or if 
any injury is suffered by any employee of the Insured by the wilful act of or 
with the connivance of the Insured, all benefits under the policy shall be 
forfeited:
 


Provided that the benefits 
under the policy shall not be forfeit­ed even though the injury to an employee 
is sustained in the course of the willful act and with the connivance of the 
Insured when the wilful act is done under orders of proper authority, or where 
the Insured permits certain measures to be taken under orders or proper 
authority, and if any question arises as to whether any act of the kind 
mentioned above has been taken under proper authority, the Central Government 
shall decide the matter and such decision shall be final and fully binding on 
the In­sured.
 


5. No refund of premium 
shall be allowed in respect of the policy except as provided by or under the 
Personal Injuries (Compensa­tion Insurance) Act, 1963 (37 of 1963).
 


6. In the event of a 
transfer of interest, this policy may be assigned but such assignment shall not 
take effect until notice of assignment has been given to the President.
 


7. The Insured shall at all 
times take due precautions for the safety of his employees. If the Insured shall 
fail to comply with any regulations or instructions made or issued under the 
authori­ty of the Central Government for the safety of his employees, all 
benefits under the policy shall be forfeited.
 


8. If in his application 
for the insurance effected by the poli­cy, and in subsequent declarations, the 
Insured shall have inten­tionally made a material mis-statement as to the number 
of his employees and their wages and allowances all benefits under the policy 
shall be forfeited.
 


9. The name of every 
employee together with the amount of wages, salary and other earnings shall be 
properly recorded and the Insured shall at all times allow an authorized 
representative of the President or of the Government Agent to inspect such 
records.
 


10. If at any time before 
the date of expiry of the present emergency the employer ceases to be an 
employer to whom the Act applies he shall not be required to pay any instalments 
of ad­vance premiums that may be notified thereafter but a final adjust­ment 
premium as on the date on which he ceases to be employer shall be payable in 
such manner and on such date (being not earlier than two months from that date) 
as may be required by the President and the policy shall cease to have effect in 
respect of any personal injury sustained by any employee of the employer after 
the date on which he ceases to be an employer to whom the Act applies:
 


Provided that if the 
employer so applies within a month of that date and if the President agrees, the 
policy may be transferred in the name of such other person (being an employer to 
whom the provisions of the Act apply) under whom the majority of the employees 
of the insured have been transferred. If such transfer is agreed to, the 
provisions of condition 6 will apply.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>