<act><tid>1773547</tid>
<title>THE RAMPUR RAZA LIBRARY ACT, <year>1975</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1975</year>
[ 9th May, <year>1975</year>.]

An Act to declare the Rampur Raza Library to be an institution of 
national importance and to provide for its administration and matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>171375</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>65082</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Rampur Raza Library Act, <year>1975</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1776928</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1764316</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of Rampur Raza Library as an institution of 
national importance. It is hereby declared that the Rampur Raza 
Library, at Rampur, is an institution of national importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1410301</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>923953</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Board established under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1609966</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>293002</tid>
<number>c</number>" deed of trust" means the deed of trust executed by the 
late Nawab Sir Syed Raza Ali Khan Bahadur of Rampur, on 
the 6th August, <year>1951</year>, and registered as No. 103, Book 
IV, Volume No. 8, on pages 74 to 93 of the Office of 
the officiating Chief Sub- Registrar, Rampur;

</section>

<section><tid>847768</tid>
<number>d</number>" Fund" means the Fund referred to in section 19;

</section>

<section><tid>1420353</tid>
<number>e</number>" library" means the Rampur Raza Library, which is 
declared by this Act to be an institution of national 
importance;

</section>

<section><tid>463402</tid>
<number>f</number>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the 
Chairman, and also includes the Vice- Chairman, if any;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>300</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 7- <year>1975</year>, vide Notification No. G. S. R. 354 (E), dt. 26- 6- <year>1975</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1403533</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1502512</tid>
<number>h</number>" Rampur" means the headquarters of the District of 
Rampur in the State of Uttar Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>52875</tid>
<number>i</number>" State Government" means the Government of the State of 
Uttar Pradesh.
CHAP

RAMPUR RAZA LIBRARY BOARD

CHAPTER II

RAMPUR RAZA LIBRARY BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1986857</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and incorporation of Board.
<section><tid>1789835</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from  
such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established, for the 
purposes of this Act, a Board, to be known as the" Rampur Raza Library 
Board".

</section>

<section><tid>1379815</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
and to contract, and may, by that name, sue and be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1382897</tid>
<number> 5</number> Composition of Board.
<section><tid>1552010</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall consist of the  
following persons, namely:-

<subsection><tid>793691</tid>
<number>a</number>the Governor of the State of Uttar Pradesh, ex officio, 
who shall be the Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>507609</tid>
<number>b</number>Shri Syed Murtaza Ali Khan, for life, who shall be the 
Vice- Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>266283</tid>
<number>c</number>Colonel Bashir Hussain Zaidi, for life;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1702793</tid>
<number>d</number>the Accountant- General, Uttar Pradesh, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>417686</tid>
<number>e</number>a descendant of the late Nawab Sir Syed Raza Ali Khan 
Bahadur of Rampur, to be nominated by the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>409949</tid>
<number>f</number>four persons to be nominated by the Central 
Government, out of whom-

<subsubsection><tid>341638</tid>
<number>i</number>two shall be persons who, in the opinion 
of the Central Government, have expert knowledge 
with regard to the collections in the library or 
are distinguished historians or scholars of 
Arabic, Persian or Urdu,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>301</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> 1- 7- <year>1975</year>: Vide Notify No. g. s. R. 355 (E), dt. 26- 6- 75.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>149276</tid>
<number>ii</number>one shall be an officer, not below the 
rank of a Deputy Secretary to the Government of 
India in the Department dealing with matters 
connected with the library,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1938269</tid>
<number>iii</number>one shall be a person who, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, has expert 
knowledge of, and experience in, management of 
public libraries;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1032469</tid>
<number>g</number>the Collector and District Magistrate, Rampur, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1103507</tid>
<number>h</number>three other persons, of whom at least two shall be 
scholars of repute, to be nominated by the State 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>456213</tid>
<number>i</number>the Director of the Library, ex officio, who shall be 
the Member- Secretary.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>805085</tid>
<number>2</number>Every nomination made under this section shall be notified by 
the Central Government in the Official Gazette and every nomination so 
notified shall take effect from the date of the notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>467007</tid>
<number> 6</number> Term of office and fresh nomination in certain cases.
<section><tid>383826</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
term of office of nominated members shall be such as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1754741</tid>
<number>2</number>Any nominated member may resign his office by giving notice 
in writing to the Government nominating him, and on such resignation 
being notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette, he 
shall be deemed to have vacated his office on the date of publication 
of such notification.

</section>

<section><tid>282999</tid>
<number>3</number>If the office of any nominated member is vacated before the 
expiry of the term of his office, the resulting vacancy may be filled 
by fresh nomination by the Government by which such member was 
nominated, and the member so nominated shall hold office for the 
remainder of the term of office of the member in whose place he is 
nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>1760689</tid>
<number>4</number>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re- nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>14532</tid>
<number>5</number>If any nominated member is, by infirmity or otherwise, 
rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent 
on leave or otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of 
his office, the Central Government or the State Government, as the 
case may be, may nominate another person to act in his place during 
his absence.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>302</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1465101</tid>
<number> 7</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts. No act of the Board 
shall be invalid merely by reason of-
<section><tid>711724</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the 
Board, or

</section>

<section><tid>1000924</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a 
member thereof, or

</section>

<section><tid>964954</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1358070</tid>
<number> 8</number> Duty of Government nominating persons.
<section><tid>857626</tid>
<number>1</number>Before nominating a  
person to be a member of the Board, the Central Government or the 
State Government, as the case may be, shall satisfy itself that the 
person will have no such financial or other interest as is likely to 
affect prejudicially the exercise or performance by him of his 
functions as a member, and the Central Government or the State 
Government, as the case may be, shall also satisfy itself from time to 
time with respect to every member nominated by it that he has no such 
interest; and any person who is or whom the Central Government or the 
State Government, as the case may be, proposes to nominate and who has 
consented to be a member shall, whenever requested by the Central 
Government or the State Government so to do, furnish to it such 
information with regard to his financial or other interest in the 
library as that Government considers necessary for the performance by 
it of its duties under this sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>842329</tid>
<number>2</number>A nominated member who is, in any way, whether directly or 
indirectly, concerned or interested in a contract or arrangement or 
proposed contract or arrangement, entered into or to be entered into, 
by or on behalf of the Board shall, as soon as possible, after 
relevant circumstances have come to his knowledge, disclose the nature 
of his concern or interest at a meeting of the Board and the 
disclosure shall be recorded in the minutes of the Board and the 
member shall not take any part after such disclosure in the 
discussion, or vote, on the contract or arrangement; and if he does 
vote, his vote shall be void.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>341841</tid>
<number> 9</number> Meetings of Board.
<section><tid>817990</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall meet at such times and  
places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2), (3) 
and (4), observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction 
of business at its meetings (including the quorum at meetings) as may 
be provided by regulations made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1312370</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or, in his absence, the Vice- Chairman, if any, 
or in the absence of both, any member chosen by the members

<pagefootnote><pagenum>303</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

present from amongst themselves, shall preside at a meeting of the 
Board.


</section>

<section><tid>1906172</tid>
<number>3</number>If an officer of Government who is nominated as a member of 
the Board by virtue of his office is unable to attend any meeting of 
the Board, he may, with the previous approval of the Chairman, 
authorise in writing, any person to attend that meeting, but the 
person so authorised shall not be entitled to vote at that meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>279550</tid>
<number>4</number>All questions at a meeting of the Board shall be decided by a 
majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in the 
case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or, in his absence, the 
Vice- Chairman, if any, or, in the absence of both, the member 
presiding shall have a second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>694901</tid>
<number> 10</number> Temporary association of persons with Board for particular 
purposes.
<section><tid>598724</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and  
for such purposes as may be provided by regulations made under this 
Act, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to have with 
regard to the performance of any of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1520175</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with it by the Board under sub- section 
 (1) for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the 
discussions of the Board relating to that purpose, but shall not, by 
virtue of this section, be entitled to vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>771207</tid>
<number> 11</number> Authentication of orders and other instruments of Board.
<section><tid>955962</tid>
<number>1</number> 
all orders and decisions of the Board shall be authenticated by the 
signature of the Chairman or the Vice- Chairman, if any, or any other 
member authorised by the Board in this behalf, and all other 
instruments issued by the Board shall be authenticated by the 
signature of an officer of the Board authorised in like manner in this 
behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1405413</tid>
<number>2</number>Orders, decisions or instruments authenticated in accordance 
with the provisions of sub- section (1) shall be evidence of the 
matters recorded therein and shall be admissible in evidence 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> 
 (1 of <year>1872</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1928197</tid>
<number>3</number>Any member, officer or other employee of the Board or any 
other person interested in the library shall be entitled to be 
furnished, within seven days after he has made a request in that 
behalf to the library, with a copy of the order, decision or 
instrument authenticated in the manner specified in sub- section (1), 
on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>304</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585900</tid>
<number> 12</number> Staff of Board.
<section><tid>628408</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section  
 (2), the Board may, for the purpose of enabling it efficiently to 
perform its functions under this Act, appoint such number of officers 
and other employees as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>804626</tid>
<number>2</number>The recruitment and conditions of service of such officers 
and employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations made 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1063500</tid>
<number>13</number>Transfer of service of existing employees to Board. Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, every person employed in the library 
immediately before the date of establishment of the Board shall, on 
and from such date, become an employee of the Board with such 
designation as the Board may determine and shall hold his office or 
service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon 
the same terms and conditions as he would have held the same on such 
date if the Board had not been established and shall continue to do so 
unless and until his employment in the Board is duly terminated or 
until such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly 
altered by the Board:
Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions 
of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage 
without the previous approval of the Central Government.



</article>



<article><tid>217978</tid>
<number>14</number>Location of library. The library and the collections thereof 
shall continue to be located at Rampur.
CHAP

PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF BOARD

CHAPTER III

PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF BOARD



</article>



<article><tid>407271</tid>
<number> 15</number> Properties and liabilities of Board.
<section><tid>1809416</tid>
<number>1</number>On the establishment  
of the Board-

<subsection><tid>1882443</tid>
<number>i</number>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, or 
realisable by, the trustees of the library constituted 
by the deed of trust, in their capacity as such, shall 
vest in, and be realisable by, the Board; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1054262</tid>
<number>ii</number>all liabilities in relation to the library, which are 
enforceable against the said trustees, shall be 
enforceable only against the Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1029722</tid>
<number>2</number>All properties, which may, after the establishment of the 
Board, be given, bequeathed or otherwise transferred to the library or 
acquired by the Board, shall vest in the Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>305</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1251126</tid>
<number> 16</number> Duties of Board.
<section><tid>1789911</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of the deed of  
trust, it shall be the general duty of the Board to manage the library 
and to plan, promote, organise and implement programmes for the 
development of the library on modern scientific lines (including  
provision of adequate facilities for preservation and photo- 
  duplication of rare manuscripts) and to perform such other functions 
as the Central Government may, from time to time, assign to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1093368</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provisions, the Board may take such steps as it thinks fit-- 
-

<subsection><tid>1543547</tid>
<number>a</number>to provide for instruction and research in matters 
relating to libraries and for the advancement of 
learning and dissemination of knowledge in such 
matters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1920143</tid>
<number>b</number>to protect, enlarge and improve the collections in the 
library;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>64069</tid>
<number>c</number>to promote study and research and to provide facilities 
to scholars for this purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1634890</tid>
<number>d</number>to do all such other things as may be necessary for the 
discharge of its functions under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1293214</tid>
<number> 17</number> Powers of Board.
<section><tid>366434</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such conditions and  
restrictions as the Central Government may think fit to impose, the 
Board may exercise all such powers as may be necessary or expedient 
for the purpose of carrying out its functions and duties under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1076452</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such regulations as may be made by the Board in 
this behalf, the Board may, from time to time, purchase or otherwise 
acquire such manuscripts, books, articles or things as may, in the 
opinion of the Board, be worthy of preservation in the library.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1462247</tid>
<number>18</number>Grants by Central Government to Board. For the purpose of 
enabling the Board to discharge its functions efficiently under this 
Act, the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Board in each financial 
year such sums of money as that Government considers necessary by way 
of grant, loan or otherwise.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>306</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>254898</tid>
<number> 19</number> Fund of Board.
<section><tid>1712413</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain a Fund to which  
shall be credited-

<subsection><tid>1194217</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys paid to it by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1005786</tid>
<number>b</number>such sums of money as the State Government may pay 
annually for specified purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479926</tid>
<number>c</number>all fees and other charges levied by it under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1224903</tid>
<number>d</number>all moneys received by the Board by way of grant, gift, 
donation, benefaction, bequest, subscription, 
contribution or transfer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1784164</tid>
<number>e</number>all other moneys received by the Board in any other 
manner or from any other source.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1702076</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for 
performing its functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated 
as expenditure payable out of the Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1966584</tid>
<number>3</number>A sum of money, not exceeding such sum as may be specified by 
regulations made under this Act, shall be kept in current account with 
any nationalised bank, or any other scheduled or other bank approved 
by the Central Government in this behalf, but any moneys in excess of 
that sum shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or with the 
agents of the Reserve Bank of India or invested in such manner as may 
be generally or specially approved by the Central Government.
Explanation.-- In this sub- section,-


<subsection><tid>1434108</tid>
<number>a</number>" nationalised bank" means a corresponding new bank as 
defined in the Banking companies (Acquisition and  
  Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1564210</tid>
<number>b</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank included for the time 
being in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>).



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>484189</tid>
<number> 20</number> Budget.
<section><tid>1216112</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall, by such date in each financial  
year as may be specified by the Central Government, submit to it for 
approval a budget for the next financial year in the form specified by 
that Government, showing therein the estimated receipts and 
expenditure, and the sums which would be required from the Central 
Government during that financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>852036</tid>
<number>2</number>The budget for a financial year, as approved by the Central 
Government for any financial year, shall be the budget of the library 
for that financial year.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>307</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1416803</tid>
<number>3</number>If any sum granted by the Central Government to the library 
for any financial year remains wholly or partly unspent in that 
financial year, the unspent sum may be carried forward to the next 
financial year and taken into account in determining the sum to be 
provided for by the Central Government for that year.

</section>

<section><tid>13254</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (5), no sum shall be 
expended by or on behalf of the Board, unless the expenditure is 
covered by provision in the budget approved by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>178648</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such conditions and restrictions as the Central 
Government may think fit to impose, the Board may sanction any re- 
appropriation from one head of expenditure to another or from a 
provision made for one purpose to that for another purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>24501</tid>
<number> 21</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1928223</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the balance- sheet in such form as may be 
specified, in accordance with such general directions as may be issued 
by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>681972</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any officer authorised by 
him in this behalf, and any expenditure incurred by him in connection 
with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1000251</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
authorised by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect the office of the Board, and the library.

</section>

<section><tid>1985521</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Board, as certified by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India or any other person authorised by him in 
this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government 
shall, as soon as may be after the receipt thereof, cause the same to 
be laid before each House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>308</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1098247</tid>
<number> 22</number> Returns and reports.
<section><tid>1213101</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall furnish to the  
Central Government, at such time and in such form and in such manner 
as the Central Government may direct, such returns, statements and 
particulars as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.

</section>

<section><tid>262445</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Board shall, as soon as possible after the commencement of each 
financial year, submit to the Central Government, within such time as 
may be specified by the Central Government, a report giving true and 
full account of the activities of the Board during the previous 
financial year and an account of activities likely to be undertaken 
during the current financial year.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>344569</tid>
<number>23</number>Power of Central Government to issue directions to Board. In 
the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Board shall be 
bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
Government may give to it from time to time:
Provided that the Board shall be given an opportunity to express 
its views before any direction is given to it under this sub- section.



</article>



<article><tid>357197</tid>
<number>24</number>Delegation of powers and duties. The Board may, by general or 
special order in writing, direct that all or any of the powers or 
duties, which may be exercised or discharged by it, shall, in such 
circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified 
in the order, be exercised or discharged also by any member, officer 
or employee of the Board specified in this behalf in the order.


</article>



<article><tid>341885</tid>
<number>25</number>Officers and employees of Board to be public servants. Every 
officer or employee of the Board shall, when acting or purporting to 
act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or 
regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be a public servant within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1115370</tid>
<number>26</number>Protection of action taken under the Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or 
any member, officer or other employee of the Board for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act 
or of any rule or regulation made thereunder.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>309</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1285057</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1182025</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
give effect to the provisions of this Act:
Provided that when the Board has been established, no such rules 
shall be made without consulting the Board.


</section>

<section><tid>1976065</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1057001</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the members nominated under clause 
 (e), clause (f) or clause (h) of sub- section (1) of 
section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1409031</tid>
<number>b</number>the travelling and other allowances payable to a member 
other than the Chairman and to a person associated with 
the Board under section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1352515</tid>
<number>c</number>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and 
the procedure to be followed in removing a member who 
is or becomes subject to any disqualification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1399307</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which, 
contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>818386</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1804655</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of on effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>302284</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power of Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>1455604</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, with  
the previous approval of the Central Government <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by notification in 
the Official Gazette,] make regulations, not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, with regard to 
the discharge of its functions under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>310</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1890212</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1844616</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions and restrictions subject to which 
manuscripts and books in the library may be used;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>318708</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which, and the purposes for which, 
persons may be associated with the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>172778</tid>
<number>c</number>the time and place of meetings of the Board, the 
procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction 
of business at such meetings and the quorum necessary 
for the transaction of business at a meeting of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911620</tid>
<number>d</number>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Board and 
the transmission of copies thereof to the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>678197</tid>
<number>e</number>the recruitment and conditions of service of officers 
and other employees of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1138450</tid>
<number>f</number>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments, 
deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1425925</tid>
<number>g</number>the maximum amount that may be kept by the Board in a 
current account;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1846245</tid>
<number>h</number>the maintenance of registers and accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1139763</tid>
<number>i</number>the compilation of catalogues and inventories of the 
manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the 
library;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1877154</tid>
<number>j</number>the steps to be taken for the preservation of the 
manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the 
library;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>566908</tid>
<number>k</number>the general management of the library;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744727</tid>
<number>l</number>the fees and other charges to be levied for the use of 
any manuscript or book in the library;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1801107</tid>
<number>m</number>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in 
the opinion of the Board, necessary for the performance 
of its functions under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>311</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>817811</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, after consultation with the 
Board, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend, vary or rescind 
any regulation which it has approved and thereupon the regulation 
shall have effect as so amended or varied or be of no effect, as the 
case may be, but without prejudice to the exercise of the powers of 
the Board under sub- sections (1) and (2).

</section>

<section><tid>205308</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1755687</tid>
<number>29</number>Act to override other enactments and instruments. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any law other than this Act for 
the time being in force or any instrument having effect by virtue of 
any enactment other than this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>312</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>