<act><title>

    The Air (PREVENTION AND 
    CONTROL OF POLLUTION) Act, 1981</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 
    1981.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole 
    of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
    force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central 
    Govern­ment may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



  


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>
“air pollutant” means any solid, liquid or gaseous substance <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[(including
noise)] present in the atmosphere in such concentra­tion as may be or tend to
be injurious to human beings or other living creatures or plants or property or
environment; 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“air pollution” means the presence in the atmosphere of any air pollutant; 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
 “approved appliance”
means any equipment or gadget used for the burning of any combustible material
or for generating or consuming any fume, gas or particulate matter and approved
by the State Board for the purposes of this Act; 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
 “approved fuel”
means any fuel approved by the State Board for the purposes of this Act; (e) 
“automobile” means any vehicle powered either by internal combustion
engine or by any method of generating power to drive such vehicle by burning
fuel; 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
 “Board” means the
Central Board or a State Board; 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
 “Central Board”
means the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Central
Pollution Control Board] constituted under section 3 of the Water (Prevention
and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 


 </section><section>
<number>h</number>
 “chimney” includes
any structure with an opening or outlet from or through which any air pollutant
may be emitted; 


 </section><section>
<number>i</number>
 “control equipment”
means any apparatus, device, equipment or system to control the quality and
manner of emission of any air pollutant and includes any device used for
securing the efficient operation of any industrial plant; 


 </section><section>
<number>j</number>
 “emission” means any
solid or liquid or gaseous substance coming out of any chimney, duct or flue or
any other outlet; 


 </section><section>
<number>k</number>
 “industrial plant”
means any plant used for any industrial or trade purposes and emitting any air
pollutant into the atmos­phere; 


 </section><section>
<number>l</number>
 “member” means a
member of the Central Board or a State Board, as the case may be, and includes
the Chairman thereof; 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>m</number>
 “occupier”, in relation to any factory or
premises, means the person who has control over the affairs of the factory or
the premises, and includes, in relation to any substance, the person in
possession of the substance;] 


 </section><section>
<number>n</number>
 “prescribed” means
prescribed by rules made under this Act by the Central Government or, as the
case may be, the State Govern­ment; 


 </section><section>
<number>o</number>
 “State Board”
means,— 


 <subsection>
<number>i</number>
 in relation to a State in which the Water (Prevention and
Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), is in force and the State 
Gov­ernment has constituted for that State a <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[State
Pollution Control Board] under section 4 of that Act, the said State Board; and 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>
 in relation to any other State, the State Board for the
Prevention and Control of Air Pollution constituted by the State Government
under section 5 of this Act. 
















</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Central 
    Pollution Control Board.—The 
    Central Pollution Control Board constituted under section 3 of the Water 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), shall, without 
    prejudice to the exercise and performance of its powers and functions under 
    that Act, exercise the powers and perform the functions of the Central 
    Pollution Control Board for the prevention and control of air pollution 
    under this Act.





  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number> State Pollution Control 
      Boards constituted under section 4 of Act 6 of 1974 to be State Boards 
      under this Act.—In any State in which the 
      Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), is in 
      force and the State Government has constituted for that State a State 
      Pollution Control Board under section 4 of that Act, such State Board 
      shall be deemed to be the State Board for the Preven­tion and Control 
      of Air Pollution constituted under section 5 of this Act, and accordingly 
      that State Pollution Control Board shall, without prejudice to the 
      exer­cise and performance of its powers and functions under that Act, 
      exercise the powers and perform the functions of the State Board for the 
      prevention and control of air pollution under this 
    Act.]
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Constitution of State Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any State in which the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 
    1974 (6 of 1974), is not in force, or that Act is in force but the State 
    Government has not constituted a <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[State 
    Pollution Control Board] under that Act, the State Government shall, with 
    effect from such date as it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint constitute a 

    1[State Pollution 
    Control Board] under such name as may be specified in the notification, to 
    exercise the powers conferred on, and per­form the functions assigned to, 
    that Board under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    State Board constituted under this Act shall consist of the following 
    members, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  a Chairman, being 
      a person having special knowledge or prac­tical experience in respect of 
      matters relating to environmental protection, to be nominated by the State 
      Government:
 
Provided that the 
      Chairman may be either whole-time or part-time as the State Government may 
      think fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  such number of 
      officials, not exceeding five, as the State Government may think fit, to 
      be nominated by the State Government to represent that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  such number of 
      persons, not exceeding five, as the State Government may think fit, to be 
      nominated by the State Government from amongst the members of the local 
      authorities functioning within the State;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  such number of 
      non-officials, not exceeding three, as the State Government may think fit, 
      to be nominated by the State Government to represent the interests of 
      agriculture, fishery or industry or trade or labour or any other interest, 
      which, in the opinion of that Government, ought to be represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  two persons to 
      represent the companies or corporations owned, controlled or managed by 
      the State Government, to be nominated by that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>f</number>  
      a full-time member-secretary having such qualifications, knowledge and 
      experience of scientific, engineering or management aspects of pollution 
      control as may be prescribed, to be appoint­ed by the State Government:]
 

      Provided that the State Government shall ensure that not less than two of 
      the members are persons having special knowledge or prac­tical experience 
      in respect of matters relating to the improve­ment of the quality of air 
      or the prevention, control or abate­ment of air pollution.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every State Board constituted under this Act shall be a body corporate with 
    the name specified by the State Government in the notification issued under 
    sub-section (1), having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, 
    subject to the provi­sions of this Act, to acquire and dispose of property 
    and to contract, and may by the said name sue or be sued.




  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number> 
      Central Board to exercise the powers and perform the functions of a State 
      Board in the Union territories.—No State Board shall be 
      constituted for a Union territory and in relation to a Union territory, 
      the Central Board shall exercise the powers and per­form the functions 
      of a State Board under this Act for that Union 
territory:
 Provided 
      that in relation to any Union territory the Central Board may delegate all 
      or any of its powers and functions under this section to such person or 
      body of persons as the Central Government may 
specify.
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Terms and conditions of service of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as other­wise provided by or under this Act, a member of a State Board 
    constituted under this Act, other than the member-secretary, shall hold 
    office for a term of three years from the date on which his nomination is 
    notified in the Official Gazette:
 

    Provided that a member shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, 
    continue to hold office until his successor enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The term of office of a member of a State Board constituted under this Act 
    and nominated under clause (b) or clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 5 
    shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to hold the office under the State 
    Government or, as the case may be, the company or corporation owned, 
    controlled or managed by the State Government, by virtue of which he was 
    nomi­nated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    member of a State Board constituted under this Act, other than the 
    member-secretary, may at any time resign his office by writing under his 
    hand addressed,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> in the case of the 
      Chairman, to the State Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> in any other case, 
      to the Chairman of the State Board, and the seat of the Chairman or such 
      other member shall thereupon become vacant.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    member of a State Board constituted under this Act, other than the 
    member-secretary, shall be deemed to have vacated his seat, if he is absent 
    without reason, sufficient in the opinion of the State Board, from three 
    consecutive meetings of the State Board or where he is nominated under 
    clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5, he ceases to be a member of the 
    local authority and such vacation of seat shall, in either case, take effect 
    from such date as the State Government may, by notifica­tion in the Official 
    Gazette, specify.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    casual vacancy in a State Board constituted under this Act shall be filled 
    by a fresh nomination and the person nominated to fill the vacancy shall 
    hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the member whose 
    place he takes was nominated.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    member of a State Board constituted under this Act shall be eligible for 
    re-nomination <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***].
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    The other terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other members 
    (except the member-secretary) of a State Board constituted under this Act 
    shall be such as may be prescribed.



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Disqualifications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall be a member of a State Board constituted under this Act, 
    who—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> is, or at any time 
      has been, adjudged insolvent, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> is of unsound mind 
      and has been so declared by a competent court, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> is, or has been, 
      convicted of an offence which, in the opin­ion of the State Government, 
      involves moral turpitude, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> is, or at any time 
      has been, convicted of an offence under this Act, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> has directly or 
      indirectly by himself or by any partner, any share or interest in any firm 
      or company carrying on the business of manufacture, sale, or hire of 
      machinery, industrial plant, control equipment or any other apparatus for 
      the improvement of the quality of air or for the prevention, control or 
      abatement of air pollution, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> is a director or a 
      secretary, manager or other salaried officer or employee of any company or 
      firm having any contract with the Board, or with the Government 
      constituting the Board or with a local authority in the State, or with a 
      company or corporation owned, controlled or managed by the Government, for 
      the carrying out of programmes for the improvement of the quality of air 
      or for the prevention, control or abatement of air pollution, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> has so abused, in 
      the opinion of the State Government, his position as a member, as to 
      render his continuance on the State Board detrimental to the interests of 
      the general public.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The State Government shall, by order in writing, remove any member who is, 
    or has become, subject to any disqualification mentioned in sub-section (1):
 

    Provided that no order of removal shall be made by the State Government 
    under this section unless the member concerned has been given a reasonable 
    opportunity of showing cause against the same.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (6) of 
    section 7, a member who has been removed under this section shall not be 
    eligible to continue to hold office until his successor enters upon his 
    office, or, as the case may be, for re-nomination as a member.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Vacation of seats by members.—If 
    a member of a State Board constituted under this Act becomes subject to any 
    of the disqual­ifications specified in section 8, his seat shall become 
    vacant.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Meetings of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purposes of this Act, a Board shall meet at least once in every 
    three months and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
    transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed:
 

    Provided that if, in the opinion of the Chairman, any business of an urgent 
    nature is to be transacted, he may convene a meeting of the Board at such 
    time as he thinks fit for the aforesaid pur­pose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Copies of the minutes of the meetings under sub-section (1) shall be 
    forwarded to the Central Board and to the State Govern­ment concerned.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Constitution of committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Board may constitute as many committees consisting wholly of members or 
    partly of members and partly of other persons and for such purpose or 
    purposes as it may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    committee constituted under this section shall meet at such time and at such 
    place, and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
    transaction of business at its meetings, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The members of a committee other than the members of the Board shall be paid 
    such fees and allowances, for attending its meet­ings and for attending to 
    any other work of the Board as may be prescribed.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article><number>12</number> 
      Temporary association of persons with Board for particular 
      purposes.— 
<section><number>1</number> 
      A Board may associate with itself in such manner, and for such purposes, 
      as may be prescribed, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire 
      to obtain in performing any of its functions under this 
      Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person 
      associated with the Board under sub-section (1) for any purpose shall have 
      a right to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to that 
      purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at a meeting of the Board and 
      shall not be a member of the Board for any other 
purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A person 
      associated with a Board under sub-section (1) shall be entitled to receive 
      such fees and allowances as may be pre­scribed.
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article><number>13</number> 
      Vacancy in Board not to invalidate acts or proceedings.—No act or proceeding of a 
      Board or any committee thereof shall be called in question on the ground 
      merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
      constitution of, the Board or such committee, as the case may 
      be.
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article><number>14</number> 
      Member-secretary and officers and other employees of State 
      Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      The terms and conditions of service of the member-secretary of a State 
      Board constituted under this Act shall be such as may be 
      prescribed.
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The member-secretary of a 
      State Board, whether constituted under this Act or not, shall exercise 
      such powers and perform such duties as may be prescribed, or as may, from 
      time to time, be delegated to him by the State Board or its 
      Chairman.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject 
      to such rules as may be made by the State Government in this behalf, a 
      State Board, whether constituted under this Act or not, may appoint such 
      officers and other employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
      performance of its func­tions under this Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The 
      method of appointment, the conditions of service and the scales of pay of 
      the officers (other than the member-secretary) and other employees of a 
      State Board appointed under sub-section (3) shall be such as may be 
      determined by regulations made by the State Board under this 
      Act.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject 
      to such conditions as may be prescribed, a State Board constituted under 
      this Act may from time to time appoint any qualified person to be a 
      consultant to the Board and pay him such salary and allowances or fees, as 
      it thinks fit.



  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Delegation of powers.—A 
    State Board may, by general or special order, delegate to the Chairman or 
    the member-secretary or any other officer of the Board subject to such 
    conditions and limita­tions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such 
    of its powers and functions under this Act as it may deem necessary.

 
 
The delegating 
      authority, by the mere act of delegation, does not completely denude 
      itself of its powers; Ram Sevak Singh v. State of Bihar, 
      1979 BLJR 496.


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Functions of Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, and without prejudice to the 
    performance of its func­tions under the Water (Prevention and Control of 
    Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), the main functions of the Central Board 
    shall be to improve the quality of air and to prevent, control or abate air 
    pollution in the country.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    functions, the Central Board may—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> advise the Central 
      Government on any matter concerning the improvement of the quality of air 
      and the prevention, control or abatement of air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> plan and cause to 
      be executed a nation-wide programme for the prevention, control or 
      abatement of air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> co-ordinate the 
      activities of the State Boards and resolve disputes among them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> provide technical 
      assistance and guidance to the State Boards, carry out and sponsor 
      investigations and research relat­ing to problems of air pollution and 
      prevention, control or abatement of air pollution;
 
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[dd)  perform such of the 
      functions of any State Board as may be specified in an order made under 
      sub-section (2) of section 18;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  plan and organise 
      the training of persons engaged or to be engaged in programmes for the 
      prevention, control or abatement of air pollution on such terms and 
      conditions as the Central Board may specify;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>  organise through 
      mass media a comprehensive programme regarding the prevention, control or 
      abatement of air pollution; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>  collect, compile 
      and publish technical and statistical data relating to air pollution and 
      the measures devised for its effec­tive prevention, control or abatement 
      and prepare manuals, codes or guides relating to prevention, control or 
      abatement of air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>  lay down standards 
      for the quality of air;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>  collect and 
      disseminate information in respect of matters relating to air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>  perform such other 
      functions as may be prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Central Board may establish or recognise a laboratory or laboratories to 
    enable the Central Board to perform its functions under this section 
    efficiently.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Central Board may—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> delegate any of its 
      functions under this Act generally or specially to any of the committees 
      appointed by it;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> do such other 
      things and perform such other acts as it may think necessary for the 
      proper discharge of its functions and generally for the purpose of 
      carrying into effect the purposes of this Act.
</subsection>



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Functions of State 
    Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, and without prejudice to the 
    performance of its func­tions, if any, under the Water (Prevention and 
    Control of Pollu­tion) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), the functions of a State Board 
    shall be—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> to plan a 
      comprehensive programme for the prevention, control or abatement of air 
      pollution and to secure the execution there­of;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> to advise the State 
      Government on any matter concerning the prevention, control or abatement 
      of air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> to collect and 
      disseminate information relating to air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> to collaborate with 
      the Central Board in organising the training of persons engaged or to be 
      engaged in programmes relat­ing to prevention, control, or abatement of 
      air pollution and to organise mass education programme relating thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> to inspect, at all 
      reasonable times, any control equipment, industrial plant or manufacturing 
      process and to give, by order, such directions to such persons as it may 
      consider necessary to take steps for the prevention, control, or abatement 
      of air pollu­tion;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> to inspect air 
      pollution control areas at such intervals as it may think necessary, 
      assess the quality of air therein and take steps for the prevention, 
      control or abatement of air pollu­tion in such areas;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> to lay down, in 
      consultation with the Central Board and having regard to the standards for 
      the quality of air laid down by the Central Board, standards for emission 
      of air pollutants into the atmosphere from industrial plants and 
      automobiles or for the discharge of any air pollution into the atmosphere 
      from any other source whatsoever not being a ship or an aircraft:
 
Provided that different 
      standards for emission may be laid down under this clause for different 
      industrial plants having regard to the quantity and composition of 
      emission of air pollutants into the atmosphere from such industrial 
      plants;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> to advise the State 
      Government with respect to the suitabili­ty of any premises or location 
      for carrying on any industry which is likely to cause air pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> to perform such 
      other functions as may be prescribed or as may, from time to time, be 
      entrusted to it by the Central Board or the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> to do such other 
      things and to perform such other acts as it may think necessary for the 
      proper discharge of its functions and generally for the purpose of 
      carrying into effect the purposes of this Act.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    State Board may establish or recognise a laboratory or laboratories to 
    enable the State Board to perform its functions under this section 
    efficiently.

 
 
The Supreme Court 
      ordered the closure of limestone quarries which were causing imbalance to 
      ecology and hazard to public health and environment. However, in order to 
      mitigate the hardship caused by such closure to the lessee, Government of 
      India and State of U.P. were directed to give priority and send intimation 
      when­ever any other area was allotted for grant of limestone or dolomite 
      quarrying to the displaced lessees; Rural Litigation and Entitlement 
      Kendra Dehradun v. State of U.P., AIR 1985 SC 651.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Power to give directions.—<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    In the performance of its functions under this Act—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the Central Board 
      shall be bound by such directions in writ­ing as the Central Government 
      may give to it; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> every State Board 
      shall be bound by such directions in writ­ing as the Central Board or the 
      State Government may give to it:
 

      Provided that where a direction given by the State Government is 
      inconsistent with the direction given by the Central Board, the matter 
      shall be referred to the Central Government for its deci­sion.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Where 
    the Central Government is of the opinion that any State Board has defaulted 
    in complying with any directions given by the Central Board under 
    sub-section (1) and as a result of such default a grave emergency has arisen 
    and it is necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by 
    order, direct the Central Board to perform any of the functions of the State 
    Board in relation to such area, for such period and for such purposes, as 
    may be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the Central Board performs any of the functions of the State Board in 
    pursuance of a direction under sub-section (2), the expenses, if any, 
    incurred by the Central Board with respect to the performance of such 
    functions may, if the State Board is empowered to recover such expenses, be 
    recovered by the Central Board with interest (at such reasonable rate as the 
    Central Government may, by order, fix) from the date when a demand for such 
    expenses is made until it is paid from the person or persons concerned as 
    arrears of land revenue or of public demand.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any directions to 
    perform the functions of any State Board given under sub-section (2) in 
    respect of any area would not preclude the State Board from performing such 
    functions in any other area in the State or any of its other functions in 
    that area.]




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Power to declare air pollution control areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, after consultation with the State Board, by 
    noti­fication in the Official Gazette, declare in such manner as may be 
    prescribed, any area or areas within the State as air pollu­tion control 
    area or areas for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The State Government may, after consultation with the State Board, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> alter any air 
      pollution control area whether by way of exten­sion or reduction;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> declare a new air 
      pollution control area in which may be merged one or more existing air 
      pollution control areas or any part or parts thereof.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the State Government, after consultation with the State Board, is of opinion 
    that the use of any fuel, other than an approved fuel, in any air pollution 
    control area or part thereof, may cause or is likely to cause air pollution, 
    it may, by notifi­cation in the Official Gazette, prohibit the use of such 
    fuel in such area or part thereof with effect from such date (being not less 
    than three months from the date of publication of the noti­fication) as may 
    be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The State Government may after consultation with the State Board, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, direct that with effect from such date 
    as may be specified therein, no appliance, other than an approved appliance 
    shall be used in the premises situated in an air pollution control area:
 

    Provided that different dates may be specified for different parts of an air 
    pollution control area or for the use of differ­ent appliances.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the State Government, after consultation with the State Board, is of opinion 
    that the burning of any material (not being fuel) in any air pollution 
    control area or part thereof may cause or is likely to cause air pollution, 
    it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, prohibit the burning of 
    such material in such area or part thereof.
 
Power of 
    authority, when not to cease
 
The power which vests in an 
    authority would not cease to exist simply for the reason that the rules have 
    not been framed or the manner of exercise of the power has not been 
    prescribed; Orissa State Prevention and Control of Pollution Board v.
    Orient Paper Mills, AIR 2003 SC 1966.
 
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>20</number> Power 
      to give instructions for ensuring standards for emis­sion from 
      automobiles.—With a view to ensuring that 
      the standards for emission of air pollutants from automobiles laid down by 
      the State Board under clause (g) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 17 are 
      complied with, the State Government shall, in consultation with the State 
      Board, give such instructions as may be deemed neces­sary to the 
      concerned authority in charge of registration of motor vehicles under the 
      Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939)*, and such authority shall, 
      notwithstanding anything contained in that Act or the rules made 
      thereunder be bound to comply with such instructions.

 
 The Motor Vehicles Act, 1988, 
        inter alia, provides for prevention and control of air pollution 
        from automobiles which constitute a major source of pollution 
        everywhere, especially in the congested metropolis. Sub-section (1) of 
        section 110 of the said Act inter alia lays down that the Central 
        Government may make rules regulating the construction, equipment and 
        maintenance of motor vehicles and trailers with respect to all or any of 
        the following matters:—  (i) the emission of smoke, visible 
        vapour, sparks, ashes, grit or oil; (ii) the reduction of noise 
        emitted by or caused by vehicles; (iii) standards for emission of air 
        pollutants.



  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Restrictions on use of certain industrial plants.—<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, no person shall, without the 
    previous consent of the State Board, establish or operate any industrial 
    plant in an air pollution control area:
 

    Provided that a person operating any industrial plant in any air pollution 
    control area immediately before the commencement of section 9 of the Air 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Amend­ment Act, 1987 (47 of 1987), for 
    which no consent was necessary prior to such commencement, may continue to 
    do so for a period of three months from such commencement or, if he has made 
    an application for such consent within the said period of three months, till 
    the disposal of such application.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application for consent of the State Board under sub-section (1) shall be 
    accompanied by such fees as may be pre­scribed and shall be made in the 
    prescribed form and shall con­tain the particulars of the industrial plant 
    and such other particulars as may be prescribed:
 

    Provided that where any person, immediately before the declara­tion of any 
    area as an air pollution control area, operates in such area any industrial 
    plant, <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[***] such person shall make the application under this 
    sub-section within such period (being not less than three months from the 
    date of such declaration) as may be prescribed and where such person makes 
    such application, he shall be deemed to be operating such industrial plant 
    with the consent of the State Board until the consent applied for has been 
    refused.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The State Board may make such inquiry as it may deem fit in respect of the 
    application for consent referred to in sub-section (1) and in making any 
    such inquiry, shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Within a period of four months after the receipt of the application for 
    consent referred to in sub-section (1), the State Board shall, by order in 
    writing, <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[and for reasons to be record­ed in the order, grant 
    the consent applied for subject to such conditions and for such period as 
    may be specified in the order, or refuse such consent:]
 
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that it shall be open to the State Board to cancel such consent before the 
    expiry of the period for which it is granted or refuse further consent after 
    such expiry if the conditions subject to which such consent has been granted 
    are not fulfilled :
 

    Provided further that before cancelling a consent or refusing a further 
    consent under the first proviso, a reasonable oppor­tunity of being heard 
    shall be given to the person concerned.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Every person to whom consent has been granted by the State Board under 
    sub-section (4), shall comply with the following conditions, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> the control 
      equipment of such specifications as the State Board may approve in this 
      behalf shall be installed and operated in the premises where the industry 
      is carried on or proposed to be carried on;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> the existing 
      control equipment, if any, shall be altered or replaced in accordance with 
      the directions of the State Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> the control 
      equipment referred to in clause (i) or clause (ii) shall be kept at all 
      times in good running condition;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> chimney, wherever 
      necessary, of such specifications as the State Board may approve in this 
      behalf shall be erected or re-erected in such premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> such other 
      conditions as the State Board may specify in this behalf; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number> the conditions 
      referred to in clauses (i), (ii) and (iv) shall be complied with 
      within such period as the State Board may specify in this behalf :
</subsection>
 
Provided that in the case 
    of a person operating any industrial plant <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[***] in an air 
    pollution control area immediately before the date of declaration of such 
    area as an air pollution control area, the period so specified shall not be 
    less than six months:
 
Provided further that—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> after the installation of any control 
      equipment in accordance with the specifications under clause (i), or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> after the alteration or replacement of 
      any control equipment in accordance with the directions of the State Board 
      under clause (ii), or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> after the erection or re-erection of any 
      chimney under clause (iv), 
</subsection>
 no control 
    equipment or chimney shall be altered or re­placed or, as the case may be, 
    erected or re-erected except with the previous approval of the State Board.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If due to any 
    technological improvement or otherwise the State Board is of opinion that 
    all or any of the conditions referred in to sub-section (5) require or 
    requires variation (including the change of any control equipment, either in 
    whole or in part), the State Board shall, after giving the person to whom 
    consent has been granted an opportunity of being heard, vary all or any of 
    such conditions and thereupon such person shall be bound to comply with the 
    conditions as so varied.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where a person to whom consent has been 
    granted by the State Board under sub-section (4) transfers his interest in 
    the indus­try to any other person, such consent shall be deemed to have been 
    granted to such other person and he shall be bound to comply with all the 
    conditions subject to which it was granted as if the consent was granted to 
    him originally.

 
 
Where a notification was 
      issued under section 19(1) of the Act by the Central Govern­ment in 
      consultation with the Central Board placing the Union territory of Delhi 
      within the control area of air pollution, any plant if established has to 
      take permission from the Central Board. In the present case the Sriram 
      Plants of Delhi fell under the schedule of the industries specified in 
      the Act, and had to obtain consent order under section 21 thereof. 
      Accordingly if the Cen­tral Board at any stage found that the conditions 
      in the consent order relating to power plant were not complied with and 
      the particular matter emitted by the stacks of the boilers was more than 
      150 mg/Nm3 it 
      could take whatever action as was warranted by law; M.C. Mehta v. 
      Union of India, (1986) 2 SCC 176.








  


</section></article> 

 <title>THE AIR (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
POLLUTION) ACT, 1981</title>
  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Persons carrying on industry, etc., not to 
allow emission of air pollutants in excess of the standards laid down by State 
Board. </title>—No person 1 [***] operating any industrial plant, in any air 
pollution control area shall discharge or cause or permit to be discharged the 
emission of any air pollutant in excess of the standards laid down by the State 
Board under clause (g) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 17. 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>22A</number> Power of Board to make 
      application to court for restrain­ing persons from causing air 
      pollution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Where it is apprehend­ed by a Board that emission of any air 
      pollutant, in excess of the standards laid down by the State Board under 
      clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 17, is likely to occur by reason 
      of any person operating an industrial plant or otherwise in any air 
      pollution control area, the Board may make an application to a court, not 
      inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of 
      the first class for restraining such person from emitting such air 
      pollutant.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of the 
      application under sub-section (1), the court may make such order as it 
      deems fit.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where under sub-section 
      (2), the court makes an order re­straining any person from discharging 
      or causing or permitting to be discharged the emission of any air 
      pollutant, it may, in that order,—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>  
        direct such person to desist from taking such action as is likely to 
        cause emission;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  
        authorise the Board, if the direction under clause (a) is not complied 
        with by the person to whom such direction is issued, to implement the 
        direction in such manner as may be specified by the 
        court.</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> All expenses
incurred by the Board in implementing the directions of the court 
      under clause (b) of sub-section (3) shall be recover­able from the 
      person concerned as arrears of land revenue or of public 
      demand.]



 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Furnishing of information to 
State Board and other agencies in certain cases. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> Where 
in any <footcitenum>21</footcitenum> [***] area the emission of any air pollutant into the 
atmosphere in excess of the standards laid down by the State Board occurs or is 
apprehended to occur due to accident or other unforeseen act or event, the 
person in charge of the premises from where such emission occurs or is 
apprehended to occur shall forthwith intimate the fact of such occurrence or the 
apprehension of such occurrence to the State Board and to such authorities or 
agencies as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of information with respect to the fact or the 
apprehension of any occurrence of the nature referred to in sub-section (1), 
whether through intimation under that sub-section or otherwise, the State Board 
and the authorities or agencies shall, as early as practicable cause such 
remedial measures to be taken as are necessary to mitigate the emission of such 
air pollutants. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Expenses, if any, incurred by the State Board, authority or 
agency with respect to the remedial measures referred to in sub-section (2) 
together with interest (at such reasonable rate, as the State Government may, by 
order, fix) from the date when a demand for the expenses is made until it is 
paid, may be recovered by that Board, authority or agency from the person 
concerned, as arrears of land revenue, or of public demand. 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Power of entry and inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, any person empowered by a State 
    Board in this behalf shall have a right to enter, at all reasonable times 
    with such assistance as he considers necessary, any place—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> for the purpose of 
      performing any of the functions of the State Board entrusted to him;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> for the purpose of 
      determining whether and if so in what manner, any such functions are to be 
      performed or whether any provisions of this Act or the rules made 
      thereunder or any notice, order, direction or authorisation served, made, 
      given or granted under this Act is being or has been complied with;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> for the purpose of 
      examining and testing any control equip­ment, industrial plant, record, 
      register, document or any other material object or for conducting a search 
      of any place in which he has reason to believe that an offence under this 
      Act or the rules made thereunder has been or is being or is about to be 
      committed and for seizing any such control equipment, industrial plant, 
      record, register, document or other material object if he has reasons to 
      believe that it may furnish evidence of the com­mission of an offence 
      punishable under this Act or the rules made thereunder.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every person <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***] 
    operating any control equipment or any industrial plant, in an air pollution 
    control area shall be bound to render all assistance to the person empowered 
    by the State Board, under sub-section (1) for carrying out the functions 
    under that sub-section and if he fails to do so without any reasonable cause 
    or excuse, he shall be guilty of an offence under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    any person wilfully delays or obstructs any person empow­ered by the State 
    Board under sub-section (1) in the discharge of his duties, he shall be 
    guilty of an offence under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), or, in 
    relation to the State of Jammu and Kashmir, or any area in which that Code 
    is not in force, the provisions of any corre­sponding law in force in that 
    State or area, shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under 
    this section as they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority 
    of a warrant issued under section 94 of the said Code or, as the case may 
    be, under the corresponding provisions of the said law.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Power to obtain information.—For 
    the purposes of carrying out the functions entrusted to it, the State Board 
    or any officer empowered by it in that behalf may call for any information 
    (including information regarding the types of air pollutants emitted into 
    the atmosphere and the level of the emission of such air pollutants) from 
    the occupier or any other person carrying on any industry or operating any 
    control of equipment or industrial plant and for the purpose of verifying 
    the correctness of such information, the State Board or such officer shall 
    have the right to inspect the premises where such industry, control 
    equipment or industrial plant is being carried on or operated.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number> Power to take samples of 
      air or emission and procedure to be followed in connection 
      therewith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      A State Board or any offi­cer empowered by it in this behalf shall 
      have power to take, for the purpose of analysis, samples of air or 
      emission from any chimney, flue or duct or any other outlet in such manner 
      as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The result of any analysis 
      of a sample of emission taken under sub-section (1) shall not be 
      admissible in evidence in any legal proceeding unless the provisions of 
      sub-sections (3) and (4) are complied with. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to the provisions 
      of sub-section (4), when a sample of emission is taken for analysis under 
      sub-section (1), the person taking the sample shall—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> serve 
        on the occupier or his agent, a notice, then and there, in such form as 
        may be prescribed, of his intention to have it so 
        analysed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in 
        the presence of the occupier or his agent, collect a sample of emission 
        for analysis;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> cause 
        the sample to be placed in a container or containers which shall be 
        marked and sealed and shall also be signed both by the person taking the 
        sample and the occupier or his agent;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> send, 
        without delay, the container or containers to the laboratory established 
        or recognised by the State Board under section 17 or, if a request in 
        that behalf is made by the occupi­er or his agent when the notice is 
        served on him under clause (a), to the laboratory established or 
        specified under sub-section (1) of section 
      28.</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> When a sample of emission 
      is taken for analysis under sub-section (1) and the person taking the 
      sample serves on the occu­pier or his agent, a notice under clause (a) 
      of sub-section (3), then,—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in a 
        case where the occupier or his agent wilfully absents himself, the 
        person taking the sample shall collect the sample of emission for 
        analysis to be placed in a container or containers which shall be marked 
        and sealed and shall also be signed by the person taking the sample, 
        and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in a 
        case where the occupier or his agent is present at the time of taking 
        the sample but refuses to sign the marked and sealed container or 
        containers of the sample of emission as required under clause (c) of 
        sub-section (3), the marked and sealed container or containers shall be 
        signed by the person taking the sample, 
 and the 
        container or containers shall be sent without delay by the person taking 
        the sample for analysis to the laboratory established or specified under 
        sub-section (1) of section 28 and such person shall inform the 
        Government analyst appointed under sub-section (1) of section 29, in 
        writing, about the wilful absence of the occupier or his agent, or, as 
        the case may be, his refusal to sign the container or 
        containers.</subsection>
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number> Reports of the result of 
      analysis on samples taken under section 26.— 
<section><number>1</number> Where a sample of emission 
      has been sent for analysis to the laboratory established or recognised by 
      the State Board, the Board analyst appointed under sub-section (2) of 
      section 29 shall analyse the sample and submit a report in the prescribed 
      form of such analysis in triplicate to the State Board
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of the report 
      under sub-section (1), one copy of the report shall be sent by the State 
      Board to the occupier or his agent referred to in section 26, another copy 
      shall be pre­served for production before the court in case any legal 
      proceed­ings are taken against him and the other copy shall be kept by 
      the State Board.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a sample has been 
      sent for analysis under clause (d) of sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) 
      of section 26 to any laborato­ry mentioned therein, the Government 
      analyst referred to in the said sub-section (4) shall analyse the sample 
      and submit a report in the prescribed form of the result of the analysis 
      in tripli­cate to the State Board which shall comply with the 
      provisions of sub-section (2).  
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any cost incurred in 
      getting any sample analysed at the request of the occupier or his agent as 
      provided in clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 26 or when he 
      wilfully absents him­self or refuses to sign the marked and sealed 
      container or con­tainers of sample of emission under sub-section (4) 
      of that section, shall be payable by such occupier or his agent and in 
      case of default the same shall be recoverable from him as arrears of land 
      revenue or of public demand.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    State Air Laboratory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by noti­fication in the Official Gazette,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> establish one or 
      more State Air Laboratories; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> specify one or more 
      laboratories or institutes as State Air Laboratories to carry out the 
      functions entrusted to the State Air Laboratory under this Act. 

</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The State Government may, after consultation with the State Board, make 
    rules prescribing—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the functions of 
      the State Air Laboratory;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the procedure for 
      the submission to the said Laboratory of samples of air or emission for 
      analysis or tests, the form of the Laboratory’s report thereon and the 
      fees payable in respect of such report;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> such other matters 
      as may be necessary or expedient to enable that Laboratory to carry out 
      its functions.
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Analysts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    such persons as it thinks fit and having the prescribed qualifications to be 
    Government analysts for the purpose of analysis of samples of air or 
    emission sent for analysis to any laboratory established or specified under 
    sub-section (1) of section 28.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of section 14, the State Board may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, and with the approval of the State 
    Government, appoint such persons as it thinks fit and having the prescribed 
    qualifications to be Board analysts for the purpose of analysis of samples 
    of air or emis­sion sent for analysis to any laboratory established or 
    recog­nised under section 17.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Reports of analysts.—Any 
    document purporting to be a report signed by a Government analyst or, as the 
    case may be, a State Board analyst may be used as evidence of the facts 
    stated therein in any proceeding under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    person aggrieved by an order made by the State Board under this Act may, 
    within thirty days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, 
    prefer an appeal to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the Appellate 
    Au­thority) as the State Government may think fit to constitute:
 

    Provided that the Appellate Authority may entertain the appeal after the 
    expiry of the said period of thirty days if such au­thority is satisfied 
    that the appellant was prevented by suffi­cient cause from filing the appeal 
    in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Appellate Authority shall consist of a single person or three persons as 
    the State Government may think fit to be ap­pointed by the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The form and the manner in which an appeal may be preferred under 
    sub-section (1), the fees payable for such appeal and the procedure to be 
    followed by the Appellate Authority shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On 
    receipt of an appeal preferred under sub-section (1), the Appellate 
    Authority shall, after giving the appellant and the State Board an 
    opportunity of being heard, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as 
    possible.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>31A</number> 
    Power to give directions.—Notwithstanding anything con­tained in any 
    other law, but subject to the provisions of this Act and to any directions 
    that the Central Government may give in this behalf, a Board may, in the 
    exercise of its powers and performance of its functions under this Act, 
    issue any directions in writing to any person, officer or authority, and 
    such person, officer or authority shall be bound to comply with such 
    direc­tions.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that the power to issue 
    directions under this section includes the power to direct—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number> the closure, 
      prohibition or regulation of any industry, operation or process; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> the stoppage or 
      regulation of supply of electricity, water or any other service.]
 

 
COMMENTS
 
The Powers under section 31A 
      are in addition to section 17. Section 17 of the Act is not exhaustive, 
      therefore the general powers to issue directions were also conferred on 
      the Board; Bihar State Pollution Control Board v. Hiranand Stone 
      Works, AIR 2005 Pat 62.
 

</section>




 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[<number>31B</number> Appeal to National Green Tribunal. </title>—Any person aggrieved by an order or decision of the Appellate Authority under section 31, made on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.] 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Contributions by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make in each financial year such contributions to the State 
    Boards as it may think necessary to enable the State Boards to perform their 
    functions under this Act
 

    Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any 

    1[State Pollution 
    Control Board ] consti­tuted under section 4 of the Water (Prevention and 
    Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), which is empowered by that Act 
    to expend money from its fund thereunder also for performing its functions, 
    under any law for the time being in force relating to the preven­tion, 
    control or abatement of air pollution.




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Fund of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every State Board shall have its own fund for the purposes of this Act and 
    all sums which may from time to time, be paid to it by the Central 
    Government and all other re­ceipts (by way of contributions, if any, from 
    the State Govern­ment, fees, gifts, grants, donations, benefactions or 
    otherwise) of that Board shall be carried to the fund of the Board and all 
    payments by the Board shall be made therefrom.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every State Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its 
    functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated as expenditure 
    payable out of the fund of that Board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall apply to any <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[State 
    Pollution Control Board] constituted under section 4 of the Water 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), which is 
    empowered by that Act to expend money from its fund thereunder also for 
    performing its functions, under any law for the time being in force relating 
    to the prevention, control or abatement of air pollution.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>33A</number> 
    Borrowing powers of Board.—A Board may, with the consent of, or in 
    accordance with the terms of any general or special authority given to it 
    by, the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, 
    borrow money from any source by way of loans or issue of bonds, debentures 
    or such other instru­ments, as it may deem fit, for discharging all or any 
    of its functions under this Act.]





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Budget.—The 
    Central Board or, as the case may be, the State Board shall, during each 
    financial year, prepare, in such form and at such time as may be prescribed, 
    a budget in respect of the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated 
    receipt and expenditure under this Act and copies thereof shall be forwarded 
    to the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>35</number> 
    Annual Report. —
<section><number>1</number> The Central Board shall, during each financial year, 
    prepare, in such form as may be prescribed, an annual report giving full 
    account of its activities under this Act during the previous financial year 
    and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government within four 
    months from the last date of the previous financial year and that Government 
    shall cause every such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament 
    within nine months of the last date of the previous financial year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every State Board shall, during each financial year, prepare, in such form 
    as may be prescribed, an annual report giving full account of its activities 
    under this Act during the previous financial year and copies thereof shall 
    be forwarded to the State Government within four months from the last date 
    of the previous financial year and that Government shall cause every such 
    report to be laid before the State Legislature within a period of nine 
    months from the last date of the previous financial year.]





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Board shall, in relation to its functions under this Act, maintain 
    proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement 
    of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government or, 
    as the case may be, the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The accounts of the Board shall be audited by an auditor duly qualified to 
    act as an auditor of companies under section 226 of the Companies Act, 1956 
    (1 of 1956).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The said auditor shall be appointed by Central Government or, as the case 
    may be, the State Government on the advice of the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every auditor appointed to audit the accounts of the Board under this Act 
    shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected 
    vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of 
    the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Every such auditor shall send a copy of his report together with an audited 
    copy of the accounts to the Central Government or, as the case may be, the 
    State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    The Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the 
    audit report under sub-section (5), cause the same to be laid before both 
    Houses of Parliament.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    The State Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the audit 
    report under sub-section (5), cause the same to be laid before the State 
    Legislature.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>37</number> 
    Failure to comply with the provisions of section 21 or section 22 or with 
    the directions issued under section 31A.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever fails to comply 
    with the provisions of section 21 or section 22 or directions issued under 
    section 31A, shall, in respect of each such failure, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year and six months 
    but which may extend to six years and with fine, and in case the failure 
    continues, with an additional fine which may extend to five thousand rupees 
    for every day during which such failure continues after the conviction for 
    the first such failure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the failure referred to in sub-section (1) continues beyond a period of one 
    year after the date of conviction, the offender shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two years but which may 
    extend to seven years and with fine.]




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number> Penalties for certain 
      acts.—Whoever—
 
 <section><number>a</number> 
        destroys, pulls down, removes, injures or defaces any pillar, post or 
        stake fixed in the ground or any notice or other matter put up, 
        inscribed or placed, by or under the authority of the Board, 
        or
 </section><section><number>b</number> 
        obstructs any person acting under the orders or directions of the Board 
        from exercising his powers and performing his functions under this Act, 
        or
 </section><section><number>c</number> 
        damages any works or property belonging to the Board, 
        or
 </section><section><number>d</number> fails 
        to furnish to the Board or any officer or other employ­ee of the 
        Board any information required by the Board or such officer or other 
        employee for the purpose of this Act, or
 </section><section><number>e</number> fails 
        to intimate the occurrence of the emission of air pollutants into the 
        atmosphere in excess of the standards laid down by the State Board or 
        the apprehension of such occurrence, to the State Board and other 
        prescribed authorities or agencies as required under sub-section (1) of 
        section 23, or
 </section><section><number>f</number> in 
        giving any information which he is required to give under this Act, 
        makes a statement which is false in any material par­ticular, 
        or
 </section><section><number>g</number> for 
        the purpose of obtaining any consent under section 21, makes a statement 
        which is false in any material particular,
 shall be 
        punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months 
        or with fine which may extend to 1[ten thousand rupees] or with 
        both.</section>



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[<number>39</number> 
    Penalty for contravention of certain provisions of the Act.—Whoever 
    contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or any order or direction 
    issued thereunder, for which no penalty has been elsewhere provided in this 
    Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    three months or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with 
    both, and in the case of continuing contravention, with an additional fine 
    which may extend to five thousand rupees for every day during which such 
    contravention continues after conviction for the first such contravention.]





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who, at the time the offence was committed, was directly in charge 
    of, and was respon­sible to, the company for the conduct of the business of 
    the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and pun­ished 
    accordingly:
 

    Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such 
    person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the 
    offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
    diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> “company” means any 
      body corporate, and includes a firm or other association of individuals; 
      and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> “director”, in 
      relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Offences by Government Departments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of 
    Government, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    of­fence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly:
 

    Provided that nothing contained in this section shall render such Head of 
    the Department liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a Department of Government and it is 
    proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance 
    of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any officer, other 
    than the Head of the Department, such officer shall also be deemed to be 
    guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecu­tion or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
    Government or any officer of the Government or any member or any officer or 
    other employee of the Board in respect of anything which is done or intended 
    to be done in good faith in pursuance of this Act or the rules made 
    thereunder.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>43</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No court shall take cognizance of any 
    offence under this Act except on a complaint made by—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> a Board or any 
      officer authorised in this behalf by it; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> any person who has 
      given notice of not less than sixty days, in the manner prescribed, of the 
      alleged offence and of his intention to make a complaint to the Board or 
      officer authorised as aforesaid,
 
and no court inferior to that of a 
      Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall 
      try any offence punishable under this Act.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a complaint has been made under clause (b) of sub-section (1), the 
    Board shall, on demand by such person, make available the relevant reports 
    in its possession to that person:
 

    Provided that the Board may refuse to make any such report avail­able to 
    such person if the same is, in its opinion, against the public interest.]




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Members, officers and employees of Board to be public serv­ants. 
    —All the members and all officers and other employees of a Board when acting 
    or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act or 
    the rules made thereunder shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
    meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Reports and returns.—The 
    Central Board shall, in relation to its functions under this Act, furnish to 
    the Central Government, and a State Board shall, in relation to its 
    functions under this Act, furnish to the State Government and to the Central 
    Board such reports, returns, statistics, accounts and other information as 
    that Government, or, as the case may be, the Central Board may, from time to 
    time, require.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Bar of jurisdiction.—No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which an Appellate Authority constituted under this 
    Act is empow­ered by or under this Act to determine, and no injunction shall 
    be granted by any court or other authority in respect of any action taken or 
    to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.

 
 
In respect of any matter 
      which an Appellate Authority is empowered, Civil Court has no jurisdiction 
      to entertain any suit and no injunction shall be granted in respect of any 
      action taken or to be taken by the Authority concerned; A.R. Ponnusamy
      v. Thoppalam, AIR 2004 Mad 147.


 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Power of State Government to supersede State Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the State Government is of opinion—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> that a State Board 
      constituted under this Act has persistent­ly made default in the 
      performance of the functions imposed on it by or under this Act, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> that circumstances 
      exist which render it necessary in the public interest so to do,
 
the State Government may, by notification in 
      the Official Ga­zette, supersede the State Board for such period, not 
      exceeding six months, as may be specified in the notification:
 

      Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-sec­tion for 
      the reasons mentioned in clause (a), the State Govern­ment shall give a 
      reasonable opportunity to the State Board to show cause why it should not 
      be superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, 
      of the State Board.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Upon the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the 
    State Board,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> all the members 
      shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> all the powers, 
      functions and duties which may, by or under this Act, be exercised, 
      performed or discharged by the State Board shall, until the State Board is 
      reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised, performed or discharged 
      by such person or persons as the State Government may direct;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> all property owned 
      or controlled by the State Board shall, until the Board is reconstituted 
      under sub-section (3), vest in the State Government.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the State Govern­ment may—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> extend the period 
      of supersession for such further term, not exceeding six months, as it may 
      consider necessary; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> reconstitute the 
      State Board by a fresh nomination or ap­pointment, as the case may be, and 
      in such case any person who vacated his office under clause (a) of 
      sub-section (2) shall also be eligible for nomination or appointment:
 

      Provided that the State Government may at any time before the expiration 
      of the period of supersession, whether originally specified under 
      sub-section (1) or as extended under this sub-section, take action under 
      clause (b) of this sub-section.
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Special provision in the case of supersession of the Central Board or the 
    State Boards constituted under the Water (Prevention and Control of 
    Pollution) Act, 1974.—Where 
    the Central Board or any State Board constituted under the Water (Prevention 
    and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), is superseded by the 
    Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, under that 
    Act, all the powers, functions and duties of the Central Board or such State 
    Board under this Act shall be exercised, preformed or discharged during the 
    period of such supersession by the person or persons, exercising, preforming 
    or discharging the powers, functions and duties of the Central Board or such 
    State Board under the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 
    (6 of 1974), during such period.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Dissolution of State Boards constituted under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As and when the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
    1974), comes into force in any State and the State Government constitutes a
    

    1[State Pollution 
    Control Board] under that Act, the State Board constituted by the State 
    Government under this Act shall stand dissolved and the Board 
    first-mentioned shall exercise the powers and perform the functions of the 
    Board second-mentioned in that State.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    the dissolution of the State Board constituted under this Act,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> all the members 
      shall vacate their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> all moneys and 
      other property of whatever kind (including the fund of the State Board) 
      owned by, or vested in, the State Board, immediately before such 
      dissolution, shall stand transferred to and vest in the <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[State Pollution Control 
      Board];
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> every officer and 
      other employee serving under the State Board immediately before such 
      dissolution shall be transferred to and become an officer or other 
      employee of the <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[State Pollution Control 
      Board] and hold office by the same tenure and at the same remuneration and 
      on the same terms and conditions of service as he would have held the same 
      if the State Board constituted under this Act has not been dissolved and 
      shall continue to do so unless and until such tenure, remu­neration and 
      terms and conditions of service are duly altered by the <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[State Pollution Control 
      Board]:
 
Provided that the 
      tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions of service of any such 
      officer or other employee shall not be altered to his disadvantage without 
      the previous sanction of the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> all liabilities and 
      obligations of the State Board of whatev­er kind, immediately before such 
      dissolution, shall be deemed to be the liabilities or obligations, as the 
      case may be, of the <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[State Pollution Control 
      Board] and any proceeding or cause of action, pending or existing 
      imme­diately before such dissolution by or against the State Board 
      constituted under this Act in relation to such liability or obligation may 
      be continued and enforced by or against the <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[State Pollution Control 
      Board.]
</subsection>




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Power to amend the Schedule.—[Rep. 
    by the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Amendment Act, 1987 (47 of 
    1987), sec. 22 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988)].

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Maintenance of register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every State Board shall maintain a register containing particulars of the 
    persons to whom consent has been granted under section 21, the standards for 
    emission laid down by it in relation to each such consent and such other 
    particulars as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The register maintained under sub-section (1) shall be open to inspection at 
    all reasonable hours by any person interested in or affected by such 
    standards for emission or by any other person authorised by such person in 
    this behalf.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Effect of other laws.—Save 
    as otherwise provided by or under the Atomic Energy Act, 1962 (33 of 1962), 
    in relation to radioactive air pollution the provisions of this Act shall 
    have effect notwith­standing anything inconsistent therewith contained in 
    any enactment other than this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, in consultation with the Central Board, by 
    notifi­cation in the Official Gazette, make rules in respect of the 
    following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the intervals and 
      the time and place at which meetings of the Central Board or any committee 
      thereof shall be held and the procedure to be followed at such meetings, 
      including the quorum necessary for the transaction of business thereat, 
      under sub-section (1) of section 10 and under sub-section (2) of section 
      11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the fees and 
      allowances to be paid to the members of a committee of the Central Board, 
      not being members of the Board, under sub-section (3) of section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the manner in which 
      and the purposes for which persons may be associated with the Central 
      Board under sub-section (1) of sec­tion 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the fees and 
      allowances to be paid under sub-section (3) of section 12 to persons 
      associated with the Central Board under sub-section (1) of 
      section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the functions to be 
      performed by the Central Board under clause (j) of sub-section (2) of 
      section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[<number>f</number>  the form in which and 
      the time within which the budget of the Central Board may be prepared and 
      forwarded to the Central Government under section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ff</number> the form in which 
      the annual report of the Central Board may be prepared under section 35;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the form in which 
      the accounts of the Central Board may be maintained under sub-section (1) 
      of section 36.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
    is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
    one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
    of the ses­sion immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
    be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Power of State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (3), the State Government may, by 
    noti­fication in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes 
    of this Act in respect of matters not falling within the purview of section 
    53.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
 <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> the qualifications, 
      knowledge and experience of scientif­ic, engineering or management aspects 
      of pollution control re­quired for appointment as member-secretary of a 
      State Board constituted under the Act;]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>36</footcitenum><number>aa</number>]  
      the terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other members 
      (other than the member-secretary) of the State Board constituted under 
      this Act under sub-section (7) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the intervals and 
      the time and place at which meetings of the State Board or any committee 
      thereof shall be held and the procedure to be followed at such meetings, 
      including the quorum necessary for the transaction of business thereat, 
      under sub-section (1) of section 10 and under sub-section (2) of section 
      11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the fees and 
      allowances to be paid to the members of a commit­tee of the State Board, 
      not being members of the Board under sub-section (3) of section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the manner in which 
      and the purposes for which persons may be associated with the State Board 
      under sub-section (1) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the fees and 
      allowances to be paid under sub-section (3) of section 12 to persons 
      associated with the State Board under sub-section (1) of 
      section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> the terms and 
      conditions of service of the member-secretary of a State Board constituted 
      under this Act under sub-section (1) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the powers and 
      duties to be exercised and discharged by the member-secretary of a State 
      Board under sub-section (2) of sec­tion 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> the conditions 
      subject to which a State Board may appoint such officers and other 
      employees as it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its 
      functions under sub-section (3) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> the conditions 
      subject to which a State Board may appoint a consultant under sub-section 
      (5) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> the functions to be 
      performed by the State Board under clause (i) of sub-section (1) of 
      section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> the manner in which 
      any area or areas may be declared as air pollution control area or areas 
      under sub-section (1) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> the form of 
      application for the consent of the State Board, the fees payable therefor, 
      the period within which such applica­tion shall be made and the 
      particulars it may contain, under sub-section (2) of section 21;   

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> the procedure to be 
      followed in respect of an inquiry under sub- 
      section (3) of section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number> the authorities or 
      agencies to whom information under sub-section (1) of section 23 shall be 
      furnished;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>  the manner in 
      which samples of air or emission may be taken under sub-section (1) of 
      section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number> the form of the 
      notice referred to in sub-section (3) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number> the form of the 
      report of the State Board analyst under sub-section (1) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number> the form of the 
      report of the Government analyst under sub-section (3) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number> the functions of 
      the State Air Laboratory, the procedure for the submission to the said 
      Laboratory of samples of air or emission for analysis or tests, the form 
      of Laboratory’s report thereon, the fees payable in respect of such report 
      and other matters as may be necessary or expedient to enable that 
      Laboratory to carry out its functions, under sub-section (2) of section 
      28;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number> the qualifications 
      required for Government analysts under sub-section (1) of section 29;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number> the qualifications 
      required for State Board analysts under sub-section (2) of section 29;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> the form and the 
      manner in which appeals may be preferred, the fees payable in respect of 
      such appeals and the procedure to be followed by the Appellate Authority 
      in disposing of the ap­peals under sub-section (3) of section 31;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[<number>w</number> 
      the form in which and the time within which the budget of the State Board 
      may be prepared and forwarded to the State Gov­ernment under section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ww</number> the form in which 
      the annual report of the State Board may be prepared under section 35;]
 <subsubsection>
<number>x</number>  the form in which 
      the accounts of the State Board may be maintained under sub-section (1) of 
      section 36;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>xx</number>  
      the manner in which notice of intention to make a com­plaint shall be 
      given under section 43;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>y</number> the particulars 
      which the register maintained under section 51 may contain;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>z</number> any other matter 
      which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    After the first constitution of the State Board, no rule with respect to any 
    of the matters referred to in sub-section (2) (other than those referred to
    

    5[in clause (aa)] 
    thereof), shall be made, varied, amended or repealed without consulting that 
    Board.








 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    The Air (PREVENTION AND  

    CONTROL OF POLLUTION) Act, 1981
 



 



 

THE 
    SCHEDULE
 


[Omitted 
    by the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Amendment Act, 1987 (47 of 
    1987) sec. 25 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988)].
 



 



 



 




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>    
    Came into force on 16-5-1981 vide G.S.R. 351(E), dated 15th May, 
    1981, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), p. 944.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Ins. by Act 47 of 1987, sec.
2 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 2, for "Central Board for the
Prevention and Control of Water Pollution".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 2, for clause (m) (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 2, for "State Board for the Prevention
and Control of Water Pollution".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 47 of 
    1987, sec. 3, for sections 3 and 4 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988). Sections 3 &amp; 4, before substitution, stood as 
    under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> State Boards for the Prevention and Control 
    of Water Pollution to be State Boards for the Prevention and Control of Air 
    Pollution. —In 
    any State in which the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 
    1974, is in force and the State Government has constituted for that State a 
    State Board for the Prevention and Control of Water Pollution under section 
    4 of that Act, such State Board shall be deemed to be the State Board for 
    the Prevention and Control of Air Pollution constituted under section  5 of 
    this Act and accordingly that State Board for the Prevention and Control of 
    Water Pollution shall, without prejudice to the exercise and performance of 
    its powers and functions under that Act, exercise the powers and perform the 
    functions of the State Board for the Prevention and Control of Air Pollution 
    under this Act.”</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 4, for “State Board for the Prevention and Control 
    of Water Pollution” (Effective date to be notified).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 4, for clause (f) (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>     The words "but not for more than two terms" omitted by Act 47 of 
    1987, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>     Subs. 
      by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 6, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 
      1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>    Ins. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> 
 Section 18 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>
 Ins. by Act 
    47 of 1987, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 9, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   The 
    words "for the purpose of any industry specified in the schedule" omitted by 
    Act 47 of 1987, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 9, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Ins. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   The 
    words "for the purpose of any industry specified in the schedule" omitted by 
    Act 47 of 1987, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> 
 Ins. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 
      1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> The words "air pollution control" omitted by Act 47 of 1987, 
sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   The 
    words “carrying on any industry specified in the Schedule and every person” 
    omitted by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> 
 Ins. by Act 47 of 
    1987, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Ins. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 15, for "State Board for the Prevention and Control 
    of Water Pollution" (Effective date to be notified).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>    Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 15, for "State Board for the Prevention and Control 
    of Water Pollution".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> 
 Ins. by Act 47 of 
    1987, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> 
 
    Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 17, for section 35 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>     
    Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 18, for section 37 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> 
 Subs. by Act 47 of 
      1987, sec. 19, for “five hundred rupees” (w.e.f. 
      1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>
 
Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, 
    sec. 20, for section 39 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>     
    Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 21, for section 43 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 15, for “State Board for the Prevention and Control 
    of Water Pollution” (Effective date to be notified).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>     
    Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 23, for clause (f) (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> 
 
Ins. by Act 47 of 1987, 
    sec. 24 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> 
 Clause (a) 
    renumbered as clause (aa) by Act 47 of 1987, sec. 24 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> 
 
Subs. by Act 47 of 1987, 
    sec. 24, for clause (w) (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> 
 
Ins. by Act 47 of 1987, 
    sec. 24 (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> 
 Subs. by Act 47 of 
    1987, sec. 24,  for ‘‘in clause (a)” (w.e.f. 1-4-1988).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>