<act><title>


The Debts Recovery Tribunal (Procedure for 
    appointment 
    as presiding Officer of the Tribunal) Rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Debts Recovery Tribunal (Procedure for Appointment 
    as Presiding Officer of the Tribunal) Rules, 1998.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Recovery 
    of Debts Due to Banks and Financial Institutions Act, 1993 (51 of 1993);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Tribunal” means the 
    Debts Recovery Tribunal established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of 
    the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Presiding Officer” 
    means a person appointed as Presiding Officer of a Tribunal under 
    sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Reserve Bank” means the 
    Reserve Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of 
    India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    all other words and 
    expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall 
    have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.   
 
  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Method of appointment under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of appointment to the post of a Presiding Officer, there shall be a Selection Committee consisting of— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> The Chief Justice of India or a Judge of the Supreme Court of India as nominated by the Chief Justice of India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance  
    (Department of Economic Affairs); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Law and Justice; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the Governor, of the Reserve Bank or the Deputy Governor of the Reserve Bank nominated by the Governor of the Reserve Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>v</number> Secretary or Additional Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance, Department of Financial Services.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chief Justice of India or the Judge of the Supreme Court shall be the Chairman of the Selection Committee. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any three members of the Committee including the Chairman shall form a quorum for meeting of the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Selection Committee may devise its own procedure for selecting a candidate for appointment as Presiding Officer. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The Selection Committee shall recommend persons for appointment as Presiding Officer,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> from amongst the persons on the list of candidates prepared by the Ministry of Finance after inviting applications; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> from amongst judicial officers nominated by a High Court.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government shall on the basis of the recommendations of the Selection Committee make a list of persons selected for appointment as Presiding Officer and the said list shall be valid for a period of two years. The appointment of a Presiding Officer shall be made from the list so prepared. 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Medical 
    Fitness.—No person shall be 
    appointed as a Presiding Officer unless he is deelared medically fit by a 
    Medical Board to be constituted by the Central Government for the purpose 
    unless he has already been declared fit by an equivalent authority.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to the interpretation of these rules the same shall be 
    referred to the Central Government for its decision.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Saving.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall affect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other 
    concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled 
    Tribes, Other Backward Classes, ex-servicemen and other special categories 
    of persons, in accordance with the orders issued by the Central Government 
    from time to time in this regard.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Oaths of 
    office and secrecy.—Every person 
    appointed to be Presiding Officer under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 4 shall, 
    before entering upon his office, make and subscribe an oath of office and 
    secrecy in the Forms annexed to these rules.
  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Debts Recovery Tribunal (Procedure for appointment  

    as presiding Officer of the Tribunal) Rules, 1998
 

 
 



    Annexure
 


Form-I
 


(See rule 7)
 



    Form of oath of office for Presiding Officer of the Debts Recovery Tribunal 
 



    “I.............(Name of the Presiding Officer) having been appointed as 
    Presiding Officer do solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of God that I will 
    faithfully and conscientiously discharge my duties as Presiding Officer to 
    the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment, without fear or favour, 
    affection or ill will.
 




    Name of the Presiding officer  

    debts recovery tribunal
 

 
 


Form-II
 


(See rule 7)
 



    Form of oath of secrecy for Presiding Officer of the Debts Recovery Tribunal
 



    “I,.............(Name of the Presiding Officer) having been appointed as 
    Presiding Officer do solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of God that I will 
    not directly or indirectly communicate or reveal to any person or persons 
    any matter which shall be brought under my consideration or shall become 
    known to me as Presiding Officer of said Debts Recovery Tribunal except as 
    may be required for the due discharge of my duties as the Presiding 
    Officer.”
 




    name of the presiding officer  

    Debts recovery tribunal
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 3(E), dated 4th January, 2011, for clause (v) (w.e.f. 5-1-2011). Clause (v), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 646(E), dated 2nd August, 2000 (w.e.f. 2-8-2000).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>