<act><title>


The Municipal Solid Wastes 
(management and Handling) 
Rules, 20001</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Municipal Solid Wastes (Management and Handling) 
Rules, 2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in these rules, they shall come into force on the date of their 
publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number>
Application.—These rules shall apply to every municipal authority 
responsible for collection, segregation, storage, transportation, processing and 
disposal of municipal solid wastes.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  “anaerobic 
digestion” means a controlled process involving microbial decomposition of 
organic matter in the absence of oxygen;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  
“authorization” means the consent given by the Board or Committee to the 
“operator of a facility”;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  
“biodegradable substance” means a substance that can be degraded by 
micro-organisms;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  
“biomethanation” means a process which entails enzymatic decomposition of the 
organic matter by microbial action to produce methane rich biogas;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  “collection” 
means lifting and removal of solid wastes from collection points or any other 
location;
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  “composting” 
means a controlled process involving microbial decomposition of organic matter;
 </section><section>
      <number>vii</number>  “demolition 
and construction waste” means wastes from building materials debris and rubble 
resulting from construction, re-modelling, repair and demolition operation;
 </section><section>
     <number>viii</number>  “disposal” 
means final disposal of municipal solid wastes in terms of the specified 
measures to prevent contamination of ground water, surface water and ambient air 
quality;
 </section><section>
       <number>ix</number>  “Form” means 
a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>x</number>  “generator of 
wastes” means persons or establishments generating municipal solid wastes;
 </section><section>
       <number>xi</number>  “landfilling” 
means disposal of residual solid wastes on land in a facility designed with 
protective measures against pollution of groundwater, surface water and air 
fugitive dust, wind-blow litter, bad odour, fire hazard, bird menace, pests or 
rodents, greenhouse gas emissions, slope instability and erosion;
 <subsection>
      <number>xii</number>  “leachate” 
means liquid that seeps through solid wastes or other medium and has extracts of 
dissolved or suspended material from it;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>xiii</number>  “lysimeter” 
is a device used to measure rate of movement of water through or from a soil 
layer or is used to collect percolated water for quality analysis;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xiv</number>  “municipal 
authority” means Municipal Corporation, Municipality, Nagar Palika, Nagar Nigam, 
Nagar Panchayat, Municipal Council including notified area committee (NAC) or 
any other local body constituted under the relevant statutes and, where the 
management and handling of municipal solid waste is entrusted to such agency;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>xv</number>  “municipal 
solid waste” includes commercial and residential wastes generated in a municipal 
or notified areas in either solid or semi-solid form excluding industrial 
hazardous wastes but including treated bio-medical wastes;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xvi</number>  “operator of a 
facility” means a person who owns or operates a facility for collection, 
segregation, storage, transportation, processing and disposal of municipal solid 
wastes and also includes any other agency appointed as such by the municipal 
authority for the management and handling of municipal solid wastes in the 
respective areas;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xvii</number>  
“pelletisation” means a process whereby pellets are prepared which are small 
cubes or cylindrical pieces made out of solid wastes and includes fuel pellets 
which are also referred as refuse derived fuel;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>xviii</number>  “processing” 
means the process by which solid wastes are transformed into new or recycled 
products;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xix</number>  “recycling” 
means the process of transforming segregated solid wastes into raw materials for 
producing new products, which may or may not be similar to the original 
products;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>xx</number>  “Schedule” 
means a schedule appended to these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xxi</number>  “segregation” 
means to separate the municipal solid wastes into the groups of organic, 
inorganic, recyclables and hazardous wastes;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>xxii</number>  “State Board 
or the Committee” means the State Pollution Control Board of a State, or as the 
case may be, the Pollution Control Committee of a Union Territory;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>xxiii</number>  “storage” 
means the temporary containment of municipal solid wastes in a manner so as to 
prevent littering, attraction to vectors, stray animals and excessive foul odour;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>xxiv</number>  
“transportation” means conveyance of municipal solid wastes from place to place 
hygienically through specially designed transport system so as to prevent foul 
odour, littering, unsightly conditions and accessibility to vectors;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>xxv</number>  “vadose water” 
water which occurs between the ground, surface and the water table that is the 
unsaturated zone;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>xxvi</number>  
“vermicomposting” is a process of using earthworms for conversion of 
bio-degradable wastes into compost.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Responsibility of 
municipal authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every municipal authority shall, within the territorial area of the 
municipality, be responsible for the implementation of the provisions of these 
rules, and for any infrastructure development for collection, storage, 
segregation, transportation, processing and disposal of municipal solid wastes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The municipal 
authority or an operator of a facility shall make an application in Form I, for 
grant of authorization for setting up waste processing and disposal facility 
including landfills from the State Board or the Committee in order to comply 
with the implementation programme laid down in Schedule I.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The municipal 
authority shall comply with these rules as per the implementation schedule laid 
down in Schedule I.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The municipal 
authority shall furnish its annual report in Form II,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to the 
Secretary-incharge of the Department of Urban Development of the concerned State 
or as the case may be of the Union Territory, in case of a metropolitan city; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to the 
District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner concerned in case of all other 
towns and cities,
 
with a copy to the State 
Board or the Committee on or before the 30th day of June every year.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Responsibility of 
the State Government and the Union Territory Administrations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Secretary-incharge of the Department of Urban Development of the concerned 
State or the Union Territory, as the case may be, shall have the overall 
responsibility for the enforcement of the provisions of these rules in the 
metropolitan cities.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The District 
Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner of the concerned district shall have the 
overall responsibility for the enforcement of the provisions of these rules 
within the territorial limits of their jurisdiction.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Responsibility of 
the Central Pollution Control Board and the State Board or the Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Board or the Committee shall monitor the compliance of the standards 
regarding groundwater, ambient air, leachate quality and the compost quality 
including incineration standards as specified under Schedules II, III and IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Board or the 
Committee, after the receipt of application from the municipal authority or the 
operator of a facility in Form I, for grant of authorization for setting up 
waste processing and disposal facility including landfills, shall examine the 
proposal taking into consideration the views of other agencies like the State 
Urban Development Department, the Town and Council Planning Department, Air Port 
or Air Base Authority, the Ground Water Board or any such other agency prior to 
issuing the authorization.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Board or the 
Committee shall issue the authorization in Form III to the municipal authority 
or an operator of a facility within forty-five days stipulating compliance 
criteria and standards as specified in Schedules II, III and IV including such 
other conditions, as may be necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The authorization 
shall be valid for a given period and after the validity is over, a fresh 
authorization shall be required.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central Pollution 
Control Board shall co-ordinate with the State Boards and the Committees with 
particular reference to implementation and review of standards and guidelines 
and compilation of monitoring data.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Management of 
municipal solid wastes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any municipal solid waste generated in a city or a town, shall be managed and 
handled in accordance with the compliance criteria and the procedure laid down 
in Schedule II.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The waste processing 
and disposal facilities to be set up by the municipal authority on their own or 
through an operator of a facility shall meet the specifications and standards as 
specified in Schedules III and IV.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Annual Reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Boards and the Committees shall prepare and submit to the Central 
Pollution Control Board an annual report with regard to the implementation of 
these rules by the 15th September every year in Form IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Pollution 
Control Board shall prepare the consolidated annual review report on management 
of municipal solid wastes and forward it to the Central Government alongwith its 
recommendations before the 15th December every year.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Accident Reporting.—When 
an accident occurs at any municipal solid wastes collection, segregation, 
storage, processing, treatment and disposal facility or landfill site or during 
the transportation of such wastes, the municipal authority shall forthwith 
report the accident in Form V to the Secretary incharge of the Urban Development 
Department in metropolitan cities, and to District Collector or Deputy 
Commissioner in all other cases.
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>