<act><title>


THE STANDARDs OF WEIGHTs AND MEASURES (GENERAL) 
RULES, 19871</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Standards of Weights and Measures (General) 
Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their notification in the Official Gazette.
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1976 (60 of 1976);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “protection” 
means the utilisation of any weight or measure or any reading obtained with the 
help of any weight or measure, for the purpose of determining whether or not 
any step is required to be taken to safeguard the well-being of any human being 
or animal or to protect any commodity vegetation or thing, whether individually 
or collectively;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “Schedule” 
means a Schedule appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “section” 
means a section of Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  words and 
expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined in the Act shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Reference Standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every reference standard weight shall conform, as regards denomination, 
material used in construction, and design, to the specifications laid down in 
Part I of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any reference standard weight, on verification 
or re-verification after adjustment, shall be such as is specified in Part I of 
the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every reference 
standard metre bar shall conform, as regards material used in construction, and 
design, to the specifications laid down in Part II of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any reference standard metre bar, on 
verification or re-verification, shall be such as is specified in Part II of 
First Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Secondary Standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every secondary standard weight shall conform, as regards denomination, 
material used in construction, and design, to the specification laid down in 
Part I of the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any secondary standard weight, on verification 
or re-verification after adjustment, shall be such as is specified in Part I of 
the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every secondary 
standard metre bar shall conform, as regards material used in construction, and 
design, to the specification laid down in Part II of the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any secondary standard metre bar, on 
verification or re-verification, shall be such as is specified in Part II of 
Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any secondary standard metre bar, on 
verification or re-verification, shall be such as is specified in 
Part II of the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every secondary 
standard capacity measure shall conform, as regards denomination, material used 
in construction, and design, to the specifications laid down in Part III of the 
Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any secondary standard capacity measure, on 
verification or reverification after adjustment, shall be such as is specified 
in Part III of the Second Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Working Standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every working standard weight shall conform, as regards denomination, material 
used in construction, design, to the specifications laid down in Part I of 
Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any working standard weight, on verification or 
re-verification after adjustment, shall be such as is specified in Part I of 
the Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every working 
standard metre bar shall conform, as regards material used in construction, and 
design, to the specification laid down in Part II of the Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any working standard meter 
bar, on verification or re-verification, shall be such as is specified in Part 
II of Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every working 
standard capacity measure shall conform, as regards denomination, material used 
in construction, and design, to the specifications laid down in Part III of the 
Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of any working standard capacity measure, on 
verification or re-verification after adjustment, shall be such as is specified 
in Part III of the Third Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to specify 
any other reference, secondary or working standard measurements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any other reference standard, or secondary standard, or working standard shall 
conform as regards the denomination, material used in construction, and design, 
to such specifications as the Central Government may, from time to time, by 
notification, specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in relation to such other reference standard, or secondary 
standard, or working standard shall be such as the Central Government may, from 
time to time, by notification, specify and different maximum permissible error 
may be specified in relation to different types of reference standards, or 
secondary standards, or working standards.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Reference Standard 
Balances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A set of reference standard balances shall be maintained at every place where 
the reference standard weights are kept for the purpose of verification of 
secondary standards.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The number, types and 
specifications of such balances shall be as are specified in Part I of the 
Fourth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every reference 
standard balance shall be verified at least once in six months and shall be 
adjusted, if necessary, to make it correct within the limits of sensitivity and 
other metrological qualities as are specified in Part I of the Fourth Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Secondary Standard 
Balances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A set of secondary standard balances shall be maintained at every place where 
secondary standard weights are kept for the purpose of verification of working 
standards.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The number, types and 
specifications of such balances shall be as are specified in Part II of the 
Fourth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every reference 
standard balance shall be verified at least once in one year and shall be 
adjusted, if necessary, to make it correct within the limits of sensitivity and 
other metrological qualities as are specified in Part II of the Fourth 
Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Working Standard 
Balances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A set of working standard balances shall be maintained at every place where 
working standard weights are kept for the purpose of verification of weights 
intended to be used for transaction, or industrial production.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The number, types and 
specifications of such balances shall be as are specified in Part III of the 
Fourth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every working 
standard balance shall be verified at least once in one year and shall be 
adjusted, if necessary, to make it correct within the limits of sensitivity and 
other metrological qualities as are specified in Part III of the Fourth 
Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power to specify 
the Standard Equipment.—The 
Central Government may, by notification, specify such other standard equipment 
as it may think necessary to carry out the provisions of the Act and every such 
standard equipment shall conform, as regards the metrological qualities, to 
such specifications as the Central Government may, in the same notification or 
subsequent notification, specify.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Weights.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in these rules, every weight used or intended to be 
used,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in any 
transaction, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for 
industrial production, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  for 
protection,
 
shall conform, as regards 
physical characteristics, configuration, constructional details, materials, 
performance, tolerances and such other details, to the corresponding 
specifications laid down for such weight in the Fifth Schedule.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in respect of such weight shall be such as is specified in 
the Fifth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to the product of an industry which is required, by or under any 
law for the time being in force, to conform to any other specifications with 
regard to the matters specified in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), if, under such 
law, the product is required to conform to the specifications laid down by the 
International Organisation of Legal Metrology with regard to the matters 
aforesaid.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Measures (other 
than measuring instruments).—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every measure used or intended to be used for,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> any 
transaction, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> industrial 
production, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> protection,
 
shall conform, as regards 
physical characteristics, configuration, constructional details, materials, 
performance, tolerances and such other details, to the corresponding 
specifications laid down for such measure in the Sixth Schedule.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum 
permissible error in such measure shall be such as is specified in the 
corresponding specifications laid down for such measure in the Sixth Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Weighing and 
measuring instruments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every weighing instrument used or intended to be used,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in any 
transaction, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for 
industrial production, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  for 
protection,
 
shall conform, as regards 
physical characteristics, configuration, constructional details, materials, 
performance, tolerances and such other details, to the corresponding 
specifications laid down for such weighing instrument 

1[in headings B to 
F] of the Seventh Schedule:
 
Provided that, for a 
period of 

2[twelve years] 
from the commencement of these rules, it shall be lawful to make or manufacture 
any weighing instrument in accordance with the provisions mentioned under 
heading A of the Seventh Schedule, and every weighing instrument made or 
manufactured during the period aforesaid in accordance with the provisions of 
the said heading A shall, so long as such instruments lasts, be deemed to have 
been lawfully made or manufactured in accordance with the provisions of these 
rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every measuring 
instrument used or intended to be used,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in any 
transaction, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for 
industrial production, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  for 
protection,
 
shall conform, as regards 
physical characteristics, configuration, constructional details, materials, 
performance, tolerances and such other details, to the corresponding 
specifications laid down for such measuring instrument in the Eighth Schedule.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The maximum 
permissible error on such weighing or measuring instrument shall be such as is 
specified in the corresponding specifications laid down for such weighing or 
measuring instrument in the Seventh Schedule or as the case may be in the 
Eighth Schedule.
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Weight or measure 
for domestic use.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every weight or measure specified in the Ninth Schedule which is intended 
exclusively for domestic use or for any use other than in any transaction, or 
for protection or for industrial production, shall conform, as regards the 
metrological characteristics and qualities, configuration, constructional 
details and materials used in construction, to the corresponding specifications 
laid down in the Ninth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every manufacturer 
who manufactures any weight or measure which is not specified in the Ninth 
Schedule and which is intended exclusively for domestic use or for any use 
other than use in any transaction, or for protection or for industrial 
production, shall forward the specifications as regards the metrological 
characteristics and qualities, configuration, constructional details and 
materials used in construction, to the Director to enable him to circulate such 
specifications to the Controllers for the purpose of verification of such 
weight or measure.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Provisions 
relating to existing weights and measures.—Any 
weight or  
measure which confirms to the specifications laid down by or under any State or
 
Central law shall, if such specifications are in force at the commencement of 
these  
rules, continue to be regarded as standard weight or measure for a period of 
three years from such commencement notwithstanding that such weight or measure 
does not conform to the specifications laid down in the First to Ninth Schedule 
(both inclusive) to these rules and every such weight or measure shall be so 
modified during the period of three years aforesaid as to make them conform to 
the specifications laid down in these rules:
 
Provided that if the 
Director is satisfied that the period beyond three years is necessary for 
carrying out the modification in such weight or measure, he  
may extend the period for such further period, not exceeding one year, as he 
may  
think fit.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Procedure for 
carrying out calibration of vehicle tanks etc.—The 
procedure for carrying out calibration of vehicle tanks etc, shall be as 
is specified in the Ninth-A Schedule.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Registration of 
exporter and importer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every manufacturer or dealer of weight or measure who intends to export or 
import any weight or measure shall apply to the Director, through the 
Controller of the State in which he carries on such business, for registration 
of his name as exporter or importer or both, as the case may be, in the form 
specified in the Tenth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person carrying 
on the business of export or import or both, immediately before the 
commencement of these rules, shall, within ninety days of such commencement, 
make an application to the Director through the Controller of the State in 
which he carries on such business, for registration as an exporter or importer 
or both.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application 
received by the Controller under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), as the case may 
be, shall be forwarded by him to the Director with a report as to the 
antecedents and technical capabilities of the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall take away or abridge the right of any person referred to in sub-rule (2) 
to carry on the business of exporting or importing of any weight or measure 
until he has been informed by the Director in writing that he cannot be 
registered as an exporter or importer or both, and on receipt of such letter he 
shall stop forthwith the export or import of any weight or measure:
 
Provided that 
registration of a person carrying on, at the commencement of these rules, the 
business of exporting or importing weights or measures shall not be refused 
except after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed action.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application for 
the registration of an exporter or importer shall be submitted to the Director, 
in the manner aforesaid, together with the fee specified in the Twelfth 
Schedule, at least one month before the date on which export or import is 
proposed to be made.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The registration of a 
person as an exporter or importer shall remain effective for a period of five 
years from the date of such registration.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> On the expiry of the 
period of registration as an exporter or importer, the Director may, on the 
application of the registered exporter or importer and on payment of the 
prescribed fee, renew registration for a like period.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The registration or 
renewal of the registration of a person as an exporter or importer or both may 
be suspended or revoked before the expiry of the period of validity thereof, if 
the Director is satisfied after an inquiry, and after giving to the person 
concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard, that any statement made by 
such person in the application for registration or renewal of registration was 
false or incorrect in material particulars or that such person has contravened 
any provision of the Act or rules made thereunder or any term or condition of 
such registration.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>18</number> Conditions, etc. for 
manufacture of a weight or measure exclusively for export.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of this rule 
shall apply to weights or measures which are made or manufactured exclusively 
for the purpose of export.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No non-standard weight or 
measure shall be made or manufactured by any person unless he has obtained the 
previous permission from the Central Government:
 Provided that it shall be lawful 
for any person, who, at the commencement of these rules,—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  is bona fide carrying on the business of export of non-standard 
weights and measures, or
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  has a firm offer for the export of any non-standard weight or 
measure,
 to continue the manufacture of 
non-standard weights and measures until he is informed by the Central Government 
in writing that the permission to manufacture non-standard weight or measure 
cannot be granted to him.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every person intending to 
manufacture any non-standard weight or measure for the purpose of export shall 
make an application for permission to the Central Government on payment of a fee 
of rupees fifty for such permission authorising him to manufacture such weight 
or measure and shall in such application indicate—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  his name and full address;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  location of the factory in which such weight or measure is proposed to 
be manufactured;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  description of weight or measure proposed to be 
manufactured;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>d</number>  documentary or other evidence indicating the existence of a firm 
contract for the export aforesaid or where there is no such firm contract for 
export, documentary or other evidence indicating that there is likely to be a 
demand for the export of non-standard weight or measure.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall, 
if it is satisfied from the documentary or other evidence produced by the 
applicant or otherwise that the applicant intends bona fide to 
manufacture non-standard weight or measure for export, grant the permission 
authorising him to manufacture such weight or measure:
 Provided that the Central 
Government may, if it is satisfied that the applicant has, contravened any of 
terms and conditions of the permission or that weights or measures manufactured 
by the applicant have found their way into the Indian market or that the 
applicant had made any statement in his application for the permission which is 
false in material particulars or he had concealed some material particulars, 
cancel the permission:
 Provided further that no 
permission shall be cancelled except after giving to the applicant a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every permission granted under 
sub-rule (4) shall remain valid for a period of one year and shall be renewed 
for a like period on payment of a like fee unless the Central Government is 
satisfied that the applicant has made any statement in his application which is 
false in material particulars or that he had concealed some material particulars 
or had contravened any provision of the Act or any rule made 
thereunder:
 Provided that no order for the 
refusal to renew a licence shall be made by the Central Government except after 
giving the applicant a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed action.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every person who is granted 
permission under this rule shall submit to the Central Government, at the end of 
the calandar year, a statement as to the quantity of the non-standard weights 
and measures exported by him and the particulars of the person to whom such 
export has been made.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Prohibition on 
sale of non-standard weight or measure within the country.—No 
non-standard weight or measure made or manufactured exclusively for export 
shall be sold or otherwise distributed within the territory of India.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Maintenance of 
record in relation to non-standard weight or measure.—Every 
person who makes or manufactures any non-standard weight or measure for export 
shall maintain a monthly record of the number of such non-standard weights or 
measure manufactured by him, number of weights or measures already exported by 
him, and number of weights or measures in stock or under production. The record 
so maintained shall be open to inspection by any officer authorised by the 
Central Government in this behalf.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Sample checking of 
weight and measure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Standard weights or measures which are intended for export shall not ordinarily 
require any verification and stamping, but if the party to whom the export is 
to be made so requires, a sample checking of such weight or measure shall be 
made by such agency as the Central Government may specify in this behalf, and 
thereupon the agency so specified shall, after checking the weight or measure, 
issue a certificate indicating whether or not such weight or measure conforms 
to the requirements of the Act and the rules made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The weight or measure 
to be checked as sample under this rule shall be selected at random and proper 
records shall be maintained with regard to the sample checking so made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government shall, while specifying the agency for checking the weight or 
measure, ensure that the agency completes the checking well in time so that the 
export of the weight or measure is not delayed by reason of such checking.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Checking of 
non-standard weights and measures sample which are to be exported.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Non-standard weight or measure, which is made or manufactured exclusively for 
export, shall not ordinarily require any verification and stamping, but if the 
party to whom the export is to be made so requires, a sample checking of such 
weight or measure shall be made by such agency as the Central Government may 
specify in this behalf; and thereupon the agency so specified shall, after 
checking the weight or measure, issue a certificate indicating whether or not 
such weight or measure conforms to the specifications given by the party to 
whom the export is to be made or, where the party aforesaid has not given any 
specification, whether the weight or measure conforms to the specification laid 
down by the manufacturer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The weight or measure 
to be checked as sample under this rule shall be selected at random and proper 
records shall be maintained with regard to the sample checking so made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fee for checking 
of any non-standard weight or measure shall be,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  if it is 
similar to any standard weight or measure, equal to the fee leviable for the 
verification and stamping of such standard weight or measure; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  where such 
non-standard weight or measure is not similar to any standard weight or 
measure, the Central Government may specify such amount as fee as is 
commensurate with the labour involved in checking the non-standard weight or 
measure.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
Government shall, while specifying the agency for checking the non-standard 
weight or measure, ensure that the agency completes the checking well in time 
so that the export of such weight or measure is not delayed by reason of such 
checking.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>23</number> Permission to get manufactured 
non-standard weight or measure for scientific investigation or 
research.—Where 
the manufacture of any non-standard weight or measure is needed exclusively for 
the purpose of scientific investigation or research, the person needing such 
non-standard weight or measure shall make an application to the Central 
Government for permission to get such non-standard weight or measure 
manufactured and on receipt of such application, if the Central Government is 
satisfied that the manufacture of such non-standard weight or measure is needed 
for the purpose aforesaid, it may authorise the applicant to get the 
non-standard weight or measure needed by him manufactured by such manufacturer 
as he may think fit, and thereupon, it shall be lawful for such manufacturer to 
manufacture the said non-standard weight or measure in accordance with the 
specification given by the applicant.
 Explanation.—For the purpose of this rule, a 
non-standard weight or measure means a weight or measure which is, or is 
proposed to be manufactured in accordance with any unit of weight or measure, 
other than standard unit of weight or measure specified by or under the 
Act.</article> 

  
 <article><number>24</number> The manner of disposal of 
goods seized under this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any goods seized under 
sub-section (1) of section 29 are subject to speedy or natural decay, the 
Director or any person authorised by him in this behalf shall have the goods 
weighted or measured on a verified weighing or measuring instrument available 
with him or near the place of seizure and enter the actual weight or measure of 
the goods in a form specified by the Director for this purpose and shall obtain 
the signature of the trader or his agent or such other person who has committed 
the offence. The goods in question shall, after such weighing or measuring be 
returned to the trader or the purchaser as the case may be:
 Provided that if the trader or his 
agent or such other person (who has committed the offence) refuses to sign the 
form, the Director or the person authorised by him in this behalf shall obtain 
the signature of not less than two persons present at the time of such refusal 
by the trader or his agent or other person.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the goods seized under 
sub-section (1) are contained in a package and the package is false or does not 
conform to the provisions of the Act or any rules made thereunder and the goods 
in such package are subject to speedy or natural decay, the Director or any 
person authorised by him in this behalf, so far as may be, may dispose of the 
goods in such package in accordance with the provisions of sub-rule 
(1).
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the goods seized under 
sub-rule (1) are not subject to speedy or natural decay, the Director or any 
person authorised by him in this behalf may retain the package for the purpose 
of prosecution under this Act after giving the trader or his agent or the other 
person (who has committed the offence) a notice of such 
seizure.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Time within which 
unverified weight and measure to be verified and stamped.—No 
unverified weight or measure, seized under section 29, shall be forefeited if 
the person, from whom such weight or measure was seized, agrees to get the same 
verified and stamped within a period of ten days or such extended period from 
the date of such seizure; and for this purpose, the person making the seizure 
of such weight or measure shall afford a reasonable opportunity by returning 
such weight or measure exclusively for the verification and stamping.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Register and 
reports to be maintained by person referred to in section 35.—Every 
person referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 35 shall maintain a register 
in the appropriate form set out in the Eleventh Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Scale of Fee.—The 
scale of fees to be collected for the service specified in column (2) of the 
Twelfth Schedule shall be at the rate specified in column 3 of the said 
Schedule.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Use of regional 
languages.—Any 
legend or denomination specified in any Schedule to these rules, which is 
required to be indicated on any weight or measure in English, or in Devanagri 
Script, may also be indicated (in addition to English or Devanagri) on such 
weight or measure in such regional language as the manufacturer may consider to 
be practicable.
  
</article><form>
 


THE STANDARDs OF 
WEIGHTs AND MEASURES (GENERAL) RULES, 1987
 

 
 

TENTH SCHEDULE
 

(See rule 17)
 

APPLICATION FORM FOR REGISTRATION OF EXPORTER/IMPORTER 
OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES
 

 
 

To
 

The Director of Legal 
Metrology,
 

Government of India
 

New Delhi.
 

Sir,
 

I/we* hereby 
apply for registration of my/our* name(s) 
as exporter and/or importer of weights and/or measures. 
 

Particulars with regard to items specified in the table below 
are given against each such item. The registration fee of Rs. 
......................... has been paid in the treasury at 
................................ vide Challan No. 
................................ dated .......................... enclosed.
 

         1.  Name and full address:
 

         2.  Whether individual/undivided Hindu 
family/registered firm:
 

         3.  Income tax registration No. (if any):
 

         4.  Date of registration as manufacturer/dealer; 
registration No. and name of registration authority:
 

         5.  Date &amp; No. of the licence to carry on the 
business of weights and measures; the name of authority by whom the licence was 
issued/renewed:
 

             (a) buying and selling or
 

             (b) manufacturing
 

         6.  Item(s) of weights and measures in relation 
to which the applicant has been registered as manufacturer and’ or dealer:
 

         7.  Item of weights and measures for which 
application is being made for registration as—
 

             (a) exporter
 

             (b) importer.
 

         8.  Items if any exported/imported during the 
period of two years immediately preceding the year in which the application is 
made:
 

         9.  Remarks:
 


*Delete 
which is not applicable.     Signature
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>