<act><tid>939004</tid>
<title>THE AGRICULTURISTS' LOANS ACT, <year>1884</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1884</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 24th July, <year>1884</year>.] Preambl

An Act to amend and provide for the extension of the Northern India 
Takkavi Act, <year>1879</year>.





<article><tid>446409</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title.
<section><tid>750982</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Agriculturists'  
Loans Act, <year>1884</year>; and
Commencement.


</section>

<section><tid>976169</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of August, <year>1884</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>853951</tid>
<number> 2</number> Local extent.
<section><tid>1241209</tid>
<number>1</number>This section <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> extends to the whole of  
India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st 
November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B States].

</section>

<section><tid>744000</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The rest of this Act extends in the first instance only to 
Uttar Pradesh, the Central Provinces, Assam and Delhi and the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in the States of Bombay, Punjab and Ajmer.]

</section>

<section><tid>1208633</tid>
<number>3</number>But any State Government may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, extend the rest of this Act to 
the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in-- 
C. P. and Berar by C. P. and Berar Acts 34 of <year>1947</year> and 54 of <year>1949</year>; 
Coorg by Coorg Act 3 of <year>1936</year>; 
Madras by Madras Act 16 of <year>1935</year>; 
Orissa by Orissa Act 6 of <year>1937</year>; 
U. P. by U. P. Acts 12 of <year>1934</year> and 12 of <year>1948</year>; and 
Bombay by Bombay Act 27 of <year>1958</year>. 
Repealed in its application to Malabar District of Kerala by 
Kerala Act 27 of <year>1961</year>. 
Extended to the whole Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 23 of <year>1958</year> 
 (when notified). 
Extended to the Hyderabad and Saurashtra area of the State of 
Bombay by Bombay Act 27 of <year>1958</year>. 
Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
This Act as at present in force in the State of Gujarat extended 
to the Union Territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli by G. S. R. 
1638, dt. 3- 12- <year>1962</year>. 
Extended to the whole of the Union territory of Lakshadweep: vide 
Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" other 
Part A States or Part C States". 
3 Subs. ibid., for" and section 3 extend to the whole of India 
except Part B States". 
4 Subs., ibid., for the former sub- section (2).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


whole or any part of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories to which this Act extends] 
under its administration.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>871966</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Repeal of Act X of <year>1879</year>, and sections 4 and 5 of Act XV of 
<year>1880</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>138613</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power for State Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1904842</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or, in a State for which there is a Board of Revenue of 
Financial Commissioner, such Board or Financial Commissioner, subject 
to the control of the State Government] may, from time to time, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
make rules as to loans to be made to owners and occupiers of arable 
land, for the relief of distress, the purchase of seed or cattle, or 
any other purpose not specified in the Land Improvement Loans Act, 
 <year>1883</year> (19 of <year>1883</year>.), but connected with agricultural objects.

</section>

<section><tid>1822910</tid>
<number>2</number>All such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1442084</tid>
<number>5</number>Recovery of Loans. Every loan made in accordance with such 
rules, all interest (if any) chargeable thereon, and costs (if any) 
incurred in making or recovering the same, shall, when they become 
due, be recoverable from the person to whom the loan was made, or from 
any person who has become surety for the repayment thereof, as if they 
were arrears of land- revenue or costs incurred in recovering the same 
due by the person to whom the loan was made or by his surety.


</article>



<article><tid>376303</tid>
<number>6</number>Liability of joint- borrowers as among themselves. When a loan 
is made under this Act to the members of a village community or to any 
other persons on such terms that all of them are jointly and severally 
bound to the Government for the payment of the whole amount payable in 
respect thereof, and a statement showing the portion of that amount 
which as among themselves each is bound to contribute is entered upon 
the order granting the loan and is signed, marked, or sealed by each 
of them or his agent duly authorized in this behalf and by the officer 
making the order, that statement shall be conclusive evidence of the 
portion of that amount which as among themselves each of those persons 
is bound to contribute.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) order, <year>1956</year>, for" the 
territories". 
2 Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I. 
3 The words" subject to the control of the G. G. in C." rep. by s. 
2 and Sch., ibid., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>