<act><title>THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF POLLUTION) RULES, 19751</title> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 19751
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Rules, 1975.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Water (Prevention and Control 
of Pollution) Act, 1974;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   “Chairman” means the Chairman of the Central 
Board;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   “Central Board Laboratory” means a laboratory 
established or recognised as such under sub-section (3) of section 16;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>   “Central Water Laboratory” means a laboratory 
established or specified as such under sub-section (1) of section 51;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>   “form” means a form set out in Schedule I;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number>   “member” means a member of the Central Board 
and includes the Chairman thereof;
 </section><section>        <number>g</number>   “Member-Secretary” means the Member-Secretary 
of the Central Board;
 </section><section>        <number>h</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>i</number>   “schedule” means a schedule appended to the 
rules;
 </section><section>         <number>j</number>   “year” means the financial year commencing on 
the first day of April.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>3</number> Salaries, allowances and 
other conditions of service of the Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall be paid a fixed monthly salary of Rs. 3,000.
 

1[(2) (a) in addition to the salary 
specified in sub-rule (1), the Chairman shall be entitled to city compensatory 
allowance and house rent allowance as admissible to a Central Government servant 
in terms of Ministry of Finance (Department of Expenditure) O.M. No. 2(3)-E. 
II(B)/64, dated the 27th November, 1965:
 Provided that where the Chairman 
is allotted an accommodation by the Central Government, he shall not be entitled 
to house rent allowance and shall be required to pay ten per cent of the 
emoluments drawn by him as house rent or licence fee;
 <subsection><number>b</number> in respect of journeys 
undertaken by the Chairman in connection with his duties as Chairman, he shall 
be entitled to travelling allowance and daily allowance at the rates permissible 
in the case of a Government officer of equivalent rank under the Supplementary 
Rules of the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the Central Board shall 
provide to the Chairman, medical facilities as admissible to an officer of the 
Central Government drawing salary of Rs. 3,000 per mensem.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rules (1) and (2), where a Government servant is appointed as 
Chairman, the terms and conditions of his service shall be such as may be 
specified by the Central Government from time to time.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>4</number> Salaries, allowances and 
other conditions of service of Member-Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Member-Secretary shall be paid a monthly pay in the scale of Rs. 
2,250-125-2,500.
 

1[(2) (a) In addition to the salary 
specified in sub-rule (1) the Member-Secretary shall be entitled to city 
compensatory allowance and house rent allowance as admissible to a Central 
Government servant in terms of Ministry of Finance (Department of Expenditure) 
O.M. No. 2(3)-E. II(B)/64, dated the 27th November, 1965:
 Provided that where the 
Member-Secretary is allotted an accommodation by the Central Government he shall 
not be entitled to house rent allowance and shall be required to pay ten per 
cent of the emoluments drawn by him as house rent or licence fee;
 <subsection><number>b</number> in respect of journeys 
undertaken by the Member-Secretary in connection with his duties as 
Member-Secretary he shall be entitled to travelling allowance and daily 
allowance at the rates permissible in the case of a Government Officer of 
equivalent rank under the Supplementary Rules of the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the Central Board shall 
provide to the Member-Secretary, medical facilities as admissible to an officer 
of the Central Government drawing salary in the scale of Rs. 2,250-125-2,500 per
mensem.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rules (1) and (2) where a Government servant is appointed as 
Member-Secretary, the terms and conditions of his service shall be such as may 
be specified by the Central Government from time to time.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>5</number> Terms and conditions of 
service of members of the Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Non-official members of the Central Board resident in Delhi shall be paid an 
allowance of 

1[rupees seventy-five] per day for each 
day of the actual meetings of the Central Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Non-official members of the 
Central Board, not resident in Delhi shall be paid an allowance of rupees 
seventy-five per day (inclusive of daily allowance) for each day of the actual 
meetings of the Central Board and also travelling allowance at such rate as is 
admissible to a Grade I officer of the Central Government:
 Provided that in case of a 
member of Parliament who is also a member of the Central Board, the said daily 
and travelling allowance will be admissible when the Parliament is not in 
session and on production of a certificate by the member that he has not drawn 
any such allowance for the same journey and halts from any other Government 
source.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>6</number> Fees and allowances to be 
paid to such members of a committee of the Central Board as are not members of 
the Board under sub-section (3) of section 9.—A 
member of a committee of the Central Board shall be paid in respect of meetings 
of the committee travelling and daily allowances, if he is a non-official, at 
the rates specified in rule 5, as if he were a member of the Central Board and, 
if he is a Government servant, at the rates, admissible under the relevant rules 
of the respective Government under whom he is serving.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>7</number> Powers and duties of the 
Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman shall have 
overall control over the day-to-day activities of the Central Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> (i) The Chairman may 
undertake tours within India for carrying out the functions of the Central 
Board:
 Provided that he shall keep the 
Central Government (Secretary to Ministry of Works and Housing) and the Central 
Board, informed of his tours.
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The Chairman may, with the 
prior approval of the Central Government, visit any country outside India.
 

1[(3)] In the matter of acceptance to 
tenders, the Chairman shall have full powers subject to the concurrence of the 
Central Board:
 Provided that no such 
concurrence is required for the acceptance of tenders up to an amount of rupees 
one thousand in each case.
 

1[(4)] Subject to overall sanctioned 
budget provision, the Chairman shall have full powers to administratively 
approve and sanction all estimates.
  


</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Creation and abolition of posts. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may create such posts as it considers necessary for the efficient performance of the Central Board and may abolish any post, so created: 
 </section><section><number>2</number> All appointments for the post created under sub-rule (1) shall be made by the Central Board in accordance with the provisions of the Central Pollution Control Board (Method of Recruitment, Terms and Conditions of Service of Officers and other Employees other than Member Secretary) Regulations, 1995 and the Scientific and Technical Group ‘A' posts in Central Pollution Control Board Regulations, 2009: 
 Provided that with respect to a post falling under the pay band-4, no appointment shall be made by the Central Board without the prior approval of the Central Government.] 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Creation and abolition of posts. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may create such posts as it considers necessary for the efficient performance of the Central Board and may abolish any post, so created: 
 </section><section><number>2</number> All appointments for the post created under sub-rule (1) shall be made by the Central Board in accordance with the provisions of the Central Pollution Control Board (Method of Recruitment, Terms and Conditions of Service of Officers and other Employees other than Member Secretary) Regulations, 1995 and the Scientific and Technical Group ‘A' posts in Central Pollution Control Board Regulations, 2009: 
 Provided that with respect to a post falling under the pay band-4, no appointment shall be made by the Central Board without the prior approval of the Central Government.] 





</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>9</number> Powers and duties of the 
Member-Secretary.—The 
Member-Secretary shall be subordinate to the Chairman and shall, subject to the 
control of the Chairman, exercise the following powers, namely:—
 <section>        <number>1</number>   The Member-Secretary shall be in charge of all 
the confidential papers of the Board and shall be responsible for preserving 
them.
 </section><section>        <number>2</number>   The Member-Secretary shall produce such papers 
whenever so directed by the Chairman or by the Central Board.
 </section><section>        <number>3</number>   The Member-Secretary shall make available to 
any member of the Central Board, for his perusal, any record of the Board.
 </section><section>        <number>4</number>   The Member-Secretary shall be entitled to call 
for the services of any officer or employee of the Central Board, and files, 
papers and documents for study from any department of the Board, as also to 
carry out inspection of any department at any time including checking of 
accounts, vouchers, bills and other records and stores pertaining to the Board 
or regional offices thereunder.
 </section><section>        <number>5</number>   The Member-Secretary may withhold any payment:
                Provided that
1[as soon 
as may be, and in any case not later than three months] after such withholding 
of payment the matter shall be placed before the Central Board for its approval.
 </section><section>        <number>6</number>   The Member-Secretary shall make all 
arrangements for holding meetings of the Central Board and meetings of the 
Committees constituted by the Central Board.
 </section><section>        <number>7</number>   All orders or instructions to be issued by the 
Central Board shall be over the signature of the Member-Secretary or of any 
other officer authorised in this behalf by the Chairman.
 </section><section>        <number>8</number>   The Member-Secretary shall authorise, sanction 
or pass all payments against allotments made or estimates sanctioned.
 </section><section>        <number>9</number>   The Member-Secretary shall write and maintain 
confidential reports of all Class I and Class II officers of the Central Board 
and shall get them countersigned by the Chairman.
 </section><section>      <number>10</number>   The Member-Secretary shall countersign the 
confidential reports of all Class III employees of the Central Board.
 </section><section>        <number>11</number> (i)  The Member-Secretary shall sanction the 
annual increments of Class I and Class II officers of the Central Board:
                   Provided that the increments of Class I 
and Class II officers shall be withheld only with the approval of the Chairman.
 <subsection>              <number>ii</number>  The annual increments of other employees 
of the Central Board not referred to in clause (i) shall be sanctioned by 
officers authorised in this behalf by the Member-Secretary.
 </subsection></section><section>      <number>12</number>   The Member-Secretary shall have full powers for 
according technical sanction of all estimates.
 </section><section>      <number>13</number>   The Member-Secretary shall exercise such other 
powers and perform such other functions as may be delegated to him from time to 
time either by the Board or by the Chairman.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>10</number> Manner and purpose of 
association of persons with Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Board may invite any person, whose assistance or advice it considers 
useful to obtain in performing any of its functions, to participate in the 
deliberations of any of its meetings.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the person associated 
with the Board under sub-rule (1) happens to be a non-official, resident in 
Delhi, he shall be entitled to get an allowance of 

1[rupees seventy-five] per day for each 
day of actual meeting of the Central Board in which he is so associated.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If such person is 
non-resident in Delhi, he shall be entitled to get an allowance of rupees 
seventy-five per day (inclusive of daily allowance) for each day of actual 
meeting of the Central Board in which he is so associated and also to travelling 
allowance at such rates as is admissible to a Grade I officer of the Central 
Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything in 
sub-rules (2) and (3), if such person is a Government servant or an employee in 
a Government undertaking he shall be entitled to travelling and daily allowance 
only at the rates admissible under the relevant rules applicable to him.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>11</number> Appointment of consulting 
engineer.—For the purpose of 
assisting the Central Board in performance of its functions, the Board may 
appoint a consulting engineer to the Board for a specified period not exceeding 
four months:
 Provided that the Board may, 
with the prior approval of the Central Government extend the period of the 
appointment from time to time:
 Provided further that if at the 
time of the initial appointment the Central Board had reason to believe that the 
services of the consulting engineer would be required for a period of more than 
four months, the Central Board shall not make the appointment without the prior 
approval of the Central Government.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>12</number> Power to terminate 
appointment.—Notwithstanding the 
appointment of a consulting engineer for a specified period under rule 11, the 
Central Board shall have the right to terminate the services of the consulting 
engineer before the expiry of the specified period, if, in the opinion of the 
Board, the consulting engineer is not discharging his duties properly or to the 
satisfaction of the Board or such a course of action is necessary in the public 
interest:
 

1[Provided that the services of a 
consulting engineer shall not be terminated under this rule by the Central Board 
except after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed action.]
  


</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>13</number> Emoluments of the 
consulting engineer.—The Central 
Board may pay the consulting engineer suitable emoluments or fees depending on 
the nature of work, and the qualifications and experience of the consulting 
engineer:
 Provided that the Central Board 
shall not appoint any person as consulting engineer without the prior approval 
of the Central Government if the emoluments or fees payable to him exceeds 
rupees two thousand per month.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>14</number> Tours by consulting 
engineer.—The consulting engineer may 
undertake tours within the country for the performance of the duties entrusted 
to him by the Central Board and in respect of such tours he shall be entitled to 
travelling and daily allowances as admissible to a Grade I officer of the 
Central Government. He shall, however, get the prior approval of the 
Member-Secretary to his tour programme.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>15</number> Consulting engineer not 
to disclose information.—The 
consulting engineer shall not disclose any information either given by the 
Central Board or obtained, during the performance of the duties assigned to him 
either from the Central Board or otherwise, to any person other than the Central 
Board without the written permission of the Board.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>16</number> Duties and functions of 
the consulting engineer.—The 
consulting engineer shall discharge such duties and perform such functions as 
are assigned to him, by the Central Board and it will be his duty to advise the 
Board on all technical matters referred to him by the Board.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>17</number> Form of the budget 
estimates.—
<section><number>1</number> The budget in respect 
of the year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and expenditure of the 
Central Board shall be prepared in Forms I, II, III and IV and submitted to the 
Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The estimated receipts and 
expenditure shall be accompanied by the revised budget estimates for the current 
year.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The budget shall as far as 
may be, based on the account heads specified in Schedule II.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>18</number> Submission of budget 
estimates to the Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The budget estimates as compiled in accordance with rule 17 shall be placed by 
the Member-Secretary before the Central Board by the 5th October each year for 
approval.
 </section><section><number>2</number> After approval of the budget 
estimates by the Central Board, four copies of the final budget proposals 
incorporating therein such modifications as have been decided upon by the 
Central Board shall be submitted to the Central Government by the 15th October 
each year.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>19</number> Estimates of 
establishment expenditure and fixed recurring charges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The estimates of expenditure on fixed establishment as well as fixed monthly 
recurring charges on account of rent, allowances, etc., shall provide for the 
gross sanctioned pay without deductions of any kind.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The estimates referred to in 
sub-rule (1) shall be added a suitable provision for leave salary based on past 
experience with due regard to the intention of the members of the staff in 
regard to leave as far as the same can be ascertained.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If experience indicates that 
the total estimate for fixed charges referred to in sub-rules (1) and (2) is not 
likely to be fully utilised, a suitable lump deduction shall be made from the 
total amount estimated.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>20</number> Re-appropriations and 
emergent expenditure.—No expenditure 
which is not covered by a provision in the sanctioned budget estimates, or which 
is likely to be in excess over the amount provided under any head, shall be 
incurred by the Central Board without provision being made by re-appropriation 
from some other head under which saving are firmly established and available.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>21</number> Power to incur 
expenditure.—The Central Board shall 
incur expenditure out of the funds received by it in accordance with the 
instructions laid down under the General Financial Rules of the Central 
Government and other instructions issued by the Government from time to time.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>22</number> Operation of fund of the 
Central Board.—The fund of the 
Central Board shall be operated by the Member-Secretary of the Central Board or 
in his absence by any officer of the Central Board who may, subject to the 
approval of the Central Government, be so empowered by the Central Board.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>23</number> Saving.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall apply to a budget already finalised before the 
commencement of these rules.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>24</number> Form of annual report.—The 
annual report in respect of the year last ended giving a true and full account 
of the activities of the Central Board during the previous financial year shall 
contain the particulars specified in the Schedule III 

1[***].
  


</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>25</number> Form of annual statement 
of accounts of the Central Board.—The 
annual statement of accounts of the Central Board shall be in Forms V to IX.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>26</number> Form of report of Central 
Board Analyst.—When a sample of any 
water, sewage or trade effluent has been sent for analysis to a laboratory 
established or recognised by the Central Board, the Central Board analyst 
appointed under sub-section (3) of section 53 shall analyse the sample and 
submit to the Central Board a report in triplicate in Form X of the result of 
such analysis.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article>

1[<number>26A</number> Qualification of Analysts.—Persons 
possessing the following qualifications are eligible for appointment as 
Government Analysts or as Board Analysts under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section 
(3), as the case may be, of section 53, namely:—
 <subsection>  <number>Essential</number>—(i)   M.Sc. Degree in Chemistry or equivalent 
or Bachelor Degree in Chemical Engineering or Bio-chemical Engineering; and
 <subsubsection>                  <number>ii</number>   10 years’ experience in analysis of 
water, sewage or industrial wastes in teaching, research or Government. 
Laboratory.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>Desirable</number>—(i)  Doctorate Degree in Chemistry or 
Bio-chemistry or Master’s Degree in Chemical Engineering or Bio-chemical 
Engineering;
 <subsubsection>                        <number>ii</number>  Evidence of published papers 
in the field.]
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>27</number> Functions of the Central 
Water Laboratory.—The Central Water 
Laboratory shall cause to be analysed any samples of water, sewage or trade 
effluent received by it from any officer authorised by the Central Board for the 
purpose, and findings 

1[shall be recorded in a report in 
triplicate] in Form XI.
  



</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article>

1[<number>28</number> Fees for report.—The fees 
payable in respect of each report of the Central Water Laboratory on any 
analysis or test mentioned in column (2) of Schedule IV shall be at the rates 
specified in the corresponding entry in column (3) thereof.]
  


</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  OF POLLUTION) RULES, 
1975
  
 <article><number>29</number> Central Board to act as 
State Board for Union Territories.—The Central Board shall act as the State Board for 
Union Territories under sub-section (4) of section 4.</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>30</number> Power to take samples.—The 
Central Board or any officer, empowered by it in this behalf shall have power to 
take for the purpose of analysis samples of water from any stream or well or 
samples of sewage or trade effluent which is passing from any plant or vessel or 
from or over any place into any such stream or well in any Union territory.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>31</number> Form of notice.—A 
notice under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (3) of section 21 shall, in the case of a 
Union territory, be in Form XII.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article>

1[<number>32</number> Application for consent.—An 
application for obtaining the consent of the Central Board for establishing or 
taking any steps to establish any industry, operation or process or any 
treatment and disposal system or any extension or addition thereto, which is 
likely to discharge sewage or trade effluent into a stream or well or sewer or 
on land (such discharge being hereinafter in this rule referred to as discharge 
of sewage); or for bringing into use any new or altered outlet for the discharge 
of sewage or beginning to make any new discharge of sewage under section 25 or 
for continuing an existing discharge of sewage under section 26 shall be made to 
the Central Board in Form XIII.]
  


</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article><number>33</number> Procedure for making 
inquiry into application for consent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of an application for consent under section 25 or section 26, the 
Central Board may depute any of its Officers, accompanied by as may assistants 
as may be necessary, to visit the premises of the applicant, to which such 
application relates, for the purpose of verifying the correctness or otherwise 
of the particulars furnished in the application or for obtaining such further 
particulars or information as such officer may consider necessary. Such officer 
may, for that purpose, inspect any place where water or sewage or trade effluent 
is discharged by the applicant, or treatment plants, purification works or 
disposal systems of the applicant and may require the applicant to furnish to 
him any plans, specifications and other data relating to such treatment plants, 
purification works or disposal systems or any part thereof, that he considers 
necessary.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such officer shall before 
visiting any premises of the applicant for the purpose of inspection under 
sub-rule (1) above, give notice to the applicant of his intention to do so in 
Form XIV. The applicant shall furnish to such officer all facilities that such 
officer may legitimately require for the purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An officer of the Central 
Board may, before or after carrying out an inspection under sub-rule (1) above, 
required the applicant to furnish to him, orally or in writing such additional 
information or clarification, or to produce before him such documents, as he may 
consider necessary for the purpose of investigation of the application and may, 
for that purpose, summon the applicant or his authorised agent to the office of 
the Central Board.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article>

1[<number>34</number> Directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any direction issued under section 33A shall be in writing.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The direction shall specify 
the nature of action to be taken and the time within which it shall be compiled 
with by the person, officer or the authority to whom such direction is given.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The person, officer or 
authority to whom any direction is sought to be issued shall be served with a 
copy of the proposed direction and shall be given an opportunity of not less 
than fifteen days from the date of service of a notice to file with an officer 
designated in this behalf the objections, if any, to the issue of the proposed 
direction.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the proposed direction 
is for the stoppage or regulation of electricity or water or any other services 
affecting the carrying on any industry, operation or process and is sought to be 
issued to an officer or an authority, a copy of the proposed direction shall 
also be endorsed to the occupier of the industry, operation or process, as the 
case may be, and objections, if any, filed by the occupier with an officer 
designated in this behalf shall be dealt with in accordance with the procedures 
under sub-rules (3) and (5) of this rule:
 Provided that no opportunity of 
being heard shall be given to the occupier, if he had already been heard earlier 
and the proposed direction referred to in sub-rule (3) above for the stoppage or 
regulation of electricity or water or any other service was the resultant 
decision of the Central Board after such earlier hearing.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Board shall 
within a period of 45 days from the date of receipt of the objections, if any, 
or from the date up to which an opportunity is given to the person, officer or 
authority to file objections whichever is earlier, after considering the 
objection, if any, received from the person, officer or authority sought to be 
directed and for reasons to be recorded in writing, confirm, modify or decide 
not to issue the proposed direction.
 </section><section><number>6</number> In a case where the Central 
Board is of the opinion that in view of the likelihood of a grave injury to the 
environment it is not expedient to provide an opportunity to file objections 
against the proposed direction, it may for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
issue directions without providing such an opportunity.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Every notice or direction 
required to be issued under this rule shall be deemed to be duly served,—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   Where the person to be served is a company, if 
the document is addressed in the name of the company at its registered office or 
at its principal office or place of business and is either—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  sent by registered post; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  delivered at its registered office or at 
the principal office or place of business;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   Where the person to be served is an officer 
serving Government, if the document is addressed to the person and a copy 
thereof is endorsed to his Head of the Department and also to the Secretary to 
the Government as the case may be, incharge of the Department in which for the 
time being the business relating to the Department in which the officer is 
employed in transacted and is either—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  sent by registered post, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  is given or tendered to him;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   In any other case, if the document is 
addressed to the person to be served and—
 <subsubsection>               <number>i</number>  is given or tendered to him, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>              <number>ii</number>  if such person cannot be found is 
affixed on some conspicuous part of his last known place of residence or 
business or is given or tendered to some adult member of his family or is 
affixed on some conspicuous part of the land or building, if any, to which it 
relates, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>iii</number>  is sent by registered post to that 
person.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub-rule—
 <subsubsubsection>        <number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
includes a firm or other association of individuals;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>        <number>b</number>   “a servant” is not a member of the family.]
  


</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
  
 <article>

1[<number>35</number> Manner of giving notice.—The 
manner of giving notice under clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 49 shall 
be as follows, namely:—
 </section><section>        <number>1</number>   The notice shall be in writing in Form XV;
 </section><section>        <number>2</number>   If the alleged offence has taken place in a 
Union territory, the person giving notice may send notice to —
 <subsection>               <number>i</number>  the Central Board; and
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>ii</number>  the Ministry of Environment and Forests 
(represented by the Secretary to the Government of India); and
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>iii</number>  the Administrator of the Union territory 
(represented by the Secretary/Head incharge of Environment).
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>3</number>   The notice shall be sent by registered post 
acknowledgement due; and
 </section><section>        <number>4</number>   The period of sixty days mentioned in clause 
(b) of sub-section (1) of section 49 of the Act, shall be reckoned from the date 
it is first received by one of the authorities mentioned in sub-rule (2).]
  


</section></article><form>
 


THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL
 

OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
 


 
 



SCHEDULE II
 




Budget and Account Heads
 


[See
rule 17 (3)]
 



ADMINISTRATION
 


Heads 
of Accounts (Expenditure)
 


1. 
Salaries.
 


2. 
Wages.
 


3. 
Travel Expenses.
 


4. 
Office Expenses:
 



        (a) Furniture
 



        (b) Postage
 



        (c) Office Machines/Equipment
 



        (d) Liveries
 



        (e) Hot and cold weather charges
 



        (f) Telephones
 



        (g) Electricity and Water charges
 



        (h) Stationery
 



         (i) Printing
 



         (j) Staff car and other vehicles
 



        (k) Other items.
 


 5. Fee 
and Honoraria.
 


 6. 
Payment for professional and special services.
 


 7. 
Rents, Rates and Taxes/Royalty.
 


 8. 
Publications.
 


 9. 
Advertising, Sales and Publicity Expenses.
 


10.  
Grants in aid/Contributions/Subsidies.
 


11.  
Hospitality Expenses/Sumptuary Allowances, etc.
 


12.  
Pensions/Gratuities.
 


13. 
Write off/Losses.
 


14.  
Suspenses.
 


15.  
Expenses in connection with the setting up and maintenance of the Board 

          Laboratory.
 


16.  
Other charges (A residuary head, this will also include rewards and prizes).
 



Heads of Accounts (Receipts)
 


 1. 
Payments by Central Government.
 


 2. 
Fees.
 


 3. 
Fines and other receipts.
</form><form>
 


THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL
 

OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
 


 
 



1[SCHEDULE 
III
 



Central Pollution Control Board
 


(See 
rule 24)
 




Annual Report from the Financial Year  

April 1, 20...... to March 31, 20......
 


CHAPTER 
1.              Introduction.
 


CHAPTER 
2.              Constitution of the Board including changes therein.
 


CHAPTER 
3.              Meeting of the Board with major decisions taken therein.
 


CHAPTER 
4.              Committees constituted by the Board and their activities.
 


CHAPTER 
5.              Monitoring Network for air, water and soil quality.
 


CHAPTER 
6.              Present state of environment, environmental problems and  

                                    counter-measures.
 


CHAPTER 
7.              Environment Research.
 


CHAPTER 
8.              Environment Training.
 


CHAPTER 
9.              Environmental Awareness and Public Participation.
 


CHAPTER 
10.             Environmental Standards including time schedule for their  

                                    enforcement.
 


CHAPTER 
11.1.          Prosecutions launched and convictions secured for environmental
 

                                    pollution control.
 


CHAPTER 
11.2.          Directions given for closure of polluting industrial units.
 


CHAPTER 
12.             Finance and accounts of the Board.
 


CHAPTER 
13.             Annual Plan of the following year.
 


CHAPTER 
14.             Any other important matter dealt with by the Central Board.
 


 
 



ANNEXURES
 



         1. Members of the Board.
 



         2. Organisation Chart.
 



         3. Staff Strength including recruitment.
 



         4.  Publications.
 



         5. Training Courses/Seminars/Workshops organised or attended.
 



         6. Consents to establish industries, operations and 
process—issued/refused.
 



         7. Consents to operate industries, operations and 
process—issued/refused.]
 

 
 


—————
 


	1. Subs. by G.S.R. 107 (E), 
dated 18th February, 1992.
</form><form>
 


THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL
 

OF POLLUTION) RULES, 1975
 


 
 



1[SCHEDULE 
IV
 




Rates of Fees Payable in Respect of a Report of  

the Central Water Laboratory
 


(See
rule 28)
 


 


       
  Sl. No.            Nature of 
  analysis                                           Rates of fees
 


 



            (1)                        
  (2)                                                            (3)
 




I.  
Chemical Analysis of Water
 





(a)                                                                      Rs. 56 (For all the tests)
 



             Dissolved solids (at 1030-1050C)
 



             P-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             M-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             Total hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Non-alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Calcium, as Ca
 



             Magnesium, as Mg
 



             Chlorides, as Cl
 



             Sulphates, as SO4
 



             Turbidity units
 



             pH
 



             Appearance and colour in units (visual)
 






 (b)                                                                      Rs. 100 (For all the tests)
 



             Dissolved solids (at 1030-1050C)
 



             P-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             M-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             Total hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Non-alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Calcium, as Ca
 



             Magnesium, as Mg
 



             Sodium, as Na
 



             Potassium, as K
 



             Iron, as Fe
 



             Manganese, as Mn
 



             Chlorides, as Cl
 



             Sulphates, as SO4
 



             Fluorides, as F
 



             Nitrates, as N
 



             Phosphates, as PO4
 



             Turbidity units
 



             pH
 



             Appearance and colour units (visual)
 



        (c)                                                                      Rs. 174 (For all the tests)
 



             Dissolved solids
 



             P-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             M-alkalinity, as CaCO3
 



             Free CO2, as 
CaCO3
 



             Total hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Non-alkaline hardness, as CaCO3
 



             Calcium, as Ca
 



             Magnesium, as Mg
 



             Sodium, as Na
 



             Potassium, as K
 



             Iron, as Fe
 



             Manganese, as Mn
 



             Chlorides, as Cl
 



             Sulphates, as SO4
 



             Fluorides, as F
 



             Nitrates, as N
 



             Phosphates, as PO4
 



             Silica, as SiO2
 



             Turbidity units
 



             pH
 



             Langelier Index
 



              Conductivity micromhos/cm
 



             Appearance and colour (visual)
 



             Probable composition of residue
 



                    CaCO3               
CaCO4                        
CaCl4                  
SiO2
 



                    MgCO3               
MgSO4                        
MgCl2                
Fe2O3
 



                   Na2CO3              
Na2SO4                        
NaCl                 Mn2O2
 



                    K2CO3                
K2SO4                          
KCl                  Al2O3
 



         II. Chemical Analysis of Irrigation Waters                 Rs. 72 (For all the 
tests)
 



             Dissolved solids 
 



             pH
 



             Boron, as B
 



             Calcium, as Ca
 



             Chloride, as Cl
 



             Conductivity, micromhos/cm
 



             Magnesium, as Mg
 



             Potassium, as K
 



             Sodium, as Na
 



             Sulphate, as SO4
 



             Oil and Grease
 



        III.  Bacteriological Analysis of Potable Waters            Rs. 50 (For all the 
tests)
 



             Standard Plate Court 
 



             Coliform
 



             EE Coli        
 



             Fecal streptococci
 



        IV.  Distilled Water (as IS: 1070-1960)           Rs. 120 (For each test)
 



         V.  Sewage and Trade Effluent                               Rs. 60 (For all the tests)
 



             BOD 200C 
5 day PH
 



             COD Suspended solids (1300-1500C)
 



             Colour (visual) units.
 



        VI.  Tests of Water, Sewage or 
Trade Efflun 
 



        (a)  Albuminoid nitrogen, as N                                     Rs. 6 (For each test)
 



             Ammoniacal nitrogen, as N
 



             Carbon dioxide, as CO2
 



             Conductivity micromhos/cm
 



             Chlorides, as Cl
 



             Chlorine demand
 



             Dissolved Oxygen
 



             Fluoride, as F
 



             Langelier Index
 



             Nitrate, as N
 



             Permanganate value
 



             Residual Chlorine
 



             Sodium, as Na
 



             Sulphates, as SO4
 



             Dissolved Solids (at 1030-1050C)
 



             Total solids
 



             Turbidity, as units
 



             Volatile solids
 



             pH
 






(b)                                                      Rs. 12 (For each test)
 



             Coliform MPN presumptive for waste 
 



             effluents only
 



             Acid solubility test for sand and gravel
 



             Available chlorine in bleaching powder
 



             Boron, as B
 



             Calcium (titrimetric), as Ca
 



             Iron, as Fe
 



             Kjedahl nitrogen, as N
 



             Loss on ignition
 



             Magnesium (titrimetric), as Mg
 



             Manganese, as Mn
 



             Silica, as SiO4
 



             Potassium in sludge and waste water, as K
 



             Sodium in sludge and waste waters, as Na
 



             Soluble phosphate, as PO4
 



             Sulphide, as S
 



             Suspended solids
 



             Total phosphorous
 



             Volatile acids
 



             Alkalinity (P &amp; M)
 



             Specific gravity
 






(c)                                                                      Rs. 24 (For each test)
 



             Heavy Metals (qualitative test)
 



             Aluminium (gravimetric)
 



             Arsenic
 



             Barium
 



             Calcium
 



             COD
 



             Chromium
 



             Copper
 



             Cyanide
 



             Insecticides
 



             Lead
 



             Magnesium (gravimetric)
 



             Mercury
 



             Nickel
 



             Selenium
 



             Silver
 



             Sulphate (gravimetric)
 



             Zinc
 



             Present Sodium
 



             Oil and Grease
 



             Phenolic Substances
 



           (d)                                                             Rs. 36 (For each test)
 



             BOD
 



             Air Samples—analysis for:
 



              (i) Carbon dioxide
 



              (ii) Carbon mono oxide
 



             (iii) Methane and 
 



             (iv) Oxygen
 



             Total fluorides by distillation
 






(e)                                                     Rs. 40 (For each test)
 



             Sieve analysis
 



             Conventional Marble Test
 



             The Enslow Stability Indicator Test
 






(f)                                                              Rs. 60 (For each test)
 



             Alum dose determination by jar test in water 
 



             treatment 
 



             Alumino non-ferric (as per IS: 260-1960)
 



             Bioassary tests without chemical analysis     

(Tim value)
 



             Plain settlement test of solution containing 
 



             fines 
 



             Filter and gravel
 



             Including sieve analysis, solubility in dilute 
 



             HCL, loss on ignition, and specific gravity
 






(g)                                                                      
Rs. 96 (For each test)
 



             Alum
 



             Jar test to evaluate optimum coagulant        

and coagulant aid doses in water      

treatment 
 



             Alumino ferric (as per IS: 299-1962)
 



             Lime
 



             Detailed analysis
 






(h)                                                                 Rs. 180 (For each test)
 



             Lead extraction test on UPVC pipe (as per 
 



             IS: 4985-1963)
 






(i)                                                                        Rs. 240 (For each test)
 



             Scale deposits (detailed analysis)
 






(j)                                                                         Rs. 40 (For each test)
 



             Attrition Test
 






(k)                                                                      Rs. 60 (For each test)
 



             To find out correlation between Jackson 
 



             Candle Turbidity and Gravimetric Units].
 


 


 
 


 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 377 
(E), dated 20th July, 1978 (w.e.f. 20-7-1978).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 803(E), dated 9th November, 2011, for rule 18 (w.e.f. 9-11-2011). Rule 18, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 803(E), dated 9th November, 2011, for rule 18 (w.e.f. 9-11-2011). Rule 18, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>