<act><title>

THE 


    CENTRAL VIGILANCE COMMISSION ACT, 2003</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—This Act may be called the 
    Central Vigilance Commission Act, 2003.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Central Vigilance Commissioner” 
      means the Central Vigilance Commissioner appointed under sub-section (1) 
      of section 4;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Commission” means the Central 
      Vigilance Commission constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Delhi Special Police Establishment” 
      means the Delhi Special Police Establishment constituted under sub-section 
      (1) of section 2 of the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946 (25 
      of 1946);
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Government company” means a 
      Government company within the meaning of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
      1956);
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
      rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “Vigilance Commissioner” means a 
      Vigilance Commissioner appointed under sub-section (1) of section 4.
</section>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of Central Vigilance Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a body to be known as the Central Vigilance 
    Commission to exercise the powers conferred upon, and to perform the 
    functions assigned to it under this Act and the Central Vigilance Commission 
    constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Central Vigilance 
    Commission Ordinance, 1999 (Ord. 4 of 1999) which ceased to operate, and 
    continued under the Government of India in the Ministry of Personnel, Public 
    Grievances and Pensions (Department of Personnel and Training) Resolution 
    No. 371/20/99-AVD III, dated the 4th April, 1999 as amended vide 
    Resolution of even number, dated the 13th August, 2002 shall be deemed to be 
    the Commission constituted under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall consist of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
      Central Vigilance Commissioner                               — 
      Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   not 
      more than two Vigilance Commissioners                 — Members.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner and the Vigilance Commissioners shall be appointed 
    from amongst persons—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    who have been or are in an All-India 
      Service or in any civil service of the Union or in a civil post under the 
      Union having knowledge and experience in the matters relating to 
      vigilance, policy making and administration including police 
      administration; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    who have held office or are holding 
      office in a corporation established by or under any Central Act or a 
      Government company owned or controlled by the Central Government and 
      persons who have expertise and experience in finance including insurance 
      and banking, law, vigilance and investigations:
 
Provided that, from amongst the Central 
      Vigilance Commissioner and the Vigilance Commissioners, not more than two 
      persons shall belong to the category of persons referred to either in 
      clause (a) or clause (b).
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
    Government shall appoint a Secretary to the Commission on such terms and 
    conditions as it deems fit to exercise such powers and discharge such duties 
    as the Commission may by regulations specify in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner, the other Vigilance Commissioners and the Secretary 
    to the Commission appointed under the Central Vigilance Commission 
    Ordinance, 1999 (4 of 1999) or the Resolution of the Government of India in 
    the Ministry of Personnel, Public Grievances and Pensions (Department of 
    Personnel and Training) Resolution No. 371/20/99-AVD-III, dated the 4th 
    April, 1999 as amended vide Resolution of even number, dated the 13th 
    August, 2002 shall be deemed to have been appointed under this Act on the 
    same terms and conditions including the term of office subject to which they 
    were so appointed under the said Ordinance or the Resolution, as the case 
    may be.
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, the expression “term of office” shall be construed as the 
    term of office with effect from the date the Central Vigilance Commissioner 
    or any Vigilance Commissioner has entered upon his office and continued as 
    such under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    headquarters of the Commission shall be at New Delhi.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Appointment of Central Vigilance Commissioner and Vigilance Commissioners.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Vigilance Commissioner and the Vigilance Commissioners shall be 
    appointed by the President by warrant under his hand and seal:
 
Provided that 
    every appointment under this sub-section shall be made after obtaining the 
    recommendation of a Committee consisting of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the 
      Prime Minister                                                  — 
      Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
      Minister of Home Affairs                                     — Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
      Leader of the Opposition in the House            
      of the 
      People                                                               — 
      Member. 
</subsection>
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “the Leader of the Opposition in the House of the People” 
    shall, when no such Leader has been so recognized, include the Leader of the 
    single largest group in opposition of the Government in the House of the 
    People.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    appointment of a Central Vigilance Commissioner or a Vigilance Commissioner 
    shall be invalid merely by reason of any vacancy in the Committee.
 




 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Terms and 
    other conditions of service of Central Vigilance Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (3) and (4), the 
    Central Vigilance Commissioner shall hold office for a term of four years 
    from the date on which he enters upon his office or till he attains the age 
    of sixty-five years, whichever is earlier. The Central Vigilance 
    Commissioner, on ceasing to hold the office, shall be ineligible for 
    reappointment in the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-sections (3) and (4), every Vigilance Commissioner 
    shall hold office for a term of four years from the date on which he enters 
    upon his office or till he attains the age of sixty-five years, whichever is 
    earlier.
 
Provided that 
    every Vigilance Commissioner, on ceasing to hold the office, shall be 
    eligible for appointment as the Central Vigilance Commissioner in the manner 
    specified in sub-section (1) of section 4:
 
Provided 
    further that the term of the Vigilance Commissioner, if appointed as the 
    Central Vigilance Commissioner, shall not be more than four years in 
    aggregate as the Vigilance Commissioner and the Central Vigilance 
    Commissioner.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner or a Vigilance Commissioner shall, before he enters 
    upon his office, make and subscribe before the President, or some other 
    person appointed in that behalf by him, an oath or affirmation according to 
    the form set out for the purpose in Schedule to this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner or a Vigilance Commissioner may, by writing under his 
    hand addressed to the President, resign his office.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner or a Vigilance Commissioner may be removed from his 
    office in the manner provided in section 6.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> On ceasing 
    to hold office, the Central Vigilance Commissioner and every other Vigilance 
    Commissioner shall be ineligible for—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any diplomatic assignment, 
      appointment as administrator of a Union territory and such other 
      assignment or appointment which is required by law to be made by the 
      President by warrant under his hand and seal.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    further employment to any office of 
      profit under the Government of India or the Government of a State.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The salary 
    and allowances payable to and the other conditions of service of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Central Vigilance Commissioner 
      shall be the same as those of the Chairman of the Union Public Service 
      Commission;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
      <number>b</number>   the Vigilance Commissioner shall be the same as those of a Member of 
      the Union Public Service Commission:
 
Provided that if the Central Vigilance 
      Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner is, at the time of his 
      appointment, in receipt of a pension (other than a disability or wound 
      pension) in respect of any previous service under the Government of India 
      or under the Government of a State, his salary in respect of the service 
      as the Central Vigilance Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner shall 
      be reduced by the amount of that pension including any portion of pension 
      which was commuted and pension equivalent of other forms of retirement 
      benefits excluding pension equivalent of retirement gratuity:
 
Provided further that if the Central 
      Vigilance Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner is, at the time of 
      his appointment, in receipt of retirement benefits in respect of any 
      previous service rendered in a corporation established by or under any 
      Central Act or a Government company owned or controlled by the Central 
      Government, his salary in respect of the service as the Central Vigilance 
      Commissioner or, as the case may be, the Vigilance Commissioner shall be 
      reduced by the amount of pension equivalent to the retirement benefits:
 
Provided also that the salary, allowances 
      and pension payable to, and the other conditions of service of, the 
      Central Vigilance Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner shall not be 
      varied to his disadvantage after his appointment.
</subsection>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Removal 
    of Central Vigilance Commissioner and Vigilance Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (3), the Central Vigilance 
    Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner shall be removed from his office 
    only by order of the President on the ground of proved misbehaviour or 
    incapacity after the Supreme Court, on a reference made to it by the 
    President, has, on inquiry, reported that the Central Vigilance Commissioner 
    or any Vigilance Commissioner, as the case may be, ought on such ground be 
    removed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    President may suspend from office, and if deem necessary prohibit also from 
    attending the office during inquiry, the Central Vigilance Commissioner or 
    any Vigilance Commissioner in respect of whom a reference has been made to 
    the Supreme Court under sub-section (1) until the President has passed 
    orders on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on such reference.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the President may by 
    order remove from office the Central Vigilance Commissioner or any Vigilance 
    Commissioner if the Central Vigilance Commissioner or such Vigilance 
    Commissioner, as the case may be,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is adjudged an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has been convicted of an offence 
      which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; 
      or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    engages during his term of office in 
      any paid employment outside the duties of his office; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is, in the opinion of the President, 
      unfit to continue in office by reason of infirmity of mind or body; or
 </subsection><subsection>

                  <number>e</number>   has acquired such financial or other interest as is 
      likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a Central Vigilance 
      Commissioner or a Vigilance Commissioner.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the 
    Central Vigilance Commissioner or any Vigilance Commissioner is or becomes 
    in any way concerned or interested in any contract or agreement made by or 
    on behalf of the Government of India or participates in any way in the 
    profit thereof or in any benefit or emolument arising therefrom otherwise 
    than as a member and in common with the other members of an incorporated 
    company, he shall, for the purposes of sub-section (1), be deemed to be 
    guilty of misbehaviour.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Power to 
    make rules by the Central Government for staff.—The 
    Central Government may, in consultation with the Commission, make rules with 
    respect to the number of members of the staff of the Commission and their 
    conditions of service.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>8</number> Functions and powers of Central Vigilance Commission.— </title>
<section><number>1</number> The functions and powers of the Commission shall be to— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> exercise superintendence over the functioning of the Delhi Special Police Establishment insofar as it relates to the investigation of offences alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), or an offence with which a public servant specified in sub-section (2) may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> give directions to the Delhi Special Police Establishment for the purpose of discharging the responsibility entrusted to it under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946 (25 of 1946): 
 Provided that while exercising the powers of superintendence under clause (a) or giving directions under this clause, the Commission shall not exercise powers in such a manner so as to require the Delhi Special Police Establishment to investigate or dispose of any case in a particular manner; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> inquire or cause an inquiry or investigation to be made on a reference made by the Central Government wherein it is alleged that a public servant being an employee of the Central Government or a corporation established by or under any Central Act, Government company, society and any local authority owned or controlled by that Government, has committed an offence under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), or an offence with which a public servant may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> inquire or cause an inquiry or investigation to be made into any complaint against any official belonging to such category of officials specified in sub-section (2) wherein it is alleged that he has committed an offence under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988) and an offence with which a public servant specified in sub-section (2) may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> review the progress of investigations conducted by the Delhi Special Police Establishment into offences alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988) or the public servant may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> review the progress of applications pending with the competent authorities for sanction of prosecution under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> tender advice to the Central Government, corporations established by or under any Central Act, Government companies, societies and local authorities owned or controlled by the Central Government on such matters as may be referred to it by that Government, said Government companies, societies and local authorities owned or controlled by the Central Government or otherwise: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> exercise superintendence over the vigilance administration of the various Ministries of the Central Government or corporations established by or under any Central Act, Government companies, societies and local authorities owned or controlled by that Government: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this clause shall be deemed to authorise the Commission to exercise superintendence over the vigilance administration in a manner not consistent with the directions relating to vigilance matters issued by the Government and to confer power upon the Commission to issue directions relating to any policy matters; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The persons referred to in clause (d) of sub-section (1) are as follows:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> members of All-India Services serving in connection with the affairs of the Union and Group `A' officers of the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> such level of officers of the corporations established by or under any Central Act, Government companies, societies and other local authorities, owned or controlled by the Central Government, as that Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf: 
 Provided that till such time a notification is issued under this clause, all officers of the said corporations, companies, societies and local authorities shall be deemed to be the persons referred to in clause (d) of sub-section (1). 
</subsection>


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Proceedings of Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    proceedings of the Commission shall be conducted at its headquarters.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission may, by unanimous decision, regulate the procedure for 
    transaction of its business as also allocation of its business amongst the 
    Central Vigilance Commissioner and other Vigilance Commissioners.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save as 
    provided in sub-section (2), all business of the Commission shall, as far as 
    possible, be transacted unanimously.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-section (3), if the Central Vigilance Commissioner and 
    other Vigilance Commissioners differ in opinion on any matter, such matter 
    shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority. 

 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner, or, if for any reason he is unable to attend any 
    meeting of the Commission, the senior-most Vigilance Commissioner present at 
    the meeting, shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No act or 
    proceeding of the Commission shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
      constitution of, the Commission; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any defect in the appointment of a 
      person acting as the Central Vigilance Commissioner or as a Vigilance 
      Commissioner; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any irregularity in the procedure of 
      the Commission not affecting the merits of the case.
</subsection>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Vigilance Commissioner to act as Central Vigilance Commissioner 
in certain circumstances.— </title>
<section><number>1</number> In the event of the occurrence of any 
vacancy in the office of the Central Vigilance Commissioner by reason of his 
death, resignation or otherwise, the President may, by notification, authorise 
one of the Vigilance Commissioners to act as the Central Vigilance Commissioner 
until the appointment of a new Central Vigilance Commissioner to fill such 
vacancy. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the Central Vigilance Commissioner is unable to discharge his 
functions owing to absence on leave or otherwise, such one of the Vigilance 
Commissioners as the President may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, 
shall discharge the functions of the Central Vigilance Commissioner until the 
date on which the Central Vigilance Commissioner resumes his duties. 


  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Power 
    relating to inquiries.—The 
    Commission shall, while conducting any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[inquiry referred to in 
    clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 8], have all the powers of 
    a civil court trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
    1908) and in particular, in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing the 
      attendance of any person from any part of India and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery and 
      production of any document;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    requisitioning any public record or 
      copy thereof from any court or office;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for the 
      examination of witnesses or other documents; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any other matter which may be 
      prescribed.
</subsection>





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>12</number> Proceedings before Commission to be judicial proceedings.— </title>The Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and every proceeding before the Commission shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 and for the purposes of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Expenses 
    of Commission to be charged on the Consolidated Fund of India.—The expenses of the Commission, including any salaries, allowances 
    and pensions payable to or in respect of the Central Vigilance Commissioner, 
    the Vigilance Commissioners, Secretary and the staff of the Commission, 
    shall be charged on the Consolidated Fund of India.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Annual 
    report.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be the duty 
    of the Commission to present annually to the President a report as to the 
    work done by the Commission within six months of the close of the year under 
    report.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The report 
    referred to in sub-section (1) shall contain a separate part on the 
    functioning of the Delhi Special Police Establishment insofar as it relates 
    to sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Delhi Special Police Establishment 
    Act, 1946 (25 of 1946).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt 
    of such report, the President shall cause the same to be laid before each 
    House of Parliament.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
    Commission, the Central Vigilance Commissioner, any Vigilance Commissioner, 
    the Secretary or against any staff of the Commission in respect of anything 
    which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Central 
    Vigilance Commissioner, Vigilance Commissioner and staff to be public 
    servants.—The Central Vigilance 
    Commissioner, every Vigilance Commissioner, the Secretary and every staff of 
    the Commission shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of 
    section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Report 
    of any inquiry made on reference by Commission to be forwarded to that 
    Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> The report of the 
    inquiry undertaken by any agency on a reference made by the Commission shall 
    be forwarded to the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall, on receipt of such report and after taking into 
    consideration any other factors relevant thereto, advise the Central 
    Government and corporations established by or under any Central Act, 
    Government companies, societies and local authorities owned or controlled by 
    that Government, as the case may be, as to the further course of action.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Government and the corporations established by or under any Central Act, 
    Government companies, societies and other local authorities owned or 
    controlled by that Government, as the case may be, shall consider the advice 
    of the Commission and take appropriate action:
 
Provided that 
    where the Central Government, any corporation established by or under any 
    Central Act, Government company, society or local authority owned or 
    controlled by the Central Government, as the case may be, does not agree 
    with the advice of the Commission, it shall, for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing, communicate the same to the Commission.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Power to 
    call for information.—The 
    Commission may call for reports, returns and statements from the Central 
    Government or corporations established by or under any Central Act, 
    Government companies, societies and other local authorities owned or 
    controlled by that Government so as to enable it to exercise general 
    supervision over the vigilance and anti-corruption work in that Government 
    and in the said corporations, Government companies, societies and local 
    authorities.
 




 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Consultation with Commission in certain matters.—The 
    Central Government shall, in making any rules or regulations governing the 
    vigilance or disciplinary matters relating to persons appointed to public 
    services and posts in connection with the affairs of the Union or to members 
    of the All-India Services, consult the Commission.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the 
    purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the number of members of the staff 
      and their conditions of service under section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any other power of the civil court to 
      be prescribed under clause (f) of section 11; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any other matter which is required to 
      be, or may be, prescribed.
</subsection>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Power to 
    make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Commission may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with 
    this Act and the rules made thereunder to provide for all matters for which 
    provision is expedient for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions 
    of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the duties and the powers of the 
      Secretary under sub-section (4) of section 3; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the procedure to be followed by the 
      Commission under sub-section (2) of section 9.
</subsection>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Notification, rule, etc., to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    notification issued under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 8 and 
    every rule made by the Central Government and every regulation made by the 
    Commission under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    issued or made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for 
    a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in 
    two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the notification or the rule or 
    the regulation, or both Houses agree that the notification or the rule or 
    the regulation should not be made, the notification or the rule or the 
    regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
    no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that notification or rule or regulation.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Power to 
    remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of 
    this Act, remove the difficulty:
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from 
    the date of commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order 
    made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid 
    before each House of Parliament.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Provisions relating to existing Vigilance Commission.—With 
    effect from the Constitution of the Commission under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 3, the Central Vigilance Commission set up by the Resolution of the 
    Government of India in the Ministry of Home Affairs No. 24/7/64-AVD, dated 
    the 11th February, 1964 (hereafter referred to in this section as the 
    existing Vigilance Commission) shall, insofar as its functions are not 
    inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, continue to discharge the said 
    functions and—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all actions and decisions taken by 
      the Vigilance Commission insofar as such actions and decisions are 
      relatable to the functions of the Commission constituted under this Act 
      shall be deemed to have been taken by the Commission;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all proceedings pending before the 
      Vigilance Commission, in so far as such proceedings relate to the 
      functions of the Commission, shall be deemed to be transferred to the 
      Commission and shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of 
      this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the employees of the Vigilance 
      Commission shall be deemed to have become the employees of the Commission 
      on the same terms and conditions;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    all the assets and liabilities of the 
      Vigilance Commission shall be transferred to the new Commission.
</subsection>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Appointments, etc., of officers of Directorate of Enforcement.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999) 
    or any other law for the time being in force,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Central Government 
      shall appoint a Director of Enforcement in the Directorate of Enforcement 
      in the Ministry of Finance on the recommendation of the Committee 
      consisting of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the Central Vigilance 
      Commissioner                      — Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Vigilance 
      Commissioners                                    — Members;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Secretary to the 
      Government of India                                
      in-charge of the Ministry of Home Affairs                       
      in the Central Government                                       
      — Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Secretary to the 
      Government of India                                
      in-charge of the Ministry of Personnel                              
      in the Central Government                                       
      — Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   Secretary to the Government 
      of India                                
      in-charge of the Department of Revenue,                         
      Ministry of Finance in the Central                                     
      Government                                                          
      —Member;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    while making a 
      recommendation, the Committee shall take into consideration the integrity 
      and experience of the officers eligible for appointment;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    no person below the 
      rank of Additional Secretary to the Government of India shall be eligible 
      for appointment as a Director of Enforcement;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    a Director of 
      Enforcement shall continue to hold office for a period of not less than 
      two years from the date on which he assumes office;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    a Director of 
      Enforcement shall not be transferred except with the previous consent of 
      the Committee referred to in clause (a);
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    the Committee referred 
      to in clause (a) shall, in consultation with the Director of Enforcement, 
      recommend officers for appointment to the posts above the level of the 
      Deputy Director of Enforcement and also recommend the extension or 
      curtailment of the tenure of such officers in the Directorate of 
      Enforcement;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    on receipt of the 
      recommendation under clause (f), the Central Government shall pass such 
      orders as it thinks fit to give effect to the said recommendation.
</section>

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Amendment of Act 25 of 1946.—In 
    the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    after section 1, the 
      following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 
“1A. Interpretation section.—Words 
      and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Central 
      Vigilance Commission Act, 2003, shall have the meanings, respectively, 
      assigned to them in that Act.”;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    for section 4, the 
      following sections shall be substituted, namely:—
 
“4. Superintendence and administration of 
      Special Police Establishment.—(1) The superintendence of the Delhi 
      Special Police Establishment insofar as it relates to investigation of 
      offences alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption 
      Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), shall vest in the Commission.
</section>
 <section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-section 
    (1), the superintendence of the said police establishment in all other 
    matters shall vest in the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The administration of the said police 
    establishment shall vest in an officer appointed in this behalf by the 
    Central Government (hereinafter referred to as the Director) who shall 
    exercise in respect of that police establishment such of the powers 
    exercisable by an Inspector-General of Police in respect of the police force 
    in a State as the Central Government may specify in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>4A</number> Committee for appointment of Director.—(1) 
    The Central Government shall appoint the Director on the recommendation of 
    the Committee consisting of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
      the Central Vigilance Commissioner                   — Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
      Vigilance Commissioners                                  
      — Members;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
      Secretary to the Government of India                        
      in-charge of the Ministry of Home                             
      Affairs in the Central Government                            
      — Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
      Secretary (Coordination and Public                          
      Grievances) in the Cabinet Secretariat                     
      — Member.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While 
    making any recommendation under sub-section (1), the Committee shall take 
    into consideration the views of the outgoing Director.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Committee shall recommend a panel of officers—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    on the basis of seniority, integrity and experience in the investigation of 
    anti-corruption cases; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    chosen from amongst officers belonging to the Indian Police Service 
    constituted under the All-India Services Act, 1951 (61 of 1951),
 
for being 
    considered for appointment as the Director.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4B</number> Terms and conditions of service of 
    Director.—(1) The Director shall, notwithstanding anything to the 
    contrary contained in the rules relating to his conditions of service, 
    continue to hold office for a period of not less than two years from the 
    date on which he assumes office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director shall not be transferred 
    except with the previous consent of the Committee referred to in sub-section 
    (1) of section 4A.
 </section><section>
<number>4C</number> Appointment for posts of Superintendent 
    of Police and above, extension and curtailment of their tenure, etc.—(1) 
    The Committee referred to in section 4A shall, after consulting the 
    Director, recommend officers for appointment to the posts of the level of 
    Superintendent of Police and above and also recommend the extension or 
    curtailment of the tenure of such officers in the Delhi Special Police 
    Establishment.t
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the recommendation under 
    sub-section (1), the Central Government shall pass such orders as it thinks 
    fit to give effect to the said recommendation.”;
 <subsection>
<number>c</number>    after section 6, the 
    following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 
“6A. Approval of Central Government to 
    conduct inquiry or investigation.—(1) The Delhi Special Police 
    Establishment shall not conduct any inquiry or investigation into any 
    offence alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption 
    Act, 1988 (49 of 1988) except with the previous approval of the Central 
    Government where such allegation relates to—
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    the employees of the 
    Central Government of the level of Joint Secretary and above; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such officers as are 
    appointed by the Central Government in corporations established by or under 
    any Central Act, Government companies, societies and local authorities owned 
    or controlled by that Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), no such approval 
    shall be necessary for cases involving arrest of a person on the spot on the 
    charge of accepting or attempting to accept any gratification other than 
    legal remuneration referred to in clause (c) of the Explanation to 
    section 7 of the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988).”.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Government of 
    India in the Ministry of Personnel, Public Grievances and Pensions 
    (Department of Personnel and Training) Resolution No. 371/20/99-AVD. III, 
    dated the 4th April, 1999 as amended vide Resolution of even number, 
    dated the 13th August, 2002 is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal and the cesser of operation of the Central 
    Vigilance Commission Ordinance, 1999, (Ord. 4 of 1999) anything done or any 
    action taken under the said Resolution and the said Ordinance including the 
    appointments made and other actions taken or anything done or any action 
    taken or any appointment made under the Delhi Special Police Establishment 
    Act, 1946 (25 of 1946) and the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 
    1973) as amended by the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made or 
    done or taken under this Act or the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 
    1946 and the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 as if the amendments made 
    in those Acts by this Act were in force at all material times.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 


    CENTRAL VIGILANCE COMMISSION ACT, 2003
 

 
 



 


The Schedule
 


    [See section 5(3)]
 


Form of oath or 
    affirmation to be made by the Central Vigilance Commissioner or Vigilance 
    Commissioner:—
 


          
    “I, A.B., having been appointed Central Vigilance Commissioner (or Vigilance 
    Commissioner) of the Central Vigilance Commission do swear in the name of 
    God/solemnly affirm
    that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the 
    Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the 
    sovereignty and integrity of India, that I will duly and faithfully and to 
    the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment perform the duties of my 
    office without fear or favour, affection or ill-will and that I will uphold 
    the Constitution and the laws.”. 




 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>     Subs. by G.S.R. 654 (E), 
    dated 28th September, 2004, for “inquiry referred to in clauses (b) and (c) 
    of sub-section (1) of section 8” (w.e.f. 1-10-2004).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>