<act><title>


the Redressal 
    of public GRIEVANCES rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Redressal of Public Grievances Rules, 1998.  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—These 
    rules shall apply to all the insurance companies operating in general 
    insurance business and in life insurance business:  
 
Provided that the Central Government may 
    exempt an insurance company from the provisions of these rules, if it is 
    satisfied that an insurance company has already a grievance redressal 
    machinery which fulfils the requirements of these rules.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> The 
    objects of these rules are to resolve all complaints relating to settlement 
    of claim on the part of insurance companies in cost‑effective, efficient and 
    impartial manner.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” 
    means Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    “Committee” means an Advisory Committee referred to in rule 19;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “financial year” means a period of twelve months commencing from the Ist day 
    of April of any year and ending on 31st day of March of the succeeding year;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “General 
    Insurance Corporation of India” means a government company formed under 
    sub‑section (1) of section 9 of the General Insurance Business (Nationalisation) 
    Act, 1972 and shall include a subsidiary company of such company;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    “governing body” means governing body of the Insurance Council constituted 
    under sub‑rule (1) of rule 5;
 


    1[(f)   Insurance 
    Council will consist of Life Insurance Corporation of India, General 
    Insurance Corporation of India and its four subsidiaries and other Insurance 
    Companies which will be permitted to do insurance business in future;]
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   
    “Insurance Regulatory Authority” means a body established by Government of 
    India vide Resolution No. 17(2)/94 Ins. V, dated 23‑1‑1996 to monitor 
    the orderly growth of insurance industry;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   
    “Insurance Company” means the Life Insurance Corporation of India, the 
    General Insurance Corporation of India and any other company which has been 
    given a licence to carry on business of life insurance or of general 
    insurance, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “insured 
    person” means an individual by whom or on whose behalf an insurance policy 
    has been taken on personal lines;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “Life 
    Insurance Corporation of India” means the Life Insurance Corporation of 
    India established under the Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   
    “personal lines” means an insurance policy taken or given in an individual 
    capacity.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Governing body of Insurance 
    Council.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be a governing body of 
    the Insurance Council which shall consist of one representative from each of 
    the insurance companies.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The representatives of an insurance 
    company shall ordinarily be Chairman or Managing Director or any one of the 
    Directors of such company.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The governing body shall formulate 
    its own procedure for conducting its business including the election of the 
    Chairman:  
 
Provided that the Chairman of the Life 
    Insurance Corporation of India shall act as the first Chairman of the 
    governing body.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Ombudsman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The governing body shall appoint one or more persons as Ombudsman for the 
    purpose of these rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Ombudsman selected may be drawn 
    from a wider circle including those who have experience or have been exposed 
    to the industry, civil service, administrative service, etc., in addition to 
    those drawn from judicial service.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An Ombudsman shall be appointed by 
    the governing body from a panel prepared by the committee consisting of—  
 <subsection>
              
    <number>a</number>   Chairman of Insurance Regulatory Authority                 —Chairman
 </subsection><subsection>
              
    <number>b</number>   Two representatives of Insurance Council including            

 

                         one each from the Life Insurance Business and 

 

                         from General Insurance Business 
    respectively               —Member
 </subsection><subsection>
              
    <number>c</number>   One representative of the Central Government             —Member
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Term of office.—An 
    Ombudsman shall be appointed for a term of three years and shall be eligible 
    for reappointment:  
 
Provided that no person shall hold 
    office as such Ombudsman after he has attained the age of 65 years.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Removal from office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An Ombudsman may be removed from service for gross misconduct committed by 
    him during his term of office.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The governing body may appoint such 
    person as it thinks fit to conduct enquiry in relation to misconduct of the 
    Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All enquiries on misconduct will be 
    sent to Insurance Regulatory Authority which may take a decision as to the 
    proposed action to be taken against the Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On recommendations of the Insurance 
    Regulatory Authority if the governing body is of opinion that the Ombudsman 
    is guilty of misconduct, it may terminate his services.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Remuneration, etc. of Ombudsman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be paid to the Ombudsman a salary which is equal to the salary 
    of the Judge of a High Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The other allowances and perquisites 
    of the Ombudsman shall be such as may be specified by the Central 
    Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Territorial jurisdiction of 
    Ombudsman.—
<section><number>1</number> The office of the Ombudsman shall 
    be located at such place as may be specified by the Insurance Council from 
    time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The governing body shall specify the 
    territorial jurisdiction of each Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Ombudsman may hold sitting at 
    various places within his area of jurisdiction in order to expedite disposal 
    of complaints.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Ombudsman shall have such secretarial staff as may be provided to him by 
    the Insurance Council after having consultation with the Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Ombudsman may engage the 
    services of professional expert with a view to assist him in discharging his 
    functions.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The salary, allowances and 
    perquisites payable to Ombudsman, the salary, allowances and other benefits 
    payable to the staff of the secretariat and all expenses incurred for the 
    purposes of these rules shall be borne by the Insurance Council.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Ombudsman shall prepare the 
    budget indicating the requirement of funds before the beginning of every 
    financial year.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The budget of the office of 
    Ombudsman will be sent to the governing body.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The governing body will finalise the 
    budget in consultation with the Ombudsman and shall allocate the funds to 
    the office of Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The total expenses on Ombudsman and 
    his staff shall be incurred by the insurance companies who are members of 
    the Insurance Council in such proportion as may be decided by the governing 
    body from time to time:  
 
Provided that till a decision is taken 
    by the governing body, the entire expenditure shall be shared equally 
    between the insurance companies in the life insurance business and general 
    insurance business in equal proportion.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The share of expenditure which is to 
    be incurred by each insurance company shall be in the ratio of premium 
    income for the previous year of such company.  
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this sub‑rule “premium income” means the gross direct premium 
    income of the insurer without taking into account from time to time income 
    on re-insurance accepted by the insurance company.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power of Ombudsman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Ombudsman may receive and consider—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    complaints under rule 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    partial or total repudiation of claims by an insurer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any 
    dispute in regard to premium paid or payable in terms of the policy;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   any 
    dispute on the legal construction of the policies insofar as such disputes 
    relate to claims;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   delay in 
    settlement of claims;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   
    non‑issue of any insurance document to customers after receipt of premium.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Ombudsman shall act as 
    counsellor and mediator in matters which are within his terms of reference 
    and, if requested to do so in writing by mutual agreement by the insured 
    person and insurance company.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Ombudsman’s decision whether the 
    complaint is fit and proper for being considered by it or not, shall be 
    final.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Manner in which complaint is to 
    be made.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person who has a grievance 
    against an insurer, may himself or through his legal heirs make a complaint 
    in writing to the Ombudsman within whose jurisdiction the branch or office 
    of the insurer complained against is located.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The complaint shall be in writing 
    duly signed by the complainant or through his legal heirs and shall state 
    clearly the name and address of the complainant, the name of the branch or 
    office of the insurer against which the complaint is made, the fact giving 
    rise to complaint supported by documents, if any, relied on by the 
    complainant, the nature and extent of the loss caused to the complainant and 
    the relief sought from the Ombudsman.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No complaint to the Ombudsman shall 
    lie unless—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   The 
    complainants had before making a complaint to the Ombudsman made a written 
    representation to the insurer named in the complaint and either insurer had 
    rejected the complaint or the complainant had not received any reply within 
    a period of one month after the insurer concerned received his 
    representation or the complainant is not satisfied with the reply given to 
    him by the insurer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   The 
    complaint is made not later than one year after the insurer had rejected the 
    representation or sent his final reply on the representation of the 
    complainant; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   The 
    complaint is not on the same subject-matter, for which any proceedings 
    before any court, or Consumer Forum, or arbitrator is pending or were so 
    earlier.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Ombudsman to act 
      fairly and equitably.—
<section><number>1</number> The Ombudsman may, if he 
      deems fit, adopt a procedure other than mentioned in sub-rules (1) and (2) 
      of rule 13 for dealing with a claim:  
 Provided that the Ombudsman 
      may ask the parties for necessary papers in support of their respective 
      claims and where he considers necessary, he may collect factual 
      information available with the insurance company.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Ombudsman shall 
      dispose of a complaint fairly and equitably.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Recommendations made by the 
    Ombudsman.—
<section><number>1</number> When a complaint is settled, 
    through mediation of the Ombudsman, undertaken by him in pursuance of 
    request made in writing by complainant and insurer through mutual agreement, 
    the Ombudsman shall make a recommendation which he thinks fair in the 
    circumstances of the case. The copies of the recommendation shall be sent to 
    the complainant and the insurance company concerned. Such recommendation 
    shall be made not later than one month from the date of the receipt of the 
    complaint.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a complainant accepts the 
    recommendation of the Ombudsman, he will send a communication in writing 
    within 15 days of the date of receipt of the recommendation. He will confirm 
    his acceptance to Ombudsman and state clearly that the settlement reached is 
    acceptable to him, in totality, in terms of recommendations made by the 
    Ombudsman in full and final settlement of complaint.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Ombudsman shall send to the 
    insurance company a copy of the recommendation along with the acceptance 
    letter received from the complainant. The insurer shall thereupon comply 
    with the terms of the recommendations immediately not later than 15 days of 
    the receipt of such recommendation and the insurer shall inform the 
    Ombudsman of its compliance.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Award.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the complaint is not settled by agreement under rule 15, the Ombudsman 
    shall pass an award which he thinks fair in the facts and circumstances of a 
    claim.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An award shall be in writing and 
    shall state the amount awarded to the complainant:  
 
Provided that Ombudsman shall not award 
    any compensation in excess of which is necessary to cover the loss suffered 
    by the complainant as a direct consequence of the insured peril, or for an 
    amount not exceeding rupees twenty lakhs (including ex gratia and 
    other expenses), whichever is lower.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Ombudsman shall pass an award 
    within a period of three months from the receipt of the complaint.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A copy of the award shall be sent to 
    the complainant and the insurer named in the complaint.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The complainant shall furnish to the 
    insurer within a period of one month from the date of receipt of the award, 
    a letter of acceptance that the award is in full and final settlement of his 
    claim.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The insurer shall comply with the 
    award within 15 days of the receipt of the acceptance letter under sub‑rule 
    (5) and it shall intimate the compliance to the Ombudsman.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Consequences of non‑acceptance of 
    award.—If the complainant does not intimate the 
    acceptance under sub‑rule (5) of rule 16, the award may not be implemented 
    by the insurance company.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Power to make ex gratia 
    payment.—If the Ombudsman deems fit, he may award 
    an ex gratia payment.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Advisory Committee.—An 
    Advisory Committee of not exceeding five eminent persons shall be notified 
    by the Government to assist the Insurance Regulatory Authority to review the 
    performance of the Ombudsman from time to time. The Insurance Regulatory 
    Authority shall decide the time, venue and quorum of such meeting. The 
    authority after discussing the matter with the governing body, may recommend 
    to Government appropriate proposals for effecting improvements in the 
    functioning of Ombudsman. In the light of recommendations made by the 
    Insurance Regulatory Authority, the Government may carry out such amendments 
    to these rules as it may deem fit.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Annual Report.—The 
    Ombudsman shall furnish a report every year containing a general review of 
    the activities of the office of the Ombudsman during preceding financial 
    year to the Central Government and such other information as may be 
    considered necessary by it. In the Annual Report, the Ombudsman will make an 
    annual review of the quality of services rendered by the insurer and make 
    recommendations to improve these services.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Recommendation of the Insurance 
    Council.—The Insurance Council may suggest to the 
    Ombudsman such recommendations as it deems fit and which in its opinion will 
    enhance the utility of the Annual Report and also so that the objectives of 
    the rules are clearly analysed in terms of the activities in the year under 
    review. Suggestion for long-term improvement of insurance sector will be 
    incorporated by the Ombudsman in his report. 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>