<act><tid>1997854</tid>
<title>THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 9th May, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances 
Act, <year>1985</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>844486</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>957699</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1909994</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act, and any 
reference in any provision to the commencement of this Act shall be 
construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1263233</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 1.- In the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic 
Substances Act, <year>1985</year> (61 of <year>1985</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in section 1, in sub- section (2), after the words 
" whole of India", the following shall be inserted, namely:-
" and it applies also-

<section><tid>1860389</tid>
<number>a</number>to all citizens of India outside India;

</section>

<section><tid>1767045</tid>
<number>b</number>to all persons on ships and aircrafts registered in India,
wherever they may be".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>858688</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1378009</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (i), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (i)" addict" means a person who has dependence on any narcotic drug 
or psychotropic substance;';


</section>

<section><tid>1248679</tid>
<number>b</number>clause (viia) shall be relettered as clause (viid) and before 
clause (viid) as so relettered, the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' (viia)" commercial quantity", in relation to narcotic drugs and 
psychotropic substances, means any quantity greater than the quantity 
specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette;


</section>

<section><tid>1383712</tid>
<number>viib</number>" controlled delivery" means the technique of allowing illicit 
or suspect consignments of narcotic drugs, psychotropic substances, 
controlled substances or substances substituted for them to pass out 
of, or through or into the territory of India with the knowledge and 
under the supervision of an officer empowered in this behalf or duly 
authorised under section 50A with a view to identifying the persons 
involved in the commission of an offence under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1158901</tid>
<number>viic</number>" corresponding law" means any law corresponding to the 
provisions of this Act;';

</section>

<section><tid>289341</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause (xxiii), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (xxiiia)" small quantity", in relation to narcotic drugs and 
psychotropic substances, means any quantity lesser than the quantity 
specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>450439</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 7A.- In section 7A of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections (2) and (3), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) The Fund shall be applied by the Central Government to meet the 
expenditure incurred in connection with the measures taken for-

<section><tid>1649814</tid>
<number>a</number>combating illicit traffic in narcotic drugs, psychotropic 
substances or controlled substances;

</section>

<section><tid>1347096</tid>
<number>b</number>controlling the abuse of narcotic drugs and psychotropic 
substances;

</section>

<section><tid>280031</tid>
<number>c</number>identifying, treating, rehabilitating addicts;

</section>

<section><tid>1080029</tid>
<number>d</number>preventing drug abuse;

</section>

<section><tid>211742</tid>
<number>e</number>educating public against drug abuse; and

</section>

<section><tid>1316106</tid>
<number>f</number>supplying drugs to addicts where such supply is a medical 
necessity.

<subsection><tid>1946361</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may constitute a Governing Body as it 
thinks fit to advise that Government and to sanction money out of the 
said Fund subject to the limit notified by the Central Government in 
the Official Gazette.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594611</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 8A.- After section 8 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
' 8A. Prohibition of certain activities relating to property derived 
from offence.- No person shall-

<section><tid>1733272</tid>
<number>a</number>convert or transfer any property knowing that such property is 
derived from an offence committed under this Act or under any other 
corresponding law of any other country or from an act of participation 
in such offence, for the purpose of concealing or disguising the 
illicit origin of the property or to assist any person in the 
commission of an offence or to evade the legal consequences; or

</section>

<section><tid>1953073</tid>
<number>b</number>conceal or disguise the true nature, source, location, disposition 
of any property knowing that such property is derived from an offence 
committed under this Act or under any other corresponding law of any 
other country; or

</section>

<section><tid>1193242</tid>
<number>c</number>knowingly acquire, possess or use any property which was derived 
from an offence committed under this Act or under any other 
corresponding law of any other country.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1320388</tid>
<number> 6</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 15 to 18.- For sections 
 15 to 18 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" 15. Punishment for contravention in relation to poppy straw.- 
Whoever, in contravention of any provisions of this Act or any rule or 
order made or condition of a licence granted thereunder, produces, 
possesses, transports, imports inter- State, exports inter- State, 
sells, purchases, uses or omits to warehouse poppy straw or removes or 
does any act in respect of warehoused poppy straw shall be 
punishable,-

<section><tid>310025</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both;

</section>

<section><tid>1697859</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves quantity lesser than commercial 
quantity but greater than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may 
extend to one lakh rupees;

</section>

<section><tid>326015</tid>
<number>c</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees but which may 
extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1256099</tid>
<number>16</number>Punishment for contravention in relation to coca plant and coca 
leaves.- Whoever, in contravention of any provision of this Act or any 
rule or order made or condition of licence granted thereunder, 
cultivates any coca plant or gathers any portion of a coca plant or 
produces, possesses, sells, purchases, transports, imports 
inter- State, exports inter- State or uses coca leaves shall be 
punishable with rigourous imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
ten years, and with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>1359647</tid>
<number> 17</number> Punishment for contravention in relation to prepared 
opium.- Whoever, in contravention of any provision of this Act or any 
rule or order made or condition of licence granted thereunder, 
manufactures, possesses, sells, purchases, transports, imports 
inter- State, exports inter- State or uses prepared opium shall be 
punishable-
<section><tid>367684</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both; or

</section>

<section><tid>54793</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves quantity lesser than commercial 
quantity but greater than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may 
extend to one lakh rupees; or

</section>

<section><tid>1266255</tid>
<number>c</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees but which may 
extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1068257</tid>
<number> 18</number> Punishment for contravention in relation to opium poppy and 
opium.- Whoever, in contravention of any provision of this Act or any 
rule or order made or condition of licence granted thereunder, 
cultivates the opium poppy or produces, manufactures, possesses, 
sells, purchases, transports, imports inter- State, exports inter- State 
or uses opium shall be punishable,-
<section><tid>1376779</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both;

</section>

<section><tid>1171458</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees which may extend 
to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees;


</section>

<section><tid>1061668</tid>
<number>c</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment which may extend to 
ten years and with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932688</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 20.- In section 20 of the principal Act, in 
clause (b), for sub- clauses (i) and (ii), the following sub- clauses 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (i) where such contravention relates to clause (a) with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years, and shall also 
be liable to fine which may extend to one lakh rupees; and

<section><tid>847316</tid>
<number>ii</number>where such contravention relates to sub- clause (b),-

<subsection><tid>1969462</tid>
<number>A</number>and involves small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to ten 
thousand rupees, or with both;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1424877</tid>
<number>B</number>and involves quantity lesser than commercial quantity but greater 
than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to ten years, and with fine which may extend to one lakh 
rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>651934</tid>
<number>C</number>and involves commercial quantity, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than ten years which may extend to twenty 
years and shall also be liable to fine which shall not be less than 
one lakh rupees but which may extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1468184</tid>
<number> 8</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 21 to 23.- For sections 
 21 to 23 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" 21. Punishment for contravention in relation to manufactured drugs 
and preparations.- Whoever, in contravention of any provision of this 
Act or any rule or order made or condition of licence granted 
thereunder, manufactures, possesses, sells, purchases, transports, 
imports inter- State, exports inter- State or uses any manufactured drug 
or any preparation containing any manufactured drug shall be 
punishable,-

<section><tid>1166848</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both;

</section>

<section><tid>1398260</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves quantity, lesser than commercial 
quantity but greater than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may 
extend to one lakh rupees;

</section>

<section><tid>535664</tid>
<number>c</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees but which may 
extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>766607</tid>
<number> 22</number> Punishment for contravention in relation to psychotropic 
substances.- Whoever, in contravention of any provision of this Act or 
any rule or order made or condition of licence granted thereunder, 
manufacturers, possesses, sells, purchases, transports, imports 
inter- State, exports inter- State or uses any psychotropic substance 
shall be punishable,-
<section><tid>1178655</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both;

</section>

<section><tid>875131</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves quantity, lesser than commercial 
quantity but greater than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may 
extend to one lakh rupees;

</section>

<section><tid>863704</tid>
<number>c</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees but which may 
extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1366047</tid>
<number> 23</number> Punishment for illegal import into India, export from India or 
transhipment of narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances.- Whoever, 
in contravention of any provision of this Act or any rule or order 
made or condition of licence or permit granted or certificate or 
authorisation issued thereunder, imports into India or exports from 
India or tranships any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance shall 
be punishable,-
<section><tid>526616</tid>
<number>a</number>where the contravention involves small quantity, with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both;

</section>

<section><tid>1342591</tid>
<number>b</number>where the contravention involves quantity, lesser than commercial 
quantity but greater than small quantity, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may 
extend to one lakh rupees;

</section>

<section><tid>1265265</tid>
<number>c</number>where the contravention involves commercial quantity, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than ten 
years but which may extend to twenty years, and shall also be liable 
to fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees but which may 
extend to two lakh rupees:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding two lakh rupees.".


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1998675</tid>
<number>9</number>Substitution of new section for section 25.- For section 25 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 25. Punishment for allowing premises, etc., to be used for 
commission of an offence.- Whoever, being the owner or occupier or 
having the control or use of any house, room, enclosure, space, place, 
animal or conveyance, knowingly permits it to be used for the 
commission by any other person of an offence punishable under any 
provision of this Act, shall be punishable with the punishment 
provided for that offence.".



</article>



<article><tid>781140</tid>
<number> 10</number> Substitution of new section for section 27.- For section 27 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 27. Punishment for consumption of any narcotic drug or psychotropic 
substance.- Whoever consumes any narcotic drug or psychotropic 
substance shall be punishable,-

<section><tid>1229415</tid>
<number>a</number>where the narcotic drug or psychotropic substance consumed is 
cocaine, morphine, diacetyl- morphine or any other narcotic drug or any 
psychotropic substance as may be specified in this behalf by the 
Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with 
fine which may extend to twenty thousand rupees, or with both; and

</section>

<section><tid>1511289</tid>
<number>b</number>where the narcotic drug or psychotropic substance consumed is 
other than those specified in or under clause (a), with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1068145</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 30.- In section 30 of the principal Act, for 
the words, figures and brackets" section 15 to section 25 (both  
  inclusive) and from the circumstances of the case", the words, figures 
and letter" sections 19, 24 and 27A and for offences involving 
commercial quantity of any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance and 
from the circumstances of the case" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1567374</tid>
<number> 12</number> Substitution of new section for section 31.- For section 31 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 31. Enhanced punishment for offences after previous conviction.- (1) 
If any person who has been convicted of the commission of, or attempt 
to commit, or abetment of, or criminal conspiracy to commit, any of 
the offences punishable under this Act is subsequently convicted of 
the commission of, or attempt to commit, or abetment of, or criminal 
conspiracy to commit, an offence punishable under this Act with the 
same amount of punishment shall be punished for the second and every 
subsequent offence with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one- half of the maximum term of imprisonment, and also be 
liable to fine which shall extend to one- half of the maximum amount of 
fine.

<section><tid>960067</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the person referred to in sub- section (1) is liable to be 
punished with a minimum term of imprisonment and to a minimum amount 
of fine, the minimum punishment for such person shall be one- half of 
the minimum term of imprisonment and one- half of the minimum amount of 
fine:
Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in the 
judgment, impose a fine exceeding the fine for which a person is 
liable.


</section>

<section><tid>143435</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any person is convicted by a competent court of criminal 
jurisdiction outside India under any corresponding law, such person, 
in respect of such conviction, shall be dealt with for the purposes of 
sub- sections (1) and (2) as if he had been convicted by a court in 
India.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1203851</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 31A.- In section 31A of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>531633</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>743864</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words, figures, brackets and letter" section 15 to section 
 25 (both inclusive) or section 27A", the words, figures and letter 
" section 19, section 24, section 27A and for offences involving 
commercial quantity of any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681106</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- clause (a), in the Table, in column (2), against entry 
 (viii), for the figures and word" 1, 500 grams", the words" lesser of 
the quantity between the quantities given against the respective 
narcotic drugs or psychotropic substances mentioned above forming part 
of the mixture" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>582301</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words, figures, brackets and letter 
" section 15 to section 25 (both inclusive), section 27A, section 28 or 
section 29", the words, figures and letter" section 19, section 24 or 
section 27A and for offences involving commercial quantity of any 
narcotic drug or psychotropic substance" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1272044</tid>
<number> 14</number> Insertion of new section 32B.- After section 32A of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 32B. Factors to be taken into account for imposing higher than the 
minimum punishment.- Where a minimum term of imprisonment or amount of 
fine is prescribed for any offence committed under this Act, the court 
may, in addition to such factors as it may deem fit, take into account 
the following factors for imposing a punishment higher than the 
minimum term of imprisonment or amount of fine, namely:-

<section><tid>1919312</tid>
<number>a</number>the use or threat of use of violence or arms by the offender;

</section>

<section><tid>54671</tid>
<number>b</number>the fact that the offender holds a public office and that he has 
taken advantage of that office in committing the offence;

</section>

<section><tid>1385356</tid>
<number>c</number>the fact that the minors are affected by the offence or the minors 
are used for the commission of an offence;

</section>

<section><tid>1279176</tid>
<number>d</number>the fact that the offence is committed in an educational 
institution or social service facility or in the immediate vicinity of 
such institution or faculty or in other place to which school children 
and students resort for educational, sports and social activities;

</section>

<section><tid>395413</tid>
<number>e</number>the fact that the offender belongs to organised international or 
any other criminal group which is involved in the commission of the 
offence; and

</section>

<section><tid>1948142</tid>
<number>f</number>the fact that the offender is involved in other illegal activities 
facilitated by commission of the offence.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1056967</tid>
<number> 15</number> Substitution of new section for section 36A.- For section 36A of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' 36A. Offences triable by Special Courts.- (1) Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>),-

<section><tid>552058</tid>
<number>a</number>all offences under this Act which are punishable with imprisonment 
for a term of more than three years shall be triable only by the 
Special Court constituted for the area in which the offence has been 
committed or where there are more Special Courts than one for such 
area, by such one of them as may be specified in this behalf by the 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>132829</tid>
<number>b</number>where a person accused of or suspected of the commission of an 
offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate under sub- section 
 (2) or sub- section (2A) of section 167 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), such Magistrate may authorise the 
detention of such person in such custody as he thinks fit for a period 
not exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such Magistrate is a 
Judicial Magistrate and seven days in the whole where such Magistrate 
is an Executive Magistrate:
Provided that in cases which are triable by the Special Court where 
such Magistrate considers-


<subsection><tid>1804309</tid>
<number>i</number>when such person is forwarded to him as aforesaid; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>424786</tid>
<number>ii</number>upon or at any time before the expiry of the period of detention 
authorised by him,
that the detention of such person is unnecessary, he shall order such 
person to be forwarded to the Special Court having jurisdiction;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>443381</tid>
<number>c</number>the Special Court may exercise, in relation to the person 
forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power which a Magistrate 
having jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under section 167 of 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), in relation to an 
accused person in such case who has been forwarded to him under that 
section;

</section>

<section><tid>477435</tid>
<number>d</number>a Special Court may, upon perusal of police report of the facts 
constituting an offence under this Act or upon complaint made by an 
officer of the Central Government or a State Government authorised in 
this behalf, take cognizance of that offence without the accused being 
committed to it for trial.

<subsection><tid>1842941</tid>
<number>2</number>When trying an offence under this Act, a Special Court may also 
try an offence other than an offence under this Act with which the 
accused may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), 
be charged at the same trial.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1728979</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
special powers of the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), and the High Court 
may exercise such powers including the power under clause (b) of 
sub- section (1) of that section as if the reference to" Magistrate" in 
that section included also a reference to a" Special Court" 
constituted under section 36.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1200394</tid>
<number>4</number>In respect of persons accused of an offence punishable under 
section 19 or section 24 or section 27A or for offences involving 
commercial quantity the references in sub- section (2) of section 167 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>) thereof to" ninety 
days", where they occur, shall be construed as reference to" one 
hundred and eighty days":
Provided that, if it is not possible to complete the investigation 
within the said period of one hundred and eighty days, the Special 
Court may extend the said period up to one year on the report of the 
Public Prosecutor indicating the progress of the investigation and the 
specific reasons for the detention of the accused beyond the said 
period of one hundred and eighty days.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1815448</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), the offences punishable under this Act 
with imprisonment for a term of not more than three years may be tried 
summarily.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1256099</tid>
<number> 16</number> Substitution of new section for section 36D.- For section 36D of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 36D. Transitional provisions.- (1) Any offence committed under this 
Act on or after the commencement of the Narcotic Drugs and 
Psychotropic Substances (Amendment) Act, <year>1988</year> (2 of <year>1989</year>), which is 
triable by a Special Court shall, until a Special Court is constituted 
under section 36, notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), be tried by a Court of Session.

<section><tid>1732378</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any proceedings in relation to any offence committed under 
this Act on or after the commencement of the Narcotic Drugs and 
Psychotropic Substances (Amendment) Act, <year>1988</year> (2 of <year>1989</year>) are pending 
before a Court of Session, then, notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub- section (1), such proceeding shall be heard and disposed of by the 
Court of Session:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall affect the 
power of the High Court under section 407 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>) to transfer any case or class of cases 
taken cognizance by a Court of Session under sub- section (1).".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1359647</tid>
<number>17</number>Amendment of section 37.- In section 37 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (b), for the words" a term of imprisonment 
of five years or more under this Act", the words, figures and letter 
" offences under section 19 or section 24 or section 27A and also for 
offences involving commercial quantity" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1068257</tid>
<number>18</number>Amendment of section 39.- In section 39 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after the words and figures" under section 27", the 
words" or for offences relating to small quantity of any narcotic drug 
or psychotropic substance" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>48633</tid>
<number> 19</number> Substitution of new sections for section 41 to 43.- For sections 
 41 to 43 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' 41. Power to issue warrant and authorisation.- (1) A Metropolitan 
Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class or any Magistrate of the 
second class specially empowered by the State Government in this 
behalf, may issue a warrant for the arrest of any person whom he has 
reason to believe to have committed any offence punishable under this 
Act, or for the search, whether by day or by night, of any building, 
conveyance or place in which he has reason to believe any narcotic 
drug or psychotropic substance or controlled substance in respect of 
which an offence punishable under this Act has been committed or any 
document or other article which may furnish evidence of the commission 
of such offence or any illegally acquired property or any document or 
other article which may furnish evidence of holding any illegally 
acquired property which is liable for seizure or freezing or 
forfeiture under Chapter VA of this Act is kept or concealed.

<section><tid>1895459</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such officer of gazetted rank of the departments of central 
excise, narcotics, customs, revenue intelligence or any other 
department of the Central Government including the para- military 
forces or the armed forces as is empowered in this behalf by general 
or special order by the Central Government, or any such officer of the 
revenue, drugs control, excise, police or any other department of a 
State Government as if empowered in this behalf by general or special 
order of the State Government if he has reason to believe from 
personal knowledge or information given by any person and taken in 
writing that any person has committed an offence punishable under this 
Act or that any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance or controlled 
substance in respect of which any offence under this Act has been 
committed or any document or other article which may furnish evidence 
of the commission of such offence or any illegally acquired property 
or any document or other article which may furnish evidence of holding 
any illegally acquired property which is liable for seizure or 
freezing or forfeiture under Chapter VA of this Act is kept or 
concealed in any building, conveyance or place, may authorise any 
officer subordinate to him but superior in rank to a peon, sepoy or a 
constable to arrest such a person or search a building, conveyance or 
place whether by day or by night or himself arrest such a person or 
search a building, conveyance or place.

</section>

<section><tid>821014</tid>
<number>3</number>The officer to whom a warrant under sub- section (1) is addressed 
and the officer who authorised the arrest or search or the officer who 
is so authorised under sub- section (2) shall have all the powers of an 
officer acting under section 42.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>793053</tid>
<number> 42</number> Power of entry, search, seizure and arrest without warrant or 
authorisation.-
<section><tid>815746</tid>
<number>1</number>Any such officer (being an officer superior in rank   
  to a peon, sepoy or constable) of the departments of central excise, 
narcotics, customs, revenue intelligence or any other department of 
the Central Government including para- military or armed forces as is 
empowered in this behalf by general or special order by the Central 
Government, or any such officer (being an officer superior in rank to  
  a peon, sepoy or constable) of the revenue, drugs control, excise, 
police or any other department of a State Government as is empowered 
in this behalf by general knowledge or information given by any person 
and taken down in writing that any narcotic drug, or psychotropic 
substance, or controlled substance in respect of which an offence 
punishable under this Act has been committed or any document or other 
article which may furnish evidence of the commission of such offence 
or any illegally acquired property or any document or other article 
which may furnish evidence of holding any illegally acquired property 
which is liable for seizure or freezing or forfeiture under Chapter VA 
of this Act is kept or concealed in any building, conveyance or 
enclosed place, may between sunrise and subset,-

<subsection><tid>1620891</tid>
<number>a</number>enter into and search any such building, conveyance or place;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>620635</tid>
<number>b</number>in case of resistance, break open any door and remove any obstacle 
to such entry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>892445</tid>
<number>c</number>seize such drug or substance and all materials used in the 
manufacture thereof and any other article and any animal or conveyance 
which he has reason to believe to be liable to confiscation under this 
Act and any document or other article which he has reason to believe 
may furnish evidence of the commission of any offence punishable under 
this Act or furnish evidence of holding any illegally acquired 
property which is liable for seizure or freezing or forfeiture under 
Chapter VA of this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1134432</tid>
<number>d</number>detail and search, and, if he thinks proper, arrest any person 
whom he has reason to believe to have committed any offence punishable 
under this Act:
Provided that if such officer has reason to believe that a search 
warrant or authorisation cannot be obtained without affording 
opportunity for the concealment of evidence or facility for the escape 
of an offender, he may enter and search such building, conveyance or 
enclosed place at any time between sunset and sunrise after recording 
the grounds of his belief.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>328570</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an officer takes down any information in writing under 
sub- section (1) or records grounds for his belief under the proviso 
thereto, he shall within seventy- two hours send a copy thereof to his 
immediate official superior.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1838694</tid>
<number> 43</number> Power of seizure and arrest in public place.- Any officer of any 
of the departments mentioned in section 42 may-
<section><tid>1383336</tid>
<number>a</number>seize in any public place or in transit, any narcotic drug or 
psychotropic substance or controlled substance in respect of which he 
has reason to believe an offence punishable under this Act has been 
committed, and, along with such drug or substance, any animal or 
conveyance or article liable to confiscation under this Act, any 
document or other article which he has reason to believe may furnish 
evidence of the commission of an offence punishable under this Act or 
any document or other article which may furnish evidence of holding 
any illegally acquired property which is liable for seizure or 
freezing or forfeiture under Chapter VA of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>457926</tid>
<number>b</number>detain and search any person whom he has reason to believe to have 
committed an offence punishable under this Act, and if such person has 
any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance or controlled substance in 
his possession and such possession appears to him to be unlawful, 
arrest him and any other person in his company.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expression" public 
place" includes any public conveyance, hotel, shop, or other place 
intended for use by, or accessible to, the public.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>387903</tid>
<number>20</number>Amendment of section 44.- In section 44 of the principal Act, 
after the words" psychotropic substance", the words" or controlled 
substance" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>396073</tid>
<number> 21</number> Amendment of section 49.- In section 49 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (4), the following sub- sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (5) When an officer duly authorised under section 42 has reason to 
believe that it is not possible to take the person to be searched to 
the nearest Gazetted Officer or Magistrate without the possibility of 
the person to be searched parting with possession of any narcotic drug 
or psychotropic substance, or controlled substance or article or 
document, he may, instead of taking such person to the nearest 
Gazetted Officer or Magistrate, proceed to search the person as 
provided under section 100 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2  
  of <year>1974</year>).

<section><tid>166282</tid>
<number>6</number>After a search is conducted under sub- section (5), the officer 
shall record the reasons for such belief which necessitated such 
search and within seventy- two hours send a copy thereof to his 
immediate official superior.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1366047</tid>
<number> 23</number> Insertion of new section 50A.- After section 50 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 50A. Power to undertake controlled delivery.- The Director General of 
Narcotics Control Bureau constituted under sub- section (3) of section 
 4 or any other officer authorised by him in this behalf, may, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, undertake controlled 
delivery of any consignment to-

<section><tid>526616</tid>
<number>a</number>any destination in India;

</section>

<section><tid>1342591</tid>
<number>b</number>a foreign country, in consultation with the competent authority of 
such foreign country to which such consignment is destined, in such 
manner as may be prescribed.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1787869</tid>
<number> 24</number> Amendment of section 53.- In section 53 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>260795</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" or Border Security Force", the 
words" or any other department of the Central Government including 
para- military forces or armed forces" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1202492</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), after the word" excise", the words" or any 
other department" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088891</tid>
<number> 25</number> Substitution of new section for section 54.- For section 54 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 54. Presumption from possession of illicit articles.- In trials under 
this Act, it may be presumed, unless and until the contrary is proved, 
that the accused has committed an offence under this Act in respect 
of-

<section><tid>986878</tid>
<number>a</number>any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance or controlled 
substance;

</section>

<section><tid>87332</tid>
<number>b</number>any opium poppy, cannabis plant or coca plant growing on any land 
which he has cultivated;

</section>

<section><tid>1402356</tid>
<number>c</number>any apparatus specially designed or any group of utensils 
specially adopted for the manufacture of any narcotic drug or 
psychotropic substance or controlled substance; or

</section>

<section><tid>782090</tid>
<number>d</number>any materials which have undergone any process towards the 
manufacture of a narcotic drug or psychotropic substance or controlled 
substance, or any residue left of the materials from which any 
narcotic drug or psychotropic substance or controlled substance has 
been manufactured,
for the possession of which he fails to account satisfactorily.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1802228</tid>
<number> 26</number> Amendment of section 60.- In section 60 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>145853</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) Whenever any offence punishable under this Act has been 
committed, the narcotic drug, psychotropic substance, controlled 
substance, opium poppy, coca plant, cannabis plant, materials, 
apparatus and utensils in respect of which or by means of which such 
offence has been committed, shall be liable to confiscation.";


</section>

<section><tid>1496077</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- sections (2) and (3), after the words" psychotropic 
substance", wherever they occur, the words" or controlled substances" 
shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1448312</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of section 61.- In section 61 of the principal Act, for 
the words" narcotic drug or psychotropic substance", the words 
" narcotic drug, psychotropic substance or controlled substance" shall 
be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1647884</tid>
<number>28</number>Amendment of section 62.- In section 62 of the principal Act, for 
the words" narcotic drug or psychotropic substance", the words 
" narcotic drug, psychotropic substance or controlled substance" shall 
be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1178923</tid>
<number> 29</number> Amendment of section 63.- In section 63 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1570905</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), in the second proviso, after the words 
" psychotropic substance", the words" controlled substance" shall be 
inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>178757</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (3) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1375682</tid>
<number>30</number>Substitution of new section for section 64A.- For section 64A of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 64A. Immunity from prosecution to addicts volunteering for 
treatment.- Any addict, who is charged with an offence punishable under 
section 27 or with offences involving small quantity of narcotic drugs 
or psychotropic substances, who voluntarily seeks to undergo medical 
treatment for de- addiction from a hospital or an institution 
maintained or recognised by the Government or a local authority and 
undergoes such treatment shall not be liable to prosecution under 
section 27 or under any other section for offences involving small 
quantity of narcotic drugs or psychotropic substances:

Provided that the said immunity from prosecution may be withdrawn if 
the addict does not undergo the complete treatment for de- addiction.".



</article>



<article><tid>1031352</tid>
<number> 31</number> Amendment of section 68A.- In section 68A of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>992365</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the word" five", the word" ten" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1540642</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (c), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (cc) every person who has been arrested or against whom a warrant or 
authorisation of arrest has been issued for the commission of an 
offence punishable under this Act with imprisonment for a term of ten 
years or more, and every person who has been arrested or against whom 
a warrant or authorisation of arrest has been issued for the 
commission of a similar offence under any corresponding law of any 
other country;";


</section>

<section><tid>454203</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clauses (d), (e) and (f), after the word, brackets and letter 
" clause (c)", the words, brackets and letters" or clause (cc)" shall 
be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>851035</tid>
<number>32</number>Amendment of section 68B.- In section 68B of the principal Act, in 
clause (g), in sub- clause (i), for the words" illicit traffic", the 
words" the contravention of any provisions of this Act" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1593646</tid>
<number>33</number>Amendment of section 68C.- In section 68C of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the proviso, the following proviso shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" Provided that no property shall be forfeited under this Chapter if 
such property was acquired, by a person to whom this Act applies, 
before a period of six years from the date he was arrested or against 
whom a warrant or authorisation of arrest has been issued for the 
commission of an offence punishable under this Act or from the date 
the order or detention was issued, as the case may be.".



</article>



<article><tid>100902</tid>
<number>34</number>Amendment of section 68E.- In section 68E of the principal Act, 
for sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) Every officer empowered under section 53 and every 
officer- in- charge of a police station shall, on receipt of information 
is satisfied that any person to whom this Chapter applies holds any 
illegally acquired property, he may, after recording reasons for doing 
so, proceed to take all steps necessary for tracing and identifying 
such property.".



</article>



<article><tid>721386</tid>
<number>36</number>Amendment of section 68-I.- In section 68-I of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (3), the following proviso shall be inserted, at the 
end, namely:-
" Provided that no illegally acquired property of any person who is 
referred to in clause (cc) of sub- section (2) of section 68A or 
relative of a person referred to in that clause or associate of a 
person referred to in that clause or holder of any property which was 
at any time previously held by a person referred to in that clause 
shall stand forfeited.".



</article>



<article><tid>1375088</tid>
<number> 37</number> Amendment of section 68-O.- In section 68-O of the principal Act, 
in sub- section 1, for the words" Any person aggrieved by an order of 
the competent authority", the words, brackets, figures and letter" Any 
officer referred to in sub- section
<section><tid>1522529</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 68E or any person  
aggrieved by an order of the competent authority" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1194056</tid>
<number> 38</number> Insertion of new section 68Z.- After section 68Y of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 68Z. Release of property in certain cases.- (1) Where the detention 
order of a detenu is set aside or withdrawn, properties seized or 
frozen under this Chapter shall stand released.

<section><tid>1359722</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause 
 (cc) of sub- section (2) of section 68A has been acquitted or 
discharged from the charges under this Act or any other corresponding 
law of any other country and the acquittal was not appealed against or 
when appealed against, the appeal was disposed of as a consequence of 
which such property could not be forfeited or warrant of arrest or 
authorisation of arrest issued against such person has been withdrawn, 
then, property seized or frozen under this Chapter shall stand 
released.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1370481</tid>
<number>39</number>Amendment of section 76.- In section 76 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (c), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' (ca) the manner in which" controlled delivery" under section 50A is 
to be undertaken;'.



</article>



<article><tid>1010471</tid>
<number>40</number>Amendment of section 77.- In section 77 of the principal Act, for 
the portion beginning with the words" Every rule made under this Act" 
and ending with" shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made or 
issued", the following shall be substituted, namely:-
" Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government and every 
notification or order issued under clause (viia), clause (xi), clause 
 (xxiiia) of section 2, section 3, section 7A, section 9A and clause 
 (a) of section 27 shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made 
or issued".



</article>



<article><tid>1784320</tid>
<number> 41</number> Application of this Act to pending cases.-
<section><tid>1494076</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in sub- section (2) of section 1, all cases pending 
before the courts or under investigation at the commencement of this 
Act shall be disposed of in accordance with the provisions of the 
principal Act as amended by this Act and accordingly, any person found 
guilty of any offence punishable under the principal Act, as it stood 
immediately before such commencement, shall be liable for a punishment 
which is lesser than the punishment for which he is otherwise liable 
at the date of the commission of such offence:
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to cases pending in 
appeal.


</section>

<section><tid>182965</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that no act or 
omission on the part of any person shall be punishable as an offence 
which would not have been so punishable if this Act has not come into 
force.


</section>

</article>



 </act>