<act><tid>796037</tid>
<title>THE GOA, DAMAN AND DIU (ABSORBED EMPLOYEES) ACT, <year>1965</year></title>

ACT NO. 50 OF <year>1965</year>
[ 22nd December, <year>1965</year>]

An Act to provide for the regulation of the conditions of service 
of persons absorbed for service in connection with the administration 
of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu and for matters connected 
therewith.

Be it enacted by Parliament in, the Sixteenth Year of the- 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>72092</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Goa, Daman and Diu 
 (Absorbed Employees) Act, <year>1965</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>898429</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1452276</tid>
<number>a</number>absorbed employee" means a person who immediately 
before the 20th day of December, <year>1961</year>, was holding an 
absorbed post and who on and after that date either 
served or has been serving in that or any other post in 
connection with the administration of the Union 
territory of Goa, Daman and Diu or in any of the 
Departments of the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1891883</tid>
<number>b</number>absorbed post" means a civil service or post 
which existed under the former Portuguese Administration 
in Goa, Daman and Diu immediately before the 20th day of 
December <year>1961</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779123</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1615141</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to make rules regulating recruitment and  
conditions of service of absorbed employees and employees of certain 
corporations. The Central Government may make rules-

<subsection><tid>750058</tid>
<number>a</number>for the regulation of recruitment to absorbed 
posts and the conditions of service of absorbed 
employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1906262</tid>
<number>b</number>for the regulation of the conditions of service of 
persons who were in the service of a Corporation 
 (whether know as a junta or otherwise) immediately 
before the 20th day of December, <year>1961</year>, and who on or 
after that date either served or have been serving in 
connection with the administration of the Union 
territory of Goa, Daman and Diu or in any of the 
Departments of the Central Government

<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>355657</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such rule may be made so as to be retrospective to any 
date not earlier than the 20th day of December, <year>1961</year>:
Provided that no person shall, by virtue of such retrospective 
effect be liable to refund any amount paid to him by way of salary or 
allowances or pension before the making of any such rule.


</section>

<section><tid>1602843</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of 
the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately follow- 
ing, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, 
thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>872207</tid>
<number> 4</number> 
<section><tid>886983</tid>
<number>1</number>Repeal. On the making of any rule under section 3, the  
corresponding law, if any, in respect of any matter for which 
provision is made in that rule, shall stand repealed with effect from 
the date of the coming into force of that rule.

</section>

<section><tid>294435</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 6 and 24 of the General Clauses 
Act, <year>1897</year>, (10 of <year>1987</year>), shall apply to such repeal as if the rule and 
the corresponding law referred to in sub- section (1) were Central 
Acts.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1026673</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act or any rule made 
thereunder in relation to any absorbed employee or any person referred 
to in clause (b) of sub- section
<section><tid>898896</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3, the Central  
Government may, by order, make such provision as appears to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that the power under this section shall not be 
exercisable after the expiration of a period of two years from the 
commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



 </act>