<act><title>


The CALCIUM CARBIDE RULES, 19871</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Calcium Carbide Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number> “Act” means the Petroleum Act, 1934 (30 of 1934);
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  “Carbide” means Calcium Carbide;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  “Chief Controller” means the Chief Controller of Explosives;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  “Conservator of the port” includes any person acting under the 
authority of the officer or body of persons appointed to be Conservator of a 
Port under section 7 of the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908);
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  “Controller of Explosives” includes a Joint Chief Controller of 
Explosives, Deputy Chief Controller of Explosives and Deputy Controller of 
Explosives;
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  “district authority” means—
 </section><section>
             
<number>a</number>  a Commissioner of Police or Deputy Commissioner of Police in any town 
having a Commissioner of Police; and
 </section><section>
             
<number>b</number>  in any other place, the District Magistrate;
 </section><section>
        
<number>g</number>  “District Magistrate” includes an Additional District Magistrate and 
in the State of Punjab and Haryana and in the Karaikal, Mahe and Yanam areas of 
the Union territory of Pondicherry, also includes a Sub‑divisional Magistrate;
 </section><section>
        
<number>h</number>  “Form” means a Form as given in the Second, Schedule;
 </section><section>
         
<number>i</number>  “Inspector” means an Officer authorised by the Central Government 
under sub‑section (1) of section 13 of the Act;
 </section><section>
         
<number>j</number>  “prescribed receptacle” means a receptacle which—
 <subsection>
              
<number>i</number>  is made of steel or any other material approved by the Chief 
Controller but has no copper in its composition;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  is hermetically closed at all times except when its contents are 
being placed within it or withdrawn from it; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  bears a stamped embossed, painted or printed warning exhibiting in 
conspicuous characters the word ‘Calcium Carbide”—
 
                   
 “Dangerous if not kept dry” and the following caution:—
 
                   
 “The contents of this package are liable, if brought into contact with 
moisture, to give off a highly inflammable gas”:
 
                      
Provided that for the containers of carbide imported, the warning shall be 
according to relevant International Code.
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>k</number>  “Sampling Officer” means an officer authorised by the Central 
Government under sub‑section (1) of section 14 of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Carbide to be packed 
in prescribed receptacles.—Carbide 
shall not be imported, transported or stored unless it is packed in prescribed 
receptacles:
 

1[Provided that the 
Chief Controller may permit any receptacle other than the prescribed one if he 
is satisfied that such a receptacle may be used without any undue hazard].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Restriction on 
delivery and despatch of carbide.—No 
person shall deliver or despatch any carbide to any person other than the holder 
of a storage licence or his authorised agent or a port authority or a railway 
administration:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to the delivery or despatch to any person of Carbide in 
quantities which are permitted by rule 26 to be stored without a licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Precautions against 
contact with water.—Every 
reasonable precaution shall be taken to prevent carbide coming into contact with 
water, and where such contact may have occurred, to prevent ignition of the gas.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Disposal of carbide 
if wet.—If any 
carbide becomes wet and the receptacle becomes hot it shall be destroyed by 
being submerged in deep water. If deep water is not available, the wet carbide, 
shall be spread out in the open in an isolated place, and all precautions shall 
be taken to prevent any fire or artificial light or article capable of igniting 
acetylene being brought near until the material has given off its gas and the 
surrounding area has become free of gas.
 
Note.—The 
fact of carbide having become wet, will be indicated by the outward appearance 
of the drum, and probably by a disagreeable odour, showing a leakage of gas.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Children and 
intoxicated persons.—No 
person shall employ or allow—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  any child under eighteen years of age; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  any person who is in a state of intoxication—
 <subsection>
             
<number>a</number>  for the purpose of loading, unloading or transport of carbide; or
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>b</number>  to enter any premises licensed under these rules.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Prohibition of 
smoking, fires and lights.—No 
person shall smoke, and no fires, artificial lights or articles capable of 
igniting acetylene shall be permitted—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  at any time within or near the place where carbide is stored;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  near a vehicle or vessel transporting carbide.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Licence for import 
of carbide.‑‑Carbide, 
other than carbide which may be possessed without a licence under rule 26, shall 
not be imported except under a licence granted under these rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Port of Import.—Carbide 
shall not be imported except at the ports of—
 
  Bombay
 
  Calcutta
 
  Cochin
 
  Tuticorin
 
  Kandla
 
  Madras
 
  Mangalore
 
  Port Blair
 
  Visakhapatnam
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Duty of Master or 
the Agent in port.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The master or the Agent of the owner of every vessel arriving at any port and 
carrying carbide shall, on entering the port and before landing any cargo, 
declare in writing to the Collector of Customs and also to the Conservator of 
the Port the quantity and description of the carbide carried by it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The master shall moor 
the vessel at such place as the Conservator of the port may direct and while any 
carbide remains on board, the master shall not, except for the purpose of 
proceedings to sea, remove the vessel without the written permission of the 
Conservator of the Port.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The master shall 
ensure that the hold of every vessel bringing carbide into port shall be 
efficiently ventilated from the time the vessel enters the port until all the 
carbide on board has been discharged or until the vessel has left the port.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Defective 
Receptacles.—The 
Collector of Customs may require that any receptacle containing carbide which 
does not satisfy the requirements of rule 3 or which is defective shall be 
submerged in deep water under the direction of the Conservator of the port, 
without compensation to the consignee.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Facilities  to 
be afforded to Inspecting Officers.—The 
master or the agent of the owner of any vessel in port with carbide on board 
shall, when so required by the, Collector of Customs or by the Conservator of 
port or by an Inspector or Sampling Officer, show to such officer all carbide 
under his control or on board, and shall afford every reasonable facility to 
enable such officer to inspect such carbide so as to ascertain whether the 
provisions of these rules are duly observed and to take samples free of charge, 
if such officer so desires.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Landing of carbide.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Carbide shall be landed only with the permission of the Collector of Customs and 
at such place or places as the Conservator of the Port may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Carbide shall be 
landed only between sunrise and sunset.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Removal after 
landing.—All 
carbide landed from any vessel shall be removed without unnecessary delay to a 
licensed premises, and if conveyed by water shall be conveyed only in an open 
barge certified as suitable for the conveyance of carbide by the Conservator of 
the Port.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Storage at Port.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in rule 15, carbide, if it cannot be removed immediately form 
the port may be stored in the ­port in a separate godown away from other 
building.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>17</number> Importation 
by land.—No 
person shall import Carbide by land save with the previous sanction in each case 
of the Central Government and subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  that the carbide is carried in prescribed receptacles;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  that all reasonable precautions are taken to prevent carbide coming 
into contact with water or metals like copper and silver during importation;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  that after carbide is landed, it is removed to a licensed storage 
premises without delay.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>18</number> Importation 
by Air.—No 
person shall import carbide by air save with the previous sanction in each case 
of the Central Government and subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  that the carbide is carried in prescribed receptacles;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  that all reasonable precautions are taken to prevent carbide coming 
into contact with water or metals like copper and silver during importation;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  that after carbide is landed, it is removed to a licensed storage 
premises without delay.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Transportation in 
quantity not exceeding 5 kilogrammes.—Carbide 
transported in any quantity not exceeding 5 kilogrammes shall be packed in 
prescribed receptacles and each receptacles containing not more than 1 
kilogramme.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Transport in 
quantity exceeding 5 kilogrammes.—Carbide 
in quantity exceeding 5 kilogrammes shall not be transported except under the 
following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  Carbide shall be carried in prescribed receptacles, no receptacle 
shall be capable of containing more than 100 kilogrammes of carbide; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the carbide shall not be deposited at any time during transit in any 
building other than a building licensed for the storage of carbide under these 
rules:
 
                        
1[Provided that the 
Chief Controller may permit transport of carbide and receptacles capable of 
containing more than 100 kilogrammes specifically approved by him to the effect 
that such receptacles are suitably designed and tested to safely carry the load 
and to prevent ingress of water:]
 
Provided further that 
carbide so transported is meant for directly charging into an acetylene 
generator and not for repacking into any other receptacle.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Transport by 
Railway or Road.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Carbide while in the custody of railway administration or a road transport 
agency for transport, shall not be stored in any goods shed with other materials 
but shall be stacked in the open under water‑proof sheets and shall be so placed 
as to prevent any receptacle containing it from becoming wet.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the carbide is 
conveyed by rail it shall be subject to all the regulations which may from time 
to time be prescribed generally or specially in that behalf by the railway 
administration.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Transport by 
Passenger Train.—Where 
carbide is transported by passenger train—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  the quantity carried by any one train shall not exceed 250 kilogrammes;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  the carbide shall be carried in brake van of the train;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  no naked lamp or other artificial light capable of igniting 
inflammable gas shall be taken into a van containing carbide; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  the van shall be well ventilated and as far as possible is 
watertight.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Transport by water.—Where 
carbide is conveyed by water it shall be packed and stored in accordance with 
the regulations contained in the Merchant Shipping Carriage of Dangerous Goods 
Rules, 1978.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Transport by Air.—Carbide 
may be transported by air in such quantities and in such a manner as may be 
allowed by the Director General, Civil Aviation.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Carbide to be 
commercially pure.—No 
carbide shall be kept at any place with or without a licence unless it is 
“commercially pure” that is, unless it contains no impurities which would render 
the gas evolved either alone or in admixture with air, liable to ignite 
spontaneously and the gas evolved shall comply with the requirements given in 
specification for calcium carbide, technical, IS: 1040.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Licence for 
storage.—No 
person shall store any carbide except under a licence granted under these rules:
 
Provided that no licence 
shall be required for storage of carbide—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  in any quantity not exceeding five kilogrammes if it is kept in 
prescribed receptacles each containing not more than one kilogramme;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  in any quantity exceeding five kilogrammes but not exceeding two 
hundred kilograms subject to the following conditions namely:—
 <subsection>
              
<number>i</number>  the receptacles shall be stored in a dry and well ventilated storage 
shed, which may form a part of or attached to a building provided that it is 
separated therefrom by a substantial partition and the only means of access to 
it is from outside air;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  due precautions shall be taken to prevent unauthorized persons from 
having access to the receptacles;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  the receptacles shall be kept securely closed except while taking 
out carbide therefrom;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  temporarily within port limits under such conditions as the 
conservator of the port may specify;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  while in transit under the custody of railway administration or road 
transport agency;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  in the possession of the Defence Forces of the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Observance of 
safety distance from the licensed storage shed necessary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Carbide shall be stored—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  if in quantities aggregating more than 200 kilogrammes but not 
exceeding 500 kilogrammes in a suitable uninhabited building at least 3 metres 
away from any other premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  if in quantities aggregating more than 500 kilogrammes and not more 
than 5000 kilogrammes in a suitable uninhabited building at least 6 metres away 
from any other premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  if in quantities aggregating more than 5000 kilogrammes, in a suitable 
uninhabited building at least 9 metres away from any other premises.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Not more than 1000 
metric tonnes of carbide shall be stored in any one building, provided that not 
more than 250 metric tonnes of carbide is stored in any one room or other part 
of the building.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A carbide storage shed 
may also form a part of, or attached to an Acetylene plant provided that it is 
separated from other portions of the plant by substantial partition and the 
entire building including the carbide storage shed, observes a safety distance 
of 15 metres from any other premises:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may allow the storage shed at a distance of less than 15 metres in 
the case of Acetylene plants which have been under operation before these rules 
have come into force and under such conditions as he may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every building storing 
carbide shall be surrounded by a wall or fence of at lest 1.8 metres high to 
prevent unauthorised persons having access to the shed and are enclosed by such 
wall or fence shall cover the safety zone required to be kept clear.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Construction of 
storage premises.—Every 
premises for storage of carbide shall—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  be construed of non-flammable material with cemented floor raised at 
least 30 centimeters from the surrounding ground level;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  be well ventilated both near the ceiling and the floor to the 
satisfaction of the licensing authority. The ventilator openings shall be 
covered with two layers of galvanized iron or other non­-corroding metal wire 
gauge having no copper and of mesh not less than 11 per linear centimetre;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  be water tight;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  be of sufficient capacity so as to conveniently accommodate the 
quantity of carbide proposed to be stored, leaving a gangway space of at least 
60 centimetres around the stack.
 
Note.—The 
floor area for storage of carbide may be calculated at the rate of 2 SQM/Tonne, 
provided that stack height is limited to 2M and height of the storage shed is 
not less than 3M.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Arrangements in 
storage premises.—Carbide 
receptacles shall be mostly stacked on racks or trestles or on a raised platform 
inside the storage premises, at least 30 centimetres above the inner floor 
level.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Grant of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Licences under that rules may be granted by the licensing authorities set forth 
in the First Schedule in the Forms specified for the purpose and on payment of a 
fee specified therein.
 

1[(2) The licensing 
authority shall grant licence under sub‑rule (1) within a period of three months 
from the date of the receipt of documents duly completed for grant of licence 
under this Chapter.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Period for which 
licences may be granted or renewed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted or renewed under these rules shall remain in force until 
the 31st day of December of the year upto which licence is granted or renewed 
subject to a maximum of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub‑rule (1), the licensing authority where it is 
satisfied that a licence is required for a specific work of festival which is 
not likely to last upto the 31st day of December of the year for which the 
licence is granted or renewed, may grant or renew a licence for such period as 
is actually necessary.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Application for 
licence.—A 
person wishing to obtain a licence under these rules shall submit an application 
in Form I to the authority empowered to grant such a licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Particulars of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall be held subject to the conditions 
specified therein and shall contain all the particulars which are contained in 
the form specified under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> One copy of the plan 
or plans for the licensed premises signed in token of approval by the licensing 
authority shall be attached to the licence which shall form part of such licence, 
and an identical copy shall be filed for record in the office of the licensing 
authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Prior approval of 
specifications and plans of premises proposed to be licensed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person desiring to obtain a licence to import and store carbide in Form 
II, Form III or Form IV, as the case may be, shall submit to the licensing 
authority an application along with—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  Specification and plans drawn to scale in duplicate clearly 
indicating—
 <subsubsection>
              
<number>i</number>  the manner in which the provisions prescribed under these rules shall 
be complied with,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  the premises proposed to be licensed, the area of which shall be 
distinctly or otherwise marked;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  the surrounding and all premises, roads etc. lying within 50 metres 
of the edge of the shed which is proposed to be licensed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iv</number>  the position, details of construction and ground and elevation views 
of storage shed;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  a scrutiny fee of Rs. 10 paid in the manner specified in rule 46.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the licensing 
authority after scrutiny of the specification and plans and after making such 
enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that carbide may be stored in the 
premises proposed to be licensed, he shall return to the applicant one copy each 
of the specifications and plans signed by him conveying his sanction subject to 
such conditions as he may specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Prior approval 
necessary for alteration in the licensed premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No alteration shall be carried out in the licensed premises until a plan or 
plans showing such alteration has been approved in writing by the licensing 
authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person wishing to 
carry out any alteration in the licensed premises, shall submit to the licensing 
authority,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  three copies of a properly drawn plan of the licensed premises showing 
distinct colour or colours the proposed alterations and reasons therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  a fee of Rs. 10 for the scrutiny of the proposed alteration.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the licensing 
authority, after scrutiny of the plan showing the proposed alteration and after 
making such enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that the proposed alteration 
may be carried out he shall return to the licensee one copy of the plan signed 
by him and conveying his sanction subject to such condition as he may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The holder of the 
licence shall apply to the licensing authority for the amendment of the licence 
as soon as the sanction for alteration has been carried out.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Amendment of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any licence granted under these rules may be amended by the authority empowered 
to grant such a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee for amendment 
of the licence shall be Rs. 10 plus the amount, if any, by which the fee that 
would have been payable if the licence had originally been issued in the amended 
form exceeds the fee originally paid by the licensee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licence who 
desires to have his licence amended shall submit to the licensing authority:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  an application duly filled in and signed in Form I;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the licence sought to be amended together with the approved plan 
attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  where any alteration in the licensed premises has been carried out, 
three copies of the properly drawn plans showing the alterations sanctioned 
under rule 35 by the licensing authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  fee for amendment of the licence as specified in sub‑rule (2).
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The licence may be renewed by the licensing authority empowered to grant such a 
licence:
 
Provided that a licence 
which has been granted by the Chief Controller may be renewed without alteration 
by the Controller of Explosives duly authorised by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence granted 
under these rules may be renewable for three calendar years where there has been 
no contravention of the Act or of the rules framed thereunder or of any 
condition of the licence so renewed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a licence which 
has been renewed for more than one year is surrendered before its expiry, the 
renewal fee paid for the unexpired portion of the licence shall be refunded to 
the licensee provided that no refund of renewal fee shall be made for any 
calendar year during which—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  the licensing authority receives the renewed licence for surrender, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  any carbide is received or stored on the authority of the licence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every application 
under sub-rule (2) shall be made in Form I and shall be accompanied by the 
licence which is to be renewed together with approved plans attached to the 
licence and the renewal fee.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application for 
the renewal of the licence shall be made so as to reach the licensing authority 
as least 30 days before the date on which it expires, and if the application is 
so made, the licence shall be deemed to be in force until such date as the 
licensing authority renews the licence or until an intimation that the renewal 
of the licence is refunded has been communicated to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the renewal of 
the licence is refused, fee paid for the renewal shall be refunded to the 
licensee after deducting therefrom the proportionate fee for the period 
beginning from the date from which the licence was to be renewed upto the date 
on which renewal thereof is refused.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The same fee shall be 
charged for the renewal of the licence for each calendar year as for the grant 
thereof:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  if the application with the accompaniments required under sub-rule (4) 
is not received within the time specified in sub‑rule (5), the licence shall be 
renewed only on payment of a fee amounting to twice the fee ordinarily payable
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  if such an application with accompaniments is received by the 
licensing authority after the date of expiry but not later than 30 days from the 
date of expiry, the licence may without prejudice to any other action that may 
be taken in this behalf, be renewed on payment of twice the fee ordinarily 
payable:
 
Provided further that in 
the case of an application for the renewal of the licence for a period of more 
than one calendar year at a time, the fee prescribed under clause (i) or (ii) of 
the first proviso, if payable, shall be paid only for the first calendar year of 
the renewal.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Refusal of licence.—Licensing 
authority refusing to grant, amend, renew or transfer the licence, shall record 
his reasons for such refusal in writing.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Suspension and 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  stand cancelled, if the licensee ceases to have any right to the site 
for storing carbide;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  be liable to be suspended or cancelled by an order of the licensing 
authority for any contravention of the Act or of any rule made thereunder or of 
any condition contained in such licence, or by order of the Central Government, 
if it is satisfied that there are sufficient ground for doing so:
 
Provided that—
 <subsubsection>
        
<number>a</number>  before suspending or cancelling a licence under this rule the holder 
of the licence shall be given an opportunity of being heard;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>b</number>  the maximum period of suspension shall not exceed three months; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>c</number>  the suspension of a licence shall not debar the holder of the licence 
from applying for its renewal in accordance with the provisions of rule 37.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything in sub‑rule (1), an opportunity of being heard may not be given to the 
holder of a licence before his licence is suspended or cancelled in cases—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  where the licence is suspended by a licensing authority as an interim 
measure for violation of any of the provisions of the Act or these rules, or of 
any conditions contained in such licence and in his opinion such violation is 
likely to cause imminent danger to the public:
 
                 
Provided that where a licence is so suspended, the licensing authority shall 
give the holder of the licence an opportunity of being heard before the order of 
suspension is confirmed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  Where the licence is suspended or cancelled by the Central Government 
if the Government considers that in public interest or in the interest of the 
security of the State such opportunity should not be given.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A licensing Authority 
or the Central Government suspending or cancelling a licence under sub‑rule (1) 
shall record its reasons for so doing in writing.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Procedure on 
expiration, suspension or cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person licensed to store carbide shall, on the expiration, suspension of or 
cancellation of his licence, forthwith give notice to the District Authority of 
tile quantity of carbide in his possession and shall comply with any direction 
which the District Authority may, on the recommendation of the Chief Controller, 
give in regard to its disposal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The District Authority 
likely grant for a term not exceeding three months from the date of expiration, 
suspension or cancellation, as the case may be, a temporary licence for the 
storage of carbide actually held at the time of the issue of the temporary 
licence:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  where the expired, suspended or cancelled licence was granted by an 
authority, other than the District Authority, no temporary licence shall be 
granted without previous consent of such other authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  the fee chargeable on a licence granted under sub‑rule (2) shall bear 
the same proportion to the fee charged on the expired or cancelled or suspended 
licence as the period covered by the temporary licence bears to a full year.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie against any order cancelling or refusing to grant amend or 
renew a licence or cancelling or suspending a licence to—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the Central Government, where an order is passed by the Chief 
Controller,
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the Chief Controller, if the order is passed by the Controller of 
Explosives;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  the immediate official superior to the District Authority, if the 
order is passed by the District Authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every appeal shall be 
in writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and 
shall be presented within 60 days of the order passed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Transfer of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The holder of a licence may at any time before the expiry of the license, apply 
to the licensing authority to transfer the licence to another person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application for 
the transfer of a licence shall be accompanied by—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  a letter signed by the holder of the licence indicating the full name 
and postal address of the person to whom he wishes to transfer the licence and 
complete possession of licensed premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the licence sought to be transferred together with approved plan or 
plans attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  an application in Form I duly filled in and signed by person to whom 
the licence is sought to be transferred;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  a fee of Rs. 10 paid in the manner specified in rule 46.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensing 
authority on receipt of the documents and fee required under sub‑rule (2) shall, 
if he approves the transfer, enter upon the licence, under his signature, an 
endorsement to the effect that licence has been transferred to the person so 
named.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person to whom the 
licence is so transferred shall enjoy the same powers and be subject to the same 
obligations under the licence as the original licensee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Procedure on death 
or disability of licensee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a licensee dies or becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is otherwise 
disabled, the person carrying on the business of such licensee shall not be 
liable to any penalty or confiscation under the Act or these rules for 
exercising the powers granted to the licensee during such time as may reasonably 
be required to allow him to make an application for a new licence in his own 
name for the unexpired portion of the original licence in respect of the year in 
which the licensee dies becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is otherwise 
disabled:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub‑rule shall be deemed to authorise the exercise of any power under this 
sub‑rule by any person after the expiry of the period of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A fee of Rs. 10 shall 
be charged for a new licence for the unexpired portion of the original licence 
granted to any person applying for it under this rule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Loss of licence.—Where 
a licence granted under these rules is defaced, lost, destroyed or otherwise 
rendered useless, a duplicate may be granted on submission of a copy of the plan 
or plans identical with those attached to the licence and on payment of a fee of 
Rs. 10.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Production of 
licence on demand.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person holding or acting under a licence granted under these rules shall 
produce it, or an authenticated copy of it, at the place to which the licence 
applies, when called upon to do so by any Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Copies of any licence 
may, for the purpose of this rule, be authenticated by the authority which 
granted the licence on payment of a fee of Rs. 10 for each authenticated copy.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Payment of fees.—All 
fees payable under these rules shall be paid in the following manner:—
 <section>
        
<number>1</number>  Fees by crossed demanded draft payable at Nagpur on any Nationalised 
Bank drawn in favour of an officer nominated by the Chief Controller of 
Explosives in the Department of Explosives, Nagpur, and in cases where amount 
payable does not exceed Rs. 100 the payment may be made by cash, postal order or 
cheque drawn on any local nationalised bank.
 </section><section>
        
<number>2</number>  Fees payable to the Controller of Explosives shall be paid by a 
crossed demand draft on any nationalised bank drawn in favour of the Controller 
of Explosives to whom the payment is made, payable at the station where his 
office is located and in cases where the amount payable does not exceed Rs. 100, 
the payment may be made by cash, postal order or cheque drawn on any local 
nationalised bank.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Procedure on 
reports of infringement.—The 
District Authority shall inform the Controller of action taken by him on any 
report of infringements of the Act or of these rules which the said Controller 
of Explosives or the Chief Controller may make to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Executive control 
over authorities.—Every 
authority other than the Central Government acting under this Chapter shall 
perform its duties subject to the control of the Central Government:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall be deemed to affect the powers of executive control of the Chief 
Controller over the officers subordinate to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Notice of 
accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The notice of an accident under section 27 of the Act shall be given forthwith:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  in case of the notice given to the Chief Controller by an Express 
telegram (Telegraphic Address: Explosives, Nagpur) followed within 24 hours by a 
letter giving particulars of the accident; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  by a quickest means of communication to the nearest Magistrate or to 
the officer‑in‑charge of Police Station having jurisdiction.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Pending the visit of 
the Chief Controller or his representative or until instructions are received 
from these authorities that he does not wish any further investigation or 
inquiry to be made, all wreckage and debris shall be left untouched except in so 
far as its removal may be necessary for the rescue of persons injured and 
recovery of the bodies of any persons killed by the accident or in the case of 
railways, for the restoration of through communication.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Carbide of Calcium Rules, 1937 are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  all licenses or duplicates granted or renewed under the said rules and 
all fees imposed or levied shall be deemed to have been granted, renewed, 
imposed or levied, as the case may be, under the corresponding provisions of 
these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all approvals given and all powers conferred by or under any 
notification or rule shall, so far as they are consistent with the provisions of 
the Act and these rules, be deemed to have been given or conferred by or under 
these rules.
</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>