<act><title>


The Depositories (Procedure for Holding Inquiry 
and Imposing Penalties By Adjudicating Officer) 
Rules, 20051</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Depositories (Procedure for Holding Inquiry and 
Imposing Penalties by Adjudicating Officer) Rules, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “adjudicating 
officer” means the officer appointed by the Board as adjudicating officer under 
section 19H of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “inquiry” 
means the inquiry referred in section 19H.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in the Depositories Act, 
1996 shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them under that Act.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Appointment of 
adjudicating officer for holding inquiry.—Whenever 
the Board is of the opinion that there are grounds for adjudging under sections 
19A, 19B, 19C, 19D, 19E, I9F and 19G of the Act, it may appoint any of its 
officer not below the rank of Division Chief to be an adjudicating officer for 
holding an inquiry for the said purpose.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Holding of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In holding an inquiry for the purpose of adjudging under sections 19A, 19B, 19C, 
19D, 19E, 19F and 19G whether any person has committed contraventions as 
specified in any of the sections 19A, 19B, 19C, 19D, 19E, 19F and 19G, the 
adjudicating officer shall, in the first instance, issue a notice to such person 
requiring him to show cause within such period as may be specified in the notice 
(being not less than fourteen days from the date of service thereof) why an 
inquiry should not be held against him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every notice under 
sub-rule (1) to any such person shall indicate the nature of offence alleged to 
have been committed by him.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If after considering 
the cause, if any, shown by such person, the adjudicating officer is of the 
opinion that an inquiry should be held, he shall issue a notice fixing a date 
for the appearance of that person either personally or through his lawyer or 
other authorised representative.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On the date fixed, the 
adjudicating officer shall explain to the person proceeded against or his lawyer 
or authorised representative, the offence, alleged to have been committed by 
such person indicating the provisions of the Act, rules or regulations in 
respect of which contravention is alleged to have taken place.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The adjudicating 
officer shall then give an opportunity to such person to produce such documents 
or evidence as he may consider relevant to the inquiry and if necessary the 
hearing may be adjourned to a future date and in taking such evidence the 
adjudicating officer shall not be bound to observe the provisions of the 
Evidence Act, 1872 (11 of 1872):
 
Provided that the notice 
referred to in sub-rule (3), and the personal hearing referred to in sub-rules 
(3), (4) and (5) may, at the request of the person concerned, be waived.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> While holding an 
inquiry under this rule the adjudicating officer shall have the power to summon 
and enforce the attendance of any person acquainted with the facts and 
circumstances of the case to give evidence or to produce any document which in 
the opinion of the adjudicating officer may be useful for or relevant to the 
subject matter of the inquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If any person fails, 
neglects or refuses to appear as required by sub-rule (3) before the 
adjudicating officer, the adjudicating officer may proceed with the inquiry in 
the absence of such person after recording the reasons for doing so.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Order of the 
adjudicating officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, upon consideration of the evidence produced before the adjudicating officer, 
the adjudicating officer is satisfied that the person has become liable to 
penalty under any of the sections specified in sub-section (1) of the section 
19H of the Act, he may, by order in writing, impose such penalty as he thinks 
fit in accordance with the provisions of the relevant section or sections 
specified in section 19H of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While adjudging the 
quantum of penalty under section 19H of the Act, the adjudicating officer shall 
have due regard to the following factors, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the amount of 
disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever quantifiable, made as a 
result of the default;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the amount of 
loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a result of the default;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the repetitive 
nature of the default.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order made under 
sub-rule (1) shall specify the provisions of the Act in respect of which default 
has taken place and shall contain brief reasons for such decisions.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every such order shall 
be dated and signed by the adjudicating officer.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Copy of the Order.—The 
adjudicating officer shall send a copy of every order made under rules by it to 
the person concerned and to the Board.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Service of notices 
and orders.—A 
notice or an order issued under these rules shall be served on the person in the 
following manner, that is to say,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  by delivering 
or tendering it to that person or his duly authorised agent;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  by sending it 
to the person by registered post with acknowledgment due to the address of his 
place of residence or his last known place of residence or the place where he 
carried on, or last carried on, business or personally works, or last worked, 
for gain; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  if it cannot be 
served under clause (a) or clause (b), by affixing it on the outer door or some 
other conspicuous part of the premises in which that person resides or is known 
to have last resided, or carried on business or personally works or last worked 
for gain and that written report thereof should be witnessed by two persons.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>