<act><title>

The Aircraft (Demolition of obstructions 
    caused by Buildings and Trees etc.) Rules, 19941</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Aircraft (Demolition of Obstructions Caused by 
    Buildings and Trees etc.) Rules, 1994.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    They extend to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions and interpretation.—In 
    these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
<number>1</number>  
    “Act” shall mean the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  
    “Aircraft” and “Aerodrome” shall have the same meaning as in the Aircraft 
    Act, 1934.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>  
    “Building” shall include any structure, whether permanent or temporary, 
    erected within a specified area around an aerodrome.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>  
    “District Collector” shall include Deputy Commissioner, District Magistrate 
    or any other designation used by any State Government for the 
    officer-in-charge of the District Administration.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>  
    “Owner” shall include the person having the control of the building, or 
    tree, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>  
    “Officer-in-charge of an Aerodrome” shall mean the officer holding charge of 
    the airport by whatever designation known.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Notification to be served.—Where 
    any notification has been issued by the Central Government under sub-section 
    
<section><number>1</number> of section 9A of the Act and the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[officer-in-charge of the 
    concerned aerodromie] has reason to believe that any building or tree exists 
    in violation of the provisions of the aforesaid notification, he shall serve
    <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***], a copy of the notification on the owner of the building 
    or tree, as the case may be, in accordance with the procedure laid down in 
    sub-section (3) of section 9A of the Act.
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Owner to furnish details.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The service of the copy of the notification under rule 3 shall be 
    accompanied by an order of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Director-General of Civil 
    Aviation or any other officer of the Civil Aviation Department authorised by 
    him in this behalf] directing the owner to furnish to the officer-in-charge 
    of the aerodrome, within a specified period, a plan showing the location of 
    the building or tree, as the case may be, and also its dimensions or any 
    other details specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The owner shall be bound to furnish the details asked for in the order 
    passed under sub-rule (1).
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Forwarding the details and their physical verification.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The details furnished by the owner of the building or tree, as the case may 
    be, shall be forwarded by the officer in-charge of the aerodrome to the 
    Director-General of Civil Aviation with his comments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Before forwarding the details to the Director-General of Civil Aviation, the 
    officer-in-charge of the aerodrome shall satisfy himself about the 
    correctness of the details and for that purpose he shall be empowered to 
    enter the premises in question and carry out physical verification of the 
    dimensions of the building, or tree, as the case may be, during day light 
    hours and with reasonable prior notice to the owner, who shall be duty bound 
    to extend full cooperation during such physical verification:
 

    Provided that in a case where the owner fails to cooperate, the 
    office-in-charge of the aerodrome shall be free to forward details to the 
    Director-General of Civil Aviation with his comments based on whatever 
    verification is possible.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Final order.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    If the 

    2[a Joint 
    Director General or a Deputy Director-General of Civil Aviation], on an 
    examination of the details forwarded to him by the officer-in-charge of the 
    aerodrome, is satisfied, after giving the owner an opportunity of being 
    heard, that the building or tree in question does violate the provisions of 
    the notification issued by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of 
    section 9A of the Act, he shall pass a final order in the matter directing 
    the owner to demolish the building, or to cut the tree, or to reduce the 
    height of the building, or the tree, as may be required for compliance with 
    the provisions of the notification, within a specified period. In case of 
    reduction in the height of the building, or tree, as the case may be, the 
    permissible height shall also be specified in the order:
 
Provided that in a 
    case where the owner has failed to furnish details in response to the order 
    under rule 4, the 

    3[a Joint 
    Director General or a Deputy Director-General of Civil Aviation] shall be 
    empowered to pass a final order based on information made available to him 
    by the officer-in-charge of the aerodrome, or any other reliable source.
 

    4[(2) The final 
    order passed under sub-rule (1) shall be served on the owner through the 
    officer-in-charge of the aerodrome in accordance with the procedure laid 
    down in sub-section (3) of section 9A of the Act.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


  
 

 

[6A 
    Appeal against the final order.—If 
    any person is aggrieved by the final order passed under rule 6, he may 
    prefer an appeal to Director General of Civil Aviation within sixty days of 
    the date of the order and the Director General shall after hearing the 
    concerned parties, desirous of being heard, either confirm or modify or 
    reject the final order.]
 

 






 



 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Owner to comply with order. </title>— <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The owner shall comply with the directions contained in the final order passed under rule 6 or confirmed or modified under rule 6A. as the case may be, within the time limit specified therein. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner may claim compensation in accordance with the provisions contained in section 9B of the Act.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Non-compliance to be reported to the District Collector. </title>— <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> [
<section><number>1</number> If the owner fails to carry out the directions contained in the order passed under  
  rule 6 or confirmed or modified under rule 6A, as the case may be, within the time limit specified therein, the officer-in-charge of the aerodrome shall report the matter to the District Collector giving brief facts of the case and a copy of the final order passed under rule 6 or confirmed or modified under rule 6A, as the case may be.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receiving the report from the officer-in-charge of the aerodrome, the District Collector shall carry out forthwith the demolition of the building or the cutting of the tree, or reduction in height of the building, as the case may be, in the same manner and by the same procedure as is followed in case of demolition of any unauthorised construction in his district. 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 Subs. by G.S.R. 302 (E), 
    dated 20th August, 1999 (w.e.f. 18-9-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Omitted by G.S.R. 302 
    (E), dated 20th August, 1999 (w.e.f. 18-9-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Omitted by G.S.R. 302 
    (E), dated 20th August, 1999 (w.e.f. 18-9-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>    Rule 
    6 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 314(E), dated 25th May, 2006 
    (w.e.f. 25-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>    Subs. 
    by G.S.R. 267(E), dated 9th April, 2002, for “the Director-General of Civil 
    Aviation” (w.e.f. 9-4-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. G.S.R. 314(E), dated 25th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 25-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. G.S.R. 314(E), dated 25th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 25-5-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>