<act><tid>188267</tid>
<title>THE SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE BOARD OF INDIA (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 59 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Securities and Exchange Board of India 
Act, <year>1992</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1170407</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>481217</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Securities and Exchange Board of India (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1170996</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day of 
October, <year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287697</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Securities and 
Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15of 1992)  (hereinafter referred to  
  as the principal Act), in sub- section 1, after clause (h), the 
following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (ha)" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under 
section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);'.



</article>



<article><tid>824978</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1682200</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>165562</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (b),-

<subsubsection><tid>515107</tid>
<number>A</number>for the word" Ministries", the word" Ministry" shall be 
substituted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>875742</tid>
<number>B</number>for the words" and Law", the words and figures" and administration 
of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)" shall be substituted;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682539</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (c), for the words and figures" the Reserve Bank of 
India constituted under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 
 <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>)", the words" the Reserve Bank" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>698253</tid>
<number>iii</number>for clause (d), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (d) five other members of whom at least three shall be the whole- time 
members,";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>706328</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4), for the words" Reserve Bank of India", the 
words" Reserve Bank" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1293014</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>958847</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), after clause (i), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (ia) calling for information and record from any bank or any other 
authority or board or corporation established or constituted by or 
under any Central, State or Provincial Act in respect of any 
transaction in securities which is under investigation or inquiry by 
the Board;";


</section>

<section><tid>900373</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (2A) Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (2), the Board may take measures to undertake inspection of any book, 
or register, or other document or record of any listed public company 
or a public company (not being intermediaries eferred to in section  
 (12) which intends to get its securities listed on any recognised stock 
exchange where the Board has reasonable grounds to believe that such 
company has been indulging in insider trading or fraudulent and unfair 
trade practices relat ng to securities market.";


</section>

<section><tid>980938</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3),-

<subsection><tid>1115001</tid>
<number>i</number>in the opening portion, for the words, brackets, letter and figure 
" clause (i) of sub- section (2)", the words, brackets, figures and 
letters" clause (i) or clause (ia) of sub- section (2) or sub- section 
 (2A)" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1632864</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (iii), the following clauses shall be inserted at 
the end, namely:-
" (iv) inspection of any book, or register, or other document or record 
of the company referred to in sub- section (2A);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>327855</tid>
<number>v</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>452761</tid>
<number>d</number>after sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4) Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- sections 
 (1), (2), (2A) and (3) and section 11B, the Board may, by an order, 
for reasons to be recorded in writing, in the interests of investors 
or securities market, take any of the following me sures, either 
pending investigation or inquiry or on completion of such 
investigation or inquiry, namely:-


</section>

<section><tid>958847</tid>
<number>a</number>suspend the trading of any security in a recognised stock 
exchange;

</section>

<section><tid>900373</tid>
<number>b</number>restrain persons from accessing the securities market and prohibit 
any person associated with securities market to buy, sell or deal in 
securities;

</section>

<section><tid>980938</tid>
<number>c</number>suspend any office- bearer of any stock exchange or self- regulatory 
organisation from holding such position;

</section>

<section><tid>452761</tid>
<number>d</number>impound and retain the proceeds or securities in respect of any 
transaction which is under investigation;

</section>

<section><tid>1210903</tid>
<number>e</number>attach, after passing of an order on an application made for 
approval by the Judicial Magistrate of the first class having 
jurisdiction, for a period not exceeding one month, one or more bank 
account or accounts of any intermediary or any person asso iated with 
the securities market in any manner involved in violation of any of 
the provisions of this Act, or the rules or the regulations made 
thereunder:
Provided that only the bank account or accounts or any transaction 
entered therein, so far as it relates to the proceeds actually 
involved in violation of any of the provisions of this Act, or the 
rules or the regulations made thereunder shall be allowed to be 
attached;


</section>

<section><tid>374650</tid>
<number>f</number>direct any intermediary or any person associated with the 
securities market in any manner not to dispose of or alienate an asset 
forming part of any transaction which is under investigation:
Provided that the Board may, without prejudice to the provisions 
contained in sub- section (2) or sub- section (2A), take any of the 
measures specified in clause (d) or clause (e) or clause (f), in 
respect of any listed public company or a public company not being 
  intermediaries referred to in section 12) which intends to get its 
securities listed on any recognised stock exchange where the Board has 
reasonable grounds to believe that such company has been indulging in 
insider trading or fraudulent and un air trade practices relating to 
securities market:

Provided further that the Board shall, either before or after passing 
such orders, give an opportunity of hearing to such intermediaries or 
persons concerned.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1169171</tid>
<number> 5</number> Substitution of new section for section 11A.- For section 11A of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely 
:-
" 11A. Board to regulate or prohibit issue of prospectus, offer 
document or advertisement soliciting money for issue of 
securities.- (1) Without prejudice to the provisions of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), the Board may, for the protection of invest 
rs,-

<section><tid>162906</tid>
<number>a</number>specify, by regulations-

<subsection><tid>251618</tid>
<number>i</number>the matters relating to issue of capital, transfer of securities 
and other matters incidental thereto; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1946430</tid>
<number>ii</number>the manner in which such matters shall be disclosed by the 
companies;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1427381</tid>
<number>b</number>by general or special orders-

<subsection><tid>607352</tid>
<number>i</number>prohibit any company from issuing prospectus, any offer document, 
or advertisement soliciting money from the public for the issue of 
securities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>11407</tid>
<number>ii</number>specify the conditions subject to which the prospectus, such 
offer document or advertisement, if not prohibited, may be issued.

<subsubsection><tid>1711133</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 21 of the 
Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, <year>1956</year>, the Board may specify the 
requirements for listing and transfer of securities and other matters 
incidental thereto.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1412997</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new sections 11C and 11D.- After section 11B of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 11C. Investigation.- (1) Where the Board has reasonable ground to 
believe that-

<section><tid>931429</tid>
<number>a</number>the transactions in securities are being dealt with in a manner 
detrimental to the investors or the securities market; or

</section>

<section><tid>354330</tid>
<number>b</number>any intermediary or any person associated with the securities 
market has violated any of the provisions of this Act or the rules or 
the regulations made or directions issued by the Board thereunder,
it may, at any time by order in writing, direct any person (hereafter  
  in this section referred to as the Investigating Authority) specified 
in the order to investigate the affairs of such intermediary or 
persons associated with the securities market and o report thereon to 
the Board.


<subsection><tid>949907</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sections 235 to 241 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), it shall be the duty of every 
manager, managing director, officer and other employee of the company 
and every intermediary referred to in section 12 or every person 
associated with the securities market to preserve and to produce to 
the Investigating Authority or any person authorised by it in this 
behalf, all the books, registers, other documents and record of, or 
relating to, the company or, as the ca e may be, of or relating to, 
the intermediary or such person, which are in their custody or power.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1254306</tid>
<number>3</number>The Investigating Authority may require any intermediary or any 
person associated with securities market in any manner to furnish such 
information to, or produce such books, or registers, or other 
documents, or record before it or any person authoris d by it in this 
behalf as it may consider necessary if the furnishing of such 
information or the production of such books, or registers, or other 
documents, or record is relevant or necessary for the purposes of its 
investigation.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>273977</tid>
<number>4</number>The Investigating Authority may keep in its custody any books, 
registers, other documents and record produced under sub- section (2) 
or sub- section (3) for six months and thereafter shall return the same 
to any intermediary or any person associated wi h securities market by 
whom or on whose behalf the books, registers, other documents and 
record are produced:
Provided that the Investigating Authority may call for any book, 
register, other document and record if they are needed again:

Provided further that if the person on whose behalf the books, 
registers, other documents and record are produced requires certified 
copies of the books, registers, other documents and record produced 
before the Investigating Authority, it shall give cer ified copies of 
such books, registers, other documents and record to such person or on 
whose behalf the books, registers, other documents and record were 
produced.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>968291</tid>
<number>5</number>Any person, directed to make an investigation under sub- section 
 (1), may examine on oath, any manager, managing director, officer and 
other employee of any intermediary or any person associated with 
securities market in any manner, in relation to the affairs of his 
business and may administer an oath accordingly and for that purpose 
may require any of those persons to appear before it personally.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>60672</tid>
<number>6</number>If any person fails without reasonable cause or refuses-

<subsubsection><tid>1055231</tid>
<number>a</number>to produce to the Investigating Authority or any person authorised 
by it in this behalf any book, register, other document and record 
which is his duty under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) to produce; 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>220069</tid>
<number>b</number>to furnish any information which is his duty under sub- section (3) 
to furnish; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>480740</tid>
<number>c</number>to appear before the Investigating Authority personally when 
required to do so under sub- section (5) or to answer any question 
which is put to him by the Investigating Authority in pursuance of 
that sub- section; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1792813</tid>
<number>d</number>to sign the notes of any examination referred to in sub- section 
 (7), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one year, or with fine, which may extend to one crore 
rupees, or with both, and also with a further fine which may extend to 
five lakh rupees for every day after the first during whi h the 
failure or refusal continues.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1864467</tid>
<number>7</number>Notes of any examination under sub- section (5) shall be taken down 
in writing and shall be read over to, or by, and signed by, the person 
examined, and may thereafter be used in evidence against him.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563409</tid>
<number>8</number>Where in the course of investigation, the Investigating Authority 
has reasonable ground to believe that the books, registers, other 
documents and record of, or relating to, any intermediary or any 
person associated with securities market in any manne, may be 
destroyed, mutilated, altered, falsified or secreted, the 
Investigating Authority may make an application to the Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction for an order for the 
seizure of such books, registers, other documents an record.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>191964</tid>
<number>9</number>After considering the application and hearing the Investigating 
Authority, if necessary, the Magistrate may, by order, authorise the 
Investigating Authority-

<subsubsection><tid>1795847</tid>
<number>a</number>to enter, with such assistance, as may be required, the place or 
places where such books, registers, other documents and record are 
kept;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>505781</tid>
<number>b</number>to search that place or those places in the manner specified in 
the order; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>207398</tid>
<number>c</number>to seize books, registers, other documents and record, it 
considers necessary for the purposes of the investigation:
Provided that the Magistrate shall not authorise seizure of books, 
registers, other documents and record, of any listed public company or 
a public company (not being the intermediaries specified under section  
  12) which intends to get its securities liste on any recognised stock 
exchange unless such company indulges in insider trading or market 
manipulation.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>405905</tid>
<number>10</number>The Investigating Authority shall keep in its custody the books, 
registers, other documents and record seized under this section for 
such period not later than the conclusion of the investigation as it 
considers necessary and thereafter shall return the same to the 
company or the other body corporate, or, as the case may be, to the 
managing director or the manager or any other person, from whose 
custody or power they were seized and inform the Magistrate of such 
return:
Provided that the Investigating Authority may, before returning such 
books, registers, other documents and record as aforesaid, place 
identification marks on them or any part thereof.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1058482</tid>
<number>11</number>Save as otherwise provided in this section, every search or 
seizure made under this section shall be carried out in accordance 
with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>) relating to searches or seizures made under that C de.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>462476</tid>
<number>11D</number>Cease and desist proceedings.- If the Board finds, after causing 
an inquiry to be made, that any person has violated, or is likely to 
violate, any provisions of this Act, or any rules or regulations made 
thereunder, it may pass an order requiring suc person to cease and 
desist from committing or causing such violation:
Provided that the Board shall not pass such order in respect of any 
listed public company or a public company (other than the  
  intermediaries specified under section 12) which intends to get its 
securities listed on any recognised stock exchange unless th Board has 
reasonable grounds to believe that such company has indulged in 
insider trading or market manipulation.".



</article>



<article><tid>370086</tid>
<number>7</number>Insertion of new Chapter VA.- After Chapter V of the principal Act, 
the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
" CHAPTER VA

PROHIBITION OF MANIPULATIVE AND DECEPTIVE DEVICES, INSIDER TRADING AND 
SUBSTANTIAL ACQUISITION OF SECURITIES OR CONTROL

</article>



<article><tid>1552897</tid>
<number> 12A</number> Prohibition of manipulative and deceptive devices, insider 
trading and substantial acquisition of securities or control.- No 
person shall directly or indirectly-
<section><tid>714424</tid>
<number>a</number>use or employ, in connection with the issue, purchase or sale of 
any securities listed or proposed to be listed on a recognised stock 
exchange, any manipulative or deceptive device or contrivance in 
contravention of the provisions of this Act or the ules or the 
regulations made thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>1990354</tid>
<number>b</number>employ any device, scheme or artifice to defraud in connection 
with issue or dealing in securities which are listed or proposed to be 
listed on a recognised stock exchange;

</section>

<section><tid>1249068</tid>
<number>c</number>engage in any act, practice, course of business which operates or 
would operate as fraud or deceit upon any person, in connection with 
the issue, dealing in securities which are listed or proposed to be 
listed on a recognised stock exchange, in contr vention of the 
provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations made 
thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>1856238</tid>
<number>d</number>engage in insider trading;

</section>

<section><tid>1194990</tid>
<number>e</number>deal in securities while in possession of material or non- public 
information or communicate such material or non- public information to 
any other person, in a manner which is in contravention of the 
provisions of this Act or the rules or the reg lations made 
thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>1412529</tid>
<number>f</number>acquire control of any company or securities more than the 
percentage of equity share capital of a company whose securities are 
listed or proposed to be listed on a recognised stock exchange in 
contravention of the regulations made under this Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1129005</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, clause (aa) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1059706</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 15A.- In section 15A of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>189051</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" a penalty not exceeding one lakh and 
fifty thousand rupees for each such failure", the words" a penalty of 
one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or 
one crore rupees, whichever is less" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1873901</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" a penalty not exceeding five 
thousand rupees for every day during which such failure continues", 
the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>626859</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (c), for the words" a penalty not exceeding ten 
thousand rupees for every day during which the failure continues", the 
words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is ess" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1460276</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of section 15B.- In section 15B of the principal Act, 
for the words" a penalty not exceeding five lakh rupees for every such 
failure", the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during 
which such failure continues or one crore rupe s, whichever is less" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1425888</tid>
<number>11</number>Substitution of new section for section 15C.- For section 15C of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 15C. Penalty for failure to redress investors' grievances.- If any 
listed company or any person who is registered as an intermediary, 
after having been called upon by the Board in writing, to redress the 
grievances of investors, fails to redress such gri vances within the 
time specified by the Board, such company or intermediary shall be 
liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.".



</article>



<article><tid>417479</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amendment of section 15D.- In section 15D of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1140945</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" a penalty not exceeding ten thousand 
rupees for each day during which he carries on any such collective 
investment scheme including mutual funds, or ten lakh rupees, 
whichever is higher", the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each 
day during which he sponsors or carries on any such collective 
investment scheme including mutual funds, or one crore rupees, 
whichever is less" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1098624</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" a penalty not exceeding ten 
thousand rupees for each day during which such failure continues or 
ten lakh rupees, whichever is higher", the words" a penalty of one 
lakh rupees for each day during which such failure conti ues or one 
crore rupees, whichever is less" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1747551</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (c), for the words" a penalty not exceeding five 
thousand rupees for each day during which such failure continues or 
five lakh rupees, whichever is higher", the words" a penalty of one 
lakh rupees for each day during which such failure co tinues or one 
crore rupees, whichever is less" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>474158</tid>
<number>iv</number>in clause (d), for the words" a penalty not exceeding one 
thousand rupees for each day during which such failure continues", the 
words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is l ss" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>368779</tid>
<number>v</number>in clause (e), for the words" a penalty not exceeding one thousand 
rupees for each day during which such failure continues", the words" a 
penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure 
continues or one crore rupees, whichever is le s" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>141239</tid>
<number>vi</number>in clause (f), for the words" a penalty not exceeding five lakh 
rupees for each such failure", the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees 
for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, 
whichever is less" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>828759</tid>
<number>13</number>Amendment of section 15E.- In section 15E of the principal Act, 
for the words" a penalty not exceeding five lakh rupees for each such 
failure", the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during 
which such failure continues or one crore rupee, whichever is less" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1972065</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of section 15F.- In section 15F of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>390871</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (b), for the words" a penalty not exceeding five 
thousand rupees for each day during which such failure continues", the 
words" a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is l ss" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>534305</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (c), for the words" a penalty not exceeding five 
thousand rupees", the words" a penalty of one lakh rupees" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1242708</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of section 15G.- In section 15G of the principal Act, 
for the words" not exceeding five lakh rupees", the words" twenty- five 
crore rupees or three times the amount of profits made out of insider 
trading, whichever is higher" shall be substit ted.


</article>



<article><tid>1604303</tid>
<number> 16</number> Amendment of section 15H.- In section 15H,-
<section><tid>1617092</tid>
<number>a</number>after clause (ii), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (iii) make a public offer by sending letter of offer to the 
shareholders of the concerned company; or


<subsection><tid>1742</tid>
<number>iv</number>make payment of consideration to the shareholders who sold their 
shares pursuant to letter of offer,";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1192620</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" not exceeding five lakh rupees", the words 
" twenty- five crore rupees or three times the amount of profits made 
out of such failure, whichever is higher" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1363292</tid>
<number>17</number>Insertion of new sections 15HA and 15HBAfter section 15H of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 15HA. Penalty for fraudulent and unfair trade practices.- If any 
person indulges in fraudulent and unfair trade practices relating to 
securities, he shall be liable to a penalty of twenty- five crore 
rupees or three times the amount of profits made out of such 
practices, whichever is higher.

</article>



<article><tid>1827038</tid>
<number>15HB</number>Penalty for contravention where no separate penalty has been 
provided.- Whoever fails to comply with any provision of this Act, the 
rules or the regulations made or directions issued by the Board 
thereunder for which no separate penalty has been pro ided, shall be 
liable to a penalty which may extend to one crore rupees.".


</article>



<article><tid>719778</tid>
<number>18</number>Amendment of section 15-IIn section 15-I of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the word, figures and letter" and 15H", the 
figures, letters and word" 15H, 15HA and 15HB" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1966723</tid>
<number>19</number>Insertion of new section 15JA.- After section 15J of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 15JA. Crediting sums realized by way of penalties to Consolidated 
Fund of India.- All sums realised by way of penalties under this Act 
shall be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.".



</article>



<article><tid>354439</tid>
<number>20</number>Substitution of new sections for sections 15L and 15M.- For 
sections 15L and 15M of the principal Act, the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 15L. Composition of Securities Appellate Tribunal.- A Securities 
Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Presiding Officer and two other 
Members, to be appointed, by notification, by the Central Government: 
Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal, consisting of one 
person only, established before the commencement of the Securities and 
Exchange Board of India (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, shall continue to 
exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority con erred on it by or 
under this Act or any other law for the time being in force till two 
other Members are appointed under this section.

</article>



<article><tid>1367105</tid>
<number> 15M</number> Qualification for appointment as Presiding Officer or Member of 
Securities Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1367801</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall not be qualified for  
appointment as the Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate 
Tribunal unless he is a sitting or retired Judge of the Supreme Court 
or a sitting or retired Chief Justice of a High Court:
Provided that the Presiding Officer of the Securities Appellate 
Tribunal shall be appointed by the Central Government in consultation 
with the Chief Justice of India or his nominee.


</section>

<section><tid>417347</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as Member of a 
Securities Appellate Tribunal unless he is a person of ability, 
integrity and standing who has shown capacity in dealing with problems 
relating to securities market and has qualification nd experience of 
corporate law, securities laws, finance, economics or accountancy:
Provided that a member of the Board or any person holding a post at 
senior management level equivalent to Executive Director in the Board 
shall not be appointed as Presiding Officer or Member of a Securities 
Appellate Tribunal during his service or tenur as such with the Board 
or within two years from the date on which he ceases to hold office as 
such in the Board.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>321947</tid>
<number>21</number>Substitution of new section for section 15N.- For section 15N of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 15N. Tenure of office of Presiding Officer and other Members of 
Securities Appellate Tribunal.- The Presiding Officer and every other 
Member of a Securities Appellate Tribunal shall hold office for a term 
of five years from the date on which he enters up n his office and 
shall be eligible for re- appointment:

Provided that no person shall hold office as the Presiding Officer of 
the Securities Appellate Tribunal after he has attained the age of 
sixty- eight years:

Provided further that no person shall hold office as a Member of the 
Securities Appellate Tribunal after he has attained the age of 
sixty- two years.".



</article>



<article><tid>1627889</tid>
<number> 22</number> Amendment of section 15-O.- In section 15-O of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1477062</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate 
Tribunal", the words" Presiding Officer and other Members of a 
Securities Appellate Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1695308</tid>
<number>b</number>in the proviso, for the words" said Presiding Officers", the words 
" Presiding Officer and other Members of a Securities Appellate 
Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>351423</tid>
<number>23</number>Amendment of section 15P.- In section 15P of the principal Act, 
for the words" office of the Presiding Officer", the words" the office 
of the Presiding Officer or any other Member," shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1964822</tid>
<number> 24</number> Amendment of section 15Q.- In section 15Q of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>37904</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>733564</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate 
Tribunal", the words" the Presiding Officer or any other Member of a 
Securities Appellate Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>215638</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the proviso, for the words" the said Presiding Officer", the 
words" the Presiding Officer or any other Member" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>834217</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" Presiding Officer" at both the 
places where they occur, the words" Presiding Officer or any other 
Member" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1005215</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3), for the words" aforesaid Presiding Officer", 
the words" the Presiding Officer or any other Member" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1640042</tid>
<number>25</number>Amendment of section 15R.- In section 15R of the principal Act, 
for the words" Presiding Officer", the words" Presiding Officer or a 
Member" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>130120</tid>
<number>26</number>Substitution of new section for section 15X.- For section 15X of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 15X. Presiding Officer, Member and staff of Securities Appellate 
Tribunals to be public servants.- The Presiding Officer, Members and 
other officers and employees of a Securities Appellate Tribunal shall 
be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).".



</article>



<article><tid>1374750</tid>
<number>27</number>Substitution of new section for section 15Z.- For section 15Z of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 15Z. Appeal to Supreme Court.- Any person aggrieved by any decision 
or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal may file an appeal to 
the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of communication of 
the decision or order of the Securities Appellat Tribunal to him on 
any question of law arising out of such order:

Provided that the Supreme Court may, if it is satisfied that the 
applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal 
within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period 
not exceeding sixty days.".



</article>



<article><tid>909765</tid>
<number> 28</number> Amendment of section 24.- In section 24 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>230920</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" one year, or with fine, or with 
both", the words" ten years, or with fine, which may extend to 
twenty- five crore rupees or with both" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>609649</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" three years or with fine which 
shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to ten 
thousand rupees or with both", the words" ten years or with fine, 
which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees or with both" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1540678</tid>
<number>29</number>Insertion of new sections 24A and 24B.- After section 24 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 24A. Composition of certain offences.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), any 
offence punishable under this Act, not being an offence punishable 
with imprisonment only, or with imprisonment and also wi h fine, may 
either before or after the institution of any proceeding, be 
compounded by a Securities Appellate Tribunal or a court before which 
such proceedings are pending.

</article>



<article><tid>624455</tid>
<number> 24B</number> Power to grant immunity.-
<section><tid>1762320</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, on  
recommendation by the Board, if the Central Government is satisfied, 
that any person, who is alleged to have violated any of the provisions 
of this Act or the rules or the regulations made hereunder, has made a 
full and true disclosure in respect of the alleged violation, grant to 
such person, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, 
immunity from prosecution for any offence under this Act, or the rules 
or the regulations ade thereunder or also from the imposition of any 
penalty under this Act with respect to the alleged violation:
Provided that no such immunity shall be granted by the Central 
Government in cases where the proceedings for the prosecution for any 
such offence have been instituted before the date of receipt of 
application for grant of such immunity:

Provided further that recommendation of the Board under this 
sub- section shall not be binding upon the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1471441</tid>
<number>2</number>An immunity granted to a person under sub- section (1) may, at any 
time, be withdrawn by the Central Government, if it is satisfied that 
such person had, in the course of the proceedings, not complied with 
the condition on which the immunity was grant d or had given false 
evidence, and thereupon such person may be tried for the offence with 
respect to which the immunity was granted or for any other offence of 
which he appears to have been guilty in connection with the 
contravention and shall also beco e liable to the imposition of any 
penalty under this Act to which such person would have been liable, 
had not such immunity been granted.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>471570</tid>
<number>30</number>Amendment of section 26.- In section 26 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" a Metropolitan Magistrate or a 
Judicial Magistrate of the first class", the words" a Court of 
Session" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>419910</tid>
<number> 31</number> Amendment of section 29.- In section 29 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1846516</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (db), for the words" Presiding Officers", the words 
" Presiding Officers, Members" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1234180</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (dc), for the words" Presiding Officers", the words 
" Presiding Officers, or other Members" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1976007</tid>
<number> 32</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1855358</tid>
<number>1</number>The Securities and Exchange Board of India  
 (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>2002</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>431064</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Securities and Exchange Board of 
India (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>2002</year>), anything done or 
any action taken under the principal Act as amended by the said 
Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or ta en under the 
principal Act, as amended by this Act.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>