<act><tid>1326525</tid>
<title>THE JAMMU AND KASHMIR (EXTENSION OF LAWS) ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 25th September, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the extension of certain laws to the State 
of Jammu and Kashmir.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>423622</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>825591</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Jammu and Kashmir (Extension of Laws) Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>714874</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>882085</tid>
<number> 2</number> Extension and amendment of certain laws.
<section><tid>1595835</tid>
<number>1</number>The Acts and  
Ordinance mentioned in the Schedule and all rules, orders and 
regulations made thereunder are hereby extended to, and shall be in 
force in, the State of Jammu and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>744245</tid>
<number>2</number>With effect from the commencement of this Act, the Acts and 
Ordinance mentioned in the Schedule shall be amended as specified 
therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1792136</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of references to laws not in force in Jammu and 
Kashmir. Any reference in any Act or in the Ordinance mentioned in the 
Schedule to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference 
to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that State.


</article>



<article><tid>1074294</tid>
<number>4</number>Construction of references to authorities where new 
authorities have been constituted. Any reference by whatever form of 
words in any law for the time being in force in the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir to any authority competent at the date of the passing of that 
law to exercise any powers or discharge any functions in that State 
shall, where a corresponding new authority has been constituted by or 
under any law now extended to that State, have effect as if it were a 
reference to the new authority.


</article>



<article><tid>800736</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeals and savings. If immediately before the commencement of 
this Act there is in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir any law 
corresponding to any Act or Ordinance now extended to that State, that 
law
<pagefootnote><pagenum>398</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 11- <year>1956</year>, vide notification No. S. R. O. 2327, dated 10- 10- <year>1956</year>, 
Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1728.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall, save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, stand 
repealed on such commencement:

Provided that the repeal shall not affect--

<section><tid>1143988</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any law so repealed or 
anything duly done or suffered thereunder,

</section>

<section><tid>675046</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under any law so repealed,

</section>

<section><tid>1682651</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any law so 
repealed, or

</section>

<section><tid>434668</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect 
of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid;
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed, as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything 
done or any action taken (including any appointment or delegation  
made, notification, instruction or direction issued, form, bye- law or 
scheme framed, certificate obtained, permit or licence granted or 
  registration effected) under any such law shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of the Act or 
Ordinance now extended to that State, and shall continue to be in 
force accordingly unless and until superseded by anything done or any 
action taken under the said Act or Ordinance.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1840995</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1951992</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of any Act or Ordinance now extended 
to the State of Jammu and Kashmir, the Central Government may, by 
order notified in the Official Gazette, make such provisions or give 
such directions as appear to it necessary for the removal of the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1220250</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, any such notified order may,--

<subsection><tid>351059</tid>
<number>a</number>specify the corresponding authorities within the meaning 
of section 4,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200505</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for the transfer of any matter pending 
immediately before the commencement of this Act before 
any Court, tribunal or other authority, to any 
corresponding Court, tribunal or authority for 
disposal,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>784248</tid>
<number>c</number>specify the areas or circumstances in which, or the 
extent to which, or the conditions subject to which, 
anything done or any action taken (including any of the  
  matters specified in the second proviso to section 5) 
under any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>399</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

law repealed by that section shall be recognised or 
given effect to under the corresponding provision of 
the Act or Ordinance now extended.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>