<act><title>

    THE BEEDI WORKERS WELFARE CESS RULES, 19771</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and Commencement.—These 
    rules may be called the Beedi Workers Welfare Cess Rules, 1977.
 <section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the fifteenth day of February, 1977. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   ‘Act’ means the Beedi Workers Welfare 
      Cess Act, 1976 (56 of 1976); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   ‘Cess’ means the cess levied and 
      collected under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   ‘Commissioner’ means a Welfare 
      Commissioner appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Beedi 
      Workers Welfare Fund Act, 1976 (62 of 1976);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   words and expressions used herein and 
      not defined but defined in the Central Excise and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 
      1944)* or the rules thereunder, have the meanings, respectively assigned 
      to them in that Act or the rules.
</subsection>






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Application of Act 1 of 1944 and the Rules made thereunder.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in these rules, the provisions of the Central Excise 
    and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 1944)* and the rules made thereunder, including the 
    provisions relating to refund of duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in 
    relation to the levy and collection of the cess as they apply in relation to 
    the levy and collection of the duty of excise on tobacco under the Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Recovery 
    of excise duty.—The duty of excise 
    levied under section 3 of the Act on tobacco issued to any person from a 
    warehouse for any purpose in connection with the manufacture of beedi, shall 
    be collected by the Central Excise Officer-in-charge of the warehouse.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Return 
    regarding Collection of Cess.—The 
    Collector of Central Excise of every region shall send to the Commissioner 
    concerned on or before the end of every month a return indicating the amount 
    of cess collected and credited to the Fund during the previous month.
 

 


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>