<act> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 19931
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Foreign Trade (Regulation) Rules, 1993.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date2
of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.
  



</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Foreign Trade (Development and 
Regulation) Act, 1992 (22 of 1992);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>   “charitable purpose” includes relief of the 
poor, education, medical relief, and the advancement of any other object of 
general public utility;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   “importer” or “exporter” means a person who 
imports or exports goods and holds a valid Importer-exporter Code Number granted 
under section 7;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>   “licensing authority” means an authority 
authorised by the Director General under sub-section (2) of section 9 to grant 
or renew a licence under these rules;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>   “Policy” means export and import Policy 
formulated and announced by the Central Government under section 5;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>   “schedule” means a Schedule appended to these 
rules;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>   “special licence” means a licence granted under 
sub-section (2) of section 8;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>   “value” has the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (41) of section 2 of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962);
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>   words and expression used in these rules and 
not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>3</number> Grant of special licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Importer-exporter Code Number granted to any person has been suspended 
or cancelled under sub-section (1) of section 8, the Director General may, 
having regard to the following factors, grant to him a special licence, namely:—
 </section><section>       <number>1</number>   that the denial of a special licence is likely 
to affect the Foreign Trade of India adversely; or
 </section><section>       <number>2</number>   that the suspension or cancellation of the 
Importer-exporter Code Number is likely to lead to non-fulfilment of any 
obligation by India under any international agreement;
 </section><section>       <number>3</number>   The special licence granted to any person under 
sub-rule (1) shall be non-transferable.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>4</number> Application for grant of 
licences.—A person may make an 
application for the grant of a licence to import or export goods in accordance 
with the provisions of the Policy or an Order made under section 3.
</article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>5</number> Fee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for a licence to import shall be accompanied by the fee 
specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The mode of deposit of fee 
shall be as specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No fee shall be payable in 
respect of any application made by—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   the Central Government, a State Government or 
any department or any office of the Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   any local authority for the bona fide 
import of goods required by it for official use;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   any institution set up for educational, 
charitable or missionary purposes for the import of goods required for its use;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>   an applicant for the import of any goods (other 
than a vehicle) if the import of the goods is for his personal use which is not 
connected with trade or manufacture.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The fee once received will 
not be refunded except in the following circumstances, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   where the fee has been deposited in excess of 
the specified scale of fee; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   where the fee has been deposited but no 
application has been made; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   where the fee has been deposited in error but 
the applicant is exempt from payment of fee.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>6</number> Conditions of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be deemed to be a condition of every licence for export that—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   no person shall transfer or acquire by 
transfer any licence issued by the licensing authority except in accordance with 
the provisions of the Policy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   the goods for the export of which the licence 
is granted shall be the property of the licensee at the time of the export.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The licensing authority may 
issue a licence for import subject to one or more of the following conditions, 
namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   that the goods covered by the licence shall not 
be disposed of except in accordance with the provisions of the Policy or in the 
manner specified by the licensing authority in the licence;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   that the applicant for a licence shall execute 
a bond for complying with the terms and conditions of the licence.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> It shall be deemed to be a 
condition of every licence for import that—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   no person shall transfer or acquire by transfer 
any licence issued by the licensing authority except in accordance with the 
provisions of the Policy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   the goods for the import of which a licence is 
granted shall be the property of the licensee at the time of import and upto the 
time of clearance through Customs;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   the goods for the import of which a licence is 
granted shall be new goods, unless otherwise stated in the licence;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>   that the goods covered by the licence for 
import shall not be exported without the written permission of the Director 
General.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Any person importing goods 
from the United States of America in accordance with the terms of the Indo-US 
Memorandum of Understanding on Technology Transfer shall also comply with all 
the conditions and assurances specified in the Import Certificate issued in 
terms of such Memorandum, and such other assurances given by the person 
importing those goods to the Government of the United States of America through 
the Government of India.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>7</number> Refusal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director General or the licensing authority may for reasons to be recorded 
in writing, refuse to grant or renew a licence if—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   the applicant has contravened any law relating 
to customs or foreign exchange;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   the application for the licence does not 
substantially conform to any provision of these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   the application or any document used in 
support thereof contains any false or fraudulent or misleading statement;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>   it has been decided by the Central Government 
to canalise the export or import of goods and distribution thereof, as the case 
may be, through special or specialised agencies;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>   any action against the applicant is for the 
time being pending under the Act or rules and Orders made thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>   the applicant is or was a managing partner in 
a partnership firm, or is or was a Director of a private limited company, having 
controlling interest, against which any action is for the time being pending 
under the Act or rules and Orders made thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>   the applicant fails to pay any penalty imposed 
on him under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>   the applicant has tampered with a licence;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>   the applicant or any agent or employee of the 
applicant with his consent has been a party to any corrupt or fraudulent 
practice for the purposes of obtaining any other licence;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>   the applicant is not eligible for a licence in 
accordance with any provision of the Policy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>   the applicant fails to produce any documents 
called for by the Director General or the licensing authority;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>   in the case of a licence for import, no 
foreign exchange is available for the purpose;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>m</number>   the application has been signed by a person 
other than a person duly authorised by the applicant under the provisions of the 
Policy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>   the applicant has attempted to obtain or has 
obtained cash compensatory support, duty drawback, cash assistance benefits 
allowed to Registered Exporters or any other similar benefits from the Central 
Government or any agency authorised by the Central Government in relation to 
exports made by him on the basis of any false, fraudulent or misleading 
statement or any document which is false or fabricated or tampered with.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The refusal of a licence 
under sub-rule (1) shall be without prejudice to any other action that may be 
taken against an applicant by the licensing authority under the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>8</number> Amendment of licence.—The 
licensing authority may of its own motion or on an application by the licensee, 
amend any licence in such manner as may be necessary or to rectify any error or 
omission in the licence.
</article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>9</number> Suspension of a licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Director General or the licensing authority may by order in writing, suspend 
the operation of a licence granted to—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   any person, if an order of detention has been 
made against such person under the provisions of the Conservation of Foreign 
Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling Activities Act, 1974 (52 of 1974); or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   a partnership firm or a private limited 
company, if the person referred to in clause (a) is a partner or a whole time 
director or managing director, as the case may be, of such firm or company:
 Provided that the order of 
suspension shall cease to have effect in respect of the aforesaid person or, as 
the case may be, the partnership firm or company, when the order of detention 
made against such person,—
 <subsubsection>        <number>i</number>   being an order of detention to which the 
provisions of section 9 of the Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention 
of Smuggling Activities Act, 1974 (52 of 1974) do not apply, has been revoked on 
the report of Advisory Board under section 8 of that Act or before receipt of 
the report of the Advisory Board or before making a reference to the Advisory 
Board; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>ii</number>   being an order of detention to which the 
provisions of section 9 of the Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention 
of Smuggling Activities Act, 1974 (52 of 1974) apply, has been revoked on the 
report of the Advisory Board under section 8 read with sub-section (2) of 
section 9 of that Act or before receipt of such report;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>iii</number>   has been set aside by a court of competent 
jurisdiction.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Director General or the 
licensing authority may by an order in writing suspend the operation of any 
licence granted under these rules, where proceedings for cancellation of such 
licence have been initiated under rule 10.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>10</number> Cancellation of the 
licence.—The Director General or the 
licensing authority may, by an order in writing, cancel any licence granted 
under these rules, if—
 <section>       <number>a</number>   the licence has been obtained by fraud, 
suppression of facts or misrepresentation; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>   the licensee has committed a breach of any of 
the conditions of the licensee; or
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   the licensee has tampered with the licence in 
any manner; or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>   the licensee has contravened any law relating 
to customs or foreign exchange or the rules and regulations relating thereto.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>11</number> Declaration as to value 
and quality of imported goods.—On the 
importation into, or exportation out of, any customs port of any goods, whether 
liable to duty or not, the owner of such goods shall, in the bill of entry or 
the shipping bill or any other documents prescribed under the Customs Act, 1962, 
state the value, quality and description of such goods to the best of his 
knowledge and belief and in case of exportation of goods, certify that the 
quality and specification of the goods as stated in those documents are in 
accordance with the terms of the export contract entered into with the buyer or 
consignee in pursuance of which the goods are being exported and shall subscribe 
to a declaration of the truth of such statement at the foot of such bill of 
entry or shipping bill or any other documents.
</article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>12</number> Declaration as to 
importer-exporter code number.— On 
the importation into, or exportation out of, any customs port of any goods, the 
importer or exporter shall, in the bill of entry or shipping bill or, as the 
case may be, in any other documents prescribed by rules made under the Act or 
the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962), state the importer-exporter code number 
allotted to him by the Competent Authority.
</article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>13</number> Utilisation of imported 
goods.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall use any 
imported goods allotted to him by the State Trading Corporation of India or any 
other agency recognised by the Central Government in a manner and for the 
purpose, otherwise than as declared by him in his application for such allotment 
or in any document submitted by him in support of such application.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall dispose of 
any goods imported by him against a licence except in accordance with the terms 
and conditions of such licence.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>14</number> Prohibition regarding 
making, signing of any declaration, statement or documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall make, sign or use or cause to be made, signed or used any 
declaration, statement or document for the purposes of obtaining a licence or 
importing any goods knowing or having reason to believe that such declaration, 
statement or document is false in any material particular.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall employ any 
corrupt or fraudulent practice for the purposes of obtaining any licence of 
importing or exporting any goods;
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>15</number> Power to enter premises 
and inspect, search and seize goods, documents, things and conveyances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person authorised by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 
10 (hereinafter called “the authorised person”) may, as any reasonable time, 
enter any premises in which—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   any imported goods or materials which are 
liable to confiscation under the provisions of the Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   any books of account or documents or things 
which, in his opinion, will be useful for or relevant to, any proceedings under 
the Act,
 are suspected to have been kept or concealed and may inspect such 
goods, materials, books of account, documents or things and may take such notes 
or extracts therefrom as he thinks fit.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If the authorised person has 
reasons to believe that—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   any imported goods or materials liable to 
confiscation under the Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   any books of account or documents or things 
which, in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any proceedings under 
the Act,
 are secreted in any premises he may enter into and search such 
premises for such goods, materials, books of account, documents or things.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> (a) If the authorised person 
has reason to believe that any imported goods or materials are liable to 
confiscation under the Act, he may seize such goods or materials together with 
the package, covering or receptable, if any, in which such goods or materials 
are found to have been mixed with any other goods or material:
 Provided that where it is not 
practicable to seize any such goods or materials, the authorised person may 
serve on the owner of the goods or materials an order that he shall not remove, 
part with or otherwise deal with the goods or materials except with the previous 
permission of the authorised person.
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where any goods or materials 
are seized under clause (a) and no notice in respect thereof is given within six 
months of the seizure of the goods or materials, the goods or materials shall be 
returned to the person from whose possession they were seized:
 Provided that the aforesaid 
period of six months may, on sufficient cause being shown, be extended by the 
Director General for a further period not exceeding six months.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The authorised person may 
seize any books of account or documents or things which in his opinion, will be 
useful for, or relevant to, any proceedings under the Act.
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The person from whose 
custody any documents are seized under this sub-rule, shall be entitled to make 
copies thereof or take extracts thereform in the presence of the authorised 
person.
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> If any person legally 
entitled to the books of account or other documents or things seized under this 
sub-rule objects, for any reason, to the retention by the authorised person of 
the books of account or the documents or things, he may move an application to 
the Central Government stating therein the reasons for such objection, request 
for the return of the books of account or documents or things.
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> On receipt of the 
application under clause (e), the Central Government may, after giving the 
applicant an opportunity of being heard, pass such order as it may think fit.
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> Where any document is 
produced or furnished by any person or has been seized from the custody or 
control of any person under the Act or has been received from any place outside 
India in the course of the investigation for any contravention referred to in 
section 11 by any person and such document is tendered in evidence against the 
person by whom it is produced or from whom it was seized or against such person 
or any other person who is jointly proceeded against, the adjudicating 
authority, shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any 
other law for the time being in force,—
 <subsubsection>        <number>i</number>   presume, unless the contrary is proved, that 
the signature and every other part of such document which purports to be in the 
hand-writing of any particular person of which the adjudicating, authority may 
reasonably assume to have been signed by or to be in the handwriting of any 
particular person, is under the person’s, handwriting, and in the case of a 
document executed or attested, it was executed or attested by the person by whom 
it purports to have been so executed or attested;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>ii</number>   admit the document in evidence notwithstanding 
that it is not duly stamped, if such document is otherwise admissible in 
evidence.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The authorised person, may, 
if he has reason to suspect that any conveyance or animal is being or is about 
to be used for the transportation of any imported goods or material which are 
liable to confiscation under the Act, and that by such transportation any 
provision of the Act has been, is being or is about to be contravened at any 
time, stop such conveyance or animal or in the case of aircraft, compel it to 
land, and—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   rummage and search the conveyance or any part 
thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   examine and search any goods or material in the 
conveyance or on the animal;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   if it becomes necessary to stop any conveyance 
or animal, he may use all lawful means for stopping it and where such means 
fail, the conveyance or animal may be fired upon,
 and where he is satisfied that it is necessary so to do to prevent 
the contravention of any provision of the Act or of the rules and orders made 
thereunder or the policy or condition of any licence, he may seize such 
conveyance or animal:
 Explanation.—Any 
reference in this rule to a conveyance shall, unless the context otherwise 
requires, be construed as including a reference to an aircraft, vehicle or 
vessel.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>16</number> Settlement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The adjudicating authority may determine the amount of settlement to be paid by 
the person to whom a notice has been issued and who has opted for settlement, 
and has admitted the contravention specified in the notice, in the following 
cases, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   where it is of the opinion that the 
contravention of any provision of the Act or these rules or the policy has been 
made without mens rea or without wilful mistake or without suppression of 
facts, or without any collusion or without fraud and forgery, or without an 
intent to cause loss of foreign exchange; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   where the person importing the goods has not 
met the requirements of the actual user conditions as specified in the policy 
and has not misutilised the said imported goods; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   where the person importing the goods has not 
fulfilled the export obligation and has not misutilised the said imported goods.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where a person has opted for 
settlement under sub-rule (1), the settlement made by the adjudicating authority 
shall be final.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>17</number> Confiscation and 
redemption.—
<section><number>1</number> Any imported goods or 
materials in respect of which—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   any condition of the licence, or letter of 
authority under which they were imported, relating to their utilisation or 
distribution; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   any condition, relating to their utilisation or 
distribution, subject to which they were received from or through an agency 
recognised by the Central Government; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   any condition imposed under the policy with 
regard to the sale disposal of such goods or materials,
 has been, is being, or is attempted to be, contravened, shall 
together with any package, covering or receptacle in which such goods are found, 
be liable to be confiscated by the adjudicating authority, and where such goods 
or materials are so mixed with any other goods or materials that they cannot be 
readily separated, such other goods or materials shall also be liable to be so 
confiscated:
 Provided that where it is 
established to the satisfaction of the adjudicating authority that any goods or 
materials which are liable to confiscation under this rule, had been imported 
for personal use, and not for any trade or industry, such goods, or materials 
shall not be ordered to be confiscated.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The adjudicating authority 
may permit the redemption of the confiscated goods or materials upon payment of 
redemption charges equivalent to the market value of such goods or materials.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Trade (Regulation)  
Rules, 1993
  
 <article><number>18</number> Confiscation of conveyance.—
<section><number>1</number> Any conveyance or 
animal which has been, is being, or is attempted to be used, for the transport 
of any goods or materials that are imported and which are liable to confiscation 
under rule 17, shall be liable to be confiscated by the adjudicating authority 
unless the owner of the conveyance or animal proves that it was, is being, or is 
about to be so used without the knowledge or connivance of the owner himself, 
his agent, if any, and the person in charge of the conveyance or animal and that 
each of them had taken all reasonable precautions against such use.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The adjudicating authority shall permit redemption of the 
confiscated conveyance or animal used for the transport of goods or passengers 
for hire upon payment of redemption charges equivalent to the market value of 
such conveyance or animal.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>