<act><title>The Small Coins 
      (Offences) Act, 1971</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and duration.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the 
      Small Coins (Offences) Act, 1971. 
 1[***]
  


 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the 
      context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    “mint” 
      means a mint of the Government of India;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    “small 
      coin” means any coin of the value of less than one rupee, which is legal 
      tender under the Indian Coinage Act, 1906 (3 of 1906).  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Prohibition on melting or destruction of small 
      coins.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      No person shall—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    melt 
      or destroy any small coin, or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    have 
      in his possession, custody or control—  
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>    any 
      melted coin, whether in the molten state or in a solid state, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    any 
      small coin in a destroyed or mutilated state, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>    
      small coins substantially in excess of his reasonable requirements in such 
      circumstances as to indicate that he is having the possession, custody or 
      control of such small coins for the purpose of melting or destroying such 
      small coins.  
 Explanation.—For the purpose of determining 
      the reasonable requirements of small coins of a person, due regard shall 
      be had to—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number>    his 
      total daily requirements of small coins,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    the 
      nature of his business, occupation or profession,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>    the 
      mode of his acquisition of small coins, and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>    the 
      manner in which, and the place at which, such small coins are being 
      possessed, held or controlled by him.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whoever is found to be in the possession of any metal, which 
      contains alloys in the same proportions in which they have been used in 
      the manufacture of any small coin, shall be presumed, until the contrary 
      is proved, to have contravened the provisions of sub-section 
      (1).  
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall 
      apply to the mint.  
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Penalty for contravention of section 3.—Whoever contravenes any provision 
      of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3 without any reasonable excuse, the burden 
      of proving of which shall lie on such person, shall be punishable with 
      imprisonment for a term of not less than three months but not more than 
      five years.
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an offence against this 
      Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
      offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
      company for the conduct of its business, shall be deemed to be guilty of 
      the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
      accordingly:  
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render 
      any person liable to punishment, if he proves that the offence was 
      committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence 
      to prevent the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where 
      any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
      proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance 
      of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, 
      manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
      manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that 
      offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
      accordingly.  
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
      “company” means any body corporate and includes a firm, society or other 
      association of individuals; and  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    
      “director”,—  
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>    in 
      relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    in 
      relation to a society or other association of individuals means the person 
      who is entrusted, under the rules of the society or other association, 
      with the management of the affairs of the society or other association, as 
      the case may be.  
 
  </subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Offences to be cognizable, bailable and not 
      compoundable.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
      Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), offences against this Act shall be cognizable 
      and bailable but shall not be compoundable.
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Offences may be tried summarily.—Notwithstanding anything contained 
      in section 260 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), 
      offences against this Act may be tried summarily by a Presidency 
      Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Forfeiture.—Any small coin or metal in 
      relation to which any offence against this Act has been committed shall be 
      forfeited to Government.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Provisions of Act 20 of 1958 not to apply to offences under this 
      Act.—Nothing in the Probation of Offenders Act, 1958, shall apply to 
      any offence against this Act.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Repeal.—The Small Coins (Offences) Ordinance, 1971 (15 of 1971), is hereby 
      repealed.  
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>