<act><tid>41392</tid>
<title>THE LAND ACQUISITION (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 12th September, <year>1962</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year>, and to 
validate certain acquisitions under that Act.





<article><tid>400355</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Land Acquisition 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1962</year>.
 2 to

Amendments to the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 2 to 6.[ Amendments to the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of  
  <year>1894</year>).] Not printed.



</article>



<article><tid>1423333</tid>
<number> 7</number> Validation of certain acquisitions. Notwithstanding any 
judgment, decree or order of any court, every acquisition of land for 
a Company made or purporting to have been made under Part VII of the 
principal Act before the 20th day of July, <year>1962</year>, shall, in so far as 
such acquisition is not for any of the purposes mentioned in clause 
 (a) or clause (b) of sub- section
<section><tid>1486905</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 40 of the principal  
Act, be deemed to have been made for the purpose mentioned in clause 
 (aa) of the said sub- section, and accordingly every such acquisition 
and any proceeding, order, agreement or action in connection with such 
acquisition shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been, as 
valid as if the provisions of sections 40 and 41 of the principal Act, 
as amended by this Act, were in force at all material times when such 
acquisition was made or proceeding was held or order was made or 
agreement was entered into or action was taken.
Explanation.-- In this section" Company" has the same meaning as 
in clause (e) of section 3 of the principal Act, as amended by this 
Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1695691</tid>
<number> 8</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1247553</tid>
<number>1</number>The Land Acquisition (Amendment)  
Ordinance, <year>1962</year> (3 of <year>1962</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>818050</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act, as if this Act had commenced on the 20th day of 
July, <year>1962</year>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>