<act><title>


The Infant Milk Substitutes, Feeding Bottles 
    and Infant Foods (Regulation of Production, Supply and Distribution) Rules, 
    19931</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Infant Milk Substitutes, Feeding Bottles and 
    Infant Foods (Regulation of Production, Supply and Distribution Rules, 1993. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the 
    date2 of 
    commencement of the Infant Milk Substitutes, Feeding Bottles and Infant 
    Foods (Regulation of Production, Supply and Distribution) Act, 1992 (41 of 
    1992). 
 

 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” 
    means the Infant Milk Substitutes, Feeding Bottles and Infant Foods 
    (Regulation of Production, Supply and Distribution) Act, 1992 (41 of 1992);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    
    “authorised officer” means an officer not below the rank of a Class I (Group 
    A or whatever name called) officer of the Government duly authorised by the 
    State Government under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “food 
    inspector” means a person appointed by the Government as such under section 
    9 of the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    
    “section” means a section of the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions used in these rules 
    and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the respective meanings 
    assigned to them in the Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Local limits of jurisdiction of food 
    inspectors.—The local limits of  jurisdiction of food inspectors shall 
    be the same as are assigned to them under the Prevention of Food 
    Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Authorised officers.—
<section><number>1</number> No officer 
    of the Government shall be authorised by the State Government under section 
    12 unless he is—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a 
    medical officer in charge of health administration of a local area; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a 
    graduate in medicine and has received at least one month’s training in food 
    inspection and sampling work approved for the purpose of food inspection 
    under the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954) by the 
    Central Government or a State Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, define the local limits of jurisdiction of 
    authorised officers.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Conditions and 
      restrictions for donation and distribution of 1[infant milk substitutes or infant foods or feeding bottles] or 
      equipments and materials relating to them through health care 
      system.—No institution, organisation or health 
      worker in private practice, engaged in health care for mothers, infants or 
      pregnant women, shall donate or distribute any educational or other  
      informational or communication aids relating to 1[infant milk substitutes or infant foods or feeding bottles] 
      without complying with the following conditions and restrictions, namely:—  
 <section><number>a</number>    the donor should be 
      informed in writing on—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    the need for 
      promoting breast feeding;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    the 
      nutritional superiority of mother’s milk;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    the 
      benefits of breast milk, that is to  say that breast milk 
      is—
 <subsubsection><number>A</number>    the best 
      natural food for infants;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>B</number>    always 
      clean;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>C</number>    protects the 
      infant from infection and diseases;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>D</number>    available 
      always;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>E</number>    requires no 
      special preparation;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>    that breast 
      feeding helps parents to space their children;
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>    the danger 
      of microbial contamination involved in bottle feeding;
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number>    informational or educational equipment or 
      material relating to 1[infant milk substitutes or infant 
      foods or feeding bottles] should be donated or distributed only in case it 
      is found necessary for healthy growth of the infant by a medical 
      practitioner.
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Conditions and restrictions for 
    donation and distribution of 
1[infant 
    milk substitutes or infant foods or feeding bottles] or equipments and 
    materials relating to them through health care system.—No 
    institution, organisation or health worker in private practice, engaged in 
    health care for mothers, infants or pregnant women, shall donate or 
    distribute any educational or other  informational or communication aids 
    relating to 
1[infant 
    milk substitutes or infant foods or feeding bottles] without complying with 
    the following conditions and restrictions, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the 
    donor should be informed in writing on—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the need for promoting breast feeding;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the nutritional superiority of 
    mother’s milk;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the benefits of breast milk, that is 
    to  say that breast milk is—
 <subsubsection>
<number>A</number>    the best natural food for infants;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>B</number>    always clean;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>C</number>    protects the infant from infection and 
    diseases;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>D</number>    available always;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>E</number>    requires no special preparation;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    that breast feeding helps parents to 
    space their children;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the danger of microbial contamination 
    involved in bottle feeding;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    informational or educational equipment or material relating to 


    1[infant milk 
    substitutes or infant foods or feeding bottles] should be donated or 
    distributed only in case it is found necessary for healthy growth of the 
    infant by a medical practitioner.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Language of the notice and 
      other particulars of declaration.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall produce, supply 
      or distribute any infant milk substitute or infant food unless the 
      container thereof or any label affixed thereto indicates in a clear, 
      conspicuous and in an easily readable and understandable manner the words 
      “IMPORTANT NOTICE”, in capital letters in English and its equivalent in 
      Hindi in Devnagri script:  
 Provided that nothing herein 
      contained shall prevent the use of any local language in addition to the 
      language required to be used under this sub-rule.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The particulars of declaration 
      to be specified on the label under the Prevention of Food Adulteration 
      Act, 1954 (37 of 1954) and the rules made thereunder shall be in English 
      or in Hindi in Devnagri script:  
 Provided that nothing herein 
      contained shall prevent the user of any language in addition to the 
      language required to be used under this sub-rule.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Language of the notice and other 
    particulars of declaration.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall produce, supply or 
    distribute any infant milk substitute or infant food unless the container 
    thereof or any label affixed thereto indicates in a clear, conspicuous and 
    in an easily readable and understandable manner the words “IMPORTANT 
    NOTICE”, in capital letters in English and its equivalent in Hindi in 
    Devnagri script:  
 
Provided that nothing herein contained shall 
    prevent the use of any local language in addition to the language required 
    to be used under this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The particulars of declaration to be 
    specified on the label under the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 
    (37 of 1954) and the rules made thereunder shall be in English or in Hindi 
    in Devnagri script:  
 
Provided that nothing herein contained shall 
    prevent the user of any language in addition to the language required to be 
    used under this sub-rule.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> 1[Particulars of labelling of infant milk substitute and infant 
      foods].—In addition to the requirements specified 
      by or under the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954) and 
      under section 6 of the Act, the label or the container of every 
      1[infant milk substitute or infant food] shall conform to the 
      following, namely:—  
 <section><number>a</number>    the types of letters used shall not be less 
      than 5 2[millimeters in size for IMPORTANT 
      NOTICE and the statement MOTHER’S MILK IS BEST FOR YOUR 
      BABY].
 </section><section><number>b</number>    the colour of the text printed or used shall 
      be different from that of the background of 1[the label or container], as the 
      case may be.
 </section><section><number>c</number>    the text of the particulars shall be 
      prominent and conspicuous in the central panel of 1[the label or 
      container].
 </section><section><number>d</number>    it shall 
      indicate—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    that 
      an infant milk substitute or an 1[infant food] should be prepared appropriately and hygienically 
      besides taking adequate care in cleaning of utensils, bottles and 
      teats.
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    a warning 
      against health hazards of inappropriate preparation as under:
 “Infant milk substitutes/Infant 
      Foods.
 “Warning/caution—Careful and 
      hygienic preparation of infant food in most essential for health. Do not 
      use fewer scoops than directed since dilute feeding will not provide 
      adequate nutrients needed by your infant. Do not use more scoops than 
      directed since concentrated feed will not provide the water needs of your 
      infant.”
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    the 
      approximate composition of nutrients per 100 grams of product including 
      its energy value in calories.
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>    the storage 
      conditions specifically stating “Store in cool and dry place in an 
      air-tight container” or the like.
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>    the feeding 
      chart and directions for use and instructions for discarding left over 
      feed, the batch number and date of manufacture.
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>    
      instructions for use of measuring scoop (level or heaped) and the quantity 
      per scoop.
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number>    the 
      prescribed period by which the infant milk substitutes or the infant food, 
      as the case may be, is to be consumed.
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number>    the 
      Protein Efficiency Ratio (PER) which shall be minimum of 2.5 if the 
      product other than the infant milk substitutes and infant foods is claimed 
      to have high quality protein.
  





 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
1[Particulars 
    of labelling of infant milk substitute and infant foods].—In 
    addition to the requirements specified by or under the Prevention of Food 
    Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954) and under section 6 of the Act, the 
    label or the container of every 
1[infant 
    milk substitute or infant food] shall conform to the following, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    
    the types of letters used shall not be less than 5 

    2[millimeters in size 
    for IMPORTANT NOTICE and the statement MOTHER’S MILK IS BEST FOR YOUR BABY].
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    the colour of the text printed or used shall be different from that of the 
    background of 

    1[the label or 
    container], as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    
    the text of the particulars shall be prominent and conspicuous in the 
    central panel of 

    1[the label or 
    container].
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    it 
    shall indicate—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    that an infant milk substitute or 
    an 1[infant 
    food] should be prepared appropriately and hygienically besides taking 
    adequate care in cleaning of utensils, bottles and teats.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    a warning against health hazards of 
    inappropriate preparation as under:
 
“Infant milk substitutes/Infant Foods.
 
“Warning/caution—Careful and hygienic 
    preparation of infant food in most essential for health. Do not use fewer 
    scoops than directed since dilute feeding will not provide adequate 
    nutrients needed by your infant. Do not use more scoops than directed since 
    concentrated feed will not provide the water needs of your infant.”
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the approximate composition of 
    nutrients per 100 grams of product including its energy value in calories.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the storage conditions specifically 
    stating “Store in cool and dry place in an air-tight container” or the like.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the feeding chart and directions for 
    use and instructions for discarding left over feed, the batch number and 
    date of manufacture.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    instructions for use of measuring 
    scoop (level or heaped) and the quantity per scoop.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    the prescribed period by which the 
    infant milk substitutes or the infant food, as the case may be, is to be 
    consumed.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    the Protein Efficiency Ratio (PER) 
    which shall be minimum of 2.5 if the product other than the infant milk 
    substitutes and infant foods is claimed to have high quality protein.
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Particulars which 
      1[a label or container] should not contain.—Without prejudice to the requirements under the Prevention of Food 
      Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954) and the rules made thereunder, the 
      following restrictions on use of words in any language on 1[the label or container], as the case may be, shall be applicable:— 
 <section><number>a</number>    1[the label or container] shall not 
      contain any reference to the Act or these rules or any comment on, or 
      reference to, or explanation of any particulars or declaration required by 
      the Act or any of these rules to be included in the label which directly 
      or by implication, contradicts, qualifies or modifies such particulars or 
      declaration.
 </section><section><number>b</number>    no words implying 
      “recommended by the medical profession” or any words which imply or 
      suggest that the food is recommended, prescribed or approved by medical 
      practitioners shall be used in a label, container or 
      advertisement.
 </section><section><number>c</number>    1[the label or container] shall not 
      contain the terms “Humanised” or “Maternalised” or any other similar 
      expressions in any language.
 </section><section><number>d</number>    No 1[label or container] of infant food 
      shall exhibit the words “Full Protein Food”, “Energy Food”, “Complete 
      Food” or “Health Food” or any other similar expressions in any 
      language.
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Particulars which 
1[a 
    label or container] should not contain.—Without 
    prejudice to the requirements under the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 
    1954 (37 of 1954) and the rules made thereunder, the following restrictions 
    on use of words in any language on 
1[the 
    label or container], as the case may be, shall be applicable:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    

    1[the label or 
    container] shall not contain any reference to the Act or these rules or any 
    comment on, or reference to, or explanation of any particulars or 
    declaration required by the Act or any of these rules to be included in the 
    label which directly or by implication, contradicts, qualifies or modifies 
    such particulars or declaration.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    no 
    words implying “recommended by the medical profession” or any words which 
    imply or suggest that the food is recommended, prescribed or approved by 
    medical practitioners shall be used in a label, container or advertisement.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    

    1[the label or 
    container] shall not contain the terms “Humanised” or “Maternalised” or any 
    other similar expressions in any language.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    
    No 

    1[label or container] 
    of infant food shall exhibit the words “Full Protein Food”, “Energy Food”, 
    “Complete Food” or “Health Food” or any other similar expressions in any 
    language.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Details of information 
      intended to reach pregnant women or mothers of infants through education 
      or other material.—
<section><number>1</number> Every educational or other material, whether 
      audio or visual, dealing with pre-natal or post-natal care or with the 
      feeding of an infant and intended to reach pregnant women and mothers of 
      infants shall, besides the information specified in clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> to (f) of 
      sub-section (1) of section 7, shall include—  
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number>    the following details of 
      advantages, as also nutritional superiority of breast 
      feeding:—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>    Immediately 
      after delivery, breast milk is yellowish and sticky. This milk is called 
      Colostrum, which is secreted during the first week of delivery. Colostrum 
      is more nutritious than that of mature milk because it contains more 
      protein, more anti-infective properties which are of great importance for 
      the infant’s defence against dangerous neo-natal infections. It also 
      contains higher levels of Vitamin ‘A’;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    breast 
      milk—
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number>    is a 
      complete and balanced food and provides all the nutrients needed by the 
      infant 1[for the first six months of life];
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number>    has 
      anti-infective properties that protect the infants from infection in the 
      early months;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>C</number>    is always 
      available;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>D</number>    needs no 
      utensils or water (which might carry germs) or fuel for its 
      preparation;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>    breast 
      feeding is much cheaper than feeding infant milk substitutes as the cost 
      of the extra food needed  by the mother is negligible compared to the 
      cost of feeding infant milk substitutes;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>    mothers who 
      breast feed usually have longer periods of infertility after child birth 
      than non-lactators;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    details of management of 
      breast feeding, as under:
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>    breast 
      feeding—
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number>    immediately 
      after delivery enables the contraction of the womb and helps the mother to 
      regain her figure quickly;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number>    is 
      successful when the infant suckles frequently and the mother wanting to 
      breast-feed is confident in her ability to do so;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    in order to 
      promote and support breast feeding the mother’s natural desire to breast 
      feed should always be encouraged by giving, where needed, practical advice 
      and making sure that she has the support of her relatives;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>    adequate 
      care for the breast and nipples should be taken during 
      pregnancy;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>    it is also 
      necessary to put the infant to the breast as soon as possible after 
      delivery;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number>    let the 
      mother and the infant stay together after the delivery, the mother and her 
      infant should be allowed to stay together (in hospital, this is called 
      “rooming-in”);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vi</number>    give the 
      infant Colostrum as it is rich in many nutrients and its anti-infective 
      factors protect the infants from infections during the few days of its 
      birth;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vii</number>    the 
      practice of discarding Colostrum and giving sugar water, honey water, 
      butter or other concoctions instead of Colostrum should be very strongly 
      discouraged;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>viii</number>    let the 
      infants suckle on demand;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ix</number>    every 
      effort should be made to breast feed the infants whenever they 
      cry;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>x</number>    mother 
      should keep her body and clothes and that of the infant always neat and 
      clean.
  






 
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>