<act><tid>166029</tid>
<title>THE SALARY, ALLOWANCES AND PENSION OF MEMBERS OF 
PARLIAMENT (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 14th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members 
of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1307524</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1204224</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> (30 of <year>1954</year>)  (hereinafter  
  referred to as the principal Act), after the proviso, the following 
provisos shall be inserted, namely:-
Provided further that in the case of salary, the provisions of this 
section shall have effect as if for the words" four thousand rupees", 
the words" twelve thousand rupees" had been substituted for a period 
of five years beginning from the date of commen ement of the Salary, 
Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>:

Provided also that in the case of the allowance, the provisions of 
this section shall have effect as if for the words" four hundred 
rupees", the words" five hundred rupees" had been substituted for a 
period of five years beginning from the date of commen ement of the 
Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2001</year>.'.



</article>



<article><tid>917727</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the Principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (c), in sub- clause (ii), for the words" six 
rupees per kilometre", the words" eight rupees per kilometre" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>824968</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 8A.- In section 8A of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>1066529</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" two thousand and five hundred rupees", the words 
" three thousand rupees" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1907704</tid>
<number>b</number>in the first proviso, for the words" five hundred rupees", the 
words" six hundred rupees" shall be substituted.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>