<act><title>


the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 20031</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 
2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date on which the Act comes into force.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number> “Act” means the Control of National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 2002 
(13 of 2003);
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number> “appellant” means a person making an appeal to the Tribunal under section 
14;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number> “appeal” means an appeal made to the Tribunal under section 14;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number> “legal practitioner” shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Advocates 
Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number> “Presiding Officer” means the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal;
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number> “Registrar” means the Registrar of a Tribunal;
 </section><section>
        
<number>g</number> “Registry” means the Registry of a Tribunal;
 </section><section>
        
<number>h</number> “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
         
<number>i</number> “Tribunal” means the National Highways Tribunal established under 
sub­-section (1) of section 5;
 </section><section>
         
<number>j</number>  the words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but are 
defined in the Act shall have the same meaning as respectively assigned to them 
in the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Sittings of the 
Tribunal.—A 
Tribunal shall hold its sittings either at its headquarters or at such other 
place failing within its jurisdiction as it may consider convenient.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Language of the 
Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The proceeding of the Tribunal shall be conducted in English or Hindi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal, reference, 
application, representation, document or other matters shall be accepted by the 
Tribunal unless the same is accompanied by a true copy of translation thereof in 
English or Hindi,
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Procedure for filing 
appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
memorandum of appeal shall be presented in the Form annexed to these rules by 
the appellant either in person, or by a legal practitioner authorised by him for 
such purpose to the Registrar or shall be sent by registered post addressed to 
such Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal sent by post 
under sub‑rule (1) shall be deemed to have been presented to the Registrar on 
the day on which it is received in the office of the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The appeal under 
sub‑rule (1) shall be presented in three complete sets in a paper book along 
with an empty file size envelope bearing full address of the respondent and 
where the number of respondent is more than one the sufficient number of extra 
paper book together with empty file size envelopes bearing full address of each 
respondent shall be furnished by the appellant.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Presentation and 
scrutiny of memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall endorse on every appeal the date on which it is presented 
under rule 5 or deem to have been presented under that rule and shall sign 
endorsement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the 
appeal is found to be order, it shall be duly registered and given a serial 
number.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If an appeal, on 
scrutiny, is found to be defective, and the defect noticed is formal in nature, 
the Registrar may allow the appellant to rectify the same in his presence and if 
the same defect is not formal in nature, the Registrar may allow the appellant 
such time to rectify the defect as he may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the appellant fails 
to rectify the defect within the time allowed in sub‑rule (3), the Registrar 
may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register 
such memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An appeal against the 
order of the Registrar under sub‑rule (4) shall be made within fifteen days of 
making of such order to the Presiding Officer, whose decision shall be final.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Place of filing 
memorandum of appeal.—The 
memorandum of appeal shall be filed by appellant with the Registrar having 
jurisdiction in the matter.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Contents of 
memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal filed under rule 5 shall set forth concisely under 
distinct head, the grounds of such appeal without any argument or narration, and 
such grounds shall be numbered consecutively and shall be typed in double line 
space on one side of the paper.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall not be 
necessary to present separate application to seek interim order or direction if 
the memorandum of appeal contains a prayer seeking an interim order pending 
final disposal of the appeal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Documents to 
accompany memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal shall be in triplicate and shall be accompanied with 
two copies of the order served attested by a notary or brief description of the 
action taken by the Highway Administration or an officer authorised on its 
behalf, as the case may be, against which the appeal is filed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The memorandum of 
appeal shall also be accompanied with an affidavit of the appellant stating 
therein that the facts stated in the memorandum of appeal and the documents 
relied upon and accompanied therewith are true to his knowledge and belief.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the appellant is 
being represented by a legal practitioner, a duly executed Vakalatnama 
authorising him to act as such shall also be appended to the memorandum of 
appeal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Plural remedies.—A 
memorandum of appeal shall seek relief or reliefs based on more than a single 
cause of action in one single memorandum of appeal unless the reliefs prayed for 
are consequential to one another.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Endorsing copy of 
appeal to the respondents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A copy of the memorandum of appeal and the paper book shall be served on each of 
the respondents as soon as they are filed by the Registrar by the registered 
post.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
service by registered post under sub‑rule (1), the appellant shall deposit the 
required envelopes and postal stamps with the registry or deposit required 
expenditure with the registry for such purpose and obtain a receipt for such 
deposit from the registry.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Filing of reply to 
the appeal and other documents by the respondents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The respondent may file three complete sets containing the reply to the appeal 
along with documents in a paper book form with the registry within one month of 
the service of the notice on him of the filing of the memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The respondent shall 
also endorse one copy of the reply to the appeal along with documents as 
mentioned in sub‑rule (1) to the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Tribunal may, in 
its discretion on application by the respondent, allow the filing of reply 
referred to in sub‑rule (1), after the expiry of the period referred to therein.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Date and place of 
hearing to be notified.—The 
Registrar shall notify the parties the date and place of hearing of the appeal 
in such manner as the Presiding Officer may, by general or special order, 
direct.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Dress regulations 
for the Presiding Officer, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Summer dress for the Presiding Officer shall be white pant with black coat and a 
black tie or a buttoned up black coat. In winter, striped or black trousers may 
be worn in place of white trousers. In the case of female Presiding Officer, the 
dress shall be black coat over white saree.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The legal practitioner 
appearing before the Tribunal shall wear their professional dress.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The dress for the 
members of the staff of the Tribunal shall be such as may be specified by the 
Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Order to be signed 
and dated.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every order of the Tribunal shall be in writing and shall be signed and dated by 
the Presiding Officer of the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The order shall be 
pronounced in the open Tribunal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Publication of 
orders.—The 
orders of the Tribunal as are deemed fit for publication in any authoritative 
report or the press may be released for such publication on such terms and 
conditions as the Tribunal may lay down.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Inspection of 
records and certified copies of orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who is a party in an appeal or a legal practitioner authorised by 
such person may make application for inspecting the records or such appeal to 
the Registrar and the Registrar may on satisfying that such person is a party in 
such appeal allow the inspection of the documents relating to such appeal by 
such person or the legal practitioner, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person or a legal 
practitioner authorised by such person may make application to the Registrar for 
obtaining a certified copy of any order or the Tribunal for such person and the 
Registrar shall direct on such application that the certified copy of such order 
may be given to such person or the legal practitioner, as the case may be, on 
payment of the expenditure for preparing such certified copy to the registry at 
the rate of five rupees for a folio or part thereof not involving typing and 
rupees ten for a folio or part thereof involving typing of statement and 
figures.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every certified copy 
of the order of the Tribunal shall be prepared in the registry and shall be 
authenticated by the Registrar or an officer authorised in this behalf under his 
hand and seal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Working hours of 
the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except on Saturdays, Sundays and other public holidays, the office of the 
Tribunal shall, subject to any other order, made by the Presiding Officer remain 
open daily from 9.30 A.M. to 6.00 P.M. but no work unless of an urgent nature 
shall be admitted after 4.30 P.M. on any working day.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The sitting hours of 
the Tribunal shall ordinarily be from 10.30 A.M. to 1.30 P.M. and 2.30 P.M. to 
5.00 P.M. subject to any general or special order made by the Presiding Officer.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Holidays.—Where 
the last day for doing any act falls on a day on which the office of the 
Tribunal is closed and by reason thereof, the act cannot be done on that day, it 
may be done on the next day on which that office opens.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Powers and 
functions of the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall have the custody of the records of the Tribunal and shall 
exercise such other functions as are assigned to him under these rules or by the 
Presiding Officer by a separate order in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The official seal 
shall be kept in the custody of the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to any general 
or special direction by the Presiding Officer, the seal of the Tribunal shall 
not be affixed to any order, notice or other process save under the authority in 
writing of the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The seal of the 
Tribunal shall not be affixed to any certified copy issued by the Tribunal save 
under the authority in writing of the Registrar.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Additional powers 
and duties of the Registrar.—An 
addition to the powers conferred elsewhere in these rules, the Registrar shall 
have the following powers and duties subject to any general or special orders of 
the Presiding Officer, namely:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number> to receive all appeals and other documents;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number> to decide all questions arising out of the scrutiny of the appeals before 
they are registered;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number> to require any appeal presented to the Tribunal to be amended in 
accordance with the rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number> subject to the directions of the Presiding Officer to fix date of hearing 
of the appeals or other proceedings and issue notices thereof;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number> direct any formal amendment of records;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number> to order grant of copies of documents to parties of the proceedings;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number> to grant leave to inspect the record of Tribunal; 
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number> to dispose of all matters relating to the service of notices or other 
processes, application for the issue of fresh notice or for extending the time 
for or ordering a particular method of service on a respondent including a 
substituted service by publication of the notice by way of advertisements in the 
newspapers;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number> to requisition records from the study of any court or other authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Seal and emblem.—The 
official seal and emblem of the Tribunal shall be such as the Central Government 
may specify.
 
 
</article><form>
 




the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2003
 


 
 




FORM
 


[See rule 5(1)]
 




Memorandum of Appeal under section 14 of the Control of  

National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 2002 (13 of 2003)
 


For use of Tribunal’s 
office
 


Date of 
filing..........................................
 


Date of receipt by 
post........................
 


Registration No. 
..................................
 


Signature
 


Registrar
 


 
 


In the National Highways 
Tribunal
 



.....................Appellant
 


.....................Respondent(s)
 


Details of appeal:
 


         
1.  Particulars of the appellant:
 


              
(i)     Name of the appellant
 


             
(ii)     Name of father/husband
 


            
(iii)     Address of appellant
 


            
(iv)     Address for service of all notices.
 


         
2. Particulars of the respondent or respondents including address of service:
 


         
3. Particulars of the order against which the appeal is filed. The appeal is 
against the following order:—
 


              
(i)     Order No.
 


             
(ii)     Date
 


            
(iii)     Passed by
 


         
4. Jurisdiction of the Tribunal.—The appellant declares that the matter 
of the appeal falls within the jurisdiction of the Tribunal.
 


         
5. Limitation.—The appellant further declares that the appeal is within 
the limitation prescribed under section 19 of the Control of National Highways 
(Land and Traffic) Act, 2002 (13 of 2003).
 


         
6. Facts of the case and orders passed or actions taken by the Highway 
Administrations or the officer authorized on its behalf, as the case may be.—The 
facts of the case are given below :
 


              
(Give here a concise statement of facts and grounds or appeal against the 
specific order passed or action taken by the Highway Administration or an 
officer authorized on its behalf, as the case may be, in a chronological order, 
each paragraph containing as neatly as possible a separate issue, fact or 
otherwise)
 


         
7. Reliefs sought.—In view of the facts mentioned in paragraph five 
above, the appellant prays for the following reliefs (specify below the relief 
sought explaining the grounds for reliefs) and the legal provisions (if any) 
relied upon.
 


         
8. Interim order, if prayed for.—Pending final decision of the appeal, 
the appellant seeks issue of the following interim order:—
 


              
(Give here the nature of the interim order prayed for with reasons)
 


         
9. Matter not pending with any other court, etc.—The appellant further 
declares that the matter regarding which this appeal has been made is not 
pending before any court of law or any other authority or any other tribunal.
 


       
10. Details of index.—An index in duplicate containing the details of the 
documents to be relied upon is enclosed.
 


       
11. List of enclosures:
 



Verification
 


I, ..................... 
(name in full in block letters) son/daughter/wife of Shri ..................... 
do hereby verify that the contents of paras 1 to 11 are true to my personal 
knowledge and belief and that I have not suppressed any material facts.
 


 
 


Signature of the applicant
 


Place .....................
 


Date .....................
 


 
 


To, 
 


The Registrar,
 



..........................................
 



..........................................
 



..........................................
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>