<act><title>THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (SALARY, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) 
RULES, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Cyber Appellate Tribunal (Salary, Allowances and Other Terms and 
Conditions of Service of Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Cyber Appellate Tribunal means the Cyber Appellate Tribunal 
  established under sub-section (1) of section 48 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Cyber Appellate Tribunal 
  under section 49 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Member means the Member of the Cyber Appellate Tribunal appointed 
  under section 49 of the Act; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All other words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but 
defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Salary and Allowances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson and Member 
shall be paid such salary and allowances, as admissible to a Secretary to the 
Government of India, including all the benefits that a Secretary is entitled to: 

 Provided that in the case of appointment of a person as the Chairperson or 
the Member, as the case may be, who has retired as a Judge of the Supreme Court 
or a High Court or who has retired from service under the Central Government or 
a State Government and who is in receipt of, or has received, or has become 
entitled to receive any retirement benefits by way of pension, gratuity, 
employer's contribution to Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of 
retirement benefits, the pay of such Chairperson or the Member, as the case may 
be, shall be reduced by the gross amount of pension or employer's contribution 
to the Contributory Provident Fund or any other form of retirement benefit, if 
any, drawn or to be drawn by him: Provided further that in case a retired 
Judge of a Supreme Court or a High Court is appointed as the Chairperson or 
Member, as the case may be, the terms and conditions of service of such 
Chairperson or Member shall be in accordance with the instructions issued by the 
Ministry of Finance in respect of appointment of Judges to various Tribunals and 
in consultation with that Ministry. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Leave. </title>The Chairperson and the Member shall be entitled 
to leave as are applicable to the Secretary to the Government of India in 
respect of earned leave, half pay leave, extraordinary leave, commutation of 
leave and casual leave. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Leave Sanctioning Authority. </title>The Secretary, Department 
of Information Technology, Ministry of Communications and Information 
Technology, Government of India, shall be the authority competent to sanction 
leave to the Chairperson and the Member. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Pension or Provident Fund. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In case a serving Judge 
of the Supreme Court or a High Court or a member of the Indian Legal Service is 
appointed to the post of the Chairperson or the Member, the service rendered in 
the Tribunal shall count for pension, to be drawn in accordance with the rules 
of the service to which he belongs, and he shall also be governed by the 
provisions of the General Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules, 1960. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In all other cases, the Chairperson and Member shall be governed by the 
provision of the Contributory Provident Fund ( India ) Rules, 1962. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Travelling and daily allowances. </title>The Chairperson or the 
Member, as the case may be, while on tour (including the journey undertaken on 
the expiry of his term in the Tribunal to proceed to his home town) shall be 
entitled to the travelling allowance, daily allowance, transportation of 
personal effects and other similar matters at the same rates as are applicable 
to the Secretary to the Government of India. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Leave Travel Concession. </title>The Chairperson and the Member 
shall be entitled to avail leave travel concession at the same rate as 
admissible to the Secretary to the Government of India. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Facility of Conveyance. </title>The Chairperson and the Member 
shall be entitled to hire a taxi on whole time basis in accordance with the 
rules or orders for the time being in force for hire of taxi by the Secretary to 
the Government of India. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> House Rent Allowance. </title>The Chairperson and the Member 
shall be entitled to house rent allowance at the same rate as are, for the time 
being, admissible to Group A' officers of the Central Government drawing 
equivalent pay and grade pay. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Facilities for medical treatment. </title>The Chairperson and 
Member shall be entitled to medical treatment and hospital facilities, as 
provided in the Central Government Health Scheme Rules, 1954 and in places where 
the Central Government Health Scheme is not in operation, the said Chairperson 
and the Member shall be entitled to the facilities as provided in the Central 
Services (Medical Attendance) Rules, 1944. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Oath of office and secrecy. </title>Every person appointed as 
the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, shall, before entering upon 
his office, make and subscribe an oath of office and secrecy, in Form I and Form 
II respectively annexed to these rules. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Declaration of financial or other interest. </title>Every 
person, on his appointment as the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, 
shall give a declaration in Form III annexed to rules, to the 
satisfaction of the Central Government, that he does not have any such financial 
or interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as such 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Residuary Provision. </title>Any matters relating to the 
conditions of service of the Chairperson and the Member with respect to which no 
express provision has been made in these rules shall be as per the rules 
applicable to Group A' officers of the Central Government drawing equivalent 
pay grade pay. 

</article><form>
 

THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (SALARY, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) 
RULES, 20091
 

 
 

FORM I 
 

( See rule 12) 
 

FORM OF OATH OF OFFICE FOR THE CHAIRPERSON/MEMBERS OF 
THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL 
 

I, ........................., having been appointed as the Chairperson/Member 
( cross out portion not applicable ) do solemnly affirm and do swear in 
the name of God that I will faithful conscientiously discharge my duties as the 
Chairperson/Member ( cross out portion not applicable) the Cyber 
Appellate Tribunal, to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgement, without 
favour, affection or ill-will. 
 

Dated.......................... 
 

Place..........................
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL 
 

---------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 778(E), dated 27th October, 2009, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), No. 618, dated 
27th October, 2009. </form><form>
 

THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (SALARY, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) 
RULES, 20091
 

 
 

FORM II 
 

( See rule 12) 
 

FORM OF OATH OF SECRECY FOR THE CHAIRPERSON/MEMBERS 
 
OF THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL 
 

I, ...................., having been appointed as the Chairperson/Member ( 
cross out portion not applicable ) do solemnly affirm and swear in the 
name of God that I will not directly or in communicate or reveal to any person 
or persons any matter which shall be brought under my consideration or shall 
become known to me as the Chairperson/ a Member ( cross out portion not 
applicable ), of the Cyber Appellate Tribunal except as may be required for 
the due discharge duties as the Chairperson/ a Member ( cross out portion 
not applicable ). 
 

Dated.......................... 
 

Place............................
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member 
 

CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL 
 

---------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 778(E), dated 27th October, 2009, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), No. 618, dated 
27th October, 2009. </form><form>
 

THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (SALARY, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) 
RULES, 20091
 

 
 

FORM III 
 

( See rule 13) 
 

DECLARATION AGAINST ACQUISITION OF ANY ADVERSE 
 
FINANCIAL OR OTHER INTEREST 
 

I, ......................., having been appointed as the Chairperson/Member ( 
cross out portion not applicable ) of Cyber Appellate Tribunal, do 
solemnly affirm and declare that I do not have, nor shall have in future any 
financial or other interest which is likely to affect prejudicially my 
functioning the Chairperson/Member ( cross out portion not applicable 
), of the Cyber Appellate Tribunal. 
 

Dated.......................... 
 

Place...........................
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member 
 

CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL 
 

---------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 778(E), dated 27th October, 2009, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), No. 618, dated 
27th October, 2009. </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-10-2009 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>