<act><tid>526333</tid>
<title>THE ADDITIONAL EMOLUMENTS (COMPULSORY DEPOSIT) ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 1st September, <year>1974</year>]

An Act to provide, in the interests of national economic 
development, for the compulsory deposit of additional emoluments and 
for the framing of a scheme in relation thereto, and for Matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1811274</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>974421</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Additional Emoluments (Compulsory Deposit) Act, <year>1974</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1493941</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1231045</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 6th day of 
July, <year>1974</year>, except section 14 which shall come into force at once.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1217136</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1229924</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 6th day of July, <year>1974</year>;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>499</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1018791</tid>
<number>b</number>" additional dearness allowance" means such dearness 
allowance as may be sanctioned from time to time, after the 
appointed day, over and above the amount of dearness 
allowance payable in accordance with the rate in force 
immediately before the date from which such sanction of 
additional dearness allowance is to take effect.
Explanation I.- Where payment of dearness allowance is linked 
to a cost of living index or any other factor, any automatic 
payment, after the appointed day, of dearness allowance in 
consequence of any rise in such cost of living index or in 
consequence of any change in such other factor shall, 
notwithstanding the provisions of this clause, be deemed to 
be the additional dearness allowance.

Explanation II.- For the purpose of computation of the 
additional dearness allowance in relation to an employee who 
enters into any post after the appointed day, dearness 
allowance payable, immediately before the appointed day, in 
relation to such post shall be deemed to be the dearness 
allowance payable to such employee as if, he were holding 
that post on the appointed day and any excess over and above 
the said dearness allowance shall be deemed, for the purposes 
of this Act, to be the additional dearness allowance in 
relation to such employee;


</section>

<section><tid>1435789</tid>
<number>c</number>" additional wages" means such wages, over and above the 
wages payable to an employee in accordance with the rates in 
force immediately before the appointed day, as may become 
payable to the employee in respect of any period after the 
appointed day in pursuance of any wage revision, whether by 
or under an agreement or settlement between the parties or 
any award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other 
authority or otherwise, but does not include-

<subsection><tid>643279</tid>
<number>i</number>any increment due to the employee in accordance 
with the time scale of pay applicable to the post held 
by him immediately before the appointed day, and any 
consequent increase in any allowance (not being dearness  
  allowance) admissible under any rule or order in force 
immediately before the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>751102</tid>
<number>ii</number>any higher wages payable to the employee on his-

<subsubsection><tid>1886419</tid>
<number>a</number>promotion to a higher post and any increment, 
being an increment within the prescribed limits, 
due to the employee in such higher post

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1181136</tid>
<number>b</number>deputation or transfer to an equivalent post 
or to any post involving higher responsibilities 
and duties;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003604</tid>
<number>iii</number>any special pay, honorarium, fee or reward 
payable for any special work done;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>230146</tid>
<number>iv</number>any remuneration payable for overtime work;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1451615</tid>
<number>v</number>any increase in wages consequent on the revision 
of the minimum rates of wages fixed under the Minimum 
Wages Act, <year>1948</year>; (11 of <year>1948</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21347</tid>
<number>vi</number>any increase in wages sanctioned in pursuance of 
the recommendations made-
 (a) by the Third Central Pay Commission;

 (b) before the appointed day, by any Pay 
Commission appointed by a State Government, in 
relation to the employees of that Government;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>500</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

 (c) by any committee constituted, before the 
appointed day, by Parliament, Supreme Court or any 
High Court in relation to any employee of 
Parliament, Supreme Court or High Court, as the 
case may be.

Explanation I.- Where any wage revision made after the 
appointed day is to be effective from a date prior to 
the appointed day, the wages payable immediately before, 
the appointed day, before such wage revision, shall, for 
the purposes of computation of additional wages', be 
deemed to be the wages.

Explanation II.- Any bonus (including incentive and pro-  
  duction bonus) paid after the appointed day at a rate 
over and above the rate at which it was last paid before 
the appointed day, shall be deemed or the purposes of 
this Act, to be additional wages;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1094880</tid>
<number>d</number>" bank deposit rate" means the highest of the maximum 
rates at which interest may be paid on different classes of 
deposits (other than those maintained in savings account or  
  those maintained by charitable or religious institutions) by 
different classes of scheduled banks in accordance with the 
directions given or issued to banking companies generally by 
the Reserve Bank of India tinder the Banking Regulation Act, 
<year>1949</year>; (10 of <year>1949</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>976588</tid>
<number>e</number>" dearness allowance" means all cash payments, by 
whatever name called, made to an employee on account of rise 
in the cost of living;

</section>

<section><tid>1891006</tid>
<number>f</number>" Deposit Account" means an account opened and 
maintained under section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>471409</tid>
<number>g</number>" emoluments" includes wages and dearness allowance;

</section>

<section><tid>314264</tid>
<number>h</number>" employer" means,-
 (i) in relation to an establishment which is a 
factory, the owner or occupier of the factory, including 
the agent of such owner or occupier, and where a person 
is named as manager of the factory under clause (f) of 
sub- section (1) of section 7 of the Factories Act, <year>1948</year>, 
 (63 of <year>1948</year>.) the person so named;


<subsection><tid>32631</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to an establishment belonging to or 
under the control of the Central Government or a State 
Government, the person or authority appointed by the 
appropriate Government for the supervision and control 
of the employees, or where no person has been so 
appointed, the head of the Department concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126465</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to an establishment belonging to or 
under the control of any local authority, the person 
appointed by such authority for the supervision and 
control of the employees, or where no person has been so 
appointed, the Chief Executive Officer of the local 
authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1243576</tid>
<number>iv</number>in any other case, the person who, or the 
authority which, has the ultimate control over the 
affairs of the establishment, and where the said affairs 
are entrusted to any other person, whether called a 
manager, managing director or by any other name, such 
person;
and includes, in the case of a deceased employer, the legal 
representative of such deceased employer;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>501</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>369295</tid>
<number>i</number>" local authority" means any municipal committee, 
district board, body of port commissioners, panchayat or other 
authority legally entitled to, or entrusted by the 
Central or any State Government with the control or 
management of any municipal or local fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>47853</tid>
<number>j</number>" nominated authority" means such authority as may be 
nominated by the Central Government for the purposes of this 
Act and different authorities may be nominated for different 
purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53698</tid>
<number>k</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1087952</tid>
<number>l</number>" Prescribed" means prescribed by- rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>370541</tid>
<number>m</number>" Scheme" means a scheme framed under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1181579</tid>
<number>n</number>" specified authority" means the authority specified 
under sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1050868</tid>
<number>o</number>" wages" means all remuneration (whether by way of  
  salary, allowances or otherwise) expressed, or capable of 
being expressed, in terms of money, which would, if the terms 
of employment, express or implied- were fulfilled, be payable 
to a person employed in respect of his employment or of work 
done in such employment, and includes-

<subsubsection><tid>908666</tid>
<number>i</number>any remuneration payable under any agreement, or 
settlement between the parties or any award, decree or 
order of any court, tribunal or other authority;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1728155</tid>
<number>ii</number>any remuneration to which the person employed is 
en, titled in respect of overtime work or holidays or any 
leave period;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1435822</tid>
<number>iii</number>any additional remuneration payable under the 
terms of employment, including bonus, whether under a 
scheme of profit sharing or otherwise;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1123656</tid>
<number>iv</number>any sum to which the person employed is entitled 
under any scheme framed under any law for the time being 
in force;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1550141</tid>
<number>v</number>any allowance paid for house accommodation, or 
where house accommodation is provided, the value of such 
accommodation, and the value of electricity or water, or 
both, supplied, and the value of medical attendance or 
other amenity,
but does not include-


<subsubsubsection><tid>11938</tid>
<number>1</number>any contribution paid by the employer to any 
pension or provident fund, and the interest which may 
have accrued thereon;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1913571</tid>
<number>2</number>any travelling or running allowance or the value 
of any travelling concession;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>502</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1943769</tid>
<number>3</number>any sum, not exceeding rupees two hundred and 
fifty per annum, paid to the employed person to defray 
special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his 
employment;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1072744</tid>
<number>4</number>any compensation or gratuity payable on the 
termination of employment;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1495367</tid>
<number>5</number>any dearness allowance.



</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>197769</tid>
<number> 3</number> Persons to whom this Act applies. This Act shall apply to an 
employee of-
<section><tid>1642098</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central or State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>719020</tid>
<number>b</number>a local authority;

</section>

<section><tid>789159</tid>
<number>c</number>a company as defined in section 3 of the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) including a foreign company within the 
meaning of section 591 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, and a 
Government company as defined in section 617 of that Act; (43  
  of <year>1961</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>646710</tid>
<number>d</number>any other corporation, including a society or body 
established by, or registered under, a Central, Provincial or 
State Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1981315</tid>
<number>e</number>any individual, association of persons or body of 
individuals, partnership firm or Hindu undivided family 
required by the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>.) to deduct 
income- tax at source from the emoluments paid to their 
employees;

</section>

<section><tid>1775514</tid>
<number>f</number>any establishment owned or maintained in India by a 
trust, fund or institution established for a charitable or 
religious purpose, and required by the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, 
 (43 of <year>1961</year>.) to deduct income- tax at source from the 
emoluments paid to their employees;

</section>

<section><tid>280536</tid>
<number>g</number>any establishment, not being an establishment owned by 
Government, local authority or person specified, 
respectively, in clauses (a) to (f)  (both inclusive), to 
which the provisions of any law relating to provident funds 
 (other than those established under the Public Provident Fund  
  Act, <year>1968</year>)  (23 of <year>1968</year>.) apply;

</section>

<section><tid>1138959</tid>
<number>h</number>any other establishment, not being an establishment to 
which any of the foregoing clauses apply, established at the 
instance, or in pursuance of a resolution, of the Central or 
State Government or wholly or substantially financed by the 
Central or State Government..
Explanation.- Where any grant or loan to an establishment from 
the Consolidated Fund of India or of any State or of any 
Union territory having a Legislative Assembly in a financial 
year is not less than rupees five lakhs and the amount of 
such grant or loan is not less than seventy- five per cent. of 
the total expenditure of that establishment, such 
establishment shall be deemed, for the purposes of this Act, 
to be substantially financed by the Central or State 
Government, as the case may be.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>503</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1508282</tid>
<number>4</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any enactment other than this Act or in any instrument 
having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.
CHAP

COMPULSORY DEPOSIT OF ADDITIONAL EMOLUMENTS

CHAPTER II

COMPULSORY DEPOSIT OF ADDITIONAL EMOLUMENTS



</article>



<article><tid>684268</tid>
<number> 5</number> Additional Wages Deposit Account and Additional Dearness 
Allowance Deposit Account.
<section><tid>709218</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be opened by such  
authorities as may be specified in the scheme two separate accounts, 
to be known, respectively, as the Additional Wages Deposit Account and 
the Additional Dearness Allowance Deposit Account, and different 
authorities may be specified for different establishments or different 
categories of employees or establishments.

</section>

<section><tid>966604</tid>
<number>2</number>The specified authority shall, in relation to each Deposit 
Account, open a separate ledger account in the name of each employee 
in relation to whom any contribution is made to the said Account, and 
credit the contributions so made in the said ledger account.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1944795</tid>
<number> 6</number> Duty of employer or other person to make deductions of 
additional wages and additional dearness allowance from emoluments.

<section><tid>172345</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of this Act, the deductions specified in sub-  
section (2) shall be made,-

<subsection><tid>1771367</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of additional wages, for a period of one 
year from the appointed day; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>522848</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of additional dearness allowance, for a 
period of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> three years] from the appointed day.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>204891</tid>
<number>2</number>On the commencement of this section,-

<subsection><tid>552494</tid>
<number>a</number>every employer, who draws, from the Consolidated Fund 
of India or of any State or of any Union territory having a 
Legislative Assembly, and disburses, after the appointed day, 
emoluments of an employee to whom this Act applies, shall, as 
and when emoluments are disbursed by him for any period, 
deduct from the emoluments so disbursed, the whole of the 
additional wages and one- half of the additional dearness 
allowance and credit the amount so deducted, in accordance 
with the scheme, to the Additional Wages Deposit Account and 
the Additional Dearness Allowance Deposit Account, 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>438311</tid>
<number>b</number>every other employer, who disburses, after the 
appointed day, emoluments to any employee to whom this Act 
applies, shall, as and when emoluments are disbursed by him 
for any period, deduct from the emoluments so disbursed, the 
whole of the additional wages and one- half of the additional 
dearness allowance, and shall remit, in accordance with the 
scheme, the amounts so deducted to the nominated authority 
and on receipt of such amounts the nominated authority shall 
credit the amounts so received to the Additional Wages 
Deposit Account and the Additional Dearness Allowance Deposit 
Account, respectively
<pagefootnote><pagenum>504</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 11. 6. <year>1976</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1410119</tid>
<number>c</number>any employee, to whom this Act applies, who draws, 
after the appointed day, his own emoluments shall,-

<subsubsection><tid>621781</tid>
<number>i</number>if he is employed in an establishment owned or 
maintained by Government, make deductions from his 
salary bill in respect of the whole of the additional 
wages and one- half of the additional dearness 
allowance and the specified authority shall credit the amount 
so deducted, in accordance with the scheme, to the 
Additional Wages Deposit Account and the Additional 
Dearness Allowance Deposit Account, respectively;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>504484</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he is employed in any other establishment, 
remit the whole of the additional wages and one- half 
of the additional dearness allowance, in accordance 
with the scheme, to the nominated authority, and on 
receipt of such amount, the nominated authority shall 
credit the amount so received to the Additional Wages 
Deposit Account and the Additional Dearness Allowance 
Deposit Account, respectively.
Explanation.- In computing the amount to be credited to the Addi- 
tional Wages Deposit Account and the Additional Dearness Allowance 
Deposit Account. the amount contributed[ in relation to such additional 
wages or additional dearness allowance shall not-


<subsubsubsection><tid>208237</tid>
<number>a</number>to the extent of the contribution which is compulsorily 
required to be made to any provident or other fund under any 
law for the time being in force; or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>986102</tid>
<number>b</number>to the extent of the contribution made to any other 
provident fund, recognised under any other law for the time 
being in force, at a rate' not exceeding the rate at which 
such contribution was being made immediate before the 
appointed day,
be taken into account.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1357770</tid>
<number>3</number>The specified authority shall, as soon as may be practicable 
after the end of each year, prepare separately, in relation to the 
amounts credited to the respective Deposit Accounts to the credit of 
each employee, and furnish to the employee a copy of the said accounts 
showing therein the amounts credited thereto in relation to the 
employee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>57163</tid>
<number> 7</number> Deposit to carry simple interest.
<section><tid>465300</tid>
<number>1</number>Every amount credited  
under section 6, in relation to an employee in a Deposit Account, 
shall carry simple interest at a rate, which shall be two and a half 
per cent. over and above the bank deposit rate.

</section>

<section><tid>874530</tid>
<number>2</number>The interest due on the amount credited in any Deposit 
Account shall be calculated in such manner as may be specified in the 
scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>851298</tid>
<number>3</number>Interest accruing on amounts credited under section 6 to any 
Deposit Account shall ensure to the benefit of the employees in 
relation to whom such amounts have been credited.

</section>

<section><tid>91743</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of the deductions under section 80L of the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) interest received on a deposit 
under this Act shall be deemed to be interest received on a deposit 
with a banking company to which the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, (10  
  of <year>1949</year>.) applies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628133</tid>
<number> 8</number> Assessment for------ purpose of income tax.
<section><tid>1292825</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purposes of computing, under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, the total 
income of an employee, the amount credited to his ledger account in 
the Additional Wages Deposit Account or the Additional Dearness 
Allowance Deposit Account Shall not be included in his total income of 
the previous year in which it is so credited; but so much of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>505</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the amount as is repaid to him shall be liable to be included in his 
total income of the previous year in which it is repaid.


</section>

<section><tid>1835019</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of computing, under the Income- tax Act, 
<year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) the total income of an employee, the amount repaid 
to him under this Act shall be deemed to be salary paid to him in 
arrears and the provisions of sub- section (1) of section 89 of that 
Act shall apply accordingly
Explanation.- In this section," previous year" and" total income 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Income- tax Act 
<year>1961</year>. (43 of <year>1961</year>.)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>160251</tid>
<number> 9</number> Repayment of deposits.
<section><tid>395373</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub-  
section (2), every amount credited to the Deposit Accounts shall be 
repayable with interest due thereon,--

<subsection><tid>1604229</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an amount credited to the Additional 
Wages Deposit Account, at any time after the expiry of one 
year from the appointed day; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>883095</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the case of an amount credited to the Additional 
Dearness Allowance Deposit Account,-

<subsubsection><tid>832104</tid>
<number>i</number>for any period ending on the 30th day of June, 
<year>1976</year>, in cash, at any time after the expiry of two years 
from the appointed day; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1327242</tid>
<number>ii</number>for any period ending after the 30th day of June, 
<year>1976</year>,-

<subsubsubsection><tid>1551594</tid>
<number>a</number>by crediting tithe provident fund account of 
the employee, at any time after the expiry of a 
period of four years from the appointed day, if 
such employee is a subscriber to any provident 
fund;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1647654</tid>
<number>b</number>in cash, at any time after the expiry of a 
period of four years from the appointed day, in the 
case of an employee who is not a subscriber to any 
provident fund:]
Provided that nothing in this section shall prevent earlier 
repayment of any amount credited to either of the Deposit Accounts 
with interest due thereon in any case in which any person authorised 
by the Central Government in this behalf is satisfied that extreme 
hardship will be caused unless such repayment is made:

Provided further that an employee may, at his option, retain the 
whole or any part of the amount, credited in relation to him in the 
Additional Wages Deposit Account or the Additional Dearness Allowance 
Deposit Account, or both, until his superannuation or until such date 
as may be specified by the Central Government in this behalf:

Provided also that the whole of the amount standing to the credit 
of an employee (not being an employee in a seasonal establishment) in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the additional Wages Deposit Account shall be repaid to him in 
cash."] on his <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Additional Wages Deposit Account shall be repaid 
to him in cash] superannuation or resignation from office or on the 
termination of his employment.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>401535</tid>
<number>2</number>The aggregate amount credited to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any Additional Wages 
Deposit Account] relation to an employee shall be repaid to the 
employee in five equal annual instalments commencing from the expiry 
of one year 1 from the appointed day, together with interest due on 
the whole, or, as the case may be, part of the amount of compulsory 
deposit which remains unpaid.

</section>

<section><tid>1669414</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The aggregate amount credited to the Additional Dearness 
Allowance Deposit Account by or in relation to an employee for the 
period ending on the 30th day of June, <year>1976</year>, shall subject to the 
provisions of sub- section (5), be repaid, in cash, to the employee in 
five equal annual instalments commencing from the expiry of a period 
of two years from the appointed day,. together with interest due on 
the whole or, as the case may be, part of the amount of compulsory 
deposit which remains unpaid.

</section>

<section><tid>899487</tid>
<number>4</number>The aggregate amount credited to the Additional Dearness 
Allowance Deposit Account by or in relation to an employee for the 
period commencing on the 1st day of July, <year>1976</year>, and ending on the 5th 
day of July, <year>1977</year>, together with interest due on the whole, or, as the 
case may be, part of the amount of' compulsory deposit which remains 
unpaid, shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (5), be repaid 
to the employee in five, equal annual instalments commencing on the 
 6th day of July, <year>1978</year>, and each such instalment shall be credited to 
the provident fund account of the employee:
Provided that the employer shall not be required to make any 
contribution under the Employees Provident Funds Act, <year>1952</year>, or under 
any other law for the time being in force, in relation to the amounts 
so credited to the provident fund account of the employee:

Provided further that, in the case of the employees who do not 
subscribe to any provident fund, the aggregate amount so repayable 
shall be repaid in cash in five equal annual instalments commencing on 
the 6th day of July, <year>1978</year>.


</section>

<section><tid>245425</tid>
<number>5</number>On the superannuation, resignation or termination of 
employment of an employee, the whole of the amount standing to the 
credit of such employee in the Additional Dearness, Allowance Deposit 
Account, shall be repaid,-

<subsection><tid>1609919</tid>
<number>a</number>in cash, in the case of any amount credited to the 
Additional Dearness Allowance Deposit Account for any period 
ending on the 30th day of June, <year>1976</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1380381</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any amount credited to the Additional 
Dearness Allowance Deposit Account for any period ending, 
after the 30th day of June, <year>1976</year>,-

<subsubsection><tid>1823162</tid>
<number>i</number>by crediting such amount- to the provident fund 
account of such employee, if he is the subscriber of 
any such account, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1144487</tid>
<number>ii</number>in cash, where such employee is not a subscriber 
to any provident fund.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," provident. fund" 
has the meaning assigned to it in section 2 (e) of the Provident Funds 
Act, <year>1925</year>.]




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>918715</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power of Central Government to frame scheme.
<section><tid>348182</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, by notification, frame one or more schemes in 
relation to the amounts credited to the Deposit Accounts under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>769725</tid>
<number>2</number>A scheme framed under sub- section (1) may provide for-

<subsection><tid>902644</tid>
<number>a</number>the authorities by which the Additional Wages Deposit 
Account and the Additional Dearness Allowance Deposit 
Account, shall be opened and maintained;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>506</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. Omitted and ins. by Act 74 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 11- 6-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>29</number>Law- 65.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1105589</tid>
<number>b</number>the time and manner in which amounts deducted from 
additional wages or additional dearness allowance shall be 
deducted and credited to the respective Deposit Account;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1288968</tid>
<number>c</number>the documents to be issued to persons in relation to 
whom amounts have been credited to the Deposit Accounts as 
evidence of such credit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1684249</tid>
<number>d</number>authority or authorities by or through which credits to 
the Deposit Accounts may be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>892666</tid>
<number>e</number>the accounts to be maintained with respect to the 
amounts credited to the Deposit Accounts and the officer by 
whom such Accounts shall be maintained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>774812</tid>
<number>f</number>the nomination of persons to receive the amount 
standing in a Deposit Account to the credit of an employee in 
the event of his death, and cancellation or change of such 
nomination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1523501</tid>
<number>g</number>the issue of duplicate of any document issued as 
evidence of any credit in the event of loss or destruction of 
the original and the fee, not exceeding rupees two, on the 
payment of which such duplicate may be issued;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1780316</tid>
<number>h</number>repayment of amounts credited to the Deposit Accounts 
with interest due thereon and the conditions, if any, under 
which such repayment may be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472626</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which may be necessary or proper for 
the effective implementation of the scheme.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1209583</tid>
<number>3</number>A scheme framed under this section may provide that all or 
any of its provisions shall take effect, either prospectively or 
retrospectively, on such date, not being a date earlier than the 
appointed day, as may be specified in this behalf in the scheme and 
every scheme framed under this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in any law (other than this Act) 
for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect by 
virtue of any enactment other than this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>492432</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may make a scheme to add to, amend or 
vary any scheme framed under sub- section M.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1261766</tid>
<number>11</number>Rounding off. Where the amount of any credit to be made in 
any Deposit Account contains a part of a rupee, then, such part, if it 
is fifty paise or more, shall be increased to one complete rupee and 
if it Is less than fifty paise, it shall be ignored.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1811134</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amounts due to be first charge in the case of insolvency or 
liquidation of the employer.
<section><tid>502991</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any amount required by this Act  
to be credited to any Deposit Account or remitted to a nominated 
authority has not been so credited or remitted by any employer, the 
amount in respect of which such omission or failure was made, together 
with interest due thereon calculated at the rate specified in sub- 
section (1) of section 7, shall, in the event of the employer being 
adjudicated by any court to be insolvent or, being a company is 
ordered by any court to be wound up, be deemed to be first charge on 
the assets of the insolvent or of the company, as the case may be, and 
shall have priority over all other debts, and be paid in full.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>507</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1592407</tid>
<number>2</number>The court shall cause the sum which is required, under sub- 
section (1), to be paid in priority to all other debts to be remitted 
to the. nominated authority for crediting the same to the appropriate 
Deposit Account.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1644953</tid>
<number>13</number>Transfer of establishments. Where an employer, in relation 
to an establishment to which this Act applies, transfers that 
establishment in whole or in part by sale, gift or otherwise or grants 
any licence in respect of such establishment the employer and the 
person to whom the establishment is so transferred or the licence is 
so given shall be jointly and severally liable to credit to the 
appropriate Deposit Account or, as the case may be, remit to the 
nominated authority, the sums which are required by this Act to be so 
credited or remitted:
Provided that the liability of the transferee or licensee shall 
be limited to the value of the assets obtained by him on such transfer 
or licence, as the case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>20689</tid>
<number> 14</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>293657</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever, with a view to- 

<subsection><tid>585935</tid>
<number>a</number>avoiding making any deduction of additional wages and 
additional dearness allowance and crediting the same to the 
Additional Wages Deposit Account or the Additional Dearness 
Allowance Deposit Account, as the case may be, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>127720</tid>
<number>b</number>aiding or abetting any other person to avoid making any 
such deduction or credit,
knowingly makes, or causes to be made, any statement or representation 
which he knows to be false or does not believe to be true, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six In 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>263137</tid>
<number>2</number>Any employer who omits or fails to credit to any Deposit 
Account or remit any amount to the nominated authority, as and when 
such credit or remittance becomes due under this Act or any scheme 
framed thereunder, shall be punished-

<subsection><tid>1390556</tid>
<number>a</number>with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less 
than three months but may extend-

<subsubsection><tid>1733981</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of the first offence, to six months, 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1384038</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of any second or subsequent offence, 
to one year:
Provided that the court may, for any adequate and special 
reasons, to be recorded by it in the judgment, impose a 
sentence of imprisonment for a term lesser than three months 
or a fine in lieu of imprisonment; and


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1315554</tid>
<number>b</number>also with fine which shall not be less than the amount 
which has not been credited to a Deposit Account or remitted 
to the nominated authority as required by this Act, and the 
interest due there on, calculated at the rate specified in 
sub- section (1) of section 7, but may extend to twice the 
said amount and the interest due thereon, and out of the 
fine, if realised, the court trying the offence shall cause 
an amount equal to the amount which has not been credited to 
a Deposit Account or remitted to the nominated authority with 
interest due thereon, to be remitted to the nominated 
authority for

<pagefootnote><pagenum>508</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

crediting the same to the appropriate Deposit Account, and on 
such amount being remitted to the nominated authority, the 
liability of the employer shall, to the extent of the amount 
so remitted by the court, stand discharged.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>811971</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever contravenes any provision of this Act or any scheme 
or order made thereunder for which no penalty has been separately pro- 
vided for shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand 
rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>486973</tid>
<number> 15</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1965835</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>353908</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act, has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1776876</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>55584</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm, and, in relation to a Hindu undivided family, means 
the Karta of such family.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>188438</tid>
<number>16</number>Cognizance of offences. No court shall take cognizance of 
any offence punishable under this Act except upon a complaint made by 
the Central Government or any officer or authority authorised in 
writing by the Central, Government in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>448139</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to exempt. Where the Central Government is of the 
opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do either in the 
public interest or having regard to the peculiar circumstances of any 
case, it may, by notification, and subject to such conditions, if any, 
as it may specify in the notification,-
<section><tid>897626</tid>
<number>a</number>exempt any establishment or category of employees, 
working in any establishment from the operation of all or any 
of the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1848301</tid>
<number>b</number>exempt, in the case of extreme hardship to any 
employee, from crediting any amount in relation to such 
employee to the Additional Wages Deposit Account;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>509</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>76627</tid>
<number>c</number>empower deductions from additional wages in relation to 
an employee or class of employees, at a rate lesser than the 
rate specified in this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1439263</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by 
notification, direct that ally power which may be exercised by it 
under this Act or any scheme framed under this Act shall, subject to 
such restrictions and conditions, if any, as it may specify in the 
notification, be exercised also by-
<section><tid>1876488</tid>
<number>a</number>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>536555</tid>
<number>b</number>such State Government or such officer or authority sub- 
ordinate to a State Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>1034170</tid>
<number>c</number>such other person or authority,
as may be specified in the notification:

Provided that the powers conferred by section 10 and section 24 
shall not be delegated under this section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>621842</tid>
<number> 19</number> Protection against attachment.
<section><tid>676548</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount standing to  
the credit of any employee in any Deposit Account shall not be liable 
to attachment under any decree or order of any court in respect of any 
debt or liability incurred by the employee.

</section>

<section><tid>1842075</tid>
<number>2</number>Any amount standing to the credit of an employee, in any 
Deposit Account at the time of his death and payable to his, nominee 
under the scheme shall vest in the nominee and shall be free from any 
debt or other liability incurred by the deceased or incurred by the 
nominee before the death of the employee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>855655</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to call for returns and inspect accounts.
<section><tid>1949899</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
nominated authority or any officer authorised by the nominated 
authority in this behalf may call for such returns, as may be 
prescribed, from any employer to whom this Act applies.

</section>

<section><tid>159437</tid>
<number>2</number>The books of account and other books and papers of any em- 
ployer to whom this Act applies shall be open to inspection by the 
nominated authority or any person authorised by the Central Government 
in this behalf during business hours:
Provided that such inspection may be made without giving any 
previous notice to the employer or any officer of the employer.


</section>

<section><tid>1128243</tid>
<number>3</number>The nominated authority or any authorised officer may, 
during the course of inspection,--

<subsection><tid>307387</tid>
<number>i</number>make, or cause to be made, copies of the books of 
account and other books and papers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1616522</tid>
<number>ii</number>place, or cause to be placed, any marks of 
identification thereon in token of the inspection having been 
made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1822749</tid>
<number>4</number>If after inspection the nominated authority or the 
authorised officer finds that any additional wages or additional 
dearness allowance has not been credited by the employer to the 
appropriate Deposit Account or, as the case may be, remitted to the 
nominated authority, it, or he shall determine the amount in respect 
of which such credit or remittance has not been made:
Provided that no such determination shall be made except after 
giving to the employer a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>510</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1004643</tid>
<number>5</number>It shall be the duty of every employer to whom this Act 
applies, to furnish to the nominated authority a copy of the award, 
decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority or agreement 
or settlement relating to wage revision or revision of dearness 
allowance and also to produce such books of account and other books 
and papers as the nominated authority or the officer making the 
inspection may require.

</section>

<section><tid>499643</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any revision of wages or dearness allowance is made 
otherwise than in pursuance of any award, decree or order of any 
court, tribunal or other authority or agreement or settlement, the 
employer shall give an intimation to the nominated authority about 
such revision of wages or dearness allowance and furnish to the 
nominated authority such books of account and other books and papers 
as that authority may require.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1157914</tid>
<number>21</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or any State 
Government or any officer authorised by the Central or State 
Government to discharge any functions under this Act, for any loss or 
damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which Is in good 
faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any 
scheme framed thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1870499</tid>
<number>22</number>Persons performing functions under this Act to be public 
servants. Any person to whom any power of the Central Government is 
delegated under section 18 or who is authorised to exercise any Power 
specified in section 20 shall, if he is not a public servant, be 
deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the 
Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1175955</tid>
<number> 23</number> Recovery of arrears. Without prejudice to the provisions of 
section 14, any amount which ought to have been credited under this 
Act to a Deposit Account or remitted to the nominated authority but 
has not been so, credited or remitted in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act or scheme or order made thereunder, shall be 
payable by the employer, together with interest due thereon calculated 
at twice the rate at which interest is payable under sub- section
<section><tid>927664</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of section 7, and in default of such payment, such amount, together 
with interest due thereon at the aforesaid rate, shall be recoverable 
as an arrear of land revenue:
Provided that where any such amount has been recovered by the 
court under sub- section (2) of section 14, the said amount shall not 
be recoverable under this section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>283847</tid>
<number>24</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1194872</tid>
<number>26</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>1435633</tid>
<number> 27</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>32708</tid>
<number>1</number>The Additional Emoluments (Compulsory   
  Deposit) Ordinance, <year>1974</year> (8 of <year>1974</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1172669</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed (including any appointment,  
  exemption, nomination, direction or order made thereunder) shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions 
of this Act, and the repeal of the said Ordinance shall not affect any 
penalty or punishment incurred in respect of any offence committed 
against the said Ordinance or any investigation or legal proceeding in 
respect of such penalty or punishment and any such investigation or 
legal proceeding may be instituted or continued and any such penalty 
or punishment may be imposed as if section 12 and other provisions of 
the said Ordinance. necessary for the purposes aforesaid, had been 
included in this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>