<act><title>
THE
PRISONERS (ATTENDANCE IN COURTS)
ACT, 1955</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the
Prisoners (Attendance in Courts) Act,1955.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act,—
 <section><number>a</number> 
‘confinement in a prison’—references to confinement in a prison, by
whatever form of words, include references to confinement or detention in a
prison under any law providing for preventive detention;
 </section><section><number>b</number> 
‘prison’ includes— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> any place which has been
declared by the State Government, by general or special order, to be a
subsidiary jail; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> any reformatory, Borstal
institution or other institution of a like nature;
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> ‘State
Government’, in relation to a Union Territory, means the Administrator
thereof.]
 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Power of courts to require appearance of prisoners to give evidence or
answer a charge.—
<section><number>1</number> Any civil or
criminal court may, if it thinks that the evidence of any person confined in any
prison is material in any matter pending before it, make an order in the form
set forth in the First Schedule, directed to the officer in charge of the
prison:
 Provided
that no civil court shall make an order under this sub-section in respect of a
person confined in a prison situated outside the State in which the court is
held.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any criminal court may, if a charge of an offence against a person confined in
any prison is made or pending before it, make an order in the form set forth in
the Second Schedule, directed to the officer in charge of the prison.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
No order made under this section by a civil court which is subordinate to a
district judge shall have effect unless it is countersigned by the district
judge; and no order made under this section by a criminal court which is
inferior to the court of a magistrate of the first class shall have effect
unless it is countersigned by the district magistrate to whom that court is
subordinate or within the local limits of whose jurisdiction that court is
situate.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
For the purposes of sub-section (3), a court of small causes outside a
presidency town or the city of Hyderabad shall be deemed to be subordinate to
the district judge within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such court is
situate.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Power of State Government to exempt certain persons from operation of section 3.—
<section><number>1</number>
The State Government may, having regard to the matters specified in sub-section
(2), by general or special order, direct that any person or class of persons
shall not be removed from the prison in which he or they may be confined, and
thereupon so long as any such order remains in force, the provisions of section
3 shall not apply to such person or class of persons.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Before making an order under sub-section (1), the State Government shall have
regard to the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number> 
the nature of the offence for which or the grounds on which the
confinement has been ordered in respect of the person or class of persons;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> 
the likelihood of the disturbance of public order if the person or class
of persons is allowed to be removed from the prison;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> 
the public interest, generally.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Prisoners to be brought up.—Upon
delivery of any order made under
section 3 to the officer in charge of the prison in which the person named
therein is confined, that officer shall cause him to be taken to the court in
which his attendance is required, so as to be present in the court at the time
of such order mentioned, and shall cause him to be detained in custody in or
near the court until he has been examined or until the judge or presiding
officer of the court authorises him to be taken back to the prison in which he
was confined.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Officer in charge of prison when to abstain from carrying out order.—Where
the person in respect of whom an order is made under section 3—
 <section><number>a</number> 
is, in accordance with the rules made in this behalf, declared to be
unfit to be removed from the prison where he is confined by reason of sickness
or other infirmity; or
 </section><section><number>b</number> 
is under committal for trial; or
 </section><section><number>c</number> 
is under remand pending trial or pending a preliminary investigation; or
 </section><section> <number>d</number> 
is in custody for a period which would expire before the expiration of
the time required for removing him under this Act and for taking him back to the
prison in which he is confined,
 the
officer in charge of the prison shall abstain from carrying out the order and
shall send to the court from which the order had been issued a statement of
reasons for so abstaining:
 Provided
that such officer as aforesaid shall not so obstain where—
 <subsection><number>i</number> 
the order has been made by a criminal court; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> 
the person named in the order is confined under committal for trial or
under remand pending trial or pending a preliminary investigation and is not
declared in accordance with the rules made in this behalf to be unfit to be
removed from the prison where he is confined by reason of sickness or other
infirmity; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> 
the place, where the evidence of the person named in the order is
required, is not more than five miles distant from the prison in which he is
confined.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Commissions for examination of prisoners.—In
any of the following cases, that is to say,—
 <section><number>a</number> 
where it appears to any civil court that the evidence of a person
confined in a prison is material in any matter pending before it and that the
attendance of such person in court cannot be secured by reason of the provisions
of section 6 or of an order under section 4 or of the district judge declining
under sub-section (3) of section 3 to counter-sign an order for removal; or
 </section><section><number>b</number> 
where it appears to any civil court as aforesaid that the evidence of a
person confined in a prison which is situated outside the State in which, or is
more than fifty miles distant from the place at which, such court is held is
material in any such matter,
 the
court may, if it thinks fit, issue a commission under the provisions of the Code
of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the examination of the person in the
prison in which he is confined.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Certain provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure and the Code of Civil
Procedure to apply.—Save as
otherwise provided in this Act and any rules made thereunder, the provisions of
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), and the Code of Criminal
Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), as the case may be, shall, so far as may be, apply
in relation to the examination on commission or otherwise of any person confined
in a prison as they apply in relation to the examination on commission of any
other person.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State
Government may, by notificaion in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying
out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
such rules may provide for—
 <subsection><number>a</number> 
the procedure for obtaining the countersignature of an order made under
section 3;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> 
the authority by whom and the manner in which a declaration that a person
confined in prison is unfit to be removed therefrom, may be made;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> 
the conditions, including payment of costs and charges, subject to which
an order made under section 3 by a civil court may be executed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> 
the manner in which a process directed against any person confined in a
prison issued from any court may be served upon him;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> 
the escort of persons confined in a prison to and from courts in which
their attendance is required and for their custody during the period of such
attendance;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> 
the amount to be allowed for the costs and charges of such escort; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> 
the guidance of officers in all other matters connected with the
enforcement of this Act.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Repeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Part IX of the Prisoners
Act, 1900 (3 of 1900), and the First and Second Schedules to the said Act are
hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If immediately before the commencement of this Act, there is in force in any
Part B State to which this Act extends any law corresponding to the provisions
of this Act, that law shall, in so far as it relates to matters dealt within
this Act, stand repealed on such commencement:
 Provided
that anything done or any action taken under any such law, shall be deemed to
have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act and shall
continue to have effect accordingly, unless and until superseded by anything
done or any action taken under this Act.
 

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
PRISONERS (ATTENDANCE IN COURTS)
ACT, 1955
 



 



 


THE
FIRST SCHEDULE 


 


[See
sub-section (1) of section 3] 


 

  


 

Court
of
...............................................................................................................................
 

To
the Officer in charge of the ....................................... (State
name of prison).
 

You
are hereby required to produce ............................................, now
confined in ......................................................,under safe
and sure conduct before the Court of ..................... at
...................................... on the .............................day
of ...................... next by ....................of the clock in the
forenoon of the same day, there to give evidence in a matter now pending before
the said Court, and after the said ....................................has then
and there given his evidence before the said Court or the said Court has
dispensed with his further attendance, cause him to be conveyed under safe and
sure conduct back to the prison.
 

The
..........................day of
...............................................................
 

A.B.
 

(Countersigned)
C.D.
 

  



 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
PRISONERS (ATTENDANCE IN COURTS)
ACT, 1955
 



 



 


THE
SECOND SCHEDULE 


 


[See
sub-section (2) of section 3] 


 

Court
of
.................................................................................................................
 

To
the Officer in charge of the ............................................ (State
name of prison).
 

You
are hereby required to produce ........................................., now
confined in ...................................................., under safe and
sure conduct before the Court of ........................................ at
............................. on the ..................... day of
........................................ next by ...................of the clock
in the forenoon of the same day, there to answer a charge now pending before the
said Court, and after such charge has been disposed of or the said Court has
dispensed with his further attendance, cause him to be conveyed under safe and
sure conduct back to the said prison.
 

The
............................day of
.........................................................
 

A.B.
 

(Countersigned)
C.D. 


 

  



 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1956, for 
clause (c) (w.e.f.
1-11-56).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>