<act><title>THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES 
RULES, 19851</title> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 19851
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Rules, 
1985.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “the Act,” means the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 
  1985 (61 of 1985); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ‘Appellate Authority” means any authority to whom an appeal may lie 
  under any provision of these rules; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> “Chemical Examiner” means the Chemical Examiner or Deputy 
  Chief Chemist or Shift Chemist or Assistant Chemical Examiner, Government 
  Opium and Alkaloid Works, Neemuch or, as the case may be, Ghazipur;] 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “Chief Controller of Factories” means the Chief Controller of 
  Government Opium and Alkaloid Factories; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “crop year” means the period beginning on and from the 1st October of 
  any year to the 30th September of the following year; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “General Manager” means the General Manager, Government Opium and 
  Alkaloid Works, Neemuch or, as the case may be, Ghazipur; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> “Issuing authority” means the Narcotic Commissioner or any other 
  officer who may be authorised in this behalf by the Central Government for 
  issuing a licence under Chapter V of these rules or issuing an import 
  certificate or export authorisation under Chapter VI of these rules in respect 
  of narcotic drugs or psychotropic substances; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “licence” means a licence issued under these rules; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> “Proper Officer”, in relation to any function to be performed under 
  these rules, means the officer of Narcotics Department who is assigned those 
  functions by the Narcotics Commissioner; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> ‘Schedule” means a Schedule annexed to these rules; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> words and expressions used herein and not defined, but defined in the 
  Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>




</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Delegation of powers.—Subject 
to such directions as may be given by the Central Government, the Narcotics 
Commissioner appointed by the Central Government under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 5 of the Act, may authorise any officer subordinate to him, to exercise 
all or any of his powers under these rules.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Narcotics Commissioner 
and other officers to exercise the powers of their subordinates.—The 
Narcotics Commissioner and such other officer as may be appointed by the Central 
Government under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5 of the Act may perform all or any 
of the functions, or exercise any of the powers, assigned under these rules to 
the officers subordinate to them.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Opium poppy cultivation 
and production of opium or poppy straw.—The 
opium poppy for production of opium or poppy straw shall not be cultivated save 
on account of the Central Government and in the tracts notified by it from time 
to time and in accordance with the conditions of a licence issued by the 
District Opium Officer under rule 8.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Fee for grant of 
licence.--The 
licence of cultivation of opium poppy may be granted by the District Opium 
Officer on payment of a fee of 

1[rupees 
twenty-five].
 
 



</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Form of licence for 
cultivation of the opium poppy.—The 
licence for cultivation of opium poppy for the production of opium or poppy 
straw shall be issued in Form No. 1 appended to these rules.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Issue of licence.—Subject 
to the general conditions relating to grant of licence notified by the Central 
Government*, the District Opium Officer may issue licence to any person for a 
crop year for cultivation of the opium poppy for production of opium or poppy 
straw on receipt of an application made by that person in Form No.2 appended to 
these rules.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Licence to specify the 
area, etc.—The 
licence for cultivation of opium poppy issued under rule 8 shall specify the 
area and designate the plots to be cultivated with opium poppy.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Designating of 
Lambardar.—The 
District Opium Officer may designate one of the cultivators of opium poppy as 
Lambardar in each village where opium poppy cultivation is permitted, who shall 
perform such functions and on such terms and conditions as may be specified from 
time to time by the Narcotics Commissioner.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Withholding or 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An officer higher in rank than the District Opium Officer may, for sufficient 
reasons to be recorded in writing, withhold or cancel a licence already issued.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No order shall be 
passed under sub-rule (1) unless the cultivator has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the said order or is heard in person, if he 
so desires.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where opium poppy has 
been cultivated under a licence which is subsequently withheld, or cancelled, 
the standing crop, if any, shall be destroyed under the supervision of the 
proper officer in such manner as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Procedure with regard 
to measurement of land cultivated with opium poppy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All plots of land cultivated with opium poppy in accordance with the licence 
issued under these rules, shall be measured in metres by the proper officer in 
the presence of the cultivator concerned and the Lambardar of the village and 
the concerned cultivator and the Lambardar of the village shall attest the 
entries made in the records to be maintained by the Lambardar, as may be 
specified by the Narcotics Commissioner in this behalf, under their 
signature/thumb-impression with date, in token of having satisfied themselves 
regarding the correctness of the measurement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The measurement 
conducted by the proper officer shall be subject to such further checks by such 
officers as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner in this behalf.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Procedure with regard 
to preliminary weighment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The cultivator shall, during the course of harvesting, produce daily before the 
Lambardar, each day’s collection of opium from his crop for weighment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Lambardar shall 
make arrangements to weigh such opium and make necessary entries in the records 
to be maintained by him as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner in 
this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The cultivator and the 
Lambardar shall attest the entries made in such records under their 
signature/thumb-impression with date, showing the quantity of opium weighed on a 
particular day.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The proper officer 
shall conduct check weighment of the opium collected by the cultivators with 
reference to the entries in the Lambardar’s record and indicate his finding 
therein which shall be attested by him and the Lambardar under their signature 
with date.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The variations between 
the quantity of opium produced by the cultivator indicated in the Lambardar’s 
record and as found by the proper officer during his check, shall be inquired 
into by the proper officer in order to ascertain the liability of the cultivator 
for punishment under section 19 of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Delivery of opium 
produced.—All 
opium, the produce of land cultivated with opium poppy, shall be delivered by 
the cultivators to the District Opium Officer or any other officer duly 
authorised in this behalf, by the Narcotics Commissioner at a place as may be 
specified by such officer.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Opium to be weighed, 
examined and classified.—All 
opium delivered by the cultivators to the District Opium Officer or any other 
officer authorised as aforesaid, shall, in the presence of the concerned 
cultivator or any person authorised by him and the Lambardar of the village, be 
weighed, examined and classified according to its quality and consistence and 
forwarded by the District Opium Officer to the Government Opium Factory in such 
manner as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Procedure where 
cultivator is dissatisfied with classification of opium.—Any 
cultivator who may be dissatisfied with the classification of his opium done by 
the officer referred to in rule 15 may have it forwarded by such officer to the 
Government Opium Factory separately, after having it properly sealed in his 
presence and in the presence of the concerned Lambardar.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Procedure for sending 
opium suspected to be adulterated.—
When opium delivered by a cultivator to the District Opium Officer or any 
other officer authorised in this behalf, is suspected of being adulterated with 
any foreign substance, it shall be forwarded to the Government Opium Factory 
separately, after it is properly sealed in the presence of the cultivator and 
the concerned Lambardar.
 
 
</article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>18</number> Drawing of samples from 
opium sent to Government Opium Factory under rule 16 or rule 17.—The sealed opium received 
separately in accordance with rule 16 or rule 17, shall be opened and sample 
drawn thereof in the presence of the cultivator, if he so desires, to whom, a 
notice intimating the date and time in this behalf, shall be sent well in 
advance.
  </article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Fixation of price of 
opium.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government shall, from time to time, fix the price of opium, to be paid 
to the cultivators, in such manner as it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such price shall be 
fixed per kilogram of opium of a standard consistence.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Provisional payment of 
price.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
District Opium Officer shall, having regard to the weight and consistence of 
opium delivered by individual cultivators, work out the weight of such opium at 
the standard consistence and determine provisionally the total price payable to 
such cultivators.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The said officer, 
shall, pay to the cultivators, ninety per cent. of the price so determined which 
shall be subject to adjustment against the final price payable to the 
cultivators to be determined as provided hereinafter.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>21</number> Weighment and examination of 
the opium at the Government Opium Factory.—The opium forwarded by the 
District Opium Officer shall be received, weighed, examined, and classified in 
the Government Opium Factory under the supervision of the General Manager in 
such manner as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner.
  </article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Confiscation of 
adulterated opium.—All 
such opium received separately under rule 17, if found to be adulterated on 
examination by the Chemical Examiner in the Government Opium Factory may be 
liable to confiscation by the General Manager.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Adjudication of 
confiscation of adulterated opium.—No 
such confiscation shall be ordered by the General Manager unless the concerned 
cultivator is given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed order and is heard in person, if he so desires.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Determination of final 
price of opium.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to rule 21, the final price of opium payable to the cultivator shall, 
having regard to the price fixed by the Central Government under rule 19, be 
determined by the General Manager on the basis of analysis report of the 
Chemical Examiner 

1[***] and 
communicated to the concerned District Opium Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The price payable in 
respect of any opium which is delivered to the District Opium Officer or any 
other officer authorised in this behalf under rule 14 and is not initially 
suspected to be adulterated but found to be adulterated on examination in the 
Government Opium Factory, shall be subject to reduction at such rates as may be 
specified by the Central Government.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Adjustment of 
cultivators’ account and recovery of dues from the cultivators.—The 
accounts of the cultivators for a particular crop year shall be adjusted by the 
District Opium Officer at the time of issuing of licences for the subsequent 
crop year and any balance that may remain due from the cultivators shall be 
recovered and any amount due to them be paid.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Adjustment of 
cultivators’ account and recovery of dues from the cultivators.—The 
accounts of the cultivators for a particular crop year shall be adjusted by the 
District Opium Officer at the time of issuing of licences for the subsequent 
crop year and any balance that may remain due from the cultivators shall be 
recovered and any amount due to them be paid.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Weights and scales.—The 
weights and scales to be used for weighing the opium at the weighment centres 
and the Government Opium Factory shall be caused to be examined at the 
appropriate time by the Deputy Narcotics Commissioner or the General Manager, as 
the case may be.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Cultivation of opium 
poppy for exclusive production of poppy straw.—The 
Central Government may, if it considers it expedient so to do, permit 
cultivation of the opium poppy for the exclusive production of poppy straw in 
accordance with a licence issued under rule 8 in such tracts and subject to such 
conditions as may be specified by it, by notification in the Official Gazette in 
this behalf:
 
Provided that the poppy 
straw produced by the cultivators or a result of the cultivation of opium poppy 
for production of opium, shall be deemed to have been produced under a valid 
licence issued under rule 8.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Appeals to the Deputy 
Narcotics Commissioner and Narcotics Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
Any person aggrieved by any decision or order made or passed under these rules 
relating to refusal, withholding or cancellation of a licence for opium poppy 
cultivation by an officer of the Narcotics Department, lower in rank than the 
Deputy Narcotics Commissioner, may appeal to the Deputy Narcotics Commissioner 
within thirty days from the date of the communication to him of such decision or 
order.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in clause (a), if the decision or order regarding withholding 
or cancellation of licence for opium poppy cultivation is passed by the Deputy 
Narcotics Commissioner, such appeal shall lie to the Narcotics Commissioner:
 
Provided that the Deputy 
Narcotics Commissioner or, as the case may be, the Narcotics Commissioner may, 
if he is satisfied that the appellant was prevented from submitting his appeal 
within the time limit specified in clause (a) due to reasons beyond his control, 
allow such appeal to be presented within a further a period of thirty days.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every appeal under 
this rule shall be accompanied by a copy of the decision or order appealed 
against and shall be in such form and in such a manner as may be specified by 
the Narcotics Commissioner in this behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>29</number> Appeals to the Chief 
Controller of Factories.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by any 
decision or order made or passed under rule 21 or rule 23 by the General Manager 
may appeal to the Chief Controller of Factories within thirty days from the date 
of the communication to him of such decision or order:
 Provided that the Chief 
Controller of Factories may, if he is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
from submitting his appeal within the said time limit due to reasons beyond his 
control, allow such appeal to be presented within a further period of thirty 
days.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal under this rule 
shall be accompanied by a copy of the decision or order appealed against and 
shall be in such form and in such manner as may be specified by the Narcotics 
Commissioner.
  </section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Procedure for appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Appellate Authority shall give an opportunity to appellant to be heard, if 
he so desires.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Appellate 
Authority may, at the hearing of an appeal, allow the appellant to go into any 
ground of appeal not specified in the grounds of appeal, if the Appellate 
Authority is satisfied that omission of that ground from the grounds of appeal 
was not wilful or unreasonable.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Appellate 
Authority may, after making such further inquiry as may be necessary, pass such 
orders as he thinks fit confirming, modifying or annulling the decision or order 
appealed against:
 
Provided that any order 
relating to the quantum of adulterated opium to be confiscated in addition to 
the opium already confiscated under rule 23 shall not be passed unless the 
appellant has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed order.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The order of the 
Appellate Authority disposing of the appeal under this rule shall be in writing 
and shall state the points for determination, the decision thereon and the 
reasons for the decision.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On the disposal of the 
appeal, the Appellate Authority shall communicate the order passed by him to the 
appellant and the officer who passed the order or made the decision appealed 
against.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No further appeal or 
revision shall lie against the order passed by the Appellate Authority under 
this rule.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>31</number> Manufacture of 
opium.—Opium 
shall not be manufactured save by the Central Government Opium Factories at 
Ghazipur and Neemuch:
 Provided that opium mixtures may 
be manufactured from opium lawfully possessed by a person authorised under the 
rules made by the State Government for the said purpose.
  </article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Export of opium.—The 
export of opium is prohibited save when the export is on behalf of the Central 
Government.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Sale to State Governments or manufacturing chemists. </title>— 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The sale of opium to the State Governments or manufacturing 
chemists or the person or entity who has been granted licence under sub-section 
(2A) of rule 36, as the case may be, shall be only from the Government Opium 
Factories, located at Neemuch and Ghazipur; 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The sale of opium from the Government Opium Factory at Neemuch and 
Ghazipur to manufacturing chemists or the person or entity who has been granted 
licence under sub-rule (2A) of rule 36, as the case may be, shall be only under 
a permit granted by or under the orders of the State Government within whose 
jurisdiction the chemist or the person or entity resides or has his place of 
business in the forms prescribed by that Government;] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The permit referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be issued, in quadruplicate 
and,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the quadruplicate copy shall be retained by the issuing authority and 
  the remaining copies forwarded to the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Government Opium Factories 
  at Neemuch and Ghazipur]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the said factory shall retain the duplicate copy for record, send the 
  original copy with the consignment of opium and return the triplicate copy to 
  the issuing authority after endorsing thereon the quantity actually supplied 
  and the date of despatch. </subsection>



</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Fixation of sales 
price of opium.—The 
price to be charged for opium sold under this Chapter shall be fixed, from time 
to time, by the Central Government in such manner as it may deem fit.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> General prohibition.—The 
manufacture of crude cocaine, ecgonine and its salts and of diacetyl morphine 
and its salts is prohibited:
 

1[Provided that 
nothing contained in this rule shall apply in case the drugs are manufactured by 
Government opium factory or by chemical staff employed under the Central Board 
of Excise and Customs or any person authorised by the Narcotics Commissioner by 
a special licence for purposes mentioned in Chapter VIIA:
 
Provided further that the 
Narcotics Commissioner shall consult the Drugs Controller-General of India 
before issuing a licence under this Chapter.]
 
 



</article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>36</number> Manufacture of natural 
manufactured drugs.—
<section><number>1</number> The manufacture of cocaine 
and its salts is prohibited save the manufacture of cocaine hydrochloride by the 
chemical staff employed under the Central Board of Excise and Customs from 
confiscated cocaine.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The manufacture of morphine, 
codeine, dionine, thebaine, dihydro-codeinone, dihydrocodeine, 
acetyldihydrocodeine, acetyldihydrocodeinone, dihydromorphine, 
dihydromorphinone, dihydrohydroxycodeinone, pholocodine and their respective 
salts is prohibited save by the Government Opium Factory.
 1[(2A) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (2), the Narcotics Commissioner or such other officer as 
may be authorized by the Central Government may, on and from the commencement of 
the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (Amendment) Rules, 2004 grant a 
licence in Form 3 appended to these rules on such terms and conditions as may be 
specified in the licence to any person or entity for manufacture of morphine, 
codeine, dionine, thebaine, dihydrocodeinone, dihydrocodeine, 
acetyldihydrocodeine, acetyldi-hydrocodeinone, dihydromorphine, 
dihydromorphinone, dihydrohydroxy-codeinone, pholcodine and their respective 
salts 2[from Indian opium, if the 
Central Government determines that such licence is necessary in public interest 
and is in consonance with India’s obligations under International treaties, 
conventions or protocols;]]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The manufacture of medicinal 
hemp shall be under a licence granted by the State Government on payment of such 
fees and in accordance with such conditions as may be prescribed by that 
Government in this behalf.
  



</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>37</number> Manufacture of synthetic 
manufactured drugs.—
<section><number>1</number> The manufacture of 
manufactured drugs notified under sub-clause (b) of clause (xi) of section 2 of 
the Act (hereafter referred to as the drug) is prohibited save under and in 
accordance with the conditions of a licence granted by the Narcotices 
Commissioner or such other officer as may be authorised by the Central 
Government in this behalf, in Form No. 3 appended to these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A fee of rupees fifty shall 
be payable in advance to the Central Government for each licence issued 
1[under this rule or sub-rule 
(2A) of rule 36] for renewal thereof.
  


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Application for 
licence.—Every 
application for a licence or for renewal thereof 

1[under rule 36 or 
rule 37] 

2[or under the 
proviso to rule 35] shall be in such form as may be specified by the Narcotics 
Commissioner.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Conditions for issue 
of licences.—No 
licence shall be issued 

1[under rule 36 or 
rule 37] 

2[or under the 
proviso to rule 35] unless the applicant therefore has—
 <section>
         <number>i</number> produced to the issuing 
authority licences granted to him under (a) the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 
(23 of 1940) for the manufacture of the drug, and (b) the rules framed under 
section 10 of the Act by State Government of the State in which he has his place 
of business, for the possession, sale and distribution of the drugs; and
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number> made a deposit of Rs. 5,000.00 
as security in the manner specified by the issuing authority for the due 
observance of the conditions of the licence and has furnished proof to the 
satisfaction of the issuing authority that he is equipped as to the land, 
building and other paraphernalia to properly carry on the business described in 
the application and is of good financial standing.
 
 




</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>40</number> Manufacture only from 
materials lawfully possessed.—The licensee shall not 
manufacture the drug save from materials which he is lawfully entitled to 
possess.
  </article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>41</number> Limits of 
manufacture.—The issuing authority, while 
issuing the licence, shall take into account all relevant factors for permitting 
the quantity of the drug to be manufactured by a licensee including the 
following:—
 <section>        <number>a</number> 
quantity allotted by the State Government for processing into any preparation in 
licensee’s own manufacture;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number> 
quantity required for supply to other firms within or outside the 
country;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number> 
quantity required for reasonable inventory:
 Provided that the total quantity 
of the drug manufactured during any one year does not exceed the estimated 
requirements of this country for the relevant year as furnished to the 
International Narcotics Control Board.
  </section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Security arrangements.—The 
licensee shall ensure all necessary security arrangements in the manufacturing 
premises as may be specified by the issuing authority.
 


</article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>43</number> Advance notice for 
commencement and cessation of manufacture.—The licensee shall give at 
least 15 days’ notice in writing to the issuing authority of the date on which 
he proposes to commence manufacture of the drug and at least one month’s notice 
before he ceases to manufacture the same.
  </article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>44</number> Cessation of 
manufacture.—Where the licensee ceases 
manufacturing operations for any reasons whatsoever, he shall forthwith inform 
the issuing authority in this behalf indicating the date on which he proposes to 
recommence manufacture:
 Provided that the issuing 
authority may prohibit all further manufacture in case the period of cessation 
of manufacture exceeds 30 days.
  </article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Possession, sale and 
distribution.—The 
licensee shall not possess or sell or distribute the drug otherwise than in 
accordance with the rules made by the State Government under the Act.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Maintenance of 
accounts and submission of returns.—The 
licensee shall maintain true accounts of all transactions including the accounts 
of materials used for the manufacture of the drug, the quantities manufactured, 
sold or otherwise disposed of and furnish returns in such forms and in such 
manner as may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Inspection of stocks, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The stocks of the drug and the materials used for its manufacture and all 
accounts and records of transactions relating thereto, shall be open to 
inspection by any officer authorised by the issuing authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A serially numbered 
Inspection Book shall be maintained by the licensee in good condition for the 
use of such officer.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Suspension and 
revocation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to any action that may be taken under the provisions of the 
Act, the issuing authority may suspend or cancel a licence—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number> if the licence is transferred or 
sublet without the prior approval of the issuing authority; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> in the event of any breach of 
any conditions of the licence; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number> if the licensee is convicted 
for any offence under the Act or under any other law relating to the narcotic 
drugs for the time being in force in any State.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No order shall be 
passed under sub-rule (1) unless the licensee has been given a reasonable 
opportunity showing cause against the said order or is heard in person, if he so 
desires.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The licensee may file an appeal against the decision or order made or passed 
under rule 48 to—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number> the Narcotics Commissioner where 
such decision or order was made or passed by any officer subordinate to him; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> the Board, in any other case,
 
within 30 days from the date of communication 
to him to such decision or order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every memorandum of 
appeal shall be accompanied by a copy of the decision or order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal under 
this rule shall be filed in such form and in such manner as may be specified by 
the Board.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Procedure for appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Appellate Authority shall give an opportunity to the appellant to be heard 
in person, if he so desires.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Appellate 
Authority may, at the hearing of an appeal allow the appellant to go into any 
ground of appeal not specified in the grounds of appeal, if the Appellate 
Authority is satisfied that omission of that ground from the grounds of appeal 
was not wilful or unreasonable.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Appellate 
Authority may, after making such further inquiry as may be necessary, pass such 
orders as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or annulling the decision or 
order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The order of the 
Appellate Authority disposing of the appeal under this rule shall be in writing 
and shall state the points for determination, the decision thereon and the 
reasons for the decision.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Surrender of licence.—A 
licensee may, if he so desires, surrender his licence, by giving not less than 
15 days’ notice in writing to the issuing authority.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Disposal of stocks of 
drugs on cancellation of licence, etc.—Such 
stocks or drugs as may be in the possession of a licensee, on the expiry or 
cancellation or surrender of his licence, shall be disposed of in such manner as 
may be specified by the Narcotics Commissioner in this behalf.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> General prohibition.—Subject 
to the other provisions of this Chapter, the import into and export out of India 
of the narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances specified in Schedule I is 
prohibited:
 

1[Provided that 
nothing in this rule shall apply in case the drug substance is imported into or 
exported out of 
India subject to an import certificate or export authorisation issued under the 
provision of this Chapter and for the purpose mentioned in Chapter VIIA.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number> Import of opium, etc . </title>—The import of— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> opium, concentrate of poppy straw, and 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> morphine, codeine, thebaine, and their salts is prohibited save by the Government Opium Factory: 
</section>
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[Provided that nothing in this rule shall apply to import of morphine, codeine, thebaine and their salts by manufacturers notified by the Government, for use in manufacture of products to be exported or to imports of small quantities of morphine, codeine and thebaine and their salts not exceeding a total of 1 kilogram <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[during a calendar year for analytical purposes by an importer], after following the procedure under rule 55 and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the import certificate issued in Form No. 4A.] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number> Import of opium, etc . </title>—The import of— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> opium, concentrate of poppy straw, and 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> morphine, codeine, thebaine, and their salts is prohibited save by the Government Opium Factory: 
</section>
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided that nothing in this rule shall apply to import of morphine, codeine, thebaine and their salts by manufacturers notified by the Government, for use in manufacture of products to be exported or to imports of small quantities of morphine, codeine and thebaine and their salts not exceeding a total of 1 kilogram <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[during a calendar year for analytical purposes by an importer], after following the procedure under rule 55 and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the import certificate issued in Form No. 4A.] 




</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Application for import 
certificate.—1[(3) 
Subject to rule 53, no narcotic drug, or psychotropic substance specified in the 
Schedule of the Act shall be imported into India without an import certificate 
in respect of the consignment issued by the issuing authority, in Form No. 4 
appended to these rules.]
 <section>
<number>2</number> The importer applying 
for an import certificate under sub-rule (1) in relation to narcotic drug shall 
submit along with his application the original or certified copy of the excise 
permit issued by the concerned State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application for 
the import certificate shall state such details as may be specified by the 
Narcotics Commissioner.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Issue of import 
certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The issuing authority shall prepare seven copies of the import certificate 
referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 55 and deal with them in the manner 
hereunder provided, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> (i) original and duplicate 
copies should be supplied to the importer who should transmit the original copy 
to the exporting country and shall produce the duplicate copy at the Customs 
House, Land Customs Station or Airport where the consignment arrives or, in the 
case of imports by parcel post, at the post office of delivery, in order to 
obtain delivery of the consignment of narcotic drugs or psychotropic substances;
 <subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> the Collector of Customs or 
Post Master shall state on the copy presented by the importer that the narcotic 
drugs or the psychotropic substances have actually been imported and return the 
document to the importer who shall indicate on it that he has received the 
goods;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number> the importer shall return 
the duplicate copy of the import certificate incorporating the endorsement from 
the Collector of Customs or Post Master and his own endorsement to the issuing 
authority—(1) where the import certificate relates to narcotic drug, through the 
excise authorities of the State from which excise permit for purposes of 
sub-rule (2) of rule 55 was produced; (2) where the import certificate relates 
to psychotropic substance, through the Drugs Controller of the concerned State;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> triplicate copy should be 
supplied to the Collector of Customs concerned who shall return it to the 
issuing authority along with the copy of the export authorisation to be received 
at the time of receipt of the consignment from the Government of the exporting 
country, with an endorsement as to actual quantity of narcotic drugs or 
psychotropic substances cleared;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> quadruplicate copy of the import 
certificate in relation to narcotic drug should be supplied to the excise 
authorities of the State into which the narcotic drug is to be imported, and the 
said copy of the certificate in relation to psychotropic substance should be 
supplied to the Drugs Controller of the concerned State for comparison with the 
copy produced before them, by the importer under sub-clause (a) of this 
sub-rule.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number> qunituplicate copy should be 
supplied to the Government of the exporting country for comparison with the copy 
furnished to them by importer under sub-clause (a) or this sub-rule;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number> sextuplicate copy should be 
retained to the Drugs Controller, Government of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number> septuplicate copy should be 
retained by the issuing authority in his office.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An import certificate 
issued under sub-rule (1) of rule 55 may allow the importation of the quantity 
of the concerned drug or the substance in more than one consignment.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Transit.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 79 of the Act and rule 53, no consignment of any 
narcotic drug, or psychotropic substances specified in 

1[Schedule of the 
Act], shall be allowed to be transited through India unless such consignment is 
accompanied by a valid export authorisation in this behalf, issued by the 
Government of the exporting country:
 
Provided that the 
provisions of this rule shall not apply to the carriage by any ship or aircraft, 
of small quantities of such narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances which are 
essential for treatment of, or medical aid to, any person on board the ship or 
aircraft.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Application for export 
authorisation.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[Subject to rules 
53 and 53A, no narcotic drugs, or psychotropic substances specified in the 
Schedule of the Act, shall be exported out of India without an export 
authorisation in respect of the consignment issued by the issuing authority in 
Form No. 5 appended to these rules].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The exporter applying 
for an export authorisation under sub-rule (1) shall submit,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> where the export authorisation 
relates to narcotic drug, along with his application the original or an 
authenticated copy of the excise permit issued by the concerned State 
Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> the import certificate in 
original, issued by the Government of the importing country certifying the 
official approval of the concerned Government.
 

2[***]
 

3[(3) The 
application for the export authorisation shall state such details as may be 
specified by the Narcotics Commissioner.
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Issue of export 
authorisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The issuing authority shall prepare five copies of the export authorisation 
referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 58 and deal with them in the manner 
hereunder provided, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> the original should be supplied 
to the consignor which shall accompany the consignment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> the duplicate copy should be 
forwarded to the Collector of Customs of the port who will return it to the 
issuing authority indicating on it the date of export and the quantity exported;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> the triplicate copy should be 
forwarded to the Government of the importing country;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number> the quadruplicate copy should be 
forwarded to the excise authority of the State in which the exporter has his 
place of business;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number> quintuplicate copy should be 
retained by the issuing authority in his office;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the consignment 
of narcotic drug or psychotropic substance is to be transhipped or transited 
through one or more countries, such additional number of copies of export 
authorisation as may be required shall be prepared and sent to the concerned 
country or, as the case may be, countries.
 
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Transhipment.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 79 of the Act and rule 53, no consignment of 
narcotic drug, or psychotropic substance specified in 

1[Schedule of the 
Act], shall be allowed to be transhipped at any port in India save with the 
permission of the Collector of Customs.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Procedure for 
transhipment.—The 
Collector of Customs while allowing any consignment of narcotic drug, or 
psychotropic substances, specified in 

1[Schedule of the 
Act,] to be transhipped shall, inter alia, satisfy himself that the 
consignment is accompanied by a valid export authorisation issued by the 
exporting country.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Diversion of 
consignment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Collector of Customs shall take all due measures to prevent the diversion of 
such consignment to a destination other than that named in the aforesaid export 
authorisation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>(a) The Collector of 
Customs may permit diversion of such a consignment to a country other than that 
named in the accompanying copy of the export authorisation subject to the 
production of export authorisation issued by the issuing authority as provided 
under rule 58, as if the diversion were an export from India to the country, or 
territory of new destination.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Collector of 
Customs shall inform the issuing authority regarding the actual quantity of the 
narcotic drug or psychotropic substance, the diversion of the consignment of 
which was allowed under clause (a), whereupon the issuing authority shall, 
inform the country from which the export of the consignment originated.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Prohibition of import 
and export of consignments through a post office box, etc.—The 
import or export of consignments of any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance 
through a post office box or through a bank is prohibited.
 


</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> General prohibition.—No 
person shall manufacture, possess, transport, import inter-State, export 
inter-State, sell, purchase, consume or use any of the psychotropic substances 
specified in Schedule I.
 


</article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>65</number> Manufacture of psychotropic 
substances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-rule (2), the manufacture of any of the 
psychotropic substances other than those specified in Schedule I shall be in 
accordance with the conditions of a licence granted under the Drugs and 
Cosmetics Rules, 1945 (hereinafter referred to as the 1945 Rules) framed under 
the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 (23 of 1940), by an authority in charge of 
Drugs Control in a State appointed by the State Government in this 
behalf:
 1[Provided that the authority in 
charge of drug control in a State referred to above may issue a licence to 
manufacture a psychotropic substance specified in Schedule III for the purpose 
of export only;]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority in charge of 
drugs control in a State (hereinafter referred to as the Licensing Authority) 
shall consult the Drugs Controller (India) in regard to the assessed annual 
requirements of each of the psychotropic substances in bulk form referred to in 
sub-rule (1) in the country and taking into account the requirement of such 
psychotropic substances in the State, the quantity of such substance required 
for supply to other manufacturers outside the State and the quantity of such 
substance required for reasonable inventory to be held by a manufacturer, shall 
specify, by order, the limit of the quantity of such substance which may be 
manufactured by the manufacturer in the State.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The quantity of the said 
psychotropic substance which may be manufactured by a licensee in an year shall 
be intimated by the Licencing Authority to the licensee at the time of issuing 
the licence:
 2[Provided that nothing contained 
in this rule shall apply in case the psychotropic substances specified in 
Schedule I are manufactured, possessed, transported, imported inter-State, 
exported inter-State, sold, purchased, consumed or used subject to other 
provisions of this Chapter which applies to psychotropic substances which are 
not included in Schedule I and for the purposes mentioned in Chapter 
VIIA:
 Provided further that the 
authority in charge of the drug control in a State referred to in sub-rule (2) 
of rule 65 shall consult the Narcotics Commissioner before issuing a licence 
under rule 65 in respect of psychotropic substances included in Schedule I 
1[and Schedule III].]
  



</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>66</number> Possession, etc., of 
psychotropic substances.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall possess any 
psychotropic substance for any of the purposes covered by the 1945 Rules, unless 
he is lawfully authorised to possess such substance for any of the said purposes 
under these Rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (1), any research institution or a hospital or dispensary 
maintained or supported by Government or local body or by charity or voluntary 
subscription, which is not authorised to possess any psychotropic substance 
under the 1945 Rules, or any person who is not so authorised under the 1945 
Rules, may possess a reasonable quantity of such substance as may be necessary 
for their genuine scientific requirements or genuine medical requirements, or 
both for such period as is deemed necessary by the said research institution or, 
as the case may be, the said hospital or dispensary or person:
 Provided that where such 
psychotropic substance is in possession of an individual for his personal 
medical use the quantity thereof shall not exceed one hundred dosage units at a 
time:
 1[Provided further that an 
individual may possess the quantity of exceeding one hundred dosage units at a 
time for his personal long term medical use if specifically prescribed by a 
Registered Medical Practitioner.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The research institution, 
hospital and dispensary referred to in sub-rule (2) shall maintain proper 
accounts and records in relation to the purchase and consumption of the 
psychotropic substance in their possession.
  


</section></article> 

   


    


 <article><number>67</number>
Transport of psychotropic substance.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions of rule 64, no consignment of psychotropic substance
shall be transported, imported inter-State or exported inter-State unless such
consignment is accompanied by a consignment note in 1[Form 6] appended to these
Rules and in the manner as provided hereinafter. (2) The consignment note
referred in sub-rule (1) shall be prepared in triplicate, and the original and
duplicate copies of the said note shall be sent along with the consignment of
psychotropic substances to the consignee who shall return the duplicate copy of
the note to the consignor for his use after endorsing on the original and
duplicate copies the particulars of the receipt of the quantity consigned.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The consignor shall make necessary entries on the triplicate copy of the said
note with reference to the receipt of quantity of the psychotropic substances
indicated on that duplicate copy of the note.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The consignor and consignee shall keep such consignment note for a period of two
years and the said note may be inspected at any time by an officer authorised in
this behalf by the Central Government.
 


 2[Provided
that consignment note in Form 6 shall not apply in cases where the sale of the
psychotropics substance is accompanied by a sale bill or invoice or cash memo or
any other document duly signed by the consignor or his authorised signatory,
which shall include the following information about the consignment:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
name, address and licence number of the consignor and the consignee; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
description, batch number and quantity; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
mode and particulars of transport: 
 
 


 Provided
further that such document shall be preserved by consignor and consignee for a
period of two years for inspection by the officers referred to in sub-rule (4)
above.
 


 Explanation.—Where
the consignee is a research institution, registered medical practitioner,
hospital or dispensary, the requirement of incorporating licence number of
consignee shall not be applicable.]  


   





</subsection></section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>67A</number> 
Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the foregoing provisions of these rules—
 <section>        
<number>a</number>  a narcotic drug and psychotropic substance may be used for—
 <subsection>              
<number>i</number> scientific requirement including analytical requirements of any Government 
laboratory or any research institution in India or 
abroad;
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>ii</number> very limited medical requirements of a foreigner by a duly authorised 
person of a hospital or any other establishment of the Government especially 
approved by that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>iii</number> the purpose of de-addiction of drug addicts by Government or local body or 
by an approved charity or voluntary organisation or by such other institution as 
may be approved by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>b</number> 
persons performing medical or scientific functions shall keep records concerning 
the acquisition of the substance and the details of their use in Form 7 of these 
rules and such records are to be preserved for at least two years after their 
(sic);
 </section><section>        <number>c</number> a 
narcotic drug and psychotropic substance may be supplied or dispensed for use to 
a foreigner pursuant to medical prescription only from the authorised licensed 
pharmacists or other authorised retail distributors designated by authorities 
responsible for public health.]
  
  


</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>67B</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, the government Opium and 
Alkaloid works may procure, manufacture or import and supply narcotic drugs and 
psychotropic substances as may be required as samples by various drug law 
enforcement agencies, testing laboratories and training institutions of the 
Central and State Governments.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Government Opium and 
Alkaloid Works may also supply samples to organisations other than those covered 
by sub-rule (1) with the prior approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any enforcement agency, 
laboratory, training institution or organisation requiring the samples shall 
apply to the Chief Controller of Factories in Form No. 8.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The quantities of various 
narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances to he supplied as samples shall be 
determined by the Central Government from time to time. The organisation 
obtaining the samples shall designate an officer, at the time of sending the 
request for samples, in whose custody the samples shall be kept.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The organisation 
requisitioning the samples shall maintain records and submit an annual report to 
the Chief Controller of Factories in Form No. 9.
 </section><section><number>6</number> When a sample is used for 
training, the organisation shall maintain a record of the quantity of drug taken 
out for training and the quantities actually used.]]
  



</section></article> 
 THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
  
 <article><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>67C</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, the Narcotics Commissioner 
may permit import or export of narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances for 
the purpose of controlled deliveries, investigations, intelligence collection 
scientific analysis.]]
  



</article> 
 
THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC 
SUBSTANCES RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Opium Rules, 1934, the Dangerous Drugs (Import, Export and 
Transhipment) Rules, 1957, and the Central Manufactured Drugs Rules, 1962 are 
hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken or purported to have been done or 
taken under any of the rules repealed by sub-rule (1) shall, in so far as it is 
not inconsistent with the provisions of these rules, be deemed to have been done 
or taken under the corresponding provisions of these rules.
 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. G.S.R. 82, dated 14th February, 1995 , for clause (c) 
(w.e.f. 25-2-1995 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 95 (E), dated 4th February, 2004, for 
sub-rules (1) and (2) (w.e.f. 4-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 95 (E), dated 4th February, 2004 , for 
“Government Opium Factory, Ghazipur” (w.e.f. 4-2-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Added by G.S.R. 736(E), dated 
22nd December, 2005 (w.e.f. 22-12-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 350(E), dated 25th 
June, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 350(E), dated 25th 
June, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by S.O. 1661(E), dated 13th July, 2010 (w.e.f. 13-7-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 470(E), dated 21st June, 2011, for “during a financial year for analytical purposes by any importer notified by the Government” (w.e.f. 21-6-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by S.O. 1661(E), dated 13th July, 2010 (w.e.f. 13-7-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 470(E), dated 21st June, 2011, for “during a financial year for analytical purposes by any importer notified by the Government” (w.e.f. 21-6-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Sub-rule (3) omitted by G.S.R. 556 
(E), dated 14th July, 1995 (w.e.f. 20-7-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Sub-rule (4) renumbered as sub-rule 
(3) by G.S.R. 556 (E), dated 14th July, 1995 (w.e.f. 20-7-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 350(E), dated 
25th June, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 104(E),
dated 25th February, 2005 (w.e.f. 25-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 350(E), dated 25th June, 1997 
(w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 350(E), 
dated 25th June, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Ins. 
by G.S.R. 639(E), dated 13th October, 2006 (w.e.f. 13-10-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 
350(E), dated 25th June, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-6-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  
Ins. by G.S.R. 639(E), dated 13th October, 2006 (w.e.f. 13-10-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>