<act><tid>1627294</tid>
<title>THE PROTECTION OF CIVIL RIGHTS ACT, <year>1955</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1955</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 8th May, <year>1955</year>.]

An Act to prescribe punishment for the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> preaching and practice of 
" Untouchability"], for the enforcement of any disability arising 
therefrom and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1004282</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>144986</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Protection of Civil Rights Act], <year>1955</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1546936</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1638784</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1084624</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>888680</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" civil rights" means any right accruing to a person by 
reason of the abolition of" untouchability" by article 17 
of the Constitution;]

</section>

<section><tid>1054141</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" hotel" includes a refreshment room, a boarding house, 
lodging house, a coffee house and a cafe;]

</section>

<section><tid>1362125</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>" place" includes a house, building and other structure 
and premises; and also includes a tent, vehicle and vessel;]

</section>

<section><tid>856238</tid>
<number>c</number>" place of public entertainment" includes any place to 
which the public are admitted and in which an entertainment 
is provided or held.
Explanation.-" Entertainment" includes any, exhibition, 
performance, game, sport and any other form of amusement;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>686</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modification by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch., to Dadra and Nagar Hevali by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 
2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1st July, <year>1965</year>) and to Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1st October, <year>1963</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2, for" practice of 
Untouchability" (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" the Untouchability (Offences) Act" 
 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number> 1st June, <year>1955</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O.. 1109, dated the 
23rd May, <year>1955</year>, Gazette of India. <year>1955</year>, Extraordinary, Part II, 
Section 3, page <year>1971</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Cl. (a) was relettered as cl. (aa) by s. 4. ibid., (w. e. f.  
  19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for cl. (b)  (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>24889</tid>
<number>d</number>" place of public worship" means a place, by whatever 
name known, which is used as a place of public religious 
worship or which is dedicated generally to, or is used 
generally by, persons professing any religion or belonging to 
any religious denomination or any section thereof, for the 
performance of any religious service, or for offering prayers 
therein; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and includes-

<subsection><tid>486905</tid>
<number>i</number>all lands and subsidiary shrines appurtenant or 
attached to any such place,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>368171</tid>
<number>ii</number>a privately owned place of worship which is, in 
fact, allowed by the owner thereof to be used as a 
place of public worship, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>882309</tid>
<number>iii</number>such land or subsidiary shrine appurtenant to such 
privately owned place of worship as is allowed by the 
owner thereof to be used as a place of public religious 
worship;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1234557</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>948451</tid>
<number>db</number>" Scheduled Castes" has the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (24) of article 366 of the Constitution;]

</section>

<section><tid>149084</tid>
<number>e</number>" shop" means any premises where goods are sold either 
whole- sale or by retail or both wholesale and by retail <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and 
includes-

<subsection><tid>1326792</tid>
<number>i</number>any place from where goods are sold by a hawker or 
vendor or from a mobile van or cart,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1099327</tid>
<number>ii</number>a laundry and a hair cutting saloon,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>126414</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other place where services are rendered to 
customers].



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>739937</tid>
<number> 3</number> Punishment for enforcing religious disabilities. Whoever on the 
ground of" untouchability" prevents any person-
<section><tid>1942576</tid>
<number>a</number>from entering any place of public worship which is open 
to other persons professing the same religion <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or any 
section thereof, as such person; or

</section>

<section><tid>586464</tid>
<number>b</number>from worshipping or offering prayers or performing any 
religious service in any place of public worship, or bathing 
in, or using the waters of, any sacred tank, well, spring or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>687</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" or belonging to the same religious denomination" 
omitted by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>]. 




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

water- course, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> river or lake or bathing at any ghat of such 
tank, water- course, river or lake] in the same manner and to 
the same extent as is permissible to other persons professing 
or any section thereof, as such the same religion, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
or any section there of, as such person;

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than 
one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall 
be rot less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred 
rupees].

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section and section 4 
persons professing the Buddhist, Sikh or Jaina religion or persons 
professing the Hindu religion in any of its forms or developments 
including Virashaivas, Lingayats, Adivasis, followers of Brahmo, 
Prarthana, Arya Samaj and the Swaminarayan Sampraday shall be deemed 
to be Hindus.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>154914</tid>
<number> 4</number> Punishment for enforcing social disabilities. Whoever on the 
ground of" untouchability" enforces against any person any disability 
with regard to-
<section><tid>1884623</tid>
<number>i</number>access to any shop, public restaurant, hotel or place 
of public entertainment; or

</section>

<section><tid>1506697</tid>
<number>ii</number>the use of any utensils, and other articles kept in any 
public restaurant, hotel, dharmshala, sarai or 
musafirkhana for the use of the general public or of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any 
section thereof]; or

</section>

<section><tid>1792086</tid>
<number>iii</number>the practice of any profession or the carrying on of 
any occupation, trade or business <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or employment in any job] 
; or

</section>

<section><tid>649137</tid>
<number>iv</number>the use of, or access to, any river, stream, spring, 
well, tank, cistern, water- tap or other watering place, or 
any bathing ghat, burial or cremation ground, any sanitary 
convenience, any road, or passage, or any other place of 
public resort which other members of the public, or <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[ any 
section thereof], have a right to use or have access to; or

</section>

<section><tid>472329</tid>
<number>v</number>the use of, or access to, any place used for a 
charitable or a public purpose maintained wholly or partly 
out of State funds or dedicated to the use of the general 
public, or <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any section thereof]; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>688</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" or belonging to the same religious denomination 
" omitted by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by s. 6., ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1851787</tid>
<number>vi</number>the enjoyment of any benefit under a charitable trust 
created for the benefit of the general public or of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ any 
section thereof]; or

</section>

<section><tid>912286</tid>
<number>vii</number>the use of, or access to, any public conveyance; or

</section>

<section><tid>1407962</tid>
<number>viii</number>the construction, acquisition, or occupation of 
any residential premises in any locality, whatsoever; or

</section>

<section><tid>901419</tid>
<number>ix</number>the use of any dharmshala, sarai or musafirkhana which 
is open to the general public, or to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any section thereof]; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1563765</tid>
<number>x</number>the observance of any social or religious custom, usage 
or ceremony or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ taking part in, or taking out, any 
religious social or cultural procession]; or

</section>

<section><tid>1319940</tid>
<number>xi</number>the use of jewellery and finery;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than 
one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall 
be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred 
rupees].

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," enforcement of 
any disability" includes any discrimination on the ground of" untouch- 
ability".]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1595238</tid>
<number> 5</number> Punishment for refusing to admit persons to hospitals etc. 
Whoever on the round of" untouchability"-
<section><tid>1940623</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses admission to any person to any hospital, 
dispensary, educational institution or any hostel <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, if 
such hospital, dispensary, educational institution or hostel 
is established or maintained for the benefit of the general 
public or any section thereof; or

</section>

<section><tid>1479247</tid>
<number>b</number>does any act which discriminates against any such 
person after admission to any of the aforesaid institutions;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than 
one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall 
be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred 
rupees].




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1478332</tid>
<number>6</number>Punishment for refusing to sell goods to render services. 
Whoever on the ground of" untouchability" refuses to sell any goods or 
refuses to render any- service to any person at. the same time and 
place and on the same terms and conditions at or on which such goods 
are sold or services are rendered to other persons in the ordinary

<pagefootnote><pagenum>689</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 6, for certain words (w. e. f. 19-  
  11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for" taking part in any religious 
procession" (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 6, ibid., (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" attached thereto" omitted by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 19-  
  11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

course of business <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
of not less than one month and not more than six months and also with 
fine which shall be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than 
five hundred rupees].



</article>



<article><tid>787276</tid>
<number> 7</number> Punishment for other offences arising out of 
" untouchability".
<section><tid>448414</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever- 

<subsection><tid>1233472</tid>
<number>a</number>prevents any person from exercising any right accruing 
to him by reason of the abolition of" untouchability" under 
article 17 of the Constitution; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53301</tid>
<number>b</number>molests, injures, annoys, obstructs or causes or 
attempts to cause obstruction to any person in the exercise 
of any such right or molests, injures, annoys or boycotts any 
person by reason of his having exercised any such right; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>500277</tid>
<number>c</number>by words, either spoken or written, or by signs or by 
visible representations or otherwise, incites or encourages 
any person or class of persons or the public generally to 
practise" untouchability" in any form whatsoever; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871064</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> insults or attempts to insult, on the ground of 
" untouchability", a member of a Scheduled Caste;]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than 
one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall 
be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred 
rupees].

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Explanation 1].- A person shall be deemed to boycott another 
person who-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1233472</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses to let to such other person or refuses to 
permit such other person, to use or occupy any house or land 
or refuses to deal with, work for hire for, or do business 
with, such other person or to render to him or receive from 
him any customary service, or refuses to do any of the said 
things on the terms on Which such things would be commonly 
done in the ordinary course of business; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53301</tid>
<number>b</number>abstains from such social, professional or business 
relations as he would ordinarily maintain with such other 
person.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>690</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 8, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Renumbered by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation II.- For the purpose of clause (c) a person shall be 
deemed to incite or encourage the practice of" untouchability"-


<subsubsection><tid>1605396</tid>
<number>i</number>if he, directly or indirectly, preaches" untouchability" 
or its practice in any form; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>61269</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he justifies, whether on historical, philosophical 
or religious grounds or on the ground of any tradition of the 
caste system or on any other ground, the practice of 
" untouchability" in any form.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>14863</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Whoever commits any offence against the person or property 
of any individual as a repraisal or revenge for his having exercised 
any right accruing to him by reason of the abolition of 
" untouchability" under article 17 of the Constitution, shall, where 
the offence is punishable with imprisonment for a term exceeding two 
years, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
less than two years and also with fine.]

</section>

<section><tid>1270108</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever-

<subsection><tid>478669</tid>
<number>i</number>denies to any person belonging to his community or any 
section thereof any right or privilege to which such person 
would be entitled as a member of such community or section, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1432871</tid>
<number>ii</number>takes any part in the ex- communication of such person, 
on the ground that such person has refused to practise 
" untouchability" or that such person has done any act in 
furtherance of the objects of this Act, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than one 
month and not more than six months, and also with fine which 
shall be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than 
five hundred rupees].



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1002096</tid>
<number> 7A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Unlawful compulsory labour when to be deemed to be a 
practice of untouchability.
<section><tid>517455</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever compels any person, on the  
ground of" untouchability", to do any scavenging or sweeping or to 
remove any carcass or to flay any animal or to remove the umbilical 
cord or to do any other job of a similar nature, shall be deemed to 
have enforced a disability arising out of" untouchability".

</section>

<section><tid>241218</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever is deemed under sub- section (1) to have enforced a 
disability arising out of" untouchability" shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months and 
not more than six months and also with fine which shall not be less 
than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred rupees.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>691</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 9, (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 10, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," compulsion" 
includes a threat of social or economic boycott.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>700185</tid>
<number>8</number>Cancellation or suspension of licences in certain cases. When a 
person who is convicted of an offence under section 6 holds any 
licence under any law for the time being in force in respect of any 
profession, trade, calling or employment in relation to which the 
offence is committed, the court trying the offence may, without 
prejudice to any other penalty to which such person may be liable 
under that section, direct that the licence shall stand cancelled or 
be suspended for such period as the court may deem fit, and every 
order of the court so cancelling or suspending a licence shall have 
effect as if it had been passed by the authority competent to cancel 
or suspend the licence under any such law.
Explanation.- In this section," licence" includes a permit or a 
permission.



</article>



<article><tid>1777317</tid>
<number>9</number>Resumption or suspension of grants made by Government. Where 
the manager or trustee of a place of public worship <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or any 
educational institution or hostel] which is in receipt of a grant of 
land or money from the Government is convicted of an offence under 
this Act and such conviction is not reversed or quashed in any appeal 
or revision, the Government may, if in its opinion the circumstances 
of the case warrant such a course, direct the suspension or resumption 
of the whole or any part of such grant.


</article>



<article><tid>740087</tid>
<number>10</number>Abetment of offence. Whoever abets any offence under this Act 
shall be punishable with the punishment provided for the offence.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Explanation.- A public servant who wilfully neglects the 
investigation of any offence punishable under this Act shall be deemed 
to have abetted an offence punishable under this Act.]



</article>



<article><tid>986760</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power of State Government to impose collective fine.
<section><tid>762308</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If, after an inquiry in the prescribed manner, the State Government is 
satisfied that the inhabitants of an area are concerned in, or 
abetting the commission of, any offence punishable under this Act, or 
harbouring persons concerned in the commission of such offence or 
failing to render all the assistance in their power to discover or 
apprehend the offender or offenders or suppressing material evidence 
of the commission of such offence, the State Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, impose a collective fine on such 
inhabitants and apportion such fine amongst the inhabitants who are 
liable collectively

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 11, (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 13, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

to pay it, and such apportionment shall be made according to the State 
Government' s judgment of the respective means of such inhabitants and 
in making any such apportionment the State Government may assign a 
portion of such fine to a Hindu undivided family to be payable by it:

Provided that the fine apportioned to an inhabitant shall not be 
realised until the petition, if any, filed by him under sub- section 
 (3) is disposed of.


</section>

<section><tid>402696</tid>
<number>2</number>The notification made under sub- section (1) shall be 
proclaimed in the area by beat of drum or in such other manner as 
the State Government may think best in the circumstances to bring the 
imposition of the collective fine to the notice of the inhabitants of 
the said area.

</section>

<section><tid>298643</tid>
<number>3</number> (a) Any person aggrieved by the imposition of the collective 
fine under sub- section (1) or by the order of apportionment, may, 
within the prescribed period, file a petition before the State 
Government or such other authority as that Government may specify in 
this behalf for being exempted from such fine or for modification of 
the order of apportionment:
Provided that no fee shall be charged for filing such petition.


<subsection><tid>1127325</tid>
<number>b</number>The State Government or the authority specified by it shall, 
after giving to the petitioner a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard, pass such order as it may think fit:
Provided that the amount of the fine exempted or reduced under 
this section shall not be realisable from any person, and the total 
fine imposed on the inhabitants of an area under sub- section (1) shall 
be deemed to have been reduced to that extent.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1583968</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), the 
State Government may exempt the victims of any offence punishable 
under this Act or any person who does not, in its opinion, fall within 
the category of persons specified in sub section (1), from the 
liability to pay the collective fine imposed under sub- section (1) or 
any portion thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1333232</tid>
<number>5</number>The portion of collective fine payable by any person 
 (including a Hindu undivided family) may be recovered in the manner 
provided by the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), for the 
recovery of fines imposed by a Court as if such portion were a fine 
imposed by a Magistrate.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1684843</tid>
<number> 11</number> Enhanced penalty on subsequent conviction. Whoever having 
already been convicted of an offence under this Act or of an abetment 
of such offence is again convicted of any such offence or abetment, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall, on convection, be punishable-
<section><tid>1333968</tid>
<number>a</number>for the second offence, with imprisonment for a term 
of not less than six months and not more than one year, and 
also

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 14, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  19- 11- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

with fine which shall be not less than two hundred rupees and 
not more than five hundred rupees;


</section>

<section><tid>583610</tid>
<number>b</number>for the third offence or any offence subsequent to the 
third offence, with imprisonment for a term of not less than 
one year and not more than two years, and also with fine 
which shall be not less than five hundred rupees and not more 
than one thousand rupees].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1679347</tid>
<number>12</number>Presumption by courts in certain cases. Where any act 
constituting an offence under this Act is committed in relation to a 
member of a Scheduled Caste <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, the court shall presume, 
unless the contrary is proved, that such act was committed on the 
ground of" untouchability".


</article>



<article><tid>987663</tid>
<number> 13</number> Limitation of jurisdiction of civil courts.
<section><tid>1235403</tid>
<number>1</number>No civil  
court shall entertain or continue any suit or proceeding or shall 
pass any decree or order or execute wholly or partially any decree or 
order if the claim involved in such suit or proceeding or if the 
passing of such decree or order or if such execution would in any way 
be contrary to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>68570</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall, in adjudicating any matter or executing any 
decree or order, recognise any custom or usage imposing any 
disability on any person on the ground of" untouchability".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1463835</tid>
<number> 14</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>842788</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing an  
offence under this Act is a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all 
due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>949576</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent of any 
director or manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" as defined in clause (24) of article 366 of the 
Constitution" omitted by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1076566</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1702092</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>698798</tid>
<number> 14A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>1743797</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or a State Government for anything which is in good faith 
done or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1529190</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or a State Government for any damage caused or 
likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1326557</tid>
<number> 15</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>594393</tid>
<number>1</number>Offences to be cognizable and triable summarily.  
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1973</year>, every offence punishable under this Act shall be 2 cognizable 
and every such offence, except where it is punishable with 
imprisonment for a minimum term exceeding three months, may be tried 
summarily by a Judicial Magistrate of the first class or in a metro- 
politan area by a Metropolitan Magistrate in accordance with the 
procedure specified in the said Code.

</section>

<section><tid>249710</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure <year>1973</year>, when any public servant is alleged to have committed 2 
the offence of abetment of an offence punishable under this Act, while 
acting or purporting to act in the discharge of his official duty, no 
court shall take cognizance of such offence of abetment except with 
the previous sanction-

<subsection><tid>1773062</tid>
<number>a</number>of the Central Government, in the case of a person 
employed in connection with the affairs of the Union; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693831</tid>
<number>b</number>of the State Government, in the case of a person 
employed in connection with the affairs of a State.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>331935</tid>
<number> 15A</number> 
<section><tid>464034</tid>
<number>1</number>Duty of State Government to ensure that the rights  
accruing from the abolition of" untouchability may be availed of by 
the concerned persons. Subject to such rules as the Central Government 
may make in this behalf, the State Government shall take such measures 
as may be necessary for ensuring that the rights arising from the 
abolition of" untouchability" are made available to, and are availed 
of by, the persons subjected to any disability arising out of 
" untouchability".

</section>

<section><tid>1963925</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the provisions of sub- section (1), such measures may include-

<subsection><tid>1838259</tid>
<number>i</number>the provision of adequate facilities, including legal 
aid, to the persons subjected to any disability arising out 
of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692c</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 17, ibid., for s. 15 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

" untouchability" to enable them to avail themselves of such 
rights;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1914520</tid>
<number>ii</number>the appointment of officers for initiating or 
exercising supervision over prosecutions for the 
contravention of the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>775378</tid>
<number>iii</number>the setting up of special courts for the trial of 
offences under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193188</tid>
<number>iv</number>the setting up of Committees at such appropriate levels 
as the State Government may think fit to assist the State 
Government in formulating or implementing such measures;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>233688</tid>
<number>v</number>provision for a periodic survey of the working of the 
provisions of this Act with a view to suggesting measures for 
the better implementation of the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1794974</tid>
<number>vi</number>the identification of the areas where persons are under 
any disability arising out of" untouchability" and adoption 
of such measures as would ensure the removal of such 
disability from such areas.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1949144</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall take such steps as may be 
necessary to co- ordinate the measures taken by the State Governments 
under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1729150</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall, every year, place on the Table 
of each House of Parliament, a report on the measures taken by itself 
and by the State Governments in pursuance of the provisions of this 
section.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>440981</tid>
<number>16</number>Act to override other laws. Save as otherwise expressly 
provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other 
law for the time being in force, or any custom or usage or any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any such law or any decree or 
order of any court or other authority.
</article>



<article><tid>317355</tid>
<number>16A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Probation of Offenders Act, <year>1958</year>, not to apply to persons 
above the age of fourteen years. The provisions of the Probation of 
Offenders Act, <year>1958</year> (20 of <year>1958</year>), shall not apply to any person above 
the age of fourteen years who is found guilty of having committed any 
offence punishable under this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>1365456</tid>
<number> 16B</number> 
<section><tid>1626939</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Ins. by Act 106 of <year>1976</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 19- 11- <year>1976</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>696285</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1339347</tid>
<number>17</number>Repeal. The enactments specified in the Schedule are hereby 
repealed to the extent to which they or any of the provisions 
contained therein correspond or are repugnant to this Act or to any of 
the provisions contained therein.

</article>



 </act>