<act><title>THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY 
  (OBLIGATIONS OF INSURERS 
  TO RURAL OR SOCIAL SECTORS) 
REGULATIONS, 20021</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Obligations of Insurers to Rural or Social Sectors) Regulations, 2002. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force from the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Authority means the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority established under the provisions of section 3 of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999); 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> Rural Sector means the places or areas classified as rural' while conducting the latest decennial population census (Census of India);] 
 </section><section><number>d</number> social sector includes unorganized sector, informal sector, economically vulnerable or backward classes and other categories of persons, both in rural and urban areas; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> unorganized sector includes self-employed workers such as agricultural labourers, bidi workers, brick kiln workers, carpenters, cobblers, construction workers, fishermen, hamals, handicraft artisans, handloom and khadi workers, lady tailors, leather and tannery workers, papad makers, powerloom workers, physically handicapped self-employed persons, primary milk producers, rickshaw pullers, safai karmacharis, salt growers,  
    seri culture workers, sugarcane cutters, tendu leaf collectors, toddy tappers, vegetable vendors, washerwomen, working women in hills, or such other categories of persons; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> economically vulnerable or backward classes means persons who live below the poverty line; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> other categories of persons includes persons with disability as defined in the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996) and who may not be gainfully employed; and also includes guardians who need insurance to protect spastic persons or persons with disability; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> informal sector includes small scale, self-employed workers typically at a low level of organization and technology, with the primary objective of generating employment and income, with heterogeneous activities like retail trade, transport, repair and maintenance, construction, personal and domestic services and manufacturing, with the work mostly labour intensive, having often unwritten and informal employer-employee relationship; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> all words and expressions used herein and not defined herein but defined in the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938), or in the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts. 
</section>








 
 <section><number>i</number> Cultivators; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Agricultural labourers; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Workers in livestock, forestry, fishing, hunting and plantations, orchards and allied activities;'. 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Obligations. </title>Every insurer, who begins to carry or insurance business after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999), shall, for the purposes of sections 32B and 32C of the Act, ensure that he undertakes the following obligations, during the first five financial years, pertaining to the persons in 
 
 <section><number>a</number> rural sector, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> in respect of a life insurer, 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>I</number> seven per cent. in the first financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>II</number> nine per cent. in the second financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>III</number> twelve per cent. in the third financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>IV</number> fourteen per cent. in the fourth financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>V</number> sixteen per cent. in the fifth financial year, of total policies written direct in that year; 
</subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> in respect of a general insurer, 
 
 
</subsection><subsection><number>I</number> two per cent. in the first financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>II</number> three per cent. in the second financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>III</number> five per cent. thereafter, of total gross premium income written direct in that year. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> social sector, in respect of all insurers, 
 
 <subsection><number>I</number> five thousand lives in the first financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>II</number> seven thousand five hundred lives in the second financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>III</number> ten thousand lives in the third financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>IV</number> fifteen thousand lives in the fourth financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>V</number> twenty thousand lives in the fifth financial year: 
</subsection>
</section>
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Provided that in cases where an insurance company commences operations in the second half of the financial year and is in operations for less than six months as at 31st March of the relevant financial year, 
<section><number>i</number> no rural or social sector obligations shall be applicable for the said period, and (ii) the annual obligations as indicated in the Regulations shall be reckoned from the next financial year which shall be considered as the first year of operations for the purpose of compliance. In cases where an insurance company commences operations in the first half of the financial year, the applicable obligations for the first year shall be 50 per cent of the obligations as specified in these Regulations:] 
 Provided further that, in case of a general insurer, the obligations specified shall include insurance for crops. 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> Obligation in the Sixth Financial Year. </title>Every insurer, who begins to carry on insurance business after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (4 of 1999), shall for the purposes of sections 32B and 32C of the Act, ensure that he undertakes the following obligations, during the Sixth Financial year of operations: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> In respect of life insurers, eighteen per cent of the total policies written direct shall be in the rural sector, 
 </section><section><number>b</number> In respect of the non-life insurers, five per cent of the total gross premium income written direct shall be in the rural sector, and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> In respect of all insurers twenty-five thousand new lives shall be covered in the social sector and the policies should be in force on 31st March of the year.] 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>3B</number> Obligations after the Sixth Financial year. </title>
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> Rural Sector: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> in respect of a life insurer, 
 
 
 of the total policies written direct in that year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> eighteen per cent in the seventh financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> nineteen per cent in the eighth and ninth financial years; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> twenty per cent in the tenth financial year. 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> in respect of a general insurer. 
 
 
 of the total gross premium income written direct in that year. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> five per cent in the seventh financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> six per cent in the eighth financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> seven per cent in the ninth and tenth financial year; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Social sector 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> in respect of all insurers, 
 
 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> twenty-five thousand lives in the seventh financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> thirty-five thousand lives in the eighth financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> forty-five thousand lives in the ninth financial year; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>IV</number> fifty-five thousand lives in the tenth financial year. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The obligations of the insurers towards the rural and social sectors for the tenth financial year shall also be applicable in respect of the financial years thereafter.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Obligations of existing insurers. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The obligations of existing insurers as on the date of commencement of IRDA Act shall be decided by the Authority after consultation with them and the quantum of insurance business to be done shall not be less than what has been recorded by them for the accounting year ended 31st March, 2002. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority shall review such quantum of insurance business periodically and give directions to the insurers for achieving the specified targets. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number>Obligations of the existing insurers for the financial years 2007-08 to 2009-10. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The obligations of the existing insurers as on the date of the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 towards the rural and social sectors from the financial year 2007-08 to the financial year 2009-10 are as under: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Life Insurance Corporation of India , 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Rural Sector 
 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> twenty-four per cent in the financial year 2007-08, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> twenty-five per cent in the financial years 2008-09 and 2009-10, of the total policies written direct in that year; 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Social Sector 
 
 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> Twenty lakh lives in the financial years 2007-08, 2008-09 and 2009-10. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> General Insurers, 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Rural Sector, 
 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> six per cent in the financial year 2007-08, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> seven per cent in the financial years 2008-09 and 2009-10. 
 of the total gross premium income written direct in that year; 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Social Sector, 
 
 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>I</number> for the financial year 2007-08 the average of the number of lives covered by the respective insurer in the social sector from the financial years 2002-03 to 2004-05 or 5.50 lakh lives, whichever is higher; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> for the financial year 2008-09, the obligations of the existing insurers shall increase by 10 per cent over the number of persons prescribed for the financial year 2007-08; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> for the financial year 2009-10, the obligations of the existing insurers shall increase by 10 per cent over the number of persons prescribed for the financial year 2008-09. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The obligations of the insurers, towards the rural and the social sectors for the financial year 2009-10 shall also be applicable in the financial years thereafter.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>5</number>Notes applicable to Regulations 3, 3A, 3B, 4 and 4A. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The term lives' referred to in Regulations 3, 3A, 3B and 4A in respect of all insurers refers to human lives insured as at the end of each financial year. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Re-insurance premium shall not be included while calculating the obligations of the insurers in respect of the rural and social sectors. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Authority may prescribe or revise the obligations as specified in these Regulations from time to time.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6</number> Compliance. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of these Regulations, compliance with the obligations towards the rural sector in respect of both general and life companies shall be based on the sale of products conforming to the proviso that all such contracts meet the stipulation as to the minimum amount of cover as laid down in Schedules I and II of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Micro Insurance) Regulations, 2005. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of these Regulations, compliance with the obligations towards the social sector in respect of both general and life companies shall be based on the sale of products conforming to the proviso that all such contracts meet the stipulations as to the cover laid down in Schedules I and II of Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Micro Insurance) Regulations, 2005.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>7</number> Submission of returns. </title>Every insurer shall submit a return, as part of the financial return to be submitted under the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Preparation of Financial Statements and Auditors Report of Insurance Companies) Regulations, 2002, the rural and social sector obligations specified under these regulations and disclose the level of compliance achieved during the said year. Such reporting shall form part of the Notes to the Accounts'.] 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Notification F. No. IRDA/Reg./3/2004, dated 30th July, 2004, for 
  clause (c) (w.e.f. 5-8-2004). Clause (c), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./2/43/2008, dated 25th January, 2008, for the first proviso (w.e.f. 29-1-2008). The first proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Third proviso omitted by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).The proviso, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./4/2005/37, dated 26th December, 2005 (w.e.f. 26-10-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>	Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>	Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>	Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/42/2008, dated 3rd January, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-2-2008).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>