<act><tid>281378</tid>
<title>THE UNION TERRITORIES TAXATION LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 73 OF <footcitenum>1971</footcitenum>
[ 24th December, <year>1971</year>]

An Act further to amend certain taxation laws in the Union 
territories.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>739227</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1083525</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Union Territories Taxation Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1678991</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to all the Union Territories;

</section>

<section><tid>955804</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>103527</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of certain taxation laws. The taxation laws as in 
force in each of the Union Territories mentioned in the Schedule, 
shall have effect subject to the amendments specified therein:
Provided that any such Amendment of a taxation law relating to 
the imposition of tax on the sale or purchase of goods declared to be 
of special importance under section 14 of the Central Sales Tax 
Act, <year>1956</year>, (74 of <year>1956</year>) shall be subject to the condition that in no 
case the amount of tax together with surcharge payable in respect 
thereof under the said taxation law shall exceed the tax calculated at 
the maximum rate prescribed under clause (a) of section 15 of the said 
Act.



</article>



<article><tid>338732</tid>
<number>3</number>Levy and collection of additional duty, tax or surcharge. Save 
as otherwise Provided, the additional duty or tax or surcharge 
leviable or chargeable under the relevant taxation law, amended as 
aforesaid, shall be levied and collected in the same manner as the 
duty or tax is levied and collected under the said taxation law and 
the provisions, of that taxation law and the rules thereunder, as far 
as may be applicable in this behalf, shall apply accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1314</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January, <year>1972</year>, see Notification No. GSR <year>1963</year>, dated 27th 
December <year>1971</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1971</year>, Extraordinary, p. 1419.

Repealed in its application to the union territories of Delhi, 
Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands, 
Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Goa, Daman and Diu, Pondicherry and 
Chandigarh, by Act 14 of <year>1973</year> (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1973</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>