<act><tid>1582229</tid>
<title>THE DAMODAR VALLEY CORPORATION ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>1948</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 27th March, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment and regulation of a 
Corporation for the development of the Damodar Valley in the Provinces 
of Bihar and West Bengal.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the establishment and 
regulation of a Corporation for the development of the Damodar Valley 
in the Provinces of Bihar and West Bengal:

AND WHEREAS in pursuance of section 103 of the Government of 
India Act, <year>1935</year>, (26 Geo. 5, c. 2.) resolutions have been passed by 
all the Chambers of the Provincial Legislatures of the said Provinces 
to the effect that certain matters dealt with in this Act which are 
enumerated in the Provincial Legislative List should be regulated in 
those Provinces by Act of the Dominion Legislature;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-

PART

INTRODUCTORY

PART I

INTRODUCTORY





<article><tid>1398497</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. (2) This Act may be 
called the Damodar Valley Corporation Act, <year>1948</year>.
<section><tid>1380010</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the States of Bihar and West Bengal.

</section>

<section><tid>206702</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>224979</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation. In this Act, unless there is anything 
repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>436150</tid>
<number>1</number>" Corporation" means the Damodar Valley Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>1642406</tid>
<number>2</number>" Damodar Valley" includes the basin of the Damodar 
river and its tributaries;

</section>

<section><tid>188496</tid>
<number>3</number>" member" means a member of the Corporation and includes 
the Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>713512</tid>
<number>4</number>" participating Governments" means the Central 
Government, the State Government of Bihar and the State 
Government of West Bengal;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Amended in west Bengal by WB Act 3 of <year>1956</year>. 
2.  2nd April, <year>1948</year>, see Gazette of India, Pt. I, p. 391.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1407113</tid>
<number>5</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
section 59;

</section>

<section><tid>675979</tid>
<number>6</number>" State Government" means the Government of Bihar or as 
the case may be of West Bengal, and" State Government" 
means the Governments of Bihar and West Bengal;

</section>

<section><tid>64312</tid>
<number>7</number>" regulations" means the regulations made by the 
Corporation under section 60.
PART

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION

PART II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476716</tid>
<number> 3</number> Incorporation.
<section><tid>152216</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the  
Central Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, 
appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a Corporation by 
the name of the Damodar Valley Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>427155</tid>
<number>2</number>The said Corporation shall be a body corporate having 
perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue 
and be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1412684</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of the Corporation.
<section><tid>219711</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall  
consist of a Chairman and two other members appointed by the Central 
Government after consultation with the State Governments.

</section>

<section><tid>313727</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall be disqualified for being appointed, or for 
continuing as, a member of the Corporation--

<subsection><tid>1751685</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is a member of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Parliament] or any State 
Legislature; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1778777</tid>
<number>b</number>if he has, directly or indirectly, any interest in a 
subsisting contract made with, or in any work being 
done for, the Corporation except as a shareholder 
 (other than a director) in an incorporated company 
provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall 
disclose to the Government the nature and extent of 
shares held by him in such Company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>616266</tid>
<number>3</number>No act or proceeding of the Corporation shall be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any 
defect in the appointment of a member thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1012136</tid>
<number> 5</number> Conditions of service of members. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 7th July <year>1948</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1948</year>, Pt. I, p. 831. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Central". 
3. Sub- section (1) omitted by Act 59 of <year>1957</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<section><tid>1709288</tid>
<number>2</number>The remuneration and other conditions of service of the 
members shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529391</tid>
<number> 6</number> Appointment of officers and servants.
<section><tid>1971747</tid>
<number>1</number>The secretary and  
the financial adviser of the Corporation shall be appointed by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1407405</tid>
<number>2</number>The secretary shall be the chief executive officer of the 
corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>866455</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation may appoint such other officers and servants 
as it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its 
functions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>895899</tid>
<number> 7</number> Conditions of service of officers and servants. The pay and 
other conditions of service of the officers and servants of the 
Corporation shall-
<section><tid>893573</tid>
<number>a</number>as respects the secretary and financial adviser, be 
such as may be prescribed; and

</section>

<section><tid>720738</tid>
<number>b</number>as respects the other officers and servants, be such as 
may be determined by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1564807</tid>
<number>8</number>Functions and duties of the financial adviser. The functions 
and duties of the financial adviser shall be such as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>960636</tid>
<number>9</number>General disqualification of all officers and servants. No 
person who has directly or indirectly, by himself or his partner or 
agent, any share or interest in any contract, by or on behalf of the 
Corporation, or in any employment under, by or on behalf of the 
Corporation otherwise than as an officer or servant thereof, shall 
become or remain an officer or servant of the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1382624</tid>
<number>10</number>Appointment of Advisory Committee. Subject to any rules made 
under section 59 the Corporation may from time to time appoint one or 
more Advisory Committees for the purpose of securing the efficient 
discharge of the functions of the Corporation, and in particular for 
the purpose of securing that those functions are exercised with due 
regard to the circumstances and requirements of particular local 
areas.
PART

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE CORPORATION

PART III

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE CORPORATION

General



</article>



<article><tid>1668342</tid>
<number> 11</number> Limits of Damodar Valley and area of operations.
<section><tid>956892</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify the limits of the Damodar Valley.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1610809</tid>
<number>2</number>The corporation shall carry out all or any of its functions 
and exercise all or any of its powers within the Damodar Valley.

</section>

<section><tid>719453</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, after consultation with the State 
Governments by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the 
Corporation shall carry out such function and exercise such power in 
such other area as may be specified therein and the area so specified 
shall be called the" area of operation" of the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1571981</tid>
<number> 12</number> Functions of the Corporation. The functions of the 
Corporation shall be--
<section><tid>1613607</tid>
<number>a</number>the promotion and operation of schemes for the 
generation, water- supply and drainage,

</section>

<section><tid>951173</tid>
<number>b</number>the promotion and operation of schemes for the 
generation, transmission and distribution of electrical 
energy, both hydro- electric and thermal,

</section>

<section><tid>1845528</tid>
<number>c</number>the promotion and operation of schemes for flood 
control in the Damodar river and its tributaries and 
the channels, if any, excavated by the Corporation in 
connection with the scheme and for the improvement of 
flow conditions in the Hooghly river,

</section>

<section><tid>1982606</tid>
<number>d</number>the promotion and control of navigation in the Damodar 
river and its tributaries and channels, if any,

</section>

<section><tid>1836638</tid>
<number>e</number>the promotion of afforestation and control of soil 
erosion in the Damodar Valley, and

</section>

<section><tid>1351414</tid>
<number>f</number>the promotion of public health and the agricultural, 
industrial, economic and general well- being in the 
Damodar Valley and its area of operation.
Irrigation and water- supply




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252765</tid>
<number>13</number>Provision for irrigation and water- supply. The Corporation 
may, with the approval of the State Government concerned which shall 
not be unreasonably withheld, construct canals and distributaries and 
maintain and operate them:
Provided that the State Government may, after giving notice and 
subject to the payment of fair compensation, take over the maintenance 
and operation of any such canal or distributary.



</article>



<article><tid>1599222</tid>
<number> 14</number> Rates for supply of water for irrigation.
<section><tid>1382519</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation  
may, after consultation with the State Government concerned, determine 
and levy rates for the bulk supply of water to that Government for 
irrigation, and fix the minimum quantity of water which shall be made 
available for such purpose.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1950213</tid>
<number>2</number>The rates at which such water shall be supplied by the State 
Government to the cultivators and other consumers shall be fixed by 
that Government after consultation with the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>295269</tid>
<number>15</number>Rates for supply of water for industrial and domestic 
purposes. The Corporation may determine and levy rates for bulk supply 
and retail distribution of water for industrial and domestic purposes 
and specify the manner of recovery of such rates.


</article>



<article><tid>769817</tid>
<number>16</number>Supply of water to those whose supply has been stopped or 
reduced. If, with a view to operating its schemes, the Corporation has 
stopped or reduced the supply of water to any person for agricultural, 
industrial or domestic purposes which such person was, prior to such 
stoppage or reduction, enjoying by virtue of any prescriptive right, 
the Corporation shall arrange such supply of water on the same terms 
as before.


</article>



<article><tid>227043</tid>
<number>17</number>Construction of dam, etc., prohibited except with the 
approval of the Corporation. Save as otherwise prescribed, no person 
shall construct, operate or maintain in the Damodar Valley any dam or 
other work or any installation for the extraction of water without the 
consent of the Corporation.
Supply and generation of electrical energy



</article>



<article><tid>874204</tid>
<number> 18</number> Supply and generation of electrical energy. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Indian Electricity Act, <year>1910</year> (9 of <year>1910</year>), or 
any licence granted thereunder--
<section><tid>1528267</tid>
<number>i</number>No person shall without the permission of the 
Corporation--

<subsection><tid>1480652</tid>
<number>a</number>sell electrical energy to any consumer in 
the Damodar Valley where the energy is taken by 
the consumer at a pressure of 30, 000 volts or 
more;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82492</tid>
<number>b</number>transmit electrical energy in the Damodar 
Valley at a pressure of 30, 000 volts or more;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1018781</tid>
<number>c</number>generate any electrical energy at an 
installation having an aggregate capacity of more 
than 10, 000 kilowatts in any part of the Damodar 
Valley lying to the north of the straight line 
drawn east to west passing through a point at 
latitude twenty- two degrees, fourteen minutes and 
forty- seven seconds and longitude eighty- seven 
degrees, fifty- one minutes and forty- two seconds 
except such portion of the municipal area of 
Burdwan as may lie to the north of such straight 
line:
Provided that nothing in sub- clause (c) shall 
apply to any person who was, at the commencement 
of this Act, generating electrical energy at an 
installation having


<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

an aggregate capacity of more than 10, 000 
kilowatts, so long as the capacity of such 
installation is not increased:

Provided further that nothing in sub- clause 
 (c) shall apply to the power station installation 
of the fertiliser factory at Sindri having an 
aggregate capacity of 80, 000 kilowatts so long as 
the capacity of such installation is not increased 
beyond 80, 000 kilowatts.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>818924</tid>
<number>ii</number>The Corporation may sell electrical energy to any 
consumer in the Damodar Valley but no such sale shall, 
except with the permission of the State Government 
concerned, be made to any consumer requiring supply at 
a pressure of less than 30, 000 volts.

</section>

<section><tid>1092090</tid>
<number>iii</number>The Corporation may, with the permission of the State 
Government concerned, extend its transmission system to 
any area beyond the Damodar Valley and sell electrical 
energy in such area.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>499574</tid>
<number> 19</number> Effect on existing licences.
<section><tid>285237</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any licence granted  
under the Indian Electricity Act, <year>1910</year> (9 of <year>1910</year>), becomes 
inoperative wholly or partly by virtue of the provisions of section 
18, the licence shall be deemed to have been revoked or modified so as 
to be consistent with those provisions.

</section>

<section><tid>773822</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a licence is deemed to have been revoked under 
sub- section (1) the Corporation shall purchase the undertaking of the 
licencee, and where a licence is modified under that sub- section, the 
Corporation shall, at the option of the licensee, either purchase the 
undertaking or pay fair compensation to the licensee.

</section>

<section><tid>670293</tid>
<number>3</number>The purchase price or the amount of compensation payable by 
the corporation under sub- section (2) shall be such as may be agreed 
to between the Corporation and the licensee or, in the event of 
disagreement, as may be determined by arbitration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>339490</tid>
<number>20</number>Charges for supply of electrical energy. The Corporation 
shall fix the schedule of charges for the supply of electrical energy, 
including the rates for bulk supply and retail distribution, and 
specify the manner of recovery of such charges:
Provided that the Corporation may in any contract for bulk supply 
of electrical energy impose such terms and conditions including a 
retail rate schedule as it may deem necessary or desirable to 
encourage the use of electrical energy.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Other activities



</article>



<article><tid>333306</tid>
<number> 21</number> Other activities of the Corporation.
<section><tid>151341</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation may  
establish, maintain and operate laboratories, experimental and 
research stations and farms for conducting experiments and research 
for--

<subsection><tid>979877</tid>
<number>a</number>utilising the water, electrical energy and other 
resources in the most economical manner for the 
development of the Damodar Valley,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1580880</tid>
<number>b</number>determining the effect of its operations on the flow 
conditions in the Hooghly river,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1214849</tid>
<number>c</number>making improvements in navigation conditions in the 
port of Calcutta, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>506418</tid>
<number>d</number>carrying out any other function specified under section 
12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>793156</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation may set up its own planning, designing, 
construction and operating agencies, or make arrangements therefor 
with the participating Governments, local authorities, educational and 
research institutions or any person carrying on the business of an 
architect, an engineer or a contractor.
Powers




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1111376</tid>
<number> 22</number> General powers of the Corporation.
<section><tid>1236361</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall  
have the power to do anything which may be necessary or expedient for 
the purposes of carrying out its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>988350</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provision, such power shall include the power--

<subsection><tid>1346611</tid>
<number>i</number>to acquire and hold such movable and immovable property 
as it may deem necessary and to lease, sell or 
otherwise transfer any such property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1826813</tid>
<number>ii</number>to construct or cause to be constructed such dams, 
barrages, reservoirs, power houses, power structures, 
electrical transmission lines and sub- stations, 
navigation works, irrigation, navigation and drainage 
canals and such other works and structures as may be 
required;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>442319</tid>
<number>iii</number>to prevent pollution of any water under its control 
and to take all measures to prevent discharges 
into such water effluents which are harmful to 
water supply, irrigation, public health or fish life;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>740663</tid>
<number>iv</number>to stock its reservoirs or water courses with fish and 
to regulate or prohibit taking out fish from the water 
under its control;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1365586</tid>
<number>v</number>to undertake resettlement of the population displaced 
by the dams, acquisition of land for reservoirs and 
protection of watersheds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1255287</tid>
<number>vi</number>to aid in the establishment of co- operative societies 
and other organisations for the better use of 
facilities made available by the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>240694</tid>
<number>vii</number>to undertake measures for the prevention of malaria.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1390403</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power to close roads and open spaces.
<section><tid>335324</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation  
may, after giving notice to the persons concerned or to the public 
generally,--

<subsection><tid>494419</tid>
<number>a</number>turn, divert or discontinue the public use of, or 
permanently close, any road or any part thereof, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>333826</tid>
<number>b</number>discontinue the public use of, or permanently close, 
any open space or any part thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>481341</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever the Corporation discontinues the public use of, or 
permanently closes, any road or open space the Corporation shall pay 
reasonable compensation to every person--

<subsection><tid>796903</tid>
<number>a</number>who was entitled, otherwise than as a licensee, to use 
such road or open space or part thereof as a means of 
access, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>701891</tid>
<number>b</number>Whose immovable property was receiving air and light on 
account of such open space or part,
and who has suffered damage--


<subsubsection><tid>1557384</tid>
<number>i</number>in any case falling under clause (a) from such 
discontinuance or closure and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>827780</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any case falling under clause (b) from the use to 
which the Corporation has put such open space or part.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>128406</tid>
<number>3</number>In determining the compensation payable to any person under 
sub- section (2), the Corporation may take into consideration any 
benefit accruing to such person from the construction, provision or 
improvement of any other road, or open space at or about the same time 
that the road or open space or part thereof, on account of which the 
compensation is to be paid, is discontinued or closed.

</section>

<section><tid>1423984</tid>
<number>4</number>When any road or open space or any part thereof is 
permanently closed under sub- section (1), the Corporation may sell or 
leave such part of it as is not required for its purposes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>19192</tid>
<number> 24</number> Powers under certain other enactments.
<section><tid>582172</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in the Acts specified in column one of Part I of 
the Schedule, the Corporation may carry out all or any of the 
functions and exercise all or any of the powers

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of a State Government in the Damodar Valley under the provisions of 
such Acts specified in column two thereof against each item of column 
one.


</section>

<section><tid>959642</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Acts specified in 
column one of Part II of the Schedule, any officer authorized by the 
Corporation may carry out all or any of the functions and exercise all 
or any of the powers of a Canal Officer, Collector, or Forest Officer, 
as the case may be, in the Damodar Valley under the provisions of such 
Acts specified in column two thereof against each item of column one.
Co- operation and avoidance of submersion




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1147395</tid>
<number>25</number>Co- operation with other authorities to minimise inconvenience 
caused by submersion. The Corporation shall co- operate with the 
participating Governments, railway authorities and local authorities 
and bodies, with a view to minimising the inconvenience likely to be 
caused by the submersion of roads and communications and shall bear 
the cost of any realignment thereof or resettlement of any population 
rendered necessary by such submersion.


</article>



<article><tid>411086</tid>
<number>26</number>Submersion of coal mines to be avoided by the Corporation. 
The Corporation shall make every endeavour to avoid submersion of coal 
or mineral deposits and shall co- operate with the coal mining industry 
and the bodies set up by the participating Governments to ensure the 
maintenance of supplies of sand for stowing purposes in coal mines and 
in other ways to minimise the inconvenience to the coal mining 
industry.
PART

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

PART IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT



</article>



<article><tid>1362585</tid>
<number>27</number>Expenditure till the Corporation is established. All 
expenditure incurred by the Central Government for and in connection 
with the establishment of the Corporation up to the date of its 
establishment shall be treated as the capital provided by the Central 
Government to the Corporation and such capital shall be adjusted 
between the participating Governments in accordance with the 
provisions of sections 30 to 36.


</article>



<article><tid>1998373</tid>
<number>28</number>Vetting of property in the Corporation. All property acquired 
and works constructed for the purposes of the Damodar Valley scheme 
before the establishment of the Corporation shall vest in the 
Corporation and all income derived and expenses incurred in this 
behalf shall be brought into the books of the Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1598252</tid>
<number> 29</number> Fund of the Corporation.
<section><tid>806989</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall have its  
own fund and all receipts of the Corporation shall be carried thereto 
and all payments by the Corporation shall be made therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>1649539</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as otherwise directed by the Central Government, all 
moneys belonging to that fund shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank 
of India or the Agents of the Reserve Bank of India or invested in 
such securities as may be approved by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>47517</tid>
<number>30</number>Liabilities of participating Governments to provide capital 
to the Corporation. The participating Governments shall, as 
hereinafter specified, provide the entire capital required by the 
Corporation for the completion of any project undertaken by it.


</article>



<article><tid>686490</tid>
<number>31</number>Payment by participating Government on specified date. Each 
participating Government shall provide its share of the capital on the 
dates specified by the Corporation and if any Government fails to 
provide such share on such dates the Corporation may raise loan to 
make up the deficit at the cost of the Government concerned.


</article>



<article><tid>1132725</tid>
<number>32</number>Expenditure on objects other than irrigation, power and flood 
control. The Corporation shall have power to spend such sums as it 
thinks fit on objects authorized under this Act other than irrigation, 
power and flood control and such sums shall be treated as common 
expenditure payable out of the fund of the Corporation before 
allocation under section 32


</article>



<article><tid>194366</tid>
<number> 33</number> Allocation of expenditure chargeable to project on main 
objects. The total capital expenditure chargeable to a project shall 
be allocated between the three main objects, namely, irrigation, power 
and flood control as follows, namely:-
<section><tid>585545</tid>
<number>1</number>expenditure solely attributable to any of these 
objects, including a proportionate share of overhead 
and general charges, shall be charged to that object, 
and

</section>

<section><tid>364531</tid>
<number>2</number>expenditure common to two or more of the said objects, 
including a proportionate share of overhead and general 
charges, shall be allocated to each of such objects in 
proportion to the expenditure which, according to the 
estimates of the Corporation, would have been incurred 
in constructing a separate structure solely for that 
object, less any amount determined under clause (1) in 
respect of that object.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1806212</tid>
<number> 34</number> Capital allocated to irrigation. The total amount of capital 
allocated to irrigation shall be shared between the State Governments 
as follows, namely:-
<section><tid>1700931</tid>
<number>1</number>the Government concerned shall be responsible for 
capital cost of the works constructed exclusively for 
irrigation in its State; and

</section>

<section><tid>410811</tid>
<number>2</number>the balance of capital cost under irrigation for both 
the States of Bihar and West Bengal shall be shared by 
the State Governments in the proportion to their 
guaranteed annual off- takes of water for agricultural 
purposes:
Provided that the divisible capital cost 
under this clause shall be provisionally shared 
between them in accordance with their previously 
declared intentions regarding their respective 
guaranteed off- takes and any payments made 
accordingly shall be adjusted after the 
determination of the guaranteed off- takes.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378293</tid>
<number>35</number>Capital allocated to power. The total amount of capital 
allocated to power shall be shared equally between the three 
participating Governments.


</article>



<article><tid>1381345</tid>
<number>36</number>Capital allocated to flood control. The total amount of 
capital up to fourteen crores of rupees allocated to flood control 
shall be shared equally between the Central Government and the 
Government of West Bengal and any amount in excess thereof shall be 
the liability of the Government of West Bengal.


</article>



<article><tid>1385751</tid>
<number> 37</number> Disposal of profits and deficits.
<section><tid>362787</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2) of section 40, the net profit, if any, 
attributable to each of the three main objects, namely, irrigation, 
power and flood control, shall be credited to the participating 
Governments in proportion to their respective shares in the total 
capital cost attributed to that object.

</section>

<section><tid>365967</tid>
<number>2</number>The net deficit, if any, in respect of any of the objects 
shall be made good by the Governments concerned in the proportion 
specified in sub- section (1):
Provided that the net deficit in respect of flood control shall 
be made good entirely by the Government of West Bengal and the Central 
Government shall have no share in such deficit.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>340553</tid>
<number>38</number>Payment of interest. The Corporation shall pay interest on 
the amount of capital provided by each participating Government at 
such rate as may, from time to time, be fixed by the Central 
Government and such interest shall be deemed to be part of the 
expenditure of the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1750325</tid>
<number>39</number>Interest charge and other expenses to be added to and 
receipts taken for reduction of capital cost. For a period, not 
exceeding fifteen years, from the establishment of the Corporation, if 
the Corporation runs in deficit, the interest

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

charges and all other expenditure shall be added to the capital cost 
and all receipts shall be taken in reduction of such capital cost.



</article>



<article><tid>841427</tid>
<number> 40</number> Provision for depreciation and reserve and other funds.
<section><tid>854434</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall make provision for depreciation and for reserve 
and other funds at such rates and on such terms as may be specified by 
the Auditor- General of India in consultation with the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>687433</tid>
<number>2</number>The net profit for the purposes of section 37 shall be 
determined after such provision has been made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>642293</tid>
<number>41</number>Corporation' s share in betterment levy by State Governments. 
In the event of any betterment levy being imposed by a State 
Government, the proportionate proceeds thereof in so far as they are 
attributable to the operations of the corporation shall be credited to 
the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1666691</tid>
<number> 42</number> Borrowing of money.
<section><tid>1723028</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation may, with the  
approval of the Central Government, borrow money in the open market or 
otherwise for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>387254</tid>
<number> 43</number> Liability to pay Central taxes.
<section><tid>615899</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall be  
liable to pay any taxes on income levied by the Central Government in 
the same manner and to the same extent as a company.

</section>

<section><tid>541707</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Governments shall not be entitled to any refund of 
any such taxes paid by the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1521480</tid>
<number> 44</number> Budget.
<section><tid>1798390</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation, in consultation with the  
financial adviser, shall in October each year prepare in such form as 
may be prescribed a budget for the next financial year showing the 
estimated receipts and expenditure and the amounts which would be 
required from each of the three participating Governments during that 
financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>69133</tid>
<number>2</number>Printed copies of the budget shall be made available to each 
of the three participating Governments by the 15th day of November 
each year.

</section>

<section><tid>1483844</tid>
<number>3</number>The budget shall be laid before <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Parliament] and the State 
Legislatures concerned as soon as may be after it is prepared.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>767974</tid>
<number> 45</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1591434</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall prepare, in such  
from as may be prescribed, an annual report within six months after 
the end of each
<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Central".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


financial year giving a true and faithful account of its activities 
during the previous financial year, with particular reference to--


<subsection><tid>810159</tid>
<number>i</number>irrigation; 
 (ii) water supply; 
 (iii) electrical energy; 
 (iv) flood control; 
 (v) navigation; 
 (vi) afforestation; 
 (vii) soil erosion; 
 (viii) use of lands; 
 (ix) resettlement of displaced population; 
 (x) sanitation and public health measures; and 
 (xi) economic and social welfare of the people.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>540714</tid>
<number>2</number>The annual report shall also give a true and faithful account 
of the income and expenditure during the previous financial year, the 
net amounts attributable to each of the three main objects and the 
distribution of the capital cost between the three participating 
Governments and show the progressive totals from the inception of the 
Corporation and the up- to- date financial results.

</section>

<section><tid>285562</tid>
<number>3</number>The payments provisionally made by each of the three 
participating Governments on the basis of the budget estimates shall 
be adjusted as soon as possible in accordance with the allocation made 
in the annual report.

</section>

<section><tid>40484</tid>
<number>4</number>Printed copies of the annual report shall be made available 
to each of the three participating Governments by the 15th day of 
October each year.

</section>

<section><tid>842308</tid>
<number>5</number>The annual report shall be laid before <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Parliament] and the 
State Legislatures concerned as soon as may be after it is prepared.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>325260</tid>
<number> 46</number> Other annual financial statements.
<section><tid>960196</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall  
also prepare such other annual financial statements in such form and 
by such dates as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1499746</tid>
<number>2</number>Printed copies of each such annual financial statement shall 
be made available to each of the three participating Governments by 
such date as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1659269</tid>
<number>47</number>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Corporation shall be 
maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the 
Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Central".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


PART

MISCELLANEOUS

PART V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>341746</tid>
<number> 48</number> Directions by the Central Government.
<section><tid>991713</tid>
<number>1</number>In discharge of its  
functions the Corporation shall be guided by such instructions on 
questions of policy as may be given to it by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>367942</tid>
<number>2</number>If any dispute arises between the Central Government and the 
Corporation as to whether a question is or is not a question of 
policy, the decision of the Central Government shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1330714</tid>
<number> 49</number> Disputes between the Corporation and Governments.
<section><tid>802461</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise expressly provided in this Act, any dispute between the 
Corporation and any participating Government regarding any matter 
covered by this Act or touching or arising out of it shall be referred 
to an arbitrator who shall be appointed by the Chief Justice of India.

</section>

<section><tid>471730</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on 
the parties.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1418963</tid>
<number>50</number>Compulsory acquisition of land for the Corporation. Any land 
required by the Corporation for carrying out its functions under this 
Act shall be deemed to be needed to be needed for a public purpose and 
such land shall be acquired for the Corporation as if the provisions 
of Part VII of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>), were 
applicable to it and the Corporation were a company within the 
meaning of clause (e) of section 3 of the said Act.


</article>



<article><tid>217300</tid>
<number> 51</number> Control of Central Government.
<section><tid>1427458</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
remove from the Corporation any member who in its opinion--

<subsection><tid>79476</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses to act,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>732587</tid>
<number>b</number>has become incapable of acting,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1863655</tid>
<number>c</number>has so abused his position as a member as to render his 
continuance on the Corporation detrimental to the 
interest of the public, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911627</tid>
<number>d</number>is otherwise unsuitable to continue as member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1274915</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may suspend any member pending an 
enquiry against him.

</section>

<section><tid>1187444</tid>
<number>3</number>No order of removal under this section shall be made unless 
the member concerned has been given an opportunity to submit his 
explanation to the Central Government, and when such order is passed 
the seat of the member removed shall be declared vacant and another 
member may be appointed under section 4 to fill up the vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>202870</tid>
<number>4</number>A member who has been removed shall not be eligible for 
reappointment as member or in any other capacity to the Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1385649</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may declare void any transaction in 
connection with which a member has been removed under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>970575</tid>
<number>6</number>If the Corporation fails to carry out its functions, or 
follow the directions issued by the Central Government under this Act, 
the Central Government shall have the power to remove the Chairman and 
the members of the Corporation and appoint a Chairman and members in 
their places.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1396070</tid>
<number>52</number>Application of certain provisions of the Indian Forest Act, 
<year>1927</year>, to the forests of the Corporation. All acts prohibited in 
respect of a reserved forest under section 26 of the Indian Forest 
Act, <year>1927</year> (16 of <year>1927</year>.) shall be deemed to be prohibited in respect of 
any forest owned by or under the supervision or control of the 
Corporation and all offences in respect of such forest shall be 
punishable under the said Act as if they were committed in respect of 
a reserved forest.


</article>



<article><tid>1685340</tid>
<number>53</number>Penalty. Whoever contravenes the provisions of sections 17 
and 18 of this Act or any rule made thereunder shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or 
with both.


</article>



<article><tid>863772</tid>
<number>54</number>Procedure for prosecution. No Court shall take cognisance of 
an offence under this Act except on the complaint of an officer of the 
Corporation authorized by it in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>974111</tid>
<number>55</number>Power of entry. Any officer or servant of the Corporation 
generally or specially authorized by the Corporation may at all 
reasonable times enter upon any land or premises and there do such 
things as may be reasonably necessary for the purpose of lawfully 
carrying out any of its works or of making any survey, examination or 
investigation preliminary or incidental to the exercise of powers or 
the performance of functions by the Corporation under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>802249</tid>
<number>56</number>Members, officers and servants of the Corporation to be 
public servants. All members, officers and servants of the 
Corporation, whether appointed by the Central Government or the 
Corporation, shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in 
pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act to be public servants 
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1893635</tid>
<number> 57</number> Protection of action of action taken under the Act.
<section><tid>277825</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
suit, prosecution, or legal proceeding shall lie against any person in 
the employment of the Corporation for anything which is in good faith 
done or purported to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>802426</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in the Act no suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against the Corporation for any damage caused

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or likely to be caused by anything in good faith done or purported to 
be done under this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>440456</tid>
<number>58</number>Effect of other laws. The provisions of this Act or any rule 
made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained 
in any enactment other than this Act or any instrument having effect 
by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>666977</tid>
<number> 59</number> Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the official Gazette, make rules to provide for all or 
any of the following matters, namely:--
<section><tid>1193899</tid>
<number>1</number>the salaries and allowances and conditions of service 
of members, the secretary and the financial adviser;

</section>

<section><tid>1198841</tid>
<number>2</number>the functions and duties of the financial adviser;

</section>

<section><tid>1299944</tid>
<number>3</number>the dams or other works or the installations which may 
be constructed without the approval of the Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>220258</tid>
<number>4</number>the forms of the budget, the annual report and the 
annual financial statements and the dates by which 
copies of the annual financial statements shall be made 
available to the participating Governments;

</section>

<section><tid>888063</tid>
<number>5</number>the manner in which the accounts of the Corporation 
shall be maintained and audited;

</section>

<section><tid>1619838</tid>
<number>6</number>the appointment of an Advisory Committee; and

</section>

<section><tid>1372029</tid>
<number>7</number>the punishment for breach of any rule made under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537911</tid>
<number> 60</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1121980</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation may, with the  
previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Gazette of India, make regulations for carrying out its functions 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>443037</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, in such regulation the Corporation may make provision 
for--

<subsection><tid>801393</tid>
<number>a</number>making of appointments and promotions of its officers 
and servants;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1179661</tid>
<number>b</number>specifying other conditions of service of its officers 
and servants;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1638363</tid>
<number>c</number>specifying the manner in which water rates and charges 
for electrical energy shall be recovered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1251753</tid>
<number>d</number>preventing the pollution of water under its control;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>343346</tid>
<number>e</number>regulating the taking out of fish from the water under 
its control;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>99722</tid>
<number>f</number>regulating its proceedings and business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>648711</tid>
<number>g</number>prescribing punishment for breach of any regulation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>41609</tid>
<number>3</number>All regulations made under sub- sections (1) and (2) shall, as 
soon as possible, be published also in the Official Gazettes of the 
State Governments.


</section>

</article>



 </act>