<act><tid>1359630</tid>
<title>THE VOLUNTARY SURRENDER OF SALARIES (EXEMPTION FROM  
  TAXATION) ACT <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 6th December, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to provide for exempting from taxes on income a portion of the 
salary or allowances payable to any person who has in the public 
interest volunteered to forego it.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1015136</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Voluntary Surrender of 
Salaries (Exemption from Taxation) Act, <year>1961</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>669936</tid>
<number> 2</number> Exemption from taxes on income in respect of salaries 
surrendered in favour of Government. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or in any 
other law for the time being in force relating to taxation on income, 
no income- tax or super- tax shall be payable by any person--
<section><tid>233273</tid>
<number>a</number>where his salary is paid out of the Consolidated Fund of 
India or of the Consolidated Fund of a State, in respect of 
that part of the salary due to him for any period after the 
 31st day of March, <year>1961</year> which he has, by a declaration in 
writing, volunteered to forego in the public interest;

</section>

<section><tid>105951</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, in respect of that part of the salary 
which is due to him for any period after the 31st day of 
March, <year>1961</year> which has been, in the public interest 
surrendered in favour of, and paid to, the Central Government 
in accordance with the rules made in this behalf by that 
Government;
and such part of the salary shall not be included in his total income 
for the purposes of any law relating to taxation on income.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1328187</tid>
<number>3</number>Provisions of section 2 apply to allowances. The provision of 
section 2 shall apply in relation to any allowances due to any such 
person as is referred to therein for any period after the 31st day of 
March, <year>1961</year> as they apply in relation to his salary.


</article>



<article><tid>290539</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1332977</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1158</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu Dadra Nagar Haveli and Pondicherry 
 (w. e. f. 1. 4. 63) by Reg. 3 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 (2) and Sch.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1952756</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
from or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>881601</tid>
<number> 5</number> 
<section><tid>206135</tid>
<number>1</number>Repeal. The Voluntary Surrender of Salaries (Exemption   
  from Taxation) Act, <year>1950</year>, (61 of <year>1950</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1429660</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal any declaration made under the 
said Act shall be deemed to be a declaration made for the purposes of 
this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1159</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>