<act><tid>644473</tid>
<title>THE FOOD CORPORATIONS ACT, <year>1964</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1964</year>
[ 10th December, <year>1964</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of Food Corporations for the 
purpose of trading in foodsgrains and other foodstuffs and for matters 
connected therewith and incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1038718</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>84556</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Food Corporations Act, <year>1964</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1336695</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1241684</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1605119</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1826583</tid>
<number>a</number>" Corporation" means the Food Corporation of India 
established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1045359</tid>
<number>b</number>" Food Corporation" means the Food Corporation of India 
established under section 3 or a State Food Corporation 
established under section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>96334</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" foodstuffs" includes edible oilseeds and oils;.]

</section>

<section><tid>530048</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>783077</tid>
<number>d</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank for the time being 
included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>607835</tid>
<number>e</number>" State Food Corporation" means a State Food Corporation 
established under section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>1335021</tid>
<number>f</number>" year" means the financial year.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 17th December, <year>1964</year>; vide Notification No. G. S. R. <year>1808</year>, dated the 
16th December, <year>1964</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (i), p. 869. 
2 Omitted by Act 67 of <year>1972</year>, s. 2. 
3 Ins. by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

THE FOOD CORPORATION OF INDIA

CHAPTER II

THE FOOD CORPORATION OF INDIA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>731043</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of Food Corporation of India.
<section><tid>1889133</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect  
from such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, the Central Government 
shall establish for the purposes of this Act a Corporation known as 
the Food Corporation of India.

</section>

<section><tid>543337</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall be a body corporate with the name 
aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of 
property and to contract, and may, by that name, sue and be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1960702</tid>
<number> 4</number> Offices and agencies.
<section><tid>1044301</tid>
<number>1</number>The head office of the Corporation  
shall be at Madras or at such other place as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>323711</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Corporation may establish offices or agencies at other 
places in or outside India:
Provided that no such office or agency shall be established at 
any place outside India without the previous approval of the Central 
Government.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1710563</tid>
<number> 5</number> Capital of Corporation.
<section><tid>929243</tid>
<number>1</number>The original capital of the  
Corporation shall be such sum not exceeding one hundred crores of 
rupees as the Central Government may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1035027</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may from time to time increase the 
capital of the Corporation to such extent and in such manner as that 
Government may determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1459030</tid>
<number>3</number>Such capital may be provided by the Central Government from 
time to time after due appropriation made by Parliament by law for the 
purpose and subject to such terms and conditions as may be determined 
by that Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>515867</tid>
<number> 6</number> Management.
<section><tid>1890514</tid>
<number>1</number>The general superintendence, direction and  
management of the affairs and business of the Corporation shall vest 
in a board of directors which may exercise all such powers and do all 
such acts and things as may be exercised or done by the Corporation 
under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January <year>1965</year>; vide Notification No. G. S. R. <year>1809</year>, dated the 
16th December, <year>1964</year> Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (i), p. 869. 
2 Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1972</year>, s. 4. (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1152557</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors, in discharging its functions, shall 
act on business principles having regard to the interests of the 
producer and consumer and shall be guided by such instructions on 
questions of policy as may be given to it by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>273091</tid>
<number>3</number>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a 
question of policy, the decision of the Central Government thereon 
shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>618830</tid>
<number> 7</number> Board of directors.
<section><tid>377766</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of directors of the  
Corporation shall consist of the following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1304903</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1362973</tid>
<number>b</number>three directors to represent respectively the Ministries 
of the Central Government dealing with--

<subsubsection><tid>1189782</tid>
<number>i</number>food,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>545983</tid>
<number>ii</number>finance, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1329796</tid>
<number>iii</number>co- operation;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>234330</tid>
<number>c</number>the managing director of the Central Warehousing 
Corporation established under section 3 of the 
Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year> (58 of <year>1962</year>), ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1976966</tid>
<number>d</number>a managing director;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452270</tid>
<number>e</number>six other directors.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>310080</tid>
<number>2</number>All the directors of the Corporation other than the director 
referred to in clause (c) of sub- section (1) shall be appointed by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>601979</tid>
<number>3</number>The managing director shall--

<subsection><tid>15094</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the 
board of directors may entrust or delegate to him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348604</tid>
<number>b</number>receive such salary and allowances as the board of 
directors may, with the approval of the Central 
Government, fix:
Provided that the first managing director shall receive such 
salary and allowances as the Central Government may fix.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>754466</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the directors of the Corporation, other than the 
director referred to in clause (c) of sub- section (1), and the other 
terms and conditions of appointment of the directors of the 
Corporation shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), be 
such as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1038512</tid>
<number> 8</number> Disqualification for office of director. A person shall be 
disqualified for being appointed as, and for being, a director of the 
Corporation--
<section><tid>40469</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated insolvent 
or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded 
with his creditors; or

</section>

<section><tid>1751073</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a 
competent court; or

</section>

<section><tid>769205</tid>
<number>c</number>if he is or has been convicted of any offence which in 
the opinion of the Central Government involves moral 
turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>1997058</tid>
<number>d</number>if he has been removed or dismissed from the service of 
the Government or a corporation owned or controlled by 
the Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>601064</tid>
<number>e</number>except in the case of the Chairman or the managing 
director, if he is a salaried official of the Food 
Corporation of India or a State Food Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>382824</tid>
<number> 9</number> Removal and resignation of directors.
<section><tid>922706</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, at any time, after consultation with the Corporation, 
remove the managing director from office after giving him a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the proposed removal.

</section>

<section><tid>815482</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors may remove any director from office 
who--

<subsection><tid>1369085</tid>
<number>a</number>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 8; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>37416</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the board of directors from 
more than three consecutive meetings thereof without 
cause sufficient, in the opinion of the board, to 
exonerate his absence.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1111141</tid>
<number>3</number>A director of the Corporation may resign his office by giving 
notice thereof in writing to the Central Government and on such 
resignation being accepted, he shall be deemed to have vacated his 
office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>842274</tid>
<number> 10</number> Meetings.
<section><tid>178379</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of directors of the Corporation shall  
meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of 
procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings 
 (including the quorum at meetings) as may be provided by regulations 
made by the Corporation under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>177421</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board or, if for any reason he is unable 
to attend any meeting, any other director elected by the directors 
present at the meeting, shall preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>365466</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the board 
shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the directors present 
and voting, and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairman, 
or in his absence, the person presiding, shall have and exercise a 
second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1118352</tid>
<number> 11</number> Advisory Committees.
<section><tid>980823</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in  
consultation with the Corporation, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, constitute one or more Advisory Committees consisting of such 
persons and on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1236882</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of any such Advisory Committee to advise 
the Central Government or the Corporation in regard to any matter 
connected with the purposes of this Act in respect of which its advice 
is sought by the Central Government, or, as the case may be, by the 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1991886</tid>
<number>3</number>The expenses in relation to the Advisory Committees shall be 
met by the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1781620</tid>
<number> 12</number> Officers and other employees of Corporation.
<section><tid>289311</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, after consultation with the Corporation, appoint a 
person to be the Secretary of the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1577771</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central 
Government in this behalf, the Corporation may appoint such other 
officers and employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions.

</section>

<section><tid>675899</tid>
<number>3</number>The methods of appointment, the conditions of service and the 
scales of pay of the officers and other employees of the Corporation 
shall--

<subsection><tid>273659</tid>
<number>a</number>as respects the Secretary, be such as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>361386</tid>
<number>b</number>as respects the other officers and employees, be such as 
may be determined by regulations made by the 
Corporation under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1920271</tid>
<number> 12A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Special provisions for transfer of Government employees 
to the Corporation in certain cases.
<section><tid>553124</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government  
has ceased or ceases to perform any functions which under section 13 
are functions of the Corporation, it shall be lawful for the Central 
Government to transfer,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


by order and with effect from such date or dates (which may be either  
retrospective to any date not earlier than the 1st January, <year>1965</year>, or 
  prospective) as may be specified in the order, to the Corporation any 
of the officers or employees serving in the Department of the Central 
Government dealing with food or any of its subordinate or attached 
offices and engaged in the performance of those functions:

Provided that no order under this sub- section shall be made in 
relation to any officer or employee in such Department or office who 
has, in respect of the proposal of the Central Government to transfer 
such officer or employee to the Corporation, intimated within such 
time as may be specified in this behalf by that Government, his 
intention of not becoming an employee of the Corporation.


</section>

<section><tid>1009967</tid>
<number>2</number>In making an order under sub- section (1), the Central 
Government shall, as far as may be, take into consideration the 
functions which the Central Government has ceased or ceases to perform 
and the areas in which such functions have been or are performed.

</section>

<section><tid>1825799</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer or other employee transferred by an order made 
under sub- section (1) shall, on and from the date of transfer, cease 
to be an employee of the Central Government and become an employee of 
the Corporation with such designation as the Corporation may determine 
and shall, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subject to the provisions of sub- sections (4), (4A), 
 (4B), (4C), (5) and (6)], be governed by the regulations made by the 
Corporation under this Act as respects remuneration and other 
conditions of service including pension, leave and provident fund, and 
shall continue to be an officer or employee of the Corporation unless 
and until his employment is terminated by the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1299101</tid>
<number>4</number>Every officer or other employee transferred by an order made 
under sub- section (1) shall, within six months from the date of 
transfer, exercise his option in writing to be governed,--

<subsection><tid>1490578</tid>
<number>a</number>by the scale of pay applicable to the post held by him 
under the Government immediately before the date of 
transfer or by the scale of pay applicable to the post 
under the Corporation to which he is transferred.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136818</tid>
<number>b</number>by the leave, provident fund, retirement or other 
terminal benefits admissible to employees of the 
Central Government in accordance with the rules and 
orders of the Central Government as amended from time 
to time or the leave, provident fund or other terminal 
benefits admissible to the employees of the Corporation 
under the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1977</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


regulations made by the Corporation under this Act, and 
such option once exercised shall be final:

Provided that the option exercised under clause (a) shall be 
applicable only in respect of the post to which such officer or 
employee is transferred to the Corporation and on appointment to a 
higher post under the Corporation, he shall be eligible only for the 
scale of pay applicable to such higher post:

Provided further that if immediately before the date of his 
transfer any such officer or employee is officiating in a higher post 
under the Government either in a leave vacancy or in any other vacancy 
of a specified duration, his pay, on transfer, shall be protected for 
the unexpired period of such vacancy and thereafter he shall be 
entitled to the scale of pay applicable to the post under the 
Government to which he would have reverted or to the scale of pay 
applicable to the post under the Corporation to which he is 
transferred, whichever he may opt:

Provided also that when an officer or other employee serving in 
the Department of the Ministry of the Central Government dealing with 
food or in any of its attached or subordinate offices is promoted to 
officiate in a higher post in the Department or office subsequent to 
the transfer to the Corporation of any other officer or employee 
senior to him in that Department or office before such transfer, the 
officer or other employee who is promoted to officiate in such higher 
post shall, on transfer to the Corporation, be entitled only to the 
scale of pay applicable to the post he would have held but for such 
promotion or the scale of pay applicable to the post under the 
Corporation to which he is transferred, whichever he may opt.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>825206</tid>
<number>4A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (4),--

<subsection><tid>803577</tid>
<number>a</number>every officer or other employee in respect of whom an 
order of transfer under sub- section (1) had been made before the 
date of commencement of the Food Corporations (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1977</year> (hereafter in this section referred to as the appointed day) 
shall, whether or not he had exercised the option under sub- 
section (4) before the appointed day, exercise such option within 
six months from the appointed day; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>678016</tid>
<number>b</number>every officer or other employee in respect of whom an 
order of transfer under sub- section (1) may be made after the 
appointed day shall, within six months from the date or such 
order, exercise his option under sub- section (4),
and in each such case such option once exercised shall be final:

Provided that where an officer or other employee having exercised 
an option under sub- section (4) before the appointed day--


<subsubsection><tid>271738</tid>
<number>i</number>has died or retired before the appointed day, or dies or 
retires after the appointed day, before exercising the option as 
required by this sub- section, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1371889</tid>
<number>ii</number>does not exercise the option as required by this sub- 
section,
the option already exercised by him shall be deemed to have been 
validly exercised by him under sub- section (4).


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>730943</tid>
<number>4B</number>Where an officer or other employee--

<subsection><tid>1125928</tid>
<number>a</number>has died or retired, or dies or retires, after an order 
of transfer under sub- section (1) in respect of such officer or 
other employee is made but before exercising the option under 
sub- section (4) or, as the case may be, as required by sub- 
section (4A); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108938</tid>
<number>b</number>has died or retired, or dies or retires, before an order 
of transfer under sub- section (1) in respect of such officer or 
other employee is made,
he shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (4) or 
sub- section (4A),--


<subsubsection><tid>629593</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case falling under clause (a), be deemed to have 
exercised an option under sub- section (4); and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1781536</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case falling under clause (b), be deemed to have 
been transferred under sub- section (1) and exercised and option 
under sub- section (4)
to be governed by the leave, provident fund, retirement or other 
terminal benefits admissible to the employees of the Central 
Government in accordance with the rules and orders of the Central 
Government as amended from time to time:

Provided that nothing in clause (a) of this sub- section shall 
apply to an officer or other employee who has, before the appointed 
day, been paid the terminal benefits as admissible to the employees of 
the Corporation under the regulations made by the Corporation under 
this Act, unless such officer or other employee refunds in a lump sum 
within six months from the appointed day the amount of contributions 
made by the Corporation towards such terminal benefits:

Provided further that nothing in clause (b) of this sub- section 
shall apply to an officer or other employee who has intimated, under 
the proviso to sub- section (1), his intention of not becoming an 
employee of the Corporation.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1418418</tid>
<number>4C</number>Where an officer or other employee has exercised an option 
under sub- section (4), or exercises, or is deemed to have exercised, 
an option under that sub- section, read with sub- section (4A) or sub- 
section (4B), to be governed by the leave, provident fund, retirement 
or other terminal benefits admissible to the employees of the Central 
Government, such benefits shall be calculated on the basis of the pay 
and allowances drawn by him in the Corporation.]

</section>

<section><tid>1501886</tid>
<number>5</number>No officer or other employee transferred by an order made 
under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1996422</tid>
<number>a</number>shall be dismissed or removed by an authority 
subordinate to that competent to make a similar or 
equivalent appointment under the Corporation as may be 
specified in the regulations made by the Corporation 
under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85989</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> shall be dismissed or removed or reduced in rank 
except after an inquiry in which he has been informed 
of the charges against him and given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in respect of those 
charges:]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 12 of <year>1977</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1976</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 53 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that where it is proposed after such inquiry, to 
impose upon him any such penalty, such penalty may be imposed on the 
basis of the evidence adduced during such inquiry and it shall not be 
necessary to give such person any opportunity of making representation 
on the penalty proposed:]

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that] this clause shall not apply,--


<subsubsection><tid>353566</tid>
<number>i</number>where an officer or employee is dismissed or removed or 
reduced in rank on the ground of conduct which has led 
to his conviction on a criminal charge; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>467963</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the authority empowered to dismiss or remove an 
officer or employee or to reduce him in rank is 
satisfied that for some reason, to be recorded by that 
authority in writing, it is not reasonably practicable 
to hold such inquiry; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>56851</tid>
<number>iii</number>to an officer or employee who, after transfer to the 
Corporation, is appointed to a higher post under the 
Corporation in response to an open advertisement and in 
competition with outsiders.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>768781</tid>
<number>6</number>If, in respect of any such officer or employee as aforesaid, 
a question arises whether it is reasonable practicable to hold such 
inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (5), the decision thereon of 
the authority empowered to dismiss or remove him or to reduce him in 
rank shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1708285</tid>
<number>7</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall apply to the 
members of the Central Secretariat Service or any other service or to 
persons on deputation to the Department referred to in that sub- 
section or to any of its attached or subordinate offices from any 
Ministry of the Central Government or from any State Government or 
from any organisation.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1102216</tid>
<number> 13</number> Functions of Corporation.
<section><tid>440123</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act, it shall be the primary duty of the Corporation to undertake 
the purchase, storage, movement transport, distribution and sale of 
foodgrains and other foodstuffs.

</section>

<section><tid>166826</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject as aforesaid, the Corporation may also, with the 
previous approval of the Central Government,--

<subsection><tid>1837077</tid>
<number>a</number>promote by such means as it thinks fit the production of 
foodgrains and other foodstuffs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>369538</tid>
<number>b</number>set up, or assist in the setting up of, rice mills, 
flour mills and other undertakings for the processing 
of foodgrains and other foodstuffs; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>567341</tid>
<number>c</number>discharge such other functions as may be prescribed or 
as are supplemental, incidental or consequential to any 
of the functions conferred on it under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 53 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1275277</tid>
<number> 14</number> Executive Committee and other commodities.
<section><tid>1047531</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of  
directors of the Corporation may constitute an Executive Committee 
which shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1243899</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman of the board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>166816</tid>
<number>b</number>the managing director; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744165</tid>
<number>c</number>three other directors, of whom one shall be a non- 
official.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>288689</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be the Chairman 
of the Executive Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>280709</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the general control, direction and superintendence 
of the board of directors, the Executive Committee shall be competent 
to deal with any matter within the competence of the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1452896</tid>
<number>4</number>The board of directors may constitute such other committees, 
whether consisting wholly of directors or wholly of other persons or 
partly of directors and partly of other persons as it thinks fit, for 
such purposes as it may decide.

</section>

<section><tid>1613354</tid>
<number>5</number>A committee constituted under this section shall meet at such 
times and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard 
to the transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum  
  at meetings) as may be provided by regulations made by the Corporation 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>872920</tid>
<number>6</number>The members of a committee (other than the directors of the  
  board) shall be paid by the Corporation such fees and allowances as 
may be fixed by it by regulations made under this Act for attending 
the meetings of the committee and for attending to any other work of 
the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>315210</tid>
<number>15</number>Member of board or committee thereof not to vote in certain 
cases. A member of the board of directors of the Corporation or a 
committee thereof who has any direct or indirect pecuniary interest in 
any matter coming up for consideration at a meeting of the board

<pagefootnote><pagenum>83</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of directors or committee thereof, shall, as soon as possible after 
relevant circumstances have come to his knowledge, disclose the nature 
of his interest at such meeting and the disclosure shall be recorded 
in the minutes of the board or the committee, as the case may be, and 
the member shall not take any part in any deliberation or decision of 
the board or committee with respect to that matter.

CHAP

BOARDS OF MANAGEMENT

CHAPTER III

BOARDS OF MANAGEMENT



</article>



<article><tid>1292398</tid>
<number> 16</number> Board of Management, their constitution and functions.
<section><tid>1645724</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, on a request received in this behalf from 
the State Government or Governments concerned or otherwise, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Board of Management 
for a State or two or more contiguous States, if no State Food 
Corporation is functioning in such State or States.

</section>

<section><tid>1023202</tid>
<number>2</number>The head office of the Board of Management shall be at such 
place as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1469645</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board of Management shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>685764</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the board of directors of 
the Food Corporation of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075923</tid>
<number>b</number>the senior- most executive officer of the said 
Corporation employed at the head office of the Board of 
Management; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>170310</tid>
<number>c</number>not more than ten other members to be appointed by the 
board of directors of the said Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>150809</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of a Board of Management referred to in clauses 
 (a) and (c) of sub- section (3) shall hold office for a term of two 
years and shall be eligible for re- appointment and the other terms and 
conditions of their appointment shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>983107</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board of Management shall advise the Corporation on such 
matters as may be generally or specifically referred to it and shall 
perform such other functions as the Corporation may delegate to it.

</section>

<section><tid>1402366</tid>
<number>6</number>The provisions of sections 20, 21 and 25 shall, so far as may 
be, apply in relation to the members of a Board of Management as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>84</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

they apply in relation to the members of the board of directors of a 
State Food Corporation:

Provided that the reference to the General Manager in clause (e) 
of section 20 shall be construed as a reference to the officer of the 
Corporation referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (3).


</section>

<section><tid>1357097</tid>
<number>7</number>The Food Corporation of India may, after consultation with a 
Board of Management, appoint such staff as it considers necessary to 
enable that Board to perform its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1784211</tid>
<number>8</number>The Board of Management may, by order in writing, authorise 
any one or more of its members to exercise and perform, subject to 
such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the 
order, such of its powers and functions as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>392373</tid>
<number>9</number>The Board of Management shall follow such procedure as may be 
provided by regulations made by the Food Corporation of India under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>504782</tid>
<number>10</number>Where a Board of Management has been established--

<subsection><tid>1289129</tid>
<number>i</number>for a State, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1957942</tid>
<number>ii</number>for two or more States,
then such Board shall stand dissolved--


<subsubsection><tid>1580422</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case referred to in clause (i), on the 
establishment of a Food Corporation for that State, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>198132</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case referred to in clause (ii), on the 
establishment of such Corporation for any one or more 
of such States.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1904129</tid>
<number>11</number>Where a Board of Management stands dissolved under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (10), the Central Government may establish a new 
Board of Management for the State or States for which no Food 
Corporation has been established.

</section>

<section><tid>641742</tid>
<number>12</number>The expenses of the Board of Management in the discharge of 
its functions under this Act shall be met by the Food Corporation of 
India.
CHAP

STATE FOOD CORPORATIONS

CHAPTER IV

STATE FOOD CORPORATIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1528177</tid>
<number> 17</number> Establishment of State Food Corporation.
<section><tid>1206116</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and after 
consultation with the Government of a State, establish a Food 
Corporation for that State under such name as may be specified in the 
notification.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>85</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>310558</tid>
<number>2</number>A State Food Corporation established under sub- section (1) 
shall be a body corporate by the name notified under that sub- section, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
and to contract, and may, by the said name, sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1420878</tid>
<number>3</number>The head office of a State Food Corporation shall be at such 
place within the State as may be notified by the Central Government in 
the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1806111</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, a State Food 
Corporation may perform such of the functions of the Food Corporation 
of India as that Corporation may delegate to it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1658470</tid>
<number> 18</number> Capital of State Food Corporation
<section><tid>1884147</tid>
<number>1</number>The capital of a State  
Food Corporation shall be such sum not exceeding ten crores of rupees 
as the Central Government may, after consultation with the Food 
Corporation of India, fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1409886</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, after such consultation, from 
time to time increase the capital of the State Food Corporation to 
such extent and in such manner as that Government may determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1634403</tid>
<number>3</number>Such capital shall be provided--

<subsection><tid>1195220</tid>
<number>a</number>by the Central Government after due appropriation made 
by Parliament by law for the purpose, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>304818</tid>
<number>b</number>by the Food Corporation of India.
in such proportion and subject to such terms and conditions as may be 
determined by the Central Government.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1326198</tid>
<number> 19</number> Management of State Food Corporation.
<section><tid>248306</tid>
<number>1</number>The general  
superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business 
of a State Food Corporation shall vest in a board of directors which 
shall consist of a Chairman, a General Manager and not more than ten 
other members, all of whom shall be appointed by the Food Corporation 
of India after consultation with the Central Government and the State 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1063198</tid>
<number>2</number>The General Manager shall--

<subsection><tid>440416</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the 
board of directors may entrust or delegate to him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>582481</tid>
<number>b</number>receive such salary and allowances and be governed by 
such terms and conditions of service as the board of 
directors may, in consultation with the Food 
Corporation of India, fix.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>86</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>732835</tid>
<number>3</number>The board of directors, in discharging its functions, shall 
act on business principles having regard to the interests of the 
producer and consumer and shall be guided by such instructions on 
questions of policy as may be given to it by the Food Corporation of 
India.

</section>

<section><tid>1014310</tid>
<number>4</number>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a 
question of policy, the matter shall be referred to the Central 
Government whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1015304</tid>
<number>5</number>The members of the board of directors, other than the General 
Manager, shall be entitled to receive by way of remuneration or fees 
such sums as may be prescribed:
Provided that no official member shall be entitled to receive any 
remuneration other than any allowances admissible to him under the 
rules regulating his conditions of service.


</section>

<section><tid>1448741</tid>
<number>6</number>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the members of the board of directors shall be such 
as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>787665</tid>
<number> 20</number> Disqualification for office of member of board of directors. 
A person shall be disqualified for being appointed as, and for being, 
a member of the board of directors of a State Food Corporation--
<section><tid>1601370</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated insolvent 
or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded 
with his creditors; or

</section>

<section><tid>298007</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a 
competent court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1730216</tid>
<number>c</number>if he is or has been convicted of any offence which in 
the opinion of the Central Government involves moral 
turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>1863072</tid>
<number>d</number>if he has been removed or dismissed from the service of 
the Government or a corporation owned or controlled by 
the Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>893094</tid>
<number>e</number>except in the case of the Chairman or the General 
Manager, if he is a salaried official of the Food 
Corporation of Indian or a State Food Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1488255</tid>
<number> 21</number> Removal and resignation of members of board of directors.
<section><tid>603352</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Food Corporation of India, may, at any time, after consultation 
with the State Food Corporation, remove the General Manager from 
officer after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause 
against the proposed removal.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>87</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1486783</tid>
<number>2</number>The board of directors of a State Food Corporation may remove 
from office any member of that board who--

<subsection><tid>1021612</tid>
<number>a</number>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 20, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1923242</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the board of directors from 
more than three consecutive meetings thereof without 
cause sufficient, in the opinion of the board, to 
exonerate his absence.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1897839</tid>
<number>3</number>A member of such board may resign his office by giving notice 
thereof in writing to the Food Corporation of India and on such 
resignation being accepted, he shall be deemed to have vacated his 
office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>474961</tid>
<number> 22</number> Meetings.
<section><tid>1635865</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of directors of a State Food  
Corporation shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such 
rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its 
meetings (including the quorum at meetings) as may be provided by 
regulations made by that Corporation under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>131894</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board of directors or, if for any reason 
he is unable to attend any meeting, any other member of the board 
elected by the members of the board present at the meeting, shall 
preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>104532</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the board 
of directors shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the 
members present and voting, and, in the event of an equality of votes, 
the Chairman or in his absence, the person presiding shall have and 
exercise a second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>58957</tid>
<number> 23</number> Appointment of officers, etc., and their conditions of 
service.
<section><tid>253844</tid>
<number>1</number>A State Food Corporation may appoint such officers and  
other employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions.

</section>

<section><tid>1495665</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person employed by a State Food Corporation under this 
Act shall be subject to such conditions of service and shall be 
entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by regulations made 
by that Corporation under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>950745</tid>
<number> 24</number> Executive Committee and other committees.
<section><tid>280507</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of  
directors of a State Food Corporation may constitute an Executive 
Committee which shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1817666</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman of the board of directors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767063</tid>
<number>b</number>the General Manager; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>88</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>746677</tid>
<number>c</number>three other members of the board of directors, of whom 
one shall be a non- official.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1328330</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be the Chairman 
of the Executive Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>182778</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the general control, direction and superintendence 
of the board of directors, the Executive Committee shall be competent 
to deal with any matter within the competence of the State Food 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1406074</tid>
<number>4</number>The board of directors may constitute such other committees, 
whether consisting wholly of members of the board or wholly of other 
persons or partly of such members and partly of other persons as it 
thinks fit, for such purposes as it may decide.

</section>

<section><tid>1548843</tid>
<number>5</number>A committee constituted under this section shall meet at such 
times and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard 
to the transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum  
  at meetings) as may be provided by regulations made by the State Food 
Corporation under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>386333</tid>
<number>6</number>The members of a committee (other than the directors of the  
  board) shall be paid by the State Food Corporation such fees and 
allowances as may be fixed by it by regulations made under this Act, 
for attending the meetings of the committee and for attending to any 
other work of that Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>910321</tid>
<number>25</number>Member of board or committee thereof not to vote in certain 
cases. A member of the board of directors of a State Food Corporation 
or a committee thereof who has any direct or indirect pecuniary 
interest in any matter coming up for consideration at a meeting of the 
board of directors or committee thereof, shall, as soon as possible 
after relevant circumstances have come to his knowledge, disclose the 
nature of his interest at such meeting and the disclosure shall be 
recorded in the minutes of the board or the committee, as the case may 
be, and the member shall not take any part in any deliberation or 
decision of the board or the committee with respect to that matter.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER V

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT



</article>



<article><tid>1584324</tid>
<number> 26</number> Submission of programme of activities and financial 
estimates.
<section><tid>1379688</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food Corporation shall, before the commencement of  
each year, prepare a statement of programme of its activities during 
the forthcoming year as well as a financial estimate in respect 
thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>89</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1180903</tid>
<number>2</number>The statement prepared under sub- section (1) Shall, not less 
than three months before the commencement of each year, be submitted 
for approval--

<subsection><tid>1341247</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Food Corporation of India, to the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>698334</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a State Food Corporation, to the Food 
Corporation of India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>634584</tid>
<number>3</number>The statement and the financial estimate of a Food 
corporation referred to in sub- section (1) may, with the approval of 
the Central Government, in the case of the Food Corporation of India, 
or with the approval of the Food Corporation of India in the case of a 
State Food Corporation, be revised by the Food Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1965134</tid>
<number> 27</number> Borrowing powers of Food Corporation. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1139495</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food  
Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying out its functions under 
this Act,--

<subsection><tid>1436854</tid>
<number>a</number>take advances against stocks of foodgrains or other 
foodstuffs held by it, or borrow money--

<subsubsection><tid>1508159</tid>
<number>i</number>from any scheduled bank, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1496937</tid>
<number>ii</number>from any other bank or financial institution 
approved by the Central Government in this behalf, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>242798</tid>
<number>iii</number>from any other authority, organisation or 
institution or from the public on such terms and conditions 
as may be approved by the Central Government; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434226</tid>
<number>b</number>issue and sell bonds and debentures carrying interest at 
such rates as may be fixed by the Central Government at the time 
the bonds or debentures are issued:
Provided that the amount borrowed by a Food Corporation under 
this sub- section shall not at any time exceed ten times the paid- up 
capital and the reserve fund established under section 33.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>330734</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may guarantee the loans and advances 
taken by a Food Corporation under sub- section (1) as to the re- payment 
of principal and the payment of interest thereon and other incidental 
charges.

</section>

<section><tid>1861604</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> A Food Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying out 
its functions under this Act, also borrow money from the Central 
Government, and that Government may, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Food Corporation such 
sums of money by way of loan on such terms and conditions as that 
Government may determine].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664425</tid>
<number>28</number>Lending by Food Corporation on security of foodgrains. A Food 
Corporation may lend or advance money to any person engaged in the 
production of foodgrains upon the security of foodgrains or such other 
security as may be prescribed, for any purpose connected with such 
production.


</article>



<article><tid>1771665</tid>
<number> 29</number> Power to enter into agreement for purchase of foodgrains 
after harvest.
<section><tid>765297</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food Corporation may enter into agreement with  
any grower of foodcrops for the purchase of foodgrains after the 
harvest of such crops and any such agreement may provide that any sum 
payable by the Corporation to the grower under such agreement shall be 
payable to any scheduled bank or other financing agency nominated by 
the grower in this behalf to such extent as may be specified in the 
agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>1321109</tid>
<number>2</number>The scheduled bank or other financing agency referred to in 
sub- section (1) may, on the basis of any agreement referred to in that 
sub- section, lend money to a grower of foodcrops who has entered into 
such agreement.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>90</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 67 of <year>1972</year>. s. 5. 
2 Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1988</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1620454</tid>
<number>30</number>Guarantee by Food Corporation. A Food Corporation may, upon 
such terms and conditions as it may think fit, guarantee any loan 
referred to in sub- section (2) of section 29, and also any other loan 
raised by a grower of foodcrops, which is re- payable within a period 
not exceeding five years.


</article>



<article><tid>1415893</tid>
<number> 31</number> Funds of Food Corporation.
<section><tid>1876082</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food Corporation shall have  
its own fund and all receipts of the Corporation shall be credited 
thereto and all payments of the Corporation shall be met therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>178847</tid>
<number>2</number>Such fund shall be applied for meeting all administrative 
expenses of the Food, Corporation and for carrying out the purposes of 
this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>891170</tid>
<number>32</number>Investment of funds. A Food Corporation may invest its funds 
in the securities of the Central Government or any State Government or 
in such other manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>492397</tid>
<number> 33</number> Allocation of surplus profits.
<section><tid>1752506</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food Corporation shall  
establish a reserve fund to which shall be credited every year such 
portion of its annual net profits as that Corporation thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1020202</tid>
<number>2</number>After making provision for such reserve fund and for bad and 
doubtful debts, depreciation in assets and all other matters which are 
usually provided for by companies registered and incorporated under 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), the balance of its annual net 
profits shall be paid--

<subsection><tid>1276466</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Food Corporation of India, to the 
Central Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>395555</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a State Food Corporation, to the Central 
Government and the Food Corporation of India in the 
same proportion as the capital provided by them.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1310785</tid>
<number> 34</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>317912</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food Corporation shall maintain  
proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual 
statement of accounts including the profit and loss account and the 
balance sheet in such form as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1384982</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of a Food Corporation shall be audited by 
auditors duly qualified to act as auditors of companies under section 
 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1931336</tid>
<number>3</number>The auditors shall be appointed annually by the Food 
Corporation from among a list of auditors approved by the Central

<pagefootnote><pagenum>91</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government on the advice of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India.


</section>

<section><tid>648327</tid>
<number>4</number>The auditors shall be supplied with a copy of the annual 
balance sheet and the profit and loss account of the Food Corporation 
and it shall be their duty to examine them together with the accounts 
and vouchers relating thereto, and they shall have a list delivered to 
them of all books kept by the Corporation and shall at all reasonable 
times have access to the books, accounts and other documents of the 
Corporation and may require from any officer of the Corporation such 
information and explanations as the auditors may think necessary for 
the performance of their duties as auditors.

</section>

<section><tid>183604</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India shall have 
power--

<subsection><tid>190306</tid>
<number>a</number>to direct the manner in which the accounts of a Food 
Corporation shall be audited by the auditors appointed under sub- 
section (3) and to give such auditors instructions in regard to 
any matter relating to the performance of their functions as 
such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897166</tid>
<number>b</number>to conduct a supplementary or test audit of the accounts 
of a Food Corporation by such person or persons as he may 
authorise in this behalf; and for the purpose of such audit, to 
require information or additional information to be furnished to 
any person or persons so authorised, on such matters, by such 
person or persons, and in such form, as the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General may, by general or special order, direct.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1459724</tid>
<number>6</number>The auditors shall send a copy of their report together with 
an audited copy of the accounts--

<subsection><tid>958405</tid>
<number>a</number>to the Food Corporation concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645434</tid>
<number>b</number>where the accounts relate to a State Food Corporation 
also to the food Corporation of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>539823</tid>
<number>c</number>to the Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1768435</tid>
<number>d</number>to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India who 
shall have the right to comment upon, or supplement the audit 
report in such manner as he may think fit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1934025</tid>
<number>7</number>Any comments upon or supplement to, the audit report, made by 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India under clause (d) of sub- 
section (6) shall be placed by the Food Corporation concerned before 
the Central Government, and where the accounts relate to a State Food 
Corporation, also before the Food Corporation of India.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1715105</tid>
<number> 35</number> Annual report on the working of Food Corporations.
<section><tid>1238778</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food  
Corporation shall, as soon as possible after the end of each year, 
submit to the Central Government an annual report on the working and 
affairs of the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1249647</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the 
receipt of such report, cause such report and the audit report 
received under section 34 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> together with any comments thereon or 
supplement thereto by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India] to 
be laid before both Houses of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1811845</tid>
<number> 36</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts or proceedings of 
Food Corporation, etc.
<section><tid>79828</tid>
<number>1</number>No act or proceeding of a Food Corporation  
or a committee thereof or a Board of Management shall be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
constitution of, the board of directors of the Food Corporation or 
such committee or Board of Management.

</section>

<section><tid>1715674</tid>
<number>2</number>No act done by any person acting in good faith as a member of 
a board of directors of a Food Corporation or of a Board of Management 
shall be deemed to be invalid by reason only of his disqualification 
for being appointed as, or for being, a member of such board of 
directors or Board of Management.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1771603</tid>
<number>37</number>Delegation. A Food Corporation may, by general or special 
order in writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member of the 
board
<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1972</year>, s. 6. 
2 Ins. by s. 7, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of directors or the Secretary or other officer of the Corporation, 
subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be 
specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this 
Act as it may deem necessary.



</article>



<article><tid>601790</tid>
<number>38</number>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. Every director, member 
of an Advisory Committee or other committee, auditor, officer or other 
employee of a Food Corporation and every member of a Board of 
Management and its staff shall, before entering upon his duties, make 
a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1564979</tid>
<number> 39</number> Indemnity of directors.
<section><tid>345356</tid>
<number>1</number>Every member of the board of  
directors of a Food Corporation and of a Board of Management shall be 
indemnified by the Corporation against all losses and expenses 
incurred by him in the discharge of his duties except such as are 
caused by his own wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>1855429</tid>
<number>2</number>A member of the board of directors of a Food Corporation or a 
Board of Management shall not be responsible for any other member or 
for any officer or other employee of the Corporation or Board of 
Management or for any loss or expense resulting to the Corporation 
from the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or title to, any 
property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the Corporation in 
good faith, or by the insolvency or wrongful act of any person under 
obligation to the Corporation or by anything done in good faith, in 
the execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>250387</tid>
<number>40</number>Protection of action taken under this Act. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against a Food Corporation or any member of 
the board of directors thereof or any officer or other employee 
thereof or any member of a Board of Management or its staff or any 
other person authorised by a Food Corporation or a Board of Management 
to discharge any functions under this Act for any loss or damage 
caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1100921</tid>
<number> 41</number> Offences.
<section><tid>1963177</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever, without the consent in writing of a  
Food Corporation, uses its name in any prospectus or advertisement, 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>93</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1780688</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under sub- 
section (1) except on a complaint in writing by an officer authorised 
in this behalf by the Food Corporation concerned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>782337</tid>
<number>42</number>Provision relating to income- tax, super- tax, etc. For the 
purposes of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), or any other 
enactment for the time being in force relating to income- tax, super- 
tax or any other tax on income, profits or gains, a Food Corporation 
shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of the Income- tax 
Act, <year>1961</year>, and shall be liable to tax accordingly on its income, 
profits and gains.


</article>



<article><tid>1273673</tid>
<number>43</number>Winding up of Food Corporation. No provision of law relating 
to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to a Food 
Corporation and it shall not be placed in liquidation save by order of 
the Central Government and in such manner as that Government may 
direct.


</article>



<article><tid>320348</tid>
<number> 44</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1906439</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>317611</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1757923</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, and the other terms and conditions of 
appointment of, the directors of the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>460601</tid>
<number>b</number>the composition of Advisory Committees and the terms and 
conditions of service of members thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1749338</tid>
<number>c</number>the additional functions which the Corporation may 
perform;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1404884</tid>
<number>d</number>the remuneration or fees payable to the members of the 
board of directors of a State Food Corporation and the 
term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, such members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1652553</tid>
<number>e</number>the securities (other than foodgrains) upon which a Food 
Corporation may lend or advance money;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1962870</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which a Food Corporation may invest its 
funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>830732</tid>
<number>g</number>the form of the annual statement of accounts and the 
balance sheet to be prepared by a Food Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>768228</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>94</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1610971</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid,] both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1831677</tid>
<number> 45</number> Power of Food Corporation to make regulations.
<section><tid>1257768</tid>
<number>1</number>A Food  
Corporation may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not 
inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provide 
for all matters for which provisions is necessary or expedient for the 
purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>8532</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The power to make regulations under this section shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of this Act, to the regulations or any 
of them but no retrospective effect shall be given to any regulation 
so as to prejudicially affect the interests of any person to whom such 
regulation may be applicable.]

</section>

<section><tid>1808441</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such regulations may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1994396</tid>
<number>a</number>the methods of appointment, the conditions of service 
and the scales of pay of the officers and employees of 
a Food Corporation, other than the Secretary of the 
Food Corporation of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802130</tid>
<number>b</number>the duties and conduct of officers and employees of a 
Food Corporation, other than the Secretary aforesaid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>653423</tid>
<number>c</number>the functions and duties which may be entrusted or 
delegated to the mananging director or, as the case may 
be, the General Manager, of a Food Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1224154</tid>
<number>d</number>the times and places at which meetings of a Food 
Corporation or any committee thereof shall be held and 
the procedure to be followed thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>354875</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees and allowances payable to the members of a 
committee under sub- section (6) of section 14 or sub- 
section (6) of section 24;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1552979</tid>
<number>f</number>generally, the efficient conduct of the affairs of a 
Food Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1170200</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, rescind any regulation which it has sanctioned and there- upon 
such regulation shall cease to have effect.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>95</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 53 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3. 
2 Ins. by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1133676</tid>
<number>4</number>Any regulation which may be made by the Food Corporation of 
India under this Act may be made by the Central Government within 
three months from the establishment of that Corporation and any 
regulation which may be made by a State Food Corporation under this 
Act may be made by the Food Corporation of India within three months 
from the establishment of such State Food Corporation; and any 
regulation so made may be altered or rescinded by the Food Corporation 
concerned in the exercise of its powers under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1513909</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive session aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1158623</tid>
<number>46</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Validation. No regulation made or purporting to have been 
made with retrospective effect, under section 45 before the 
commencement of the Food Corporations (Amendment) Act, <year>1982</year> shall be 
deemed to be invalid or ever to have been invalid merely on the ground 
that such regulation was made with retrospective effect and 
accordingly every such regulation and any action taken or thing done 
thereunder shall be as valid and effective as if the provisions of 
section 45, as amended by the Food Corporations (Amendment) Act, <year>1982</year>, 
were in force at all material times when such regulation was made or 
action or thing was taken or done.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 53 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4. 
2 Ins. by s. 5, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>