<act><tid>418991</tid>
<title>THE RAIPUR AND KHATTRA LAWS ACT, <year>1879</year></title>

ACT NO. 19 OF <year>1879</year>
[ 29th October, <year>1879</year>.]

An Act to amend the law in force in thanas Raipur and Khattra.

Preamble.

WHEREAS the territory comprised in the thana of Raipur (including  
  the independent police- outpost of Simlapal) and the thana of Khattra 
has been transferred from the district of Manbhum to the district of 
Bankura;

AND WHEREAS the said territory, when included in the district of 
Manbhum, formed portion of the Chota Nagpur Division, which is a 
Scheduled District under Act No. 14 of <year>1874</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (the Scheduled  
  Districts Act, <year>1874</year>);

AND WHEREAS it is expedient that the law in force in the said 
territory should be the same as the law in force in the district of 
Bankura; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1358506</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title, commencement. This Act may be called the Raipur 
and Khattra Laws Act, <year>1879</year>: and it shall come into force at once.


</article>



<article><tid>1111231</tid>
<number>2</number>Laws of Bankura to apply. Other laws repealed. All enactments 
which on the first day of October, <year>1879</year>, were in force in the district 
of Bankura and not in the said territory shall be deemed to have come 
into force in the said territory on that day; and all enactments which 
on that day were in force in the said territory and not in the 
district of Bankura shall be deemed to have been repealed on and from 
that day in the said territory.


</article>



<article><tid>1021690</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Pending proceedings.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 
 <year>1891</year> (12 of <year>1891</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1426790</tid>
<number>4</number>Territory to cease to be a Scheduled District. The said 
territory shall be deemed to have ceased to be a Scheduled District on 
the said first day of October, <year>1879</year>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>