<act><title>


THE RULES FOR THE MANUFACTURE, USE, IMPORT, 
EXPORT AND STORAGE OF HAZARDOUS MICRO-ORGANISMS/GENETICALLY ENGINEERED 
ORGANISMS OR CELLS, 19891*</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Rules for the Manufacture, Use, Import, Export and 
Storage of Hazardous Micro-Organisms/Genetically Engineered Organisms or Cells, 
1989.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules shall come 
into operation on the date to be notified for this purpose in the Official 
Gazette.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules are applicable to the manufacture, import and storage of 
micro-organisms and gene-technological products.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules shall 
apply to genetically engineered organisms/micro-organisms and cells and 
correspondingly to any substances and products and food and stuffs, etc., 
of which such cells, organisms or tissues thereof form part.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> These rules shall also 
apply to new gene-technologies apart from those referred to in clauses (ii) and 
(iv) of rule 3 and these rules shall apply to organisms/micro-organisms and 
cells generated by the utilisation of such other gene-technologies and to 
substances and products of which such organisms and cells form part.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> These rules shall be 
applicable in the following specific cases:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> sale, offers 
for sale, storage for the purpose of sale, offers and any kind of handling over 
with or without a consideration;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> exportation and 
importation of genetically engineered cells or organisms;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> production, 
manufacturing, processing, storage, import, drawing off, packaging and 
repackaging of the genetically engineered products;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> production, 
manufacture, etc., of drugs and pharmaceuticals and food stuffs, distilleries 
and tanneries, etc., which make use of micro-organisms/genetically engineered 
micro-organisms one way or the other.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> These rules shall be 
applicable to the whole of India.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context requires,—
 <section>
        <number>i</number> 
“Biotechnology” means the application of scientific and engineering principles 
to the processing of materials by biological agents to produce goods and 
services;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  “cell 
hybridisation” means the formation of live cells with new combinations of 
genetic material through the fusion of two or more cells by means of methods 
which do not occur naturally;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  “Gene 
Technology” means the application of the gene technique called genetic 
engineering, include self-cloning and deletion as well as cell hybridisation;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  “genetic 
engineering” means the technique by which heritable material which does not 
usually occur or will not occur naturally in the organism or cell concerned, 
generated outside the organism or the cell is inserted into said cell or 
organism. It shall also mean the formation of new combinations of genetic 
material by incorporation of a cell into a host cell, where they occur naturally 
(self-cloning) as well as modification of an organism or in a cell by deletion 
and removal of parts of the heritable material;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number> 
“micro-organisms” shall include all the bacteria, viruses, fungi, mycoplasma, 
cell lines, algae, protozoans and nematodes indicated in the Schedule and those 
that have not been presently known to exist in the country.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Competent 
Authorities.—
 <section>
<number>1</number> Recombinant DNA 
Advisory Committee (RDAC)
 
This Committee shall 
review developments in Biotechnology at national and international levels and 
shall recommend suitable and appropriate safety regulations for India in 
recombinant research, use and applications from time to time. The Committee 
shall function in the Department of Biotechnology.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Review Committee on 
Genetic Manipulation (RCGM) 
 
This Committee shall 
function in the Department of Biotechnology to monitor the safety related 
aspects in respect of on-going research projects and activities involving 
genetically engineered organisms/hazardous micro-organisms. The Review Committee 
on Genetic Manipulation shall include representatives of (a) Department of 
Biotechnology (b) Indian Council of Medical Research (c) Indian Council of 
Agricultural Research (d) Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (e) 
other experts in their individual capacity. Review Committee on Genetic 
Manipulation may appoint sub-groups.
 
It shall bring out manuals 
of guidelines specifying procedure for regulatory process with respect to 
activities involving genetically engineered organisms in research, use and 
applications, including industry, with a view to ensure environmental safety. 
All ongoing projects involving high risk category and controlled field 
experiments shall be reviewed to ensure that adequate precautions and 
containment conditions are followed as per the guidelines.
 
The Review Committee on 
Genetic Manipulation shall lay down procedures restricting or prohibiting 
production, sale, importation and use of such genetically engineered organisms 
or cells as are mentioned in the Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Institutional 
Bio-safety Committee (IBSC)
 
This Committee shall be 
constituted by an occupier or any person, including research institutions, 
handling micro-organisms/genetically engineered organisms. The Committee shall 
comprise the Head of the Institution, scientists engaged in DNA work, a medical 
expert and a nominee of the Department of Biotechnology. The occupier or any 
person including research institutions handling micro-organisms/genetically 
engineered organisms shall prepare, with the assistance of the Institutional 
Bio-safety Committee (IBSC) an up-to-date on-site emergency plan according to 
the manuals/guidelines of the RCGM and make available copies to the District 
Level Committee/State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee and the Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Genetic Engineering 
Approval Committee (GEAC)
 
This Committee shall 
function as a body under the Department of Environment, Forests and Wildlife for 
approval of activities involving large scale use of hazardous micro-organisms 
and recombinants in research and industrial production from the environmental 
angle. The Committee shall also be responsible for approval of proposals 
relating to release of genetically engineered organisms and products into the 
environment, including experimental field trials.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> State Biotechnology 
Co-ordination Committee (SBCC) 
 
There shall be a State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee in the States wherever necessary. It shall 
have powers to inspect, investigate and take punitive action in case of 
violation of statutory provisions through the Nodal Department and the State 
Pollution Control Board/Directorate of Health/Medical Services. The Committee 
shall review periodically the safety and control measures in the various 
industries/institutions handling genetically engineered organisms/hazardous 
micro-organisms.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> District Level 
Committee (DLC)
 
There shall be a District 
Level Biotechnology Committee (DLC) in the districts wherever necessary under 
the District Collectors to monitor the safety regulations in installations 
engaged in the use of genetically modified organisms/hazardous micro-organisms 
and its applications in the environment.
 
The District Level 
Committee or any other persons authorised in this behalf shall visit the 
installation engaged in activity involving genetically engineered organisms, 
hazardous micro-organisms, formulate an information chart, find out hazards and 
risks associated with each of these installations and co-ordinate activities 
with a view to meeting any emergency. They shall also prepare an off-site 
emergency plan. The District Level Committee shall regularly submit its report 
to the State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee and the Genetic Engineering 
Approval Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Classification of 
micro-organisms or genetically engineered product.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of those rules, micro-organisms or genetically engineered 
organisms, products or cells shall be dealt with under two major heads: animal 
pathogens and plant pests and these shall be classified in the manner specified 
in the Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any of the 
micro-organisms/genetically engineered organism or cell falls within the limits 
of more than risk class as specified in the Schedule, it shall be deemed to 
belong exclusively to the last in number of such classes.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Micro-organisms laid 
down in the Schedule are divided into the following.—
 <section>
        <number>i</number> Bacterial 
Agents;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number> Fungal 
Agents;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number> Parasitic 
Agents;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number> Viral, 
Rickettsial and Chlamydial Agents;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number> Special 
Category.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Approval and 
Prohibition, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall import, export, transport, manufacture, 
process, use or sell any hazardous micro-organism or genetically engineered 
organism/substance or cell except with the approval of the Genetic Engineering 
Approval Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Use of pathogenic 
micro-organism or any genetically engineered organism or cell for the purpose of 
research shall only be allowed in laboratories or inside laboratory areas 
notified by the Ministry of Environment and Forests for this purpose under the 
Environment (Protection) Act, 1986.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee shall give directions to the occupier to 
determine or take measures concerning the discharge of 
micro-organisms/genetically engineered organisms or cells mentioned in the 
Schedule from the laboratories, hospitals and other areas including prohibition 
of such discharges and laying down measures to be taken to prevent such 
discharges.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person operating 
or using genetically engineered organisms/micro-organisms mentioned in the 
Schedule for scale up or pilot operations shall have to obtain licence issued by 
the Genetic Engineering Approval Committee for any such activity. The possessor 
shall have to apply for licence in the prescribed proforma.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Certain experiments 
for the purpose of education within the field of gene technology or 
micro-organism may be carried outside the laboratories and laboratory areas 
mentioned in sub-rule (2) and will be looked after by the Institutional 
Bio-safety Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Production.—Production 
in which genetically engineered organisms or cells or micro-organisms are 
generated or used shall not be commenced except with the consent of Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee with respect to the discharge of genetically 
engineered organisms or cells into the environment. This shall also apply to 
production taking place in connection with development, testing and experiments 
where such production, etc., is not subject to rule 7.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Deliberate or 
unintentional release.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Deliberate or unintentional release of genetically engineered 
organisms/hazardous micro-organisms or cells, including deliberate release for 
the purpose of experiment shall not be allowed.
 
Note.—Deliberate 
release shall mean any intentional transfer of genetically engineered 
organisms/hazardous micro-organisms or cells to the environment or nature, 
irrespective of the way in which it is done.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee may in special cases give approval of deliberate 
release.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Permission and 
approval for certain substances.—Substances 
and products, which contain genetically engineered organisms or cells or 
micro-organisms shall not be produced, sold, imported or used except with the 
approval of the Genetic Engineering Approval Committee.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Permission and 
approval for food stuffs.—Food 
stuffs, ingredients in food stuffs and additives, including processing aids, 
containing or consisting of genetically engineered organisms or cells, shall not 
be produced, sold, imported or used except with the approval of the Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Guidelines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who applies for approval under rules 8-11 shall, as determined by the 
Genetic Engineering Approval Committee submit information and make examinations 
or cause examinations to be made to elucidate the case, including examinations 
according to specific directions and at specific laboratories. He shall also 
make available an on-site emergency plan to the Genetic Engineering Approval 
Committee before obtaining the approval. If the authority itself makes an 
examination, it may order the applicant to defray the expenses incurred by it in 
doing so.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person to whom an 
approval has been granted under rules 8-11 above shall notify the Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee of any change in or addition to information 
already submitted.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Grant of Approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In connection with the granting of approval under rules 8-11 above, terms and 
conditions shall be stipulated, including terms and conditions as to the control 
to be exercised by the applicant, supervisions, restriction on use, the layout 
of the enterprise and as to the submission of information to the State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee or to the District Level Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All approvals of the 
Genetic Engineering Approval Committee shall be for a specified period not 
exceeding four years at the first instance renewable for 2 years at a time. The 
Genetic Engineering Approval Committee shall have powers to revoke such approval 
in the following situations:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if there is 
any new information as to the harmful effects of the genetically engineered 
organisms or cells;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> if the 
genetically engineered organisms or cells cause such damage to the environment, 
nature or health as could not be envisaged when the approval was given; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> non-compliance 
of any condition stipulated by the Genetic Engineering Approval Committee.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Supervision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Genetic Engineering Approval Committee may supervise the implementation of 
the terms and conditions laid down in connection with the approvals accorded by 
it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee may carry out this supervision through the State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee or the State Pollution Control 
Board/District Level Committee or through any person authorised in this behalf.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If an order is not complied with, the District Level Committee or State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee may take measures at the expense of the 
person who is responsible.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case where 
immediate intervention is required in order to prevent any damage to the 
environment, nature or health, the District Level Committee or State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee may take the necessary steps without 
issuing any orders or notice. The expenses incurred for this purpose will be 
repayable by the person responsible for such damage.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee/District Level Committee may take samples 
for a more detailed examination of organisms and cells.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State 
Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee/District Level Committee shall be 
competent to ask for assistance from any other Government authority to carry out 
its instructions.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Responsibility to 
notify interruption or accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who under rules 7-11 is responsible for conditions or arrangements 
shall immediately notify the District Level Committee, State Biotechnology 
Co-ordination Committee and the state medical officer of any interruption of 
operations or accidents that may lead to discharges of genetically engineered 
organisms or cells which may be harmful to the environment, nature of health or 
involve any danger thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any notice given under 
sub-rule (1) above shall not lessen the duty of the person who is responsible to 
try effectively to minimise or prevent the effects of interruption of operations 
or accidents.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Preparation of 
Off-site Emergency Plan by the DLC.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the DLC to prepare an off-site emergency plan detailing 
how emergencies relating to a possible major accident at a site will be dealt 
with and in preparing the plan, the DLC shall consult the occupier and such 
other person as it may deem necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
enabling the DLC to prepare the emergency plan required under sub-rule (1), the 
occupier shall provide the DLC with such information relating to the handling of 
hazardous micro-organisms/genetically engineered organisms under his control as 
the DLC may require, including the nature, extent and likely off-site effects of 
a possible major accident and the DLC shall provide the occupier with any 
information from the off-site emergency plan which relates to his duties under 
rule 16.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Inspection and 
information regarding finance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee or the Genetic Engineering 
Approval Committee/ the DLC or any person with special knowledge duly authorised 
by the State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee or the Genetic Engineering 
Approval Committee or the DLC where it is deemed necessary, at any time on due 
production of identity be admitted to public as well as to private premises and 
localities for the purpose of carrying out supervision.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person who is 
responsible for activities subject to rules 7-11 above shall at the request of 
District Level Committee or State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee or the 
Genetic Engineering Approval Committee submit all such information, including 
information relating to financial conditions and accounts, as is essential to 
the authority’s administration under these rules. He shall also follow 
supervision or inspection by the authorities or persons indicated in sub-rule 
(1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Genetic 
Engineering Approval Committee may fix fees to cover, in whole or in part, the 
expenses incurred by the authorities in connection with approvals, examinations, 
supervision and control.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by a decision made by the Genetic Engineering Approval 
Committee/State Biotechnology Co-ordination Committee in pursuance of these 
rules may within thirty days from the date on which the decision is communicated 
to him, prefer an appeal to such authority as may be appointed by the Ministry 
of Environment and Forests provide that the Appellate Authority may entertain 
the appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days if such authority 
is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing 
the appeal in time.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Exemption.—The 
Ministry of Environment and Forests shall, wherever necessary, exempt an 
occupier handling a particular micro-organism/genetically engineered organism 
from rules 7-11.
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>