<act><tid>1886473</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR EXPORT PROMOTION ACT, <year>1958</year></title>

ACT NO. 30 OF <year>1958</year>
[ 16th September, <year>1958</year>.]

An Act to provide for the export of sugar in the public interest and 
for the levy and collection in certain circumstances of an additional 
duty of excise on sugar produced in India.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1353450</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>709011</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Sugar  
Export Promotion Act, <year>1958</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>766537</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1937088</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>915826</tid>
<number>a</number>" export" means taking out of India by sea, land or air;

</section>

<section><tid>1580018</tid>
<number>b</number>" export agency" means any such agency as may be 
specified in this behalf under section 3, and when no 
such agency has been so specified, the Central 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>88876</tid>
<number>c</number>" export quota" means the export quota referred to in 
section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>929425</tid>
<number>d</number>" factory" means any premises (including the precincts  
  thereof) wherein sugar is being produced by the vacuum 
pan process;

</section>

<section><tid>1400361</tid>
<number>e</number>" owner"--

<subsection><tid>746783</tid>
<number>i</number>with reference to any factory the possession 
of which has been transferred by lease, mortgage or 
otherwise, means the transferee so long as his right to 
possession subsists,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>196682</tid>
<number>ii</number>with reference to any factory for which an 
agent, by whatever name called, is employed, means the 
agent, if, and in so far as, he has been duly 
authorised by the owner in that behalf, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1465166</tid>
<number>iii</number>with reference to any factory the management 
of which has been taken over by any person or body of 
persons under the Industries (Development and 

<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

  Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>), means that person 
or body of persons;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>858737</tid>
<number>f</number>" sugar" means any form of sugar containing more than 
ninety per cent. of sucrose;

</section>

<section><tid>445894</tid>
<number>g</number>" year" means the year beginning on the first day of May.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1465235</tid>
<number> 3</number> Export agency.
<section><tid>1339894</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of this Act, the Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify as an 
export agency any company within the meaning of the Companies Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or any body of persons established or recognised as 
a body corporate by or under any other law for the time being in 
force.

</section>

<section><tid>846121</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such company or other body corporate has been 
specified as an export agency, it shall be lawful for such agency to 
perform all or any of the functions of an export agency under this 
Act, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
memorandum or articles of association of the company or, as the case 
may be, the law applicable thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>666933</tid>
<number> 4</number> Fixation of quantity of sugar for purposes of export.
<section><tid>1137830</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, fix 
from time to time the quantity of sugar which may be exported during 
any period, and, in fixing such quantity, the Central Government shall 
have regard to--

<subsection><tid>1164645</tid>
<number>a</number>the quantity of sugar available in India,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>363055</tid>
<number>b</number>the quantity of sugar which, in its opinion, would be 
reasonably required for consumption in India,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>746446</tid>
<number>c</number>the necessity for exporting sugar with a view to earning 
foreign exchange in the public interest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1680648</tid>
<number>2</number>The power conferred by sub- section (1) shall be so exercised 
as to ensure that the quantity fixed under that sub- section for any 
year does not exceed in the aggregate twenty per cent. of the quantity 
of sugar produced in India in the season ending with the month of 
October falling within that year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1430744</tid>
<number>5</number>Export quotas for factories. The Central Government shall, by 
order in writing, apportion the quantity of sugar fixed from time to 
time for purposes of export under section 4 among the owners in 
proportion to the quantity of sugar produced, or likely to be 
produced, by them respectively during the season referred to in sub- 
section (2) of section 4, and such order shall be communicated to each 
of the owners, and the quantity so apportioned shall be deemed to be 
the export quota for the factory of that owner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>57</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1168664</tid>
<number> 6</number> Liability of owner to deliver export quota to export agency.

<section><tid>468812</tid>
<number>1</number>Every owner shall, on demand by the export agency, deliver to it  
from time to time sugar produced in his factory in such quantities 
 (not exceeding in the aggregate his export quota fixed for the factory  
  or group of factories, as the case may be), of such grade, in such 
manner, within such time and at such place, as may be specified by the 
export agency in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>228886</tid>
<number>2</number>When sugar has been delivered by an owner in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- section (1), the owner shall retain no rights in 
respect of such sugar except his right to receive payment therefor 
under section 9.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1448349</tid>
<number> 7</number> Levy of additional excise duty on sugar.
<section><tid>1328345</tid>
<number>1</number>Where sugar  
delivered by any owner falls short of the export quota fixed for it by 
any quantity (hereinafter referred to as the said quantity), there 
shall be levied and collected on so much of the sugar despatched from 
the factory for consumption in India as is equal to the said quantity, 
a duty of excise at the rate of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> forty- five rupees and fifty- five 
naye paise per quintal].

</section>

<section><tid>496860</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise referred to in sub- section (1) be in 
addition to the duty of excise chargeable on sugar under any other law 
for the time being in force, and be paid by the owner to such 
authority as may be specified in the notice demanding the payment of 
duty and within such period not exceeding ninety days as may be 
specified in such notice.

</section>

<section><tid>415834</tid>
<number>3</number>If any such owner does not pay the whole or any part of the 
duty payable by him within the period referred to in sub- section (2), 
he shall be liable to pay in respect of every period of thirty days or 
part thereof during which the default continues a penalty which may 
extend to ten per cent. of the duty outstanding from time to time, the 
penalty being adjudged in the same manner as the penalty to which a 
person is liable under the rules made under the Central Excises and 
Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>), is adjudged.

</section>

<section><tid>205139</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1  
  of <year>1944</year>), and the rules made thereunder, including those relating to 
refunds and exemptions from duty, shall, so far a may be, apply in 
relation to the levy and collection of the duty of excise or any other 
sum referred to in this section as they apply in relation to he levy 
and collection of the duty on sugar or other sums of money payable to 
the Central Government under that Act or the rules made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>503090</tid>
<number> 8</number> Sale by export agency of sugar delivered.
<section><tid>577710</tid>
<number>1</number>The export  
agency shall take all practical measures to export sugar delivered to 
it under this Act:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1960</year>, s. 8, for" seventeen rupees per maund" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that, if the export agency is of opinion that having 
regard to the quality of the sugar delivered to it by any owner, or to 
the expenses involved in transporting the sugar from one place to 
another, or to the delay likely to be involved in exporting it, or to 
the conditions prevailing in the markets for sugar, whether in or out 
of India, or to any other relevant circumstance, it is expedient so to 
do, the export agency may sell the whole or any part of the sugar in 
India and may, if it thinks fit, purchase such quantity of sugar as it 
may consider necessary for export at the appropriate time.


</section>

<section><tid>1906922</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the export agency may 
itself sell sugar or permit the owner to sell the whole or any part of 
the export quota in his custody at a prise approved by it on condition 
that the sale- proceeds are payable to it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>770684</tid>
<number> 9</number> Payments to owners in respect of sugar delivered.
<section><tid>910968</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
export agency shall, at such time as it thinks fit, make to the owners 
who have delivered sugar to it under this Act, payments determined in 
accordance with the provisions hereinafter in this section contained.

</section>

<section><tid>1651130</tid>
<number>2</number>From the total sale- proceed in respect of the quantity fixed 
for export under section 4 for any year, there shall be deducted the 
total expenditure incurred by the export agency in respect of the 
sugar, whether by way of administrative expenses or otherwise, and the 
balance shall be apportioned among the owners in proportion to the 
quantity of sugar delivered by them respectively during that year.

</section>

<section><tid>1060364</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any distribution under this section, the export 
agency shall make such adjustments as may be necessary having regard 
to the grade of sugar delivered by any owner, the adjustments being 
made on the basis of sugar of ISS- E- 29 grade and with reference to the 
price differential schedule for different grades of sugar which the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
publish in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1346651</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section and 
subject to the rules which may be made in this behalf, the export 
agency may make on account payments to owners against documents of 
delivery of sugar furnished by them, and such payments shall be 
adjusted at the time of final payment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>749424</tid>
<number>10</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. The export 
agency specified under section 3 shall be bound, in the discharge of 
its functions under this Act, by such general or special directions, 
as the Central Government may give to it in writing.


</article>



<article><tid>758156</tid>
<number>11</number>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct, that any power conferred 
on it by this Act shall,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the 
notification, be exercisable also by such officer or authority 
subordinate to the Central Government as may be specified in the 
notification.



</article>



<article><tid>1869860</tid>
<number>12</number>Protection of action taken under Act. No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the export agency or the 
Central Government or any of its officers for or in respect of 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1143627</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>193324</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1121817</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all any of the following 
matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1684457</tid>
<number>a</number>the submission by owners to such authority as may be 
specified in this behalf, of returns or reports or 
other information relating to the manufacture, sale, 
despatch, stocks and prices of sugar;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1308433</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which the accounts of the export agency 
may be maintained and audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1014057</tid>
<number>c</number>the inspection of records and registers of factories and 
the export agency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488691</tid>
<number>d</number>the making of payments by the export agency to owners;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985033</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1551776</tid>
<number>3</number>In making a rule under this section, the Central Government 
may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to five thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>64617</tid>
<number>4</number>All rules made under this Act shall be laid for not less than 
thirty days before each House or Parliament as soon as may be after 
they are made and shall be subject to such modifications as Parliament 
may make during the session in which they are so laid or the session 
immediately following.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537989</tid>
<number>14</number>[ Repeal and saving.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 
 <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

</article>



 </act>