<act><title>


THE CINEMATOGRAPH (CERTIFICATION) RULES, 19831</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Cinematograph (Certification) Rules, 1983.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on 1st day of June, 1983.
 





 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    “Act” means the Cinematograph Act, 1952 
    (37 of 1952); 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    “advisory panel” means the advisory 
    panel of the Board constituted under Rule 7; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    “applicant” means a person applying 
    for certification of a film for public exhibition under section 4; 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    “Assistant Regional Officer” means an 
    assistant regional officer appointed under Rule 9 and includes the Secretary 
    to Chairman; 
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    “Board” means the Board of Film 
    Certification constituted under section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Board; 
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    “Chief Executive Officer” means a 
    Chief Executive Officer appointed under Rule 9; 
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>    “Examining Officer” means a
    <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Chief 
    Executive Officer or] a Regional Officer or an Additional Regional Officer 
    or an Assistant Regional Officer, or the Secretary to Chairman or such other 
    officer who is a member of the examining committee appointed under sub-rule 
    (1) of Rule 22; 
 

2[(ix)    
    “feature film” means fictionalized story film exceeding 2000 metres in 
    length in 35 mm or corresponding length in other gauges or on video;] 
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>    “imported” means bringing into India 
    from a place outside India; 
 
3[(xi)    
    “long” film is a film with a length exceeding 2000 metres in 35 mm or 
    corresponding length in other gauges or compact video disc;] 
 <subsection>
<number>xii</number>    “member” means a member of the Board 
    and includes the Chairman; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiii</number>    “Regional Officer” means a Regional 
    Officer appointed under Rule 9 and includes a Chief Executive Officer, an 
    Additional Regional Officer and an Assistant Regional Officer, or such other 
    officer appointed under that rule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiv</number>    “Secretary to the Tribunal” means the 
    officer of Government appointed to function as the Secretary to the 
    Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (7) of section 5D; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xv</number>    “Section” means a section of the Act; 
 
4[(xvi)    
    “short film” means a film with a length upto and including 2000 metres in 
    length in 35mm or corresponding length in other gauges or on video tape or 
    compact video disc;]. 
 

 
 






</subsection></section></article> 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Terms of 
    office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A member of the Board shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (1), the Chairman shall hold office for a period 
    of three years and shall continue to hold office until his successor is 
    appointed:  
 
Provided that 
    pending the appointment of his successor the Central Government may appoint 
    another person to act as Chairman for a period not exceeding one year.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (1); every other member shall hold office for a 
    period not exceeding three years.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A retiring 
    member or a member whose term of office has expired by efflux of time shall 
    be eligible for re-appointment.  
</section></article> 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>3A</number> 
    Representation of women in the Board.—The 
    Central Government may take such steps as it thinks fit to appoint women 
    members in the Board so that there is due representation for women.]  
 
 




</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Casual 
    vacancy.—A casual vacancy caused 
    in the Board by resignation, death or removal of a member or otherwise shall 
    be filled by the appointment of another member who shall hold office for the 
    full term of membership provided under sub-rule (3) of Rule 3. 
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Headquarters.—Unless otherwise 
    directed by the Central Government, the headquarters of the Board shall be 
    at Bombay. 
</article> 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>6</number> Temporary 
    absence of Chairman.—Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, 
    when the Chairman is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, 
    illness or any other cause, the Central Government may nominate a member of 
    the Board who will discharge the functions of the Chairman until the 
    Chairman resumes his duties:]  
 
Provided that 
    where no such appointment is made, the Chief Executive Officer or the 
    Regional Officer at Bombay shall, in addition to his other duties, exercise 
    the powers and perform the duties of the Chairman and shall have the right 
    to participate in the meetings of the Board, but shall not be entitled to 
    preside at any meetings.  
 
 



</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Constitution of advisory panels.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall constitute an advisory panel at each of the 
    regional offices of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    advisory panel constituted under sub-rule (1) shall consist of such number 
    of members as the Central Government may, after consultation with the Board, 
    determine.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, after consultation with the Board, appoint any 
    person whom it thinks fit to be a member of an advisory panel:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may dispense with such consultation in respect of 
    such number of members not exceeding one-third of the total number of the 
    members of the advisory panel, as that Government thinks fit:  
 


    1[Provided further 
    that there shall be due representation to women in an advisory panel.]  
 
 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Term of 
    office of members of advisory panels.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A member of an advisory panel shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
    Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (1), every such member shall hold office for a 
    period not exceeding two years:  
 
Provided that 
    any person holding office as a member immediately before the commencement of 
    these rules shall hold such office only for the remainder of the term for 
    which he was appointed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A retiring 
    member or a member whose term of office has expired by efflux of time shall 
    be eligible for re-appointment.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A casual 
    vacancy in an advisory panel caused by the resignation, death or removal of 
    any member or otherwise shall be filled by fresh appointment and the person 
    so appointed shall hold office for a period not exceeding two years.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government may remove from office any member of an advisory panel 
    before the expiration of his term of office:  
 
Provided that 
    a member appointed to an advisory panel after consultation with the Board 
    shall not be so removed except on the recommendation of or after 
    consultation with the Board. 
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Officers 
    of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose 
    of enabling the Board to perform its functions under the Act, the Central 
    Government may appoint a Chief Executive Officer, Regional Officers, 
    Additional Regional Officers, Assistant Regional Officers and such other 
    officers at the headquarters and at each of the regional offices of the 
    Board:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may delegate to the Chairman/Chief Executive Officer 
    subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified by 
    it, the power of appointment conferred on it under this sub-rule other than 
    the powers of appointment in relation to the posts of Regional Officer and 
    Additional Regional Officer:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Chairman/Chief Executive Officer may grant leave to or 
    suspend or remove from service any officer appointed by him under the powers 
    delegated to him under this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Regional Officers, Additional Regional Officers, Assistant Regional Officers 
    and other officers appointed under sub-rule (1) shall perform such duties as 
    may be assigned to them under these rules, or by the Chairman/Chief 
    Executive Officer or by the Board. 
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Duties 
    of the Board.—The Board shall, in 
    addition to other duties prescribed under these rule,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    submit an annual report to the Central 
    Government reviewing the work done by the Board during the preceding 
    financial year and the report shall contain a detailed analytical study of 
    the trends in film industry;  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    prescribe the manner in which the 
    registers, records and accounts of the Board shall be kept; and  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    review the work of Regional Officers 
    and members of the Advisory Panels. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>11</number> 
Assessment of public reactions to films.—With a view to determining the principles to be 
observed in certifying films, the Board may take such steps as it thinks fit to 
assess public reactions to films, and for that purpose, the Board may hold 
symposia or seminars of film critics, film writers, community leaders and 
persons engaged in the film industry, or such other persons and also undertake 
local or national surveys to study the impact of various kinds of films on the 
public mind.</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Terms 
    and conditions of service (other than salary and allowances) of the Chairman 
    of the Board and allowances payable to the other members of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairman, if he is a paid full-time officer, shall be entitled to draw 
    travelling and daily allowances as admissible under the Fundamental and 
    Supplementary Rules and shall be entitled to leave and leave salary and such 
    other benefits and shall be governed by such conditions of service as are 
    applicable to Central Government officers engaged on contract: 
 
Provided that 
    in the case of an officer of an All India or Central Civil or General 
    Central Service or State Service being appointed as Chairman he shall be 
    entitled to leave and leave salary and other benefits admissible to officers 
    of such service so long as he continues to belong to that service:  
 
Provided 
    further that if an officer who has already been holding a post under 
    Government on contract with the benefits of Contributory Provident Fund is 
    appointed as Chairman, he shall be allowed to carry forward the unutilized 
    portion of leave earned by him during previous service and he shall also 
    continue to be eligible for the Contributory Provident Fund benefits.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    honorary member (including the Chairman where he does not receive any 
    salary) may,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if he is an out-station member,  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    travel by air or by train as admissible 
    according to the orders issued by the Central Government from time to time 
    in respect of journeys undertaken by him for the performance of his duties 
    as such members;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    be paid a consultancy fee for 
    attending the preview of a film or meeting of the Revising Committee or the 
    Board at the rate of Rs. 75 for each day of such preview or meeting;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    be paid daily allowance at the rate 
    of Rs. 50 per day for the day preceding the meeting and that following the 
    meeting, if the member actually stays at the place of the meeting;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if he is a local member, be paid a 
    consultancy fee for attending the preview of a film or meeting of the 
    Revising Committee or the Board at the rate of Rs. 50 for each day of such 
    preview or meeting:  
 
Provided that 
    daily allowance will not be admissible in addition for the day or days for 
    which consultancy fee is paid.  
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Allowances payable to members of the advisory panel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every member of the advisory panel shall be entitled to draw travelling and 
    daily allowances for journeys performed by him for attending the meetings of 
    the Board outside the headquarters or for the purpose of discharging any 
    other duties prescribed under the Act on the scale provided under the 
    Fundamental and Supplementary Rules applicable to First Grade officers of 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    member of the advisory panel shall be entitled to receive a consultancy fee 
    for attending a preview of film or a meeting of the Committee or Panel or 
    for verification of cuts and affected reels at the rate of Rs. 50 per diem, 
    provided that daily allowance in terms of (1) above will not be admissible 
    in addition for the day or days for which consultancy fee is paid.  
 


    1[(3) Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-rules (1) and (2), if any member of the advisory 
    panel is a Member of Parliament, he shall not be entitled to any 
    remuneration other than the allowances defined in clause (a) of section 2 of 
    the Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959 (10 of 1959).  
 
 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Meetings of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board shall ordinarily meet once a quarter for the transaction of business 
    but the Chairman may at any time call an extraordinary meeting, if he 
    considers it necessary to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Meetings 
    of the Board shall be held at such places as the Chairman may at his 
    discretion fix for the purpose.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Co-opted members.—The Chairman 
    may co-opt the Chief Executive Officer or any one or more of the Regional 
    Officers or any officer of the Central Government as a member or members of 
    the Board for the purpose of attending a particular meeting of the Board and 
    such officer or officers shall then be entitled to participate in the 
    deliberations of the Board at that meeting but shall not be entitled to 
    vote.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Notice of meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At least 

    1[twenty-one clear 
    days’] notice of all meetings of the Board shall be given to each member but 
    an urgent meeting may be called by the Chairman at three clear days’ notice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice 
    shall state the business to be transacted at the meetings and no business 
    other than that stated shall be transacted at such meeting except with the 
    consent of the Chairman or on his motion. 
 
 
 

 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>17</number> 
Business ordinarily to be transacted at meetings.—The business of the Board shall ordinarily be 
transacted at a meeting duly called in accordance with the provisions of these 
rules:
 Provided 
that the Chairman may, if he thinks fit, circulate any urgent matter among the 
members for their opinion.</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Quorum.—At 
    every meeting of the Board four members if the Chairman be present, and six 
    members if he be absent, shall form a quorum.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    President of the meeting.—Meetings 
    of the Board shall be presided over by the Chairman or in his absence by a 
    member elected by the members present from among themselves.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Question to be decided by majority of votes.—Every 
    question before the Board shall be decided by a majority of votes and in the 
    case of equality of votes, the Chairman or the member elected to preside 
    under Rule 19, as the case may be, shall have a second or casting vote. 
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Application for examination of films.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application to certify a film for public exhibition shall be made in 
    writing in 

    1[Form I or Form IA or 
    Form II or Form IIA, as the case may be,] set out in the Second Schedule 
    according as the film is produced in or imported into India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    application shall be addressed to the Board and delivered to the Regional 
    Officer concerned as per the First Schedule:  
 
Provided that 
    where films are imported into India, the Chairman may direct or permit 
    applications in respect of them to be delivered to a Regional Officer other 
    than the Regional Officer to whom such applications would have been 
    delivered but for this proviso:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Chairman may in the following circumstances direct or 
    permit applications in respect of any films or class of films to be 
    delivered to a Regional Officer other than the Regional Officer to whom such 
    applications would have been delivered but for this proviso, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    where the Chairman is satisfied that 
    immediate action for examination of a film is necessary; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    where examination of a film with the 
    assistance of persons well acquainted with the language of the film is not 
    possible at the place where, but for the provisions of this proviso, it 
    would have been delivered for examination; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    for such other reasons as may be 
    specified by the Chairman in writing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every such 
    application shall be accompanied by—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the fee prescribed under Rule 36;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    eight copies in the case of feature 
    films and five copies in the case of other films, of the synopsis of the 
    film, together with full credit titles and of the full text of the songs if 
    any with reel number, one copy of complete shooting script as prescribed and 
    a statement showing the reelwise length of the film:  
 
Provided that where the film is in a language 
    other than English or any Indian language, the applicant shall furnish eight 
    typed or printed copies of the translation in English or Hindi of the 
    synopsis and of the full text of the songs, if any, and one copy of the 
    translation in English or Hindi of dialogues:  
 
Provided further that in the case of a 
    film referred to in the preceding proviso, the Regional Officer may direct 
    the applicant to furnish also eight typed or printed copies of the 
    translation in English or Hindi of the full text of the dialogue, speeches 
    or commentary; 
2[***]  
 

3[(bb)    
    a declaration made in writing by the producer of the film declaring that no 
    cruelty was caused to the animals used during shooting of the films produced 
    in India.  
 
Explanation-1.—For the purposes of this 
    clause—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    “animal” shall have the meaning 
    assigned to it in clause (a) of section 2 of the Prevention of Cruelty to 
    Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 1960);  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    “cruelty” means treating the animals 
    in any manner specified in clauses (a) to (o) of sub-section (1) of section 
    11 of the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 1960);]  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    If the application is made for 
    the purpose of a fresh certificate under sub-rule (2) of Rule 29, the 
    original certificate or duplicate certificate; 
3[and]  
 

4[(d)    
    if the application is made by a person other than the producer or copyright 
    holder of the film, an authorization in writing on a stamped paper of 
    appropriate value to be notified by the Chairman from the producer or 
    copyright holder of the film.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If, in the 
    case of a newsreel, documentary or other short film if the Regional Officer 
    is satisfied that the applicant is not able to furnish the documents 
    specified in sub-rule (3) along with the application for reasons beyond his 
    control, the Regional Officer may direct that such documents may be 
    furnished within such period after the examination of the film as he may 
    specify or that the submission of such documents may be dispensed with.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No such 
    application shall be accompanied by any documents other than those mentioned 
    in sub-rule (3).  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-rules, in the case 
    of a film which is imported,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the applicant shall furnish the 
    original or a certified copy of the import licence together with the customs 
    clearance permit and with the customs clearance papers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where there is a doubt or dispute 
    about the validity or genuineness of the documents referred to in clause 
    (a), the Board may before the application is considered refer such documents 
    for ascertaining their validity or genuineness to the authority which issued 
    the same; 
5[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Board shall not take any steps for 
    certification of a film in a case where any matter regarding the validity of 
    the documents referred to in clause (b) is pending before any court or any 
    public authority until the disposal of such matter by the court or 
    authority; and  
 

6[(d)    
    such film shall not be examined by the Board for certification for public 
    exhibition in India unless the Board is satisfied that the film is validly 
    imported in accordance with the import policy of the Government.]  
 

    Explanation.—For the purpose of 
    certification for public exhibition every revised version or shorter version 
    of a film shall be deemed to be a fresh film.  
 
 








</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Examining committee.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
    receipt of an application under Rule 21, the Regional Officer shall appoint 
    an Examining Committee to examine the film. The examination shall be made at 
    the cost of the applicant on such date, at such place and at such time as 
    the Regional Officer may determine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Examining Committee shall consist of,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in the case of a short film, a 
    member of the advisory panel and an examining officer 
1[either 
    of whom shall be a women]; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the case of a long film, four 
    members of the advisory panel and an examining officer 
1[of 
    whom two persons shall be women]:  
 
Provided that 
    if the examining officer is unavoidably absent at the examination of a film, 
    the Examining Committee shall consist of two members of the advisory panel 
    in a case falling under clause (a) and five members of the advisory panel in 
    a case falling under clause (b):  
 


    2[Provided further 
    that in the Examining Committee, in a case falling under clause (a) one 
    member shall be a woman and in a case falling under clause (b) two members 
    shall be women.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The film 
    to be examined by the Examining Committee shall be in its final form with 
    the background music and all sound effects duly recorded on the film itself.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    previews of films for the purposes of examination for certification and the 
    reports and records relating thereto shall be treated as confidential.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The names 
    of the members of the Examining Committee examining the film shall not be 
    disclosed to any official or non-official not concerned with the preview of 
    the particular film or to any other person including the applicant or his 
    representative.  
 


    3[(5A) Nothing in 
    sub-rules (4) and (5) shall affect the disclosure of names of persons in the 
    certificate granted by the Board.]  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    applicant or his representative shall not be allowed to be present inside 
    the preview theatre.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rules (4), (5) and (6) the 
    Chairman may by special or general order permit any member of the staff to 
    be present at the preview to render such assistance as may be required.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Examining Commitee shall examine the film having regard to the principles 
    for guidance in certifying films specified in section 5B(1) and the 
    guidelines issued by Government under section 5B(2).  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> 
    Immediately after the examination of the film each member of the Examining 
    Committee attending the examination shall, before leaving the preview 
    theatre record his opinion in writing in Form VIII set out in the Second 
    Schedule spelling out in clear terms the reasons therefor and state whether 
    he or she considers,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the film is suitable for 
    unrestricted public exhibition, i.e., fit for ‘U’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the film is suitable for 
    unrestricted public exhibition but with an endorsement of caution that the 
    question as to whether any child below the age of 12 years may be allowed to 
    see the film should be considered by the parents or guardian of such child,
    i.e., fit for ‘UA’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the film is suitable for public 
    exhibition restricted to adults, i.e., fit for ‘A’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that the film is suitable for public 
    exhibition restricted to members of any profession or any class of persons 
    having regard to the nature, content and theme of the film, i.e., fit 
    for ‘S’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    that the film is suitable for ‘U’ or 
    ‘UA’ or ‘S’ certificate, as the case may be, if a specified portion or 
    portions be excised or modified therefrom; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    that the film is not suitable for 
    unrestricted or restricted public exhibitions, i.e., that the film be 
    refused a certificate,  
 
and if the Chairman is away from the regional 
    centre where the film is examined, the form aforesaid shall be prepared in 
    duplicate.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    examining officer shall distribute copies of the synopsis with credit titles 
    and, songs among the members of the Committee and furnish them the form and 
    such other documents as may be specified by the Board for making their 
    recommendation.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> After the 
    screening of the film, the examining officer shall see that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the recommendation of every member of 
    the Committee is recorded in unambiguous terms and each excision or 
    modification is properly specified in clear terms with reason or reasons 
    therefor;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the same is duly signed by the members 
    of the Committee; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where the report of any member of the 
    Committee is incomplete, that fact is brought to the notice of the member 
    concerned before he leaves the preview theatre.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>12</number> The 
    examining officer shall within three working days send the recommendations 
    of all the members of the Examining Committee to the Chairman and the 
    Chairman is away from the centre where the film is examined, by registered 
    post.  
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> It shall 
    be the personal responsibility of the examining officer to examine whether 
    each and every guideline issued by Government has been followed and to bring 
    any lapse or deviation to the notice of the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> The 
    quorum for the Examining Committee for a long film shall be four 


    4[of whom at least two 
    persons shall be women.]  
 
 
 
 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Certification.—On receipt of the 
    record referred to in sub-rule (12) of Rule 22, the Chairman, unless the 
    provisions of sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of Rule 24 are attracted, direct the Regional 
    Officer concerned to take further action on behalf of the Board in 
    conformity with the recommendation of the Examining Committee either 
    unanimous or by majority:  
 
Provided that 
    in case of a short film when the Committee is divided in its opinion, the 
    Chairman shall either examine the film himself and take, or direct the 
    Regional Officer concerned to take further action on behalf of the Board to 
    give effect to his decision.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Revising Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
    receipt of the record referred to in Rule 22, the Chairman may, of his own 
    motion or on the request of the applicant, refer it to a Revising Committee 
    constituted for the purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Revising Committee shall, subject to sub-rule (5), consist of a Chairman and 
    not more than nine members, being members of the Board or members of any of 
    the advisory panels, to be specified by the Chairman:  
 


    1[Provided that 
    subject to the provisions of sub-rule (11), the Chairman shall give due 
    representation to women in the Committee by nominating such number of women 
    members as he thinks fit.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman or in his absence a member of the Board nominated by the Chairman 
    shall preside at every meeting of the Revising Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Regional Officer of the Centre where the application was received under Rule 
    21, may be invited to attend any meeting of a Revising Committee and 
    participate in proceedings thereof but he shall have no right to vote 
    thereat.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No member 
    of the advisory panel who has been a member of the Examining Committee for 
    any film shall be a member of the Revising Committee in respect of the same 
    film.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    provisions of sub-rules (4) to (8) of Rule 22 shall apply mutatis 
    mutandis to the examination of films by the Revising Committee or the 
    Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Revising Committee shall examine the film at the applicant’s expense, on 
    such date, at such place and at such time, as the Chairman may determine.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> For the 
    purpose of examination by a Revising Committee,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the applicant shall present the same 
    clear runnable print of the film which was shown to the Examining Committee 
    and he shall make no change whatsoever in it and he shall furnish the 
    necessary declaration in writing in that behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the applicant shall be required to 
    furnish fifteen typed or printed copies of the complete synopsis of the film 
    together with the full credit titles and of the full text of songs, if any, 
    with reel number, and where he has made a representation under sub-section 
    (2) of section 4, fifteen copies thereof shall also be furnished:  
 
Provided that 
    where the film is in a language, other than English or any Indian language, 
    the applicant shall furnish fifteen typed or printed copies of the 
    translation in English or in Hindi of the synopsis together with full credit 
    titles and of the full text of the songs, if any:  
 
Provided 
    further that in the case of a film referred to in the preceding proviso, the 
    Chairman may direct the applicant to furnish also fifteen typed or printed 
    copies of the translation in English or Hindi of the full text of the 
    dialogue, speeches or commentary:  
 
Provided also 
    that where the Chairman is satisfied that the applicant is not able to 
    furnish the documents specified in this sub-rule for reasons beyond his 
    control the Chairman may direct that the submission of such documents be 
    dispensed with.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> 
    Immediately after examination of the film, each member of the Revising 
    Committee shall before leaving the preview theatre record his 
    recommendations in writing in Form VIII set out in the Second Schedule 
    spelling out in clear terms the reasons therefor and stating whether he or 
    she considers—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the film is suitable for 
    unrestricted public exhibition, i.e., fit for ‘U’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the film is suitable for 
    unrestricted public exhibition but with an endorsement of caution that the 
    question as to whether any child below the age of twelve years may be 
    allowed to see the film should be considered by the parents or guardian of 
    such child, i.e., fit for ‘UA’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the film is suitable for public 
    exhibition restricted to adults, i.e., fit for ‘A’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that the film is suitable for public 
    exhibition restricted to members of any profession or any class of persons 
    having regard to the nature, content and theme of the film, i.e., fit 
    for ‘S’ certificate; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    that the film is suitable for grant of 
    ‘U’ or ‘UA’ or ‘A’ or ‘S’ certificate, as the case may be, if a specified 
    portion or portions be excised or modified therefrom; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    that the film is not suitable for 
    unrestricted or restricted public exhibition, i.e., that the film be 
    refused a certificate,  
 
and if the Chairman is away from the regional 
    centre where the film is examined the form aforesaid shall be prepared in 
    duplicate.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    Presiding Officer of the Revising Committee shall, within three days, send 
    the recommendations of all the members of the Revising Committee to the 
    Chairman and where the Chairman is away from the centre where the film is 
    examined, by registered post.  
 


    2[(11) The quorum of 
    the Revising Committee shall be five members of whom at least two persons 
    shall be women:  
 
Provided that 
    the number of women members shall not be less than one-half of the total 
    members of a Committee constituted under sub-rule (2).]  
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The 
    decision of a Revising Committee shall be that of the majority of the 
    members attending the examination of the film and, in the event of an 
    equality of votes, the presiding officer shall have a second or casting 
    vote:  
 
Provided that 
    where the Chairman disagrees with the decision of the majority of the 
    Committee, the Board shall itself examine the film or cause the film to be 
    examined again by another Revising Committee and that the decision of the 
    Board or the second Revising Committee, as the case may be, shall be final.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number> 
      On receipt of the orders of the Board under section 4 or section 5A, the 
      Regional Officer shall communicate the same to the applicant by registered 
      post or in such other manner as in the circumstances of the case he deems 
      fit and take such other steps in accordance with the said orders as he may 
      deem necessary.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Issue 
    of certificate subject to removal of portions of film.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the applicant is informed by a Regional Officer that a film will not 
    be granted ‘U’ or ‘UA’ or ‘A’ or ‘S’ certificate, as the case may be, unless 
    a specified portion or portions thereof be removed from the film, the 
    Regional Officer may issue such a certificate, if he is satisfied on a 
    declaration made in writing (in Form IX set out in Second Schedule) by the 
    applicant that the portion or portions objected to have been excised from 
    the negative of the film and from all copies thereof, whether in the 
    possession of the applicant or the laboratory where the film was processed, 
    the distributor, the exhibitor or any other person and surrendered to him.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purpose of 
    being satisfied that the portion or portions objected to have been excised 
    from the negative of the film and from all copies thereof,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Regional Officer or the Chairman 
    may at the expense of the applicant examine the relevant portions of the 
    negative of the film or copies thereof or cause it or them to be examined by 
    one or more members of the advisory panel at such time and place as he may 
    determine;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the Regional Officer may require the 
    applicant to produce a certificate from the owner or the manager of the 
    laboratory where the film was processed, in such form as may be specified by 
    the Board in this behalf in regard to the number of positive and negative 
    copies of the film made in the laboratory.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    certificate issued under sub-rule (1) shall be endorsed with a specification 
    of the portion or portions required to be removed and a statement of the 
    exact length of each part or parts removed and in the case of reduction of 
    scene or sequences, it shall mention the length of the portion reduced and 
    the length of the portion retained and shall bear a clearly visible triangle 
    drawn at the left hand bottom corner of the certificate.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    film has been granted a certificate under this rule subject to the condition 
    that a specified portion or portions thereof be removed from the film, any 
    person who imports or otherwise acquires a copy of the film after the date 
    of certificate aforesaid, shall surrender to the Board such portion or 
    portions in any such copy.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number> 
      The portion or portions of the film and of all copies surrendered to the 
      Regional Officer as provided in Rule 26 shall be preserved for a period of 
      six months in the Board’s office and unless required by the Board shall 
      thereafter be handed over to an authorized officer of the National Film 
      Archive of India, Poona for study and research.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Deposit of a copy of certified film.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the case of a feature film after 

    1[the Chairman or] the 
    Regional Officer has affixed his signature to the certificate granted under 
    the foregoing rules and prior to the delivery or despatch of the certificate 
    to the applicant, a copy in any gauge of the film as certified by the Board 
    shall be deposited by the applicant with the Board at his own expense for 
    the purpose of record.  
 

    Explanation.—A video copy of the 
    film shall be treated as a copy of the film for the purpose of this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the 
    copy deposited under sub-rule (1) the negative side number (key numbers) 
    shall be clearly printed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The copy 
    deposited under sub-rule (1) except where it is a video copy may, at the 
    discretion of the Regional Officer concerned, be returned to the applicant 
    on the expiry of one year from the date of first release of the film.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Before 
    return of the copy of the film under sub-rule (3), the applicant shall 
    deliver to the Board the full shooting script of the film together with 
    dialogues:  
 
Provided that 
    where the script as aforesaid is not delivered within one month after the 
    expiry of one year from the first release of the film, the film shall be 
    sent to the Curator of the National Film Archive of India, Poona, and the 
    applicant shall thereafter collect the same at his own expense, only after 
    obtaining a release order from the Board after delivering the script 
    aforesaid.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No 
    application for the return of the copy of film deposited with the Board in 
    exchange, for the full shooting script under the proviso to sub-rule (4) 
    shall be entertained after two years from the date of the first release of 
    the film:  
 
Provided that 
    the Chairman may, on being satisfied that there is sufficient cause for not 
    making the application within the said period of two years, entertain the 
    application before the expiry of a further period of one year.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In the 
    case of films other than feature films, that is, shorts, documentaries, 
    newsreels, advertisement films and such other films after the Regional 
    Officer has affixed his signature to the certificate granted under the 
    foregoing rules and prior to the delivery or despatch of the certificate to 
    the applicant, the applicant shall deposit with the Board a copy of the film 
    or in lieu of such deposit, the shooting script or a verbatim commentary or 
    a tape record of the commentary:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of such films where the Chairman is of the opinion that the 
    applicant for reasons beyond his control is unable to deposit a copy of the 
    film or script or verbatim commentary or tape record of that commentary 
    prior to the delivery or despatch of the certificate, he may direct that the 
    certificate be delivered to the applicant on his giving an undertaking in 
    writing that he shall deposit the said copy of the film or script or 
    verbatim commentary or tape record of the commentary within such time not 
    exceeding 60 days as may be specified by the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All such 
    copies of films, scripts or commentaries or tape records of commentaries 
    deposited with the Board shall be accompanied by a declaration in Form X set 
    out in the Second Schedule.  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Validity of certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
    certificate granted by the Board under sub-section (1) of section 5A in 
    respect of a film shall be valid for a period of ten years from the date on 
    which the certificate is granted.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where in relation to the certificate of a film the period has expired a 
    fresh certificate in 

    1[Form IV, IVA, V, VA, 
    VI, VIA, VII, or VIIA] set out in the Second Schedule, as the case may be, 
    may be issued on an application made in this behalf and the same shall be 
    dealt with as if it were an original application:  
 
Provided that 
    a Regional Officer may, with the prior approval of the Chairman, dispense 
    with examination of the film, if the application is for the issue of 
    certificate in the same form in which it was issued earlier.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    applicant for a fresh certificate shall be required to deposit copy of 
    shooting script or verbatim commentary or tape recorded commentary of the 
    film only in cases where at the time of making application for the initial 
    certificate the same was not deposited.  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Compliance with section 6A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The manner of notification to the distributor or exhibitor for the purpose 
    of section 6A, shall be by delivery of a duplicate copy of the certificate 
    (containing both parts I and II thereof) with each copy of the certified 
    film to be distributed or exhibited:  
 


    1[Provided that in the 
    case of video film, a copy of the certificate showing the serial number, the 
    category and other details should be pasted on every video cassette as well 
    as on its case.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of sub-rule (1) shall apply in relation to an amendment of a 
    certificate in respect of a film as it applied in relation to the 
    certificate itself.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    duplicate copy of the certificate of a film referred to in sub-rule (1) 
    shall accompany the film and be prominently exhibited in the theatre on all 
    days on which the film is exhibited therein.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Uncertification of a film under section 6.—Where 
    in exercise of the powers conferred by section 6 of the Act, the Central 
    Government by notification directs that a certified film shall be deemed to 
    be an uncertified film in the whole of India; the applicant and any other 
    person or persons to whom the rights in the film have passed, shall stop the 
    exhibition of the film forthwith and surrender the certificate and all 
    copies of the duplicate certificate granted in respect of the film to the 
    Board within one month from the date of the notification:  
 


    1[Provided that the 
    Chairman may, at the written request of the applicant or any other person 
    concerned, extend the said period and the total period so extended shall not 
    exceed six months.]  
 

 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Re-examination of certified films.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where in respect of a film which has been certified for public exhibition, 
    any complaint is received by the Board, the same shall be forwarded to the 
    Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, if it considers it necessary so to do, direct the 
    Chairman to re-examine any film (in respect of which a complaint has been 
    received by it directly or through the Board) in such manner and with such 
    assistance as may be specified in the direction.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman may, for the purpose of re-examination aforesaid, require by 
    written notice the person who made the application for certification of the 
    film or the person to whom the rights of ownership or distribution in the 
    film have passed, to arrange at his expense to deliver a print of the 
    certified film to any specified Regional Officer within such time as may be 
    specified in the notice for the purpose of re-examination.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The place, 
    date and time of such re-examination shall be determined by the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Chairman shall forward his opinion together with the print of the film in 
    relation to which a certificate was issued earlier to the Central Government 
    who may after such enquiry as it deems fit, pass such orders thereon in 
    exercise of the revisional powers under section 6.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    provisions of this rule shall apply only in cases where the revisional 
    powers are exercisable by the Central Government under section 6.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Alteration of film after issue of certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a film is altered by excision, addition, colouring or otherwise after 
    it has been certified under these rules, it shall not be exhibited unless 
    the portion or portions excised, added, coloured or otherwise altered, have 
    been reported to the Board in Form III in the Second Schedule and the Board 
    has endorsed the particulars of the alteration or alterations on the 
    certificate.  
 
Explanation 
    I.—Reasonable wear and tear in 
    the normal course of handling or projecting a film shall not be deemed to be 
    an alteration of the film within the meaning of this sub-rule.  
 
Explanation 
    II.—Any addition, deletion, 
    alteration or replacement of background music in a film or, (unless the 
    Chairman by general or special order otherwise directs) a mere change in 
    gauge shall not be deemed to be an alteration of the film within the meaning 
    of this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purpose of exercising its powers under sub-rule (1), the Regional Officer 
    shall appoint an Examining Committee to examine at the expense of the 
    applicant, the reel or reels of the film in which the portion or portions 
    are altered in such manner and with such assistance as he may deem fit and 
    where the Examining Committee considered it necessary so to do, it shall 
    re-examine the entire film:  
 
Provided that 
    where a film is altered by excision or by the change of a coloured film into 
    black and white version only it shall not ordinarily be necessary to appoint 
    an Examining Committee unless the Regional Officer in any case otherwise 
    directs.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Examining Committee appointed under sub-rule (2) shall consist of 


    1[one] member of the 
    Advisory Panel and an examining officer:  
 
Provided that 
    where the examining officer is unavoidably absent at the examination of the 
    film or any reel thereof, the Examining Committee shall consist of two 
    members of the Advisory Panel.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Pending 
    examination of the altered film under this rule, the applicant shall not 
    exhibit the film incorporating the proposed alteration.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    film or any portion thereof as the case may be, is re-examined under this 
    rule, the Chairman shall unless for reasons to be recorded in writing, he 
    declines permission for the alteration, make suitable endorsement in the 
    certificate granted in relation to the film.  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Amendment of certificate granted by the Board after notification under 
    section 6.—When a notification is 
    published under the powers conferred by section 6 of the Act declaring that 
    a film in respect of which a ‘U’ certificate or a ‘UA’ certificate or an ‘S’ 
    certificate has been granted shall be deemed to be a film in respect of 
    which an ‘A’ certificate has been granted, the person to whom the 
    certificate has been granted or the person to whom the rights in the film 
    have passed as the case may be, shall surrender within one month from the 
    date of issue of the order the original certificate and all the duplicate 
    copies thereof to the Board for the issue of a fresh certificate of the new 
    category.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Certificates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A certificate authorizing the public exhibition of a film shall be in one of 
    the 

    1[Forms IV, IVA, V, 
    VA, VI, VIA, VII or VIIA] set out in the Second Schedule according as the 
    film is fit for ‘U’ or ‘UA’ or ‘A’ or ‘S’ 

    2[or ‘U’ or ‘V/A’ or 
    ‘V/UA’ or ‘V/S’] certificate as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    certificate shall be signed for and on behalf of the Board by the Chairman 
    or by a Regional Officer for the Chairman.  
 


    2[(3) The prescribed 
    mark of the Board shall be a film copy of the certificate, that is, a 
    trailer certificate, which shall be affixed to the film and always exhibited 
    with it. The trailer certificate shall be for such duration as one can read 
    it on the screen:  
 
Provided that 
    Part I of the certificate shall be shown for a minimum duration of 10 
    seconds:  
 
Provided 
    further that if there are no excisions or modifications ordered by the 
    Board, Part II of the certificate need not be shown.]  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 

   


 <article><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>36</number>
Fees.—
<section><number>1</number>
A fee shall be charged for the examination of every film at the rates laid down
in the following Table and the same shall be paid either in cash or remitted by
postal order or bank draft to the regional center of the Board where the film is
to be examined.
 


 Table
of Fees 
 
 


 Part I—Examination Fee: 


  


 
Predominantly 
 Educational

 Other than
 Predominantly 
 inclusive 
inclusive of)

Flms Rs.                                                         
Educational films Rs.
 
 


300 
200
1000
 
600
400
2000
 


 
900 
600
3000
 


 
1200 
 
800
 
4000
 


 
1500 
1000
5000
 


 
1800 
 1200
6000
 


 
2100 
1400
7000
 


 
2400 
1600
8000
 


 
2700 
1800
9000
 


 
3000 
2000
10000
 


 
3300 
2200
 
11000
 


 
3600 
2400
 
12000
 


 
3900 
2600
13000
 


 
4200 
2800
 
14000
 


 
4500 
3000
15000
 


 
4800 
3200
 
16000  
 5100                                                                                                
3400
 
17000
 


 
5400 
3600
18000
 


 
5700 
3800
19000
 


 
6000
4000
20000
 <subsection> <number>ii</number> Other than Celluloid Films

  Duration 
in minuts (upto and 
Predominantly  
Educational  
 
Other than    Predominantly
  
inclusive of)     


         
films
Educational films 
 
 


10 
280 
950 
 
        
20                                                                                     
560                                                                              
1850
 


30 
 600 
3000  
   
          40 
740 
3700 

 


 
50 
920 
4600 

 


 
60 
1100 

5500 

 


 
70                                                                                    
1280                                                                            
6400          
 


 
80 
                                                            
1480                                                                            
7400 
 


 
90 
 
                                    
1660                                                                            
8300  
 


 
100 
 
                                    
1840                                                                           
9200
 


 
110 
 
                                     
2020                                                                           
10100  
 


 
120 
                                                            
2200                                                                           
11000         
 


 
130 
                                                            
2400                                                                           
12000 
 


 
140                                                                                   
2560                                                                           
12000
 


 
150 
 
                                          
2740                                                                           
13700  
 


 
160 
 
2940 
 
14700 

 


 
170 
3120 
 
15600 

 


 
180 
3300 
16500 

 


 
190 
3500 
 
17500 

 


 

200 
3660 


 Part
II. In addition to the Examination Fee mentioned in Part I above, Screening Fee
shall be charged as under:—
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
Celluloid Films
  
Length in meters (upto and  inclusive of)
 Screening Fee (Rs.)
 


   
                        
1
2
 


 
300 
100 

 


 
600 
200 

 


 
900 
300 

 


 
1200 
400 

 


 
1500 
500 

 


 
1800
600 

 


 
2100
700 

 


 
2400 
800 

 


 
2700 
900 

 


                
3000 and above 
1000 

 


 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
Other than Celluloid Films
 Duration
in minuts (upto and inclusive)                                        
Screening fees (Rs.)
   
                          
1
2
 


 
10
70 

 


 
20 
140 

 


 
30 
210
 


 
40 
280
 


 
50 
350
 


 
60 
420
 


 
70 
490
 


 
80 
560
 


 
90 
630
 


 
100 
700
 


 
110 
770
 


 
120 
840
 


 
130 
910
 


 
140 
980
 


 
150 
1050
 


 
160 
1120
 


 
170 
1190
 


 
180 
1260
 


 
190 
1330
 


 
200 
1400
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Fee for examination for certifying alterations under Rule 33.—Fee for the
examination of a film for certifying alterations under Rule 33 shall be
calculated only with reference to the reel or reels (or cassette or cassettes),
in which the portion or portions excised, added, coloured or otherwise altered
occur and for the purposes the rate specified in the table aforesaid for
original certification shall be applicable:
 


 Provided
that where the alteration is by excision, the fee chargeable shall be at the
rate of rupees seventy per each endorsement.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A fee of rupees seventy shall be paid for a duplicate copy of the certificate.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
In the event of an application for certification being withdrawn before the film
is examined, the Board may on an application made to it in that behalf. refund
to the applicant the amount of fee paid towards the examination of the film
after deducting twenty-five per cent of the amount so paid.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
In the event of an applicant failing to present a runnable print before the
Examination Committee or the Revising Committee on the day and time and at the
place fixed for such examination, an additional fee of twenty-five per cent of
the fee payable for examination of the film under this Table shall be paid
before another place, date and time for the examination of the film is fixed.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
If, by mistake, miscalculation or such other reason, the applicant pays towards
fee for the examination of any film
any amount in excess of the amount of fee payable under these rules, the Board
may, on an application made in that behalf, within a period of one year from the
date of certification of the film, refund to the applicant the amount so paid in
excess.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
Any person who applies to the Board for information regarding the certification
or any other particular in respect of a film shall along with the application,
pay a search fee of rupees thirty-five per each title of the film.]


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power 
    of entry.—The Chairman or any 
    member of the Board or an advisory panel or a Regional Officer or any other 
    officer or member of the staff of the Board or any officer of the Central 
    Government authorized in writing by the Chairman or members or any officer 
    or member of the staff of the Appellate Tribunal or any officer of the 
    Central Government authorized in writing by the Secretary to the Government 
    of India in the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting in this behalf, may 
    enter any place licensed under the law in force relating to cinemas, in the 
    discharge of his duties under the Act or these rules and thereupon the owner 
    or the manager of such place shall provide him with a seat of the highest 
    rate or the next lower class to view the film without charging the admission 
    fee and entertainment tax.  
  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Advertisement of films.—Any 
    person advertising a film granted ‘UA’, ‘A’ or ‘S’ certificate or the 
    exhibition of such film by means of insertions in newspapers, hoardings, 
    posters, handbills or trailers shall, after the date of its certification, 
    indicate in such insertions in newspapers, hoardings, posters, handbills or 
    trailers that the film has been certified for such public exhibition. 


    1[Such advertisement 
    shall indicate only the certified title of a film.]  
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Maintenance of register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall 

    1[maintain] a register 
    in which these shall be entered,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the name of every film examined under 
    the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the name of the person applying for 
    certificate;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the name of the person or company 
    producing or releasing the film;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the name of the country in which the 
    film was original produced;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the name of the place where the film 
    was exhausted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the date of the examination;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the names of the persons who examined 
    the film;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the result of the examination and of 
    any further proceeding thereon;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the number and date of the certificate 
    issued, if any, together with a copy of any endorsement made thereon.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purpose of enabling the Board to maintain such a register, the Regional 
    Officers concerned shall each maintain similar registers in respect of 
    applications for certification made to them and send to the Board a 
    duplicate copy of every entry made in it, as soon as may be, after it has 
    been made.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of 
    the entries in the register maintained by the Board made during any month 
    shall be sent to all the Regional Officers during the next following month.  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Certain 
    films to continue to remain uncertified films.—If 
    a film has been declared by a notification issued before the 15th January, 
    1951 by any State Government to be an uncertified film in any part or parts 
    of the State concerned and if the said notification has not ceased to be in 
    force by virtue of the proviso to sub-rule (2) of Rule 35 of the 
    Cinematograph (Censorship) Rules, 1951, the film shall not be publicly 
    exhibited unless it is certified for public exhibition in accordance with 
    the provisions of these rules:  
 
Provided that 
    before certifying any such film for public exhibition the Board shall obtain 
    the prior approval of the Central Government.  
  
  
 
  


</article> 

   


 <article><number>41</number>
Time limit in relation to certification of films.—
<section><number>1</number>
After an application under Rule 21 for the certification of a film, complete in
all respects (including the proof of payment of fees) is received, the Board
shall scrutinize the application within seven days from the receipt thereof.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
On receiving an intimation from the applicant that a clear runnable print of the
film is available for examination, the Board shall, within 15 days therefrom
refer the film for examination to an Examining Committee.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The films may be referred to the Examining Committee in the order in which the
applications are received:
 


 Provided
that the Regional Officer may on receipt of a written request from any
applicant, if satisfied that there are grounds for an early examination, alter
the order of examination of the film after recording the reasons in writing.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
(a) In cases where the Examining Committee, after examination of the film,
considered that a scrutiny of the shooting script is necessary or the
authenticity of the incidents depicted in a film of historical, mythological,
biographical or legendary nature is to be verified, a provisional report to that
effect shall be submitted by the Regional Officer to the Chairman within a
maximum of three working days after such examination.
 


 <subsection><number>b</number>
A written communication shall be sent to the applicant within a maximum of three
working days following the receipt of the Chairman’s orders on the provisional
report referred to in clause (a) and the applicant shall submit the script or
the authentic sources on which the subject of his film is based within ten days
from the date of receipt of such communication.
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
In cases where the members of the Examining Committee after the examination of
the film submit to the Chairman a provisional report indicating that expert
opinion on subjects depicted in the film such as subjects relating to defence or
foreign relations or any particular religion or law or medicine or any other
subject, should be sought before the final report is submitted, the Chairman may
after taking into consideration the circumstances of the case specify a time
limit for obtaining the expert opinion and for the submission of the final
report of the Examining Committee thereafter.
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
In other cases, the script submitted by the applicant or the authentic sources
furnished by him shall be scrutinized by the examining officer and the final
report of the Examining Committee shall be forwarded by the examining officer of
the Chairman within ten days from the date of receipt of the script or the
authentic sources, as the case may be.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
(a) On receipt of the orders of the Board on the recommendations of the
Examining Committee, in cases where sub-section (2) of section 4 is applicable,
the communication to the applicant shall be issued within three days.
 


 <subsection><number>b</number>
The applicant shall submit his reply within fourteen days of the receipt of the
communication.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number>
In cases where the film is not referred to a Revising Committee, certificate
shall be issued or decision communicated within seven days.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
(a) In cases where a film is to be referred to a Revising Committee, a Revising
Committee shall be constituted within twenty days from the receipt of the
necessary documents from the applicant. 


 <subsection><number>b</number>
The provisions of sub-rules (3) to (6) shall apply mutatis mutandis to
the examination of films by the Revising Committee.
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
When a film is referred to another Revising Committee or to the Board in terms
of proviso to sub-rule (12) of Rule 24, the time limit will be further extended
on the lines of (a) and (b) of this sub-rule.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number>
The applicant shall surrender the cuts, if any, and the affected reels together
with full particulars thereof, within a period of fourteen days from the date of
receipt of the final orders of the Board under section 4:
 


 Provided
that where the applicant applies to the Board that he intends to appeal against
the orders of the Board, the Board may extend the period specified above for
surrender of the cuts by such periods as it thinks fit, but in any case not
beyond fourteen days from the date of disposal of the appeal or from the date of
expiration of the period for filing the appeal in cases where no appeal is
filed.
 


 </section><section><number>9</number>
The cuts and the affected reels shall be examined by the Regional Officer within
ten days of the submission of the same.
 


 </section><section><number>10</number>
If the cuts are found to be adequate on the scrutiny of the relevant reels and
all particulars necessary for the presentation of the certificate are fully
furnished certificate shall be prepared and issued within five days of the
deposit of a copy of the film or script, as the case may be, as required under
these rules.
 


 </section><section><number>11</number>
If, however, the cuts are found to be inadequate on a scrutiny of the relevant
reels, the Regional Officer shall record the same on the file and send within
two days a further communication to the applicant for compliance with the orders
of the Board.
 


 </section><section><number>12</number>
The applicant shall submit further cut to the Regional Officer within three days
from the date of receipt of the communication.
 


 </section><section><number>13</number>
The Regional Officer shall again verify further cuts and the reels within five
days of the receipt of the same and if the cuts are found to be adequate a
certificate shall be issued.
 


 </section><section><number>14</number>
The Chairman may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax the time-limits
prescribed by this rule for the performance of any act if he is satisfied that
it is necessary so to do to avoid any undue hardship.
 


 Explanation.—In
calculating the periods specified in this rule working days alone shall be taken
into account and Sundays and other holidays shall be excluded.
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Preservation of records of certification of films.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Records of certification of feature/long film shall be preserved by the 
    Board for a minimum period of twelve years.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Records of 
    certification of all short films shall be preserved by the Board for a 
    minimum period of two years:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of short films if thereby cuts made by the Board or alterations 
    made therein under Rule 33 or if complaints have been received against the 
    film, records of certification of the film shall be preserved for a minimum 
    period of twelve years.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Terms 
    and conditions of service of the Chairman and members of the Appellate 
    Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman and 
    members of the Appellate Tribunal shall hold office during the pleasure of 
    the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (1), the Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal shall 
    hold office for a period of three years and shall continue to hold office 
    until his successor is appointed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (1), every other member of the Appellate Tribunal 
    shall hold office for a period not exceeding three years.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A retiring 
    Chairman or a member of the Appellate Tribunal whose term of office has 
    expired by efflux of time shall be eligible for reappointment.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-rules, when the 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal is unable to discharge his functions 
    owing to absence, illness or any other cause, the Central Government may 
    appoint another person to discharge the functions of the Chairman until the 
    Chairman resumes his duties.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Central Government may, after consultation with the Chairman of the 
    Appellate Tribunal appoint any person whom it thinks fit to be a member of 
    the Appellate Tribunal:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, dispense 
    with such consultation.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A casual 
    vacancy in the membership of the Appellate Tribunal caused by the 
    resignation, death or removal of any member or otherwise shall be filled by 
    fresh appointment and the person so appointed shall hold office for a period 
    not exceeding three years.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Central Government may remove from office any member of the Appellate 
    Tribunal before the expiration of his term of office:  
 
Provided that 
    a member appointed to the Appellate Tribunal after consultation with the 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be so removed except on the 
    recommendation of or after consultation with the Chairman of the Appellate 
    Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> For the 
    purpose of enabling the Appellate Tribunal to perform its functions under 
    the Act, the Central Government may appoint a Secretary to the Appellate 
    Tribunal and such other officers for the Appellate Tribunal as may be 
    considered necessary:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may delegate to the Chairman of the Appellate 
    Tribunal subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be 
    specified by it, the power of appointment conferred on it under this 
    sub-rule, other than the powers of appointment in relation to the post of 
    Secretary to the Appellate Tribunal:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal may grant leave to or 
    suspend or remove from service any officer appointed by him under the powers 
    delegated to him under this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    Secretary to the Tribunal and other officers appointed under sub-rule (9) 
    shall perform such duties as may be assigned to him by these rules or by the 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-rules, the Chairman 
    of the Appellate Tribunal may, for the purpose of enabling the Tribunal to 
    discharge its functions under the Act, make appointments to posts other than 
    Group A posts and may assign to the persons holding such posts, duties as he 
    may deem fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal, if he is a paid full time officer, shall 
    receive such pay and allowances as are admissible to a serving Judge of a 
    High Court. He shall be entitled to all facilities and concessions not less 
    favourable than those admissible to a serving Judge of a High Court:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of a retired Judge of a High Court re-employed as Chairman of 
    the Appellate Tribunal, the pay and other terms and conditions of service 
    shall be the same as are applicable to re-employed Judges of a High Courts 
    under the orders of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> Every 
    honorary member (including the Chairman where he does not receive any 
    salary) may,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if he is an out-station member,  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    travel by air or by train as admissible 
    according to the orders issued by the Central Government from time to time 
    in respect of journeys undertaken by him for the performance of his duties 
    as such member;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    be paid a consultancy fee for 
    attending the preview of a film or meeting of the Appellate Tribunal at the 
    rate of Rs. 100 for each day of such preview or meeting; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    be paid daily allowance at the rate 
    of Rs. 50 per day for each day preceding the meeting and that following the 
    meeting, if the member actually stays at the place of the meeting;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if he is a local member, be paid a 
    consultancy fee for attending the preview of a film or meeting of the 
    Appellate Tribunal at the rate of Rs. 75 per day for each day of such 
    preview or meeting:  
 
Provided that 
    daily allowance will not be admissible in addition for the day or days for 
    which the consultancy fee is paid.  
 

  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Fees 
    for appeal to the Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to sub-rule (2) below, fees at the rates laid down in the following 
    table shall be payable along with every appeal petition preferred under 
    sub-section (2) of section 5C and the same shall be paid either in cash or 
    remitted by postal order or bank draft to the Secretary to the Tribunal:  
 
Table of 
    Fees  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Long film : Rs. 750 irrespective of 
    length and gauge of film;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Short film : Rs. 100 irrespective of 
    length and gauge of film.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal may at his discretion and for reasons to 
    be recorded in writing, waive the payment of fee in any particular case.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the 
    event of an appeal being withdrawn before the film is previewed, the 
    Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal may, on application made to it in that 
    behalf, refund to the appellant the amount of fee paid towards appeal after 
    deducting 25 per cent of the amount so paid.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the 
    event of an appellant failing to present a runnable print before the 
    Appellate Tribunal on the day and time and at the place fixed for preview, 
    an additional fee of 25 per cent of the fee payable for consideration of 
    appeal under the Table in sub-rule (1) shall be paid before another date and 
    time for the preview of the film is fixed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, by 
    mistake, miscalculation or such other reason, the applicant pays towards fee 
    for the consideration of appeal any amount in excess of the amount of fee 
    payable under these rules, the Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal may, on an 
    application made in that behalf, within a period of one year from the date 
    the appeal has been decided, refund to the applicant the amount so paid in 
    excess.  
 

  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    Form I
 



    Form of application for certification for public  

    exhibition of a film produced in India
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 21]
 

 
 


No. and date of application (to be entered by 
    Board’s Office)
 


To
 


The Central Board of Film Certification 
    through the Regional Officer at.......................
 


Application for certification for public 
    exhibition of a film produced in India at...........
 


(1)    (a) Name of the film
 


(b) Language of the film
 


(c) Length of the film in 
    ft...................................................................................Metre
 


(d) Number of reels
 


(e) Gauge of the film
 


(f) Type of the film, i.e., whether it 
    is 2-D, 3-D, cinemascope, vistavision, etc.
 


(g) Whether the film is silent or a talkie
 


(h) Colour of the film
 


(i) Name and address of the producer
 


(j) Name of the director
 


(2) State whether the film is a newsreel/ 
    documentary/scientific/ educational/ feature/advertisement film.
 


(2A) Specify the certificate requested: ‘U’, ‘UA’, 
    ‘A’ or ‘S’.
 


(3) State separately the number of negative 
    and positive prints of the film.
 


(a) produced 
    (negative................................................ 
    positive...................................)
 


(b) in the applicant’s possession 
    (negative............................... positive......................)
 


(c) Name and address of the processing 
    laboratory.
 


(4)    (a) Whether the present 
    film is a dubbed version or a re-make of any other film? If so, state the 
    particulars alongwith full details of certificates issued to that film.
 


(b) Whether any pre-censorship advice was 
    obtained and if so, the details thereof.
 


(c) Whether permission for any shooting abroad 
    was obtained and, if so, the details thereof.
 


(d) Whether the film contains any 
    dialogue/commentary in any language other than the language of the film and, 
    if so, specify the language and the reels in which they occur.
 


(5) Has any previous application been made to 
    certify this film as suitable for public exhibition in India? If so,
 


(a) Where and to whom was it made
 


(b) What was the result of the application
 


*(i)  A ‘U’/’UA’/An ‘A’/’S’ certificate 
    No........... dated....... was granted subject to the following 
    cuts..............
 


*(ii) Certificate was refused.
 


(6) Has the exhibition of this film been at 
    any time suspended or the film declared uncertified by the Central or any 
    State Government? State particulars:
 


(7) Does the film contain any dialogue, song, 
    poem, speech or commentary in any language other than English, or an Indian 
    language?
 


If so, specify that reel or reels in which the 
    dialogue, song, poem, speech or commentary occurs and the language or 
    languages used.
 


(8) Amount of fee accompanying the application 
    on account of the fee prescribed in Rule 36.
 


Vide (i) Receipt No. 
    .......................................................dated.........................................
 


(ii)       Bank draft No. ................... 
    dated........................ on.......................................... 
    Bank.
 


(iii) Postal Order No. 
    ............................................................................................... 
             dated 
    ................................................................. on 
    ..............................................          Post Office.
 



1[(8A) 
    Whether any animal has been used in shooting of the Film? If so, whether 
    declaration specified in clause (bb) of sub-rule (3) of rule 21 has been 
    filed?:]
 


(9) Name, address, and telephone number, if 
    any of the applicant. Telephone No.:
 


(10) I declare that the print of the film is 
    ready for examination by the Board and the Statements recorded above are 
    true in every particular.
 

 
 


Date....................            

 


Signature of applicant
 


*Score out the word or words which are not 
    applicable.
 



 
 




    -------------------------------
 



         1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 646(E), dated 12th November, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    12-11-1997).
 



 



 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 




1[Form 
    IA
 



Form of application for certification for public  

    exhibition of a 

    2[film on 
    video tape or compact  

    video disc] produced in India
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 21]
 

 
 


No. and date of application (to be entered by 
    Board’s Office)
 


To
 


The Central Board of Film Certification 
    through the Regional Officer at.................
 


Application for certification for public 
    exhibition of a 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] produced in 
    India at................
 


(1)   (a) Name of the 
3[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]
 


(b)  Language of the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]
 


(c)  Running time
 


(d)  Number of cassettes
 


(e)  Any other particulars of the video 
    conversion
 


(f)  Type of the film, i.e., whether it 
    is 2-D, 3-D, cinemascope, vistavision, etc
 


(g)  Whether the film is silent or a talkie
 


(h)  Colour of the film
 


(i)  Name and address of the producer
 


(j) Name of the director
 


(2) State whether the 
3[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is a 
    newsreel/documentary/scientific/educational/feature/advertisement video 
    film.
 


(2A) Specify the certificate requested: ‘U’, 
    ‘UA’ ‘A’ or ‘S’.
 


(3) State separately the number of 
    negative and positive prints of the 
4[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]
 


(a) produced 
    (negative................................................. 
    positive..................................)
 


(b) in the applicant’s possession 
    (negative................................ positive......................)
 


(c) Name and address of the laboratory/company 
    where copies were made.
 


(4)   (a)  Whether the 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] for which the application has been made 
    is a replica/exact copy of a cinematograph film on celluloid in respect of 
    which a certificate has already been granted by the Central Board of Film 
    Certification? Also state particulars of the film certified.
 


(b)  Where the 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is a modified version of a certified 
    cinematograph film on celluloid containing additions, deletions/or other 
    alterations (details of modifications may be provided).
 


(c) Whether the application being made 
    is in respect of an original 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] and not a copy of an already certified 
    cinematograph film on celluloid.
 


(d) Whether the present 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is a dubbed version or remake of any 
    other 
    5[film on video tape or compact video disc]? If so, 
    state the particulars along with full details of certificates issued to that
    1[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc].
 


(e) Whether any pre-censorship advice was 
    obtained and if so, the details thereof.
 


(f) Whether permission for any shooting abroad 
    was obtained and, if so, the details thereof.
 


(g) Whether the 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]contains any dialogue/commentary in any 
    language other than the language of the 
1[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] and, if so, specify the language and 
    the cassette in which they occur.
 


(5) Has any previous application been 
    made to certify this 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] as suitable for public exhibition in 
    India? If so,
 


(a)  Where and to whom was it made
 


(b)  What was the result of the application
 


*(i) A‘U’/‘UA’/An ‘A’/‘S’ certificate 
    No............ dated....... was granted subject to the following 
    cuts...............
 


*(ii) Certificate was refused.
 


(6) Has the exhibition of this 
1[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]/film been at any time suspended or the
    5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]/film declared uncertified by the 
    Central or any State Government? State particulars:
 


(7) Does the 
5[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] contain any dialogue, song, poem, 
    speech or commentary in any language other than English, or an Indian 
    language?
 


If so, specify that Cassette or Cassettes in 
    which the dialogue, song, poem, speech or commentary occurs and the language 
    or languages used.
 


(8) Amount of fee accompanying the application 
    on account of the fee prescribed in Rule 36.
 


Vide (i)  Receipt 
    No......................................................... 
    dated.......................................
 


(ii)  Bank draft No........................ 
    dated......................... on........................... Bank.
 


(iii) Postal Order No.................... 
    dated..................... on...................... Post Office.
 



6[(8A) 
    Whether any animal has been used in shooting of the film? If so, whether 
    declaration specified in clause (bb) of sub-rule (3) of rule 21 has been 
    filed?]
 


(9) Name, address, and telephone number, if 
    any, of the applicant. Telephone No.:
 


(10) I declare that the 
7[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is ready for examination by the Board 
    and the statements recorded above are true in every particular. I also 
    declare that I own the rights of the 
    7[film on video tape or compact video disc] in 
    question. I further declare that I have the right to use in the 
7[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] the additional material in the feature 
    film in the form of trailers, advertisement shorts, documentary films,
    etc.
 

 
 


Date............... 
 

 
 


Signature of applicant
 


*Score out the word or words which are not 
    applicable.]
 


 
 


------------------------
 



         1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 1-3-1984).
 



         2.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207(E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 10-4-1997).
 



         3.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207(E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 10-4-1997).
 



         4.   Ins. by G.S.R. 646(E), dated 12th November, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    12-11-1997).
 



         5.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207 (E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    10-4-1997).
 



         6.   Ins. by G.S.R. 646 (E), dated 12th November, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    12-11-1997).
 



         7.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207 (E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    10-4-1997).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


FORM II
 



    Form of application for certification for public exhibition  

    of a film imported into India
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 21]
 


No. and date of application (to be entered by 
    Board’s Office)
 


To
 


The Central Board of Film Certification 
    through the Regional Officer at Bombay/Calcutta/Madras.
 


Application for certification for public 
    exhibition of a film first imported into India at..............
 


1.     (a)  Name of the 
    film
 


(b) Language of the film
 


(c) Length of the film in 
    ft................... metres. Length of the film as shown in the CCP and/or 
    import licence. 
 


Have any cuts been made voluntarily by the 
    applicant and if so give details.
 


(d) Number of reels
 


(e) Gauge of the film
 


(f) Type of the film, i.e., whether it 
    is 2-D, 3-D, cinemascope, vistavision, etc
 


(g) Whether the film is silent or a talkie
 


(h) Colour of the film
 


(i) Name of the producer
 


(j) Name of the director
 


(k) Country in which produced
 


2. State whether the film is a 
    *newsreel/documentary/scientific/ educational/feature/advertisement film.
 


3. State separately, the number of negative 
    and positive prints of the film:
 


(a) imported by the applicant 
    (negative................................. 
    positive.........................)
 


(b) in the applicant’s possession 
    (negative.............................positive..........................)
 


4. In what other language/languages, if any, 
    has this been produced or dubbed?
 


Where the title is not the same in each 
    language, state the title of each version in which it has been produced or 
    dubbed.
 


5. Has any previous application been made to 
    certify this film (under its present or any other title) in.
 


(a) India:
 


(b) United States of America:
 


(c) United Kingdom:
 


(d) Any other country:
 


If so,
 


(i) Where and to whom was it made?
 


(ii) What was the result of the application 
    i.e.
 


*(i) A ‘U’/‘UA’/An ‘A’/‘S’ certificate 
    No...................... dated................... was granted subject to the 
    following cuts........................
 


*(ii)       Certificate was refused.
 


In the case of film made in the United States 
    of America, state the rating of this film according to (a) the national 
    groups and (b) the legion of decency.
 


       (a) 
    ........................... (b).......................
 


6. Has exhibition of this film been at any 
    time suspended or the film declared uncertified by the Central or any State 
    Government? State particulars:
 


7. Does the film contain any dialogue, song, 
    poem, speech or commentary in any language other than English, or any Indian 
    language?
 


If so, specify that reel or reels in which the 
    dialogue, song, poem, speech or commentary occurs and the language or 
    languages used.
 


8. Amount of fees accompanying the application 
    on account of the fee prescribed in Rule 36.
 


(i) Receipt 
    No............................................................ 
    dated........................................
 


(ii) Bank draft 
    No................................ dated.......................... 
    on........................ Bank.
 


(iii) Postal Order 
    No.............................. dated......................... 
    on............... Post Office.
 


9.     Name, address and telephone number, if 
    any, of the applicant.
 



    .............................................................................................................................................
 



    .............................................................................................................................................
 



    ..............................................................................................................................................
 


10. (a)  Name, address and telephone, if any, 
    of the importer of the film..............................
 


     (b)  Number and date 
    of the import 
    licence....................................................................
 


     (c) Date of clearance 
    through the 
    customs.....................................................................
 


11. Has the film been produced by or in 
    collaboration with South African or Rhodesian nationals wholly or in part in 
    South Africa, South West Africa or Rhodesia or in the film owned wholly, or 
    in part, by South African or Rhodesian nationals? If so, give details.
 



1[11A. 
    Whether any animal has been used in shooting of the film? If so, whether 
    declaration specified in clause (bb) of sub-rule (3) of rule 21 has been 
    filed?”]
 


12. I declare that the print of the film is 
    ready for examination by the Board and the statements above recorded are 
    true in every particular.
 

 
 


Date......................          

 


Signature of applicant
 


*Score out the word or words which are not 
    applicable.
 


 
 


---------------------------
 



         1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 646 (E), dated 12th November, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    12-11-1997).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 




1[Form 
    IIA
 



Form of application for certification for public  

    exhibition of a 

    2[film on 
    video tape or compact  

    video disc] imported into India.
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 21]
 


No. and date of application (to be entered by 
    Board’s Office)
 


To
 


The Central Board of Film Certification 
    through the Regional Officer at.......................
 


Application for certification for public 
    exhibition of a 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] first 
    imported into India at......................................................................................
 


1.    (a)  Name of the
    2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]
 


(b) Language of the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]
 


(c) Running time of the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]....................... 
    ........................................metre
 


Running time of the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] as shown in the CCP and/or import 
    licence. Have any cuts been made voluntarily by the applicant and if so give 
    details.
 


(d) Number of Cassettes
 


(e) Any other particulars of the video 
    conversion
 


(f) Type of the film, i.e., whether it 
    is 2-D, 3-D, cinemascope, vistavision, etc.
 


(g) Whether the film is silent or a talkie
 


(h) Colour of the film
 


(i) Name of the producer
 


(j) Name of the director
 


(k) Country in which produced
 


2. State whether the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is a *newsreel/documentary/ 
    scientific/educational/feature/advertisement video film.
 


3. State separately, the number of 
    negative and positive prints of the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]:
 


(a) imported by the applicant 
    (negative........ positive........)
 


(b) in the applicant’s possession 
    (negative.......positive......)
 


4.    (a)  Whether the
    2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] for which the application has been made 
    is a replica/exact copy of a cinematograph film on celluloid in respect of 
    which a certificate has already been granted by the Central Board of Film 
    Certification? Also state particulars of the film certified.
 


(b)  Where the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is a modified version of a certified 
    cinematograph film on celluloid, containing additions, deletions/other 
    alterations (details of modifications may be provided).
 


(c) Whether the application being made 
    is in respect of an original 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] and not a copy of an already certified 
    cinematograph film on celluloid.
 


(d) In what other language/languages, if any, 
    has this been produced or dubbed?
 


Where the title is not the same in each 
    language, stated the title of each version in which it has been produced or 
    dubbed.
 


5. Has any previous application been 
    made to certify this 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc]/film (under its present or any other 
    title) in
 


(a) India:
 


(b) United States of America:
 


(c) United Kingdom:
 


(d) Any other country:
 


If so,
 


(i) Where and to whom was it made?
 


(ii) What was the result of the application 
    i.e.
 


*(i)       A ‘U’/’UA’/An ‘A’/‘S’ certificate 
    No........... dated....... was granted subject to the following 
    cuts..................
 


*(ii)       Certificate was refused.
 


In the case of film made in the United States 
    of America, state the rating of this film according to (a) the national 
    groups and (b) the legion of decency.
 


       
    (a).............. (b).................
 


6. Has exhibition of this 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] been at any time suspended or the film 
    declared uncertified by the Central or any State Government? State 
    particulars:
 


7. Does the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] contain any dialogue, song, poem, 
    speech or commentary in any language other than English, or any Indian 
    language?
 


If so, specify the Cassette or Cassettes in 
    which the dialogue, song, poem, speech or commentary occurs and the language 
    or languages used.
 


8. Amount of fees accompanying the application 
    on account of the fee prescribed in Rule 36.
 


(i)  Receipt 
    No............................................................... 
    dated.....................................
 


(ii) Bank draft 
    No.............................. dated............................. 
    on....................... Bank.
 


(iii) Postal Order 
    No............................. dated......................... 
    on................ Post Office.
 


9. Name, address, and telephone number, if 
    any, of the applicant.
 


10. (a)  Name, address and telephone 
    number, if any, of the importer of the 
2[film/films 
    on video tape or compact video disc]...........................
 


(b) Number and date of the import licence..................
 


(c) Date of clearance through the 
    Customs..................
 


11. Has the 
2[film/films 
    on video tape or compact video disc] been produced by or in collaboration 
    with South African or Rhodesian nationals wholly or in part in South Africa, 
    South West Africa or Rhodesia or is the film owned wholly, or in part, by 
    South African or Rhodesian nationals? If so, give details.
 



3[11A. 
    Whether any animal has been used in shooting of the film? If so, whether 
    declaration specified in clause (bb) of sub-rule (3) of rule 21 has been 
    filed?]
 


12. I declare that the 
2[film 
    on video tape or compact video disc] is ready for examination by the Board 
    and that the statements above recorded are true in every particular. I also 
    declare that I own the video rights of the film in question. I further 
    declare that I have the right to use in the video film the additional 
    material in the feature film in the form of trailers, advertisement shorts, 
    documentary films, etc.
 

 
 


Date...............     
 


                             Signature of 
    applicant
 


*Score out the word or words which are not 
    applicable.
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 83 (E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).
 



         2.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207 (E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    10-4-1997).
 



         3.   Ins. by G.S.R. 646(E), dated 12th November, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    12-11-1997).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

Form III
 

[See rule 33]
 

(To be submitted in 
      duplicate)
 

 
 

[Report under rule 33 of the Cinematograph 
      (Certification) Rules, 1983, regarding an alteration or alterations in a 
      certified film.]
 

1. Name of the applicant:
 

2. Name of the film:
 

3. Certificate No............ 
      dated...................
 

4. Particulars of alterations:
 

Reel No. Scene No. Description of the 
      scene/dialogue/song length.
 

(Specify the exact alteration or alterations, length 
      and the number of the reel or reels in which the alteration or alterations 
      occurs or occur).
 

1[In the case of 2[films on video tape or compact video disc], instead of length and 
      number of reels, duration in minutes and number of cassettes may be 
      given.]
 

To
 

The Chairman, Central Board of Film Certification 
      through the Regional Officer at Bombay/Calcutta/Madras.*
 

I declare that the above particulars are true in every 
      respect and are a full description of the alteration or alterations made 
      in the film after its certification.
 

Date:
 

Address:        
      
 

Signature of applicant
 

*Score out the word or words which are not 
      applicable.
 

 
 

-------------------------
 

     
      1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
      1-3-1984).
 

     
      2.   Subs. by G.S.R. 207(E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f. 
      10-4-1997)
 

 
  </form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



1[FORM 
    IV
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 


This 
    Certificate is valid for theatrical release only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................................ 
    Dated ...............................................
 



    category “u” 
    ....................................................................................................................
 



    Film.................... Gauge MM............................... 
    Length...................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for unrestricted public 
    exhibition subject to excisions and modifications listed in Part II on the 
    reverse:—
 



    Unrestricted Public Exhibition
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


Part 
    II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications:]
 


 
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms IV, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1996).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM IVA
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



This Certificate 
    is valid for Video Films only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................
    Dated..........................
    Category “V/U”
 



    Film...................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length....................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for unrestricted public 
    exhibition subject to excisions and modifications listed in Part II on the 
    reverse:—
 



    Universal Video
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


 
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications:]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms IVA, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 
    (w.e.f. 1-1-1996).
 


 
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM V
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



This Certificate 
    is valid for Theatrical Release only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................... 
    Dated ........................... Category “A”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM ........................... 
    Length....................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition, 
    restricted to adults only, subject to excisions and modifications listed in 
    Part II on the reverse:—
 


Adults 
    Only
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications:]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms V, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1996).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM VA
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



This Certificate 
    is valid for Video Films only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ...................................
    Dated ........................... 
    Category “v/A”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length..................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition, 
    restricted to adults only, subject to excisions and modifications listed in 
    Part II on the reverse:—
 


Adults 
    Only video
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications :]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms VA, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 
    (w.e.f. 1-1-1996).
 


 
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM VI
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



This Certificate 
    is valid for Theatrical Release only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................... 
    Dated ........................... Category “UA”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length..................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition with an 
    endorsement of caution that the question as to whether any child below the 
    age of 12 years may be allowed to see the film should be considered by the 
    parents or guardian of such child, and also subject to excisions and 
    modifications listed in Part II on the reverse:—
 



    Parental Guidance
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of the applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


Part 
    II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications:]
 


 
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms VI, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1996).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM VIA
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



This Certificate 
    is valid for Video Films
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................... 
    Dated ...........................Category “V/UA”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length..................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition with an 
    endorsement of caution that the question as to whether any child below the 
    age of 12 years may be allowed to see the film should be considered by the 
    parents or guardian of such child, and also subject to excisions and 
    modifications listed in Part II on the reverse:—
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications :]
 


 
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms VIA, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 
    (w.e.f. 1-1-1996).
 


-------------------------
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM VII
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 


This 
    Certificate is valid for Theatrical Release only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................... Dated 
    ........................... Category “s”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length..................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition restricted 
    to members of any profession of any class of persons, subject to excisions 
    and modifications listed in Part II on the reverse:—
 



    Specialised Audience
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications :]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms VII , subs. by the G.S.R. 705 (E), dated 30th October, 1995 
    (w.e.f. 1-1-1996).
 


-------------------------
 


 
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


1[FORM VIIA
 


[See rule 35(1)]
 


GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 


CENTRAL BOARD OF FILM CERTIFICATION
 



    This Certificate is valid for 
2[film 
    on video tape  

    or compact video disc] only
 


PART I
 



    Certificate No. ................................... Dated 
    ........................... Category “v/s”
 



    Film....................... Gauge MM .......................... 
    Length..................... Mts Reels
 


After examination of the film by the members 
    of the Examining Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate 
    Tribunal mentioned below and on the recommendations of the said Examining 
    Committee/Revising Committee/Film Certification Appellate Tribunal, the 
    Board hereby certifies that the film is fit for public exhibition, 
    restricted to members of any profession or any class of persons, subject to 
    excisions and modifications listed in Part II on the reverse:—
 



    Specialised Audience Video
 


Further certified that the excisions and 
    modifications imposed by the Board have actually been carried out.
 


Name of applicant
 


Name of the Producer
 



    Chairman
 


PART II
 


Particulars of excisions and modifications : ]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 



         1.   Forms VIIA, subs. by the G.S.R. 705 
    (E), dated 30th October, 1995 (w.e.f. 1-1-1996).
 



         2.   Subs. G.S.R. 207(E), dated 10th 
    April, 1997 (w.e.f. 10-4-1997).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



1[Form 
    VIII
 


[See rules 22(9) and 24(9)]
 



Central board of 
    film certification
 



    Report of Member of Examining/Revising Committee
 


N.B. :—Please study the guidelines 
    issued by Government once again before you preview the film.
 


Title of the film and 
    language.......................Colour/Black and White Length of the 
    film..................(metres)/Running 
    time.............................(minutes) 
    Reels............................... Casette................... Gague.........................
 


Date of 
    examination........................................Name of the 
    member........................
 


1. I certify that I have cerefully examined 
    the above film with reference to the guidelines.
 


I recommend refusal of certificate to the 
    film. OR
 


I recommend the grant of following certificate
 


‘U’/‘UA’/‘A’/‘S’
 


with excisions or/and modifications
 


without excisions or/and, modifications
 


[Delete whichever is not applicable]
 


II. In the case of grant of ‘S’ certificate, 
    please specify the class or group of persons which should constitute the 
    specialised audiences:—
 


III. Reasons for refusal of certificate or 
    grant of ‘UA’/‘A’/‘S’ certificate.
 


Note:—‘U’—Unrestricted public 
    exhibition.
 


‘UA’—Unrestricted public exhibition with an 
    endorsement that it is necessary to caution that the question as to whether 
    any child below the age of twelve years may be allowed to see the film 
    should be considered by the parents or guardian of such child.
 


‘A’—Public exhibition restricted to adults.
 


‘S’—Public exhibition restricted to members of 
    any profession or any class of persons.
 


IV. Details of excisions/modifications (Please
    see notes below)
 
 
 
Sl. No.
 
Reel No.
 
Clear and Specific description of excision 
        or modification
 
Persons with specific reference to 
        guidelines

 
  
  
  
  


 

 
 


V. Thematic classification (only in the case 
    of feature films):—
 


VI. Any other remarks (including justification 
    for permitting certain visuals and/or words prima facie appear to be 
    objectionable)
 


VII. I certify that there would be no 
    infraction of the guidelines if the film is granted a certificate as 
    recommended above.
 


I also certify that the film has been judged 
    in its entirety from the point of view of its overall impact; that the film 
    has been examined in the light of the period depicted in the film and 
    contemporary standards of the country and the people to which the film 
    relates; and that the film does not deprive the morality of the people.
 


I certify that while recommending the film for 
    unrestricted public exhibition I have satisfied myself that the film is 
    suitable for family viewing, including children.
 


Signature.................
 


Notes: 1. While recommending excisions 
    the beginning and end of the excision should be clearly described and the 
    length of the excision may be given as a percentage of the total scene or in 
    meters/feet.
 


             2. If a scene or sequence is to 
    be reduced to a flash, only 1/2 to 1 metre will be kept in the film.
 


             3. Also if certain portions are 
    to be completely deleted while reducing a scene or sequence these should be 
    specified.
 


 
 


 
 



    ----------------
 



         1.   Subs by G.S.R. 173(E), dated 25th March, 1997 (w.e.f. 1-5-1997).
 


 
  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 


Form IX
 


[See rule 26]
 


I/We .................... the applicant(s) in 
    respect of the film............. do hereby declare that the portion or 
    portions objected to by the Board of Film Certification in the film......... 
    as endorsed on the certificate have been excised from the film and the 
    original negative (picture and sound), inter negative, inter positive and 
    all positive prints thereof are hereby surrendered to the Central Board of 
    Film Certification.
 


I/We further declare that the above 
    declaration is correct in all respects.
 



                                                                                                            
    Signature of applicant
 



    Place:                                                                                                
    Name:
 



    Date:                                                                                                 
    Address:
 


 
 


Notes:
 


(1) If so required by the Regional Officer the 
    applicant shall produce a certificate from the owner or manager of the 
    laboratory, where the film was processed in such form as may be specified by 
    the Board in this behalf, in regard to the number of positive and negative 
    copies of the film made in that laboratory.
 


(2) All the cuts should be joined in the order 
    of reel numbers indicated in the Board’s direction with white pieces in 
    between two different cuts to distinguish them. Length of each cut should be 
    indicated in metres separately. In case of a scene required to be reduced as 
    per directive of the Board, the producer shall indicate the length reduced 
    and total length retained separately.
  


</form><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

Form X
 

[See rule 28(7)]
 

Copy/script/commentary/tape record 
      of commentary of Film.
 

This is to certify that the copy 
      of film/script of the film/commentary/tape record of commentary noted 
      above submitted to the Central Board of Film Certification under Rule 28 
      of the Cinematograph (Certification) Rules, 1983, is an exact copy of the 
      film or its script or commentary, as the case may be, as certified by the 
      Board with complete dialogue, song, sound effects and picturisation. The 
      correct reelwise length of the film as actually measured and certified is 
      given below:
 

 
 

Reel 
      No.        Length in metres
 

1.
 

2.
 

3.
 

TOTAL :
 

 
 

N.B.—This includes the length of the ‘Interval’ 
      and ‘End’ pieces.
 

 
 

Signature of the 
applicant
 

 
 

 
 

 
  </form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



THE CINEMATOGRAPH (CERTIFICATION) RULES, 1983
 

 
 



First Schedule
 


[See rule 21]
 


Applications for certification of films 
    imported into or produced in the States/Union Territories mentioned in 
    column 3 shall be presented at the regional office in column 2:
 
 
  

 
 
Sl. No.
 
Regional Office Situated at
 
Films imported into or produced in

 
  

 
 
1
 
2
 
3

 
  

 
 
1.
 Bangalore
 State of 
        Karnataka.

 
 
2.
 Bombay
 States of 
        Gujarat, Madhya Pradesh and Maharashtra and the Union Territories of 
        Dadra and Nagar Haveli and Goa,   Daman and Diu.

 
 
3.
 Calcutta
 
1[States 
        of Bihar, West Bengal and the Union Territories of Andaman and Nicobar 
        Islands.]

 
 
2[44.
 Cuttack
 State of 
        Orissa.]

 
 
3[5.
 Guwahati
 States of 
        Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland, Sikkim 
        and Tripura.] 

 
 
3[4[6.]]
 Delhi
 States of 
        Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir, Punjab, Rajasthan and 
        Uttar Pradesh and the Union Territories of Chandigarh and Delhi.

 
 
3[4[7.]]
 Hyderabad
 State of 
        Andhra Pradesh.

 
 
3[4[8.]]
 Madras
 State of 
        Tamil Nadu and the Union Territory of Pondicherry.

 
 
3[4[9.]]
 Trivendrum
 TState of 
        Kerala and the Union Territory of Lakshadweep. 

 
  

 
  
  
  


 


Note.—5[(1)] 
    The dubbed version of a film, in whatever Indian language, will be submitted 
    for certification only to the Regional Office where the original version of 
    the film was certified in the first instance.
 



6[(2)] 
    The following two norms will define the “place of production” of films:—
 


(i)  The location of the producer’s 
    association/council/chamber, etc., with whom the film-title was registered 
    before starting production of film concerned. In the case of registration of 
    the title with more than one association/council/chamber, etc., only the 
    earlier registration to be considered; and
 


(ii)  The location of the Head 
    Office/Regional Office/production office of the film 
6[producing] 
    company.
 


 
 


 
 



---------------------------
 



         1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 134(E), dated 18th March, 1996 (w.e.f. 18-3-1996).
 



         2.   Ins. by G.S.R. 702(E), dated 27th November, 1991 (w.e.f. 
    27-11-1991).
 



        3.   Serial numbers 4 to 7 re-numbered as serial numbers 5 to 8 by G.S.R. 702 (E), dated 27th November, 1991 (w.e.f. 27-11-1991).
 



        4.   Serial numbers 6, 7 and 8 re-numbered as serial numbers 7, 8 and 9 
    by G.S.R. 134(E), dated 18th March, 1996 (w.e.f. 18-3-1996).
 



        5.   Note (1) omitted and Notes (2) and (3) re-numbered as Notes (1) 
    and (2) respectively by G.S.R. 134(E), dated 18th March, 1996.
 



         6.   Subs. by G.S.R. 134(E), dated 18th March, 1996.
 

 

  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 83(E), 
    dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 817(E), 
    dated 16th November, 1994 (w.e.f. 16-11-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 67(E), 
    dated 30th January, 1992 (w.e.f. 30-1-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 817(E), dated 16th November, 1994 (w.e.f. 
    16-11-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 67(E), dated 30th January, 1992 (w.e.f. 30-1-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 798(E), dated 15th December, 1995 (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 603(E), dated 3rd August, 1994 (w.e.f. 3-8-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 816(E), dated 16th November, 1994 (w.e.f. 
    16-11-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Added by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 67(E), dated 30th January, 1992 (w.e.f. 
    30-1-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>
 Subs. by G.S.R. 457(E), dated 2nd July, 2007, for rule 36 and rule 44
(w.e.f. 2-7-2007). Earlier rule 36 was amended by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th
February, 1984 (w.e.f. 1-3-1984) and by G.S.R. 207(E), dated 10th April, 1997 (w.e.f.
10-4-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 413(E), dated 29th May, 1984.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 28th February, 1984 (w.e.f. 1-3-1984).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>