<act><tid>1005961</tid>
<title>THE EPIDEMIC DISEASES ACT, <year>1897</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1897</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 4th February, <year>1897</year>.]

An Act to provide for the better prevention of the spread of Dangerous 
Epidemic Diseases.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the better prevention of 
the spread of dangerous epidemic disease; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:-





<article><tid>1004223</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1377764</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the Epidemic  
Diseases Act, <year>1897</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1944160</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
Part B States.]]
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.






</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1974874</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Powers of Central Government. When the Central Government 
is satisfied that India or any part thereof is visited by, or 
threatened with, an outbreak of any dangerous epidemic disease and 
that the ordinary provisions of the law for the time being in force 
are insufficient to prevent the outbreak of such disease or the spread 
thereof, the Central Government may take measures and prescribe 
regulations for the inspection of any ship or vessel leaving or 
arriving at any port in <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the territories to which this Act extends] 
and for such detention thereof, or of any person intending to sail 
therein, or arriving thereby, as may be necessary.]


</article>



<article><tid>244497</tid>
<number>3</number>Penalty. Any person disobeying any regulation or order made 
under this Act shall be deemed to have committed an offence punishable 
under section 188 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1992125</tid>
<number>4</number>Protection to persons acting under Act. No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against any person for anything done or in good 
faith intended to be done under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. I. in C.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Paragraph (a) omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for s. 2A ins. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and 
Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for, a Part A 
State or a Part C State".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>