<act><title>

THE POLICE ACT, 1861</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Interpretation clause.—The 
    following words and expressions in this Act shall have the meanings assigned 
    to them, unless there be something in the subject or context repugnant to 
    such construction, that is to say—
 
the words 
    “Magistrate of the district” shall mean the chief officer charged with the 
    executive administration of a district and exercising the powers of a 
    Magistrate, by whatever designation the chief officer charged with such 
    executive administration is styled;
 
the word 
    “Magistrate” shall include all persons within the general police district, 
    exercising all or any of the powers of a Magistrate; 
 
the word 
    “police” shall include all persons who shall be enrolled under this Act; 
 
the 
    words “general police-district” shall embrace any<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> presidency, 
    State or place or any part of any presidency, State or place in which this 
    Act shall be ordered to take effect;
 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the 
    words “District Superintendent” and “District Superintendent of Police” 
    shall include any Assistant District Superintendent or other person 
    appointed by general or special order of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    to perform all or any of the duties of a District Superintendent of Police 
    under this Act in any district;]
 
the word 
    “property” shall include any movable property, money or valuable security; 
 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[* 
    * *] 
 
the word 
    “person” shall include a company or corporation; 
 
the word 
    “month” shall mean a calendar month; 
 
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[the 
    word “cattle” shall, besides horned cattle, include elephants, camels, 
    horses, asses, mules, sheep, goats and swine. 
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[References 
    to the subordinate ranks of a police-force shall be construed as references 
    to members of that force below the rank of Deputy Superintendent.] 
  
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—Section 1 
    shall be re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof and after that section so 
    re-numbered add the following as sub-section (2), namely:—
 
       “(2) Unless the context 
    otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  ‘public place’ 
    means a place (including a road, street or way, whether a thoroughfare or 
    not, and a landing place) to which the public are granted access or have a 
    right to resort, or over which they have a right to pass;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  ‘State 
    Government’ means the Central Government and includes the Administration of 
    the Union Territory of Pondicherry appointed by the President under article 
    239 of the Constitution.
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 6 
    of 1966, sec. 2 (10-3-1966)]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In section 1, 
    after the definition of the word ‘cattle’ insert the following, namely:—
 
       “The 
    words ‘public place’ shall mean a place (including a road, street or way, 
    whether a thoroughfare or not, and a landing place) to which the public are 
    granted access to have a right to resort, or over which they have a right to 
    access.”
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Acts 22 
    of 1955, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 21-9-1955); 14 of 1962, sec. 4 and  Sch. II 
    (9-1-1963)]
  













 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum><number>2</number> 
    Constitution of the force.—The 
    entire police-establishment under a <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[State Government] shall, 
    for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be one<footcitenum>9</footcitenum> police-force 
    and shall be formally enrolled; and shall consist of such number of officers 
    and men, and shall be constituted in such manner, <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***] as shall 
    from time to time be ordered by the State Government <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***].
 
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, the pay and all other conditions of service 
    of members of the subordinate ranks of any police-force shall be such as may 
    be determined by the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[State Government]].
  
 

State Amendment
 
West Bengal.—After 
    section 2, the following section 2A has been inserted and deemed always to 
    have been inserted:—
 
       “2A. Power of 
    State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of this 
    Act, the State Government may make rules relating to recruitment, conditions 
    of service, disciplinary proceedings and punishments in respect of members 
    of the subordinate ranks of the police force.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any rules, orders or 
    regulations made before the commencement of the Police (West Bengal 
    Amendment) Act, 1963, by any authority in respect of the aforesaid matters 
    shall in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
    Act, be deemed to have been validly made and shall continue in force until 
    other provisions are made in this behalf.”
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 38 
    of 1963, sec. 3.]
  













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Superintendence in the State Government.—The 
    superintendence of the police throughout a general police-district shall 
    vest in and <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[***]
shall be exercised by 
    the State Government to which such district is subordinate, and except as 
    authorised under the provisions of this Act, no person, officer or Court 
    shall be empowered by the <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[State Government] to <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[***] 
    supersede or control any police functionary.
  










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Inspector-General of Police, etc.—<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>The 
    administration of the police throughout a general police-district shall be 
    vested in an officer to be styled the Inspector-General of Police, and in 
    such Deputy Inspectors-General and Assistant Inspectors-General, as the <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[State Government] shall deem fit.
 
The 
    administration of the police throughout the local jurisdiction of the 
    Magistrate of the district shall, under the general control and direction of 
    such Magistrate, be vested in a District Superintendent and such Assistant 
    District Superintendents as the <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[State Government] shall 
    consider necessary.
 
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***]
  
 

state amendment
 
West Bengal.—Substitute 
    the following section 4A:—
 
       “4A. Special 
    and Additional Inspectors-General of Police.—
<section><number>1</number> If, at any time the 
    State Government considers it necessary so to do, it may appoint one or more 
    officers to be Special Inspectors General of Police and may also appoint one 
    or more officers to be additional Inspectors-General of Police, and each of 
    the officers so appointed shall be subordinate to the Inspector-General of 
    Police.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> The Special or, as 
    the case may be, Additional Inspector-General of Police shall be competent 
    to exercise all or any of the powers conferred on, and perform all or any of 
    the functions or duties imposed upon, the Inspector-General of Police by or 
    under this Act or any other law for the time being in force.”
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 5 
    of 1973, sec. 3 (17-3-1973)]
  











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Powers of Inspector-General—Exercise 
    of Powers.—The Inspector-General of Police shall have the full powers of 
    a Magistrate throughout the general police-district but shall exercise those 
    powers subject to such limitation as may, from time to time, be imposed by 
    the <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[State 
    Government].
  
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Section 5 shall 
    be omitted.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 11 of 
    1960, sec. 87 (1-5-1960)]
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
    application to the State of Bombay, section 5 shall be omitted.
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 21 
    of 1954, sec. 3 and Sch. II (8-4-1954).]
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Magisterial powers of police officers.—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 1882), sec. 2 and Sch. 1.] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Appointment, dismissal, etc. of inferior officers.—<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Subject 
    to the provisions of article 311 of the Constitution, and to such rules] as 
    the <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[State Government] may, from time to time, make under this 
    Act, the Inspector-General, Deputy Inspectors-General, Assistant 
    Inspectors-General and District Superintendents of Police may at any time 
    dismiss, suspend or reduce any police-officer of the subordinate ranks] whom 
    they shall think remiss or negligent in the discharge of his duty, or unfit 
    for the same; <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[or may award any one of the following punishments 
    to any police-officer <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[of the subordinate ranks] who shall 
    discharge his duty in a careless or negligent manner, or who by any act of 
    his own, shall render himself unfit for the discharge thereof, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    fine of any amount not exceeding one 
    month’s pay; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    confinement to quarters for a term not 
    exceeding fifteen days with or without punishment-drill, extra guard, 
    fatigue or other duty; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    deprivation of good-conduct pay; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    removal from any office of distinction 
    or special emolument]. 
  































 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Certificates to police officers.—<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>Every 
    police-officer <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[appointed to the police-force, other than an officer 
    mentioned in section 4] shall receive on his appointment, a certificate in 
    the form annexed to this Act, under the seal of the Inspector-General or 
    such other officer as the Inspector-General shall appoint, by virtue of 
    which the person holding such certificate shall be vested with the powers, 
    functions, and privileges of a police officer. 
 

    Surrender of Certificate.—<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[Such 
    certificate shall cease to have effect whenever the person named in it 
    ceases for any reason, to be a police-officer, and on his ceasing to be such 
    an officer, shall be forthwith surrendered by him to any officer empowered 
    to receive the same. 
 
A 
    police-officer shall not, by reason of being suspended from office, cease to 
    be a police-officer. During the term of such suspension, the powers, 
    functions and privileges vested in him as a police-officer shall be in 
    abeyance, but he shall continue subject to the same responsibilities, 
    discipline and penalties and to the same authorities, as if he had not been 
    suspended.]
  
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Orissa</number>—In 
    section 8 the following shall be added, namely:—
 
       “Provided that every 
    police officer appointed to the police force in any merged State prior to 
    the 31st December, 1947 or 1948 and continued in service after that date 
    shall, till the 1st March, 1948 or 1949, be deemed to be a police officer 
    for the purposes of this Act, but after the latter date he shall cease to be 
    a police officer unless he is enrolled under this section.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 4 of 
    1950, Sch. (3-3-1950).]  
 </section><section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After 
    section 8, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
       “8A. Unlawful 
    assumption of police functions, personation, etc.—Any person who—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  unlawfully 
    assumes any function assigned to, or power conferred on a police officer, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  has in his 
    possession, without any lawful excuse, any distinctive article of any dress 
    required to be worn exclusively by a police officer, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  puts on any 
    dress with the intention of being taken as a police officer, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  personates a 
    police officer.
 
shall, in addition to any other 
    punishment to which he may be liable for any offence committed by him under 
    such assumed character, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to six months or with fine or with both.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
 <number>8B</number> Penalty 
    for offences against police officers.—If any person maliciously or 
    without reasonable and probable cause prefers any false or frivolous charge 
    against any police officer in any court of law, he shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine or 
    with both.”
 
[Vide Pondichery Act 6 of 
    1966, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 10-3-1966).]
 
 
























 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Police-officers not to resign without leave or two months’ notice.—No 
    police-officer shall be at liberty to withdraw himself from the duties of 
    his office unless expressly allowed to do so by the District Superintendent 
    or by some other officer authorized to grant such permission, or without the 
    leave of the District Superintendent, to resign his offices, unless he shall 
    have given to his superior officer notice in writing, for a period of not 
    less than two months, of his intention to resign. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Police-officers not to resign without leave or two months’ notice.—No 
    police-officer shall be at liberty to withdraw himself from the duties of 
    his office unless expressly allowed to do so by the District Superintendent 
    or by some other officer authorized to grant such permission, or without the 
    leave of the District Superintendent, to resign his offices, unless he shall 
    have given to his superior officer notice in writing, for a period of not 
    less than two months, of his intention to resign. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Police-officers not to engage in other employment.—No 
    police-officer shall engage in an employment or office whatever other than 
    his duties under this Act, unless expressly permitted to do so in writing by 
    the Inspector-General. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Police 
    superannuation fund.—[Rep. by 
    the Repealing Act, 1874 (16 of 1874), sec. 1 and Sch.] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Power of Inspector-General to make rules.—The 
    Inspector-General of Police may, from time to time, subject to the approval 
    of the <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[State 
    Government], frame such orders and rules as he shall deem expedient relative 
    to the organisation, classification and distribution of the police-force, 
    the places at which the members of the force shall reside, and the 
    particular services to be formed by them; their inspection, the description 
    of arms, accountrements and other necessaries to be furnished to them; the 
    collecting and communicating by them of intelligence and information, and 
    all such other orders and rules relative to the police-force as the 
    Inspector-General shall, from time to time, deem expedient for preventing 
    abuse or neglect of duty, and for rendering such force efficient in the 
    discharge of its duties.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Additional police-officers employed at cost of individuals.—It 
    shall be lawful for the Inspector-General of Police or any Deputy 
    Inspector-General or Assistant Inspector-General, or for the District 
    Superintendent, subject to the general direction of the Magistrate of the 
    district, on the application of any person showing the necessity thereof, to 
    depute any additional number of police-officers to keep the peace at any 
    place within the general police-district and for such time as shall be 
    deemed proper. Such force shall be exclusively under the orders of the 
    District Superintendent and shall be at the charge of the person making the 
    application: 
 
Provided that 
    it shall be lawful for the person on whose application such deputation shall 
    have been made, on giving one month’s notice in writing to the 
    Inspector-General, Deputy Inspector-General or Assistant Inspector-General, 
    or to the District Superintendent to require that the police-officers so 
    deputed shall be withdrawn; and such person shall be relieved from the 
    charge of such additional force from the expiration of such notice.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Appointment of additional force in the neighbourhood of railway and other 
    works.—Whenever any railway, 
    canal or other public work, or any manufactory or commercial concern shall 
    be carried on or be in operation in any part of the country and it shall 
    appear to the Inspector-General that the employment of an additional 
    police-force in such place is rendered necessary by the behaviour or 
    reasonable apprehension of the behaviour of the persons employed upon such 
    work, manufactory or concern, it shall be lawful for the Inspector-General, 
    with the consent of the State Government, to depute such additional force to 
    such place, and to employ the same so long as such necessity shall continue, 
    and to make orders, from time to time, upon the person having the control or 
    custody of the funds used in carrying on such work, manufactory or concern, 
    for the payment of the extra force so rendered necessary, and such person 
    shall, thereupon, cause payment to be made accordingly.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>15</number> 
    Quartering of additional police in disturbed or dangerous districts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be lawful for the State Government, by proclamation to be notified 
    in the Official-Gazette, and in such other manner as the State Government 
    shall direct, to declare that any area subject to its authority has been 
    found to be in a disturbed or dangerous state, or that, from the conduct of 
    the inhabitants of such area or of any class or section of them, it is 
    expedient to increase the number of police.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall, 
    thereupon, be lawful for the Inspector-General of Police, or other officer 
    authorised by the State Government in this behalf, with the sanction of the 
    State Government, to employ any police-force in addition to the ordinary 
    fixed complement, to be quartered in the area specified in such proclamation 
    as aforesaid. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-section (5) of this section, the cost of such 
    additional police-force shall be borne by the inhabitants of such area 
    described in the proclamation. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Magistrate of the district, after such enquiry as he may deem necessary, 
    shall apportion such cost among the inhabitants who are, as aforesaid, 
    liable to bear the same and who shall not have been exempted under the next 
    succeeding sub-section. Such apportionment shall be made according to the 
    Magistrate’s judgment of the respective means within such area of such 
    inhabitants. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> It shall 
    be lawful for the State Government, by order, to exempt any persons or class 
    or section of such inhabitants from liability to bear any portion of such 
    cost. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Every proclamation issued under sub-section (1) of this section shall state 
    the period for which it is to remain in force, but it may be withdrawn at 
    any time or continued from time to time for a further period or periods as 
    the <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[State Government] may, in each case, think fit to direct.
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, “inhabitants” shall include persons who themselves or by their 
    agents or servants, occupy or hold land or other immovable property within 
    such area; and landlords who themselves or by their agents or servants, 
    collect rents direct from raiyats or occupiers in such area, 
    notwithstanding that they do not actually reside therein.]
  






 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>15A</number>
Awarding compensation to sufferers from misconduct of inhabitants or persons
interested in land.—
<section><number>1</number> If, in any area in regard to which any
proclamation notified under the last preceding section is in force, death or
grievous hurt, or loss of, or damage to, property has been caused by or has
ensued from the misconduct of the inhabitants of such area or any class or
section of them, it shall be lawful for any person, being an inhabitant of such
area, who claims to have suffered injury from such misconduct, to make, within
one month from the date of the injury or such shorter period as may be
prescribed, an application for compensation to the Magistrate of the district or
of the sub-division of a district within which such area is situated. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It shall, thereupon, be lawful for the Magistrate of the district, with the
sanction of the 2[State
Government] after such enquiry as he may deem necessary, and whether any
additional police-force has or has not been quartered in such area under the
last preceding section, to— 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
declare the persons to whom injury has been caused by or has ensued from
such misconduct; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
fix the amount of compensation to be paid to such persons and the manner
in which it is to be distributed among them; and 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
assess the proportion in which the same shall be paid by the inhabitants
of such area other than the applicant who shall not have been exempted from
liability to pay under the next succeeding sub-section: 


 Provided
that the Magistrate shall not make any declaration or assessment under this
sub-section, unless he is of opinion that such injury, as aforesaid, had arisen
from a riot or unlawful assembly within such area, and that the person who
suffered the injury was himself free from blame in respect of the occurrences
which led to such injury. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
It shall be lawful for the 1[State
Government], by order, to exempt any persons or class or section of such
inhabitants from liability to pay any portion of such compensation. 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every declaration or assessment made or order passed by the Magistrate of the
district under sub-section (2) shall be subject to revision by the Commissioner
of the Division or the 1[State
Government], but save as aforesaid, shall be final. 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
No civil suit shall be maintainable in respect of any injury for which
compensation has been awarded under this section. 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Explanation.—In this section, the word “inhabitants” shall have the
same meaning as in the last preceding section]. 


 state
amendments 


 <subsection><number>Orissa</number>—Substitute
the following section 15A:— 


 
“15A.
Awarding compensation to sufferers from misconduct of inhabitants of any
area.—(1)
If, in any area, death or grievous hurt or loss of or damage to property
(including public property) has been caused by or has ensued from the misconduct
of the inhabitants of such area or any class or section of them or from the
failure on their part to render assistance in preventing such loss or damage, it
shall be lawful for any person who claims to have suffered injury, loss or
damage from such misconduct or failure, to make within one month from the date
of the injury, loss or damage, as the case may be, an application for
compensation to the Magistrate of the district within which such area is
situated. 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>
It shall thereupon be lawful for the Magistrate of the district, with the
sanction of the State Government, after such enquiry as he may deem necessary,
and whether any additional Police Force has or has not been quartered in such
area under the last preceding section, to— 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
declare the limits of the area the inhabitants of which have, in his
opinion, been guilty of such misconduct or failure; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
declare the persons to whom injury, loss or damage has been caused by or
has ensued from such misconduct or failure; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
fix the amount of compensation to be paid to such person and where there
are more than one such person, the manner in which it is to be distributed among
them; and 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
assess the proportion in which the same shall be paid by the inhabitants
(other than the applicant) of such area who shall not have been exempted under
sub-section (3) from the liability to pay: 


 

Provided that where the applicant is a private individual, the Magistrate
shall not make may declaration unless he is of opinion that such injury, loss or
damage as aforesaid has arisen from a riot or unlawful assembly within such area
and that the applicant was himself free from blame in respect of the occurrence
which led to the injury, loss or damage. 
(3) It shall be lawful for the State Government, by order, to exempt any
person or class or section of such inhabitants from the liability to pay any
portion of such compensation. 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number>
Every declaration or assessment made or order passed by the Magistrate of the
district under sub-section (2) shall be subject to revision by the Revenue
Divisional Commissioner or the State Government, but save as aforesaid shall be
final. 


 </section><section>
<number>5</number>
No civil suit shall be maintainable in respect of any injury, loss or damage for
which compensation has been awarded under this section. 


 

Explanation I.—In
this section— 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
“inhabitants” shall have the same meaning as in section 15; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
“person” shall include the Central Government, the Government of any
State,  any Local
Authority, any Company, any Corporation and any Association of body of
individuals, whether incorporated or not; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
“public property” shall have reference to any property owned by or
belonging to— 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> the Central Government or the Government of any State; 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> any local authority; 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number> any Corporation established under any law which is owned, controlled
or  managed partly
or wholly, by the Central Government or any State Government; 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number> any Company in which not less than fifty-one per cent of the share
capital is held by the Central Government or any State Government or jointly by
more than one such Government; and 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number> any autonomous body established under any law. 


 

Explanation II.—An
application under sub-section (1) may be made— 


 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>
in case of the Government, by such officer as the Government may
authorise in that behalf, and 


 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>
in the case of any local authority, company, corporation, Association or
body, by the person who is in charge of the property.” 


 [Vide
Orissa Act 5 of 1976, sec. 2 (8-3-1976).] 


 Tamil
Nadu.—(i) In sub-section
(1) omit the words “in regard to which any proclamation notified under the
last preceding section is in force” and the words “being an inhabitant of
such area”; 


 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>
in sub-section (2), clauses (a), (b) and (c) shall be re-lettered as clauses
(b), (c) and (d) respectively and the following shall be inserted as clause (a),
namely:— 


 
“(a)
declare the limits of the local area the inhabitants of which have, in
his opinion been guilty of such misconduct or caused or contributed to the
same.” 


 [Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 13 of 1948, sec. 2 (4-5-1948)] 


 Uttar
Pradesh.—In its application
to the whole of Uttar Pradesh except the Jaunsar-Bawar Pargana of the Dehradun
district and the portion of the Mirzapur district south of Kaimur Range, (a) in
sub-section (1) of section 15A, for the words “one month” the words “three
months” shall be substituted; (b) to sub-section (1) of section 15A, add the
following proviso, namely:— 


 

“Provided that the period of limitation for such application for
compensation in respect of death or grievous hurt or loss of, or damage to
property caused before the first day of April, 1939, shall be four months” 


 [Vide
Uttar Pradesh Act 2 of 1939, sec. 2 (1-1-1939).] 


    


 ------------ 1.	Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for
“Provincial Government”."
 

 <subsubsubsection><number>1</number>
Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 5. 	2.	Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec.
5."
 

 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>2</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”. 	1.	Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”."
 

   


</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[<number>16</number> 
    Recovery of moneys payable under sections 13, 14, 15 and 15A, and disposal 
    of same when recovered.—
<section><number>1</number> All moneys payable under sections 13, 14, 15 
    and 15A shall be recoverable by the Magistrate of the district in the manner 
    provided by sections 386 and 387 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 
    of 1882)<footcitenum>32</footcitenum> for the recovery of fines, or by suit in any competent 
    Court.
 
<footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All moneys 
    paid or recovered under section 15A shall be paid by the Magistrate of the 
    district to the persons to whom, and in the proportions in which, the same 
    are payable under that section.] 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Special 
    police-officer.—When it shall 
    appear that any unlawful assembly or riot or disturbance of the peace has 
    taken place, or may be reasonably apprehended, and that the police force 
    ordinarily employed for preserving the peace is not sufficient for its 
    preservation and for the protection of the inhabitants and the security of 
    property in the place where such unlawful assembly or riot or disturbance of 
    the peace has occurred, or is apprehended, it shall be lawful for any 
    police-officer, not below the rank of Inspector, to apply to the nearest 
    Magistrate, to appoint so many of the residents of the neighbourhood as such 
    police-officer may require, to act as special police-officer for such time 
    and within such limits as he shall deem necessary, and the Magistrate to 
    whom such application is made shall, unless he sees cause to the contrary, 
    comply with the application. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Powers 
    of special police-officers.—Every 
    special police-officer so appointed, shall have same powers, privileges and 
    protection and shall be liable to perform the same duties shall be amenable 
    to the same penalties and be subordinate to the same authorities, as the 
    ordinary officer of police. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Refusal 
    to serve as special police-officer.—If 
    any person, being appointed as special police-officer as aforesaid, shall 
    without sufficient excuse, neglect or refuse to serve as such, or to obey 
    such lawful order or direction as may be given to him for the performance of 
    his duties, he shall be liable, upon conviction before a Magistrate, to a 
    fine not exceeding fifty rupees for every such neglect, refusal or 
    disobedience. 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 
20 
    Authority to be exercised by police-officers.—Police-officers 
    enrolled under this Act shall not exercise any authority, except the 
    authority provided for a police-officer under this Act and any Act which 
    shall, hereafter, be passed for regulating criminal procedure.
  






 



 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Village 
    police-officers.—Nothing in this 
    Act shall affect any hereditary or other village police-officer, unless such 
    officer shall be enrolled as a police-officer under this Act. When so 
    enrolled, such officer shall be bound by the provisions of the last 
    preceding section. No hereditary or other village police-officer shall be 
    enrolled without his consent and the consent of those who have the right of 
    nomination.
 

    Police chaukidars in the Presidency of Fort William.—If 
    any police-officer appointed under<footcitenum>35</footcitenum>
Act XX of 1856 (to 
    make better provision for the appointment and maintenance of Police-chaukidars 
    in Cities, Towns, Stations, Suburbs, and Bazars in the Presidency of Fort 
    William in Bengal) is employed out of the district for which he shall 
    have been appointed under that Act, he shall not be paid out of the rates 
    levied under the said Act for that district.
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Police-officers always on duty and may be employed in any part of district.—Every 
    police-officer shall, for all purposes in this Act contained, be considered 
    to be always on duty, and may, at any time, be employed as a police-officer 
    in any part of the general police-district.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Duties 
    of police-officers.—It shall be 
    the duty of every police-officer promptly, to obey and execute all orders 
    and warrants lawfully issued to him by any competent authority; to collect 
    and communicate intelligence affecting the public peace; to prevent the 
    commission of offences and public nuisances; to detect and bring offenders 
    to justice and to apprehend all persons whom he is legally authorised to 
    apprehend, and for whose apprehension sufficient ground exists; and it shall 
    be lawful for every police-officer, for any of the purposes mentioned in 
    this section, without a warrant to enter and inspect, any drinking-shop, 
    gaming-house or other place of resort of loose and disorderly characters.
 

 

state amendment
 <section>
<number>Orissa</number>—Insert as under—
 
                “23A. Powers in relation to 
    cognizable offences in a running train.—Without prejudice to the 
    provision contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 a sub-inspector 
    of police, posted to the mobile out-post of the Government Railway Police, 
    shall, while performing duty in a running train, exercise the powers of the 
    officer-in-charge of the local Government Railway Police Station for the 
    purposes of investigation into cognizable offences committed in a running 
    train and when so exercising such powers, shall be deemed to be the 
    officer-in-charge of such police station discharging the functions of such 
    officer within the limits of that police station.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 1986, sec. 2 
    (29-11-1986).]
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Police-officer may lay information, etc.—It 
    shall be lawful for any police-officer to lay any information before a 
    Magistrate and to apply for a summon, warrant, search-warrant or such other 
    legal process as may, by law, be issued against any person committing an 
    offence 
<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[***].
 









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Police-officers to take charge of unclaimed property and be subject to 
    Magistrate’s orders as to disposal.—It 
    shall be the duty of every police-officer to take charge of all unclaimed 
    property, and to furnish an inventory thereof, to the Magistrate of the 
    district. 
 
The 
    police-officers shall be guided as to the disposal of such property by such 
    orders, as they shall receive from the Magistrate of the district. 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Magistrate may detain property and issue proclamation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Magistrate of the district may detain the property and issue a 
    proclamation, specifying the articles of which it consists, and requiring 
    any person who has any claim thereto, to appear and establish his right to 
    the same, within six months from the date of such proclamation. 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The provisions 
    of section 525 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882
    (10 of 1882)<footcitenum>38</footcitenum> shall 
    be applicable to property referred to in this section.]
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[<number>27</number> Confiscation of 
    property if no claimant appears.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If no person shall within the period allowed, claim such property, or the 
    proceeds thereof, if sold, it may, if not already sold under sub-section (2) 
    of the last preceding section, be sold under the orders of the Magistrate of 
    the district.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    sale-proceeds of property sold under the preceding sub-section and the 
    proceeds of property sold under section 26 to which no claim has been 
    established shall be <footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[at the disposal of 
    the State Government.]
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Persons 
    refusing to deliver up certificate, etc., on ceasing to be 
    police-officers.—Every person, 
    having ceased to be an enrolled police-officer under this Act, who shall not 
    forthwith deliver up his certificate, and the clothing, accountrements, 
    appointments and other necessaries which shall have been supplied to him for 
    the execution of his duty, shall be liable, on conviction before a 
    Magistrate, to a penalty not exceeding two hundred rupees, or to 
    imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a period not exceeding six 
    months, or to both.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Penalties for neglect of duty, etc.—Every 
    police-officer who shall be guilty of any violation of duty or wilful breach 
    or neglect of any rule or regulation of lawful order made by competent 
    authority, or who shall withdraw from the duties of his office without 
    permission, or without having given previous notice for the period of two 
    months, <footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[or who, being absent 
    on leave shall fail, without reasonable cause, to report himself for duty on 
    the expiration of such leave] or who shall engage without authority in any 
    employment other than his police-duty, or who shall be guilty of cowardice, 
    or who shall offer any unwarrantable personal violence to any person in his 
    custody, shall be liable, on conviction before a Magistrate, to a penalty 
    not exceeding three months’ pay, or to imprisonment, with or without hard 
    labour, for a period not exceeding three months, or to both.
 

 

state amendments
 
Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh.—In section 
    29 in its application to Punjab State (now split up into Punjab, Haryana and 
    Chandigarh) omit the words “before a Magistrate.”
 
[Vide Punjab Act 25 of 1964, sec. 2 and 
    Sch. 14 (2-10-1964) Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88  
    (1-11-1966)]
 <section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After section 29, insert 
    the following sections, namely:—
 
 “29A. Prohibition of 
    smoking in places of entertainments.—(1) If any entertainment (including 
    cinematograph exhibition, dance or drama) to which members of the public are 
    admitted, whether on payment or not, is held in an enclosed place or 
    building, then, not person shall during the prohibited period, as defined in 
    sub-section (2), smoke either—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  on the stage 
    except in so far as smoking may be any part of the entertainment, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the 
    auditorium, that is to say, in that portion of the enclosed place or 
    building in which the accommodation is provided for members of the public:
 
       Provided that the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official-Gazette, exempt any class of 
    entertainments from the provisions of this sub-section.
 <subsubsection>
       <number>2</number> For the purposes of 
    sub-section (1), “prohibited period” means so much of the period commencing 
    thirty minutes before the beginning of the entertainment and ending with the 
    termination thereof, as may fall within the hours which the State Government 
    may, by notification in the Official-Gazette, specify in this behalf for 
    entertainment generally or any class of entertainments.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>3</number> Any person who 
    contravenes the provisions of this section shall be liable to be ejected 
    summarily from the enclosed place or building by any police-officer and 
    shall also be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>4</number> A person ejected 
    under sub-section (3) shall not be entitled to the refund of any payment 
    made by him for admission to the entertainment or to any other compensation.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section></article><article>
 <number>29B</number> Powers of Police on 
    occurrence of fire.—
<section><number>1</number> On the occurrence of a fire, any police-officer 
    above the rank of a constable, or any member of the Fire Services above the 
    rank of a fireman, may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  remove or order 
    the removal of any persons who by their presence, interfere with or impede 
    the operations for extinguishing the fire or for saving life or property;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  close any 
    street or passage in or near which any fire is burning;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  by himself or 
    those acting under his orders, break into or through, or pull down, or use 
    for the passage of hoses, or other appliances, any premises for the purpose 
    of extinguishing the fire, doing as little damage as possible;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  cause the mains 
    and pipes in any area to be shut off so as to give greater pressure of water 
    in the place where the fire has occurred:
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  call on the 
    persons in charge of any fire-engine to render such assistance as may be 
    possible; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>f</number>  generally, take 
    such measures as may appear necessary for the preservation of life and 
    property.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any damage done on 
    the occurrence of fires by members of Fire Services or any fire-brigade or 
    by police-officers or their assistants in due execution of their duties 
    shall be deemed to be damage by fire within the meaning of any police of 
    insurance against fire.
 
 Explanation.—Nothing in 
    this section shall exempt any police-officer or any member of Fire-Services 
    or fire-brigade from liability to damages on account of any acts done by him 
    without reasonable causes.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>29C</number> Penalty for false 
    alarm of fire.—Whoever gives or causes to be given to any fire-brigade 
    or to any member thereof or to any member of the Fire Services, whether by 
    means of street fire alarm, statement, message or otherwise, any alarm of 
    fire which he knows to be false, shall be punishable for the first offence 
    with fine which may extend to fifty rupees and for a second or subsequent 
    offence with imprisonment which may extend to six months and with fine.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 6 of 1966, sec. 4 
    (10-3-1966).]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[<number>30</number> Regulation of 
    public assemblies and processions and licensing of the same.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    District Superintendent or Assistant District Superintendent of Police may, 
    as occasion requires, direct the conduct of all assemblies and processions 
    on the public roads, or in the public streets or thoroughfares, and 
    prescribe the routes by which, and the times at which, such processions may 
    pass. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He may 
    also, on being satisfied that it is intended by any person or class of 
    persons to convene or collect an assembly in any such road, street or 
    thoroughfare, or to form a procession which would in the judgment of the 
    Magistrate of the district, or of the sub-division of a district, if 
    uncontrolled, be likely to cause a breach of the peace, required by general 
    or special notice, that the persons convening or collecting such assembly or 
    directing or promoting such procession shall apply for a licence. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On such 
    application being made, he may issue a licence, specifying the names of the 
    licensees and defining the conditions on which alone such assembly or such 
    possession is to be permitted to take place, and otherwise giving effect to 
    this section: 
 
Provided that 
    no fee shall be charged on the application for, or grant of any such 
    licence. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Music 
    in the streets.—He may also regulate the extent to which music may be 
    used in streets on the occasion of festivals and ceremonies.]
 

 

state amendment
 
Tamil Nadu.—(i) In sub-section (1), for 
    the words “on the public roads, or in the public streets or thoroughfares” 
    substitute “in public places.”
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> In sub-section (2), for the words “in any 
    such road, street or thoroughfare” substitute “in any such public place.”
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> In sub-section (4), for the words “in 
    the streets” substitute “in public places”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 22 of 1955, sec. 2 
    (21-9-1955) and Tamil Nadu Act 14 of 1962, sec. 3 and Sch. 1 (9-1-1963)]
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[<number>30A</number> Powers with 
    regard to assemblies and processions violating conditions of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any Magistrate or District Superintendent of Police or Assistant District 
    Superintendent of Police or Inspector of Police or any police-officer in 
    charge of a station may stop any procession which violates the conditions of 
    a licence granted under the last foregoing section, and may order it or any 
    assembly, which violates any such conditions, as aforesaid, to disperse.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    procession or assembly which neglects or refuses to obey any order given 
    under the last preceding sub-section, shall be deemed to be an unlawful 
    assembly.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Police 
    to keep order on public roads, etc.—It 
    shall be the duty of the police to keep order on the public roads, and in 
    the public streets, thoroughfares, ghats and landing-places, and at all 
    other places of public resort, and to prevent obstruction on the occasions 
    of assemblies and processions on the public roads and in the public streets, 
    or in the neighbourhood of places of worship, during the time of public 
    worship, and in any case when any road, street, thoroughfare, ghat or 
    landing-place may be thronged or may be liable to be obstructed. 
 

 

state amendment
 
Tamil Nadu.—In section 31, for the 
    words “on the publications in the public streets, thoroughfares, ghats and 
    landing-places,and at all other places of public resort” substitute the 
    words “in public places”; for the words “on the public roads and in the 
    public streets” substitute “in public places”, and for the words “road, 
    street thoroughfare, ghat or landing-place” substitute the words “public 
    place”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 22 of 1955, sec. 2 
    (21-9-1955).]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Penalty for disobeying orders issued under last three sections, etc.—Every 
    person opposing or not obeying the orders issued under the last <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[three] preceding 
    sections, or violating the conditions of any licence granted by the District 
    Superintendent or Assistant District Superintendent of Police for the use of 
    music, or for the conduct of assemblies and processions, shall be liable, on 
    conviction before a Magistrate, to a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees.<footcitenum>45</footcitenum>
 

 

state amendments
 
Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh.—In section 
    32 in its application to the State of Punjab (now split up into Punjab, 
    Haryana and Chandigarh), omit the words “before a Magistrate”.
 
[Punjab Act 25 of 1964, sec. 2 and Sch. IV 
    (2-10-1964): Act 32 of 1966, sec. 88 (1-11-1966)]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—Insert as under:
 
 “32A. Power to prohibit 
    mass drill or mass training, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Magistrate of the district 
    may, whenever he considers it necessary so to do for preservation of the 
    public peace or public safety or for the maintenance of public order, by 
    public notice or by order directed to individuals in any place prohibit, in 
    any area within his jurisdiction, the carrying of arms or the holding of or 
    taking part it any mass drill or mass training with arms where it arouses 
    reasonable apprehension that the participant in such drill or training are 
    likely to cause fear or alarm or a feeling of insecurity among the public or 
    any section thereof.
 
 Explanation.—For the 
    purpose of this section “arms” means any type of offensive weapon and 
    includes lathi, danda, stick and belcha.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> No prohibition under 
    this section shall remain in force for more than three months:
 
       Provided that if the State 
    Government considers it necessary so to do for the preservation of public 
    peace or public safety or for the maintenance of public order, it may, by 
    notification, direct that a public notice or order issued by Magistrate of 
    the district under sub-section (1) shall remain in force for such further 
    period, not exceeding six months fromt the date on which such notice or 
    order would have, but for such direction, expired as it may specify in the 
    said notification.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> The Magistrate of the 
    district may, either on his own motion or on the application of any person 
    aggrieved, reseind or after any order made by him under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number> The State Government may, 
    either on its own motion or on the application of any person aggrieved, resceind or alter any order made by it under the proviso to sub-section (2) 
    or by the Magistrate of the District under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number> Where an application 
    under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) is received, the Magistrate or the 
    District or the State Government, as the case may be, shall afford to the 
    applicant an opportunity of appearing before him or it either in person or 
    by Pleader and showing cause against the order: and if the Magistrate of the 
    District or the State Government, as the case may be, rejects the 
    application wholly or in part, he or, it shall record in writing the reasons 
    for so doing.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>32B</number> Penalty for 
    contravention of prohibition under section 32A.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever contravenes 
    any prohibition made under section 32A, shall be liable, on conviction 
    before a Magistrate, to imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
    months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees or with both.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, an offence 
    punishable under this section shall be cognizable.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 5 of 1985, sec. 
    5 (1-8-1985).]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Saving of control of Magistrate of district.—Nothing 
    in the last <footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[four] preceding 
    sections shall be deemed to interfere with the general control of the 
    Magistrate of the district over the matters referred to therein.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Punishment for certain offences on roads, etc.—Powers 
    of police-officers.—Any person who, on any road or in any 

    1[open place or] 
    street or thoroughfare within the limits of any town to which this section 
    shall be specially extended by the 

    2[State Government], 
    commits any of the following offences, to the obstruction, inconvenience, 
    annoyance, risk, danger of damage of the 

    3[residents or 
    passengers] shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to a fine 
    not exceeding fifty rupees, or to imprisonment 

    4[with or without hard 
    labour] not exceeding eight days; and it shall be lawful for any 
    police-officer to take into custody, without a warrant, any person who, 
    within his view, commits any of such offences, namely:—
 
First—Slaughtering 
    cattle, furious riding, etc.—Any person who slaughters any cattle 
    or cleans any carcass; any person who rides or drives any cattle recklessly 
    or furiously, or trains or breaks any horse or other cattle; 
 
Second—Cruelty 
    to animal.—Any person who wantonly or cruelly beats, abuses or tortures 
    any animal; 
 
Third—Obstructing 
    passengers.—Any person who keeps any cattle or conveyance of any kind 
    standing longer, than is required, for loading or unloading or for taking up 
    or setting down passengers, or who leaves any conveyance in such a manner as 
    to cause inconvenience or danger to the public: 
 
Fourth—Exposing 
    goods for sale.—Any person who exposes any goods for sale; 
 
Fifth—Throwing 
    dirt into street.—Any person who throws or lays down any dirt, filth, 
    rubbish or any stones or building materials, or who constructs any cowshed, 
    stable or the like, or who causes any offensive matter to run from any 
    house, factory, dung-heap or the like; 
 
Sixth—Being 
    found drunk or riotous.—-Any 
    person who is found drunk or riotous or who is incapable of taking care of 
    himself; 
 
Seventh—Indecent 
    exposure of person.—Any person who wilfully and indecently exposes his 
    person, or any offensive deformity or disease, or commits nuisance by easing 
    himself, or by bathing or washing in any tank or reservoir, not being a 
    place set apart for the purpose; 
 
Eighth—Neglect 
    to protect dangerous places.—-Any person who neglects to fence in 
    or duly to protect any well, tank or other dangerous place or structure. 
 

 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 34, for the word 
    “town” substitute the words “local area”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 34 of 1954, sec. 2 
    (24-11-1954)]
 

 </section><section>
<number>Manipur</number>—1. In section 34, for the 
    words “not exceeding fifty rupees or to imprisonment with or without hard 
    labour not exceeding eight days” substitute the words “not exceeding five 
    hundred rupees, or to imprisonment with or without hard labour not exceeding 
    three months for an offence under clause sixth and to a fine not exceeding 
    fifty rupees, or to imprisonment with or without hard labour not exceeding 
    eight days for the rest of the offence.
 
[The Police (Manipur Second Amendment) Act, 
    1976, sec. 2]
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> The proviso inserted by the Police (Manipur 
    Second Amendment) Act, 1976 after clause eighth shall be omitted.—
 
[Vide Manipur Act 12 of 1977 sec. 2 
    (15-12-1977)
 
After section 34, inset the following section 
    namely:—
 
 “34A. Penalty for annoying 
    females.—Whoever with a view to annoying any female, wilfully and 
    indecently exposes his person or any portion thereof, makes any gesture, 
    utters any word or makes any other sound, in any office, street, public 
    place or vehicle, in such manner as to be seen or heard by such female, 
    whether or not from within any house or building shall be punishable with 
    fine which may extend to fifty rupees.
 
[Vide Manipur Act 1 of 1969, sec. 2 
    (24-2-1969)]
 
After section 34A, insert the following 
    section, namely:—
 
 “34B. Power to arrest.—It 
    shall be lawful for any police officer to take into custody, without a 
    warrant, any person who within his view commits the offence punishable under 
    section 34A.
 
[Vide Manipur Act 1 of 1969, sec. 2 
    (24-2-1969)]
 
After section 34B, add the following section, 
    namely:—
 
 “34C. Prohibition of sale 
    at a higher price of tickets once issued for admission to an entertainment.—(1) 
    For the purpose of preventing disorder or disturbance at or near any place 
    where entertainment is held, the District Magistrate concerned may with the 
    previous sanction of the State Government by order (of which public notice 
    shall be given), prohibit within a radius of one furlong from the place of 
    entertainment the sale or the offer for sale of tickets once issued for 
    admission as spectators to such entertainment at a price higher than the 
    price at which such tickets were originally issued.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Whoever contravenes 
    any order referred to in sub-section (1) shall be liable to imprisonment for 
    a term which may extend to three months or to a fine which may extend to one 
    hundred rupees or to both.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Any police officer 
    not below the rank of Sub-Inspector may arrest without warrant any person 
    committing an offence punishable under this section.
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section the expression the entertainment means any exhibition, performance, 
    amusement, game or sport to which persons are admitted as spectators on 
    production of tickets.”
 
[The Police (Manipur Second Amendment) Act, 
    1976, sec. 3]
 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Orissa</number>—After section 34 insert the 
    following section, namely:—
 
 “34A. Punishment for unauthorised sale of tickets for admission to a place of entertainment.—(1) 
    Any person who sells or attempts to sell tickets for admission to place of 
    entertainment, except under the orders of, and at the place provided and 
    price fixed in this behalf by, the proprietor of the entertainment shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine 
    which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.
 <subsection>
       <number>2</number> If any person is 
    convicted for any second or subsequent offence under sub-section (1) he 
    shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less 
    than twenty-one days but which may extend to one year and shall also be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Any Police Officer 
    not below the rank of Sub-Inspector may take into custody without warrant, 
    any person who, within his view commits any offence punishable under 
    sub-section (1) or seize any ticket in respect of which he is satisfied that 
    any such offence has been committed.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> A court trying an 
    offence under sub-section (1) or under sub-section (2) may without prejudice 
    to any other or further order or orders, that may, in its opinion, be passed 
    in the case, direct the forfeiture of any ticket which may have been seized 
    under sub-section (3).
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section,—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  “entertainment” 
    means any exhibition, performance, amusement game or sports to which persons 
    are admitted on production of tickets; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>b</number>  the expression 
    “proprietor” in relation to any entertainment includes any person 
    responsible for the management of such entertainment.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 34 of 1976, sec. 2 
    (23-8-1976)]
 

 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After section 34, insert 
    the following sections 34A to 34F, namely:—
 
 “34A. Penalty for being 
    found armed between sunset and sunrise intending to commit an offence.—Whoever 
    is found between sunset and sunrise—
 <subsection>
       <number>i</number>  armed with any dangerous 
    instrument with intent to commit an offence; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ii</number>  having his 
    face covered or otherwise disguised with intent to commit an offence; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  lying or loitering or 
    squatting in any bazar, yard or public place and without being able to give 
    a satisfactory account on himself; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  in any 
    dwelling house, or other building, or on board any vessel or boat, without 
    being able to account satisfactorily for his presence there; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  having in his 
    possession, without lawful excuse any instrument of house breaking.
 
        shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    for a term which may extend to three months.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
 <number>34B</number> Penalty for certain 
    offences in public place.—Whoever, in any public place,—
 <section>
       <number>i</number>  drives, drags or pushes any 
    vehicle at any time between half an hour after        sunset and half an 
    hour before sunrise without sufficient light;
 </section><section>
       <number>ii</number>  without reasonable cause, 
    drives, drags or purshes any vehicle otherwise than in accordance with the 
    rules of the road notified from time to time by the Sate Government, or 
    fails to obey the directions of a police-officer for the time being in 
    charge of regulation of traffic;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  leads or 
    rides any animal or drives, drags or pushes any vehicle upon any foot-way, 
    or fastens any animal so that it can stand across or upon any foot-way;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  permits any 
    cattle or vehicle to be under the control of a child under the age of twelve 
    years;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  conveys through 
    the streets any article which projects more than five-feet in front or 
    behind the vehicle or vehicles on which it is placed;
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  beats a drum or tom-tom, or 
    blows a horn or trumpet or beats or sounds any brass or other instrument or 
    utensil or plays any music or use any sound amplifier except at such time 
    and place and subject to such conditions as may be specified in a licence 
    issued in this behalf by the Inspector-General or Police or by any authority 
    authorised in this behalf by him;
 </section><section>
       <number>vii</number>  without the consent of the 
    owner or occupier, in any manner affixes or causes to be affixed any bill 
    notice, document, paper or other thing upon any place or any building, 
    monument, statute, effigy, post, wall fence, tree or other erection therein 
    or in any manner disfigures, writes upon or otherwise marks, or causes to be 
    defaced, disfigured, written upon, or otherwise maked any such public place 
    or any such building, monument, statute, effigy, wall fence, post, tree or 
    erection;
 </section><section>
       <number>viii</number>  begs or 
    applies for alms, or exposes or exhibits any sore, wound bodily ailment or 
    deformity with the object of exciting charity or extorting alms;
 </section><section>
       <number>ix</number>  uses any 
    indecent, threatening abusive or insulting words or behaves in a threatening 
    or insulting manner or posts up or affixes or exhibits any indecent, 
    threatening, abusive or insulting paper or drawing with intent to provoke a 
    breach of peace or whereby a breach of peace may be occasioned;
 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
    to fifty rupees or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one 
    month.
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 5 of 1966, sec. 5 
    (10-3-1966)]
 
After section 34B insert the following new 
    section:—
 
 “34BB. Penalty for annoying 
    females in public place or office.—Whoever, with a view to annoying any 
    female, wilfully and indecently, exposes his person or any portion thereof, 
    makes any gesture, utters any word, or makes any sound, intending that such 
    person or portion thereof or gesture shall be seen or that such word or 
    sound shall be heard by such female in any public place or office, whether 
    such exposure, gesture, word or sound is made or uttered from within any 
    house or building or not, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to one month or with fine which may extend to fifty rupees 
    or with both.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 7 of 1968, sec. 2 
    (11-5-1968)]
 
 “34C. Penalty for 
    committing nuisance in public place.—Whoever in or by the side of or 
    near to any public place commits a nuisance by easing himself or passing 
    urine, or whoever having the care or custody of any child under seven years 
    of age omits to prevent such child committing a nuisance by easing himself 
    or passing urine, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty 
    rupees.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>34D</number> Penalty for lighting 
    bonfire, burning straw, discharging fire-arm, etc., in or near any public 
    place.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever, except at such times and places as the 
    Inspector-General of Police or any person authorised in the behalf by him 
    may allow, in or near any public place lights any bonfire, sets fire to or 
    burns any straw or other matter, discharges any fire-arm or air-gun, lets 
    off or discharges any fire work or sends up any fire baloon or permits such 
    act to be done in premises over which he has control, shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> In the event of any 
    such act as is referred to in sub-section (1), being done within any private 
    premises, the person having the immediate control of such premises shall be 
    deemed to have permitted the act, unless he can prove that the act was 
    committed without his knowledge.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>34E</number> Penalty for 
    drunkenness or riotous or indecent behaviour in public place.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever is found drunk and incapable of taking care of himself or is guilty 
    of any riotous, disorderly or indecent behaviour in any public place, in any 
    place of public amusement, or on board any passenger boat or vessel, shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month or 
    with fine which may extend to fifty rupees or with both.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Whoever is guilty of any 
    violent disorderly or indecent behaviour in any police-office or station 
    shall be punishable with imprisonment for any term which may extend to one 
    month or with fine which may extend to fifty rupees or with both.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>34F</number> Pawn-brokers etc., to 
    report stolen property if tendered for pawn or sale.—
<section><number>1</number> Any officers of 
    police may deliver to any pawn-broker, dealer in second hand property or 
    worker in metals, a list of any property believed to have been stolen, and 
    thereupon it shall be the duty of such pawn-broker, dealer or worker as 
    aforesaid, upon any article answering the description of any of the property 
    set forth in any such list, being offered him in pawn, for sale or 
    otherwise, to inquire the name and address of the party offering such 
    article, to seize and detain the article, and forthwith to communicate to 
    the nearest police station, the fact of such article having been offered and 
    such name and address as may be given by the party offering.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any pawn-broker, 
    dealer or worker who fails, without any reasonable excuse, to comply with 
    the requirement of sub-section (1), shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to fifty rupees for every such offence.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A pawn-broker, dealer or 
    worker to whom any article as is referred to in sub- 
    section (1) is offered may detain the person offering such article, pending 
    the arrival of the police.” 
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 6 of 1966, sec. 5 
    (10-3-1966)]
 
After section 34F insert the following 
    section, namely:—
 
 “34G. Prohibition of sale 
    of tickets for admission to an entertainment except under the orders of, and 
    at the place provided and price fixed by the proprietor of the 
    entertainment.—(1) Whoever sells or attempts to sell tickets for 
    admission to a place of entertainment, except under the order of, and at the 
    place provided and price fixed in this behalf by, the proprietor of the 
    entertainment, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to three months or with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees 
    or both.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any police-officer 
    who takes cognizance of any offence under sub-section (1) may seize any 
    ticket in respect of which he is satisfied that any such offence has been 
    committed.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A court trying any 
    offence punishable under sub-section (1) may, without prejudice to any other 
    or further order or orders that may, in its opinion, be passed in the case, 
    direct the forfeiture of any ticket which may have been seized under 
    sub-section (2).
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “entertainment” 
    means any exhibition, performance, amusement, game or sport to which persons 
    are admitted on production of tickets; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “proprietor”, 
    in relation to any entertainment includes any person responsible for the 
    management of such entertainment. 
 <subsubsection>
[<number>Regn</number> 2 of 1979, sec. 2 (9-4-1979)]
 

 
Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh.—In section 
    34 in its application to the State of Punjab (now split up into Punjab, 
    Haryana and Chandigarh), omit the words “before a Magistrate”
 
[Punjab Act 25 of 1964, sec. 2 and Sch. 
    (2-10-1964); Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88 (1-11-1956)]
 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>Sikkim</number>—After section 34 insert the 
    following section, namely:—
 
 “34A. Power to prohibit, 
    restrict, regulate or impose conditions on the use of microphones etc.—(1) 
    If, in the opinion of the Magistrate of the district or Superintendent of 
    Police of the district or sub-divisional Police Officer, it is necessary so 
    to do for the purpose of preventing annoyance to, or injury to the health 
    of, the public or any section thereof, or for the purpose of maintaining 
    public peace and tranquillity, he may, by order, prohibit, restrict, 
    regulate or impose conditions on the use or operation, in any area within 
    his jurisdiction or in any vehicle within such area, of microphones, 
    loudspeakers or other apparatus for amplifying human voice or for amplifying 
    music or other sounds.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
       <number>2</number> The State Government 
    may, on its own motion or on the representation of any person or persons 
    aggrieved, modify, alter or cancel any order made under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A police-officer, not 
    below the rank of Sub-Inspector, may take such steps or use such force as 
    may be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with any order made 
    under sub-section (1) or any such order as modified or altered by the State 
    Government under sub-section (2) and may seize any microphone, loudspeaker 
    or other apparatus used or operated in contravention of the order.
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number> A police officer, who 
    seizes any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus under sub-section (3), 
    may also at the same time seize any vehicle in which such microphone, 
    loudspeaker or other apparatus is being carried or conveyed or is being kept 
    at that time:
 
       Provided that any 
    police-officer of the police-station within the limits of which the vehicle 
    is seized, not below the rank of Sub-Inspector, may release such vehicle on 
    a bond for such sum not exceeding five hundred rupees as he deems reasonable 
    being executed by the owner of the vehicle in favour of the State Government 
    to produce the vehicle at the time of the investigation or the trial, and to 
    surrender the vehicle, if directed to be forfeited under sub-section (5).
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number> Any person who 
    contravenes any order made by the Magistrate of the district or 
    Superintendent of Police of the district or any sub-divisional police 
    officer under sub-section (1) or any such order as modified or altered by 
    the State Government under sub-section (2) shall, on conviction before a 
    Magistrate, be liable to a fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and 
    the Court trying an offence under this section may also direct the 
    forfeiture of any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus seized under 
    sub-section (3) or any vehicle seized under sub-section (4) or released 
    under the proviso to that sub-section.
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number> The provisions of 
    this section shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the powers 
    conferred by any other section of the Act. 
 
[Vide Sikkim Act 7 of 1980, sec. 3 
    (4-7-1980)]
 </section></article><article>
 <number>34B</number> Power to prohibit sale 
    of tickets for admission to an entertainment except under the orders and at 
    the place provided and price fixed etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person who sells or 
    attempts to sell ticket for admission to a place of entertainment, except 
    under the order of, and at the place provided for and price fixed in this 
    behalf, by the proprietor of the entertainment shall on conviction before a 
    Magistrate, be liable to imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    months or fine which may extend to one hundred rupees or with both.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any police-officer 
    not below the rank of Head-Constable may take into custody, without warrant, 
    any person who, in his view, commits any offence punishable under 
    sub-section (1) or seize any tickets in respect of which he is satisfied 
    that any such offence has been committed.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A Court trying any 
    offence punishable under sub-section (1) may, without prejudice to any order 
    or further order or orders that may, in its opinion be passed in the case, 
    direct the forfeiture of any ticket which may have been seized under 
    sub-section (2).
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “entertainment” 
    means any exhibition, performance, amusement, game or sport to which persons 
    are admitted on production of ticket, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the expression 
    “proprietor” in relation to any entertainment includes any person 
    responsible for the management of such entertainment.”
 
[Vide Sikkim Act 7 of 1980, sec. 3 
    (4-7-1980)]
 

 
Tamil Nadu.—In section 34, for the 
    words “on any road or in any open place or street or thoroughfare” 
    substitute “any public place”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Acts 22 of 1955, sec. 
    2 (21-9-1955); 14 of 1962, sec. 2 and Sch.]
 

 <subsubsection>
<number>Tripura</number>—In section 34, after clause 
    eight, insert the following clause, namely:—
 
       “Ninth—any person who 
    rides a bicycle without a bell at any hour of day or night, or without a 
    light, during the hours indicated below, namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
            <number>a</number>  April to September:
 
                   6-30 p.m. to 5 a.m.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
           <number>b</number>  October to March:
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
                   <number>5</number>30 p.m. to 5 a.m.
 
[Vide Tripura Act 5 of 1965, sec. 2]
 
After section 34 insert the following section, 
    namely:—
 </section></article><article>
 <number>34A</number> Prohibition of sale of 
    tickets for admission to an entertainment except under the orders of, and at 
    the place provided and price fixed by, the proprietor of the entertainment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who sells or attempts to sell tickets for admission to a place of 
    entertainment, except under the orders of and at the place provided and 
    price fixed in this behalf by, the proprietor of the entertainment, shall, 
    on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding eight days or to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any police-officer 
    not below the rank of Sub-Inspector may take into custody, without a 
    warrant, any person who, within his view, commits any offence punishable 
    under sub-section (1) or seize any ticket in respect of which he is 
    satisfied that any such offence has been committed.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A Court trying an 
    offence punishable under sub-section (1) may, without prejudice to any other 
    or further order or order that may, in its opinion, be passed in the case, 
    direct the forfeiture of any ticket which may have been seized under 
    sub-section (2).
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section.—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  entertainment 
    means any exhibition, performance amusement, game or sport to which persons 
    are admitted on production of tickets; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the expression 
    ‘proprietor’ in relation to any entertainment includes any person 
    responsible for the management of such entertainment.
 
[Vide Tripura Act 6 of 1965, sec. 3]
 
After section 34A insert the following 
    section, namely:—
 </subsection></section></article><article>
 <number>34B</number> Offences under 
    sections 32, 34, 34A to be compoundable.—
<section><number>1</number> An offence punishable under 
    section 32, 34 or 34A may, with the permission of the Court before which any 
    prosecution for such offence is pending, be compounded by the District 
    Superintendent of Police or any person authorised in this behalf by him.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> The composition of an 
    offence under sub-section (1) shall have the effect of an acquittal of the 
    accused with whom the offence has been compounded. 
 
[Vide Tripura Act 5 of 1965, sec. 3]
 

 
Uttar Pradesh.—(i) the existing section 
    34 shall be re-numbered as section 34(1).
 <subsection>
       <number>ii</number> in sub-section (1) as so re-numbered, 
    word “visitors” shall be inserted between the words “residents” and “or 
    passengers”, and for the words “section” the word “sub-section” shall be 
    substituted.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> After sub-section (1) as so re-numbered 
    the following shall be added as new sub-sections (2) and (3):—
 
       “(2) The State Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend to any rural area, 
    specified in the notification the provisions of sub-section (1) and 
    thereupon its provisions shall apply to such area as if it were a town to 
    which the said sub-section (1) and thereupon its provisions shall apply to 
    such area as if it were a town to which the said sub-section had been 
    specially extended.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>3</number> The extension under 
    sub-section (2) shall be for a specified period and in respect of all or any 
    of the offences as may be specified.
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 32 of 1952, 
    sec. 2 (20-1-1952)]
 
After section 34 insert the following section 
    34A:—
 
 “34A. Compounding of 
    offences under sections 32 and 34.—An offence punishable under section 
    32 or section 34 may, subject to any general or special order of the State 
    Government in this behalf, be compounded by the District Superintendent of 
    Police, either before or after the institution of the prosecution, on 
    realisation of such amount of composition fee as he thinks fit not exceeding 
    the maximum amount of fine fixed for the offence; and when the offence is so 
    compounded—
 <subsection>
       <number>i</number>  before the institution of the 
    prosecution, the offender shall not be liable to prosecution, for such 
    offence and shall if in custody, be set at liberty;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ii</number>  after the 
    institution of the prosecution the composition shall amount to acquittal of 
    the offender.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 35 of 1979, 
    sec. 5 (21-12-1979)]
 

 
West Bengal.—After section 34 insert 
    the following section, namely:—
 
 “34A. Power to prohibit, 
    restrict, regulate or Impose conditions on the use of microphones, etc.—(1) 
    If, in the opinion of the Magistrate of the district or any Sub-Divisional 
    Magistrate, or Magistrate of the first class, it is necessary so to do for 
    the purpose of preventing annoyance to, or injury to the health of, the 
    public or any section thereof, or for the purpose of maintaining public 
    peace and tranquillity, he may, by order, prohibit, restrict, regulate or 
    impose conditions on, the use or operation, in any area within his 
    jurisdiction or in any vehicle within such area, of microphones, 
    loudspeakers or other apparatus for amplifying human voice or for amplifying 
    music or other sound. 
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>2</number> The State Government 
    may, on its own motion or on the representation of any person or persons 
    aggrieved, modify, alter or cancel any order made under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A police officer, not 
    below the rank of Sub-Inspector, may take such steps or use such force as 
    may be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with any order made 
    under sub-section (1) or any such order as modified or altered by the State 
    Government under sub-section (2) and may seize any microphone, loudspeaker 
    or other apparatus used or operated in contravention of the order.
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number> A police-officer, who 
    seizes any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus under sub-section (3), 
    may also at the same time seize any vehicle in which such microphone, 
    loudspeaker or other apparatus is being carried or conveyed or is being kept 
    at that time:
 
       Provided any police-officer of 
    the police-station within the limits of which the vehicle is seized, not 
    below the rank of Sub-Inspector, may release such vehicle on a bond for such 
    sum not exceeding five hundred rupees as he deems reasonable being executed 
    by the owner of the vehicle in favour of the State Government to produce the 
    vehicle at the time of the investigation or the trial, and to surrender the 
    vehicle, if directed to be forfeited under sub-section (5).
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number> Any person who 
    contravenes any order made by the Magistrate of the district or any 
    Sub-Divisional Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class under sub-section 
    (1) or any such order as modified or altered by the State Government under 
    sub-section (2), shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to a 
    fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and the Court trying an offence 
    under this section may also direct the forfeiture of any microphone, 
    loudspeaker or other apparatus seized under sub-section (3) or any vehicle 
    seized under sub-section (4) or released under the proviso to that 
    sub-section.
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number> The provisions of 
    this section shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the powers 
    conferred by any other section of this Act.”
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 38 of 1963, sec. 
    5 (3-2-1964)] 
 
After section 34A, insert the following 
    section 34B:—
 
 “34B. Prohibition of sale 
    of tickets for admission to an entertainment except under the orders of, and 
    at the place provided and price fixed by, the proprietor of the 
    entertainment.—(1) Any person who sells or attempts to sell tickets for 
    admission to a place of entertainment, except under the orders of, and at 
    the place provided and price fixed in this behalf by, the proprietor of the 
    entertainment, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine which 
    may extend to one hundred rupees or to both.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any police officer 
    not below the rank of Sub-Inspector may take into custody, without warrant, 
    any person who, within his view, commits any offence punishable under 
    sub-section (1) or seize any ticket in respect of which he is satisfied that 
    any such offence has been committed.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A court trying any 
    offence punishable under sub-section (1) may, without prejudice to any other 
    or further order or orders that may, in its opinion, be passed in the case, 
    direct the forfeiture of any ticket which may have been seized under 
    sub-section (2).
 
 Explanation.—In this 
    section.—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “entertainment” 
    means any exhibition, performance, amusement, game or sport to which persons 
    are admitted on production of tickets; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the expression 
    “proprietor” in relation to any entertainment includes any person 
    responsible for the management of such entertainment.”
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 26 of 1964, sec. 
    4 (12-12-1964).]
 
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Jurisdiction 
<footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[***].—Any 
    charge against a police-officer above the rank of a constable, under this 
    Act shall be enquired into and determined only by an officer exercising the 
    powers of a 

    2Magistrate.
 

 

state amendments
 
Maharashtra, Gujarat.—In its 
    application to the State of Bombay in section 35, for the words ‘exercising 
    the power of a Magistrate’, substitute “of such rank as the State Government 
    may by a general or special order, direct.”
 <section>
[<number>Bom</number> Act 21 of 1954, sec. 3 and Sch. II 
    (8-4-1954); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (1-5-1960)]
 </section><section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After section 35, insert 
    the following sections, namely:—
 
 “35A. Fee for licence.—For 
    every licence or permission granted under this Act the Inspector-General of 
    Police may levy such fee not exceeding two rupees as may from time to time, 
    be fixed by the State Government.
 </section></article><article>
 <number>35B</number> Police Officer may 
    arrest without a warrant in view of offence.—Any Police Officer may 
    arrest without a warrant any person committing in his view any offence made 
    punishable under sections 29A, 34A, 34B, 34C, 34D, 34E or 34G.
 </article><article>
 <number>35C</number> Penalty for breach of 
    conditions of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> For any breach of the conditions of a 
    licence granted under this Act, the offender shall be liable on conviction 
    to fine, not exceeding one hundred rupees and such fine may be recovered 
    from the person licenced, notwithstanding that such breach may have been 
    owing to the default or carelessness of his servant or agent in charge of 
    the shop or place.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> Any licence granted to a 
    person who is convicted for any breach of any of the conditions of a licence 
    granted under this Act shall also be liable to be cancelled at the 
    discretion of the Inspector-General of Police.” 
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 6 of 1966, sec. 5 
    (10-3-1966)]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> Power 
    to prosecute under other law not affected.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall be construed to prevent any person from being 
    prosecuted under any other Regulation or Act for any offence made punishable 
    by this Act, or from being liable under any other Regulation or Act or any 
    other or higher penalty or punishment that is provided for such offence by 
    this Act.
 <section>
<number>Proviso</number>—Provided 
    that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[<number>37</number> Recovery of 
    penalties and fines imposed by Magistrates.—The provisions of sections 
    64 to 70, both inclusive, of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and of <footcitenum>54</footcitenum>sections 386 to 389, 
    both inclusive, of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 1882) with 
    respect to fines, shall apply to penalties, and fines imposed under this Act 
    on conviction before a Magistrate:
 
Provided that, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in section 65 of the first-mentioned 
    Code, any person sentenced to fine under section 34 of this Act, may be 
    imprisoned in default of payment of such fine for any period not exceeding 
    eight days.]
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Procedure until return is made to warrant of distress.—[Rep. 
    by the Police Act (1861) Amendment Act, 1895 (8 of 1895), sec.14.] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Imprisonment of distress not sufficient.—[Rep. 
    by the Police Act (1861) Amendment Act, 1895 (8 of 1895), sec. 14.] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> Levy of 
    fines from European British Subject.—[Rep. 
    by the Police Act (1861) Amendment Act, 1895 (8 of 1895), sec. 14.] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Rewards to police and informers payable to General Police Fund.—[Rep. 
    by the A.O. 1937<footcitenum>55</footcitenum>]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>56</footcitenum><number>42</number> Limitation of 
      actions.—All actions and prosecutions against any 
      person, which may be lawfully brought for anything done or intended to be 
      done under the provisions of this Act, or under the general police powers 
      hereby given shall be commenced within three months after the act 
      complained of shall have been committed, and not otherwise; and notice in 
      writing of such action and of the cause thereof shall be given to the 
      defendant, of to the District Superintendent or an Assistant District 
      Superintendent of the district in which the act was committed, one month, 
      at least before the commencement of the action.
 Tender of amends.—No plaintiff shall recover in any such action, 
      if tender of sufficient amends shall have been made before such action 
      brought, or if a sufficient sum of money shall have been paid into Court 
      after such action brought, by or on behalf of the defendant, and though a 
      decree shall be given for the plaintiff in any such action, such plaintiff 
      shall not have cost against the defendant, unless the Judge before whom 
      the trial is held shall certify his approbation of the action: 
 <section><number>Proviso</number>—Provided always that no action shall, in any 
      case, lie where such officers shall have been prosecuted criminally for 
      the same act.
  




 
</section></article> 

   

   

 <article><number>43</number> Plea that act was done under 
warrant.—When any action of prosecution shall be brought or 
any proceedings held against any police-officer for any act done by him in such 
capacity, it shall be lawful for him to plead that such act was done by him 
under the authority of a warrant issued by a Magistrate. 

 Such plea shall be proved by the production of the warrant 
directing the act, and purporting to be signed by such Magistrate and the 
defendant shall, thereupon, be entitled to a decree in his favour, 
notwithstanding any defect of jurisdiction in such Magistrate. No proof of the 
signature of such Magistrate shall be necessary, unless the Court shall see 
reason to doubt its being genuine:  
 <section><number>Proviso</number>—Provided 
always that any remedy which the party may have against the authority issuing 
such warrant shall not be affected by anything contained in this 
section.</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>44</number>
Police-officers to keep diary.—It
shall be the duty of every officer in-charge of a police-station to keep a
general diary in such form as shall, from time to time, be prescribed by the <footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[State
Government] and to record therein, all complaints and charges preferred, the
names of all persons arrested, the names of the complainants, the offences
charged against them, the weapons or property that shall have been taken from
their possession or otherwise, and the names of the witnesses who shall have
been examined. 


 The
Magistrate of the district shall be at liberty to call for and inspect such
diary. 








</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>45</number> <footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[State
Government] may prescribe form of returns.—The
<footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[State
Government] may direct the submission of such returns by the Inspector-General
and other police-officers as to such <footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[State
Government] shall seem proper, and may prescribe the form in which such returns
shall be made. 


 state
amendments 


 Madhya Pradesh.—After
section 45, the following section shall be deemed to be inserted, namely:— 


 
“45A. Conferment of powers of
police-officers.—The State Government
may, by notification, confer on any person any of the powers which may be
exercised by a police officer under any Act for the time being in force and such
person shall be subject to the orders of the District Superintendent of
Police.” 


 <section>[<number>C</number>P.
and Berar Act 3 of 1937, sec. 2 (15-10-1937) read with M.P. Act 23 of 1958, sec.
3 and Sch.]


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[<number>46</number> Scope of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act shall not, by its own 
      operation, take effect in any <footcitenum>60</footcitenum>presidency, <footcitenum>61</footcitenum>[State] 
      or place.
 But the <footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[State Government] by an order to be published 
      in the <footcitenum>63</footcitenum>[Official Gazette], may extend the whole or any part of 
      this Act to any Presidency, <footcitenum>64</footcitenum>[State] or place, and the whole or 
      such portion of this Act, as shall be specified in such order shall, 
      thereupon, take effect in such presidency, <footcitenum>64</footcitenum>[State] or 
      place.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the whole or any part of this Act shall have been so 
      extended, the <footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[State Government] may, from time 
      to time, by notification in the <footcitenum>63</footcitenum>[Official Gazette], make rules 
      consistent with this Act—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    to regulate 
      the procedure to be followed by Magistrates and police-officers in the 
      discharge of any duty imposed upon them by or under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    to prescribe 
      the time, manner and conditions within and under which claims for 
      compensation under section 15A are to be made, the particulars to be 
      stated in such claims, the manner in which the same are to be verified, 
      and the proceedings (including local inquiries, if necessary) which are to 
      be taken consequent thereon; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    generally, 
      for giving effect to the provisions of this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> All rules made under this Act, may, from time to time be 
      amended, added to or cancelled by the <footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[State 
      Government].]
  
 state amendments
 Maharashtra, Gujarat.—In its 
      application to the State of Bombay in clause (a) of sub-section (2) of 
      section 46 for the words `Magistrate,’ substitute `executive 
      Magistrates,’
 [Vide Bombay Act 21 of 1954, 
      sec. 3 and Sch. 11 (8-4-1954); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 
       (1-5-1960).]
 <subsection><number>Orissa</number>—In section 46, 
      sub-section (1) and the first fourteen words of sub-section (2) shall be 
      omitted.
 [Vide Orissa Act 4 of 1950, 
      Sch. (3-3-1950)]
  


























 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Authority of District Superintendent of Police over village-police.—It 
    shall be lawful for the 

    1[State Government] in 
    carrying this Act into effect in any part of the territories subject to such
    
<footcitenum>65</footcitenum>[State Government], 
    to declare that any authority which now is or may be exercised by the 
    Magistrate of the district over any village-watchman or other village 
    police-officer for the purposes of police, shall be exercised subject to the 
    general control of the Magistrate of the district, by the District 
    Superintendent of Police.
 
 





 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Under section 2 of the 
    Police Act, 1888 (3 of 1888), the Central Government may notwithstanding 
    this provision, create a special police-district, consisting of parts of two 
    or more States. As to Delhi State see Gazette of India, 1912, Pt. 1, 
    p. 1105.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, 
    sec. 1. tc " 3. Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 1."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   The definitions 
    relating to “number” and “gender” rep. by Act 10 of 1914, sec. 3 and Sch. 
    II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Cf. definition of 
    “cattle” in section 3 of the Cattle-trespass Act, 1871 (1 of 1871).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Section. 2, so far as 
    it is related to the provinces under the administration of the 
    Lieutenant-Governor of Bengal, rep. by the Bengal Police Act, 1869 (Bengal 
    Act 7 of 1869).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   See note to 
    section 8 infra, as to enrolment of the police force in certain 
    places.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   The words “and the 
    members of such force shall receive such pay” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   The word “appoint,” 
    omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   In the town and 
    suburbs of Calcutta, the administration of the police vests in the 
    “Commissioner of Police”, see section 3 of the Calcutta Police Act, 
    1866 (Bengal Act 4 of 1866).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Subs. by the A.D. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by the A.D. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for certain words. tc " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for certain words."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950 
    (as amended by C.O. 29), for “subject to such rules”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 
    1895, sec. 2, for certain words. tc " 4. Subs. by Act 
    8 of 1895, sec. 2, for certain words."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 1937. tc 
    " 5. Ins. by the A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   As to enrolment, 
    maintenance and discipline of—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937 for “so appointed”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 
    1895, sec. 3, for the original second paragraph.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”. tc " 1. Subs. by 
    the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 
    1895, sec. 4, for section 15.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 6, for section 16.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   See now sections 421 and 422 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Sub-section (2) omitted by the A.O. 1937. See, however, 
    para 4 of the Indian and Burma (Transitory Provisions) Order, 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   For some cases in which the application of section 20 has been 
    restricted, see the Assam Police-Officers Regulation, 1883 (2 of 
    1883), and section 2 of the Punjab Frontier Police-Officers Regulation, 1893 
    (7 of 1893).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   The Bengal Chaukidari Act, 1856. tc 
    " 2. The Bengal Chaukidari Act, 1856."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   The words “and to prosecute such person up to final judgement” 
    rep. by Act 10 of 1882, sec. 2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 7. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 7."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   See now section 459 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (Act 2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 8, for section 27.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “at the disposal of Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 9. tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 9."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 10, for section 30.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 11. tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 11."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 12, for “two”. tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 12, for “two”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>   This section was extended to the State of Sandur by Madras Act 35 
    of 1949, sec. 14. Sundur State now forms part of Mysore State—[See 
    Act 37 of 1956].</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 12, for “three”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 13. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 13."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”. tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 13, for “residents and passengers”. tc 
    " 4. Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 13, for “residents and passengers”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>   Ins. by Act 1 of 1903, sec. 3 and Sch. II. tc 
    " 5. Ins. by Act 1 of 1903, sec. 3 and Sch. II."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>   Certain words rep. by Act 10 of 1882, sec. 2 and Sch. tc 
    " 1. Certain words rep. by Act 10 of 1882, sec. 2 and Sch."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>   i.e., by a Magistrate of the first class, See 
    sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
    1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 1895, sec. 14, for section 37.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>   See now sections 421 to 424 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>   See, however, paragraph 4 of the India and Burma 
    (Transitory Provisions) Order, 1937, section 41 reads as follows:—‘All sums 
    paid for the service of process by police-officers, and all rewards, 
    forfeiture and penalties or shares of rewards, forfeitures and penalties 
    which by law are payable to informers shall when the information is laid by 
    a police-officer, be paid into the general police Fund.’</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>   So much of 
      section 42 (the portion printed in italics) as relates to the limitation 
      of suits rep. by Act 9 of 1871, sec. 2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”.    tc " 	3.	Subs.
by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>See, however,
paragraph 4 of the India and Burma (Transitory Provisions) Order, 1937, section
41 reads as follows:—‘All sums paid for the service of process by
police-officers, and all rewards, forfeiture and penalties or shares of rewards,
forfeitures and penalties which by law are payable to informers shall when the
information is laid by a police-officer, be paid into the general police
Fund.’ tc "1.	See,
however, paragraph 4 of the India and Burma (Transitory Provisions) Order,
1937, section 41 reads as follows\:—‘All sums paid for the service of process
by police-officers, and all rewards, forfeiture and penalties or shares of
rewards, forfeitures and penalties which by law are payable to informers shall
when the information is laid by a police-officer, be paid into the general
police Fund.’"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>   Subs. by 
      Act No. 8 of 1895, sec. 15, for section 46.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number>   In the 
      States of Madras and Bombay, there are special Police Acts, see the 
      Madras District Police Act, 1859 (24 of 1859) and the Bombay District 
      Police Act, 1867 (Bombay Act 7 of 1867). In the Lower Provinces of Bengal, 
      Bengal Act 7 of 1869 is to be read and taken as part of Act 5 of 1861, 
      see section 6 of the former Act.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial 
      Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Gazette of 
      India”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”. tc 
    " 1. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government”."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>