<act><tid>472128</tid>
<title>THE COTTON TEXTILES CESS ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 1st March, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to impose a cess on <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manufacture of certain cotton 
textiles].

WHEREAS it is expedient to impose a cess on <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manufacture of 
certain cotton textiles];

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>16419</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>560839</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Cotton Textiles Cess Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1632733</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India, except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].

</section>

<section><tid>791230</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 31st day of 
December, <year>1947</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>376746</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1203719</tid>
<number>a</number>" cloth" and" yarn" mean respectively the cloth and yarn 
of which prices fixed by any order made under section 3 
or continued by section 17 of the Essential Supplies 
 (Temporary Powers) Act, <year>1946</year> (24 of <year>1946</year>), were in 
force immediately before the commencement of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>948321</tid>
<number>b</number>" producer" means a person engaged in the production of 
cloth or yarn or both by power as defined in clause (f) 
of section 2 of the Factories Act, <year>1934</year> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (25 of  
  <year>1934</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>725190</tid>
<number>3</number>Levy of cess. The Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 
in the Official Gazette, levy on any cloth or yarn held in stock by a 
producer or a wholesale dealer on such date as the Central Government 
may fix in this behalf a cess at such rate as may be specified in the 
notification.


</article>



<article><tid>18133</tid>
<number>4</number>Effect on contracts. Where before the date mentioned in 
section 3 a producer or wholesale dealer has made a contract of sale 
in respect of any cloth or yarn on which a cess is levied under that 
section, it shall be lawful
<pagefootnote><pagenum>66</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" certain cotton textiles 
manufactured in the Provinces of India". 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
3. See now the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>). 
4. No. 90 4 Tex. I 48 (i), dated the 2nd March, <year>1948</year>, Gazette of 
India, <year>1948</year>, Extraordinary, p. 407.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for him to charge the amount of the cess to the buyer in addition to 
the contract price.



</article>



<article><tid>1209649</tid>
<number>5</number>Payment of cess. The cess shall be paid by the producer or the 
wholesale dealer as the case may be to such authority within such time 
and in such manner as may be specified in the notification.


</article>



<article><tid>1694199</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalty for non- payment. If any cess payable under this Act is 
not paid as prescribed, it shall be deemed to be in arrears and the 
authority appointed in this behalf by the Central Government may, 
after such enquiry as he deems fit, impose on the producer or the 
dealer a penalty not exceeding the amount of cess in arreras.


</article>



<article><tid>952504</tid>
<number>7</number>Recovery of cess and penalty. The amount of cess in arrears 
and any sum imposed as penalty under section 6 shall, without 
prejudice to any other liability incurred under this Act be recovered 
as arrears of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>76561</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power of inspection, entry and search. Any authority 
authorized by the Central Government in this behalf may, with a view 
to securing compliance with this Act,--
<section><tid>1870674</tid>
<number>a</number>require any producer or dealer to furnish to such 
authority such information relating to his business as 
that authority may specify;

</section>

<section><tid>1903509</tid>
<number>b</number>inspect or cause to be inspected any books or other 
documents belonging to or under the control of such 
producer or dealer;

</section>

<section><tid>1163623</tid>
<number>c</number>enter and search or authorize any person to enter and 
search any premises and seize or authorize any person 
to seize any cloth or yarn in respect of which he has 
reason to believe that a contravention of this Act has 
been or is about to be committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150196</tid>
<number> 9</number> Penalty for evasion of cess or failure to comply with order 
under section 8.
<section><tid>166025</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever evades or attempts to evade the payment  
of cess payable by him under this Act or fails to comply with any 
order issued to him under clause (a) of section 8 or furnishes any 
information which is false and which he knows or has reasonable cause 
to believe to be false or does not believe to be true, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment which may extend to 6 months or with fine 
which may extend to two thousand rupees or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>952496</tid>
<number>2</number>Any Court trying any offence under this Act may order that 
any cloth or yarn together with the packages or coverings thereof in 
respect of which the Court is satisfied that an offence under this Act 
has been committed shall be forfeited to the Central Government.


</section>

</article>



 </act>