<act><title>


    The statutory Investigation into Railway Accidents Rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>1</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Statutory Investigation into Railway 
    Accidents Rules, 1998. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 

 





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>2</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> (a) Inquiry into a serious accident by the Commissioner of Railway 
    Safety.—Where the Commissioner of Railway Safety receives notice under 
    section 113 of the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989) hereinafter referred to 
    as the Act, of the occurrence of an accident which he considers of a 
    sufficiently serious nature to justify such a course, he shall, as soon as 
    may be, notify the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety, the Railway Board 
    and the Head of the Railway Administration concerned of his intention to 
    hold an inquiry and shall, at the same time, fix and communicate the date, 
    time and place for the inquiry. He shall also issue or cause to be issued a 
    Press Note in this behalf inviting the public to tender evidence at the 
    inquiry and send information relating to the accident to his office address. 
 </section><section>

    <number>1</number> (b) While notifying his intention to hold an inquiry as aforesaid, the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety shall also inform or cause to inform the 
    Chief Secretary of the State, the District Magistrate and the Superintendent 
    of Police of the district concerned.  
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> For the purpose of this rule, every accident to a train carrying 
    passengers which is attended with loss of life of a passenger or passengers 
    in the train or with grievous hurt, as defined in the Indian Penal Code 
    (hereinafter referred to as the grievously hurt) to a passenger or 
    passengers in the train or with serious damage or railway property of a 
    value exceeding twenty-five lakh rupees and any other accident which in the 
    opinion of the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety or the Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety requires the holding of an inquiry shall be deemed to be an 
    accident of such a serious nature as to require the holding of an inquiry.  
 

    These accidents shall be termed as “Serious train accidents”.  
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> However, for any accident the Chief Commissioner may either hold the 
    inquiry himself or direct any Commissioner of Railway Safety to do so.  
 

Explanation.—The 
    inquiry under this rule shall be obligatory only in those cases where the 
    passengers, killed or grievously hurt were travelling in the train carrying 
    passengers. If an accident involving a train carrying passengers leads to 
    loss of life or grievous injury to any Railway Servant(s) irrespective of 
    whether he was travelling in that passenger train or not, inquiry under this 
    rule shall be obligatory. However, if a person being a railway servant or 
    holding valid pass or ticket or otherwise travelling outside the Rolling 
    Stock of a Passenger train (such as on footboard or roof or buffers but 
    excluding the inside of vestibules between coaches) is killed or grievously 
    hurt, or is run over at a level crossing or elsewhere on the railway track, 
    an inquiry under this rule shall not be obligatory. Similarly, if in a 
    collision between a road vehicle and a passenger train at a level crossing, 
    no passenger in the train is killed or grievously hurt, it shall not be 
    obligatory to hold an inquiry. For the purpose of this rule, workmen’s 
    trains or ballast trains or Material trains or Accident Relief Trains or 
    Tower wagons or such other trains carrying workmen or cattle 
    specials/Military specials carrying authorised escorts or similar such 
    trains shall also be treated as passenger trains and in the event of a 
    workman or escort being killed or grievously hurt as a result of an accident 
    to the train, an inquiry under this rule shall be obligatory.  
 </section><section>

    <number>4</number> When an accident requiring the holding of an inquiry occurs at a station 
    whether the jurisdiction of two or more Commissioners of Railway Safety 
    meet, the duty of complying with this rule shall devolve on the Commissioner 
    of Railway Safety within whose jurisdiction the railway working such station 
    lies. At other such locations where the issue cannot be resolved then it 
    shall be finalised by the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety.  
 </section><section>

    <number>5</number> (a) If, for any reason, the concerned Commissioner of Railway Safety is 
    unable to hold an inquiry at an early date after the occurrence of such an 
    accident, he shall intimate by the fastest means of communication without 
    any delay to the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety of the reasons why the 
    inquiry cannot be held by him. The Chief Commissioner may choose to conduct 
    the inquiry himself or direct any other Commissioner to take up the inquiry 
    or decide to let the inquiry be conducted by the Railway Administration. The 
    concerned Commissioner shall thereafter notify the Railway Administration 
    and the Railway Board accordingly.  
 <subsection>

    <number>b</number> On receipt of the proceedings of the joint inquiry (inquiry made by a 
    Committee of Railway Officers) from the Head of the Railway Administration 
    in accordance with Rule 15 of Railway (Notices of and Inquiries into 
    Accidents) Rules, 1997, the Commissioner of Railway Safety shall scrutinise 
    the same, and in case he agrees with the findings of the joint inquiry, 
    shall forward a copy of the report to the Chief Commissioner of Railway 
    Safety along with his views on the findings and recommendations made. In 
    case the Commissioner feels, he may direct the Railway Administration either 
    to conduct inquiry de novo or re-examine specific issues and submit 
    revised findings. On the other hand the Commissioner of Railway Safety, 
    after examination of the joint inquiry proceedings, considers that an 
    inquiry should be held by himself, he shall, as soon as possible, notify the 
    Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety, the Railway Board, and the Head of the 
    Railway Administration concerned, of his intention to hold as inquiry and he 
    shall at the same time fix, and communicate the date, time and place for the 
    inquiry.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>6</number> (a) Where having regard to the nature of the accident, the Central 
    Government has appointed a Commission of Inquiry to inquire into the 
    accident under the Commission of Inquiry Act, 1952 (60 of 1952), or has 
    appointed any other authority to inquire into it and for that purpose has 
    made all or any of the provisions of the said Act applicable to that 
    authority, the Commissioner of Railway Safety to whom notice of the accident 
    has been given shall not hold his inquiry and where he has already commenced 
    his inquiry he shall not proceed further with it and shall hand over the 
    evidence, records or other documents in his possession, relating to the 
    inquiry, to such authority as may be specified by the Central Government in 
    this behalf.  
 <subsection>

    <number>b</number> If, as a result of the Police Investigation a regular case is lodged in 
    a Criminal Court by the Police or arising out of the accident, a case is 
    lodged in a Civil Court by interested person(s), the Commissioner shall 
    finalise his report and circulate the same as per Rule 4, as a strictly 
    confidential document.  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>3</number> Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety to submit a brief preliminary narrative report.—Where 
    a Commissioner of Railway Safety has held an inquiry in respect of any of 
    the accidents described in sub-rule (2) of Rule 2, he shall submit a brief 
    preliminary narrative report to the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety and 
    the Railway Board simultaneously. In case Chief Commissioner of Railway 
    Safety has held an inquiry in terms of Rule 2(3) and 2(5) he shall submit 
    the brief preliminary narrative report to the Railway Board. The report 
    shall be factual and shall not contain any reference to persons implicated.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>4</number> Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety to submit a report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever the Commissioner of Railway Safety has made an inquiry under Rule 
    2, he shall submit a confidential report in writing to the Chief 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety and shall forward copies of the report to—
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>    the Railway Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>    the Railway Administration of all the Zonal Railways;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iii</number>    in the case of a Railway under the control of a State Government or 
    Local Administration to such Government or administration if the accident 
    has occurred in that Railway;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iv</number>    other Commissioner of Railway Safety;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>v</number>    the Director, Intelligence Bureau, Ministry of Home Affairs, 
    Government of India, if the Commissioner of Railway find that the accident 
    was caused by sabotage or train wrecking.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> In case the inquiry has been held by the Chief Commissioner of Railway 
    Safety he shall forward his report to the authorities mentioned in (i) to 
    (vi) of sub-rule (1) of this Rule.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>5</number> Publication of 
    reports.—Recommendations 
    in regard to the publication of reports shall be made by the Chief 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety and Railway Board (Ministry of Railways) 
    informed accordingly. In case the Railway Board has reservations on the 
    recommendations of the Chief Commissioner, the matter shall be finally 
    decided by the Central Government (Ministry of Civil Aviation).
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>6</number> District 
    Magistrate or his representative to attend the inquiry conducted by 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety.—Where 
    no Magisterial inquiry is being made under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or (b) of Rule 17 of 
    the Railway (Notices of and Inquiries into Accidents) Rules, 1997, the 
    District Magistrate shall, as far as possible, attend the inquiry conducted 
    by the Commissioner of Railway Safety personally or depute some other 
    officer to represent him at the inquiry. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>7</number> District 
    Superintendent of Police or his representative.—The 
    District Superintendent of Police shall, as far as possible also attend the 
    inquiry conducted by the Commissioner of Railway Safety personally or depute 
    some other officer to represent him at the inquiry.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>8</number> Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety to assist the Magistrate of the Commission of Inquiry etc. 
    in clarifying technical matters.—The 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety, as far as possible, assist any Magistrate 
    making a judicial inquiry or an inquiry under Rule 17 of Railway (Notices of 
    and Inquiries into Accidents) Rules, 1997 or a Commission of Inquiry 
    appointed under the Commission of Inquiry Act, 1952 (60 of 1952), or any 
    other authority appointed by the Central Government to which all or any of 
    the provisions of the said Act have been made applicable, whenever he may be 
    called upon to do so for the purpose of clarification of any technical 
    matters.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>9</number> Powers of the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall, except to the extent provided in sub-rule (6) of Rule 
    2, be deemed to limit or otherwise affect the exercise of any of the powers 
    conferred on Commissioner of Railway Safety by sections 7 and 8 of the Act 
    of 1989.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>

<number>10</number> Repeal and 
    Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The ‘Statutory Investigation into Railway Accident Rules, 1973’, published 
    with notification of Government of India in the Ministry of Tourism &amp; Civil 
    Aviation No. 22, dated 2-6-1973, Part II, Section 3 are hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    rules hereby repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of these rules.    
 


  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 26th December, 1998.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>