<act><title>THE REGULATION ON GUIDELINES FOR REGISTRATION OF CONSUMER ORGANIZATIONS/NON-GOVERNMENT ORGANIZATIONS (NGOS) AND THEIR INTERACTION WITH TRAI, 20011</title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> This regulation shall be called the Regulation on Guidelines for Registration of Consumer Organizations/Non-Government Organizations (NGOs) and their Interaction with TRAI, 2001. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> This regulation prescribes the guidelines for the registration of the Consumer Organizations &amp; NGOs and their interaction with TRAI. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> This regulation shall be applicable to- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> All Consumer Organizations concerned with cause of users of telecommunication services throughout the territory of India . 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> All Non Government Organizations (NGOs) concerned with telecommunication services in the territory of India . 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>iv</number> This regulation shall come into effect from the Fifteenth day of January 2001. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Criteria for Registration of consumer organisation/NGOs. </title>-The criteria for the registration for consumer organisations/NGOs with TRAI are as follows:- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> The consumer organisations and NGOs should be those registered either under Societies Act or Companies Act. The organisations registered with MRTPC and BIS shall also be eligible for registration with TRAI. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The organisations should be non-profit and non-political. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> The organisations should have a minimum <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[one year] of experience in the areas of representing views of consumers <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[and assisling them in redressal of complaints regarding shortfall in the supplies and deficienty in services.] 
</section>




</article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> </title> Where the Authority is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, for giving adequate representations to those regions/states which are either not represented or not adequately represented in the list of consumer organisations/NGOs registered with the Authority, the Authority may by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing relax the provision relating to experience as given in sub-regulation (iii) of regulations 2 and register such consumer organisation(s) and non-government organisation(s) from such regions/states.] 



</article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>3</number> Rules Governing Registration. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> All the organisations interested in getting themselves registered with TRAI, should submit their application along with Registration Form, which is enclosed at Annexure 'A'. 
 
 





</section><section><number>ii</number> TRAI will complete the registration process within 45 days of receipt of a complete Registration Form along with all the enclosures indicated in the Registration Form. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> The organisations, which are found suitable for registration with TRAI, will be sent a written communication bearing Registration Number allocated uniquely to them. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> The Registration Number will have to be quoted by the registered organisation in every correspondence with TRAI. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum></title>[<number>v</number> The organisations, which have been allocated Registration Number under sub-regulation (iii) and same remains valid, shall submit a copy of the annual report of the organisation to TRAI by the 30th September of every year;] 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> The registration will be valid initially for a period of <title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum></title>[three years]. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum></title>[<number>vii</number> The TRAI, after taking into account- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the usefulness of the organization to protect the interest of consumers in telecom sector; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the capacity of the organization to advocate the cause of the consumers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the performance of the organization; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> and fulfilment of other conditions specified in these regulations, may consider the renewal of the registration of the organizations referred to in sub-regulation (iii) after the period of three years;] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>viii</number> The organisations, which are at present registered with TRAI will have to apply afresh for registration as per the procedure stipulated above; 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> In the event of the TRAI observing any conduct on the part of consumer organisation, unbecoming of such an organisation, the TRAI will have the right to cancel the registration after advising the reason, and that the TRAI's decision in this regard will be final. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>4</number> Interaction with TRAI. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> All consumer organisations/NGOs may interact with TRAI. Specific facilities mentioned below will, however, be available only to consumer organisation/NGOs registered with TRAI. 
 
 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The registered organisations shall be informed to attend open house discussions held by TRAI on various issues. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> An open regular two way communication channel will be maintained with the consumer organisations and NGOs registered with the Authority, with the objective of sharing additional data/information and discussions over and above what is shared through other channels. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> In addition to the open house discussions held in various parts of the country, TRAI shall hold half yearly meetings with registered consumer organisations to increase interaction for better understanding of the problems of consumers across the country. These meetings may be organised in different parts of country for better participation. 
</section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>v</number> The organizations referred to in sub-regulation (iii) of regulations 3 may be invited to assist TRAI in organising seminars, symposia and workshop on  
the subject of consumer welfare and consumer education in the field of telecommunication;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>vi</number> All the organization referred to in sub-regulation (iii) of regulation 3 shall, for the purpose of registration of consumer organisations and other consumer related issues, interact with the Nodal Officer in TRAI, being the Deputy Advisor (Consumer Affairs) in the Quality of Service Division or such other officer as the Authority may specify to be the Nodal Officer in TRAI.] 




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>5</number> Mode of Data sharing. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> TRAI shall continue to share information through various consultation papers, through website, e-mail and letters. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> The consumer organizations/NGOs shall also submit the data available with them regarding the customer perception about the telecom services being provided by various service providers and information on other issues, which may be used for the benefit of the consumers. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> The information about any survey, opinion poll conducted by any consumer organizations/NGOs shall be shared with TRAI either free of cost or through a reasonably priced document. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>6</number> </title><title>Review. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> The Authority may, from time to time, review and modify guidelines for Registration of Consumer Organizations/NGOs and their Interaction with TRAI, 2001. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> The Authority, on reference from any affected party, and for good and sufficient reasons, may review and modify this regulation. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>7</number> Explanatory Memorandum. </title>-This regulation contains at Annexure 'B', an Explanatory Memorandum detailing the need for this regulation and the process adopted by the Authority. (Annexure 'B' not published). 


</article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>8</number> Interpretation. </title>-In case of disputes regarding interpretation of any of the provisions of this Regulation, the decision of the Authority shall be final and binding. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007, for "three years".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Notification No. 330-2/2007–CA, dated 21st August, 2007.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007, for sub-regulation (v).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007, for "two years"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007, for sub- 
  regulation (vii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2009, for sub- 
  regulation (v).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Notification No. 330-2/2007-CA, dated 21st August, 2007, for sub- 
  regulations (vi).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>