<act><tid>1320297</tid>
<title>THE TEA COMPANIES (ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF SICK TEA UNITS) 
ACT, <year>1985</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1985</year>
[ 28th May, <year>1985</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the sick tea 
units specified in the First Schedule and the right, title and 
interest of the tea companies in respect of the said tea units with a 
view to securing proper reorganisation and management of such tea 
units so as to subserve the interests of the general public by 
augmenting the production and manufacture of different varieties of 
tea which are essential to the needs of the economy of the country and 
for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS the sick tea units specified in the First Schedule had 
been engaged in the production and manufacture of different varieties 
of tea;

AND WHEREAS the management of the said tea units was taken over by 
the Central Government under the Tea Act, <year>1953</year> (29 of <year>1953</year>);

AND WHEREAS the Central Government had invested large sums of 
money with a view to making the said tea units viable;

AND WHEREAS further investment of large sums of money is 
necessary for reorganising and rehabilitating the said tea units;

AND WHEREAS the acquisition by the Central Government of the said 
tea units is necessary to enable it to invest such large sums of money 
and to protect the large investments already made and also the 
interests of the workmen employed therein by proper reorganisation and 
management of the said tea units and thereby to augment the production 
and manufacture of different varieties of tea which area essential to 
the needs of the economy of the country;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>751101</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1082854</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Tea Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Sick Tea Units) Act, <year>1985</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>224746</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 8th day of 
April, <year>1985</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>192</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>399326</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>860743</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1771150</tid>
<number>b</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments 
appointed under section 13;

</section>

<section><tid>1412273</tid>
<number>c</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>476395</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>797523</tid>
<number>e</number>" sick tea unit" means a tea unit, specified in column 
 (2) of the First Schedule, the management of which had, before 
the appointed day, been taken over by the Central Government 
under the Tea Act, <year>1953</year> (29 of <year>1953</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1144929</tid>
<number>f</number>" specified date", in relation to any provision of this 
Act, means such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification, specify for the purposes of that provision and 
different dates may be specified for different provisions of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1106682</tid>
<number>g</number>" tea companies" means the companies being companies as 
defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>). specified in 
column (3) of the First Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1166176</tid>
<number>h</number>" Tea Trading Corporation" means the Tea Trading 
Corporation of India Limited, a company incorporated and 
registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>; (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1529820</tid>
<number>i</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Tea Act, <year>1953</year> (29 of <year>1953</year>), shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>38145</tid>
<number>j</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined either 
in this Act or in the Tea Act, <year>1953</year> (29 of <year>1953</year>), but defined in 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.
CHAP

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>415599</tid>
<number> 3</number> Acquisition of rights of tea companies in respect of sick tea 
units.
<section><tid>1868593</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, every sick tea unit and the right,  
title and interest of every tea company in relation to its sick tea 
units or, as the case may be, sick tea unit shall, by virtue of this 
Act, stand transferred to, and vest in, the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1814210</tid>
<number>2</number>Every sick tea unit which stands vested in the Central 
Government by virtue of sub- section (1) shall, immediately after it 
has so vested, stand transferred to, and vested in, the Tea Trading 
Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>193</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>460217</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting.
<section><tid>226375</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sick tea unit shall be  
deemed to include all assets, rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities 
and privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including 
lands, buildings, workshops, stores, instruments, machinery and 
equipment, cash balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments, 
book debts and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of, 
such property as were, immediately before the appointed day, in the 
ownership, possession, power or control of the tea company concerned, 
whether within or outside India, and all books of account, registers 
and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall 
also be deemed to include the liabilities specified in sub- section (1) 
of section 24.

</section>

<section><tid>171936</tid>
<number>2</number>All properties as aforesaid which have vested in the Tea 
Trading Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3 shall, by force 
of such vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation, 
mortgage, charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting them and 
any attachment, injunction, decree or order of any court, tribunal or 
other authority restricting the use of such properties in any manner 
or appointing any receiver in respect of the whole or any part of such 
properties shall be deemed to have been withdrawn.

</section>

<section><tid>294400</tid>
<number>3</number>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this 
Act in the Tea Trading Corporation and every person holding any 
charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation to, any such 
property shall give, within such time and in such manner as may be 
prescribed, an intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, 
charge, lien or other interest.

</section>

<section><tid>338853</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (3) or any other 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation 
to, any such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with 
his rights and interests, payment of the mortgage money or other dues, 
in whole or in part, out of the amounts directed to be given under 
sections 6 and 7 to the tea company concerned but no such mortgage, 
charge, lien or other interest shall be enforceable against any 
property which has vested in the Tea Trading Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>824939</tid>
<number>5</number>Any licence or other instrument granted to a tea company in 
relation to its sick tea unit which has vested in the Tea Trading 
Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3 at any time before the 
appointed day and in force immediately before that day shall continue 
to be in force on and after such day in accordance with its tenor in 
relation to and for the purposes of such sick tea unit, and that 
Corporation shall be deemed to be substituted in such licence or other 
instrument as if such licence or other instrument had been granted to 
such Corporation and such Corporation shall hold it for the remainder 
of the period for which the tea company would have held it under the 
terms thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1979493</tid>
<number>6</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other 
proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to any matter specified in 
sub- section (1) of section 24, in respect of the sick tea unit of any 
tea company which has vested in the Tea Trading Corporation under sub- 
section (2) of section 3, instituted or preferred by or against that 
company, is pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be, 
in any way, prejudicially

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

affected by reason of the transfer of the sick tea unit of such tea 
company or of anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or 
other proceeding may be continued, prosecuted or enforced by or 
against the Tea Trading Corporation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1064095</tid>
<number> 5</number> Tea companies to be liable for certain prior liabilities. 
Subject to the other provisions of this Act, every liability, other 
than the liability specified in sub- section
<section><tid>1344551</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 24, of a  
tea company in respect of any period prior to the appointed day, shall 
be the liability of that company and shall be enforceable against it 
and not against the Tea Trading Corporation.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1470542</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment of amount. Every tea company shall be given, by the 
Central Government, for the transfer to and vesting in that Government 
under sub- section
<section><tid>910374</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 of the sick tea unit or, as the  
case may be, each sick tea unit of that company and the right, title 
and interest of that company in relation to such sick tea unit, in 
cash and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, such amount as is 
specified against the name of that sick tea unit in column (4) of the 
First Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>187040</tid>
<number> 7</number> Payment of further amount.
<section><tid>687665</tid>
<number>1</number>Every tea company shall be  
given, by the Central Government, per annum, for the deprivation of 
the management of its sick tea unit, an amount as is specified against 
the name of that sick tea unit in column (5) of the First Schedule, 
for the period commencing on the date on which the management of such 
sick tea unit was taken over in pursuance of the order made by the 
Central Government under the provisions of the Tea Act, <year>1953</year> (29 of  
  <year>1953</year>) and ending on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>159542</tid>
<number>2</number>Every amount specified in columns (4) and (5) of the First 
Schedule shall carry simple interest at the rate of four per cent. per 
annum for the period commencing on the appointed day and ending on the 
date on which the payment of such amount is made by the Central 
Government to the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1322223</tid>
<number>3</number>The amounts determined in relation to any tea company in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (2) shall be given by 
the Central Government to the tea company in addition to the amounts 
specified in columns (4) and (5) of the First Schedule against that 
company.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>848029</tid>
<number>8</number>Management, etc., of the sick tea units of the tea companies. 
The Tea Trading Corporation or any person which that Corporation may, 
by order in writing, specify, shall be entitled to exercise the powers 
of general superintendence, direction, control and management of the 
affairs and business of a sick tea unit, the right, title and interest 
of the tea company in relation to which have vested in the Corporation 
under sub- section (2) of section 3, and do all such things as the tea 
company of the sick tea unit is authorised to exercise and do.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>842742</tid>
<number> 9</number> Duty of persons in charge of management of the sick tea units 
to deliver all assets, etc.
<section><tid>1699255</tid>
<number>1</number>On the vesting of the management of  
the sick tea units of the tea companies in the Tea Trading 
Corporation, the persons in charge of the management of such sick tea 
units immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to the 
Tea Trading Corporation all assets, books of account, registers and 
all other documents in their custody relating to such sick tea units.

</section>

<section><tid>222134</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may 
deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the Tea Trading 
Corporation and the said Corporation may also, if it is considered 
necessary so to do, apply to the Central Government at any time for 
instructions as to the manner in which the management of the sick tea 
units of the tea companies shall be conducted or in relation to any 
other matter arising in the course of such management.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1664400</tid>
<number> 10</number> Duty of persons to account for assets, etc., in their 
possession.
<section><tid>233608</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who has, on the appointed day, in his  
possession or under his control any assets, books, documents or other 
papers relating to any sick tea unit owned by a tea company which has 
vested in the Tea Trading Corporation under this Act shall be liable 
to account for the said assets, books, documents and other papers to 
the Tea Trading Corporation and shall deliver them up to that 
Corporation or to such person or persons as that Corporation may 
specify in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1811024</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tea Trading Corporation may take or cause to be taken all 
necessary steps for securing possession of the sick tea units of the 
tea companies which have vested in that Corporation under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1503861</tid>
<number>3</number>Every tea company shall, within such period as the Tea 
Trading Corporation may allow in this behalf, furnish to that 
Corporation a complete inventory of all property and assets, as on the 
appointed day pertaining to its sick tea unit, which have vested in 
that Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and for this 
purpose, the Corporation shall afford to such company all reasonable 
facilities.
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TEA COMPANIES

CHAPTER V

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TEA COMPANIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1969265</tid>
<number> 11</number> Continuance of employees.
<section><tid>787746</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who has been,  
immediately before the appointed day, employed in any sick tea unit of 
any of the tea companies shall become, on and from the appointed day, 
an employee of the Tea Trading Corporation and shall hold office or 
service under that Corporation, with the same rights and privileges as 
to pension, gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible 
to him if there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so 
unless and until his employment under that Corporation is duly 
terminated or until his remuneration and other conditions of service 
are duly altered by that Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1092582</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>). or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person 
employed in any sick tea unit of any tea company, to the Tea Trading 
Corporation, shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any 
compensation under this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or 
other authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1855767</tid>
<number> 12</number> Provident fund and other funds.
<section><tid>1343409</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a tea company has  
established a provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or 
other funds for the benefit of persons employed in a sick tea unit 
owned by it, the monies relatable to its employees whose services have 
become transferred by or under this Act to the Tea Trading Corporation 
shall, out of the monies standing, on the appointed day, to the credit 
of such provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or other 
funds, stand transferred to, and vest in, the Tea Trading Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>620440</tid>
<number>2</number>The monies which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to 
the Tea Trading Corporation, shall be dealt with by that Corporation 
in such manner as may be prescribed.
CHAP

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS

CHAPTER VI

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1822921</tid>
<number> 13</number> Appointment of Commissioner of Payments.
<section><tid>1408187</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable 
under sections 6 and 7 to the tea companies, by notification, appoint 
a Commissioner of Payments.

</section>

<section><tid>1617056</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it 
may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act 
and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>924055</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of 
the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers 
in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have been 
conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of 
authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>57732</tid>
<number>4</number>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>340277</tid>
<number> 14</number> Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>263083</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified 
date, pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to every tea 
company,--

<subsection><tid>286570</tid>
<number>a</number>an amount equal to the amounts or amount specified 
against the name of that company in column (4) of the First 
Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507084</tid>
<number>b</number>a further amount equal to the amounts or amount 
specified against the name of that company in column (5) of the 
First Schedule.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1751899</tid>
<number>2</number>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government 
in favour of the Commissioner in the Public Account of India, and 
every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be 
deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account and the 
said deposit account shall be operated by the Commissioner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>197</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1830023</tid>
<number>3</number>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in 
respect of each of the tea companies in relation to which payment has 
been made to him under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>287779</tid>
<number>4</number>Interest accruing on the amount in relation to a tea company 
standing to the credit of the deposit account referred to in sub- 
section (2) shall enure to the benefit of such tea company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>175605</tid>
<number> 15</number> Certain powers of the Tea Trading Corporation.
<section><tid>519430</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tea  
Trading Corporation shall be entitled to receive, up to the specified 
date, to the exclusion of all other persons, any money due to any tea 
company in relation to its sick tea unit which has vested in the 
Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and realised after the 
appointed day, notwithstanding that the realisation pertains to a 
period prior to the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1309079</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tea Trading Corporation may make a claim to the 
Commissioner with regard to every payment made by that Corporation, 
after the appointed day, for discharging any liability of a tea 
company, not being any liability specified in sub- section (1) of 
section 24, in relation to any sick tea unit owned by it in respect of 
any period prior to the appointed day; and every such claim shall have 
priority, in accordance with the priorities attaching under this Act 
to the matter in relation to which such liability has been discharged 
by the Tea Trading Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1651643</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities of a 
tea company in relation to any sick tea unit owned by it in respect of 
any transaction prior to the appointed day, which have not been 
discharged on or before the specified date, shall be the liabilities 
of that company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1990996</tid>
<number> 16</number> Claims to be made to the Commissioner.[
<section><tid>6246</tid>
<number>1</number>] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every person  
having a claim against a tea company with regard to any of the matters 
specified in the Second Schedule, pertaining to any sick tea unit 
owned by it, shall prefer such claim before the Commissioner within 
thirty days from the specified date:
Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant 
was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the 
said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a 
further period of thirty days, but not thereafter.


</section>

<section><tid>1298304</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
all the claims preferred before the Commissioner after the period or 
the further period specified in that sub- section but on or before the 
 27th day of July, <year>1989</year>, shall be deemed to have been validly 
preferred.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>645832</tid>
<number> 17</number> Priority of claims. The claims made under section 16 shall 
have priorities in accordance with the following principles, namely:--
<section><tid>802855</tid>
<number>a</number>Category I shall have precedence over all other 
categories and Category II shall have precedence over Category 
III, and so on;

</section>

<section><tid>512165</tid>
<number>b</number>the claims specified in each of the categories shall 
rank equally and be paid in full, but if the amount paid to the 
Commissioner under this Act is insufficient to meet such claims 
in full, they shall abate in equal proportions and be paid 
accordingly; and

</section>

<section><tid>1450247</tid>
<number>c</number>the question of discharging any liability with regard to 
a matter specified in a lower category shall arise only if a 
surplus is left after meeting all the liabilities specified in 
the immediately higher category.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>198</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Re- numbered by Act 56 of <year>1991</year>, S. 2 
2. Ins. by s. 2 ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1977644</tid>
<number> 18</number> Examination of claims.
<section><tid>1158945</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of the claims made  
under section 16, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the 
order of priorities specified in the Second Schedule and examine the 
same in accordance with such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1345640</tid>
<number>2</number>If on an examination of the claims against a tea company, the 
Commissioner is of the opinion that the amount paid to him under this 
Act for payment to such company is not sufficient to meet the 
liabilities specified in any lower category, he shall not be required 
to examine any claim in respect of such lower category.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>594480</tid>
<number> 19</number> Admission or rejection of claims.
<section><tid>1216516</tid>
<number>1</number>After examining the  
claims against a tea company, with reference to the priorities set out 
in the Second Schedule, the Commissioner shall fix a date on or before 
which every claimant against the tea company shall file the proof of 
his claim.

</section>

<section><tid>1410466</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of any daily newspaper in 
the English language having circulation in the major parts of the 
country and one issue of any daily newspaper in such regional language 
as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every such notice shall 
call upon the claimant to file the proof of his claim with the 
Commissioner within the period specified in the advertisement.

</section>

<section><tid>1590648</tid>
<number>3</number>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the period specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from 
the disbursements made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>944977</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary and after giving the tea company concerned 
an opportunity of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, by order in writing, admit or 
reject the claim in whole or in part.

</section>

<section><tid>1001244</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his 
functions, including the place or places at which he may hold his 
sittings and shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under 
this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit in 
respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1697617</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1261937</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other 
material object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>185866</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>429866</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witnesses.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>354167</tid>
<number>6</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a Civil Court for the purposes of section 195 and 
Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>199</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1945340</tid>
<number>7</number>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the 
Commissioner may prefer an appeal against such decision to the High 
Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the registered 
office of the tea company concerned is situated and every such appeal 
shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that 
High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>717689</tid>
<number>20</number>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner. After admitting a 
claim against a tea company under this Act, the amount due in respect 
of such claim shall be paid by the Commissioner to the person or 
persons to whom such amount is due and on such payment, the liability 
of such tea company in respect of such claim shall stand discharged.


</article>



<article><tid>1806025</tid>
<number> 21</number> Disbursement of amounts to the tea companies.
<section><tid>529879</tid>
<number>1</number>If out of  
the monies paid to him in relation to a tea company, there is a 
balance left after meeting the liabilities as specified in the Second 
Schedule, the Commissioner shall disburse such balance to such tea 
company.

</section>

<section><tid>377100</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the possession of any machinery, equipment or other 
property possessed by a tea company has vested in the Tea Trading 
Corporation under this Act but such machinery, equipment or other 
property does not belong to such tea company, it shall be lawful for 
that Corporation to continue to possess such machinery or equipment or 
other property on the same terms and conditions under which they were 
possessed by such tea company immediately before the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>716500</tid>
<number>22</number>Undisbursed or unclaimed amounts to be deposited with the 
general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which 
remains undisbursed or unclaimed on the date immediately preceding the 
date on which the office of the Commissioner is finally wound up, 
shall be transferred by the Commissioner, before his office is finally 
wound up, to the general revenue account of the Central Government, 
but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to the 
Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and shall be 
dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, and the order, if 
any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the refund 
of revenue.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>169551</tid>
<number>23</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or 
in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>456852</tid>
<number> 24</number> Assumption of liability.
<section><tid>1316992</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any liability of a tea  
company arising out of any item specified in Category I of the Second 
Schedule is not discharged fully by the Commissioner out of the 
amounts paid to him under this Act, the Commissioner shall intimate in 
writing to the Central Government the extent of the liability which 
remains undischarged and that liability shall be assumed by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>614798</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by order, direct the Tea Trading 
Corporation to take over the liability assumed by the Central 
Government under sub- section (1), and on receipt of such direction, it 
shall be the duty of that Corporation to discharge such liability.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>200</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>971643</tid>
<number> 25</number> Management to continue to vest in certain persons until 
alternative arrangements have been made. Notwithstanding the vesting 
under this Act of a sick tea unit of any tea company in the Tea 
Trading Corporation--
<section><tid>1092740</tid>
<number>a</number>any person who has been managing the affairs of such 
sick tea unit before the date on which that unit had so vested 
shall, until alternative arrangements have been made by the Tea 
Trading Corporation for the management of such unit, continue to 
manage the affairs of the unit, as if such person had been 
authorised by the Tea Trading Corporation, to manage such unit;

</section>

<section><tid>1888767</tid>
<number>b</number>such person shall, until alternative arrangements have 
been made by the Tea Trading Corporation, continue to be 
authorised to operate, in relation to the sick tea unit of such 
tea company, any account of such unit in any bank as if he had 
been authorised by the Tea Trading Corporation to operate such 
account.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904552</tid>
<number> 26</number> contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the Tea 
Trading Corporation. Every contract entered into by any tea company in 
relation to any sick tea unit owned by it which has vested in the Tea 
Trading Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, for any 
service, sale or supply and in force immediately before the appointed 
day, shall, on and from the expiry of a period of one hundred and 
eighty days from the appointed day, cease to have effect unless such 
contract is, before the expiry of that period, ratified in writing by 
the Tea Trading Corporation, and in ratifying such contract, the Tea 
Trading Corporation may make such alterations or modifications therein 
as it may think fit:
Provided that the Tea Trading Corporation shall not omit to 
ratify a contract and shall not make any alteration or modification in 
a contract--

<section><tid>239833</tid>
<number>a</number>unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly 
onerous or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental 
to the interests of the Tea Trading Corporation; and

</section>

<section><tid>147227</tid>
<number>b</number>except after giving the parties to the contract a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard and except after recording 
in writing its reasons for refusal to ratify the contract or for 
making any alteration or modification therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>572479</tid>
<number> 27</number> Penalties. Any person who,--
<section><tid>1219559</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of a sick tea unit owned by any tea company 
wrongfully withholds such property from the Tea Trading 
Corporation; or

</section>

<section><tid>792425</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains any 
property forming part of, a sick tea unit owned by any tea 
company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1430056</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Tea 
Trading Corporation or any person or body of persons specified by 
that Corporation, any document or inventory relating to a sick 
tea unit owned by any tea company, which may be in his 
possession, custody or control; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>201</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1676150</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to deliver to the Tea Trading Corporation or any 
person or body of persons specified by that Corporation, any 
assets, books of account, registers or other documents in his 
possession, custody or control relating to a sick tea unit owned 
by any tea company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1962335</tid>
<number>e</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming part 
of a sick tea unit owned by any tea company or prefers any claim 
under this Act which he knows or has reason to believe to be 
false or grossly inaccurate, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and also 
with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>793335</tid>
<number> 28</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>984893</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence punishable under  
this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the 
time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>716312</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


<subsection><tid>1913319</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>258206</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1244366</tid>
<number> 29</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>953121</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer of that Government or the Tea Trading 
Corporation or other person authorised by that Government or 
Corporation for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>405430</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any of its officers or other employees or the 
Tea Trading Corporation or any officer or other person authorised by 
that Corporation for any damage caused or likely to be caused for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>202</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1009087</tid>
<number>30</number>Tea companies not to be wound up by the court. No proceeding 
for the winding up of a tea company, the right, title and interest in 
relation to a sick tea unit owned by which have vested in the Tea 
Trading Corporation under this Act or for the appointment of a 
receiver in respect of the business of the sick tea unit shall lie or 
be proceeded with in any court except with the consent of the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1038840</tid>
<number> 31</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>872720</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act, other than the powers conferred by this section and 
section 32 and 33, may also be exercised by such person or persons as 
may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1806265</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1762721</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1458418</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>219315</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1671260</tid>
<number>a</number>the time within which, and the manner in which, an 
intimation referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 shall be 
given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1308109</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which the monies in any provident fund or 
other fund, referred to in sub- section (2) of section 12, shall 
be dealt with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443380</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>300803</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>850266</tid>
<number>33</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>1290440</tid>
<number> 34</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>145054</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tea Companies (Acquisition and   
  Transfer of Sick Tea Units) Ordinance, <year>1985</year> (3 of <year>1985</year>), is hereby 
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1555277</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>203</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>