<act><tid>1702370</tid>
<title>THE WILD BIRDS AND ANIMALS PROTECTION ACT, <year>1912</year></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1912</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 18th September, <year>1912</year>.]

An Act to make better provision for the protection and preserva- 
tion of certain wild birds and animals.

WHEREAS it is expedient to make better provision for the protec- 
tion and preservation of certain wild birds and animals; It is hereby 
enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>484345</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>540420</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Wild  
Birds and Animals Protection Act, <year>1912</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>77890</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804023</tid>
<number> 2</number> Application of Act.
<section><tid>1541227</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act applies, in the first  
instance, to the birds and animals specified in the Schedule, when in 
their wild state.

</section>

<section><tid>1809264</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, apply the provisions of this Act to any kind of wild bird or 
animal, other than those specified in the Schedule, which, in its 
opinion, it is desirable to protect or preserve.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1690700</tid>
<number> 3</number> Close time. The State Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, declare the whole year or any part thereof to be 
a close time throughout the whole or any part of its territories for

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been amended in its application to West Bengal by 
the Bengal Rhinoceros Preservation Act, <year>1932</year> (Ben. 8 of <year>1932</year>); the U. P. 
by the Wild Birds and Animals Protection (U. P. Amendment) Act, <year>1934</year> 
 (U. P. 13 of <year>1934</year>), and in its application to the C. P. by the Wild 
Birds and Animals Protection (C. P. Amendment) Act, <year>1935</year> (C. P. 27 of  
  <year>1935</year>); Ajmer by the Wild Birds and Animals Protection (Ajmer  
  Amendment) Act, <year>1954</year> (Ajmer 4 of <year>1954</year>).

The Act has been extended to-

the whole of Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 23 of <year>1958</year>; and

the whole of the Union Territory of Lakshadweep by Reg. 8 of 
<year>1965</year>, S. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).

The Act has been extended to and brought into force in-

Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>); and

Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

The Act has been repealed in its application to-

the Bellary District by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>; and

the State of West Bengal by W. B. Act 25 of <year>1959</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" Part B 
States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

any kind of wild bird or animal to which this Act applies, or for 
female or immature wild birds or animals of such kind; and, subject to 
the provisions hereinafter contained, during such close time, and 
within the areas specified in such notification, it shall be unlawful-

<section><tid>179868</tid>
<number>a</number>to capture any such bird or animal, or to kill any such 
bird or animal which has not been captured before the com- 
mencement of such close time;

</section>

<section><tid>768534</tid>
<number>b</number>to sell or buy, or offer to sell or buy, or to possess, 
any such bird or animal which has not been captured or 
killed before the commencement of such close time, or the 
flesh thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>592050</tid>
<number>c</number>if any plumage has been taken from any such bird 
captured or killed during such close time, to sell or buy, or 
to offer to sell or buy, or to possess, such plumage.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1898362</tid>
<number> 4</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>245637</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever does, or attempts to do, any act in  
contravention of section 3, shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>357569</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever, having already been convicted of an offence under 
this section, is again convicted thereunder shall, on every subsequent 
conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to one hundred 
rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>719307</tid>
<number> 5</number> Confiscation.
<section><tid>1349997</tid>
<number>1</number>When any person is convicted of an offence  
punishable under this Act, the convicting Magistrate may direct that 
any bird or animal in respect of which such offence has been 
committed, or the flesh or any other part of such bird or animal, 
shall be confiscated.

</section>

<section><tid>461867</tid>
<number>2</number>Such confiscation may be in addition to the other Punishment 
provided by section 4 for such offence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030292</tid>
<number>6</number>Cognizance of offences. No Court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the second class shall try 
any offence against this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>783003</tid>
<number>7</number>Power to grant exemption. Where the State Government is of 
opinion that, in the interests of scientific research, such a course 
is desirable, it may grant to any person a license, subject to such 
restrictions and conditions as it may impose, entitling the holder 
thereof to do any act which is by section 3 declared to be unlawful.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1837095</tid>
<number>8</number>Savings. Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to apply to 
the capture or killing of a wild animal by any person in 
defence of himself or any other person, or to the capture or killing 
of any wild bird or animal in bona fide defence of property.


</article>



<article><tid>1034526</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Repeal.] Rep. by the Second Repealing and Amending Act, 
 <year>1914</year> (17 of <year>1914</year>), s. 3 and Sch. II.

</article>



 </act>