<act><title>

THE SPECIAL PROTECTION GROUP ACT, 1988</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Special Protection Group Act, 1988. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1
    as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “active duty” in relation to a 
    member of the Group means any duty as such member during the period when he 
    is posted to physically protect the Prime Minister of India and the members 
    of 1[his 
    immediate family or a former Prime Minister and the members of his immediate 
    family], wherever he or they may be; 
3[his 
    immediate family or a former Prime Minister and the members of his immediate 
    family], wherever he or they may be;" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Director” means the Director of 
    the Group appointed under sub-section (1) of section 5;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Group” means the Special 
    Protection Group constituted under section 4;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “member of the Group” means a 
    person who has been appointed to the Group by the prescribed authority 
    whether before or after the commencement of this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “members of immediate family” 
    means wife, husband, children and parents;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “proximate security” means 
    protection provided from close quarters, during journey by road, rail, 
    aircraft, watercraft or on foot or any other means of transport and shall 
    include the places of functions, engagements, residence or halt and shall 
    comprise ring round teams, isolation cordons, the sterile zone around, and 
    the rostrum and access control to the person or members of his immediate 
    family;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    all words and expressions used 
    and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Penal Code shall have 
    the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Code.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Members subject to this Act.—Every member of the Group shall be 
      subject to this Act, whenever he may be.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Constitution of the Group.—1[2[
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be an armed force of the Union called the Special Protection 
    Group for providing proximate security to—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the Prime Minister and members of 
    his immediate family; and  
 

3[(ii)    
    any former Prime Minister or to the members of his immediate family—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    for a period of one year from the 
    date on which the former Prime Minister ceased to hold office and beyond one 
    year based on the level of threat as decided by the Central Government, so 
    however that not more than twelve months shall elapse between two 
    consecutive assessments made in regard to the need for proximate security:  
 
Provided that while deciding the level 
    of threat, the Central Government shall take into account, among other 
    things, the following factors, namely:—  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>A</number>    that the threat emanates from any 
    militant or terrorist organisation or any other source; and  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>B</number>    that the threat is of a grave and 
    continuing nature;  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    on their visits abroad, based on 
    entitlement to proximate security and the level of threat as assessed by the 
    Central Government.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>1A</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1),—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any former Prime Minister or any 
    member of the immediate family of the Prime Minister or of a former Prime 
    Minister may decline proximate security;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the proximate security is 
    withdrawn from a former Prime Minister, whether before or after the 
    commencement of the Special Protection Group (Amendment) Act, 1999, such 
    proximate security shall also stand withdrawn from the immediate family 
    members of such former Prime Minister:  
 
Provided 
    that where the level of threat faced by any member of the immediate family 
    of a former Prime Minister warrants proximate security or any other 
    security, such security shall be provided to that member.]]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to that provisions of this Act, the Group shall be constituted in 
    such manner as may be prescribed and the terms and conditions of service of 
    the members of the Group shall be such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, any person or any member 
    of any other armed force of the Union may be appointed to the Group by the 
    Central Government by a general or special order and for such period as may 
    be specified in such order, and the person so appointed shall, during the 
    period of his appointment, be deemed to be a member of the Group, and the 
    provisions of this Act shall, so far as may be, apply to such person or 
    member.  
 













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Control, direction, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The general superintendence, direction and control of the Group shall vest 
    in, and be exercised by, the Central Government and subject thereto and to 
    the provisions of this Act and the rules, the command and supervision of the 
    Group shall vest in an officer to be appointed by the Central Government as 
    the Director of the Group. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director shall, in the discharge of his duties under this Act, be assisted 
    by such number of 

    1[Inspectors General, 
    Deputy Inspectors General, Assistant Inspectors General] and other officers 
    as may be appointed by the Central Government. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Liability for service in and outside India.—Every 
    member of the Group shall be liable to serve in any part of India as well as 
    outside India.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Members of the Group always in active 
      duty.—Every 
      member of the Group, not on leave or under suspension, shall for all 
      purposes of this Act, be always on active duty and may at any time be 
      employed or deployed in any manner which is consistent with the duties and 
      responsibilities of the Group under this Act.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Resignation and withdrawal from the post.—No 
    member of the Group shall be at liberty—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    to resign his appointment during 
    the term of his engagement; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    to withdraw himself from all or 
    any of the duties of his appointment, 
 
 
except with the previous permission in 
    writing of the prescribed authority.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Tenure of service.—Every 
    member of the Group shall hold office during the pleasure of the President.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Restrictions respecting right to form associations, freedom of speech, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No member of the Group shall, without the previous sanction in writing of 
    the Central Government or of the prescribed authority,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    be a member of, or be associated 
    in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association or 
    with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    be a member of, or be associated 
    in any way with, any society, institution, association or organisation that 
    is not of a purely social, recreational or religious nature; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    communicate with the press or 
    publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other document except 
    where such communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge 
    of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific character 
    or is of a prescribed nature.  
 

    Explanation.—If 
    any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or 
    organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under 
    clause (b) or whether any book, letter or document is a communication or 
    publication in the bona fide discharge of his duties or is of a 
    purely literary, artistic or scientific character or is of a prescribed 
    nature under clause (c), the decision of the Central Government thereon 
    shall be final.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    member of the Group shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take 
    part in any demonstration organised by any body of persons for any political 
    or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Termination of service.—The 
    prescribed authority may, by order in writing, terminate the appointment of 
    any member of the Group in the public interest and such termination shall be 
    deemed to be discharged simpliciter and shall not amount to dismissal 
    or removal.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any member of the Group aggrieved by an order under section 11 may, within 
    thirty days from the date of such order, prefer an appeal to a Board to be 
    constituted by the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall consist of such persons as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    decision of the Board shall be final and shall not be called in question in 
    any court or tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Board shall have power to regulate its own procedure.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Powers and duties conferable on members of the Group.—The 
    Central Government may, by general or special order published in the 
    Official Gazette, direct that, subject to such conditions and limitations as 
    may be specified in that order, any member of the Group may exercise or 
    discharge such powers or duties as may be specified in the said order for 
    giving effect to the provisions of this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Assistance to Group.—It 
    shall be the duty of every Ministry and Department of the Central Government 
    or the State Government or the Union territory Administration, every Indian 
    Mission, every local or other authority or every civil or military authority 
    to act in aid of the Director or any member of the Group whenever called 
    upon to do so in furtherance of the duties and responsibilities assigned to 
    such Director or member.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Protection of action taken under this 
      Act.—No 
      suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Group or 
      any member thereof on whom powers have been conferred or duties have been 
      imposed under this Act, or any order issued or any rule made thereunder 
      for anything which is in good faith done or purported to be done or 
      omitted to be done in pursuance of this Act or any order issued or any 
      rule made thereunder or any order issued under any such 
rule.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner in which the Group 
    shall be constituted and the terms and conditions of service of its members 
    under sub-section (2) of section 4;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the authorities to be prescribed 
    under section 8, sub-section (1) of section 10 and section 11;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the nature of the communication 
    or publication under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 10;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the purposes, other than 
    political purposes, for which a person subject to this Act shall not 
    participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in the demonstration 
    under sub-section (2) of section 10;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the persons who shall be members 
    of the Board under sub-section (2) of section 12; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any other matter which has to be, 
    or may be prescribed.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Laying of orders and rules.—Every 
    order issued under section 13 and every rule made under section 16 shall be 
    laid, as soon as may be after it is issued or made, before each House of 
    Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which 
    may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and, 
    if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
    the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree making any modification 
    in the order or the rule or both Houses agree that the order or rule should 
    not be made, the order or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that order or rule.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Provision as to existing Special Protection Group.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Special Protection Group in existence at the commencement of this Act 
    shall be deemed to be the Group constituted under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    members of the Special Protection Group in existence at the commencement of 
    this Act shall be deemed to have been appointed as such under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Anything done or any action taken before the commencement of this Act in 
    relation to the constitution of the Special Protection Group referred to in 
    sub-section (1) and in relation to any person appointed, shall be as valid 
    and as effective in laws as if such thing or action was done or taken under 
    this Act.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>