<act><tid>1994355</tid>
<title>THE SONTHAL PARGANAS ACT, <year>1855</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1855</year> 
[ 22nd December, <year>1855</year>.]
An Act to remove from the operation of the general Laws and 
Regulations certain districts inhabited by Sonthals and others, 
and to place the same under the superintendence of an officer to 
be specially appointed for that purpose.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS the general Regulations and Acts of Government 
now in force in the Presidency of Bengal are not adapted to the 
uncivilized race of people called Sonthals, and it is therefore 
expedient to remove from the operation of such laws the district 
called the Damin- i- Koh, and other districts which are inhabited 
principally by that tribe; it is enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1695059</tid>
<number>1</number>Districts removed from operation of general Regulations.-- 2 
Clause 1.- The districts described in the Schedule to this Act are 
hereby removed from the operation of the general Regulations of the 
Bengal Code and of the laws passed by the Governor- General of India in 
Council, except so far as is hereinafter provided; and <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> no 
Central Act passed before the commencement of Part III of the 
Government of India Act, <year>1935</year> 26 Geo 5 c- 2,] shall be deemed to 
extend to any part of the said districts, unless the same shall be 
specially named therein:
Proviso.-- Provided that nothing herein contained shall <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 
remove any part of the said districts from the operation of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 
Regulation 10 of <year>1804</year> of the Bengal Code; nor shall this Act affect 
any revenue- settlement, nor any law relating to the recovery of 
permanently- settled land- revenue due under the same, nor any law 
relating to the sale of lands for arrears of revenue, or relating to 
patni taluks or to the sale thereof for arrears of rent, nor any law 
relating to mutations or batwara or to any other matter to which the 
State Government shall at any time notify in the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Official 
Gazette] that the general Laws and Regulations shall extend.

Superintendence of districts.-- Clause 2.-- The said districts 
shall be placed under the superintendence and jurisdiction of an 
officer or officers <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> to be appointed in that behalf by the State 
Government and such officer or officers shall be subject to the 
directions <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> and control of the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>491199</tid>
<number>2</number>Administration of justice and collection of revenue.-- The 
administration of civil and criminal justice and the collection of the 
revenue, not being permanently- settled land- revenue within the said 
district, and hereby vested in the officer or officers to be so 
appointed:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Amending Act, <year>1903</year> (1 of <year>1903</year>), Sch. I.

This Act extends only to the Sonthal Parganas, as described in 
the Schedule

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl. 1 of s. 1 appears to have been superseded by the Sonthal 
Parganas Settlement Regulation, <year>1872</year> (3 of <year>1872</year>), s. 3

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" no law which shall hereafter be 
passed by the Governor- General of India in Council".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" extended to or affect any case now pending in any 
Court, nor," rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The Bengal State- offences Regualtion, <year>1804</year>, was rep. by the 
Special Laws Repeal Act, <year>1922</year> (4 fo <year>1922</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Calcutta Gazette".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>For provisions as to Courts of officers appointed under this 
section, see the Sonthal parganas Justisce Regulation, <year>1893</year> (5 of  
  <year>1893</year>), Ch. III, Part II.

Any directions issued under cl. 2 of s. 1 must be consistent with 
enactments in force in the Sonthal Paraganas, See Regulation 5 of 
<year>1893</year>, s. 27.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Suits exceeding value of one thousand rupees.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided 
that all civil suits in which the matter in dispute shall exceed the 
value of one thousand rupees shall be tried and determined according 
to the general laws and Regulations in the same manner as if this Act 
had not been passed:

Collection of permanently- settled land- revenue.-- Provided also 
that all permanently- settled land- revenue shall be collected and paid 
at the same places and in the same manner as if this Act had not been 
passed.



</article>



<article><tid>407292</tid>
<number>3</number>Administration of civil and criminal justice.-- In the 
administration of civil and criminal justice the officer or officers 
appointed under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may hold his or their Courts either 
within the said district or at any place or places that may be 
appointed for that purpose by the State Government; and any person 
liable to be imprisoned in any civil or criminal jail may be 
imprisoned in any civil or criminal jail, as the case may be, which 
the State Government may order, whether the same be in or out of the 
said district.

</article>



<article><tid>793981</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Decisions final; confirmation of death- sentence; appeal; 
procedure on references to Sadar Court.] Rep. by the Sonthal Parganas 
Justice Regulation, <year>1893</year> (5 of <year>1893</year>).

</article>



<article><tid>1763000</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Saving of laws relating to European British subjects.] Rep., 
ibid.

</article>



<article><tid>766683</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Commencement of Act.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> (14 of  
  <year>1870</year>).

</article>



 </act>