<act><title>


The Central Industrial Security 
    Force Rules, 20011</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Central Industrial Security Force Rules, 2001.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Central Industrial 
    Security Force Act, 1968 (50 of 1968);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Appendix” means an appendix to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “close arrest” means confinement of any 
    enrolled member of the Force within the Force or a detachment of the Force 
    or a post quarter guard, building or tent under charge of a guard;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Magistrate” means any Magistrate as 
    referred to in section 3 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “open arrest” means confinement of any 
    enrolled member of the Force within the precinct of any barrack, lines or 
    camp for the time being occupied by any detachment of the Force;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to 
    these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   the expressions “assault”, “criminal 
    force”, “reason to believe”, “wrongfully restrain” and “voluntarily causes 
    hurt” have the meaning assigned to them respectively in Indian Penal Code;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   words and expressions used in these 
    rules and not defined, but defined in the Act, shall have the meaning 
    respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The force shall consist of the following three branches, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Executive Branch;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Fire Service Branch; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Ministerial Branch.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    Branch shall consist of such supervisory officers (other than the Director 
    General) and enrolled members of the force as the Director General may from 
    time to time specify.  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Composition of the Force. 
</title>—The Supervisory Officers and enrolled members of the Force shall be 
classified in accordance with the ranks in the following categories, namely:— 

 
 <section><number>1</number> (a) Supervisory Officers 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Director General; 
 <subsubsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ia</number> Additional Director General]; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Inspector General; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Deputy Inspector General, Deputy Inspector General 
    (Fire), 1 [Director (Medical), Additional Deputy Inspecor General] 
    <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum><number>iiia</number> Senior Commandant, Assistant Inspector 
    General;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Commandant, Assistant Inspector General, Assistant 
    Inspector General (Fire), Commandant (Fire), Group Commandant, Principal, 
    Recruits Training Centre, Principal, Fire Service Training Institute 1 [and 
    Commandant (Medical Officer)]; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> Deputy Commandant and Deputy Commandant (Fire) 
    <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> Assistant Commandant, Vice Principal, Recruits Training 
    Centre, Assistant Commandant (Junior Administrative Officer) and Assistant 
    Commandant (Fire), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Assistant Commandant (Medical Officer)] 
    <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]. </subsection>
 <subsection><number>b</number> Enrolled Members 
 
 <subsubsection><number>vii</number> Inspector (Executive, Stenographer, Ministerial, Fire 
    and Armourer); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>viii</number> Sub-Inspector (Executive, Stenographer, Ministerial, 
    Fire and Armourer); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ix</number> Assistant Sub-Inspector (Executive, 3 [Stenographer,] 
    Ministerial, Fire and Armourer), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Pharmacist, Band and Motor 
    Mechanic]; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>x</number> Head Constable (Driver, Executive, 
    <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Ministerial,] Fire and Armourer); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xi</number> Constables (Executive, Fire, Armourer, 
    <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Driver, Driver-cum-Pump Operator, Nursing Assistant, Band and 
    Fitter]); and 
 </subsubsection>
 Each of the above categories of ranks other than the ranks 
  mentioned at item No. (xii) shall be the immediate superior in rank to the 
  rank mentioned below that category. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xii</number> Followers (Cook, Kahar, Sweeper, Mochi, Barber, 
    Carpenter, Tailor, Dhobi, Charge Mechanic, Motor Pump Attendant, Switch 
    Board Attendant, Painter and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Wardboy, Mason and Plumber]). 
  </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Unless the context otherwise requires, reference to 
  Commandant, Deputy Commandant, Assistant Commandant, Inspector, Sub-Inspector, 
  Assistant Sub-Inspector, Head Constable, Constable and Followers in these 
  rules shall be deemed respectively to include references to all or any of the 
  ranks of Supervisory Officers or enrolled members of the Force as the case may 
  be specified in items (iv) to (xii) of sub-rule (1). </section>



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Conferment of local rank.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in these rules, the Director General may, subject to 
    confirmation of the Central Government, grant to an officer of the Force a 
    higher rank than held by him, as a local rank whenever considered necessary 
    by him in the interest of better functioning of the Force—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   a local rank shall be conferred by the 
    Director General up to and including the rank of Commandant only;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   local rank to the officers of the level 
    of Deputy Inspector General and above shall be conferred after prior 
    approval of the Ministry of Home Affairs;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   the power of conferring local ranks 
    will not be further delegated by the Director General to any of the officers 
    subordinate to him;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   an officer of the Force who has been 
    granted a local rank—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   shall exercise the command and be vested 
    with the powers of an officer holding that rank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   shall cease to hold that rank, if the 
    grant of such rank is not confirmed within 21 days by the Central 
    Government, or when so ordered by the Director General or when he ceases to 
    hold the appointment for which the rank is granted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   shall not be entitled to any extra pay 
    and allowances for holding such rank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   shall not be entitled to claim any 
    seniority over other officers of the Force by virtue of having held such 
    rank.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Duties 
    of Director General.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Director General shall be the Head of the Force and shall be responsible for 
    maintaining it in a state of high efficiency, training, discipline and 
    morale and he shall for that purpose take all such steps as he may consider 
    necessary, by way of tours, inspections, examination of records, calling for 
    reports, framing regulations, issuing instructions and giving directive on 
    all matters pertaining to the administration of the Force. He shall in 
    particular guide and direct the supervisory officers and it shall be his 
    duty to ensure that each supervisory officer maintains the Force in his 
    charge at a high level of efficiency and discipline.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director General shall keep himself in touch with the Chairman, Managing 
    Directors and General Managers of the Public Sector Undertakings where the 
    Force is deputed and post himself from time to time with the problems and 
    needs of each such Undertakings in relation to the Force. He shall maintain 
    close liaison with the Police and other authorities of the State so as to 
    secure effective co-ordination between the State Police and the Force in 
    regard to matters pertaining to the protection and security of Public Sector 
    Undertakings. He shall keep the Central Government duly informed of all 
    matters of importance.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Duties 
    of Sector Inspectors General in Central Industrial Security Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    To exercise powers of Head of Department in the respective sectors for 
    inclusion which may consist one or more zones in financial and 
    administrative matters as provided under the various rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> To closely 
    monitor the crime situations in the field units and adopt proper crime 
    control measures in the respective sectors.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> To 
    exercise operational control of the Force, deployed under his charge 
    including those in various Public Sector Undertakings and to render timely 
    directions to the respective Zonal/Plant Deputy Inspectors General. This 
    also includes deployment on Internal Security duties, Election duties, etc.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> To guide 
    and direct all concerned to ensure effective security arrangements in the 
    Industrial Undertakings.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> To 
    establish and maintain liaison and coordination with the Chief Secretaries, 
    Director General of Police/Inspector General of Police of the States and 
    Heads/Chief Executives of the Public Sector Establishments.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> To carry 
    out the inspections of Units in his sector as per the Circulars from Force 
    Headquarters.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> To 
    scrutinise the inspection reports conducted by the Zonal/Plant Deputy 
    Inspectors General relating to various Units and monitoring of the 
    compliance of short-falls pointed out therein,  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> To conduct 
    special enquiries within the sector or elsewhere as and when so directed by 
    Force Headquarters.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> To 
    scrutinise and approve the tour programmes, inspection notes and monthly 
    diaries of Zonal/Plant Deputy Inspectors General.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> To 
    exercise powers for grant of leave as per the rules instructions issued by 
    Force Headquarters.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> To order 
    postings transfers of enrolled members of the Force within the sector.  
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> To ensure 
    speedy disposal of departmental enquiry cases and close monitoring of court 
    cases.  
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> To ensure 
    timely recovery of Central Industrial Security Force dues.  
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> To ensure 
    proper training of the Force personnel under his charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> To look 
    after and to take effective steps for the welfare of Force personnel under 
    his charge to keep their morale high.  
 </section><section>
<number>16</number> To ensure 
    timely action by Units on information/details asked for by Force 
    Headquarters.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Duties 
    of Deputy Inspector General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For proper supervision of the Force, the country shall be divided in zones. 
    A Deputy Inspector General shall be the incharge of each zone. He shall be 
    responsible for maintaining the Force in his charge in a state of high 
    efficiency, training, discipline and morale. For this purpose, he shall 
    inspect the Units and the Industrial Undertakings in Public Sector in his 
    Zone where the Force is deputed at least twice a year and send his 
    Inspection Reports to the Inspector General, giving details of the state of 
    the Force and its administration.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Deputy Inspector General shall be readily available to the Commandants and 
    shall aid, advice and control them. He shall keep in touch with the 
    Chairman, Managing Directors and General Managers of the Undertakings in his 
    Zone and shall also keep liaison with the State authorities with a view to 
    secure full cooperation between the State Police and the Force in ensuring 
    proper protection and security of the property of the Industrial 
    Undertakings in the public sector in his Zone. He shall keep the Inspector 
    General fully informed of all developments which need his attention 


    1[Normally] all 
    communications between the Commandant and Inspector General shall be 
    channalized through the Deputy Inspector General though in cases of great 
    urgency the Commandant may write to the Inspector General direct in which 
    case, he shall endorse a copy to the Deputy Inspector General.  
 


    2[(3) When Deputy 
    Inspector General is place as head of the Unit, he shall discharge all 
    duties enumerated in rule 10 and he shall report all developments to 
    Inspector General.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Duties of Managing Director and General Manager.—The 
    Force deputed to an Undertaking shall work under the general supervision, 
    direction and control of the Managing Director of that Undertaking. 


    1[The Unit Commander] 
    of the force shall keep the Managing Director fully informed of all 
    developments including the state of the Force. The Managing Director shall 
    inspect the posts of the Force situated in his Undertaking at least once a 
    year.  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Duties 
    of Commandant.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commandant 
    shall be the head of the Unit. He shall be responsible for the efficiency 
    discipline and morale of the Unit and for the proper management of each 
    branch of the Force under him. He shall periodically inspect the Units of 
    the Force under his command. All orders to the Force under him shall emanate 
    from him and all communication from the Force under him shall pass through 
    him.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commandant shall regularly inspect the detachments of the Force posted 
    outside the headquarters and ensure that they remain in a high state of 
    efficiency. He shall ensure that all 

    1[***] members of the 
    Force under him attend Parade and refresher courses in turn according to a 
    programme. When at headquarters, he shall attend the parade every 


    2[Monday] and Friday 
    and hold the Orderly Room every Friday.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commandant shall be responsible for the security of the Undertaking in which 
    the detachment of his Units are posted. For that purpose he shall remain in 
    close touch with the district as well as Police authorities and the heads of 
    the various departments in the said Undertaking. He shall keep the Managing 
    Director and the General Manager of the said undertaking as well as the 
    Deputy Inspector General fully informed of all the developments and send 
    them regular fortnightly reports as prescribed. Matters of urgent nature, 
    however, shall be brought to their notice by the quickest possible means. He 
    shall pay his personal attention to the working of the Intelligence wing and 
    ensure that intelligence is efficiently collected and conveyed promptly to 
    the Managing Director, General Manager and the Deputy Inspector General.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Duties 
    of Deputy Commandant.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Deputy Commandant shall assist the Commandant in the discharge of his 
    duties; and where he is placed as head of the Unit, he shall discharge all 
    the duties of a Commandant and shall exercise only those financial powers 
    that are delegated to him under the relevant rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Deputy 
    Commandant shall be responsible for the efficiency, discipline and morale of 
    the personnel under him and shall also be responsible for the security of 
    the undertaking or its part entrusted to him.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12</number> Duties of 
    Assistant Commandant.—The 
    Assistant Commandant shall assist the Commandant and unless specifically 
    directed to the contrary in the regulations framed for the purpose he shall 
    perform all the functions of the Commandant when so required by the latter. 
    He shall be responsible for the efficiency, discipline and morale of the 
    personnel under him and shall also be responsible for the security of the 
    Undertaking and any other duties entrusted to him. He will assist Deputy 
    Commandant where the Deputy Commandant is the head of the Unit.]
 
 




 



</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>12A</number> </title>For the other posts, which 
have been sanctioned/created or may be sanctioned/created from time to time by 
the Central Government, their duties shall be assigned by the Director General 
Central Industrial Security Force, by a separate order.] 

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In making an arrest, under sub-section (1) of section 11 of the Act, the 
    member of the Force shall actually touch or confine the body of the person 
    to be arrested.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such 
    person forcibly resists the endeavour to arrest him, or attempts to evade 
    the arrest, the member of the Force may use all means necessary to effect 
    the arrest. In case of use of force, it should be minimum, required in that 
    particular situation.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    person arrested shall not be 

    1[subjected] to more 
    restraint than necessary to prevent his escape.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The member 
    of the Force making the arrest, may search such person, and place in safe 
    custody all articles including weapons, if any, other than necessary wearing 
    apparels, found upon him. An inventory of all such articles shall be 
    prepared in the presence of at least two respectable witnesses and in the 
    presence of the arrested person and a copy of the inventory duly signed by 
    the witnesses and the person conducting the search, shall be given to the 
    person so arrested after obtaining due receipt.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Such 
    arrested person as well as the seized articles and its inventory shall be 
    handed over to a police officer or at the nearest police station without 
    avoidable delay alongwith a brief note giving the time, date and reasons of 
    arrest.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Search.—Whenever 
    a search of a person and of his 

    1[belongings] is 
    conducted under section 12 of the Act, an inventory shall be prepared in the 
    presence of the two respectable witnesses and a copy of the inventory duly 
    signed by the witnesses and the person who conducted the search, shall be 
    given to the person concerned after obtaining due receipt. The property so 
    found on such search, shall also be sent to the police alongwith the person. 
    If nothing is found on such search, a nil inventory statement duly signed 
    shall be sent to the police alongwith the person.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Prescribed rank.—The prescribed 
    rank for the purposes of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 of the Act shall be 
    the Head Constable.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Powers 
    of appointment.—Subject to the 
    provisions of the Act and these rules, appointments to the post of Inspector 
    shall be made by the Deputy Inspector General concerned and to the ranks of 
    Sub-Inspector, Assistant Sub-Inspector, Head Constable, Constable and 
    Followers shall be made by the Commandant.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Conditions of eligibility for appointment to the Force.—No 
    person shall be eligible for appointment to the Force unless—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>  (i)   he is a citizen of India; or  
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>   he belongs to such categories of 
    persons as may, from time to time, be declared by the Central Government as 
    being eligible for appointment to the Force;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>   he bears a good moral character;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   he obtains a health certificate in the 
    form prescribed in Appendix “C” certified by a Medical Officer of Central 
    Industrial Security Force or any other Medical Officer or Assistant Surgeon 
    belonging to Grade 1 of any Government Hospital or Dispensary.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Disqualification.—No person,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   who has entered into or contracted a 
    marriage with a person having a spouse living; or   
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   who, having a spouse living, has entered 
    into or contracted a marriage with another person,   
 
shall be eligible for appointment to the 
    Force:
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, if satisfied that such marriage is permissible 
    under the personal law applicable to such person and the other party to the 
    marriage and there are other grounds for so to do, exempt any person from 
    the operation of this rule.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Name of 
    the posts, their classification and scales of pay.—The 
    name of posts of members of the Force, their number and classification and 
    the scale of pay attached thereto shall be as specified in the Recruitment 
    Rules as amended from time to time.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Method 
    of recruitment, age limits and other qualifications.—The 
    method of recruitment, age limits, qualifications and other matters relating 
    to each of the said post shall be as specified in the Recruitment Rules as 
    amended from time to time.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Agreement.—Every enrolled member 
    of the Force except those appointed on transfer or deputation shall execute 
    at the time of his initial appointment an agreement in the form specified in 
    Appendix “A”.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Cadre.—Each 
    of the three branches mentioned in rule 3 shall form a separate cadre for 
    the purpose of seniority, promotion and confirmation.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> During the period of deputation, the officer on deputation shall be 
    governed by the provisions of the Act and the rules and regulations made 
    thereunder:  
 
Provided that 
    the provisions of rules 58, 59 and 71 shall not apply to him.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Without 
    prejudice to the foregoing, every such officer shall be subject to the rules 
    of discipline applicable to the corresponding rank to the Force.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as 
    aforesaid, the other terms and conditions of deputation shall be such as may 
    be agreed upon between the lending authority and the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, the Central Government or 
    the Director General, as the case may be, may, without assigning any reason 
    terminate the period of deputation of any officer at any time and such 
    termination shall not be deemed to be a punishment.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Promotion.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in these rules specially deserving Constable or Head 
    Constable who have put in fifteen or twenty years of service may be promoted 
    to the rank of Head Constable or Assistant Sub-Inspector, as the case may 
    be, on the basis of their service records by the Commandant with the 
    approval of the Deputy Inspector General, but the total number of such 
    promotions shall not exceed 10% of the posts which may be filled by the 
    method of promotion.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Probation.—
<section><number>1</number> Every member of 
    the Force except those appointed on deputation/absorption, shall be on 
    probation for the period specified in relevant column of the Recruitment 
    Rules:  
 
Provided that 
    in the absence of a specific order of confirmation or a declaration of 
    satisfactory completion of probation, a member of the Force shall be deemed 
    to be on probation:  
 
Provided 
    further that no member of the Force shall ordinarily be kept on probation 
    for more than twice the period prescribed in respective Recruitment Rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    during the period of probation the appointing authority is of the opinion 
    that a member of the Force is not fit for permanent appointment, the 
    appointing authority may discharge him 

    1[or terminated the 
    services] from the Force after issue of notice of one month or after giving 
    one month’s pay in lieu of such notice, or revert him to the rank from which 
    he was promoted or repatriate to his parent department, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    successful completion of probation by a member of the Force, the appointing 
    authority shall pass an order confirming the member of the Force in the 
    grade in which he joined the Force.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Termination.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the appointing authority has terminated the services of probationer, 
    the Inspector, General may on his own motion or otherwise, reopen the case 
    and after making such enquiry as he thinks fit may; (i) confirm the action 
    taken by the appointing authority; (ii) withdraw the notice; (iii) reinstate 
    the probationer in service; or (iv) make such other order in the case as he 
    may consider proper:  
 
Provided that 
    except in special circumstances, which should be recorded in writing, no 
    case shall be reopened under this sub-rule after expiry of three months—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   from the date of notice, in a case where 
    notice is given;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   from the date of termination of service 
    in a case where no notice is given.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a probationer is reinstated in service under above rule, the order of 
    reinstatement shall specify (i) the amount of proportion of pay and 
    allowances, if any, to be paid to the probationer for the period of his 
    absence between the date of termination of his services and date of his 
    reinstatement; and (ii) whether the said period shall be treated as a period
    

    1[spent] on duty for 
    any specified purpose or purposes.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    Inspector General has terminated the service of a probationer, acting as 
    appointing authority, all the powers prescribed in sub-rules (1) and (2) 
    above shall be exercised by the Director General and where the Director 
    General has issued the order of termination by the Central Government.  
 


    2[(4)) During the 
    period of probation or its extension thereof, as the case may be, the 
    appointing authority may without assigning any reason terminate the services 
    of a member of the Force on the grounds of furnishing false or incorrect 
    information at the time of appointment of that member of the Force or for 
    his failure to pass the basic training or repeat course, by tendering a 
    notice of one month to that effect or one month’s pay in lieu thereof.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Special 
    provision for certain categories of persons.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall effect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other 
    concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, the Schedule 
    Tribes, Ex-servicemen and other special categories of persons, in accordance 
    with the order issued by the Central Government from time to time in this 
    regard.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Power 
    to relax.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the foregoing rules, where, in the interest of the 
    formation and the due functioning of the Force, it is necessary so to do 
    relaxation under these rules (other than the requirement of  
    being medically fit) may be made at the time of direct recruitment by the 
    Director General—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   Constable—any of the eligibility 
    criteria.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   Followers—age limit only.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Manuals.—The Director General 
    shall frame Training Manual, Establishment Manual as well as other manuals 
    for administration of the Force with the approval of the Central Government.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Solemn 
    affirmation of allegiance.—On 
    appointment, each recruit or cadet shall be required to solemnly affirm his 
    allegiance in the form given in Appendix “B” and shall receive a certificate 
    of appointment as prescribed in section 6 of the Act.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Rules 
    governing discipline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Supervisory officers shall be governed by the rules applicable to the 
    officers of the Central Government of corresponding class in respect of 
    disciplinary proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    enrolled members of the Force shall in such matters be governed by the rules 
    in this Chapter.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Disciplinary Authorities.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    disciplinary authority in respect of an enrolled member of the Force for the 
    purpose of imposing any particular penalty or the passing of any 
    disciplinary order shall be the authority specified in this behalf in 
    Schedule I under whose administrative control the enrolled member is serving 
    and shall include any authority mentioned in the said Schedule superior to 
    such authority.  
 


    1[(2) Whenever an 
    enrolled member of the Force is deployed for operational duty or any other 
    duty or course of training outside the place of his permanent posting then a 
    supervisory officer under whose control such member has been so deployed 
    shall be competent to place him under suspension. Such supervisory officer 
    shall refer the matter to concerned disciplinary authority as mentioned in 
    sub-rule (1).]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    disciplinary authority competent under Schedule I to impose any of the 
    penalties specified in clauses (vi) to (x) of rule 34 may institute 
    disciplinary proceedings against any enrolled member of the Force for 
    imposition of any of the penalties specified in clauses (i) to (v) of rule 
    34 notwithstanding that such disciplinary authority is not competent under 
    Schedule I to impose any such penalties.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Suspension. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The appointing authority 
or any authority to which it is subordinate or the disciplinary authority or any 
other authority empowered in that behalf by the President by general or special 
order may place an enrolled member of the Force under suspension— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where a disciplinary proceedings against him is 
  contemplated or is pending; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where a case against him in respect of any criminal 
  offence is under investigation, inquiry or trial; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> where in the opinion of the authority aforesaid, he 
  engaged himself in activities prejudicial to the interest of the security of 
  the State; Provided that where the order of suspension is made by an authority 
  lower than the appointing authority, such authority shall forthwith report to 
  the appointing authority the circumstances in which the order was made and 
  obtain his approval within 30 days from the date of the order. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> An enrolled member of the Force shall be deemed to have been 
placed under suspension by an order of the appointing authority— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> with effect from the date of his detention, if he is 
  detained in custody, whether on a criminal charge or otherwise, for a period 
  exceeding <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[forty-eight] hours; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> with effect from the date of his conviction in the event 
  of a conviction for an offence, he is sentenced to a term of imprisonment 
  exceeding <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[forty-eight] hours and is not forthwith dismissed or 
  removed or compulsorily retired <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[consequent] to such conviction. 
  
 Explanation. —The period of forty-eight hours 
  referred to in clause (b) of this sub-rule shall be computed from the 
  commencement of the imprisonment after the conviction and for this purpose, 
  intermittent periods of imprisonment, if any, shall be taken into account. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a penalty of dismissal, removal or compulsory 
retirement from service imposed upon an enrolled member of the Force under 
suspension is set aside in appeal or on review under these rules and the case is 
remitted for further enquiry or action or with any other directions, the orders 
of his suspension shall be deemed to have continued in <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[force] on 
and from the date of the original order of dismissal, removal or compulsory 
retirement and shall remain in <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[force] until further orders. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where a penalty of dismissal, removal or compulsory 
retirement from service imposed upon an enrolled member of the Force is set 
aside or declared or rendered void in consequence of or by a decision of a court 
of law and the disciplinary authority, on consideration of the circumstances 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[of] the case, decides to hold a further inquiry against him on the 
allegations on which the penalty of dismissal, removal or compulsory retirement 
was originally imposed, the enrolled member of the Force shall be deemed to have 
been placed under suspension by the appointing authority from the date of the 
original order of dismissal, removal or compulsory retirement and shall continue 
to remain under suspension until further orders. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> (a) An order of suspension made or deemed to have been made 
under this rule shall continue to remain in force until it is modified or 
revoked by the authority competent to do so. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where an enrolled member of the Force is suspended or is 
  deemed to have been suspended (whether in connection with any disciplinary 
  proceedings or otherwise) and any other disciplinary proceeding is commenced 
  against him during the continuance of that suspension, the authority competent 
  to place him under suspension, may for reasons to be recorded by him in 
  writing, direct that the enrolled member of the Force shall continue to be 
  under suspension until the termination of all or any of such proceedings. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> An order of suspension made or deemed to have been made 
  under this rule may at any time be modified or revoked by the authority which 
  made or is deemed to have been made the order or by any authority to which 
  that authority is subordinate. </subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> An order of suspension made or deemed to have 
been made under this rule shall be reviewed by the authority competent to modify 
or revoke the suspension, before expiry of ninety days from the date of order of 
suspension, on the recommendations of the Review Committee constituted for the 
purpose and pass orders either extending or revoking the suspension. Subsequent 
reviews shall be made before expiry of the extended period of suspension. 
Extension of suspension shall not be for a period exceeding one hundred and 
eighty days at a time. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (5), an order 
of suspension made or deemed to have been made under sub-rule (1) or (2) of this 
rule shall not be valid after a period of ninety days unless it is extended 
after review, for a further period before the expiry of ninety days.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Nature of Penalties. 
</title>—The following penalties may, for good and sufficient reasons and as 
hereinafter provided, be imposed on an enrolled member of the Force, namely:— 

 Major Penalties — 
 
 <section><number>i</number> dismissal from service which shall ordinarily be a 
  disqualification for future employment under the Government; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> removal from service which shall not be a 
  disqualification for future employment under the Government; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> compulsory retirement; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> reduction to a lower time scale of pay, grade, post or 
  service which shall ordinarily be a bar to the promotion of the Government 
  servant to the time scale of pay, grade, post or service from which he was 
  reduced with or without further directions regarding conditions of restoration 
  to the grade or post or service from which enrolled member of the Force was 
  reduced and his seniority and pay on such restoration to that grade, post or 
  service; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> save as provided for in clause (viii) below, reduction to 
  a lower stage in the time scale of pay for a specified period with further 
  directions as to whether or not the enrolled member will earn increments of 
  pay during the period of such reduction and whether on the expiry of such 
  period, the reduction will have the effect of postponing the future increments 
  of his pay. </section>
 Minor Penalties — 
 
 <section><number>vi</number> censure; 
 </section><section><number>vii</number> withholding of his promotion; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>17</footcitenum> [<number>viii</number> reduction to a lower stage in the time 
  scale of pay by one stage for a period not exceeding three years, without 
  cumulative effect and not adversely affecting his pension”;] 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> withholding of increment of pay; 
 </section><section><number>x</number> fine to any amount not exceeding of 7 days' pay. 
 Explanation. —The following shall not amount to a 
  penalty within the meaning of this rule, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> withholding of increment of an enrolled member for failure 
  to pass a departmental examination in accordance with the rules or orders or 
  the terms of his appointment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> stoppage of increment of an enrolled member at the 
  efficiency bar in a time scale of pay on the ground of his unfitness to cross 
  the bar; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> non-promotion of an enrolled member whether in a 
  substantive or officiating capacity, after consideration of his case, to a 
  rank or post for promotion to which he is eligible; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> reversion of an enrolled member officiating in a higher 
  rank or post to a lower rank or post, on the ground that he is considered 
  after trial, to be unsuitable for such higher rank or post or on any 
  administrative grounds unconnected with his conduct; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> reversion of an enrolled member appointed on probation to 
  any other rank or post during or at the end of the period of probation in 
  accordance with the terms of his appointment or the rules and orders governing 
  such probation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> replacement of the services of an enrolled member whose 
  services had been borrowed from any department of the Central Government or 
  State Government or any authority under the Central Government or the State 
  Government at the disposal of the Central Government or the State Government 
  or the authority from which the services of such enrolled member had been 
  borrowed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> compulsory retirement of an enrolled member in accordance 
  with the provisions relating to his superannuation or retirement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> Termination of service— 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> of an enrolled member appointed on probation during or at 
  the end of the period of his probation, in accordance with the terms of his 
  appointment or the rules and orders governing such probation; or 
 </subsection></section><section><number>ii</number> of a temporary enrolled member in accordance with the 
  provisions of rule 25; or 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> of an enrolled member, employed under an agreement, in 
  accordance with the terms of such agreement; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> treatment of absence from duty as “dies-non” ordered by a 
  competent authority under rule 55. </section>
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Petty 
    punishments.—Head Constable, 
    Constable and Follower may also be awarded, as punishment, extra drill, 
    guard, fatigue or other duty for a term not exceeding fourteen days.  
 
Explanation.—Petty 
    punishments shall ordinarily be awarded in Orderly Room as provided in rule 
    38 of this Chapter.  

 
  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Procedure for imposing major penalties. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> Without prejudice to the provisions of the Public 
Servants<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[(Inquiries)] Act, 1850 (37 of 1850), no order imposing on 
an enrolled member of the Force any of the penalties as specified in clauses (i) 
to (v) of rule 34 shall be made except after an inquiry held, as far as may be, 
in the manner hereinafter provided. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whenever the disciplinary authority is of the opinion that 
there are grounds for inquiring into the truth of any imputation of misconduct 
or misbehaviour against an enrolled member of the Force, it may itself inquire 
into, or appoint an authority to inquire into the truth thereof. 
 Explanation. —Where the disciplinary authority itself 
holds the inquiry, any reference in sub-rules (7) to (18) of this rule shall be 
construed as a reference to the disciplinary authority. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> Where there is a complaint of sexual 
harassment within the meaning of rule 3C of the Central Civil Services (Conduct) 
Rules, 1964, the Complaints Committee established in Central Industrial Security 
Force for inquiries into such complaints, shall be deemed to be the inquiring 
authority appointed by the disciplinary authority for the purpose of these rules 
and the Complaints Committee shall hold, if separate procedure has not been 
prescribed for the Complaints Committee for holding the inquiry into the 
complaints of sexual harassment, the inquiry as far as practicable in accordance 
with the procedure laid down in these rules.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where it is proposed to hold an inquiry against an enrolled 
member of the Force under this rule the disciplinary authority shall draw up or 
cause to be drawn up— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the substance of the imputation of misconduct or 
  misbehaviour into definite and distinct articles of charge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a statement of the imputation of misconduct of 
  misbehaviour in support of each article of charge, which shall contain— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> a statement of all relevant facts including any 
    admission or confession made by the enrolled member of the Force, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> a list of documents by which, and a list of witnesses by 
    whom, the articles of charge are proposed to be sustained. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The disciplinary authority shall deliver or cause to be 
delivered to the enrolled member of the Force a copy of the articles of charge, 
the statement of imputations of misconduct or misbehaviour and a list of 
documents and witnesses by which each article of charge is proposed to be 
sustained and shall require the enrolled member of the Force to submit, within 
such time as may be specified, a written statement of his defence and to state 
whether he desires to be heard in person. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> (a) On receipt of the written statement of defence, the 
disciplinary authority may itself inquire into such of the articles of charge as 
are not admitted, or if it considers it necessary to do so, appoint under 
sub-rule (2), an inquiring authority not below the rank of Inspector for the 
purpose, and where all the articles of the charge have been admitted by the 
enrolled member of the Force in his written statement of defence, the 
disciplinary authority shall record its findings on each charge after taking 
such evidence as it may think fit and shall pass an order in the manner laid 
down in sub-rules (20) to (22). 
 <subsection><number>b</number> If no written statement of defence is submitted by the 
enrolled member of the Force, the disciplinary authority may itself inquire into 
the articles of charge, or may, if it considers it necessary to do so, appoint, 
under sub-rule (2) an inquiring authority for the purpose. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> Where the Disciplinary Authority itself 
inquiries into any article of charge or appoints an Inquiring Authority for 
holding any enquiry into such charge, it may, by an order, appoint a member of 
the Force to be known as the ‘Presenting Officer' to present on its behalf the 
case in support of the articles of charge.] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The disciplinary authority shall, where it is not the 
Inquiring Authority, forward to the inquiring authority— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a copy of the articles of charge and the statement of the 
  imputations of misconduct or misbehaviour; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a copy of the written statement of defence, if any, 
  submitted by the enrolled member of the Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> a copy of the statement of witnesses, if any, referred 
  to in sub-rule (3); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> evidence proving the delivery of the documents referred 
  to in sub-rule (3) to the enrolled member of the Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>v</number> a copy of the order appointing the Presenting 
  Officer.] </subsection>
 </section><section><number>7</number> The enrolled member of the Force shall appear in person 
before the inquiring authority on such day and at such time and place, within 
ten working days from the date of receipt by him of the article of charge and 
the statement of imputation of misconduct or misbehaviour as the inquiring 
authority may, by notice in writing, specify in this behalf or within such 
further time, not exceeding ten days as the inquiring authority may allow. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> (a) The enrolled member of the Force so charged may be 
permitted by the inquiring authority to present his case with the assistance of 
any other member of the Force posted at the place of inquiry. He will give three 
choices for his defence assistance and the controlling officer will depute any 
one of the three indicated by him. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> The <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***] member of the Force cannot have more 
than three cases in hand in which he is rendering defence assistance. However, 
the controlling authority of such person who is sought to be engaged may refuse 
permission for his working as defence assistant if the public interest so 
demands. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>9</number> If the enrolled member of the Force who has not admitted any 
of the article of charge in his written statement of defence or has not 
submitted any written statement of defence, appears before the inquiring 
authority, such authority shall ask him whether he is guilty or has any defence 
to make and if he pleads guilty to any of the articles of charge, the enquiring 
authority shall record the plea, sign the record and obtain the signature of the 
enrolled member of the Force thereon. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> (a) The Inquiring Authority shall return a 
finding of guilt in respect of those articles of charge to which the enrolled 
member of the Force pleads guilty; 
 <subsection><number>b</number> The Inquiring Authority shall, if the enrolled member of the 
Force fails to appear within the specified time or refuses or omits to plead, 
require the Presenting Officer to produce the evidence by which he proposes to 
prove the articles of charge, and shall adjourn the case to a later date, not 
exceeding thirty days, after recording an order that the enrolled member of the 
Force may, for the purpose of preparing his defence— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> inspect within five days of the order or within such 
  further time not exceeding five days as the Inquiring Authority may allow, the 
  documents specified in the list referred to in sub-rule (3); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> submit a list of witnesses to be examined on his behalf; 
  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> give a notice within ten days of the order or within 
  such further time not exceeding ten days as the Inquiring Authority may allow, 
  for the discovery or production of any documents which are in the possession 
  of Government but not mentioned in the list referred to in sub-rule (3).] 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection></section><section><number>11</number> The inquiring authority shall, on receipt of the notice for 
the discovery or production of documents forward the same or copies thereof to 
the authority in whose custody or possession the documents are kept, with a 
requisition for the production of the documents by such date as may be specified 
in such requisition: 
 <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[Provided that the Inquiring Authority may, for 
reasons to be recorded by it in writing, refuse to requisition such of the 
documents as are, in its opinion, not relevant to the case.] 
 </section><section><number>12</number> On receipt of the requisition referred to in sub-rule (11), 
every authority having the custody or possession of the requisitioned documents 
shall produce the same before the inquiring authority: 
 Provided that if the authority having the custody or possession 
of the requisitioned documents is satisfied for reasons to be recorded by it in 
writing that the production of all or any of such documents would be against the 
public interest or security of the State, it shall inform the inquiring 
authority accordingly and the inquiring authority shall, on being so informed, 
communicate the information to the enrolled member of the Force and withdraw the 
requisition made by it for the production or discovery of documents. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><number>14</number> <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [***] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>15</number> On the date fixed for the inquiry, the oral 
and documentary evidence by which the articles of charge are proposed to be 
proved shall be produced by or on behalf of the Disciplinary Authority. The 
witnesses shall be examined by or on behalf of the Presenting Officer and may be 
cross-examined by or on behalf of the enrolled member of the Force. The 
Presenting Officer shall be entitled to re-examine the witnesses on any points 
on which they have been cross examined, but not on any new matter, without the 
leave of the Inquiring Authority. The Inquiring Authority may also put such 
questions to the witnesses as it thinks fit.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>16</number> If it shall appear necessary before the close 
of the case on behalf of the Disciplinary Authority, the Inquiring Authority 
may, in its discretion, allow the Presenting Officer to produce evidence not 
included in the list given to the enrolled member of the Force or may itself 
call for new evidence or recall and re-examine any witness and in such case the 
enrolled member of the Force shall be entitled to have, if he demands it, a copy 
of the list of further evidence proposed to be produced and an adjournment of 
the enquiry for three clear days before the production of such new evidence, 
exclusive of the day of adjournment and the day to which the enquiry is 
adjourned. The Inquiring Authority shall give the enrolled member of the Force 
an opportunity of inspecting such documents before they are taken on the record. 
The Inquiring Authority may also allow the enrolled member of the Force to 
produce new evidence, if it is of the opinion that the production of such 
evidence is necessary, if the interests of justice. 
 <title>Note. </title>—New evidence shall not be permitted or 
called for or any witness shall not be recalled to fill up any gap in the 
evidence. Such evidence may be called for only when there is an inherent lacuna 
of defect in the evidence which has been produced originally.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>17</number> When the case for the Disciplinary Authority 
is close, the enrolled member of the Force shall be required to state his 
defence, orally or in writing as he may prefer. If the defence is made orally it 
shall be recorded, and the enrolled member of the Force shall be required to 
sign the record. In either case, a copy of the statement of defence shall be 
given to the presenting Officer, if any appointed.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>18</number> (a) The evidence on behalf of the enrolled 
member of the Force shall then be produced. The enrolled member of the Force may 
examine himself in his own behalf if he so prefers. The witnesses produced by 
the enrolled member of the Force shall then be examined and shall be liable to 
cross-examination, re-examination and examination by the Inquiring Authority 
according to the provisions applicable to the witnesses for the Disciplinary 
Authority. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> The Inquiring Authority may, after the enrolled member of 
the Force closes, his case, and shall, if the enrolled member of the Force has 
not examined himself, generally question him on the circumstances appearing 
against him in the evidence for the purpose of enabling the enrolled member of 
the Force to explain any circumstances appearing in the evidence against him. 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The Inquiring Authority may, after the completion of the 
production of evidence, hear the Presenting Officer, if any, appointed and the 
enrolled member of the Force, or permit them to file written briefs of their 
respective case, if they so desire. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Whenever any Inquiring Authority, after having heard and 
recorded the whole or any part of the evidence in any inquiry ceases to exercise 
jurisdiction therein, and is succeeded by another Inquiring Authority which has, 
and which exercises, such jurisdiction, the Inquiring Authority so succeeding 
may act on the evidence so recorded by its predecessor, or partly recorded by 
its predecessor and partly recorded by itself: 
 Provided that if the succeeding Inquiring Authority is of the 
opinion that further examination of any of the witnesses whose evidence has 
already been recorded is necessary in the interests of justice, it may recall, 
examine, cross-examine and re-examine any such witnesses as hereinbefore 
provided. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> If the enrolled member of the Force to whom a copy of the 
articles of charge has been delivered, does not submit written statement on or 
before the date specified for the purpose or does not appear in person before 
the Inquiring Authority or otherwise fails or refuses to comply with the 
provisions of this rule, the Inquiring Authority may hold the inquiry 
ex-parte .] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>19</number>(i) After the conclusion of the inquiry, a report shall be 
prepared and it shall contain— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the articles of charge and the statement of the 
  imputations of misconduct or misbehaviour; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the defence of the enrolled member in respect of each 
  article of charge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> an assessment of the evidence in respect of each article 
  of charge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the findings on each article of charge and reasons 
  thereof. </subsection>
 Explanation. —If, in the opinion of the inquiring 
authority the proceedings of the inquiry establish any article of charge 
different from the original article of the charge, it may record its findings on 
such article of charge: 
 Provided that the findings on such article of charge shall not 
be recorded unless the enrolled member has either admitted the fact on which 
such article of charge is based or has had a reasonable opportunity of defending 
himself against such article of charge. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The inquiring authority, where it is not itself the 
disciplinary authority, shall forward to the disciplinary authority the records 
of enquiry which shall include— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> the report prepared by it under clause (i); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> the written statement of defence, if any, submitted by the 
  enrolled member; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> the oral and documentary evidence produced in the course 
  of inquiry; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> written brief, if any, filed by the enrolled member 
  <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[or the Presenting Officer] during the course of the inquiry; and 
  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number> the orders, if any, made by the disciplinary authority and 
  the inquiry authority in regard to the enquiry. </subsubsection>
 </subsection></section><section><number>20</number> (i) Where a disciplinary authority competent to impose any 
of the minor penalties and not competent to impose any of the major penalties 
specified in rule 34 has itself inquired into or cause to be inquired into the 
articles of any charge and that authority having regard to his own finding or 
having regard to his decision on any of the findings of any inquiring authority 
appointed by it, is of the opinion that the major penalty specified in rule 34 
should be imposed upon the enrolled member, that authority shall forward the 
records of the inquiry to such disciplinary authority as is competent to impose 
any of the major penalties. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The disciplinary authority to which the records are so 
forwarded may act on the evidence on the record or may remit the case to the 
disciplinary authority from whom the records were forwarded or the inquiring 
authority, as the case may be, for further inquiry and report on any point. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>21</number> (i) The disciplinary authority, if it is not itself the 
inquiry authority, may consider the records of inquiry and record its findings 
on each charge. The disciplinary authority may, for reasons to be recorded by it 
in writing, remit the case to the inquiring authority for further inquiry and 
report and the inquriy authority shall thereupon proceed to hold the further 
inquiry according to the provisions of this rule as far as may be. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The disciplinary authority shall, if it disagrees with the 
findings of the inquiring authority on any article of charge, record its reasons 
for such disagreement and record its own findings on such charge if the evidence 
on record is sufficient for the purpose. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>28</footcitenum> [<number>iii</number> The Disciplinary Authority shall forward or 
cause to be forwarded a copy of the report of the inquiry, if any, held by the 
Disciplinary Authority or where the Disciplinary Authority is not the Inquiring 
Authority, a copy of the report of the Inquiring Authority together with reasons 
for disagreement, if any, and record its own findings on any article of charge, 
to the enrolled member of the Force who shall be required to submit, if he so 
desires, his written representation or submission to the Disciplinary Authority 
within fifteen days irrespective of whether the report is favourable or not to 
the enrolled member of the Force. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> The Disciplinary Authority shall consider the 
representation, if any, submitted by the enrolled member of the Force before 
proceeding further in the manner as provided in sub-rule (22) of Rule 36.] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>22</number> (i) If the disciplinary authority having regard to its 
findings on all or any of the articles of charge is of the opinion that any of 
the minor penalties specified in rule 34 should be imposed on the enrolled 
member, it shall, notwithstanding anything contained in rule 37, make an order 
imposing such penalty. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If the disciplinary authority having regard to its findings 
on all or any of the articles of charge and on the basis of evidence adduced 
during the course of inquiry, is of the opinion that any of the major penalties 
specified in rule 34 should be imposed on the enrolled member, it shall make an 
order imposing such penalties and it shall not be necessary to give the enrolled 
member any opportunity of making representation on the penalty proposed to be 
imposed. 











</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Procedure for imposing minor penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No order imposing any of minor penalties specified in rule 34 shall be made 
    except after—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   informing the enrolled member in writing 
    of the imputations of misconduct or misbehaviour on which it is proposed to 
    be taken and giving him a reasonable opportunity of making such 
    representation as he wishes to make against the proposal;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   holding an inquiry, if the disciplinary 
    authority so desires, in the manner laid down in sub-rules (3) to (22) of 
    rule 36;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   taking the representation, if any, 
    submitted by the enrolled member under clause (a) and the record of inquiry, 
    if any, held under clause (b) into consideration; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   recording the findings on each 
    imputation of misconduct or misbehaviour.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (b) of sub-rule (1), if in a 
    case it is proposed after considering the representation, if any, made by 
    the Government servant under clause (a) of that sub-rule to withhold 
    increments of pay and such withholding of increments is likely to affect 
    adversely the amount of pension payable to the government servant or to 
    withhold increments of pay for a period exceeding 3 years or to withhold 
    increments of pay with cumulative effect for any period an inquiry shall be 
    held in the manner laid down in sub-rules (3) to (22) of rule 36 before 
    making any order imposing on the enrolled member of the Force any such 
    penalty.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The records 
    of the proceedings in such cases shall include—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   a copy of the intimation to the enrolled 
    member so charged of the proposal to take action against him;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   a copy of the statement of imputation 
    of misconduct or misbehaviour delivered to him;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   his representation, if any;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the evidence produced during the 
    enquiry, if any;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   the findings on each imputation of 
    misconduct or misbehaviour; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   the orders on the case together with 
    the reasons therefor.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Procedure for imposing petty punishment.—Petty 
    breaches of discipline and trifling cases of misconduct by the enrolled 
    members of the Force not above the rank of the Head Constable shall be 
    inquired into and disposed of in the Orderly Room. The punishment enumerated 
    in rule 35 may be awarded, making a record of a summary proceedings in the 
    Orderly Room register which shall be maintained for keeping record of such 
    punishments. There shall be no appeal against the punishment awarded in the 
    Orderly Room.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>39</number> Special 
    procedure in certain cases.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in rules 36 to 38—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   where any penalty is imposed on an 
    enrolled member of the Force on the ground of conduct which has led to his 
    conviction on a criminal charge; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   where the disciplinary authority is 
    satisfied for reasons to be recorded by it in writing that it is not 
    reasonably practicable to hold an inquiry in the manner provided in these 
    rules; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   where the President is satisfied that 
    in the interest of the security of the State, it is not expedient to hold 
    any inquiry in the manner provided in these rules, the disciplinary 
    authority may consider the circumstances of the case and make such orders 
    thereon as it deems fit:  
 
Provided that 
    the enrolled member of the Force may be given an opportunity of making 
    representation against the penalty proposed to be imposed before any order 
    is made in case under clause (i).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Provisions regarding enrolled members of the Force borrowed from State 
    Governments etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
    order of suspension is made or a disciplinary proceeding is conducted 
    against an enrolled member of the Force whose services have been borrowed 
    from another department of the Central Government or from a State Government 
    or an authority subordinate thereto, the authority lending his services 
    (hereinafter in these rules referred to as the “lending authority”) shall 
    forthwith be informed of the circumstances leading to the order of 
    suspension of the enrolled member of the Force or the commencement of the 
    disciplinary proceedings, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the 
    light of the findings in the disciplinary proceeding conducted against such 
    an enrolled member of the Force, if the disciplinary authority is of the 
    opinion that any of the penalties specified in clauses (vi) to (x) of rule 
    34 should be imposed on him, it may, subject to the provisions of sub-rule 
    (22)(i) of rule 36 and after consultation with the lending authority, pass 
    such orders on the case as it may deem necessary—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   provided that in the event of difference 
    of opinion between the borrowing authority and the lending authority, the 
    services of such enrolled member of the Force shall be re-placed at the 
    disposal of the lending authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if the disciplinary authority is of the 
    opinion that any of the penalties specified in clauses (i) to (v) of rule 34 
    should be imposed on the enrolled member of the Force, it shall re-place the 
    services of such enrolled member of the Force at the disposal of the lending 
    authority and transmit to it the proceedings of the enquiry for such action 
    as it may deem necessary.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Provisions regarding enrolled member of the Force lent to State Government 
    etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the services of an enrolled member of the Force are lent to another 
    department of the Central Government or to a State Government or other 
    authority 

    1[hereinafter] in this 
    rule referred to as “borrowing authority” the borrowing authority shall have 
    the powers of the appointing authority for the purpose of placing such 
    enrolled member of the Force under suspension and of the disciplinary 
    authority for the purpose of conducting a disciplinary against him:  
 
Provided that 
    the borrowing authority shall forthwith inform the authority which lent the 
    services of such enrolled member of the Force hereinafter in this rule 
    referred to as ‘the lending authority’ of the circumstances leading to the 
    order of suspension of such enrolled member of the Force or the commencement 
    of the disciplinary proceeding, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the 
    light of findings in the disciplinary proceedings conducted against the 
    enrolled member of the Force—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   If the borrowing authority is of the 
    opinion that any of the penalties specified in clauses (vi) to (x) of rule 
    34 should be imposed on such a member, it may, after consultation with the 
    lending authority, make such orders on the case as it may deem necessary:  
 
Provided that in the event of difference of 
    opinion between the borrowing authority and the lending authority, the 
    services of such enrolled member of the Force shall be re-placed at the 
    disposal of the lending authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   If the borrowing authority is of 
    the opinion that any of the penalties specified in clauses (i) to (v) of 
    rule 34 should be imposed on the enrolled member, it shall re-place his 
    services at the disposal of lending authority and transmit the proceedings 
    of the enquiry and thereupon the lending authority may, if 
1[it] 
    is a disciplinary authority, pass such orders thereon as it may deem 
    necessary, or if he is not a disciplinary authority, submit the case to the 
    appropriate disciplinary authority which shall pass orders on the case as it 
    may deem necessary:  
 
Provided that before passing any such order 
    the disciplinary authority shall comply with the provisions of sub-rule (22) 
    of rule 36.
 
Explanation.—The 
    disciplinary authority may make an order under this clause on the record of 
    the inquiry transmitted to it by the borrowing authority or after holding 
    such further inquiry as it may deem necessary, as far as may be in 
    accordance with rule 36.  
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Reduction in rank etc.—No enrolled 
    member of the Force shall be reduced to a rank lower than that to which he 
    was first appointed to the service nor shall be reduced permanently in the 
    sense that he may never be eligible for re-promotion however meritorious his 
    subsequent service may be. When reduction to a lower rank class, grade or a 
    lower time scale or a lower stage in the time scale is ordered, the order 
    shall also specify the position in the lower rank on such reduction as well 
    as the period for which the reduction shall hold good.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Withholding of increment.—In case 
    of withholding of increment as a punishment, the order shall state the 
    period for which the increment is to be withheld and whether it shall have 
    the effect of postponing further increments.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>44</number> Appeal 
    against order of suspension.—An 
    enrolled member of the Force may appeal against the order of suspension to 
    the authority, to which the authority which made or is deemed to have made 
    the order is immediately subordinate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>45</number> Orders 
    against which no appeal lies.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this chapter, no appeal shall lie against—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   any order of interlocutory nature 
    or of the nature of 
1[step-in-aid 
    of] the final disposal of disciplinary proceedings other than an order of 
    suspension; and   
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   any order passed by an inquiring 
    authority in the course of inquiry under rule 36.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>46</number> Appeal 
    against order imposing penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An enrolled member may prefer an appeal against all or any of the following 
    orders, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   an order of suspension made or deemed to 
    have been made under rule 33;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   an order imposing any of the penalties 
    specified in rule 34, made by the disciplinary authority or by any appellate 
    or revising authority.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Such appeal 
    shall be made to the authority immediately superior to the authority who has 
    imposed the penalty.  
 
Note.—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Appeal against the order of Deputy 
    Inspector General shall lie to the Sector Inspector General and against the 
    order of the Sector Inspector General to the Director General.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Appeal against the order of the Deputy 
    Inspector General at Force Headquarters including Deputy Inspector General 
    (Training and Fire) shall lie to Inspector General (Headquarters) and 
    against the order of Inspector General (Headquarters) to the Director 
    General.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Appeal against the order of the 
    Director General shall lie to the Central Government.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Where the person who made the order 
    appealed against becomes, by virtue of his subsequent appointment or 
    otherwise the appellate authority in respect of such order, an appeal 
    against such order shall lie to the authority to whom such person is 
    immediately subordinate.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> There shall 
    be no second appeal. But when the appellate authority imposes a penalty 
    higher than the one appealed against, an appeal shall lie to the authority 
    next superior to the appellate authority.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>47</number> Period 
    of limitation for appeals.—No 
    appeal under these rules shall be entertained unless it is submitted within 
    a period of 30 days from the date on which the appellant received a copy of 
    the order appealed against:  
 
Provided that 
    the appellate authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the 
    said period, if it is satisfied that the appellant had sufficient cause for 
    not preferring the appeal in time.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>48</number> Form and 
    contents of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    enrolled member preferring an appeal shall do so separately in his own name.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    appeal shall be addressed to the authority to whom the appeal 

    1[lies and it] shall 
    contain all material statements and arguments on which the appellant relies, 
    shall not contain any disrespectful or improper language, and shall be 
    complete in itself.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Submission of Appeals.—The 
    appellant shall submit such appeal to the authority which made the order 
    appealed against:  
 
Provided that 
    if the appellant at the time of submitting such appeal is not serving under 
    that authority, shall submit the appeal to the authority under whom he is 
    serving and that authority shall forward it forthwith to the appropriate 
    authority. If the appellant is not in service, he shall submit his appeal 
    direct to the appellate authority, a copy of the appeal will also be 
    forwarded by the appellant to the authority which made the order appealed 
    against.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Withholding of appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    authority which made the order appealed against, may withhold the appeal if—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   it is an appeal against an order for 
    which no appeal lies under rule 45; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   it is not in conformity with the 
    provisions of rule 48; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   it is not submitted within the period 
    specified in rule 47 and no sufficient cause is shown for the delay; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   it is repetition of any appeal already 
    decided and no new facts of circumstances are adduced:  
 
Provided that 
    an appeal withheld on the ground only that it was not in conformity with 
    provisions of rule 48, shall be returned to the appellant and if 
    re-submitted within 30 days thereof, after compliance with the said 
    provisions, shall not be withheld.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    appeal is withheld on any grounds under sub-rule (1) of this rule, the 
    appellant shall be informed of the facts and the reasons therefor.   


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Transmission of appeals.—The 
    authority which made the order appealed against, shall on receipt of such 
    appeal, forward the same together with the relevant records, to the 
    appellate authority without any avoidable delay and without waiting for any 
    directions from the appellate authority unless the appeal is withheld under 
    rule 50.  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>52</number> Consideration of appeals. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In the case of an appeal against an order of suspension, the appellate authority shall consider whether in the light of the provisions of <footcitenum>32</footcitenum> [rule 33] and having regard to the circumstances of the case, the order of suspension is justified or not and confirm or revoke the order accordingly. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of an appeal against the order imposing any of the penalties specified in rule 34, or enhancing any penalty imposed under the said rules, the appellate authority shall consider— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> whether the procedure laid down in these rules has been complied with and if not whether such non-compliance has resulted in the violation of any provisions of the Constitution of India or in the failure of justice; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> whether the findings of the disciplinary authority are warranted on the basis of the evidence on the record; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> whether the penalty or the enhanced penalty imposed is excessive, or adequate, or inadequate and pass orders— 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> confirming, enhancing, reducing or setting aside the penalty; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> remitting the case to the authority which imposed or enhanced the penalty, or to any other authority with such directions it may deem fit in the circumstances of the case; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>33</footcitenum> [<number>iii</number> No order imposing enhanced penalty shall be made in any other case unless the appellant has been given a reasonable opportunity, as far as may be in accordance with the provisions of rule 37, of making a representation against such enhanced penalty.] 
 Provided that— 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number> If such enhanced penalty which the appellate authority proposes to impose is one of the penalties specified in clauses (i) to (v) of rule 34 and an inquiry under rule 36 has not already been held in the case, the appellate authority shall, subject to the provisions of rule 39, itself hold such an inquiry or direct that such inquiry be held in accordance with rule 36 and thereafter on a consideration of the proceedings of such inquiry make such orders as it may deem fit; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> If the enhanced penalty which the appellate authority proposes to impose is one of the penalties specified in clauses (i) to (v) of rule 34 and an inquiry under rule 36 has already been held in the case, the appellate authority shall make such orders as it may deem fit. 
  



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Implementation of orders in appeal.—The 
    authority which made the order appealed against shall give effect to the 
    orders passed by the appellate authority.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>54</number> Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any authority superior to the authority making the order may either on his 
    own motion or otherwise call for the records of any inquiry and revise any 
    order made under these rules, and may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   confirm, modify or set aside the order; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   confirm, reduce, enhance or set aside 
    the penalty imposed by the order, or impose any penalty where no penalty has 
    been imposed; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   remit the case to the authority which 
    made the order or to any other authority directing such authority to make 
    such further enquiry as it may consider proper in the circumstances of the 
    case; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   pass such order as it may deem fit, 
    within six months of the date of communication of the order proposed to be 
    revised:  
 
Provided that 
    no order imposing or enhancing any penalty shall be made by any revisioning 
    authority unless the enrolled  member of the Force concerned has been given 
    a reasonable opportunity of making a representation against the penalty 
    proposed and where it is proposed to impose any of the penalties specified 
    in clauses (i) to (v) of rule 34 or to enhance the penalty imposed by the 
    order sought to be revised to any of the penalties specified in those 
    clauses, and if any, inquiry under rule 36 of Central Industrial Security 
    Force Rules, 2001 has not already been held in the case no such penalty 
    shall be imposed except after an enquiry in the manner laid down in the 
    aforesaid rules.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of rule 52 relating to appeals shall apply so far as may be to 
    such orders in revision.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Orders and 
    instructions issued by the Central Government on this subject from time to 
    time shall be applicable mutatis mutandis as applicable under Central 
    Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965.]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Dies-non.—Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in these rules a disciplinary authority while passing final order 
    to impose a penalty upon an enrolled member of the Force or an appellate 
    authority or a revising authority may, on reinstatement of an enrolled 
    member of the Force in service after setting aside a penalty of dismissal, 
    removal or compulsory retirement without exonerating such enrolled member of 
    the Force of the charges which resulted in any of these penalties, after 
    giving an opportunity to the enrolled member of the Force concerned to show 
    cause against such action and for reasons to be recorded in writing, order 
    that the intervening period between the date of dismissal, removal or 
    compulsory retirement, as the case may be, and the date of reinstatement be 
    treated as dies-non for purposes of service.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Petitions.—
<section><number>1</number> Any enrolled member 
    of the Force may submit a petition in respect of any matter connected with 
    his official position in which his personal interests are involved other 
    than a matter covered by the rule relating to appeals and revision.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each such 
    enrolled member of the Force shall submit a petition solely relating to his 
    individual case.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Joint 
    petitions of any kind whatsoever shall not be taken notice of and submission 
    of such petitions shall be deemed to be an act of indiscipline.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Such 
    petition shall be in proper form and not couched in improper language and be 
    submitted to the immediate superior even if the petitioner be on leave at 
    the time. A petition submitted in contravention of this rule shall be 
    summarily rejected.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Such 
    immediate superior shall submit it through his immediate superior to the 
    authority competent to dispose it of. An officer superior to him may 
    withhold any such petition if it is couched in intemperate language or is 
    otherwise improperly written, in which case he shall inform the petitioner 
    in writing that his petition has been withheld.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In any 
    subsequent petition to the competent authority, the petitioner shall also 
    attach to his petition a copy of the order on his previous petition as 
    communicated to him by his immediate superior officer.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Other 
    methods forbidden.—The supervisory 
    officers and enrolled members of the Force are forbidden from resorting to 
    any method other than that prescribed in these rules for pressing their 
    claims or for obtaining redress of alleged grievances or reversal, any such 
    attempt on their part shall be deemed to be an act of indiscipline.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> The appointing 
    authority may during the period of probation or thereafter permit any member 
    of the Force to resign from his post with effect from such date as may be 
    specified in the order accepting his resignation:  
 
Provided that 
    before acceptance of resignation of any such member of the force up to the 
    period of ten years from the date of appointment in the Force, for reasons 
    other than accepting a job elsewhere for which cadre clearance has been 
    given, shall be required to refund the cost of training imparted to him in 
    the Force or a sum equal to three months’ pay and allowances, whichever is 
    more.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    resignation of a member of the Force who is under trial or whose conduct is 
    under inquiry may be refused.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Discharge Certificate.—Whenever a 
    member of the Force ceases to be such member for any reason whatsoever, a 
    discharge certificate in the Form specified in Appendix “D” annexed to these 
    rules shall be given to him.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Free 
    accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> Normally, the 
    undertaking where the Force has been deputed shall provide accommodation in 
    the township itself to all supervisory officers and at the rate of 45 per 
    cent married and 55 per cent unmarried or as amended by the Central 
    Government from time to time, to the enrolled members of the Force.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accommodation to the enrolled member of the Force shall be rent-free but 
    where such facilities are not available they shall get house rent allowance 
    in lieu thereof as applicable to other central government employees.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The members 
    of the Force shall also get compensation in lieu of married accommodation in 
    terms of orders issued by the Government from time to time in this respect. 
    The compensation shall be payable to that percentage of members of the Force 
    who are entitled to get married accommodation minus those members of the 
    Force who are allotted accommodation by the Undertaking.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Supervisory 
    officer of the Force who is provided accommodation by the Public Sector 
    Undertakings or allotted accommodation by Directorate of Estate will pay 
    licence fee to the Public Sector Undertakings at the rates as applicable to 
    their own employees or the licence fee as fixed by the Central Government 
    for general pool accommodation from time to time with reference to plinth 
    area of accommodation as the case may be.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Medical 
    facilities.—Members of the Force 
    shall be entitled to the facilities of the Central Government Health Scheme 
    and in places where these facilities are not available, they shall be 
    governed by the Central Civil Services (Medical Attendant) Rules, 1944:  
 
Provided that 
    when they are deployed in a Public Sector Undertaking,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   in a case where such Public Sector 
    Undertaking provides medical facilities to its employees, such members of 
    the Force shall be entitled to avail such facilities free of charge; and   
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   if such facilities are not available, 
    the authorised medical attendant for such members of the Force will be as 
    provided in Central Civil Services (Medical Attendant) Rules, 1944.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Leave.—The 
    Supervisory officers and 

    1[enrolled members of 
    the Force] shall be governed by the Leave Rules as are applicable to 
    employees of the Central Government, excepting that they shall be entitled 
    to fifteen days Casual Leave in a calender year in respect of field 
    formation where no specific working hours in a day or working weeks are 
    prescribed and entitlement of Casual leave in static formation like Force 
    Head Quarters, Sector Head Quarters, etc., of Central Industrial Security 
    Force will be 8 days in a calender year as per Ministry of Home Affairs’ 
    Office Memorandum No. 27012/6/98/PF.I/ 419 dated 7-7-2000. The 
    Regularisation of leave will be subject to orders issued by Central 
    Government from time to time.  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Recall 
    from Leave.—The Supervisory 
    officers and enrolled members of the Force on leave may be recalled at any 
    time by the authority empowered to sanction their leave. They may be 
    directed to report for duty either at Headquarters or to proceed direct to 
    the place at which their services are required.  
 
In either case, 
    travelling allowance as on tour (by shortest route) for the return journey 
    may be allowed to them at the discretion of the authority recalling them 
    from leave.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Free Leave Pass and Leave Travel 
    Concession.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Free Leave Pass and Leave Travel Concession shall be admissible to the 
    members of the Force of and below the rank of 

    1[Inspector] as 
    follows, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   When living away from their families one 
    Free Leave Pass every year from places of duty to the railway stations 
    nearest to their towns and return subject to the Leave Travel Concession for 
    their families in a block period of two years.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   In case they are living with their 
    families and propose to avail themselves of Leave Travel Concession for 
    their families also, they shall be entitled to Free Leave Pass to home towns 
    and return for self only once in two years and Leave Travel Concession (once 
    in a block period of two years) to the family members under the normal Leave 
    Travel Concession Rules applicable to other Central Government employees.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   Free Leave Pass when proceeding on 
    medical leave of duration of not less than one month, provided it is 
    certified that the illness or injury which necessitated medical leave was 
    not brough about by any fault or negligence on the part of the member of the 
    Force.  
 

2[(ca)   
    An additional leave travel concession is admissible to the member to the 
    Force in the event of death, serious illness or marriage of a member of the 
    family of the member of the Force. The additional leave travel concession is 
    limited only to the onward journey from the place of duty.]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   Leave Travel Concession once in four 
    years for self and family members to travel to any place in India as 
    admissible to other Central Government employees:  
 
Provided that 
    the Leave Travel Concession admissible under clause (d) shall be in lieu of 
    the Free Leave Pass admissible under clause (a) and the Leave Travel 
    Concession and Free Leave Pass admissible under clause (b).  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Supervisory 
    officers and members of the Force of and above the rank of Assistant 
    Sub-Inspector, shall be eligible to the same leave travel concession to 
    which the other Central Government employees are eligible pursuant to the 
    orders of the Central Government in this behalf.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Power to 
    grant monetary rewards.—Monetary 
    rewards may be granted to the enrolled members of the Force non-gazetted 
    Government servants, employees and workers of the industrial undertakings 
    and members of the public in accordance with rules 67, 68 and 69.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    Eligibility for monetary rewards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Monetary rewards may be granted only to the enrolled members of the Force 
    for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   doing outstanding work, requiring 
    special courage, skill or initiative such as—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the arrest of a criminal; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   securing of information leading to the 
    detection of a crime or matters connected therewith; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   making exceptionally good enquiries; 
    or           
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   an encounter with a criminal, if 
    connection with the protection, safeguard and security of an industrial 
    undertaking;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   doing work of a less outstanding nature 
    but requiring prompt, honest and intelligent observance of, and obedience to 
    order so as to be of material assistance in the protection, safeguard and 
    security of an industrial undertaking;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   doing extra hard works in connection 
    with the protection, safeguard and security of industrial undertaking;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   smartness, markmanship, diligence, 
    praiseworthy attention to the employees and workers of the industrial 
    undertakings or to the persons who visit the industrial undertakings on 
    business or for any other purpose which, in exceptional cases, is calculated 
    to promote the efficiency of the Force.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) 
    Monetary rewards in the form of books or articles of value not exceeding one 
    thousand rupees for each prize may also be granted to enrolled members of 
    the Force for proficiency during training for every batch of trainees who 
    pass out of the Training College or Training Centre, as specified below:  
 
I Prize—for all 
    round efficiency first rank;  
 
II Prize—for 
    all round efficiency second rank;  
 
III Prize—for 
    proficiency in parade, muskety and sports.  
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Monetary 
    rewards shall not be granted on request.  
 
Explanation.—For 
    the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that it shall be permissible to 
    grant also the III Prize to a trainee who has been granted I Prize or II 
    Prize.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Monetary 
    rewards may be granted to the non-gazetted Government servants, employees 
    and workers of the industrial undertakings and the members of the public as 
    an incentive for assisting the Force—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   in the detection of any serious case, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in the apprehension of an offender, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   in resisting a criminal or an 
    anti-social element, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   for any other purpose, which is for the 
    better protection, safeguard and security of the industrial undertakings.  
 
Explanation.—For 
    the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that for the purposes of this 
    rule—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   ‘general good work’ shall not be a 
    ground for the grant of monetary rewards.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   monetary rewards shall not be granted 
    on request.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Authorities competent to grant monetary rewards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The supervisory officers are empowered, subject to the budget provisions of 
    the Force, to offer and grant monetary rewards under rule 67 as prescribed 
    by the Central Government from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A monetary 
    reward under rule 67 shall be granted by an officer competent to grant the 
    same if he is of opinion, for reasons to be recorded in writing, that the 
    person fulfils the requirements in this behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The order 
    granting such monetary reward shall indicate the reasons therefor and the 
    provisions of rule 67 under which it is granted.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Monetary 
    rewards offered by the Managing Director of the industrial undertakings.—A 
    supervisory officer of the Force may permit an enrolled member of the Force 
    to accept monetary reward offered by a Managing Director of an industrial 
    undertaking for a purpose relatable to sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 67.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>70</number> Benefits on account of risk of 
      “office”/special risk of “office”.—In these matters, supervisory officer and 
      enrolled members of the Force shall be governed by Central Civil Services 
      (Extra Ordinary Pension) Rules as amended from time to time.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>71</number> Superannuation etc.—The rules relating to superannuation pension, 
      provident fund and gratuity of supervisory officers and enrolled members 
      of the Force shall be the same as those applicable to the Central 
      Government employees.   
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>72</number> Transfer.—
<section><number>1</number> Transfers of members of the Force may be 
      made as under:  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   of supervisory 
      officers, by the Director General;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   of and upto the 
      rank of Head Constable from one unit to another unit under the 
      administrative control of one Commandant, by the Commandant;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   of the enrolled 
      members of the Force from one unit to another within the Zone by the 
      Deputy Inspector General of that Zone;   
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>   of the 
      enrolled members of the Force from one unit to another unit within the 
      sector by the 1[Inspector General] of that sector; and   
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>   of the 
      enrolled members of the Force from one unit or zone to another in the 
      entire Force by the 1[Deputy Inspector General of Force Headquarters.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> An authority superior to the authority 
      competent under sub-rule (1) may make an order of transfer, annul, change 
      or modify any order of transfer made under sub-rule (1).  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>73</number> Payment of charges.—The charges payable by an industrial 
      undertaking in public sector for the deputation of supervisory officers 
      and enrolled members of the Force under section 14 of the Act to such 
      undertaking, shall be paid for such periods and in such manner as the 
      Central Government may from time to time specify.  
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this rule, charges payable 
      by an industrial undertaking in public sector shall include—  
 <section><number>i</number>   the pay and 
      allowances, leave salary contribution and pension contribution payable to 
      officers and enrolled members of the Force deputed to that undertaking;  
 </section><section><number>ii</number>   the cost of 
      clothing, equipment, transport, arms and ammunitions and other 
      accoutrements necessary for the proper discharge of the functions of such 
      officers and members; and   
 </section><section><number>iii</number>   the amount which 
      the Central Government may, having regard to the number of officers and 
      members of the Force deputed to the industrial undertaking, determine from 
      time to time, as the proportionate amount being payable by the industrial 
      undertaking towards the cost of maintaining the Headquarters and other 
      establishments of the Force.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>74</number>
Non-applicability of rules in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules shall 
      not apply to 1[***] members of the Force taken on 
      contract who shall be governed by the conditions of their 
      contract.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in these rules shall be deemed to 
      preclude the President—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   from making any 
      appointment to the Force which he may consider necessary, or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   from passing any 
      order or revising, whether on his own motion or otherwise, any order 
      passed under these rules by any subordinate authority.  
  




 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>75</number> Award of Director General’s Commendation 
      Disc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Director General’s Commendation 1[Disc] will be awarded to the CISF 
      personnel on the following grounds:—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   for conspicuous 
      achievement during operations;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   commendable work 
      in natural calamities;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   outstanding 
      achievement in sports for the country at international level;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   any innovation 
      which may bring significant improvement in the working of the Force;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>   clean and good 
      record of service for 15 years;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>   accident free 
      driving and good record for a continuous period of 20 years;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>   for being graded 
      “AX” in Army courses of 12 weeks duration or more;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>   for any 
      conspicuous efforts in processing of difficult cases;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>   for any 
      conspicuous work which may be considered of a commendable nature;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>   recovery of 
      property worth more than Rs. 20,000 in case of Constable to Head Constable 
      and more than Rs. 50,000 in case of Assistant Sub-Inspector to Inspectors 
      and more than Rs. 1,00,000 in case of 2[Gazetted Officers]. The property so recovered should not be of 
      unclaimed nature;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>   outstanding action 
      in dealing with terrorists/criminals which does not call for award of a 
      gallantry medal;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>   standing first in 
      Force level professional courses or standing 1st, 2nd or 3rd in an 
      Inter-Force level training course;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>   personnel who have 
      been promoted out of turn owing to some outstanding work can also be 
      considered.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Detailed instructions on this subject shall 
      be issued separately from time to time with the approval of Central 
      Government.  
  





 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>76</number> Ministerial staff.—Ministerial staff (Civilian) shall be governed 
      by the recruitment rules framed under article 309 of the Constitution of 
      India. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>77</number> Other conditions of service.—The members of the Force shall, in respect of 
      all matters regarding conditions of service for which no provision or 
      insufficient provisions have been made in these rules be governed by the 
      rules and orders for the time being applicable to officers holding 
      corresponding posts in the Central Government in respect of such 
      matters.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>78</number> Magisterial Powers.—For the purpose of inquiring into or trying 
      offences specified in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 18 of the Act and in 
      respect of all matters incidental to such inquiry or trial of such 
      offences, every officer holding rank of Commandant or equivalent as 
      mentioned in sub-clause (iv) of clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-rule (1) of rule 4, 
      shall exercise the powers of a Magistrate of the first class.  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>79</number> Judicial trials.—All trials in relation to any of the offences 
      specified in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 18 of the Act shall be held in 
      accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 
      of 1974).  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>80</number> Magistrate.—For the purpose of this Chapter ‘Magistrate’ 
      means the Commandant on whom the powers of a Magistrate have been 
      conferred under sub-section (2A) of section 18 of the Act. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>81</number> Language to be used in the proceedings 
      before Commandant.—Either 
      English or Hindi may be used by the Commandant while exercising the powers 
      of a Magistrate for inquiring into or trying any offence under sub-section 
      
<section><number>1</number> of section 18 of the Act.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>82</number> Magistrate not to try enrolled members of 
      the Force.—Where an enrolled 
      member of the Force is brought before the Magistrate and charged with an 
      offence referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 18 of the Act, for which 
      he is liable to be tried, such Magistrate shall not proceed to inquire 
      into or try the offence unless—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   he is of the 
      opinion for reasons to be recorded in writing that he should so proceed 
      without being moved thereto by the Unit Commander; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   he is moved 
      thereto by the Unit Commander. 
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>83</number> Magistrate to give notice.—Before proceeding under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 82, 
      the Magistrate shall give written notice to the Unit Commander and until 
      the expiry of a period of 21 days from the date of service of such notice 
      he shall not—  
 </section><section><number>a</number>   convict or acquit 
      the accused under section 252, section 255(1) and (2), section 256 or 
      section 257 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 or hear him in defence 
      under section 254 of the said Code; or  
 </section><section><number>b</number>   frame in writing a 
      charge against the accused under section 238 or section 246(1) of the said 
      Code; or  
 </section><section><number>c</number>   make an order 
      committing the accused for trial by the Court of Session under section 193 
      of the said Code; or  
 </section><section><number>d</number>   transfer the case 
      for enquiry or trial under section 192 of the said Code.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>84</number> Magistrate to be informed of the trial of 
      the accused.—
<section><number>1</number> When an 
      accused person has been delivered by the Magistrate, the Unit Commandar 
      shall, as soon as may, inform the Magistrate whether the accused has been 
      tried by him or any other official proceedings have been taken, ordered to 
      be taken against the accused or not.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the Magistrate has been informed under 
      sub-rule (1) that the accused has not been tried or other official 
      proceedings have not been taken or ordered to be taken against him, the 
      Magistrate shall report the circumstances to the Central Government for 
      taking appropriate steps to ensure that the accused person is dealt with 
      in accordance with law.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>85</number> Unit Commander to deliver the accused to the 
      Magistrate.—Where an enrolled 
      member of the Force has committed an offence which in the opinion of the 
      Unit Commander is to be tried by a Magistrate in accordance with the law 
      in force the Unit Commander shall after giving written notice to the 
      Magistrate concerned, deliver such person under proper escort to the 
      Magistrate.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>86</number> Manner of imprisonment.—Any enrolled member of the Force sentenced to 
      imprisonment under the Act shall be confined in the nearest jail:  
 Provided that if the sentence of imprisonment is 
      for one month or less or where the Unit Commander is satisfied that due to 
      the difficulty of transport and escort of the enrolled member of the force 
      sentenced to imprisonment to the nearest jail it is so desirable such 
      person shall be confirmed in the Quarter Guard of the Force.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>87</number> Force custody.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a Unit Commander is of the opinion 
      that any enrolled member of the Force has committed an offence and should 
      be tried by a Commandant who is vested with powers of Magistrate under 
      section 18(2A) it shall be lawful for such Commandant, with the prior 
      approval of the Deputy Inspector General to order the enrolled member of 
      the Force to be taken into Force custody and kept either in close arrest 
      or open arrest as he may deem fit from time to time depending on the 
      gravity of the charge and the attending circumstances:  
 Provided that no enrolled member of the Force 
      shall be detained in Force custody for a period of more than eight days 
      without a trial having been convened by a Commandant/Magistrate or without 
      a punishment having been awarded to him under section 8 of the Act.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> In each unit or group, there shall be one or 
      more places of confinement, as may be considered necessary by the Deputy 
      Inspector General, where arrested enrolled member of the Force shall be 
      confined. Such places shall be under the supervision of the Commandant, 
      Deputy Commandant or Assistant Commandant of the Unit, who shall be 
      responsible for their upkeep.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> If any enrolled member of the Force in Force 
      custody escapes or is rescued, the member of the Force from whose custody 
      he escaped or was rescued shall report the escape or rescue to the 
      officer-in-charge of the Police Station and may immediately pursue and 
      arrest such enrolled member in any place in India.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>88</number> Promulgation of sentence.—The sentence awarded by a Magistrate shall be 
      promulgated at the earliest opportunity after it has been pronounced and 
      shall subject to the provisions of the Act be carried out without delay 
      after promulgation.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>89</number> Transmission of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> The proceeding of every Magistrate without 
      delay be forwarded to the Deputy Inspector General within whose command 
      the trial was held for his information.  
 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>90</number> Appeals. </title>—Any person convicted on a trial 
held by a Magistrate under this Chapter may appeal to the Court of session. The 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 relating to appeals in that 
Code shall apply to appeals under this rule. </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>91</number> Technical consultancy services to the 
      industrial establishments in the private sector.—
<section><number>a</number> The Central Industrial Security Force may 
      provide technical consultancy services to industrial establishments in the 
      Central/State Government Departments, Public/Joint/Private sector, 
      autonomous bodies or any other institution approved by the Government 
      which may cover—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   Study of 
      industrial security and fire protection related problems and suggesting 
      appropriate solutions.   
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   Imparting of 
      knowledge and skills in the field of industrial security and fire 
      protection to the consulter (hereinafter called client) or his employees 
      through training programmes which may be conducted at Central Industrial 
      Security Force Training Institutions or at the client’s industrial 
      establishment(s) or at any other place as deemed appropriate by the 
      Director General.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   To conduct 
      training and certification courses in the fields of Industrial Safety, 
      Security and Fire Protection and charge prescribed fees for the same. The 
      fees for various such courses will be determined by the Director General.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>   Planning, 
      designing and effecting industrial security and fire protection schemes 
      measures, controls and systems for the client.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>   Providing feed 
      back after monitoring the functioning of suggested measures, controls and 
      systems.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>   Planning and 
      designing of communication network and preparation of related operating 
      instructions.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number>   Drafting 
      industrial security and fire protection related instructions, standing 
      orders and standing operating procedures.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number>   Preparing 
      disaster management and contingency plan and supervising or conducting 
      rehearsals of such plans.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number>   Conducting audits 
      in the field of industrial security, industrial safety or fire safety.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number>   Undertaking 
      research and development activities independency or in collaboration with 
      the clients and or other reputed agencies in the field of industrial 
      security, industrial safety and fire protection and related matters.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number> On receipt of request from the Managing 
      Director of any industrial establishment in the Private Sector or any 
      other person authorized by him, in this behalf, subject to any general 
      directions issued by the Central Government, the Director General, if 
      deems it appropriate, after examination of the request, may forward terms 
      and conditions of providing technical consultancy services to the Managing 
      Director or any other person authorized by him and may ask to remit 
      prescribed fee for technical consultancy services.  
 </section><section><number>c</number> On remittance of prescribed fees from the 
      Managing Director of an industrial establishment in the Private Sector the 
      Director General may nominate any officers of the Force or constitute a 
      team of officers for conducting technical study of the concerned 
      industrial establishment relating to any matter enumerated in sub-rules 
      (i) to (x) of rule 91(a).  
 </section><section><number>d</number> The Director General may, if deems it 
      appropriate and if the nature of consultancy sought so requires, also 
      associate any person(s) expert in the field, expertise whereof is not 
      available with the officers of the force, with the team constituted under 
      sub-rule (c).  
 </section><section><number>e</number> The expert person associated with the team 
      under provisions of sub-rule (d) shall be paid such amount as deemed 
      appropriate considering his/her expertise, contribution in terms of period 
      of time, services and state of availability of such experts in the given 
      circumstances.  
 </section><section><number>f</number> The officer so nominated or the team so 
      constituted by the Director General under sub-rule (c) shall prepare a 
      report after conducting such study as they may deem appropriate and submit 
      the same to the Director General. After due approval of Director General 
      of the Force, the consultancy report, so prepared will be communicated to 
      the Managing Director of concerned industrial establishment in the Private 
      Sector or to the person authorized by him in this behalf.  
 </section><section><number>g</number> The consultancy report so prepared for 
      client(s) establishment shall be the property of that establishment and 
      such reports shall not be used by any member of the Force or by such 
      person associated with the consultancy board for any personal benefit. 
      Such reports, however, can be used for academic purposes.  
 </section><section><number>h</number> Consultancy Fee.—The consultancy fees 
      shall be charged from the Industrial Establishments in the Private Sector 
      as prescribed from time to time.  
 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[<number>91A</number> 
Retirement/discharge of Gazetted Officers on the grounds of Medical unfitness. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> Where an officer not below the rank of a Deputy Inspector General 
considers that an officer of the Force is unfit to perform his duties because of 
his medical unfitness, the officer shall be brought before a Medical Board. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The Medical Board shall consist of such officers and shall 
be constituted in such manner as may, from time to time, be laid down by the 
Director General. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Medical Board considers the officer to be unfit 
for service, the Central Government shall communicate to the said officer the 
findings of the Medical Board and thereupon, within a period of fifteen days of 
such communication, the officer may make a representation against it to the 
Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may, on receiving the representation 
from the officer, refer the case to be reviewed by a fresh Medical Board 
constituted for the purpose and order the retirement of the said officer if the 
decision of the fresh Medical Board is adverse to him. 
  

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>91B</number> Retirement of enrolled member of 
the Force on the grounds of Medical unfitness. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Where a Commandant 
is satisfied that any enrolled member of the Force is unable to perform his 
duties by reason of medical unfitness, he may direct that the said enrolled 
member to be brought before a Medical Board. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Medical Board shall be constituted in such manner as may 
be determined by the Director General. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the said enrolled member is found by the Medical Board 
to be unfit for further service in the Force, the Inspector General, the Deputy 
Inspector General or as the case may be, the Commandant, may, if he agrees with 
the findings of the Medical Board order the retirement of enrolled member: 
 Provided that before the said enrolled member is so retired the 
findings of the Medical Board and the decision to retire him shall be 
communicated to him. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The enrolled member may, within a period of fifteen days 
from the date of receipt of such communication, make a representation to the 
officer next superior in rank to the one who ordered the retirement. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The said superior officer shall have the case referred to a 
Review Medical Board which shall be constituted in such manner as may be 
determined by the Director General. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The superior officer may, having regard to the findings of 
the Review Medical Board, pass such order as he may deem fit. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Where a representation has been made to a superior officer 
under sub-rule (4), an order passed under sub-rule (3) shall, not take effect 
till it is confirmed by such superior officer.] </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>92</number> Repeal and Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Industrial Security Force 
      Rules, 1969 are hereby repealed.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal anything done or 
      any action taken under the said rules, shall be deemed to have been done 
      or taken under the corresponding provisions of these rules.  
  
 
  </section></article><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

The Central 
      Industrial Security  
Force Rules, 2001
 

 
 

Appendix 
      “A”  
 

(See rule 21)  
 

FORM OF 
      AGREEMENT
 

To
 

The President of India  
 

 
 

In consideration of the President of India having agreed to appoint 
      me as   
 
 
 
 
 

*an 
            Inspector
 

*a 
            Sub-Inspector
 

*an Asstt. 
            Sub-Inspector
 

*a Head 
            Constable
 

*a 
            Constable
    in the Central 
            Industrial Security Force.
 

 
 

I, ........................................................., son 
      of.....................................……………, hereby agree and undertake 
      to—
 

(i)   serve in the 
      Central Industrial Security force for a period of not less than ten years 
      with effect from the date of my appointment in the force;  
 

(ii)   carry out 
      all duties entrusted to me and all lawful orders given to me by my 
      superiors in rank;  
 

(iii)   refund all 
      the cost of training imparted to me in the Force or sum equal to three 
      months’ pay and allowances whichever is more in the event of tendering my 
      resignation from the Force for reasons other than accepting a job 
      elsewhere for which cadre clearance has been given, during the period of 
      my initial training or thereafter during the period of ten years from the 
      date of joining Central Industrial Security Force; and  
 

(iv)   if, after 
      ten years I desire to resign, I will submit my request in writing and will 
      not withdraw from my duties until I am duly relieved.  
 

1[(v)   I understand and agree that my services can be 
      terminated by the appointing authority on my failure to pass the final 
      examination of initial training course or for suppression of any factual 
      information at the time of enrolment by issuing of notice of one month or 
      the tender of one month’s pay in lieu of such notice.]  
 

Note.—The terms “pay and allowance” used in clause (iii) above means the 
      usual pay and allowances received by him during the period of three months 
      immediately prior to the date of his resignation.  
 

 
 

* Strike out whichever is not applicable.
 

 
 

Witness
 
 
 
 Signature............................................. 
Designation.........................................  
Date..................................................... 
Place..................................................... 
 
 

Signature of the 
            employee..................................              
            Designation........................................................ 
            Date.....................................................................       
            Place..................................................................
 



 

 
 

ACCEPTED
 

 
 

For and on behalf of the President of 
      India.
 

 
 

----------------------
 

     1.   Ins. by 
      G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).  
 

----------------------
 

 
  </form><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

The Central 
      Industrial Security  
Force Rules, 2001
 

 
 

Appendix 
      “B”  
 

solemn affirmation of allegiance  
 

(See rule 30)  
 

 
 

“I, ................................, do solemnly affirm that I 
      will be faithful and bear true allegiance to India and to the Constitution 
      of India as by law established and that I will carry out the duties of my 
      office loyally, honestly and with impartiality”.
 

 
 

Signature.....................................................
 

 
 

Signature and designation of the  
Supervisory Officer (in whose 
       
presence the affirmation is made)
 

 
  </form><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

The Central 
      Industrial Security  
Force Rules, 2001
 

 
 

APPENDIX “C”
 

(See rule 17)  
 

Medical Examination Report  
 

(For Group C and Group D CISF Personnel)
 

Part 
      1  
 

 
 

Form to be used when a candidate is granted authority to present 
      himself for medical examination for fitness on appointment  
 

Name..................................................... Caste or 
      Race 
      ...............................................
 

Residence..................................................................................................................
 

Father’s name and 
      residence..........................................................................................
 

Date of Birth by Christian era as nearly as can be 
      ascertained.............................................
 

Exact height by measurement:  
 

Height......................................................  
 

Chest........................................................  
 

Weight.....................................................  
 

 
 

Signature of the 
      individual.....................................................
 

Station...............................................     
      Signature of Appointing 
Officer..........................
 

Date...................................................     
      Designation.........................................................
 

 
 

Part 
      2  
 

Candidate’s Statement and 
      Declaration  
 

The candidate must make the statement required below, prior to his 
      medical examination and must sign the declaration appended thereto. His 
      attention is specially directed to the warning contained in the note 
      below:  
 
 
 
 
 

1.  
            (a)   Have you ever had a small pox, intermittent or any 
            other fever, enlargement or suppuration of glands, spitting of blood 
            as heart disease, fainting, attack, rheumatism?  
 

     (b)   Any other disease or 
            accident requiring confinement to bed and prolonged medical or 
            surgical treatment.  
 

2.   When 
            you were last vaccinated?  
 

3.   Have 
            you or any other relative been affected with consumption, 
            sorofulous, gout asthma, fits, epilepsy or insanity?  
 

4.   Have 
            you suffered from any form of nervousness due to overwork or any 
            other cause?  
 

5.   Have 
            you been examined and declared unfit for Government service by 
            Medical Officer/Medical Board within the last three years. 
  
 

I declare that all the above answers are to the best of my belief 
      true and correct. I also solemnly affirm that I have not received 
      disability certificate/pension on account of any disease or other 
      condition.  
 

Candidate’s 
      Signature......................................................
 

Signed in my 
      presence.....................................................
 

 
 
 

Note.—The candidate 
      will be held responsible for accuracy of above statement, by willfully 
      suppressing any Information will incur the risk or losing the appointment 
      and if appointed of forfeiting all the superannuation allowances or 
      gratuity.  
 

 
 

PART 
      3
 

It is certified that I/We have examined 
      ................................. s/o 
      ........................................ a candidate for employment in the 
      Central Industrial Security Force and cannot discover that he has any 
      disease, constitutional aflication or bodily infirmity excluding knock 
      knee, flat feet 
      and.....................................................  
 

I/We consider/do not consider this as a disqualification for 
      employment in Central Industrial Security Force. His age according to his 
      own statement is......................................  
 

This may be filled up after examining the candidate for knock knee, 
      flat feet, bow legs, squint eyes, inability close the left eye, inability 
      to flax the fingers properly, varicose veins or any other obvious 
      disabilities which are likely to affect his functioning as a member of the 
      Central Industrial Security Force.  
 
 
 
 
 

1.  General 
            Development                Good             Fair              
            Poor
 

2.  Body 
            built                               Thin              Average        Obese
 

3.  Eyes                                      Right             Left
 

(A)  Any obvious 
            disease
 

(i)    
            External
 

(ii)   
            Media  
 

(B)   Visual 
            Acuity.....................................................
 

(i)    
            Distant  
 

(ii)   
            Near  
 

(C)  Colour 
            Vision  
 

4.  Ear, Nose &amp; 
            Throat                                      Right              
            Left
 

(a)   Any obvious 
            disease  
 

(b)   
            Hearing  
 

(c)    
            PNS  
 

5.  Conditions of 
            teeth.................. Dental 
            points..................
 

6.  Respiratory 
            System  
 

(i)    
            Appearance of Chest  
 

(ii)   Breathing 
            Rate  
 

(iii)  Any abnormality 
            on stethescopic examination.
 

7. (A)  Circulatory 
            System  
 

Heart: Any organic 
            lesion...............
 

Rate: 
            Standing..............
 

   After hopping 25 
            times................
 

   2 Minutes after 
            hopping..............
 

                
            (B) Blood pressure
 

Systolic....................
 

Disstolic....................
 

8. Abdomen  
 

(a)   
            Tenderness............................
 

(b)   
            Palpability  
 

(i)    
            Liver:  
 

(ii)   
            Spleen:  
 

(iii)  
            Kidneys:  
 

(c) 
            Haemorrhoids:  
 

(d) 
            Fissure/fistula:  
 

(e) 
            Hernia/Hydrocele:  
 

(f)  Any 
            other:  
 

9. Locomotor 
            System  
 

(i)    
            Condition of spine  
 

(ii)   Condition of 
            limb joints  
 

10. Nervous 
            System  
 

(i)    
            Evidence of nervous instability:
 

(ii)   
            Tremers:  
 

(iii)  History of Mental 
            Disease:  
 

11. Report of Radiological 
            examination of chest if done:
 

12. Is there anything in the 
            health of candidate likely to render him unfit for the efficient 
            discharge of his duties on the service for which he is a 
            candidate?
 

13. State the service for which the candidate has been 
            examined (GD/Follower/Trades/Communication/Medical 
            etc.).
 

14. Small pox vaccination 
            marks (Give number and site).
 

15. Mild defects noted, not 
            sufficient for rejection.
 

16. Out line reasons 
            declaring candidate unfit.
 

17. Unfit/Temporary 
            Unfit/Fit.  
 

 
  
 

Signature of the 
      candidate.....................................................
 

Place................................
 

Date................................
 

                                                                                 
      Signature of Medical Officer with date
 

                                                                                 
      1................................................................
 

                                                                                 
      2................................................................
 

 
  </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Omitted by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007, for 
clause (viii) (w.e.f. 3-8-2007). Clause (viii), before substitution, stood as 
under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 
    (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 
    462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
      9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   Omitted by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
      9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 462 (E), dated 23rd May, 2003 (w.e.f. 
      9-6-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 31st July, 2007 (w.e.f. 
3-8-2007).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>