<act><title>


The Mica Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1946</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called The Mica Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1946.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to 

1[the whole of 
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir].
 
 



</section></article> 
 


The Mica Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1946
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Imposition and 
collection of a cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
With effect from such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf, there shall be levied and collected, as a cess for the purposes of 
this Act, on all mica, in whatever state, exported from 

2[the territories 
to which this Act extends] a duty of customs at such rate, not exceeding six and 
one-quarter per centum ad valorem, as may from time to time be fixed by 
the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazatte:
 
Provided that until the 
1st day of April, 1947, the rate of duty so fixed shall not exceed two and 
one-half per centum ad valorem.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the last day of 
each month or as soon thereafter as may be convenient, there shall be paid to 
the credit of fund to be called the Mica Mines Labour Welfare Fund (hereinafter 
referred to as Fund) the proceeds of the duty of customs recovered during that 
month after deduction of the expenses, if any, for collection and recovery.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> The Mica Mines 
Labour Welfare Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Fund shall be applied by the Central Government to meet expenditure incurred 
in connection with measures in the opinion of the Central Government necessary 
or expedient to promote the welfare of labour employed in the Mica mining 
industry.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of sub-section (1), the Fund may be utilised to defray—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the cost of 
measures for the benefit of labour employed in the mica mining industry directed 
towards—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  the 
improvement of public health and sanitation, the prevention of diseases and the 
provision and improvement of medical facilities,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  the 
provision and improvement of water supplies and facilities for washing,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  the 
provision and improvement of educational facilities,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iv</number>  the 
improvement of standards of living, including housing and nutrition, the 
amelioration of social conditions and the provision of recreational duties,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>v</number>  the 
provision of transport to and from work,
 
 

1[(vi)  the 
provision of family welfare, including family planning, education and services;]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the grant to 
a 

2[State] 
Government, a local authority or the owner, agent or manager of a mica mine, of 
money in aid of any scheme approved by the Central Government for any purpose 
for which the Fund may be utilised;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the cost of 
administering the Fund, including the allowances, if any, of members of the 
Advisory Committees constituted under section 4, and the salaries and the 
allowances, if any, of officers appointed under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  any other 
expenditure which the Central Government may direct to be defrayed from the 
Fund.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
shall have power to decide whether any particular expenditure is or is not 
debitable to the Fund and its decision shall be final. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall publish annually in the Official Gazette report of the activities financed 
from the Fund together with an estimate of receipts and expenditure of the Fund 
and a statement of accounts.







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Advisory Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
the Central Government shall constitute 

1[as many Advisory 
Committees as it thinks fit but not exceeding one for each State], to advise the 
Central Government on any matters arising out of the administration of this Act 
or the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The members of the 
Advisory Committees shall be appointed by the Central Government, and shall be 
of such number and chosen in such manner as may be prescribed by rules made 
under this Act:
 
Provided that each 
Committee shall include an equal number of members representing mica mine owners 
and workmen employed in the mica-mining industry, and that at least one member 
of each committee shall be a woman, and at least one member of each Committee 
shall be a member of the Legislature of the 

2[State] concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairman of each 
Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all members of the Advisory 
Committees.







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Appointment and 
powers of officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may appoint Inspectors, Welfare Administrators and such 
other Officers as it thinks necessary to administer the Fund or to supervise or 
carry out the activities financed from the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Officer so 
appointed shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 
21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any Inspector or 
Welfare Administrator may—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  with such 
assistance, if any, as he thinks fit, enter at any reasonable time any place 
which he considers it necessary to enter for the purpose of supervising or 
carrying out the activities financed from the Fund, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  do within 
such place anything necessary for the proper discharge of his duties.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
to carry into effect the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the making of 
refunds, remissions and recoveries of the duty of customs imposed by sub-section 
(1) of section 2;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the 
composition  of the Advisory Committees constituted under section 4, the manner 
in which the members thereof shall be chosen, the term of office of such 
members, the allowances, if any, payable to them, and the manner in which the 
Advisory Committees shall conduct their business;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the 
conditions governing the grant of money from the fund under clause (b) of 
sub-section (2) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the form of 
the estimate and statement referred to in sub-section (4) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the 
conditions of service and the duties of all officers appointed under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  the 
furnishing by owners or agents or managers of mica mines of statistical or other 
information, and the punishment by fine of failure to comply with the 
requirements of any rule made under this clause. 
 

1[(3) Every rule, 
made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that  the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under this rule.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>