<act><title>


The Static and Mobile Pressure Vessels (Unfired) 
Rules, 19811</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Static and Mobile Pressure Vessels (Unfired) 
Rules, 1981.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Indian Explosives Act, 1884 (4 of 1884);
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  “approved” means a drawing, design, specification or code approved by 
the Chief Controller;
 
 

1[(bb)  
“bottling plant” means a premises where cylinders are filled with compressed 
gas;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  “Chief Controller” means the Chief Controller of Explosives;
 



2[(d)  
“competent person” means a person or an organisation recognised by the Chief 
Controller, for such gases and for such period as may be specified as competent 
for carrying out tests, examination, inspections and certification for 
installations and transport vehicles as stipulated in these rules, if such a 
person or organisation possesses the qualifications, experience and other 
requirements as set out in Appendix II to these rules and is recognised as per 
procedure laid down in rule 11A:
 
                   
Provided that the Chief Controller may relax the requirements of qualifications 
in respect of a competent person if such a person is exceptionally experienced 
and knowledgeable, but not the requirements in respect of the facilities at its 
command;]
 



3[(e)  
“compressed gas” means any permanent gas, liquefiable gas or gas dissolved in 
liquid or cryogenic liquid under pressure or gas mixture which in a closed 
pressure vessel exercises a pressure exceeding one atmosphere (gauge) at maximum 
working temperature and includes Hydrogen Fluoride. In case of vessel without 
insulation or refrigeration, the maximum working temperature shall be considered 
as 55oC;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  “Controller of Explosives” includes the Deputy Chief Controller of 
Explosives, Deputy Controller of Explosives and Assistant Controller of 
Explosives;
 </section><section>
        
<number>g</number>  “corrosion” means all forms of wastage, and includes oxidation, 
scaling, mechanical abrasion and erosion;
 
 

4[(gg)  
“critical temperature” means the temperature above which gas cannot be liquefied 
by the application of pressure alone;
 </section><section>
     <number>gga</number>  
“cryogenic liquid” means liquid form of permanent gas having normal boiling 
point below minus 165°C;
 </section><section>
     <number>ggb</number>  
“cryogenic pressure vessel” means a pressure vessel intended for storage or 
transportation of cryogenic liquid and includes cold converters, vacuum 
insulated evaporators, vacuum insulated storage or transport tanks and 
thermosyphon tanks;
 </section><section>
     <number>ggg</number>  
“cylinder” or “gas cylinder” means any closed metal container intended for 
storage and transport of compressed gas having the same meaning as assigned to 
it in clause (xvi) of rule 2 of the Gas Cylinder Rules, 1981;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>h</number>  “design” includes drawings, calculation, specifications, models, codes 
and all other details necessary for the complete description of the pressure 
vessel and its construction;
 </section><section>
         
<number>i</number>  “design pressure” means the pressure used in the design, calculations 
of a vessel for the purpose of determining the minimum thickness of the various 
component parts of the vessel;
 



5[(ii)  
“dispenser” means an equipment installed in liquefied petroleum gas dispensing 
station, meant for dispensing liquefied petroleum gas as automotive fuel to 
motor vehicles;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>j</number> “district authority” means—
 <subsection>
              
<number>i</number>  in towns having a Commissioner of Police, the Commissioner or a Deputy 
Commissioner of Police; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  in any other place, the District Magistrate;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>k</number>  “filling density” means the ratio of weight of liquefiable gas allowed 
in a pressure vessel to the weight of water that the vessel will hold at 15oC;
 
 

5[(kk)  “fill 
point” means the point of the inlet pipe connection of a vessel where hose is 
connected for filling the compressed gas into the vessel;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>l</number>  “flammability range” means the difference between the minimum and 
maximum percentage by volume of the gas in mixture with air that forms a 
flammable mixture at atmospheric pressure and ambient temperature;
 </section><section>
       
<number>m</number>  “flammable compressed gas” means gas 13 per cent. or less of which 
when mixed with air forms a flammable mixture or whose flammable range with air 
is greater than 12 per cent.;
 </section><section>
        
<number>n</number>  “Form” means the Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
        
<number>o</number>  “gas free” in relation to a pressure vessel means the concentration of 
flammable or toxic gases or both if such pressure vessel is within the safe 
limits specified for persons to enter and carry out hot work in such vessels;
 



6[(p)  
“Inspector” means a professional organisation recognised by the Chief Controller 
for certifying pressure vessels and their fittings after carrying out stagewise 
inspection during fabrication as stipulated in the rules so as to ensure that 
the pressure vessels are designed and constructed in accordance with IS: 2825 or 
any other code approved by the Chief Controller, if the constituent members of 
the organisation possesses the qualifications and experience and other 
requirements as set out in Appendix II to these rules and the recognition is 
granted as per procedure laid in rule 11A;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>q</number>  “installation” means any place which has been specially prepared for 
the storage of compressed gas in pressure vessels;
 </section><section>
         
<number>r</number>  “liquefiable gas” means any gas that may be liquefied by pressure 
above 0oC, 
but will be completely vapourised when in equilibrium with normal atmospheric 
pressure (760 mm Hg) at 30oC;
 
 

7[(ra)  
“liquefied petroleum gas” includes hydrocarbon gases in liquefied state at 
normal ambient temperature by the application of pressure, and conforming to the 
Indian Standard Specification No. IS: 4576;
 </section><section>
       
<number>rb</number>  “liquefied petroleum gas dispensing station” means a premises used 
for storing and dispensing liquefied petroleum gas as automotive fuel to the 
motor vehicles;
 </section><section>
       
<number>rc</number>  “motor vehicle” means a vehicle having the meaning assigned to it in 
sub‑section (28) of section 2 of the Motor Vehicle Act, 1988 (59 of 1988);
 </section><section>
       
<number>rd</number>  “petroleum service station” means a premises used for storage of 
petroleum for the purpose of fuelling motor vehicles, and licensed in Form XII 
of the Petroleum Rules, 1976;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>s</number>  “permanent gas” means a gas whose critical temperature is lower than 
10oC;
 



6[(t)  
”pressure vessel” means any closed metal container of whatever shape, intended 
for the storage and transport of any compressed gas which is subjected to 
internal pressure and whose water capacity exceeds one thousand litres and 
includes interconnecting parts and components thereof upto the first point of 
connection to the connected piping and fittings, but does not include containers 
wherein steam or other vapour is or is intended to be generated or water or 
other liquid is or is intended to be heated by the application of fire or the 
products of combustion or by electrical means, heat exchangers, evaporators, air 
receivers, steam type digestors, steam type steri­lizers, autoclaves, reactors, 
calorifiers, pressure piping components, such as, separators or strainers and 
vessels containing a liquid under a blanket of compressed inert gas;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>u</number>  “safety relief device” means an automatic pressure relieving device 
actuated by the pressure upstream of the valve and characterised by fully opened 
pop action, intended to prevent the rupture of a pressure vessel under certain 
conditions of exposure;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  “source of ignition” means naked lights, fires, exposed incandescent 
materials, electric welding arcs, lamps other than those specially approved for 
using flammable atmosphere, or a spark or flame produced by any means;
 
 

8[(vv)  “tank 
truck loading or unloading gantry” or “hard stand” means the position of parking 
of tank truck or mobile pressure vessel for loading or unloading of compressed 
gas into or from it;]
 </section><section>
       
<number>w</number>  “transport” means the transport of a pressure vessel filled with any 
compressed gas from one place to another but does not include movement of the 
vessel from one place to another in the same premises;
 </section><section>
        
<number>x</number>  “vehicle” means a mechanically propelled carriage designed to 
transport by land compressed gas in a pressure vessel mounted thereon, and shall 
not include a vessel forming the barrel of a rail tank wagon;
 </section><section>
        
<number>y</number>  “vessel” means a pressure vessel;
 </section><section>
        
<number>z</number>  “water capacity” means capacity in litres of the pressure vessel when 
completely filled with water at 15oC.
 
 










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>3</number> General 
exemptions.—Nothing 
in these rules shall apply to vessels which form part of a processing plant. For 
the purpose of this rule vessels forming part of a processing plant shall mean 
vessels in which a unit process or unit operation is carried out and vessels 
which contain, as a process requirement, a compressed gas received from and 
consumed in the same processing plant, provided that the water capacity of the 
vessel(s) shall be such that the gas stored therein at the maximum working 
pressure shall not exceed the requirement for feeding the consuming point(s) for 
a period not exceeding 16 hours at the designed flow rate.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>4</number> Restriction on filling, 
manufacture and import.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall fill any 
compressed gas in any vessel or transport any vessel filled with any compressed 
gas unless such vessel has been manufactured in accordance with a type or 
standard or code as specified under rule 12.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall manufacture 
any vessel approved under sub‑rule (1) without the prior approval of the Chief 
Controller.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any person seeking approval of 
the Chief Controller under sub‑rule (2) shall submit to him—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  the particulars specified in Appendix I to these rules; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred in the manner specified under 
rule 11.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> No person shall import any 
vessel without the prior approval of the Chief Controller.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any person seeking the 
approval of the Chief Controller under sub‑rule (4) shall submit to 
him—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  a test and inspection certificate of the vessel from the manufacturer 
or the inspecting agency of the country of origin;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  the design details of the vessel, its fittings and particulars of 
specifications of the materials used in construction thereof; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred in the manner specified under 
rule 11.]
  


</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Restriction on 
delivery and despatch.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall deliver or despatch any compressed gas filled in a vessel to any 
person other than the holder of a storage licence issued under these rules or to 
a port authority or a railway administration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No compressed gas 
delivered or despatched under sub‑rule (1) shall exceed the quantity which the 
person to whom it is delivered or despatched is authorised to store under the 
licence held by him.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Repair to pressure 
vessels.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
person shall carry out any repairs, additions or alterations to any vessel 
unless the proposed repairs, additions or alterations and their method of 
execution have been approved by the Chief Controller. Any such repairs, 
additions or alterations approved by the Chief Controller shall be carried out 
in the manner and by practices acceptable under the design code referred to in 
rule 12:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to the replacement of any of the fitments of the vessel 
which does not involve any heating.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before any repairs, 
additions or alterations are carried out to any vessel, the same shall be 
completely emptied and purged with an inert gas.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Complete record of 
repairs, additions or alterations referred to in sub‑rule (1) shall be 
maintained and made available to the Chief Controller and his permission shall 
be obtained before recommissioning the vessel.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> </title><title>Purging of pressure vessels used for flammable gases.— </title>
<section><number>1</number> Before using any new vessel or before the refilling of any existing vessel which has been made gas-free, air contained therein shall be purged by an inert gas or by the gas for which the vessel is to be used. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the vessel is purged by means of a flammable gas, the flammable mixture so formed shall be vented from the vessel only after taking adequate precautions to prevent its ignition. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> </title><title>Prohibition of employment of children and intoxicated persons.— </title>No person under the age of eighteen years or who is in a state of intoxication shall be employed for the loading, unloading or transport of any vessel containing compressed gas, or in any premises licensed under these rules. 
</article> 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Prohibition of smoking, fires, 
lights etc.—No 
person shall smoke and no matches, fires, lights or articles or substance, 
capable of causing ignition of any flammable gas shall be allowed, at any time 
in proximity to a place where any compressed gas is stored, handled or 
transported in a vessel.</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>9A</number> Supervision 
and operation within the licensed premises.—The 
operation of the licensed premises shall be under the supervision of persons 
having knowledge of the equipments being used in the premises and who is/are 
trained in handling the compressed gas, and other operators shall be conversant 
with the hazards associated with the compressed gas and fire- fighting 
operations.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Special precautions 
against accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall commit or attempt to commit any act which may tend to cause a 
fire or explosion in or about any place where any compressed gas is stored, 
handled or transported in a vessel.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All empty vessels 
which had contained any flammable or toxic gases, shall, except when they are 
opened for the purposes of filling or cleaning, or for rendering them gas‑free, 
be kept securely closed until they have been cleaned or freed of the gas, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every person storing 
compressed gas in a vessel and every person in charge of, or engaged in the 
storage, handling and transport of such gas in vessels, shall at all times—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  comply with the provisions of these rules and the conditions of any 
licence issued thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  observe all precautions for the prevention of accident by fire or 
explosion; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  prevent any person from committing any act referred in sub‑rule (1).
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>11</number> Procedure for 
payment of fees.—All 
fees payable under these rules shall be paid through crossed demand draft on any 
nationalised bank in favour of the Chief Controller of Explosives, Nagpur and in 
case when the amount payable does not exceed Rs. 100, the payment may be made by 
cash, money-order, postal order or cheque drawn on a local bank.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>11A</number> Procedure 
for grant and revocation of recognition to competent person and Inspector.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Anybody intending to be recognised as competent person or Inspector shall submit 
to the Chief Controller an application in the form prescribed in Appendix III. 
Every application shall be accompanied by scrutiny fees of Rs. 500 for 
application for competent person and Rs. 1000 for application for Inspector. The 
Chief Controller shall register such application and within a period of sixty 
days of the date of receipt of the application, either after having satisfied 
himself with regard to competence and professional ethics recognise the 
applicant as a competent person or an Inspector, as the case may be, or reject 
the application specifying the reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The Chief Controller 
may after giving an opportunity to the Inspector or competent person of being 
heard revoke the recognition—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  if he has reason to believe that an Inspector or competent person has 
violated any condition stipulated in the letter of recognition or has carried 
out a test, examination, and inspection or has acted in a manner inconsistent 
with the intent or the purpose of these rules; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  for any other reason to be recorded in writing.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Design code.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Vessels shall be designed, constructed and tested in accordance with the Indian 
Standard 2825, as amended from time to time, or such other standard or code 
approved by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A test and inspection 
certificate issued by the manufacturer of the vessel duly countersigned by an 
Inspector that the vessel meets with the requirements of the standard or code 
referred to in sub‑rule (1) shall be furnished to the Chief Controller.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Design pressure.—The 
design pressure of a vessel shall not be less than—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  the vapour pressure of the gas in the vessel at 55oC, 
if the vessel is meant for the storage of liquefiable gases:
 
                   
Provided that if the vessel is insulated, the vapour pressure of the gas in the 
vessel shall correspond to the maximum temperature that is likely to be attained 
by the gas in the vessel;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the developed pressure of the gas in the vessel at 55oC, 
if the vessel is meant for the storage of a permanent gas;
 



1[(c)  the 
maximum allowable service pressure with additional allowances for vacuum and 
static head or surge due to acceleration or deceleration, as the case may be, in 
respect of the cryogenic liquid proposed to be stored or transported.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>14</number> Design of vessels for gases at 
low temperature.—
<section><number>1</number> Refrigerated 
vessels,—
 <subsection>         
<number>i</number>  vessels used for storage of refrigerated gases shall be designed in 
accordance with low temperature requirements under the Design Code referred to 
in sub‑rule (1) of rule 12;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  the capacity of the refrigeration system shall be adequate to 
maintain the gas in the vessel at a temperature so that its vapour pressure does 
not exceed the design pressure of the vessel and shall also remain below the 
pressure‑setting of the relief valve on the vessel.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Insulated vessels,—
 <subsection>         
<number>i</number>  the shell of the vessel and its manhole nozzle shall be insulated with 
a material approved by the Chief Controller. The entire insulation shall be 
covered with a metal jacket of a thickness not less than 3 mm. nominal and 
flushed around all openings so as to be weather‑tight;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  the insulation shall be of sufficient thickness so that the thermal 
conductance at 15oC (expressed in calories or sq. 
cm. per hour per degree centigrade temperature differential) does not exceed the 
limit prescribed by the Chief Controller.
 1[(3) “Cryogenic pressure 
vessels”—
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>i</number>  the design service temperature of the cryogenic pressure vessels shall 
not be warmer than the normal boiling point of the cryogenic liquid;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  the materials of construction of the inner vessel, its piping and 
fittings shall be suitable for the service temperature and compatible for the 
specific cryogenic liquid;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>iii</number>  the outer vessel shall be made of steel not less than 3 mm nominal 
thickness or of aluminium not less than 4 mm nominal thickness and shall have 
required structural strength and capable for supporting the inner vessel 
together with cryogenic liquid, insulation and other fittings. The outer vessel 
of vacuum insulated cryogenic tanks shall be designed for a minimum collapsible 
pressure of one atmosphere (gauge). The suitable protecting coating shall be 
provided on the outer vessel to avoid corrosion. The outer vessel shall also be 
provided with suitable lifting arrangement and supports for installation or 
mounting;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>iv</number>  the inner-supports between the inner vessel and the outer vessel 
shall be of non‑inflammable materials and capable of supporting the inner vessel 
together with the maximum allowable cryogenic liquid. The supports shall be able 
to withstand expansion or contraction within the operating temperature range. 
Cryogenic pressure vessels meant for transport purpose, shall be able to 
withstand combined loading of vertical down of two, vertical upward of one and a 
half, longitudinal of one and a half and lateral of one and a half times the 
weight of the vessel with attachment and the full load of cryogenic liquid. The 
factor of safety of the supports shall be as per the design code;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>v</number>  the air in the annular space between the inner and outer vessel shall 
be evacuated and the space shall be filled with suitable insulating material 
compatible with the particular cryogenic liquid.]
  


</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Filling capacity 
and filling pressure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The maximum quantity of liquefiable gas filled into any vessel shall be limited 
to the filling density of the gas and shall be such that the vessel shall not be 
liquid‑full due to expansion of the contents with rise of the temperature to 55oC. 
If vessel is uninsulated, or to the highest temperature which the contents are 
likely to reach in service, if the vessel is refrigerated or insulated. This 
requirement shall be applicable irrespective of the ambient temperature of the 
product at the time of filling.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No vessel shall be 
filled with any permanent gas in excess of its design pressure.
 

1[(3) The water 
capacity of the cryogenic pressure vessel shall be rated in terms of gross water 
capacity and the usable water capacity in litres at 15°C. The usable water 
capacity shall not exceed 95% of the gross water capacity. An overflow pipe 
shall be provided at the maximum usable capacity level as a safeguard against 
filling the vessel beyond the maximum usable capacity.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Markings on 
pressure vessels.—Every 
vessel shall have a metal plate permanently fixed to it showing the following 
particulars which shall be visible from the ground level, namely:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number> manufacturer’s name and identification marks;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number> the standard or code to which the vessel is constructed; 
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number> official stamp of the Inspector;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number> design pressure in Kg/cm2;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number> date of initial hydrostatic test and the subsequent test; 
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number> hydrostatic test pressure in Kg/cm2;

 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number> water capacity in litres;
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number> gas capacity, if filled with liquefiable gas; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number>  name or chemical symbol of the gas for which the vessel is to be 
used.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Painting of 
vessels.—Vessels 
shall be adequately painted externally to prevent corrosion and shall have a 
reflecting surface.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Fittings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
General:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  Fittings.—Each vessel shall be provided with each of the 
following fittings all of which should be suitable for use with the gas at 
pressures not less than the design pressure of the vessel to which they are 
fitted and for temperatures appropriate to the characteristics of the gas and 
operating conditions, namely:—
 
              
—  pressure relief valve connected to the vapour space;
 
              
—  drains;
 
              
—  contents gauge or maximum level indicator;
 
              
—  pressure gauge connected to the vapour space;
 
              
—  means of measuring the temperature of the contents of the vessel.
 



1[(ii)  
Vessel connections.—Connections of vessels shall be designed and attached to 
the vessel in accordance with the design code specified under rule 12. All 
static vessels for storage of corrosive, flammable or toxic gas in liquefied 
state shall not have more than one pipe connection at the bottom for inlet or 
outlet, apart from the drainage. The drainage pipe, if provided, shall be 
extended beyond the shadow of the vessel and provided with two shut‑off valves. 
No drainage pipe shall be provided direct from spherical vessel. The bottom 
inlet or outlet pipe for spherical vessel shall be integrally welded to the 
vessel and extended upto three metres beyond the shadow of the vessel, at the 
end of which, combination of manual and remote operated valve shall be 
provided.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Pressure relief:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  every vessel shall be provided with two or more pressure relieving 
devices in accordance with the provisions of the design code referred to in rule 
12;
 



2[(ia)  for 
cryogenic pressure vessels, the outer vessel shall be provided with a vacuum 
valve and safety relief device (disc) to release internal pressure. The 
discharge area of such device shall be at least 0.34 sq mm/litre of water 
capacity of the inner vessel. The relief device shall function at a pressure not 
exceeding the internal design pressure of the outer vessel;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the relief valves shall be spring loaded and shall be set to 
discharge and reach full flow conditions as required by the design code referred 
to in rule 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  weight loaded relief valves shall not be permitted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  the relief valves be so designed that they cannot be inadvertently 
loaded beyond the set pressure;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  the design of the valves shall be such that the breakage of any part 
will not obstruct free discharge of the liquid under pressure.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  safety relief valves on any vessel shall be set to start to discharge 
at a pressure not in excess of 110 per cent. of the design pressure of the 
vessel and shall have a total relieving capacity sufficient to prevent the 
maximum pressure in the vessel of more than 120 per cent. of the design 
pressure;
 
 

3[(via)  in 
case of cryogenic pressure vessels, the safety relief devices shall be set to 
discharge in such a manner that at least one such device shall be set at a 
pressure not higher than the maximum allowable working pressure and the other 
device may be set at a pressure not higher than 110 per cent. of the maximum 
allowable working pressure;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vii</number>  each safety relief valve shall be plainly and permanently marked 
with the pressure in Kg/cm2 at 
which it is set to discharge, with the actual rate of discharge of the device in 
cubic meters per minute of the gas at 15oC 
and at atmospheric pressure, and with the manufacturer’s name. The rated 
discharge capacity of the device shall be determined at a pressure of 120 per 
cent. of the design pressure of the vessel;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>viii</number>  connections of safety relief devices shall be of sufficient size to 
pro­vide the required rate of discharge through the safety relief valves;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ix</number>  safety relief valves shall be so arranged that the possibility of 
tampering is minimised and if the pressure setting or adjustment is external, 
the safety relief valve shall be provided with suitable means of sealing 
adjustment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>x</number>  each safety relief valve shall be provided with shut‑off valve between 
it and the vessel. The arrangement of the shut‑off valve installed between the 
safety relief valve and the vessel shall be so designed as to afford full 
required capacity flow through at least one of the safety relief valves;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>xi</number>  safety relief valves shall have direct communication with the vapour 
space of the vessel;
 <subsubsection>
       
<number>xii</number>  for vessels other than those mounted on the vehicles of over 4500 
litres water capacity, relief valves shall be fitted with extended vent pipes 
adequately supported and having outlets at least 2 metres above the top of the 
vessel and at least 3.5 metres above the ground level and the vent pipes shall 
be fitted with loose‑fitting rain caps;
 
 

4[(xiii)  
relief valves shall be tested by a competent person for correct operation not 
less than once in a year and a record of such test shall be maintained. The test 
certificate shall be issued in the prescribed pro forma.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Shut‑off and emergency 
shut‑off valves:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  all liquid and vapour connections on vessels, except those for relief 
valves, plugged openings, and those where the connection is not greater than 1.4 
mm diameter opening, shall have shut‑off valves located as close to the vessels 
as practicable;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all liquid and vapour connections on vessels, except those for relief 
valves, and drainage connections of small diameter, shall have an emergency 
shut‑off valve, such as, an excess flow valve, an automatically operated valve 
or a remotely controlled valve. The emergency shut‑off valve shall be in 
addition to this shut-off valve referred to in clause (i), unless the emergency 
shut‑off valve is a remotely controlled valve which can be operated from a safe 
area and shall be of a type which shall not fail:
 
                                
5[Provided that the 
emergency shut‑off valve is not required in cases where the connection to a 
vessel is not greater than three millimetres in diameter for liquid and eight 
millimetres in diameter for vapour, or for vessels meant for storage of 
non‑corrosive, non‑flammable or non‑toxic gas;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  where the emergency shut‑off valve is of the excess flow type, its 
closing rate of flow shall be below the rate which is likely to result from a 
fracture of the line it is protecting, calculated under the most adverse weather 
conditions likely to be experienced. Excess‑flow valves shall have a rated flow 
capacity sufficiently above normal flow requirements to prevent valve chatter.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Liquid level gauging 
device:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  a vessel used for liquefiable gas or dissolved gas shall be equipped 
with a liquid level gauging device to afford ready determination of the amount 
of liquid in the vessel at any time;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all liquid level indicators shall be suitable for operation at the 
design pressure of the vessel;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  every vessel shall, in addition, be equipped with a fixed maximum 
level indicating device depending upon the liquefiable gas or dissolved gas 
filled in the vessel;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  gauging devices that require bleeding of the contents of the vessel, 
such as, a rotary tube, fixed tube and slip tube shall be designed in such a 
manner that the same cannot be completely withdrawn in normal gauging 
operations.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Pressure gauge—Every 
vessel shall be provided with at least one pressure gauge.
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Periodic testing of 
pressure vessel in service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All vessels shall be hydraulically tested by a competent person at a pressure 
marked on the vessel at intervals of not more than five years after the date of 
first test, provided that in the case of vessels, containing corrosive or toxic 
gases, the periodic test shall be done at an interval of two years. 
 

1[In case of 
vessels which are so designed, constructed or supported that they cannot be 
safely filled with water or liquids for hydraulic testing, or which are used in 
services where traces of water cannot be tolerated, Chief Controller may permit 
pneumatic testing along with non‑destructive tests instead of hydraulic testing, 
as per procedure laid down in vessel fabrication code; after satisfying himself 
about the adequacy of the safety precautions undertaken.]
 

2[(lA) Cryogenic 
pressure vessel and vessel for liquid Carbon dioxide shall be periodically 
tested with pneumatic pressure at 1.1 times of maximum allowable working 
pressure.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The competent person 
carrying out the test as required under sub‑rule (1) shall issue a certificate 
of test 

3[in prescribed 
proforma].
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Precautions to be 
observed in carrying out hydraulic test.—In 
carrying out the hydraulic test referred to in rule 19, the following 
precautions shall be observed, namely:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  before the test is carried out, each pressure vessel shall be 
thoroughly cleaned and examined externally, and as far as practicable, 
internally also for surface defects, corrosion and foreign matters. During the 
process of cleaning and removal of sludge, if any, all due precautions shall be 
taken against fire or explosion, if such sludge is of pyropheric nature or 
contains spontaneously combustible chemicals;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  as soon as the test is completed, the vessel shall be thoroughly 
dried internally and shall be clearly stamped with the marks and figures 
indicating the person by whom the test has been carried out and the date of test 
and a record shall be kept of all such tests;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  any vessel which fails to pass the hydraulic test or which for any 
other reason is found to be unsafe for use shall be destroyed or rendered 
unsuitable under intimation to the Chief Controller.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All vessels meant for storage of compressed gas shall be installed entirely 
above‑ground, that is to say, no part of the vessel shall be buried below the 
ground level.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Vessels and first 
stage regulating equipment shall be located in the open.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Vessels shall not be 
installed one above the other.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Vessels within a group 
shall be so located that there longitudinal axes are parallel to each other.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No vessel shall be 
located within the bonded area of petroleum or other flammable liquid storages.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Sufficient space shall 
be provided between two vessels to permit fire­-fighting operations.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Two or more vessels 
installed in batteries shall be so installed that the top surface of the vessels 
are on the same plane.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Vessels installed with 
their dished ends facing each other shall have screen walls in between them.
 

1[(9) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑rules (1) to (8) above, vessels for 
storage of liquefied petroleum gas can be placed underground or covered by earth 
in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be specified by a 
notifications by the Central Government.]
 

2[(10) Aboveground 
vessel for storage of corrosive, flammable or toxic gas in liquefied state shall 
be provided with enclosure wall all around the ground. The minimum distance 
between vessel and enclosure wall shall be the diameter of the vessel or five 
metres, whichever is less. The ground shall be graded to form a slope away from 
pumps, compressors or other equipments. The height of the enclosure wall shall 
be thirty centimetres on the upper side and gradually increasing to maximum 
sixty centimetres on the lower side, at the end of which a shallow sump for 
collection of the spilled liquid, if any, shall be provided. The minimum 
separation distance between the vessel and the sump shall be,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  diameter of the vessel, in case of vessels with water capacity not 
exceeding forty thousand litres,
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  fifteen metres, if the water capacity of the vessels exceeds forty 
thousand litres.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Foundations for 
pressure vessels.—
<section><number>1</number>
General.—The materials, principles, methods and details of design and 
construction of foundations and supports of vessels shall comply with approved 
specifications, standards or codes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Ground conditions.—A 
thorough knowledge of the ground condition shall be obtained by the person 
installing the vessel with particular reference to esta­blishing an allowable 
bearing pressure, total and differential settlements expected, risk of 
floatation and possible deterioration of original conditions.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Materials.—(i) 
The choice of materials for construction shall be determined by the ground 
conditions, loading and detailed design constructions.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The materials may be 
of—
 <subsubsection>
        
<number>a</number> brick‑work masonry; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>b</number> re‑inforced concrete; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>c</number> steel plate, steel pipe or structural steel.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Loading.—The 
greatest combined effect of static and imposed loadings shall be used for design 
as under:
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  static loading : weight of vessel and its contents;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  test loading if tested by water;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  wind loading;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  operational loading, such as, vibration or thermal (natural and 
operational). 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Settlement.—Any 
particular differential settlement shall be limited to prevent excessive stress 
in the conducted pipe work and vessel shell.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Vessel supports.—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number> the design of supports for vessels shall follow the standard or code to 
which the vessel is constructed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number> the spacing of vessel support shall be decided after close consi­deration 
of vessel‑shell stressing and transmission of the loadings to the ground;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number> the design of supports for vessels shall provide flexibility to allow for 
movement of the vessel as a result of pressure and thermal expansion;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number> the vessel shall be securely anchored or weighed or provided with adequate 
pier height to avoid floatation due to flood waters;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number> in case of structural steel supports such supports, excluding vessel saddles 
or supporting feet 45 cm or less in height, shall be encased in fire‑resisting 
materials of adequate thickness.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Fencing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The area where vessels pumping equipment, loading and unloading facilities and 
direct fired vaporisers are provided shall be enclosed by an industrial type 
fence at least 2 metres high along the perimeter of the safety zone.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every fence shall have 
at least two means of exits and the gates of such exits shall open outwards and 
shall not be self‑locking.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Cleanliness.—An 
area of three metres around the vessel shall be kept free from readily ignitable 
materials, such as, weeds and long dry grass.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Earthing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All vessels used for storage of flammable liquefiable gases shall be 
electrically connected with the earth in an efficient manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Pipelines conveying 
flammable liquids shall be adequately prepared for electrical continuity and 
connected with the earth in an efficient manner.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> No smoking.—A 
permanent notice with letters at least 5 cms. in height prohibiting smoking and 
naked lights shall be fixed to the fence surrounding the area where flammable or 
oxidising gases are stored and the notice shall be visible from outside.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Fire protection.—All 
vessels used for the storage of flammable compressed gases shall be protected 
against the hazards as under:
 



1[
<section><number>i</number>  
provision shall be made for an adequate supply of water and fire protection in 
the storage area in accordance with the provision of the rules and the 
regulation applicable in that area. The application of water may be by hydrants, 
hoses and mobile equipments, fixed monitors or by fixed spray systems which may 
be automatic. Control of water flow should be possible from outside any danger 
area. The fire water system shall be designed with medium velocity sprinklers 
for above-ground storage vessels, filling sheds, loading or unloading area, and 
pump sheds having minimum spray density of ten litres per minute per square 
metre for the single largest risk area and with additional requirements for 
hydrant points. In plants referred to in Table 4A of rule 22, the quantity of 
water available shall be sufficient for four hours of fire-fighting, and in 
plants referred to in Table 4B of rule 22, the same shall be for two hours of 
fire-fighting. For other installations not covered under Tables 4A and 4B, the 
fire water storage shall be as approved by the Chief Controller.]
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  hydrants, where provided, shall be readily accessible at all times 
and so spaced as to provide for the protection of all vessels;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  sufficient length of fire hose shall be provided and be readily 
available. The outer of each hose line shall be equipped with a combination jet 
and fog nozzle. The hoses should be maintained well and periodically inspected;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  mobile equipment, fixed monitors or fixed spray systems shall be 
designed to discharge water at a rate sufficient to maintain an adequate film of 
water over the surface of the vessel and supports under fire conditions;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  consideration shall be given to the provision of mobile or fixed water 
spray systems giving suitable and effective protection for vehicle loading and 
unloading areas;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  at least two dry chemical powder type fire extinguishers of 9 kg. 
capacity each shall be installed at each point of access to the installations.
 
       
2[(vii)  in 
liquefied petroleum gas dispensing station for fuelling motor vehicles, having 
only under-ground or earth covered (mounded) liquefied petroleum gas storage 
vessels, two numbers seventy kilograms dry chemical type fire extinguishers 
shall be provided. In dispensing stations having above-ground liquefied 
petroleum gas storage vessels, hydrants with minimum water pressure of seven 
kilograms per square centimetre shall be provided at convenient positions for 
alround coverages of storage vessels and handling area, and water sprinklers 
with spray density of ten litres per minutes per square metre shall be provided. 
The fire water pump shall be preferably diesel engine driven with capacity to 
deliver water at the rate and pressure specified above. The minimum fire water 
storage at the premises shall be that needed for fighting fire atleast for one 
hour.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Loading and 
unloading facilities.—
<section><number>1</number>
Pumps:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  pumps may be centrifugal or positive displacement pumps;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  design materials and construction of pumps shall be suitable for the 
type of gas to be handled and they shall be designed for the maximum outlet 
pressure to which they will be subjected to in operations;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  positive displacement pumps shall have a by‑pass valve or other 
suitable protection against over pressure.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Compressors:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the design, material and construction of compressors shall be suitable 
for the type of gas which they are to handle and they shall be designed for the 
maximum outlet pressure to which they will be subjected to in operation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  compressors other than multi‑stage compressors shall take suction 
from the vapour space of the vessels being filled.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Transfer systems:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  transfer systems shall be so designed that the risk of a gas of a 
higher vapour pressure being transferred to equipment designed for gas of a 
lower vapour pressure is minimised;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  there shall be positive means of rapidly shutting-off flow, located 
at a safe distance from the vessel which is being filled or emptied;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  automatic alarm device to indicate the approach to maximum 
permissible height of automatic shut‑off valves shall be used to prevent over 
filling.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Hoses:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the hoses for liquid transfer shall be designed to withstand not less 
than four times the maximum operating pressure they will carry in service;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the hoses shall be mechanically and electrically continuous.
 

1[(5) In the 
tank‑truck loading or unloading gantry, number of bays for parking tank‑trucks 
shall not exceed eight, and number of such gantries in a premises shall not 
exceed two.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Rail tank wagon 
loading or unloading shall be restricted to a maximum of half a rake (six 
hundred tonnes). If full rake handling is required, it shall be placed in two 
separate gantries with fifty metres, distance in between them.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All valves on the 
vessel and pipelines in the premises shall be permanently marked in a manner 
clearly indicating the direction of opening and closing.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Transfer 
operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before transfer of gas—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  every vehicle shall be carefully examined at the installation to 
ensure that it complies in all respects with the requirements of these rules and 
shall be completely emptied before it is passed for filling;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a visual check shall be made of the surroundings for unusual or 
dangerous situations before any filling or discharging procedure is commenced;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  warning notices as necessary shall be displayed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  the receiving vessel shall be checked to ensure that it has 
sufficient ullage to receive quantity of gas being transferred to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  the inter‑connecting system, that is pipework‑fittings, valves or 
hoses, shall be checked to ensure that it is in safe working condition and that 
only valves and other fittings required in the transfer operations or any other 
operations proceeding simultaneously, are open.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> During transfer the 
receiving vessel shall be checked to ensure that it is not being filled above 
its safe filling capacity or beyond its design pressure.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On completion of 
transfer before the vehicle is allowed to leave the licensed premises it shall 
be weighed over weigh‑bridge to ascertain the quantity of the compressed gas 
filled therein, if the vehicle is filled with a liquefiable gas.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When filling the 
vessels on vehicles with compressed gas, the following procedure shall be 
complied with in addition to the other requirements, namely:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the place where the vehicle is parked shall be properly levelled;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the vehicle shall be prevented from accidental movement during the 
transfer operation, the parking brake of the vehicle shall be on and the engine 
shall remain stopped, except when it is necessary to drive the pump. Where 
necessary wheel chock blocks shall be used;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  any driving units or electrical equipment not required and not 
speci­fically designed for the transfer operation shall be stopped or isolated;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  the vessel mounted on a vehicle shall be electrically bonded to the 
fixed installation before any flammable liquefied gas transfer operation is 
carried out;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  before a vehicle is moved, the electrical and the liquid and vapour 
connections shall be disconnected, care being exercised to avoid spillage. Where 
wheel chock blocks have been used they shall be removed. The vehicle shall be 
checked to ensure that it is in safe working order and the surrounding areas 
checked to ensure that any liquefied flammable gas that may have leaked or has 
to be vented has safely dispersed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> For keeping attention 
during operations—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  a competent person shall remain in attendance during all the 
operations connected with the transfer and ensure that all the requirements of 
these rules are complied with;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  if it is necessary to discontinue a vehicle loading operation 
tempo­rarily, the loading hose, shall be disconnected from the vehicle for the 
period of such discontinuance.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The person incharge of 
transfer operations shall ensure that transfer operations are stopped in the 
event of—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  any leakage;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a fire occurring in the vicinity;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  a severe electrical storm occurring in the vicinity in the case of 
an operation which involves venting of flammable gas.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>30A</number> Dispenser 
for liquefied petroleum gas dispensing station.—The 
dispenser and connected fittings used for dispensing liquefied petroleum gas in 
motor vehicles provided in the liquefied petroleum gas dispensing station shall 
be designed, constructed, tested and maintained in accordance with the 
requirements laid down in Schedule II of these rules and be of a type approved 
in writing by the Chief Controller.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>30B</number> Special 
provisions for filling fuel tanks of motor vehicles and unloading of tank‑truck 
in liquefied petroleum gas dispensing station.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Liquefied petroleum gas shall not be filled in fuel tank of motor vehicle while 
the engine of the vehicle is running.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> During the period of 
unloading of liquefied petroleum gas from tank- ­truck to the storage vessels, 
operation of dispensing liquefied petroleum gas to motor vehicles shall not be 
carried out.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Electrical 
apparatus and installations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No electrical wire shall pass over any storage vessel.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All electrical wires 
installed within the safety zone or any storage vessel for the storage of 
flammable compressed gases shall consist of insulated cables of approved type. 
The cables shall be mechanically continuous throughout and effectively earthed 
away from the vessels.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For pumps rooms used 
for pumping flammable compressed gases—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  all electrical metres, distribution boards, switches, fuses, plugs and 
sockets shall be of flame-proof construction complying with the requirements of 
IS: 2148: 1968 and the frames shall be effectively earthed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all electrical fixed lamps shall be enclosed in a well glass 
flame-proof fitting conforming to IS: 2206 (Part I) 1962.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> All electrical 
portable hand lamps shall be of a type approved by the Chief Controller.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>31A</number> 
Classification of hazardous area for flammable gases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A hazardous area for flammable gases shall be deemed to be—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  a division ‘0’ area, if inflammable gases of vapours are expected to 
be continuously present in the area;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  a division ‘1’ area, if inflammable gases or vapours are likely to be 
present in the area under normal operating conditions; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  a division ‘2’ area, if inflammable gases or vapours are likely to be 
present in the area only under abnormal operating conditions or failure or 
rupture of an equipment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
as to whether hazardous area is a division ‘0’ area or a division ‘1’ area or a 
division ‘2’ area, the decision thereon of the Chief Controller shall be final.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>31B</number> Extent of 
hazardous area.—The 
extent of hazardous area for liquefied petroleum gas dispenser shall be as 
under:
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  Entire space within the dispenser enclosure cabinet and forty-six 
centimetres horizontally from the exterior of enclosure cabinet and upto an 
elevation of one hundred and twenty-two centimetres above dispenser base and the 
entire pit or open space beneath the dispenser shall be division ‘1’;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  Upto forty-six centimetres vertically, above the surrounding ground 
level and horizontally beyond forty-six centimetres upto six metres on all sides 
of the dispenser enclosure cabinet shall be division ‘2’.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Lighting of storage 
and opening areas.—Operations 
shall not be carried out during the night unless adequate artificial lightings 
of approved type are available and used.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Certificate of 
safety.—A 
certificate of safety in the proforma 

1[prescribed by the 
Chief Controller] and signed by a competent person shall be furnished to the 
licensing authority before any vessel is used for the storage of any compressed 
gas or whenever any addition or alteration to the installations or foundations 
for the vessel is carried out.
 

2[***]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Application.—The 
rules in this Chapter shall apply to the transport of compressed gas by 
vehicles.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Vehicles for 
transport of compressed gas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every vehicle for the transport of compressed gas shall be of a type approved, 
in writing, by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where approval is 
sought to a vehicle under sub‑rule (1) or to any of its special safety fittings, 
12 numbers of detailed drawing drawn to scale and a scouting fee of rupees fifty 
shall be forwarded to the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Chief 
Controller, after receipt of the drawing under sub‑rule (2) and after making 
such further inquiries as he deems necessary, is satisfied that the vehicle or 
the special safety fittings, as the case may be, meets with the requirements 
laid down in these rules, he shall approve the drawing and return to the 
applicant one copy thereof duly endorsed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Design.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every vessel used for the transportation of compressed gas shall be constructed 
and tested in accordance with the requirements of rule 12 and shall meet the 
requirements of sub‑rules (2), (3), (4) and (5) of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The design stress 
shall include an allowance to enable the vessel to withstand shocks normally 
encountered by movements on road, such as, acceleration and declaration for a 
minimum of 3g. When the vessel is self‑supporting, the vessel design shall 
provide for carrying the additional stresses normally carried by the chassis 
frame. Provision shall be made for distributing the localised stresses arising 
from attachments to the vessels.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Mounting of vessels on 
the chassis or underframe shall be done in such a manner as to keep the 
vibrations to the minimum.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All attachments to the 
vessel shall be protected against accidental damage which may result from 
collision, overturning or other operational cause.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All vessels shall be 
designed to withstand the most severe combined stresses to which they may be 
subjected to by the pressure of the gas, the pumping pressures and shock loading 
caused by transport conditions.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Protection of 
valves and accessories.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All valves and accessories shall be safeguarded against accidental damage or 
interference.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Valves and accessories 
shall be mounted and protected in such a way that risk of accidental rupture of 
the branch to which the valve or accessory is connected is minimised.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Valves or accessories 
situated at the rear of a vehicle shall be protected by the rear cross member of 
the frame of the vehicle against, damage and shall comply with sub‑rule (2).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Equipment.—
<section><number>1</number>
Piping, fittings, pumps and meters:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  all pipings, fittings, pumps and meters permanently mounted on the 
vehicle shall be designed to withstand the most severe combined stresses imposed 
by the following, namely:—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>a</number>  the maximum designed pressure of the vessel;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>b</number>  the super imposed pumping pressure of the shock loading caused by road 
movements;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the materials used for vessel equipment shall be sufficient ductile 
to withstand rough usage and accidental damage. Brittle materials, such as, cast 
iron shall not be used.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Protection of 
piping and equipment:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  all piping and equipment shall be adequately protected to minimise 
accidental damage, which may be caused by rough usage, collision or 
over‑turning;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  any equipment or section of piping in which liquid may be trapped 
shall be protected against excessive pressure caused by thermal expansion of the 
contents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Marking of 
connections.—All connections on the vehicle which require manipulation by 
the operator of the vehicle should be clearly marked to prevent incorrect 
operation. The form of this marking should correspond with the operating 
procedure laid down for the vehicle.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Vehicle design 
considerations.—
<section><number>1</number>
General.—The vessel shall be securely attached to the chassis of the 
vehicle in such a manner as to take care of the forward movement of the vessel 
due to sudden deacceleration of the vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Design safety 
requirements—Mechanical:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the engine of the vehicle shall be of an internal combustion type;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  where the fuel system is gravity‑fed, a quick action cut‑off‑valve 
shall be fitted to the fuel feed pipe in an easily accessible and clearly marked 
position;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  the engine and exhaust system together with all electrical 
gene­rators, motors, batteries, switch-gears and fuses shall be efficiently 
screened from the vessel or the body of the vehicle by a fire‑resisting shield 
or by enclosure within an approved fire resisting compartment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  when the equipment referred to in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) are 
mounted forward of the back of the driving cab, the cab can be considered to act 
as an acceptable shield, provided the back, the roof and the floor of the cab, 
are of fire‑resisting construction for the full width of the cab, without any 
opening in the back or roof, and that the back extends downwards to the top of 
the chassis;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  when the cab construction, does not conform to the requirements 
mentioned above, a separate fire-resisting shield should be installed extending 
upwards without any openings from the top of the chassis to the top of the 
vessels;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  in any case, where windows are provided in the shield, they should be 
fitted in fire‑resisting framing with wired glass or other heat­-resisting 
material and shall not be capable of being opened;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vii</number>  when the equipment referred to in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) are 
mounted to the rear of the back of the cab, it shall be contained wholly within 
an approved fire‑resisting compartment;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>viii</number>  in any case where the fuel used to propel a vehicle gives off a 
flammable vapour at a temperature less than 65oC. 
the fuel tank shall not be behind the shield unless the following requirements 
are complied with, namely:—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>a</number>  the fuel tank is protected from blows by stout steel guards or by the 
frames of the vehicles;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>b</number>  the fill pipe of the fuel tank of the vehicle is provided with a cover 
having locking arrangement;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>c</number>  the fuel feed apparatus placed in front of the fire‑resisting shield 
is used to lift the contents of the fuel tank;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ix</number>  where a transfer pump is driven by the engine of the vehicle 
provision shall be made to stop the engine from outside the cab.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Design safety 
requirements—Electrical:
 
The following requirements 
shall be complied with in connection with the electrical and anti-static 
properties of the vehicle, namely:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  The electrical system shall have—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>a</number>  the battery in an easily accessible position;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>b</number>  a readily accessible cut‑off switch of not less than 300 Amps rating;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>c</number>  wiring so fixed and protected as to minimise accidental damage or 
undue wear.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  The vessel shall be electrically continuous with the chassis.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  The vehicle shall be provided with a bonding point or bonding cable.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  Tyres shall be of the “anti‑static” type.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Design safety 
requirements—General:
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> There shall be a clear 
space of at least 15 cm. between the back of the cab and the front of the 
vessel.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> The rear of the 
vessel shall be protected by a robust steel bumper and this bumper shall be—
 <subsubsection>
        
<number>a</number>  attached so that collision stresses will be transmitted to the frame 
work of the vehicle or, in the case of an articulated vehicle to the frame work 
carrying the wheels of the vessel;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>b</number>  situated at least 7.5 cm. to the rear of the rear most part of the 
vessel;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>c</number>  extend on each side of the vehicle to at least the maximum width of 
the vessel.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> The maximum weight 
of the liquefied gas for which the vehicle is designed should not exceed the 
difference in weight between the unladen weight of the vehicle and the maximum 
gross weight permitted for that class of vehicle under the appropriate transport 
regulations.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Marking of vehicle.—All 
vehicles shall be conspicuously marked on the vessel to show the product which 
is being carried.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Fire protection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Two serviceable fire extinguishers of suitable size and type shall be provided 
on each vehicle on each side and should be accessible from outside the cab.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person, while in, or 
attending any vehicle conveying flammable gas shall not smoke or use matches or 
lighters.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No fire, artificial 
light or article capable of causing fire or explosion shall be taken or carried 
on any vehicle carrying flammable gas.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Drivers shall be carefully selected and given appropriate training in driving 
and safe handling of the equipment and the compressed gas carried in the 
vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When loading or 
discharging of a vehicle takes place within the operator’s own premises, a 
competent person shall be present throughout the operations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When discharge is in 
progress, at a customer’s premises, the driver shall remain his vehicle in such 
a position as to be able to stop the discharge immediately in an emergency.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every vehicle shall be 
constantly attended to by at least one person who is familiar with the rules in 
this Chapter:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub‑rule shall apply to vehicle which are left in places previously 
approved for the purpose by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of an 
over-night stop away from home base, prior arrangements shall be made for the 
safe parking of the vehicle over-night. In an emergency, a driver may seek the 
co‑operation of the local police in finding suitable parking facilities for his 
vehicle.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Certificate of 
safety 

1[in prescribed 
proforma].—A 
certificate of safety 

1[in prescribed 
proforma] signed by a competent person shall be furnished to the licensing 
authority before any vehicle is used for the transportation of any compressed 
gas to the effect that the vehicle meets with the provisions of the rules in 
this Chapter.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Inspection and 
maintenance of vehicles.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[The licensee for 
any vehicle shall] ensure that it is at all times road-worthy, and that it is in 
a fit condition to fill, transport and discharge its load safely.
 

1[(2) An 
examination of the vehicle to check that the vehicle is maintained as per 
sub‑rule (1) shall be carried out every six months by a competent person and a 
certificate in the prescribed proforma shall be issued by him.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Licence for storage 
of compressed gas.—No 
person shall store any compressed gas in any vessel except under and in 
accordance with the conditions of a licence granted under these rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Prior approval of 
specification and place of vessels and premises proposed to be licensed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person desiring to obtain a licence to store any compressed gas in any 
vessel shall submit to the Chief Controller—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  specifications and plans drawn to scale in triplicate clearly 
indicating—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>a</number>  the manner in which the provisions prescribed in these rules shall be 
complied with;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>b</number>  the premises proposed to be licensed, the area of which shall be 
distinctly coloured or otherwise marked;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>c</number>  the surrounding area lying within 100 meters of the edge of all 
facilities which are proposed to be licensed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>d</number>  the position, capacity, materials of construction and ground and 
elevation views of all vessels, all valves and fittings, filling and discharge 
pumps and fire‑fighting facilities where provided and all other facilities 
forming part of the premises proposed to be licensed; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees one hundred paid in the manner specified in 
rule 11.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Chief 
Controller, after scrutiny of the specifications and plans and after making such 
inquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that compressed gas can be stored in the 
premises proposed to be licensed, he shall return to the applicant one copy each 
of all the specifications and plans signed by him conveying his sanction which 
may be subject to such conditions as he may specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>46A</number> No-objection 
Certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An applicant for a new licence other than a licence in Form IV, shall apply to 
the District Authority with two copies of site plan showing the location of the 
premises proposed to be license under these rules for a certificate to the 
effect that there is no objection to the applicant’s receiving a licence for 
storage of compressed gas in pressure vessel at the site proposed, and the 
District Authority shall, if he sees no objection, grant such certificate to the 
applicant who shall forward it to the Chief Controller with his application.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every certificate 
issued by the District Authority under sub‑rule (1) above shall be accompanied 
by a copy of the plan of the proposed site duly endorsed by him under his 
official seal.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Controller, 
may refer an application not accompanied by a certificate granted under sub‑rule 
(1) to the District Authority for his observation.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the District 
Authority, either on a reference being made to him or otherwise, intimates to 
the Chief Controller that any licence which has been applied for should not, in 
his opinion, be granted, such licence shall not be issued without the sanction 
of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub‑rules (1) to (4) above, all licences granted or 
renewed under the said rules prior to the date on which the above provisions 
come in force, shall be deemed to have been granted or renewed under these 
rules.]
 

2[(6) The 
provisions of this rule shall not apply to non‑flammable, non‑toxic compressed 
gases.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Licence for 
transport of compressed gas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No compressed gas filled in a vessel shall be transported by a vehicle except 
under and in accordance with the conditions for a licence granted under these 
rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to the transport of compressed gas filled in a vessel by a railway 
administration.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Grant of licence.—A 
licence prescribed under these rules shall be granted by the Chief Controller on 
payment of the fees specified in the 

1[Schedule I] 
attached to these rules.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>49</number> Application 
for licence.—A 
person intending to obtain a licence under these rules shall submit to the Chief 
Controller,—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number> an application,—
 <subsection>
             
<number>a</number>  in Form I, if the application is in respect of a licence to store 
compressed gas in pressure vessels;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>b</number>  in Form II, if the application is in respect of a licence to transport 
compressed gas in a pressure vessel by a vehicle;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>c</number>  in Form IA, if the application is in respect of a licence to store and 
dispense liquefied petroleum gas as automotive fuel;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  a certificate of safety under rule 33 or rule 43 as the case may be;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  a test and inspection certificate as required under sub‑rule (2) of 
rule 12;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  four copies of the drawings approved by the Chief Controller under 
rules 35 and 46;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  licence fee as specified in the Schedule I;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  No-Objection Certificate from the District Authority in respect of 
storage of compressed gas in pressure vessels along with the site- plan duly 
endorsed;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number>  copy of the Registration Certificate of the vehicle issued under 
Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) in respect of mobile pressure vessels for 
transport of compressed gas.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Period for which 
licences may by granted or renewed.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence, in Form III or Form V for the storage of compressed gas in pressure 
vessel, or in Form IV for the transport of the compressed gas in a pressure 
vessel by a vehicle, shall be granted or renewed subject to a maximum of three 
years and shall remain in force until the thirty-first day of March of the year 
upto which the same is granted or renewed.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub‑rule (1), the Chief Controller may, if he is satisfied 
that a licence is required for a specific work which is not likely to last up to 
the 31st day of March of the year up to which the licence is granted or renewed 
grant or renew a licence for such period as is necessary.
 

2[***]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Particulars of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall be subject to the conditions 
specified therein and shall contain all the particulars which are contained in 
the form specified under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> One copy of the plan 
or plans for the licensed premises, signed in token of approval by the Chief 
Controller, shall be attached to the licence which shall form part of such 
licence and an identical copy shall be filed for record in the office of the 
Chief Controller.
 

1[(3) Every 
licensed premises under these rules shall have prominently marked thereon the 
number of the licence held for it.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The emergency 
telephone numbers of local fire service, police and the principal marketing 
company or supplier of the compressed gas, and emergency instructions shall be 
conspicuously displayed in the licensed premises.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Power of licensing 
authority to alter conditions.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in rule 51, the Chief Controller may omit, alter or add to 
any of the conditions specified in the Form of a licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Prior approval 
necessary for alteration in the licensed premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No alteration shall be carried out in the licensed premises until the plan 
showing such alteration has been approved in writing by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person wishing to 
carry out any alteration in the licensed premises shall submit to the Chief 
Controller—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  three copies of a properly drawn plan of the licensed premises showing 
in distinct colour or colours the proposed alteration and the reasons therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees fifty paid in the manner specified in rule 
11.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Chief 
Controller, after scrutiny of the plan showing the proposed alteration and after 
making such enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that the proposed alteration 
may be carried out, he shall return to the licensee one copy of the plan signed 
by him and conveying his sanction subject to such condition or conditions as he 
may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The holder of a 
licence shall apply to the Chief Controller for the amendment of the licence as 
soon as the sanctioned alteration has been carried out.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Amendment of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any licence granted under these rules may be amended by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee for amendment 
of a licence shall be rupees ten plus the amount, if any, by which the 
fee that would have been payable if the licence had originally been issued in 
the amended Form exceeds the fee originally paid for the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A licensee who desires 
to have his licence amended shall submit to the Chief Controller—
 



1[(i)  an 
application duly filled in and signed in Form I, or in Form IA or in Form II, as 
the case may be;]
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the licence sought to be amended together with the approved plans 
attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  where any alteration in the licensed premises has been carried out, 
three copies of the properly drawn plan showing the alteration sanctioned under 
rule 53 by the Chief Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  fee for the amendment of the licence as specified in sub‑rule (2);
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  a certificate of safety, if required under rule 33.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence granted under these rules may be renewed by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence granted 
under these rules, 

1[***], may be 
renewable for three financial years where there has been no contravention of the 
Act or the rules framed thereunder or of any conditions of the licence so 
renewed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a licence which 
has been renewed for more than one year is surrendered before its expiry, the 
renewal fee paid for the unexpired portion of the licence shall be refunded to 
the licensee, provided that no refund of renewal fee shall be made for any 
financial year during which the Chief Controller receives the renewed licence 
for surrender.
 

2[(4) Every 
application for renewal of the licence shall be made in Form I, or Form IA or 
Form II, as case may be, and shall be accompanied by the licence and prescribed 
fee.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application for 
the renewal of a licence shall be made so as to reach the licensing authority at 
least thirty days before the date on which it expires, and if the application is 
so made, the licence shall be deemed to be in force until such date as the Chief 
Controller renews the licence or until an intimation that the renewal of the 
licence is refused has been communicated to applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the renewal of a 
licence is refused, the fee paid for the renewal shall be refunded to the 
licensee after deducting therefrom the proportionate fee for the period 
beginning from the date from which the licence was to be renewed up to the date 
on which renewal thereof is refused.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The same fee shall be 
charged for the renewal of a licence for each financial year as for the grant 
thereof:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  if the application with accompaniments required under sub‑rule (4), is 
not received within the time specified in sub‑rule (5), the licence shall be 
renewed only on payment of a fee amounting to twice the fee ordinarily payable;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  if such an application with accompaniments is received by the Chief 
Controller after the date of expiry but not later than thirty days from that, 
the licence may, without prejudice to any other action that may be taken in this 
behalf, be renewed on payment of twice the fee ordinarily payable:
 
                   
Provided further that in the case of an application for the renewal of a licence 
for a period of more than one financial year at a time, the fee prescribed under 
clause (i) or clause (ii) of the first proviso, if payable, shall be paid only 
for the first financial year of renewal.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> No licence shall be 
renewed if the application for renewal be received by the Chief Controller after 
thirty days of the date of its expiry.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Refusal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Controller refusing to grant, amend, renew or transfer a licence, 
shall record his reasons for such refusal in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the order 
containing the reasons for such refusal shall be given to the applicant on 
payment of a fee of rupees five paid in the manner specified in rule 11.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Suspension and 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall be liable to be suspended or 
cancelled, by an order of the Chief Controller for any contravention of the 
provisions of the Act or these rules or of any condition contained in such 
licence, or by an order of the Central Government if at any time the continuance 
of the licence in the hands of the licensee is deemed objectionable:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  before suspending or cancelling a licence under this rule, the holder 
of the licence shall be given an opportunity of being heard;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the maximum period of suspension shall not exceed three months; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  the suspension of a licence shall not debar the holder of the 
licence from applying for its renewal in accordance with the provisions of rule 
55.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything in sub‑rule (1), an opportunity of being heard may not be given to the 
holder of a licence before his licence is suspended or cancelled in case—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  where the licence is suspended by the Chief Controller as an interim 
measure for the violation of the provisions of the Act or these rules, or of any 
condition contained in such licence or in his opinion such violation is likely 
to cause imminent danger to the public:
 
                   
Provided that where a licence is so suspended, the Chief Controller shall give 
the holder of the licence an opportunity of being heard before the order of 
suspension is confirmed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  where the licence is suspended or cancelled by the Central 
Government, if that Government considers that in the public interest or in the 
interest of the security of the State such opportunity should not be given.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Controller 
or the Central Government suspending or cancelling a licence under sub‑rule (1), 
shall record his or its reasons for so doing in writing.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Procedure on 
expiration, suspension or cancellation of licence.—A 
person licensed to store compressed gas shall, on the expiration, suspension or 
cancellation of his licence, forthwith give notice to the Chief Controller of 
the nature and quantity of compressed gas in his possession and shall comply 
with any directions which the Chief Controller may give in regard to its 
disposal.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall be with the Central Government against any order passed by the 
Chief Controller refusing to grant, amend or renew a licence or cancelling or 
suspending a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every appeal shall be 
in writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and 
shall be presented within sixty days of the order passed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Procedure on death 
or disability of licensee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a licensee dies or becomes insolvent or is mentally incapable or is otherwise 
disabled the person carrying on the business of such licensee shall not be 
liable to any penalty or confiscation under the Act or these rules for 
exercising the powers granted to the licensee during such time as may reasonably 
be required to allow him to make an application for a new licence in his own 
name for the unexpired portion of the original licence in respect of the year in 
which the licensee dies or becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is 
otherwise disabled:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub‑rule shall be deemed to authorise the exercise of any power under this 
sub‑rule by any person after the expiry of the period of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A fee of rupees five 
shall be charged for a new licence for the expired portion of the original 
licence granted to any person applying for it under this rule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Loss of licence.—When 
a licence granted under these rules is lost or accidentally destroyed, a 
duplicate may be granted on the submission of a copy of the plan or plans 
identical with those attached to the licence and on payment of a fee of rupees 
ten paid in the manner specified in rule 11.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Production of 
licence on demand.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person holding or acting under a licence granted under these rules shall 
produce it, or an authenticated copy of it, at the place to which the licence 
applies, when called upon to do so by any of the officers specified in rule 69.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Copies of any licence 
may, for the purpose of this rule, be authenticated by the authority which 
granted the licence—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  on payment of a fee of rupees five in the manner specified in rule 11 
for each authenticated copy; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  on the submission of a copy or copies of the plans identical with the 
approved plan or plans attached to the licence.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>62A</number> Compliance 
of instructions of licensing authority.—If 
the licensing authority calls upon the holder of the licence by a notice in 
writing to execute any repairs in the licensed premises which are, in the 
opinion of such authority, necessary for the safety of the premises, the holder 
of the licence shall execute the repairs within such periods as may be specified 
in the notice.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Procedure on 
reports of infringement.—The 
district authority shall inform the Chief Controller of the action taken by him 
on any reports of infringement of the Act or of these rules which the Chief 
Controller may make to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Executive control 
over authorities.—Every 
authority, other than the Central Government, acting under this Chapter shall 
perform its duties subject to the control of the Central Government:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rules shall be deemed to affect the powers of executive control of the 
Chief Controller over the officers subordinate to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Powers to exempt.—The 
Central Government may, on the recommendation of the Chief Controller, in 
exceptional cases, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, exempt 
storage and transportation of any compressed gas in any vessel from all or any 
of the provisions of these rules, on such conditions, if any, as may be 
specified in the order.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Notice of accident.—The 
notice of an accident required to be given under sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 8 of 
the Act shall be given forthwith—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  to the Chief Controller by express telegram (Telegraphic 
Address—Explosives, Nagpur) followed within twenty‑four hours by a letter giving 
particulars of the occurrence; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  to the officer‑in‑charge of the nearest police station by the 
quickest route. Pending the visit of the Chief Controller, or his 
representative, or until instruction is received from the Chief Controller that 
he does not wish any further investigation or inquiry to be made, all wreckage 
and debris shall be left untouched except in so far as its removal may be 
necessary for the rescue of persons injured, and recovery for the bodies of any 
persons killed by the accident or in the case of railways, for the restoration 
of through communication.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Inquiry into 
accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever a District Magistrate, a Commissioner of Police or a Magistrate 
subordinate to a District Magistrate holds an inquiry under sub‑section (1) of 
section 9 of the Act, he shall adjourn such an inquiry unless the Chief 
Controller or an officer nominated by him is present to watch the proceedings or 
the Magistrate has received written information from the Chief Controller that 
he does not wish to send a representative.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Magistrate shall, 
at least fourteen days before holding the adjourned inquiry, send to the Chief 
Controller notice in writing of the time and place of holding the adjourned 
inquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an accident has 
been attended with loss of human life, the Magistrate, before the adjournment, 
may take evidence to identify any bodies and may order the internment thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chief Controller 
or his representative shall be at liberty at any such inquiry to examine any 
witness, subject to the order of the Magistrate, on points of law.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where evidence is 
given at an inquiry at which the Chief Controller or an officer nominated by him 
is not present, of any neglect as having caused or contributed to the explosion 
or accident or of any defect in or about or in connection with any installation 
or any vehicle appearing to the Magistrate or jury to require a remedy, the 
Magistrate shall send to the Chief Controller notice in writing of the neglect 
or defect.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Inquiry into more 
serious accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever an inquiry is held under section 9A of the Act, the persons holding 
such inquiry shall hold the same in open court in such manner and under such 
conditions as they may think most effectual for ascertaining the causes and 
circumstances of the accident, and enabling them to make the report under this 
rule:
 
Provided that where the 
Central Government so directs, the inquiry may be held in camera.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Persons attending as 
witnesses before the court under sub‑rule (1) shall be allowed such expenses as 
are paid to witnesses attending before a Civil Court subordinate to the High 
Court having jurisdiction in the place where the inquiry is held and in case of 
any dispute as to the amount to be allowed, the question shall be referred to 
the local Magistrate who, on a request being made to the court, shall ascertain 
and certify the proper amount of such expenses.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All expenses incurred 
in or about in inquiry or investigation under this rule shall be deemed to be 
part of the expenses of the Department of Explosives in carrying the Act into 
execution.
</section></article><form>
 




The Static and Mobile Pressure Vessels (Unfired)  

Rules, 1981
 


 
 




1[APPENDIX 
I]
 


[See 
rule 4(3)(a)]
 


1. Applicant’s name and 
full address.
 


2. Whether the applicant 
has manufactured any unfired pressure vessel. Yes/No If yes—
 


           
(i) Date from which such vessels were manufactured.
 


          
(ii) For whom the vessels were fabricated and their approximate numbers.
 


         
(iii) Details of the vessels manufactured.
 


3. Specifications or code 
proposed to be adopted for the manufacture of the vessels or containers.
 


4. Organisational set‑up 
with specific reference to qualifications and experience of the personnel 
engaged in the manufacture of vessels.
 


5. Organisational set‑up of 
the inspecting personnel engaged by the applicant.
 


6. Process of manufacture 
of vessel or containers, beginning with raw material and ending with the 
finished vessels or containers.
 


7. Quality control checks 
or tests carried out at each stage of manufacture of vessels or containers.
 


8. (i) Details of the 
equipment installed for chemical analysis and mechanical tests.
 


(ii) Details of templates 
or gauges provided to check or test.
 


(iii) Steps taken to check 
the accuracy of testing and checking equipment and frequency of such checking.
 


9. Equipment available for 
carrying out non‑destructive examination such as radiography, Gama ray, 
ultrasonic tests, etc.
 


10. List of machinery 
provided for manufacturing vessels or containers.
 


11. Name and address of the 
independent inspecting authority.
 


12. Records and 
certificates of tests:
 


           
(i)  Proforma of records for various tests carried out by the inspecting 
and certifying organisation; and
 


          
(ii)  Proforma of test and inspection certificate issued by the independent 
inspecting authority.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Appendix 
renumbered as Appendix I by G.S.R. 264(E), dated 10th March, 1993.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>