<act><tid>1534878</tid>
<title>THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF OFFICERS OF PARLIAMENT ACT, <year>1953</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1953</year>
[ 16th May, <year>1953</year>.]

An Act to provide for the salaries and allowances of certain 
Officers of Parliament.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1756980</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1722669</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salaries and Allowances of Officers of Parliament Act, <year>1953</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1781744</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the first day 
of May, <year>1953</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>752360</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act" officer of Parliament" means any of 
the following officers, namely, the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of 
the Council of States and the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the 
House of the People.


</article>



<article><tid>552702</tid>
<number> 3</number> Salaries etc., of officers of Parliament.
<section><tid>1881679</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
paid to the Chairman of the Council of States a salary of seven 
thousand five hundred rupees per menses <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> and an allowance for each 
day during the whole of his terms as the Chairman at the same rate as 
is specified in section 3 of the Salary, Allowances and Pension of 
Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> with respect to members of 
Parliament.]

</section>

<section><tid>1906386</tid>
<number>2</number>Each officer of Parliament, other than the Chairman of the 
council of States shall be entitled to receive a salary per mensem 
and an allowance for each day during the whole of his term as officer 
at the same rates as are specified in section 3 of the Sallaries, 
Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> with respect 
to members of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1133707</tid>
<number>3</number>Each officer of Parliament, other than the Chairman of the 
Council of States, shall be entitled to receive a constituency 
allowance at the same rate as is specified under section 8 of the said 
Act with respect to members of Parliament.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1018812</tid>
<number> 4</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1911805</tid>
<number>1</number>] Residence for officers of parliament. Each officer of  
Parliament shall be entitled without pay- ment of rent to the use of a 
furnished residence throughout his term of office and for a period of 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> one month] immediately thereafter, and no charge shall fall on the 
officer personally in respect of the maintenance of such residence.

</section>

<section><tid>274552</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> In the event of the death of an officer of Parliament, his 
family shall be entitled to the use of the furnished residence 
occupied by the officer of Parliament-

<subsection><tid>1597175</tid>
<number>a</number>for a period of one month immediately after his 
death, without payment of rent and no charge shall fall on 
the family of the officer of Parliament in respect of the 
maintenance of such residence, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>623766</tid>
<number>b</number>for a further period of one month, on payment of rent 
at such rates as may be prescribed by rules made in this

<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2, for the former section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>S. 4 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 49 of 
<year>1970</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1969</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" fifteen days" (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1969</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1969</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 75 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1990</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

behalf under section 11 and also charges in respect of 
electricity and water consumed in that residence during such 
further period.]

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," residence" 
includes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto 
and the garden thereof, and" maintenance" in relation to a residence 
includes the payment of local rates and taxes and the provision of 
electricity and water.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1701958</tid>
<number>5</number>Sumptuary allowance. There shall be paid to the Chairman of 
the Council of States and the Speaker of the House of the People a 
sumptuary allowance of one thousand rupees per mensem and to the 
Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker a sumptuary allowance of five 
hundred rupees per mensem.]


</article>



<article><tid>335026</tid>
<number> 6</number> Travelling and daily allowances to officers of parliament.
<section><tid>1082691</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to any rules made in this behalf under section 11, an officer 
of Parliament shall be entitled to-

<subsection><tid>489848</tid>
<number>a</number>travelling allowances for himself and the members of 
his family and for the transport of his and his family' s 
effects:

<subsubsection><tid>1482540</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of the journey to Delhi from his usual 
place of residence outside Delhi for assuming office, 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>530810</tid>
<number>ii</number>in respect of the journey from Delhi to his usual 
place of residence outside Delhi on relinquishing 
office; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>955853</tid>
<number>b</number>travelling and daily allowances in respect of tours 
undertaken by him in the discharge of his official duties, 
whether by sea, land or air.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1868996</tid>
<number>1A</number>A Ministter and any one member of this family accompany- 
ing him shall be entitled to travelling allowances in respect of not 
more than six return journeys performed, during each year, within 
India, at the same rates at which travelling allowances are payable 
to such Minister under clause (b) of sub- section (1) in respect of 
tourns referred to in that clause.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," return 
journey" mears a journey form one place to another place and the 
return journey form such other place to the first mentioned place.;


</section>

<section><tid>514897</tid>
<number>2</number>Any travelling allowance under this section may be paid in 
cash or free official transport may be provided in lieu thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>861377</tid>
<number>7</number>Medical facilities to officers of Parliament. Subject to any 2 
rules made in this behalf under section 11, an officer of Parliament 
and the members of his family shall be entitled free of charge to 
accommodation in hospitals maintained by the Government and also to 
medical treatment.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such rules. see Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. II, Sec., 3, p. 
810.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 75 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1787883</tid>
<number>8</number>Advances to officers of Parliament for puchase of motorcars. 
There may be paid to any officer of Parliament by way of a repayable 
advance such sum of money as may be determined by rules 1 made in this 
behalf under section 11 for the purchase of a motor- car in order that 
he may be able to discharge conveniently and efficiently the duties of 
his office.


</article>



<article><tid>738480</tid>
<number>9</number>Officers of Parliament not to draw salary or allowances as 
Members of Parliament. No officer of Parliament in receipt of a 
salary or allowance under this Act shall be entitled to receive any 
sum out of funds provided by Parliament by way of salary or allowance 
in respect of his membership of either House of Parliament.


</article>



<article><tid>14955</tid>
<number>10</number>Notification respecting appointment etc., of officers of 
parliament to be conclusive evidence thereof. The date on which any 
person became or ceased to be an officer of Parliament shall be 
published in the Official Gazette and any such notification shall be 
conclusive evidence of the fact that he became, or ceased to be, an 
officer of Parliament on that date for all the purposes of this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>590060</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Exemption from liability to pay income- tex on daily 
allowance received by the Chairman and certain perquisites received by 
an Officer of Parliament. Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Income- tax Act <year>1961</year>,
<section><tid>1934438</tid>
<number>a</number>in computing the total income of a previous year of the 
Chairman of the Council of States, any income by way of an 
allowance referred to in sub- section (1) of section 3 shall 
not be included;

</section>

<section><tid>969607</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of rent free furnished residence (including  
  maintenance thereof) provided to an officer of Parliament 
under sub- section (1) of section 4 shall not be included in 
the computation of his income chargeable under the head 
" Salaries" under section 15 of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1807115</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>336725</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in  
consultation with the Chairman and the Speaker, make 2 rules for 
carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1590412</tid>
<number>2</number>All rules made under this Act shall be laid before both 
Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after they are made.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Officers of Parliament (Advances for Motor Cars) Rules, 
<year>1953</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. IT, Sec. 3, p. 1463.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For such rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. II, See. 3, p. 810.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1990</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>