<act><title>


THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
    POLLUTION) CESS ACT, 1977</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess 
    Act, 1977. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), it applies to all the States 
    to which the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
    1974) applies and the Union territories.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “local authority” means a 
    municipal corporation or a municipal council (by whatever name called) or a 
    cantonment board or by other body, entrusted with the duty of supplying 
    water under the law by or under which it is constituted;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;
 

1[(c) 
       “industry” includes any operation or process, or treatment and disposal 
    system, which consumes water or gives rise to sewage effluent or trade 
    effluent, but does nto include any hydel power unit;]
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    words and expressions used but 
    not defined in this Act and defined in the Water (Prevention and Control of 
    Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in that Act.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Levy and collection of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be levied and collected a cess for the purposes of the Water 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) and utilisation 
    thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    cess under sub-section (1) shall be payable by—
 <subsection>
               <number>a</number>    every person 
    carrying on any 
1[industry]; 
    and
 </subsection><subsection>
               <number>b</number>    every local 
    authority,
 
and shall be calculated on the basis of the 
    water consumed by such person or local authority, as the case may be, for 
    any of the purposes specified in column (1) of Schedule II, at such rate, 
    not exceeding the rate specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) 
    thereof, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, from time to time, specify.
 


    2[(2A) Where any 
    person carrying on any 

    3[industry] or any 
    local authority consuming water for domestic purpose liable to pay cess 
    fails to comply with any of the provisions of section 25 of the Water 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) or any of the 
    standards laid down by the Central Government under the Environment 
    (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986), cess shall be, notwithstanding anything 
    contained in sub-section (2) of this section, calculated and payable at such 
    rate, not exceeding the rate specified in column (3) of Schedule II, as the 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, from time 
    to time, specify.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any local authority supplies water to any person carrying on any
    

    3[industry] or to any 
    other local authority and such person or other local authority is liable to 
    pay cess 

    4[under sub-section 
    (2) or sub-section (2A)] in respect of the water so supplied, then, 
    notwithstanding anything contained 

    4[in those 
    sub-sections], the local authority first mentioned shall not liable to any 
    such cess in respect of such water.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section and section 4, “consumption of water” includes 
    supply of water.  
 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Affixing of meters.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of measuring and recording the quantity of water consumed, 
    every person carrying on any 

    1[industry] and every 
    local authority shall affix meters of such standards and at such places as 
    may be prescribed and it shall be presumed that the quantity indicated by 
    the meter has been consumed by such person or local authority, as the case 
    may be, until the contrary is proved.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any person or local authority fails to affix any meter as required by 
    sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, after notice to such person 
    or local authority, as the case may be, cause such meter to be affixed and 
    the cost of such meter together with the cost for affixing the meter may be 
    recovered from such person or local authority by the Central Government in 
    the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.  
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number>
Furnishing of returns.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Every person carrying on any 

    2[industry] and every 
    local authority, liable to pay the cess under section 3, shall furnish such 
    returns, in such form, at such intervals and containing such particulars to 
    such officer or authority, as may be prescribed.
 


    1[(2) If a person 
    carrying on any 

    2[industry] or a local 
    authority, liable to pay the cess under section 3, fails to furnish any 
    return under sub-section (1), the officer or the authority shall give a 
    notice requiring such person or local authority to furnish such return 
    before such date as may be specified in the notice.]
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Assessment of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The officer or authority to whom or which the return has been furnished 
    under section 5 shall, after making or causing to be made such inquiry as he 
    or it thinks fit and after satisfying himself or itself that the particulars 
    stated in the return are correct, by order, assess the amount of cess 
    payable by the concerned person carrying on any 

    1[industry] or local 
    authority, as the case may be.  
 


    2[(1A) If the return 
    has not been furnished to the officer or authority under sub-section (2) of 
    section 5, he or it shall, after making or causing to be made such inquiry 
    as he or it thinks fit, by order, assess the amount of cess payable by the 
    concerned person carrying on any 

    2[industry] or local 
    authority, as the case may be.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    order of assessment made under sub-section (1) 

    3[or sub-section (1A)] 
    shall specify the date within which the cess shall be paid to the State 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    copy each of the order of assessment made under sub-section (1) 


    4[or sub-section (1A)] 
    shall be sent to the person or, as the case may be, to the local authority 
    concerned and to the State Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    State Government shall, through such of its officers or authorities as may 
    be specified by it in this behalf by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    collect the cess from the person or local authority liable to pay the same 
    and pay the amount so collected to the Central Government in such manner and 
    within such time as may be prescribed.  
 
 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Rebate.—Where 
    any person or local authority, liable to pay the cess under this Act, 
    installs any plant for the treatment of sewage or trade effluent, such 
    person or local authority shall from such date as may be prescribed, be 
    entitled to a rebate of 

    1[twenty-five per 
    cent.] of the cess payable by such person or, as the case may be, local 
    authority:  
 


    2[Provided that a 
    person or local authority shall not be entitled to any rebate, if he or it—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    consumes water in excess of the 
    maximum quantity as may be prescribed in this behalf for any 
3[industry] 
    or local authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    fails to comply with any of the 
    provisions of section 25 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) 
    Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) or any of the standards laid down by the Central 
    Government under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986).]
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Crediting proceeds of cess to Consolidated Fund of India and application 
    thereof.—The 
    proceeds of the cess levied under section 3 shall first be credited to the 
    Consolidated Fund of India and the Central Government may, if Parliament, by 
    appropriation made by law in this behalf, so provides, pay the Central Board 
    and every State Board, from time to time, from out of such proceeds, after 
    deducting the expenses on collection, such sums of money as it may think fit 
    for being utilised under the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) 
    Act, 1974 (6 of 1974):  
 
Provided 
    that while determining the sum of money to be paid to any State Board under 
    this section, the Central Government shall have regard to the amount of cess 
    collected by the State Government concerned under sub-section (4) of section 
    6.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “State Board” includes a Joint Board, if any, 
    constituted under section 13 of the Water (Prevention and Control of 
    Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Power of entry.— 
    Any officer or authority of the State Government specially empowered in this 
    behalf by that Government may,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    with such assistance, if any, as 
    he or it may think fit, enter at any reasonable time any place which he or 
    it considers it necessary to enter for carrying out the purposes of this Act 
    including the testing of the correctness of the meters affixed under section 
    4;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    do within such place anything 
    necessary for the proper discharge of his or its duties under this Act; and
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    exercise such other powers as may 
    be prescribed.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Interest payable for delay in payment of cess.—If 
    any person carrying on any 

    1[industry] or any 
    local authority fail to pay any amount of cess payable under section 3 to 
    the State Government within the date specified in the order of assessment 
    made under section 6, such person or local authority, as the case may be, 
    shall be liable to pay 

    2[interest on the 
    amount to be paid at the rate of two per cent. for every month or part of a 
    month comprised in the period from the date on which such payment is due 
    till such amount is actually paid.]
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Penalty for non-payment of cess within the specified time.—If 
    any amount of cess payable by any person carrying on any 

    1[industry] or any 
    local authority under section 3 is not paid to the State Government within 
    the date specified in the order of assessment made under section 6, it shall 
    be deemed to be in arrears and the authority prescribed in this behalf may, 
    after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on such person or, as the case 
    may be, local authority, a penalty not exceeding the amount of cess in 
    arrears:  
 
Provided 
    that before imposing any such penalty, such person or, as the case may be, 
    the local authority shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard 
    and if after such hearing the said authority is satisfied that the default 
    was for any good and sufficient reason, no penalty shall be imposed under 
    this section.  
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Recovery of amount due under the Act.—Any 
    amount due under this Act (including any interest or penalty payable under 
    section 10 or section 11, as the case may be) from any person carrying on 
    any 

    1[industry] or from 
    any local authority may be recovered by the Central Government in the same 
    manner as an arrear of land revenue.  
 
 






 



</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Appeals. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any person or local authority aggrieved by an order of assessment made under section 6 or by an order imposing penalty made under section 11 may, within such time as may be prescribed, appeal to such authority in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal preferred under sub-section (1) shall be accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> After the receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), the appellate authority shall, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard in the matter, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as possible. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every order passed in appeal under this section <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[shall, if no appeal has been filed under section 13A, be final] and shall not be called in question in any court of law. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>13A</number> Appeal to National Green Tribunal. </title>— Any person aggrieved, by an order or decision of the appellate authority made under section 13, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.] 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever, being under an obligation to furnish a return under this Act, 
    furnishes any return knowing, or having reason to believe, the same to be 
    false shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months 
    or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever, being liable to pay cess under this Act, wilfully or intentionally 
    evades or attempts to evade the payment of such cess shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may 
    extend to one thousand rupees or with both.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this section save 
    on a complaint made by or under the authority of the Central Government.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence, 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body 
    corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation 
    to a firm, means a partner in the firm.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>16</number> Power of Central 
    Government to exempt the levy of water cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3, the Central Government may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt any industry, consuming 
    water below the quantity specified in the notification, from the levy of 
    water cess.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    exempting an industry under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall 
    take into consideration—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the nature of raw 
    material used;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the nature of 
    manufacturing process employed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the nature of 
    effluent generated;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the source of 
    water extraction;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the nature of 
    effluent receiving bodies; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the production 
    data, including water consumption per unit production, 
 
 
in the industry and the location of the 
    industry.]  
 
 
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
    Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
    provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the standards of the 
    meters to be affixed and the places at which such meters are to be affixed 
    under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the returns to be 
    furnished under section 5, the form in which and the intervals at which such 
    returns are to be furnished, the particulars which such returns shall 
    contain and the officer or authority to whom or which such returns shall be 
    furnished;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the manner in which and 
    the time within which the cess collected shall be paid to the Central 
    Government under sub-section (4) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the date from 
    which any person or local authority liable to pay cess shall be entitled to 
    the rebate 
1[and 
    the maximum quantity of water in excess of consumption whereof any person or 
    local authority shall not be entitled to the rebate]; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the powers which may be 
    exercised by the officer or authority under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the authority which may 
    impose penalty under section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the authority to which 
    an appeal may be filed under sub-section (1) of section 13 and the time 
    within which and the form and manner in which such appeal may be filed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the fees which shall 
    accompany an appeal under sub-section (2) of section 13; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    any other matter which 
    has to be or may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule 
    made under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of on effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.
 
 





 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
    POLLUTION) CESS ACT, 1977
 

 
 

 
 


1[***]
 





 




    -------------------
 




         1.   Schedule I omitted by Act 19 of 
    2003, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 6-5-2003).
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
    POLLUTION) CESS ACT, 1977
 



 

 
 




    1[SCHEDULE 
    II
 




    (See 
    section 3)
 

 
 
 
 
Purpose for which water 
         

        is consumed
 
Maximum rate under sub-section(2) of 
        Section 3
 
Maximum rate under sub-section (2A) of 
        Section 3

 
 
(1)
 
(2)
 
(3)

 
 
1. Industrial 
        cooling, spraying in 

    mine pits or boiler feeds
 
Five paise 
        per kiloletre
 
Ten paise per 
        kiloletre

 
 
2. Domestic 
        purpose
 
Two paise per 
        kiloletre
 
Three paise 
        per kiloletre

 
 
3. Processing 
        whereby water gets 

    polluted and the pollutants are— 

    (i)   easily biodegradable; or 

    (ii)  non-toxic; or 

    (iii) both non-toxic and easily  

         biodegradable
 
Ten paise per 
        kiloletre
 
Twenty paise 
        per kiloletre

 
 
4. Processing 
        whiereby water get 

    polluted and the pollutants are— 

    (i)   not easily biodegradable; or 

    (ii)  toxic; or 

    (iii)  both toxic and not easily 

           biodegradable.
 
Fifteen paise 
        per kiloletre
 
Thirty paise 
        per kiloletre].

 
  


 

 
 




    ------------------------------
 




         1.   Subs. by Act 19 of 2003, sec. 6, for Schedule II (w.e.f. 
    6-5-2003).
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch., for “shall be final”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>