<act><tid>1123621</tid>
<title>THE MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 39 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 3rd July, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to co- operative 
societies, with objects not confined to one State and serving the 
interests of members in more than one State, to facilitate the 
voluntary formation and democratic functioning of co- operati es as 
people' s institutions based on self- help and mutual aid and to enable 
them to promote their economic and social betterment and to provide 
functional autonomy and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1734142</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>45369</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>790369</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1633595</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any 
reference in any such provision to the commencemen of this Act shall 
be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that 
provision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959215</tid>
<number> 2</number> Application.- This Act shall apply to-
<section><tid>229236</tid>
<number>a</number>all co- operative societies, with objects not confined to one State 
which were incorporated before the commencement of this Act,-

<subsection><tid>1355766</tid>
<number>i</number>under the Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>552026</tid>
<number>ii</number>under any other law relating to co- operative societies in force 
in any State or in pursuance of the Multi- unit Co- operative Societies 
Act, <year>1942</year> (6 of <year>1942</year>) or the Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, 
 <year>1984</year> (51 of <year>1984</year>),
and the registration of which has not been cancelled before such 
commencement; and


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1855989</tid>
<number>b</number>all multi- State co- operative societies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1636607</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>504691</tid>
<number>a</number>" area of operation" means the area from which the persons are 
admitted as members;

</section>

<section><tid>1234069</tid>
<number>b</number>" board" means the board of directors or the governing body of a 
multi- State co- operative society, by whatever name called, to which 
the direction and control of the management of the affairs of the 
society is entrusted;

</section>

<section><tid>797476</tid>
<number>c</number>" bye- laws" means the bye- laws for the time being in force which 
have been duly registered or deemed to have been registered under this 
Act and includes amendments thereto which have been duly registered or 
deemed to have been registered under this Ac;

</section>

<section><tid>1025162</tid>
<number>d</number>" Central Registrar" means the Central Registrar of Co- operative 
Societies appointed under sub- section (1) of section 4 and includes 
any officer empowered to exercise the powers of the Central Registrar 
under sub- section (2) of that section;

</section>

<section><tid>109662</tid>
<number>e</number>" Chief Executive" means a Chief Executive of a multi- State 
co- operative society appointed under section 51;

</section>

<section><tid>1149110</tid>
<number>f</number>" co- operative bank" means a multi- State co- operative society which 
undertakes banking business;

</section>

<section><tid>96463</tid>
<number>g</number>" co- operative principles" means the co- operative principles 
specified in the First Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1432393</tid>
<number>h</number>" co- operative society" means a society registered or deemed to be 
registered under any law relating to co- operative societies for the 
time being in force in any State;

</section>

<section><tid>741210</tid>
<number>i</number>" co- operative year", in relation to any multi- State co- operative 
society or class of such societies, means the year ending on the 31st 
day of March of the year and where the accounts of such society or 
class of such societies are, with the previous s nction of the Central 
Registrar, balanced on any other day, the year ending on such day;

</section>

<section><tid>1732103</tid>
<number>j</number>" Deposit Insurance Corporation" means the Deposit Insurance and 
Credit Guarantee Corporation established under section 3 of the 
Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>966119</tid>
<number>k</number>" federal co- operative" means a federation of co- operative 
societies registered under this Act and whose membership is available 
only to a co- operative society or a multi- State co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>1891889</tid>
<number>l</number>" general body", in relation to a multi- State co- operative society, 
means all the members of that society and in relation to a national 
co- operative society or a federal co- operative means all the delegates 
of member co- operative societies or delegate of multi- State 
co- operative societies and includes a body constituted under the first 
proviso to sub- section (1) of section 38;

</section>

<section><tid>27579</tid>
<number>m</number>" general meeting" means a meeting of the general body of a 
multi- State co- operative society and includes special general meeting;

</section>

<section><tid>1257423</tid>
<number>n</number>" member" means a person joining in the application for the 
registration of a multi- State co- operative society and includes a 
person admitted to membership after such registration in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act, the rules and the bye- la s;

</section>

<section><tid>1802575</tid>
<number>o</number>" member co- operative" means a co- operative society or a 
multi- State co- operative society which is member of a federal 
co- operative;

</section>

<section><tid>792136</tid>
<number>p</number>" multi- State co- operative society" means a society registered or 
deemed to be registered under this Act and includes a national 
co- operative society and a federal co- operative;

</section>

<section><tid>956959</tid>
<number>q</number>" multi- State co- operative society with limited liability" means a 
society having the liability of its members limited by its bye- laws to 
the amount, if any, unpaid on the shares, respectively, held by them 
or to such amount as they may, respectively, thereby undertake to 
contribute to the assets of the society, in the event of its being 
wound up;

</section>

<section><tid>1447879</tid>
<number>r</number>" national co- operative society" means a multi- State co- operative 
society specified in the Second Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1786749</tid>
<number>s</number>" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1084962</tid>
<number>t</number>" officer" means a president, vice- president, chairperson, 
vice- chairperson, managing director, secretary, manager, member of a 
board, treasurer, liquidator, an administrator appointed under section 
 123 and includes any other person empowered under th s Act or the 
rules or the bye- laws to give directions in regard to the business of 
a multi- State co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>531042</tid>
<number>u</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules;

</section>

<section><tid>235894</tid>
<number>v</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under 
the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>11882</tid>
<number>w</number>" rules" means the rules made under this Act.
CHAP

CENTRAL REGISTRAR AND REGISTRATION OF MULTI- STATE 
CO- OPERATIVE 
SOCIETIES

CHAPTER II

CENTRAL REGISTRAR AND REGISTRATION OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE 
SOCIETIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>976283</tid>
<number> 4</number> Central Registrar.-
<section><tid>1129907</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may appoint a person  
to be the Central Registrar of Co- operative Societies and may appoint 
such other persons as it may think fit to assist the Central 
Registrar.

</section>

<section><tid>879795</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification, direct that any power 
exercisable by the Central Registrar under this Act (other than the  
  power of registration of a multi- State co- operative society) shall, in 
relation to such society, and such matters a may be specified in the 
notification, be exercisable also by any other officer of the Central 
Government or of a State Government as may be authorised by the 
Central Government subject to such conditions as may be specified 
therein:
Provided that no officer of a State Government shall be empowered to 
exercise such power in relation to a national co- operative society.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1179874</tid>
<number> 5</number> Multi- State co- operative societies which may be registered.-
<section><tid>779645</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
multi- State co- operative society shall be registered under this Act, 
unless,-

<subsection><tid>1527145</tid>
<number>a</number>its main objects are to serve the interests of members in more 
than one State; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1332405</tid>
<number>b</number>its bye- laws provide for social and economic betterment of its 
members through self- help and mutual aid in accordance with the 
co- operative principles.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1903152</tid>
<number>2</number>The word" limited" or its equivalent in any Indian language shall 
be suffixed to the name of every multi- State co- operative society 
registered under this Act with limited liability.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1568339</tid>
<number> 6</number> Application for registration.-
<section><tid>624697</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of registration  
of a multi- State co- operative society under this Act, an application 
shall be made to the Central Registrar in such form and with such 
particulars as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1262922</tid>
<number>2</number>The application shall be signed,-

<subsection><tid>99016</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a multi- State co- operative society of which all the 
members are individuals, by at least fifty persons from each of the 
State concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1946533</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a multi- State co- operative society of which the 
members are co- operative societies, by duly authorised representatives 
on behalf of at least five such societies as are not registered in the 
same State; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>483935</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a multi- State co- operative society of which another 
multi- State co- operative society and other co- operative societies are 
members, by duly authorised representatives of each of such societies:
Provided that not less than two of the co- operative societies referred 
to in this clause, shall be such as are not registered in the same 
State;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>913934</tid>
<number>d</number>in the case of a multi- State co- operative society of which the 
members are co- operative societies or multi- State co- operative 
societies and individuals, by at least-

<subsubsection><tid>1967596</tid>
<number>i</number>fifty persons, being individuals, from each of the two States or 
more; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>205073</tid>
<number>ii</number>one co- operative society each from two States or more or one 
multi- State co- operative society.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>974625</tid>
<number>3</number>The application shall be accompanied by four copies of the 
proposed bye- laws of the multi- State co- operative society and the 
persons by whom or on whose behalf such application is made shall 
furnish such information in regard to the society as the Ce tral 
Registrar may require.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1937147</tid>
<number> 7</number> Registration.-
<section><tid>1578203</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Registrar is satisfied- 

<subsection><tid>1290070</tid>
<number>a</number>that the application complies with the provisions of this Act and 
the rules;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1220143</tid>
<number>b</number>that the proposed multi- State co- operative society satisfies the 
basic criterion that its objects are to serve the interests of members 
in more than one State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1838254</tid>
<number>c</number>that its bye- laws provide for social and economic betterment of 
its members through self- help and mutual aid in accordance with the 
co- operative principles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>955434</tid>
<number>d</number>that the proposed bye- laws are not contrary to the provisions of 
this Act and the rules, he may register the multi- State co- operative 
society and its bye- laws.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1646474</tid>
<number>2</number>The application for registration shall be disposed of by the 
Central Registrar within a period of four months from the date of 
receipt thereof by him.

</section>

<section><tid>276830</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Central Registrar refuses to register a multi- State 
co- operative society, he shall communicate, within a period of four 
months from the date of receipt of the application for registration, 
the order of refusal together with the reasons ther for to the 
applicant or applicants, as the case may be:
Provided that no order of refusal shall be made unless the applicants 
have been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard:

Provided further that if the application for registration is not 
disposed of within a period of four months specified in sub- section 
 (2) or the Central Registrar fails to communicate the order of refusal 
within that period, the application shall be deeme to have been 
accepted for registration and the Central Registrar shall issue the 
registration certificate in accordance with the provisions of this Act 
and the rules made thereunder.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1532385</tid>
<number>8</number>Registration certificate.- Where a multi- State co- operative society 
is registered under this Act, the Central Registrar shall issue a 
certificate of registration signed by him, which shall be conclusive 
evidence that the society therein mentioned is du y registered under 
this Act, unless it is proved that the registration of the society has 
been cancelled.


</article>



<article><tid>217547</tid>
<number> 9</number> Multi- State co- operative society to be body corporate.-
<section><tid>1511534</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
registration of a multi- State co- operative society shall render it a 
body corporate by the name under which it is registered having 
perpetual succession and a common seal, and with power t acquire, hold 
and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, enter into 
contract, institute and defend suits and other legal proceedings and 
to do all things necessary for the purpose for which it is 
constituted, and shall, by the said name, sue o be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1608758</tid>
<number>2</number>All transactions entered into in good faith prior to the 
registration of a multi- State co- operative society shall be deemed to 
be its transactions after registration for furtherance of the objects 
of its registration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1129199</tid>
<number> 10</number> Bye- laws of multi- State co- operative societies.-
<section><tid>241013</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
multi- State co- operative society may make its bye- laws consistent with 
the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1976767</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such bye- laws may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>256510</tid>
<number>a</number>the name, address and area of operation of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1157656</tid>
<number>b</number>the objects of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950658</tid>
<number>c</number>the services to be provided to its members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1407390</tid>
<number>d</number>the eligibility for obtaining membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1284365</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure for obtaining membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>987718</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions for continuing as member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>629246</tid>
<number>g</number>the procedure for withdrawal of membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>487632</tid>
<number>h</number>the transfer of membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850194</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for expulsion from membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>519961</tid>
<number>j</number>the rights and duties of the members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>584468</tid>
<number>k</number>the nature and amount of capital of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>593563</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner in which the maximum capital to which a single member 
can subscribe;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1547726</tid>
<number>m</number>the sources from which the funds may be raised by the multi- State 
co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>469684</tid>
<number>n</number>the purpose for which the funds may be applied;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1737092</tid>
<number>o</number>the manner of allocation or disbursement of net profits of the 
multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1088575</tid>
<number>p</number>the constitution of various reserves;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>777630</tid>
<number>q</number>the manner of convening general meetings and quorum thereof other 
than those provided under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1278080</tid>
<number>r</number>the procedure for notice and manner of voting, in general and 
other meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>894360</tid>
<number>s</number>the procedure for amending the bye- laws;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>699514</tid>
<number>t</number>the number of members of the board not exceeding twenty- one;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728715</tid>
<number>u</number>the tenure, of directors, chairperson and other office- bearers of 
the society, not exceeding five years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1198310</tid>
<number>v</number>the procedure for removal of members of the board and for filling 
up of vacancies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1449912</tid>
<number>w</number>the manner of convening board meetings, its quorum, number of such 
meetings in a year and venue of such meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1048195</tid>
<number>x</number>the frequency of board meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591711</tid>
<number>y</number>the powers and functions of the Chief Executive in addition to 
those provided under section 52;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079175</tid>
<number>z</number>the manner of imposing the penalty;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1833184</tid>
<number>za</number>the appointment, rights and duties of auditors and procedure for 
conduct of audit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344587</tid>
<number>zb</number>the authorisation of officers to sign documents and to institute 
and defend suits and other legal proceedings on behalf of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866836</tid>
<number>zc</number>the terms on which a multi- State co- operative society may deal 
with persons other than members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681683</tid>
<number>zd</number>the terms on which a multi- State co- operative society may 
associate with other co- operatives societies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591839</tid>
<number>ze</number>the terms on which a multi- State co- operative society may deal 
with organisations other than co- operative societies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1701805</tid>
<number>zf</number>the rights, if any, which the multi- State co- operative society 
may confer on any other multi- State co- operative society or federal 
co- operative and the circumstances under which such rights may be 
exercised by the federal co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>997829</tid>
<number>zg</number>the procedure and manner for transfer of shares and interest in 
the name of a nominee in case of death of a member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1412534</tid>
<number>zh</number>the educational and training programmes to be conducted by the 
multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>792324</tid>
<number>zi</number>the principal place and other places of business of multi- State 
co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1107865</tid>
<number>zj</number>the minimum level of services to be used by its members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>306475</tid>
<number>zk</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1641972</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society.-
<section><tid>1307144</tid>
<number>1</number> 
No amendment of any bye- law of a multi- State co- operative society 
shall be valid, unless such amendment has been registered under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>858476</tid>
<number>2</number>The amendment to the bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative 
society shall be made by a resolution passed by a two- third majority 
of the members present and voting at general meeting of the society.

</section>

<section><tid>1375573</tid>
<number>3</number>No such resolution shall be valid unless fifteen clear days' 
notice of the proposed amendment has been given to the members.

</section>

<section><tid>1932078</tid>
<number>4</number>In every case in which a multi- State co- operative society proposes 
to amend its bye- laws, an application to register such amendments 
shall be made to the Central Registrar together with-

<subsection><tid>354027</tid>
<number>a</number>a copy of the resolution referred to in sub- section (2);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>243141</tid>
<number>b</number>a statement containing the particulars indicating-

<subsubsection><tid>132399</tid>
<number>i</number>the date of the general meeting at which the amendments to the 
bye- laws were made;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>375532</tid>
<number>ii</number>the number of days' notice given to convene the general meeting;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>695751</tid>
<number>iii</number>the total number of members of the multi- State co- operative 
society;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>666246</tid>
<number>iv</number>the quorum required for such meeting;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>684830</tid>
<number>v</number>the number of members present at the meeting;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1433192</tid>
<number>vi</number>the number of members who voted in such meeting;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1717343</tid>
<number>vii</number>the number of members who voted in favour of such amendments to 
bye- laws;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135668</tid>
<number>c</number>a copy of the relevant bye- laws in force with the amendment 
proposed to be made together with reasons justifying such amendments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1163169</tid>
<number>d</number>four copies of the text of the bye- laws incorporating therein the 
proposed amendments signed by the officer duly authorised in this 
behalf by the general body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>250342</tid>
<number>e</number>a copy of the notice given to the members and the proposal to 
amend the bye- laws;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1801658</tid>
<number>f</number>a certificate signed by the person who presided at the general 
meeting certifying that the procedure specified in sub- sections (2) 
and (3) and the bye- laws had been followed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>152978</tid>
<number>g</number>any other particular which may be required by the Central 
Registrar in this behalf.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>999252</tid>
<number>5</number>Every such application shall be made within sixty days from the 
date of the general meeting at which such amendment to the bye- laws 
was passed.

</section>

<section><tid>81524</tid>
<number>6</number>The procedure given in sub- sections (2) to (5) of this section 
shall apply to the amendment of the bye- laws of a co- operative society 
desiring to convert itself into a multi- State co- operative society as 
per the provisions of section 22.

</section>

<section><tid>519436</tid>
<number>7</number>If, on receipt of application under sub- section (5), the Central 
Registrar is satisfied that the proposed amendment-

<subsection><tid>991346</tid>
<number>a</number>is not contrary to the provisions of this Act or of the rules;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>261173</tid>
<number>b</number>does not conflict with co- operative principles; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>355307</tid>
<number>c</number>will promote the economic interests of the members of the 
multi- State co- operative society,
he may register the amendment within a period of three months from the 
date of receipt thereof by him.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1332743</tid>
<number>8</number>The Central Registrar shall forward to the multi- State 
co- operative society a copy of the registered amendment together with 
a certificate signed by him within a period of one month from the date 
of registration thereof and such certificate shall be conclusive 
evidence that the amendment has been duly registered.

</section>

<section><tid>823985</tid>
<number>9</number>Where the Central Registrar refuses to register an amendment of 
the bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society, he shall 
communicate the order of refusal together with the reasons therefor to 
the Chief Executive of the society in the manner pres ribed within 
fifteen days from the date of such refusal:
Provided that if the application for registration is not disposed of 
within a period of three months specified in sub- section (7) or the 
Central Registrar fails to communicate the order of refusal within 
that period, the application shall be deemed to ha e been accepted for 
registration and the Central Registrar shall issue registration 
certificate in accordance with the provisions of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1976563</tid>
<number>12</number>When amendment of bye- laws comes into force.- An amendment of the 
bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society shall, unless it is 
expressed to come into operation on a particular day, come into force 
on the day on which it is registered.


</article>



<article><tid>197639</tid>
<number> 13</number> Change of name.-
<section><tid>359393</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society may, by an  
amendment of its bye- laws, change its name but such change shall not 
affect any right or obligation of the multi- State co- operative society 
or of any of its members or past members, an any legal proceedings 
which might have been continued or commenced by or against the 
multi- State co- operative society by its former name, may be continued 
or commenced by or against its new name.

</section>

<section><tid>1488828</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a multi- State co- operative society changes its name, the 
Central Registrar shall enter the new name on the register of 
multi- State co- operative society in place of the former name and shall 
amend the certificate of registration accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>599228</tid>
<number>14</number>Change of address.- Every multi- State co- operative society shall 
have a principal place of business and an address registered in the 
manner prescribed to which all notices and communications may be sent.


</article>



<article><tid>669216</tid>
<number> 15</number> Publication of name by multi- State co- operative society.- Every 
multi- State co- operative society-
<section><tid>1394579</tid>
<number>a</number>shall paint or affix its name and the address of its registered 
office and keep the same painted or affixed, on the outside of every 
office or place in which its business is carried on, in conspicuous 
position, in letters easily legible; and if the haracters employed 
therefor are not those of the language, or of one of the languages in 
general use in that locality, also in the characters of that language 
or of one of those languages;

</section>

<section><tid>120952</tid>
<number>b</number>shall have its name engraven in legible characters on its seal; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1606444</tid>
<number>c</number>shall have its name and the address of its registered office 
mentioned in legible characters in all its business letters, in all 
its bill heads and letter paper, and in all its notices and other 
official publications; and also have its name so mentio ed in all 
bills of exchange, hundies, promissory notes, endorsements, cheques 
and orders for money or goods purporting to be signed by or on behalf 
of the multi- State co- operative society, and in all bills of parcels, 
invoices, receipts and letters of c edit of the multi- State 
co- operative society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>829115</tid>
<number> 16</number> Liability.-
<section><tid>467151</tid>
<number>1</number>No multi- State co- operative society with unlimited  
liability shall be registered after the commencement of this Act:
Provided that where a multi- State co- operative society with unlimited 
liability was functioning before the commencement of this Act, such a 
society shall exercise the option within a period of one year from 
such commencement either to continue to functio as such or to convert 
itself into a multi- State co- operative society with limited liability 
by following the procedure specified in sub- sections (2) to (4).


</section>

<section><tid>926626</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules, a multi- State 
co- operative society may, by an amendment of its bye- laws, change the 
extent of its liability.

</section>

<section><tid>272426</tid>
<number>3</number>When a multi- State co- operative society has passed a resolution to 
change the extent of its liability, it shall give notice thereof in 
writing to all its members and creditors, and, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the bye- laws or contract to th contrary, any 
member or creditor shall, during the period of one month from the date 
of service of the notice upon him, have the option of withdrawing his 
shares, deposits or loans, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>519249</tid>
<number>4</number>Any member or creditor who does not exercise his option within the 
period specified in sub- section (3) shall be deemed to have assented 
to the change.

</section>

<section><tid>394540</tid>
<number>5</number>An amendment of a bye- law of a multi- State co- operative society 
changing the extent of its liability shall not be registered or shall 
not take effect until either-

<subsection><tid>1389478</tid>
<number>a</number>the assent thereto of all members and creditors has been obtained; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1702108</tid>
<number>b</number>all claims of members and creditors who exercise the option 
referred to in sub- section (3) within the period specified therein 
have been met in full or otherwise satisfied.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1301556</tid>
<number> 17</number> Amalgamation or transfer of assets and liabilities, or division 
of multi- State co- operative societies.-
<section><tid>1970727</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative  
society may, by a resolution passed by a majority of not less than 
two- thirds of the members, present and voting at general meeting of 
the society held for the purpose,-

<subsection><tid>1398604</tid>
<number>a</number>transfer its assets and liabilities in whole or in part to any 
other multi- State co- operative society or co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>371121</tid>
<number>b</number>divide itself into two or more multi- State co- operative societies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>540873</tid>
<number>c</number>divide itself into two or more co- operative societies.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1374642</tid>
<number>2</number>Any two or more multi- State co- operative societies may, by a 
resolution passed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the 
members present and voting at a general meeting of each such society, 
amalgamate themselves and form a new multi- State co- perative society.

</section>

<section><tid>1365674</tid>
<number>3</number>The resolution of a multi- State co- operative society under 
sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall contain all particulars of 
the transfer or division or amalgamation, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>598065</tid>
<number>4</number>When a multi- State co- operative society has passed a resolution 
under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), it shall give notice thereof 
in writing to all the members and creditors, and, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the bye- laws or contract to the contrary,
any member or creditor shall, during the period of one month of the 
date of service of the notice upon him, have the option of withdrawing 
his shares, deposits or loans, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>222558</tid>
<number>5</number>Any member or creditor who does not exercise his option within the 
period specified in sub- section (4) shall be deemed to have assented 
to the proposals contained in the resolution.

</section>

<section><tid>1162533</tid>
<number>6</number> (a) A resolution passed by a multi- State co- operative society 
under this section shall not take effect until the assent thereto of 
all the members and creditors has been obtained.

<subsection><tid>1076839</tid>
<number>b</number>The multi- State co- operative society shall make arrangements for 
meeting in full or otherwise satisfying all claims of the members and 
creditors who exercise the option within the period specified in 
sub- section (4).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1533116</tid>
<number>7</number>On receipt of an application for the registration of new societies 
formed by division in accordance with the resolution passed under 
sub- section (1) or of a new society formed by amalgamation in 
accordance with the resolution passed under sub- section (2), the 
Central Registrar, on being satisfied that the resolution has become 
effective under sub- section (6) shall, unless for reasons to be 
recorded in writing he thinks fit to refuse so to do, register the new 
society or societies, as the case may be, and the bye- laws thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1195116</tid>
<number>8</number>On the issue of an order under sub- section (7), the provisions of 
section 21 shall, so far as may be, apply to the multi- State 
co- operative society so divided or the multi- State co- operative 
societies so amalgamated.

</section>

<section><tid>593897</tid>
<number>9</number>Where a resolution passed by a multi- State co- operative society 
under this section involves the transfer of any assets and 
liabilities, the resolution shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
in any other law for the time being in force, be a suffic ent 
conveyance to vest the assets and liabilities in the transferee 
without any further assurance.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1899648</tid>
<number> 18</number> Central Registrar to prepare scheme of amalgamation or 
reorganization of a co- operative bank in certain cases.- When an order 
of moratorium has been made by the Central Government under 
sub- section (2) of section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10  
  of <year>1949</year>) in respect of a co- operative bank, the Central Registrar, 
with the previous approval of the Reserve Bank in writing, may, during 
the period of moratorium, prepare a scheme-
<section><tid>33550</tid>
<number>a</number>for the amalgamation of the co- operative bank with any other 
co- operative bank; or

</section>

<section><tid>719646</tid>
<number>b</number>for the reorganisation of the co- operative bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1496434</tid>
<number> 19</number> Promotion of subsidiary institution.-
<section><tid>225786</tid>
<number>1</number>Any multi- State  
co- operative society may, by a resolution passed at general meeting by 
a majority of members present and voting, promote one or more 
subsidiary institutions, which may be registered under any l w for the 
time being in force, for the furtherance of its stated objects.

</section>

<section><tid>1054498</tid>
<number>2</number>Any subsidiary institution promoted under sub- section (1) shall 
exist only as long as general body of the multi- State co- operative 
society deems its existence necessary:
Provided that a multi- State co- operative society, while promoting such 
a subsidiary institution, shall not transfer or assign its substantive 
part of business or activities undertaken in furtherance of its stated 
objects. Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1949814</tid>
<number>a</number>an institution shall be deemed to be a subsidiary institution if 
the multi- State co- operative society-

<subsubsection><tid>165432</tid>
<number>i</number>controls the management or board of directors or members of 
governing body of such institution; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>264230</tid>
<number>ii</number>holds more than half in nominal value of equity shares of such 
institutions; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1182032</tid>
<number>iii</number>if one or more members of such multi- State co- operative society, 
hold whether by themselves or together with subsidiary institution or 
their relatives, as the case may be, the majority of equity shares in 
that institution;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>683079</tid>
<number>b</number>a subsidiary institution shall not include a partnership firm.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1569119</tid>
<number>3</number>The annual reports and accounts of any such subsidiary institution 
shall be placed each year before general meeting of the promoting 
multi- State co- operative society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>727211</tid>
<number>20</number>Liability of a co- operative bank to Deposit Insurance and Credit 
Guarantee Corporation.- Notwithstanding anything contained in section 
 17 or any other provision of this Act, where a co- operative bank, 
being an insured bank within the meaning of the De osit Insurance and 
Credit Guarantee Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>), is amalgamated or 
reorganised and the Deposit Insurance Corporation has become liable to 
pay to the depositors of the insured bank under sub- section (2) of 
section 16 of that Act, th bank with which such insured bank is 
amalgamated or the new co- operative bank formed after such 
amalgamation, or, as the case may be, the insured bank or transferee 
bank shall be under an obligation to repay to the Deposit Insurance 
Corporation in the c rcumstances, to the extent and in the manner 
referred to in section 21 of the Deposit Insurance and Credit 
Guarantee Corporation Act, <year>1961</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1764046</tid>
<number> 21</number> Cancellation of registration certificate of multi- State 
co- operative societies in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1448665</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the whole of the  
assets and liabilities of a multi- State co- operative society are 
transferred to another multi- State co- operative society or to a 
co- operative society in accordance with the provisions of section 17, 
the registration of the first- mentioned multi- State co- operative 
society shall stand cancelled and the society shall be deemed to have 
been dissolved and shall cease to exist as a co porate body.

</section>

<section><tid>1271235</tid>
<number>2</number>Where two or more multi- State co- operative societies are 
amalgamated into a new multi- State co- operative society in accordance 
with the provisions of section 17, the registration of each of the 
amalgamating societies shall stand cancelled on the regi tration of 
the new society, and each of the amalgamating societies shall be 
deemed to have been dissolved and shall cease to exist as a corporate 
body.

</section>

<section><tid>1700862</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a multi- State co- operative society divides itself into two 
or more multi- State co- operative societies or two or more co- operative 
societies in accordance with the provisions of section 17, the 
registration of that society shall stand cancelled n the registration 
of the new societies, and that society shall be deemed to have been 
dissolved and shall cease to exist as a corporate body.

</section>

<section><tid>1710516</tid>
<number>4</number>The amalgamation or division of multi- State co- operative societies 
shall not in any manner whatsoever affect any right or obligation of 
the resulting multi- State co- operative society or societies or render 
defective any legal proceedings by or agains the multi- State 
co- operative society or societies, and any legal proceedings that 
might have been continued or commenced by or against the multi- State 
co- operative society or societies, as the case may be, before the 
amalgamation or division, may be con inued or commenced by or against 
the resulting multi- State co- operative society or societies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>483956</tid>
<number> 22</number> Conversion of a co- operative society into a multi- State 
co- operative society.-
<section><tid>1311622</tid>
<number>1</number>A co- operative society may, by an amendment  
of its bye- laws, extend its jurisdiction and convert itself into a 
multi- State co- operative society: Provided that no such amendment of 
bye- laws of a co- operative society shall be valid unless it has been 
registered by the Central Registrar.

</section>

<section><tid>596264</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) Every proposal for such amendment of bye- laws shall be 
forwarded to the Central Registrar in accordance with the provisions 
contained in sub- section (4) of section 11.

<subsection><tid>105989</tid>
<number>b</number>If the Central Registrar, after consulting the Registrars of 
Co- operative Societies of the States concerned, has satisfied himself 
that such amendment-

<subsubsection><tid>186404</tid>
<number>i</number>fulfils the requirements of the members being from more than one 
State;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1765760</tid>
<number>ii</number>is in accordance with the provisions contained in sub- section (4) 
of section 11,
he may register the amendment within a period of six months from the 
date of receipt thereof by him:

Provided that no co- operative society shall be deemed to have been 
converted into a multi- State co- operative society on any ground 
whatsoever unless such society is registered as a multi- State 
co- operative society.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1490806</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Registrar shall forward to the co- operative society a 
copy of the registered amendment together with a certificate signed by 
him and such certificate shall be conclusive evidence that the 
amendment has been registered.

</section>

<section><tid>1517140</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the Central Registrar refuses to register an amendment of 
the bye- laws of a co- operative society, he shall communicate the order 
of refusal together with the reasons therefor to the society in the 
manner prescribed within seven days from the da e of refusal.

</section>

<section><tid>1919372</tid>
<number>5</number> (a) Once the amendment of bye- laws has been registered by the 
Central Registrar, the co- operative society shall, as from the date of 
registration of amendment, become a multi- State co- operative society.

<subsection><tid>184298</tid>
<number>b</number>The Central Registrar shall forward to the co- operative society a 
certificate signed by him to the effect that such society has been 
registered as a multi- State co- operative society under this Act and 
also forward a copy of the same to the Registrar f Co- operative 
Societies of the State concerned.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>690834</tid>
<number>c</number>The Registrar of Co- operative Societies referred to in clause (b) 
shall thereupon make an order directing that the society had, as from 
the date of registration by the Central Registrar, ceased to be a 
society under the law relating to co- operative s cieties in force in 
that State.
CHAP

REGISTRATION AND FUNCTIONS OF FEDERAL CO- OPERATIVES

CHAPTER III

REGISTRATION AND FUNCTIONS OF FEDERAL CO- OPERATIVES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1067071</tid>
<number> 23</number> Registration of federal co- operative.-
<section><tid>1691018</tid>
<number>1</number>Every federal  
co- operative shall obtain registration certificate in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>487178</tid>
<number>2</number>Every federal co- operative shall in its general meeting be 
represented by its member co- operative.

</section>

<section><tid>612950</tid>
<number>3</number>The classification of federal co- operative and other terms and 
conditions applicable to it shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1761602</tid>
<number>4</number>All provisions of this Act, applicable to a multi- State 
co- operative society shall, as far as may be, apply to a federal 
co- operative.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1124029</tid>
<number> 24</number> Functions of federal co- operative.-
<section><tid>1562753</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions  
of this Act and any other law for the time being in force, a federal 
co- operative may discharge the functions to facilitate the voluntary 
formation and democratic functioning of co- oper tive societies as 
federal co- operative or multi- State co- operatives based on self- help 
and mutual aid.

</section>

<section><tid>1628934</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in 
sub- section (1), the federal co- operative may-

<subsection><tid>1810843</tid>
<number>a</number>ensure compliance of the co- operative principles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>560915</tid>
<number>b</number>make model bye- laws and policies for consideration of its member 
co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>436499</tid>
<number>c</number>provide specialised training, education and data- base information;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630908</tid>
<number>d</number>undertake research, evaluation and assist in preparation of 
perspective development plans for its member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>500533</tid>
<number>e</number>promote harmonious relations amongst member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>202056</tid>
<number>f</number>help member co- operative to settle disputes among themselves;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1212173</tid>
<number>g</number>undertake business services on behalf of its member co- operative, 
if specifically required by or under the resolution of the general 
body or the board, or bye- laws of a member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>679098</tid>
<number>h</number>provide management development services to a member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>576598</tid>
<number>i</number>evolve code of conduct for observance by a member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>924745</tid>
<number>j</number>evolve viability norms for a member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1786338</tid>
<number>k</number>provide legal aid and advice to a member co- operative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>741881</tid>
<number>l</number>assist member co- operative in organising self- help;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1856170</tid>
<number>m</number>develop market information system, logo brand promotion, quality 
control and technology upgradation.
CHAP

MEMBERS OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES AND THEIR DUTIES, RIGHTS 
AND 
LIABILITIES

CHAPTER IV

MEMBERS OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES AND THEIR DUTIES, RIGHTS 
AND LIABILITIES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>659281</tid>
<number> 25</number> Persons who may become members.-
<section><tid>445162</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be admitted  
as a member of a multi- State co- operative society except the 
following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1099050</tid>
<number>a</number>an individual, competent to contract under section 11 of the 
Indian Contract Act, <year>1872</year> (9 of <year>1872</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>280220</tid>
<number>b</number>any multi- State co- operative society or any co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1846444</tid>
<number>c</number>the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1982866</tid>
<number>d</number>a State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>152416</tid>
<number>e</number>the National Co- operative Development Corporation established 
under the National Co- operative Development Corporation Act, <year>1962</year> (26  
  of <year>1962</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1320807</tid>
<number>f</number>any other corporation owned or controlled by the Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370896</tid>
<number>g</number>any Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>889170</tid>
<number>h</number>such class or classes of persons or association of persons as may 
be permitted by the Central Registrar having regard to the nature and 
activities of a multi- State co- operative society.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1839168</tid>
<number>2</number>No individual person shall be eligible for admission as a member 
of a national co- operative society or a federal co- operative.

</section>

<section><tid>955040</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person eligible for membership of a multi- State co- operative 
society may, on his application, be admitted as a member by such 
society.

</section>

<section><tid>526962</tid>
<number>4</number>Every application for admission as a member of a multi- State 
co- operative society shall be disposed of by such society within a 
period of four months from the date of receipt of the application, and 
the decision of such society on the application sha l be communicated 
to the applicant within fifteen days from the date of such decision:
Provided that if the application is not disposed of within the period 
aforesaid, or the decision is not communicated within a period of 
fifteen days of the expiry of the aforesaid period of four months, the 
multi- State co- operative society shall be deeme to have made a 
decision, on the date of expiry of such period, refusing admission to 
the applicant.


</section>

<section><tid>467019</tid>
<number>5</number>It shall be the duty of every member of a multi- State co- operative 
society to promote and protect the interests and objects of such 
society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635660</tid>
<number>26</number>Nominal or associate member of society.- A multi- State 
co- operative society may, if provided in its bye- laws, admit a person 
as nominal or associate member:
Provided that no such nominal or associate member shall be entitled to 
subscribe the shares of such society or have any interest in the 
management thereof including right to vote, elect as a director of the 
board or participate in the general body meetin s.



</article>



<article><tid>1996291</tid>
<number> 27</number> Educational course for members.-
<section><tid>697524</tid>
<number>1</number>Every multi- State  
co- operative society shall organise co- operative education programmes 
for its members, directors and employees.

</section>

<section><tid>183715</tid>
<number>2</number>Every multi- State co- operative society may provide funds for such 
co- operative education programmes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1889551</tid>
<number>28</number>Members not to exercise rights till due payment made.- No member 
of a multi- State co- operative society shall exercise the rights of a 
member, unless he has made the payment to the society in respect of 
membership, or has acquired such interest in the ociety, as may be 
specified in the bye- laws.


</article>



<article><tid>1340069</tid>
<number> 29</number> Disqualification for member of a multi- State co- operative 
society.- No person shall be eligible for being a member of a 
multi- State co- operative society if-
<section><tid>386198</tid>
<number>a</number>his business is in conflict or competitive with the business of 
such multi- State co- operative society; or

</section>

<section><tid>1976423</tid>
<number>b</number>he used for two consecutive years the services below the minimum 
level specified in the bye- laws; or

</section>

<section><tid>851872</tid>
<number>c</number>he has not attended three consecutive general meetings of the 
multi- State co- operative society and such absence has not been 
condoned by the members in the general meeting; or

</section>

<section><tid>16717</tid>
<number>d</number>he has made any default in payment of any amount to be paid to the 
multi- State co- operative society under the bye- laws of such society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>384590</tid>
<number> 30</number> Expulsion of members.-
<section><tid>1743951</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society may,  
by resolution passed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the 
members present and voting at a general meeting of members held for 
the purpose, expel a member for acts which are detrimental to the 
proper working of the society: Provided that the member concerned 
shall not be expelled unless he has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of making representation in the matter.

</section>

<section><tid>1936842</tid>
<number>2</number>No member of the multi- State co- operative society who has been 
expelled under sub- section (1), shall be eligible for re- admission as 
a member of that society, for a period of one year from the date of 
such expulsion.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1901753</tid>
<number> 31</number> Vote of members.- Every member of a multi- State co- operative 
society, including a member who is an employee of such society, shall 
have one vote in the affairs of the society:
Provided that-

<section><tid>413494</tid>
<number>a</number>a member who is an employee of such society shall not be entitled 
to vote-

<subsection><tid>523827</tid>
<number>i</number>at the election of a member of the board of such society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>874611</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any general meeting convened for framing the bye- laws of such 
society or any amendments thereto;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>861185</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an equality of votes, the chairperson shall have a 
casting vote;

</section>

<section><tid>1428581</tid>
<number>c</number>where any of the authorities, multi- State co- operative society or 
a co- operative society referred to in clauses (b) to (g) of 
sub- section (1) of section 25 is a member of a multi- State 
co- operative society, each person nominated by such authority or 
society, on the board in accordance with the provisions contained in 
this Act and the rules, shall, have one vote;

</section>

<section><tid>135715</tid>
<number>d</number>a multi- State co- operative society, the membership of which 
include co- operative societies or other multi- State co- operative 
societies, may provide in its bye- laws for an equitable system of 
voting having regard to the membership of, and the extent o business 
carried on, by such co- operative societies or multi- State co- operative 
societies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>761206</tid>
<number>32</number>Manner of exercising vote.- Every member of a multi- State 
co- operative society shall exercise his vote in person and no member 
shall be permitted to vote by proxy:
Provided that a multi- State co- operative society or a co- operative 
society or any other institution which is a member of any other 
multi- State co- operative society may, subject to the provisions of 
sub- section (3) of section 38 and the rules, appoint its 
representative to vote on its behalf in the affairs of such 
multi- State co- operative society.



</article>



<article><tid>1323965</tid>
<number> 33</number> Restriction on holding of shares.- No member, other than the 
authorities referred to in clauses (c) to (g) of sub- section
<section><tid>127129</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 25 or a multi- State co- operative society or a co- operative 
society, shall hold more than such portion of the total share capital 
of the society (in no case exceeding one- fifth thereof) as may be 
prescribed in the rules or bye- laws of such mutli- State co- operative 
society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1204326</tid>
<number>34</number>Restriction on transfer of shares or interest.- The transfer of 
share or interest of a member in the capital of a multi- State 
co- operative society shall be subject to such conditions as to maximum 
holding as specified in section 33.


</article>



<article><tid>1537560</tid>
<number> 35</number> Redemption of shares.-
<section><tid>698604</tid>
<number>1</number>Shares held in a multi- State  
co- operative society by any of the authorities referred to in clauses 
 (c) to (g) of sub- section (1) of section 25 shall be redeemable in 
accordance with the bye- laws of such multi- State co- operat ve society 
and in a case where the bye- laws do not contain any provision in this 
regard, in such manner as may be agreed upon between the multi- State 
co- operative society and such authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1399972</tid>
<number>2</number>The redemption of shares referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
on the face value of the shares.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>47120</tid>
<number> 36</number> Transfer of interest on death of members.-
<section><tid>1395553</tid>
<number>1</number>On the death of a  
member, a multi- State co- operative society may transfer the share or 
interest of the deceased member to the person nominated in accordance 
with the bye- laws made in this behalf or, if th re is no person 
nominated, to such person as may appear to the board to be the heir or 
legal representative of the deceased member, or pay to such nominee, 
heir or legal representative, as the case may be, a sum representing 
the value of such member' s sh re or interest as ascertained in 
accordance with the rules:
Provided that no such transfer or payment shall be made except with 
the consent of the nominee, heir or legal representative, as the case 
may be.


</section>

<section><tid>412089</tid>
<number>2</number>A multi- State co- operative society shall, unless within six months 
of the death of the member prevented by an order of a competent court, 
pay to such nominee, heir or legal representative, as the case may be, 
all other moneys due to the deceased mem er from the society.

</section>

<section><tid>198569</tid>
<number>3</number>All transfers and payments made by a multi- State co- operative 
society in accordance with the provisions of this section shall be 
valid and effectual against any demand made upon the society by any 
other person.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>50764</tid>
<number> 37</number> Liabilities of past member and estate of deceased member.-
<section><tid>1543102</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the liability of a past 
member or of the estate of a deceased member of a multi- State 
co- operative society for the debts of the society as the existed,-

<subsection><tid>1453145</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a past member, on the date on which he ceased to be 
a member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>595901</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a deceased member, on the date of his death, shall 
continue for a period of two years from such date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>896704</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where a 
multi- State co- operative society is ordered to be wound up under 
section 86, the liability of a past member who ceased to be a member 
or of the estate of a deceased member who died within two years 
immediately preceding the date of the order of winding up, shall 
continue until the entire liquidation proceedings are completed, but 
such liability shall extend only to the debts of the society as they 
existed on the date of cessation of membe ship or death, as the case 
may be.
CHAP

DIRECTION AND MANAGEMENT OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES

CHAPTER V

DIRECTION AND MANAGEMENT OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1682474</tid>
<number> 38</number> Constitution, powers and functions of general body.-
<section><tid>1330528</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
general body of a multi- State co- operative society shall consist of 
all the members of such society:
Provided that where the bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society 
provide for the constitution of a smaller body consisting of delegates 
of members of the society elected or selected in accordance with such 
bye- laws, that smaller body shall exercise such powers of the general 
body as may be prescribed or as may be specified in the bye- laws of 
the society.


</section>

<section><tid>460407</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the rules and the bye- laws, 
the ultimate authority of a multi- State co- operative society shall 
vest in the general body of its members:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall affect the 
exercise by the board or any officer of a multi- State co- operative 
society of any power conferred on such board or such officer by this 
Act or the rules or the bye- laws.


</section>

<section><tid>174520</tid>
<number>3</number>Where in any meeting of the general body or the board of a 
multi- State co- operative society, a co- operative society or another 
multi- State co- operative society is to be represented, such 
co- operative society or other multi- State co- operative society hall be 
represented in such meeting only through the Chairperson or the 
president or the Chief Executive or a member of the board of such 
co- operative society or other multi- State co- operative society, as the 
case may be, if such member is so authorised y the board and where 
there is no board of such co- operative society or other multi- State 
co- operative society, for whatever reasons, through the administrator, 
by whatever name called, of such co- operative society or other 
multi- State co- operative socie y:
Provided that where the bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society 
provide for representation of other institutions in any meeting of 
general body or the board of such multi- State co- operative society, 
such institutions shall be represented through i s nominee.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>879533</tid>
<number> 39</number> Annual general meeting of general body.-
<section><tid>546079</tid>
<number>1</number>The board of every  
multi- State co- operative society shall, within such period as may be 
prescribed, and not later than six months after the close of the 
corresponding year, call the annual general meeting i the manner 
prescribed for the purpose of-

<subsection><tid>718410</tid>
<number>a</number>consideration of the audited statement of accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>23450</tid>
<number>b</number>consideration of the audit report and annual report;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1176903</tid>
<number>c</number>consideration of audit compliance report;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>482546</tid>
<number>d</number>disposal of net profits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1016951</tid>
<number>e</number>review of operational deficit, if any;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693038</tid>
<number>f</number>creation of specific reserves and other funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291564</tid>
<number>g</number>approval of the annual budget;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>233870</tid>
<number>h</number>review of actual utilisation of reserve and other funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1165361</tid>
<number>i</number>approval of the long- term perspective plan and the annual 
operational plan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1436448</tid>
<number>j</number>review of annual report and accounts of subsidiary institution, if 
any;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>794260</tid>
<number>k</number>expulsion of members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1233920</tid>
<number>l</number>list of employees who are relatives of members of the board or of 
the Chief Executive;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>775361</tid>
<number>m</number>amendment of bye- laws, if any;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>715709</tid>
<number>n</number>formulation of code of conduct for the members of the board and 
officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1830941</tid>
<number>o</number>election of members of the board, if any.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1655996</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the board of a multi- State co- operative society fails to 
convene the annual general meeting within the period specified in 
sub- section (1), the Central Registrar or the person authorised by him 
in this behalf shall be competent to convene such nnual general 
meeting within a period of ninety days from the date of expiry of the 
period mentioned in that sub- section and the expenditure incurred on 
such meeting shall be borne by the society.

</section>

<section><tid>147314</tid>
<number>3</number>At every annual general meeting of a multi- State co- operative 
society, the board shall lay before the society a statement showing 
the details of the loans or goods on credit, if any, given to any of 
the members of the board or to the spouse or a son or daughter of a 
member of the board during the preceding year or outstanding against 
him or against such spouse or son or daughter of the member of the 
board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171469</tid>
<number> 40</number> Special general meeting of general body.-
<section><tid>1571721</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Executive  
may, at any time, on the direction of the board, call a special 
general meeting of the society and shall call such meeting within one 
month after the receipt of a requisition in writing from the Central 
Registrar or from such member or members or a proportion of the total 
number of members, as may be provided in the bye- laws.

</section>

<section><tid>279540</tid>
<number>2</number>If a special general meeting of a multi- State co- operative society 
is not called in accordance with the requisition referred to in 
sub- section (1), the Central Registrar or any person authorised by him 
in this behalf shall have the power to call such meeting and that 
meeting shall be deemed to be a meeting called by the Chief Executive 
in accordance with the provisions of that sub- section and the Central 
Registrar may order that the expenditure incurred in calling such 
meeting shall be paid out of th funds of the society or by such person 
or persons who, in the opinion of the Central Registrar, was or were 
responsible for the refusal or failure to convene the special general 
meeting.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>138403</tid>
<number> 41</number> Board of directors.-
<section><tid>755039</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and  
rules, there shall be a board of directors for every multi- State 
co- operative society consisting of such number of members as specified 
in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>1447426</tid>
<number>2</number>The members of a multi- State co- operative society, by a resolution 
in a general meeting, shall elect directors who shall be members of 
board.

</section>

<section><tid>544158</tid>
<number>3</number>The board shall consist of such number of directors as may be 
specified in the bye- laws:
Provided that the maximum number of directors in no case shall exceed 
twenty- one:

Provided further that the board may co- opt two directors in addition 
to twenty- one directors specified in the first proviso:

Provided also that the functional directors in the national 
co- operative societies shall also be the members of the board and such 
members shall be excluded for the purpose of counting the total number 
of directors specified in the first proviso.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>496858</tid>
<number>42</number>Association of employees in management decision making 
process.- Every multi- State co- operative society shall devise such 
procedure, as may be specified in the bye- laws or in the 
administrative instructions of such society, for the association of 
the epresentatives of employees of such multi- State co- operative 
societies at such level or bodies as may be specified in the bye- laws 
or the instructions issued in this regard, in the management decision 
making process.


</article>



<article><tid>591256</tid>
<number> 43</number> Disqualifications for being a member of board.-
<section><tid>320640</tid>
<number>1</number>No member of  
any multi- State co- operative society or nominee of a member, society 
or a national co- operative society shall be eligible for being chosen 
as, or for being, a member of the board of such multi- State 
co- operative society or a national co- operative society, or of any 
other co- operative society to which the multi- State co- operative 
society is affiliated, if such member-

<subsection><tid>555782</tid>
<number>a</number>has been adjudged by a competent court to be insolvent or of 
unsound mind;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1190272</tid>
<number>b</number>is concerned or participates in the profits of any contract with 
the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1045662</tid>
<number>c</number>has been convicted for an offence involving moral turpitude;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>624070</tid>
<number>d</number>holds any office or place of profit under the society:
Provided that the Chief Executive or such full- time employee of the 
society as may be notified by the Central Government from time to time 
or a person elected by the employees of such society to represent them 
on the board of such society shall be eligi le for being chosen as, or 
for being, a member of such board;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>46402</tid>
<number>e</number>has been a member of the society for less than twelve months 
immediately preceding the date of such election or appointment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>231107</tid>
<number>f</number>has interest in any business of the kind carried on by the society 
of which he is a member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>745185</tid>
<number>g</number>has taken loan or goods on credit from the society of which he is 
a member, or is otherwise indebted to such society and after the 
receipt of a notice of default issued to him by such society, has 
defaulted-

<subsubsection><tid>608046</tid>
<number>i</number>in repayment of such loan or debt or in payment of the price of 
the goods taken on credit, as the case may be, within the date fixed 
for such repayment or payment or where such date is extended, which in 
no case shall exceed six months, within the da e so extended, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1112266</tid>
<number>ii</number>when such loan or debt or the price of goods taken on credit is 
to be paid in instalments, in payment of any instalment, and the 
amount in default or any part thereof has remained unpaid on the 
expiry of six months from the date of such default:
Provided that a member of the board who has ceased to hold office as 
such under this clause shall not be eligible, for a period of one 
year, from the date on which he ceased to hold office, for re- election 
as a member of the board of the multi- State co- o erative society of 
which he was a member or for the election to the board of any other 
multi- State co- operative society;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1716714</tid>
<number>h</number>is a person against whom any amount due under a decree, decision 
or order is pending recovery under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1236450</tid>
<number>i</number>is retained or employed as a legal practitioner on behalf of or 
against the multi- State co- operative society, or on behalf of or 
against any other multi- State co- operative society which is a member 
of the former society.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause,'' legal practitioner'' 
has the same meaning as in clause (i) of sub- section (1) of section 2 
of the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>682662</tid>
<number>j</number>has been convicted for any offence under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>241842</tid>
<number>k</number>is disqualified for being a member under section 29;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1742572</tid>
<number>l</number>has been expelled as a member under section 30;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1792972</tid>
<number>m</number>absents himself from three consecutive board meetings and such 
absence has not been condoned to by the board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488703</tid>
<number>n</number>absents himself from three consecutive general body meetings and 
such absence has not been condoned by the members in the general body.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>215949</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be eligible for being elected as member of 
board of a multi- State co- operative society for a period of five years 
if the board of such multi- State co- operative society fails-

<subsection><tid>1020586</tid>
<number>a</number>to conduct elections of the board under section 45; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>814674</tid>
<number>b</number>to call the annual general meeting under section 39; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>821572</tid>
<number>c</number>to prepare the financial statement and present the same in the 
annual general meeting.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>306384</tid>
<number> 44</number> Prohibition to hold office of chairperson or president or 
vice- chairperson or vice- president in certain cases.-
<section><tid>516110</tid>
<number>1</number>No member of  
a board shall be eligible to be elected as the chairperson or 
president or vice- chairperson or vice- president of a multi- S ate 
co- operative society if such member is a Minister in the Central 
Government or a State Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1826224</tid>
<number>2</number>No member of a board shall be eligible to be elected as the 
chairperson or president of a multi- State co- operative society, after 
he has held the office, as such during two consecutive terms, whether 
full or part: Provided that a member who has ceased to hold the 
office of the chairperson or president continuously for one full term 
shall again be eligible for election to the office as such.
Explanation.- Where any member holding the office of the chairperson or 
president at the commencement of this Act is again elected to that 
office after such commencement, he shall for the purpose of this 
section, be deemed to have held office for one term before such 
election.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1726839</tid>
<number> 45</number> Elections of members of board.-
<section><tid>975342</tid>
<number>1</number>The conduct of elections to  
the board of a multi- State co- operative society shall be the 
responsibility of the existing board.

</section>

<section><tid>605557</tid>
<number>2</number>The election of members of board shall be held by secret ballot in 
the manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1511691</tid>
<number>3</number>The election of the members of the board shall be held in the 
general meeting of the members of the multi- State co- operative 
society.

</section>

<section><tid>1198803</tid>
<number>4</number>The elected members of the board shall, if the bye- laws of such 
society permit, be eligible for re- election.

</section>

<section><tid>565832</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of office of the elected members of the board shall be 
such, not exceeding five years from the date of elections, as may be 
specified in the bye- laws of a multi- State co- operative society:
Provided that elected members shall continue to hold office till their 
successors are elected or nominated under the provisions of this Act 
or the rules or bye- laws and assume charge of their office.


</section>

<section><tid>767877</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the board fails to conduct election of the members of board, 
the Central Registrar shall hold the election within a period of 
ninety days from the date when such election became due.

</section>

<section><tid>843937</tid>
<number>7</number>No person shall be eligible to be elected as a member of the board 
of a multi- State co- operative society unless he is a member of the 
general body of that society.

</section>

<section><tid>1029955</tid>
<number>8</number>The expenses for holding election by the Central Registrar shall 
be borne by the multi- State co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>1985555</tid>
<number>9</number>The Central Government may make rules generally to provide for or 
to regulate matters in respect of election of members of the board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1986126</tid>
<number>46</number>Holding of office in co- operative society.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, no person shall be eligible to hold, 
at the same time, office of a president or chairperson or 
vice- president or vice- chairperson on the board of more than two 
multi- State co- operative societies.


</article>



<article><tid>319432</tid>
<number>47</number>Removal of elected members by general body.- An elected member of 
a board, who has acted adversely to the interests of multi- State 
co- operative society, may on the basis of a report of the Central 
Registrar or otherwise be removed from the board upon resolution of 
the general body passed at its meeting by a majority of not less than 
two- third of the members present and voting at the meeting:
Provided that the member concerned shall not be removed unless he has 
been given a reasonable opportunity of making a representation in the 
matter.



</article>



<article><tid>388679</tid>
<number> 48</number> Nominee of Central Government or State Government on board.-
<section><tid>1465898</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where the Central Government or a State Government has subscribed to 
the share capital of a multi- State co- operative society, the Central 
authorised by the Central Government or the State Government shall 
have right to nominate on the board such number of persons as its 
members on the following basis, namely:- Government or the State 
Government, as the case ay be, or any person

<subsection><tid>1716479</tid>
<number>a</number>where the total amount of issued equity share capital held by the 
Central Government or the State Government is less than twenty- six per 
cent. of the total issued equity share capital, one member of the 
board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1738192</tid>
<number>b</number>where the total amount of issued equity share capital held by the 
Central Government or the State Government is twenty- six per cent or 
more but less than fifty- one per cent. of the total issued equity 
share capital, two members of the board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1340917</tid>
<number>c</number>where the total amount of issued equity share capital held by the 
Central Government or the State Government is fifty- one per cent. or 
more of the total issued share capital, three members of the board:
Provided that the number of such nominated persons shall not exceed 
one- third of the total number of members of the board:

Provided further that where the Central Government or a State 
Government has guaranteed the repayment of principal and payment of 
interest on debentures issued by a multi- State co- operative society or 
has guaranteed the repayment of principal and payment of interest on 
loans and advances to a multi- State co- operative society or has given 
any assistance by way of grants or otherwise to a multi- State 
co- operative society, the Central Government or the State Government 
in this behalf, as the case may be, or any person authorised by the 
Central Government, shall have the right to nominate person on the 
board of such a society in the manner as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1680618</tid>
<number>2</number>A person nominated under this section shall hold office during the 
pleasure of the Government by which he has been so nominated.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1571234</tid>
<number> 49</number> Powers and functions of board.-
<section><tid>1406182</tid>
<number>1</number>The board may exercise all  
such powers as may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
carrying out its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1801089</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such 
powers shall include the power-

<subsection><tid>1281676</tid>
<number>a</number>to admit members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744899</tid>
<number>b</number>to interpret the organisational objectives and set- up specific 
goals to be achieved towards these objectives;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>571734</tid>
<number>c</number>to make periodic appraisal of operations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>423742</tid>
<number>d</number>to appoint and remove a Chief Executive and such other employees 
of the society as are not required to be appointed by the Chief 
Executive;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549474</tid>
<number>e</number>to make provisions for regulating the appointment of employees of 
the multi- State co- operative society and the scales of pay, allowances 
and other conditions of service of, including disciplinary action 
against such employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>231129</tid>
<number>f</number>to place the annual report, annual financial statements, annual 
plan and budget for the approval of the general body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>807746</tid>
<number>g</number>to consider audit and compliance report and place the same before 
the general body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>572176</tid>
<number>h</number>to acquire or dispose of immovable property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>790383</tid>
<number>i</number>to review membership in other co- operatives;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1430020</tid>
<number>j</number>to approve annual and supplementary budget;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>78558</tid>
<number>k</number>to raise funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735041</tid>
<number>l</number>to sanction loans to the members; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1590435</tid>
<number>m</number>to take such other measures or to do such other acts as may be 
prescribed or required under this Act or the bye- laws or as may be 
delegated by the general body.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>250279</tid>
<number> 50</number> Meeting of board.-
<section><tid>119503</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Executive shall convene the  
meetings of the board at the instance of the chairperson or president 
of the multi- State co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>695042</tid>
<number>2</number>The total number of meetings of the board in a year and the venue 
of meetings as may be specified in the bye- laws:
Provided that the board shall meet at least once in every quarter:

Provided further that not more than two persons may be invited by the 
board in its meetings.


</section>

<section><tid>654620</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairperson, or if for any reason, he is unable to attend a 
meeting of the board, any other member of the board chosen by the 
members of the board present from amongst themselves at the meeting, 
shall preside at the meeting.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1036636</tid>
<number> 51</number> Chief Executive.-
<section><tid>1656285</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Chief Executive, by  
whatever designation called, of every multi- State co- operative society 
to be appointed by the board and he shall be a full- time employee of 
such multi- State co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>868875</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive shall be a member of the board and of the 
Executive Committee and such other committees or sub- committees as may 
be constituted under sub- section (1) of section 53.

</section>

<section><tid>1137203</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Central Government or the State Government holds 
fifty- one per cent. or more of the equity share capital or of total 
shares of the multi- State co- operative society, the salary and 
allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of serv ce 
including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits of the Chief 
Executive shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613880</tid>
<number> 52</number> Powers and functions of Chief Executive.- The Chief Executive 
shall under the general superintendence, direction and control of the 
board, exercise the powers and discharge the functions specified 
below, namely:-
<section><tid>1497741</tid>
<number>a</number>day- to- day management of the business of the 
multi- State- co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>474137</tid>
<number>b</number>operating the accounts of the multi- State co- operative society and 
be responsible for making arrangements for safe custody of cash;

</section>

<section><tid>556770</tid>
<number>c</number>signing on the documents for and on behalf of the multi- State 
co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>1907800</tid>
<number>d</number>making arrangements for the proper maintenance of various books 
and records of the multi- State co- operative society and for the 
correct preparation, timely submission of periodical statements and 
returns in accordance with the provisions of this Act, the rules and 
the bye- laws;

</section>

<section><tid>759053</tid>
<number>e</number>convening meetings of the general body of the multi- State 
co- operative society, the board and the Executive Committee and other 
committees or sub- committees constituted under sub- section (1) of 
section 53 and maintaining proper records for such meeti gs;

</section>

<section><tid>1789674</tid>
<number>f</number>making appointments to the posts in the multi- State co- operative 
society in accordance with the bye- laws;

</section>

<section><tid>1540498</tid>
<number>g</number>assisting the board in the formulation of policies, objectives and 
planning;

</section>

<section><tid>1692521</tid>
<number>h</number>furnishing to the board periodical information necessary for 
appraising the operations and functions of the multi- State 
co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>821856</tid>
<number>i</number>appoint the person to sue or be sued on behalf of the multi- State 
co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>802079</tid>
<number>j</number>present the draft annual report and financial statements for the 
approval of the board within thirty days of closure of the financial 
year;

</section>

<section><tid>551383</tid>
<number>k</number>performing such other duties, and exercising such other powers, as 
may be specified in the bye- laws of the multi- State co- operative 
society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1323091</tid>
<number> 53</number> Committees of board.-
<section><tid>732681</tid>
<number>1</number>The board may, subject to such  
conditions as may be prescribed, constitute an Executive Committee and 
other committees or sub- committees as may be considered necessary:
Provided that other committees or sub- committees, other than the 
Executive Committee shall not exceed three.


</section>

<section><tid>1433621</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Committee or other committee or sub- committee 
referred to in sub- section (1) shall perform such functions as are 
assigned to it in accordance with the bye- laws of the multi- State 
co- operative society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1590839</tid>
<number> 54</number> Securing possession of records, etc.-
<section><tid>975728</tid>
<number>1</number>If- 

<subsection><tid>1706331</tid>
<number>a</number>the records, including registers and books of account of a 
multi- State co- operative society are likely to be tampered with or 
destroyed or the funds or other property of such society are likely to 
be mis- appropriated; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1781988</tid>
<number>b</number>the board of a multi- State co- operative society is reconstituted 
at a general meeting of the society; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>526324</tid>
<number>c</number>a multi- State co- operative society is ordered to be wound up under 
section 86 and the outgoing members of the board refuse to handover 
charge of the records and property of the society to those having or 
entitled to receive such charge,
the Chief Executive may apply to the magistrate within whose 
jurisdiction the multi- State co- operative society functions for 
securing the records and property of the society.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>686535</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of an application under sub- section (1), the magistrate 
may, by a warrant, authorise any police officer not below the rank of 
a sub- inspector to enter and search any place where such records and 
property are kept or are believed to be kept and to seize such records 
and property; and the records and property so seized shall be handed 
over to the new board or the liquidator, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1165619</tid>
<number>3</number>Every such search and seizure shall be made in accordance with the 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).
CHAP

PRIVILEGES OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES

CHAPTER VI

PRIVILEGES OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030647</tid>
<number>55</number>Charge and set- off in respect of share or contribution or 
interest of members.- A multi- State co- operative society shall have a 
charge on the share or contribution or interest in the capital and on 
the deposits of a member or past or deceased member a d on any 
dividend, bonus or profits payable to a member or past member or the 
estate of a deceased member in respect of any debt due from such 
member or past member or the estate of such deceased member to the 
society and may set- off any sum credited or ayable to a member or past 
member or the estate of deceased member in or towards payment of any 
such debt.


</article>



<article><tid>618859</tid>
<number> 56</number> Share or contribution or interest not liable to attachment.-
<section><tid>1525304</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of section 55, the share or contribution or 
interest of a member or past or deceased member in the capital of a 
multi- State co- operative society shall not be li ble to attachment or 
sale under any decree or order of any court in respect of any debt or 
liability incurred by such member, and an official assignee or a 
receiver under any law relating to insolvency shall not be entitled 
to, or have any claim on, suc share or contribution or interest.

</section>

<section><tid>1424031</tid>
<number>2</number>The reserve fund, or the bad debt reserves, or the provident fund 
of the employees, of a multi- State co- operative society invested by 
such society in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the 
bye- laws shall not be liable to attachment under ny decree or order of 
a court in respect of any debt or liability incurred by the society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>174715</tid>
<number> 57</number> Register of members.- Any register or list of members or shares 
kept by any multi- State co- operative society shall be prima facie 
evidence of any of the following particulars entered therein, namely:-
<section><tid>1987621</tid>
<number>a</number>the date on which any person entered in such register or list 
became a member; and

</section>

<section><tid>1725996</tid>
<number>b</number>the date on which any such person ceased to be a member.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>721986</tid>
<number> 58</number> Admissibility of copy of entry as evidence.-
<section><tid>459970</tid>
<number>1</number>A copy of any  
entry in a book of a multi- State co- operative society regularly kept 
in the course of its business shall, if certified in such manner as 
may be prescribed, be received in any suit or legal proceedings as 
prima facie evidence of the existence of such entry and shall be 
admitted as evidence of the matters, transactions and accounts therein 
recorded in every case where, and to the same extent, as the original 
entry itself is admissible.

</section>

<section><tid>912764</tid>
<number>2</number>No officer of a multi- State co- operative society and no officer in 
whose office the books of a multi- State co- operative society are 
deposited after liquidation shall, in any legal proceedings to which 
the society or the liquidator is not a party, be ompelled to produce 
any of the society' s books or documents the contents of which can be 
proved under this section, or to appear as a witness to prove the 
matters, transactions and accounts therein recorded, except under an 
order of a court or an arbitra or made for a special cause.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1519227</tid>
<number> 59</number> Exemption from compulsory registration of instruments.- Nothing in 
clauses (b) and (c) of sub- section
<section><tid>1870660</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 17 of the  
Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>) shall apply to-

<subsection><tid>758726</tid>
<number>a</number>any instrument relating to shares in a multi- State co- operative 
society notwithstanding that the assets of the society consist in 
whole or in part of immovable property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1784675</tid>
<number>b</number>any debenture issued by any such society and not creating, 
declaring, assigning, limiting or extinguishing any right, title or 
interest to or in immovable property, except in so far as it entitles 
the holder thereof to the security afforded by a regi tered instrument 
whereby the society has mortgaged, conveyed or otherwise transferred 
the whole or part of its immovable property or any interest therein to 
trustees upon trust for the benefit of the holders of such debentures; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1068440</tid>
<number>c</number>an endorsement upon transfer of any debenture issued by any such 
society.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795171</tid>
<number> 60</number> Deduction from salary to meet multi- State co- operative society' s 
claim in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1461093</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any  
law for the time being in force, a member of a multi- State 
co- operative society may execute an agreement in favour f that society 
providing that his employer disbursing his salary or wages shall be 
competent to deduct every month from the salary or wages payable to 
him, such amount as may be specified in the agreement and to pay the 
amount so deducted to the society n satisfaction of any debt or other 
demand the member owes to the society.

</section>

<section><tid>1757062</tid>
<number>2</number>On the execution of such agreement, the employer disbursing the 
salary or wages of the members shall, if so required by the 
multi- State co- operative society, by a requisition in writing and so 
long as the society does not intimate that the whole of s ch debt or 
other demand has been paid, make the deduction in accordance with the 
agreement and pay the amount so deducted to the society within a 
period of fourteen days of the date on which deduction has been made, 
as if it were a part of the salary or ages payable on the day as 
required under the Payment of Wages Act, <year>1936</year> (4 of <year>1936</year>), and such 
payment shall be valid discharge of the employer for his liability to 
pay the amount deducted.

</section>

<section><tid>1130974</tid>
<number>3</number>If after the receipt of a requisition made under sub- section (2), 
the employer disbursing the salary or wages of the member at any time 
fails to deduct the amount specified in the requisition from the 
salary or wages payable to the member concerned o makes default in 
remitting the amount deducted to the multi- State co- operative society, 
the society shall be entitled to recover any such amount from such 
employer as arrears of land revenue and the amount so due from such 
employer shall rank in priorit in respect of the liability of such 
employer equal to that of the salary or wages in arrears.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>997910</tid>
<number> 61</number> Government aid to multi- State co- operative 
societies.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, the Central Government or a State Government, on 
receipt of request from a multi- State co- operative society and with a 
vi w to promoting co- operative movement, may,-
<section><tid>1333537</tid>
<number>a</number>subscribe to the share capital of a multi- State co- operative 
society;

</section>

<section><tid>1076550</tid>
<number>b</number>give loans or make advances to a multi- State co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>1365206</tid>
<number>c</number>guarantee the repayment of principal and payment of interest on 
debentures issued by a multi- State co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>753245</tid>
<number>d</number>guarantee the repayment of share capital of a multi- State 
co- operative society and dividends thereon at such rates as may be 
specified by the Central Government or the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>241396</tid>
<number>e</number>guarantee the repayment of principal and payment of interest on 
loans and advances to a multi- State co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>838704</tid>
<number>f</number>give financial assistance in any other form, including subsidies, 
to any multi- State co- operative society; and

</section>

<section><tid>1402430</tid>
<number>g</number>provide aid to any other multi- State co- operative society on such 
terms and conditions as may be prescribed.
CHAP

PROPERTIES AND FUNDS OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES

CHAPTER VII

PROPERTIES AND FUNDS OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>595677</tid>
<number> 62</number> Funds not to be divided by way of profits.-
<section><tid>1179083</tid>
<number>1</number>No part of the  
funds, other than net profits, of a multi- State co- operative society 
shall be divided by way of bonus or dividend or otherwise distributed 
among its members.

</section>

<section><tid>676976</tid>
<number>2</number>The net profits of a multi- State co- operative society referred to 
in sub- section (1) in respect of a society earning profits shall be 
calculated by deducting from the gross profit for the year, all 
interest accrued and accruing in relation to amounts which are 
overdue, establishment charges, interest payable on loans and 
deposits, audit fees, working expenses including repairs, rent, taxes 
and depreciation, bonus payable to employees under the law relating to 
payment of bonus for the time being in fo ce, and equalisation fund 
for such bonus, provision for payment of income- tax and making 
approved donations under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), 
development rebate, provision for development fund, bad debt fund, 
price fluctuation fund, dividend e ualisation fund, share capital 
redemption fund, investment fluctuation fund, provision for retirement 
benefits to employees, and after providing for or writing off bad 
debts and losses not adjusted against any fund created out of profit:
Provided that such society may add to the net profits for the year 
interest accrued in the preceding years, but actually recovered during 
the year:

Provided further that in the case of such multi- State co- operative 
societies as do not have share capital, the surplus of income over 
expenditure shall not be treated as net profits and such surplus shall 
be dealt with in accordance with the bye- laws.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>105212</tid>
<number> 63</number> Disposal of net profits.-
<section><tid>878781</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society  
shall, out of its net profits in any year,-

<subsection><tid>1161261</tid>
<number>a</number>transfer an amount not less than twenty- five per cent. to the 
reserve fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1427247</tid>
<number>b</number>credit one per cent. to co- operative education fund maintained, 
by the National Co- operative Union of India Limited, New Delhi, in the 
manner as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>642882</tid>
<number>c</number>transfer an amount not less than ten per cent. to a reserve fund 
for meeting unforeseen losses.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>822588</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, the balance of 
the net profits may be utilised for all or any of the following 
purposes, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1784711</tid>
<number>a</number>payment of dividend to the members on their paid- up share capital 
at a rate not exceeding the prescribed limit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1837570</tid>
<number>b</number>constitution of, or contribution to, such special funds including 
education funds, as may be specified in the bye- laws;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>317963</tid>
<number>c</number>donation of amounts not exceeding five per cent. of the net 
profits for any purpose connected with the development of co- operative 
movement or charitable purpose as defined in section 2 of the 
Charitable Endowments Act, <year>1890</year> (6 of <year>1890</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1093074</tid>
<number>d</number>payment of ex gratia amount to employees of the multi- State 
co- operative society to the extent and in the manner specified in the 
bye- laws.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1616186</tid>
<number> 64</number> Investment of funds.- A multi- State co- operative society may 
invest or deposit its funds-
<section><tid>1799237</tid>
<number>a</number>in a co- operative bank, State co- operative bank, co- operative land 
development bank or Central co- operative bank; or

</section>

<section><tid>474673</tid>
<number>b</number>in any of the securities specified in section 20 of the Indian 
Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>612130</tid>
<number>c</number>in the shares or securities of any other multi- State co- operative 
society or any co- operative society; or

</section>

<section><tid>608168</tid>
<number>d</number>in the shares, securities or assets of a subsidiary institution or 
any other institution; or

</section>

<section><tid>1452061</tid>
<number>e</number>with any other bank; or

</section>

<section><tid>651751</tid>
<number>f</number>in such other mode as may be provided in the bye- laws.
Explanation.- For the purposes of clause (e),'' bank'' means any 
banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking 
Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>), and includes-


<subsection><tid>138090</tid>
<number>i</number>the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank of India 
Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1644918</tid>
<number>ii</number>a subsidiary bank as defined in clause (k) of section 2 of the 
State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383728</tid>
<number>iii</number>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the 
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> 
 (5 of <year>1970</year>) or a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of 
the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfe of Undertakings) Act, 
 <year>1980</year> (40 of <year>1980</year>).



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913975</tid>
<number>65</number>Restriction on contribution.- No multi- State co- operative society 
shall make a contribution, either in money or in kind, whether 
directly or indirectly, to an institution which has an object of 
furtherance of the interest of a political party.


</article>



<article><tid>1803354</tid>
<number> 66</number> Restriction on loans.-
<section><tid>775183</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society,  
other than a co- operative bank, shall not make a loan to a member on 
the security of his share or on the security of a non- member.

</section>

<section><tid>1327655</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a 
multi- State co- operative society may make a loan to a depositor on the 
security of his deposit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1751209</tid>
<number> 67</number> Restriction on borrowing.-
<section><tid>1723238</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society  
may receive deposits, raise loans and receive grants from external 
sources to such extent and under such conditions as may be specified 
in the bye- laws:
Provided that the total amount of deposits and loans received during 
any financial year shall not exceed ten times of the sum of subscribed 
share capital and accumulated reserves:

Provided further that while calculating the total sum of subscribed 
share capital and accumulated reserves, the accumulated losses shall 
be deducted.


</section>

<section><tid>1382245</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), a multi- State 
co- operative society may accept funds or borrow funds for the 
fulfilment of its objects on such terms and conditions as are mutually 
contracted upon.

</section>

<section><tid>1185774</tid>
<number>3</number>A multi- State co- operative society may issue non- convertible 
debentures or other instruments subject to the provisions of any law 
for the time being in force to raise resources for the fulfilment of 
its objects to the extent of twenty- five per cent. f its paid- up 
share capital.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1384363</tid>
<number>68</number>Restriction on other transactions with non- members.- Save as 
provided in sections 66 and 67, the transaction of a multi- State 
co- operative society with any person other than a member, shall be 
subject to such prohibitions and restrictions, if any, as ay be 
specified in the bye- laws.


</article>



<article><tid>1880092</tid>
<number> 69</number> Contributory provident fund.-
<section><tid>469155</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of the  
Employees' Provident Fund and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1952</year> (19  
  of <year>1952</year>), a multi- State co- operative society having such number or 
class of employees as may be prescribed, may est blish a contributory 
provident fund for the benefit of its employees to which shall be 
credited all contributions made by the employees and the society in 
accordance with the bye- laws of the society.

</section>

<section><tid>1869293</tid>
<number>2</number>Monies standing to the credit of any contributory provident fund 
established by a multi- State co- operative society under sub- section 
 (1) shall not-

<subsection><tid>1762231</tid>
<number>a</number>be used in the business of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1780271</tid>
<number>b</number>form part of the assets of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>368993</tid>
<number>c</number>be liable to attachment or be subject to any other process of any 
court or other authority.
CHAP

AUDIT, INQUIRY, INSPECTION AND SURCHARGE

CHAPTER VIII

AUDIT, INQUIRY, INSPECTION AND SURCHARGE




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1357558</tid>
<number> 70</number> Appointment and remuneration of auditors.-
<section><tid>1085563</tid>
<number>1</number>Every multi- State  
co- operative society shall cause to be audited by an auditor referred 
to in sub- section (2), its accounts at least once in each year.

</section>

<section><tid>348303</tid>
<number>2</number>Every multi- State co- operative society shall, at each annual 
general meeting, appoint an auditor or auditors to hold office from 
the conclusion of that meeting until the conclusion of the next annual 
general meeting and shall, within seven days of th appointment, give 
intimation thereof to every auditor so appointed:
Provided that such auditor or auditors may be appointed from a panel 
of auditors approved by the Central Registrar or from a panel of 
auditors, if any, prepared by the multi- State co- operative society.


</section>

<section><tid>1594550</tid>
<number>3</number>Every auditor appointed under sub- section (1) shall, within thirty 
days of the receipt from the multi- State co- operative society of the 
intimation of his appointment, inform the Central Registrar in writing 
that he has accepted, or refused to accept, the appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>520373</tid>
<number>4</number>A retiring auditor shall be re- appointed unless-

<subsection><tid>1381414</tid>
<number>a</number>he is not qualified for re- appointment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309084</tid>
<number>b</number>he has given the multi- State co- operative society a notice in 
writing of his unwillingness to be re- appointed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1986500</tid>
<number>c</number>a resolution has been passed at the general meeting of members 
appointing some body instead of him or providing expressly that he 
shall not be re- appointed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>602338</tid>
<number>d</number>where notice has been given of an intended resolution to appoint 
some person or persons in the place of a retiring auditor, and by 
reason of the death, incapacity or disqualification of that person or 
all those persons, as the case may be, the resolu ion cannot be 
proceeded with.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1565736</tid>
<number>5</number>Where at an annual general meeting no auditors are appointed or 
re- appointed, the Central Registrar may appoint a person to fill the 
vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>170085</tid>
<number>6</number>First auditor or auditors of a multi- State co- operative society 
shall be appointed by the board within one month of the date of 
registration of such society and the auditor or auditors so appointed 
shall hold office until the conclusion of the first nnual general 
meeting:
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1026328</tid>
<number>a</number>the multi- State co- operative society may, at a general meeting, 
remove any such auditor or all or any of such auditors and appoint in 
his or their places any other person or persons who have been 
nominated for appointment by any member of the multi- S ate 
co- operative society and of whose nomination notice has been given to 
the members of the multi- State co- operative society not less than 
fourteen days before the date of the meeting; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>432934</tid>
<number>b</number>if the board fails to exercise its powers under this sub- section, 
the multi- State co- operative society in the general meeting may 
appoint the first auditor or auditors.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1961807</tid>
<number>7</number> (a) The multi- State co- operative society may fill any casual 
vacancy in the office of an auditor; but while any such vacancy 
continues, the remaining auditor or auditors, if any, may act:
Provided that where such vacancy is caused by the resignation of an 
auditor, the vacancy shall only be filled by the multi- State 
co- operative society in general meeting.


<subsection><tid>978204</tid>
<number>b</number>Any auditor appointed in a casual vacancy shall hold office until 
the conclusion of the next annual general meeting.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>672817</tid>
<number>8</number>Any auditor appointed under this section may be removed from 
office before the expiry of his term by the multi- State co- operative 
society in general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1365649</tid>
<number>9</number>The remuneration of the auditors of a multi- State co- operative 
society-

<subsection><tid>938106</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an auditor appointed by the board or the Central 
Registrar may be fixed by the board or the Central Registrar, as the 
case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>512284</tid>
<number>b</number>subject to clause (a), shall be fixed by the multi- State 
co- operative society in general meeting or in such manner as the 
multi- State co- operative society in general meeting may determine.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, any sums paid by 
the multi- State co- operative society in respect of the auditors' 
expenses shall be deemed to be included in the expression 
" remuneration".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>979816</tid>
<number> 71</number> Provision as to resolutions for appointing or removing 
auditors.-
<section><tid>418666</tid>
<number>1</number>A special notice shall be required for a resolution at  
an annual general meeting appointing as auditor a person other than a 
not be re- appointed. retiring auditor, or providing expressly that a 
retiring auditor shall

</section>

<section><tid>336645</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of notice of such a resolution, the multi- State 
co- operative society shall forthwith send a copy thereof to the 
retiring auditor.

</section>

<section><tid>219907</tid>
<number>3</number>Where notice is given of such a resolution and the retiring 
auditor makes with respect thereto representations in writing to the 
multi- State co- operative society (not exceeding a reasonable length) 
and requests their notification to members of the mu ti- State 
co- operative society, the multi- State co- operative society shall, 
unless the representations are received by it too late for it to do 
so,-

<subsection><tid>161280</tid>
<number>a</number>in any notice of the resolution given to members of the 
multi- State co- operative society, state the fact of the 
representations having been made; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1297727</tid>
<number>b</number>send a copy of the representation to every member of the 
multi- State co- operative society to whom notice of the meeting is 
sent, whether before or after the receipt of the representations by 
the multi- State co- operative society, and if a copy of the 
representations is not sent as aforesaid because they were received 
too late or because of the multi- State co- operative society' s default, 
the auditor may (without prejudice to his right to be heard orally) 
require that the represent tions shall be read out at the meeting.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>307255</tid>
<number> 72</number> Qualifications and disqualifications of auditors.-
<section><tid>369498</tid>
<number>1</number>A person  
shall not be qualified for appointment as an auditor of a multi- State 
co- operative society unless he is a chartered accountant within the 
meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (3 of <year>1949</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1468285</tid>
<number>2</number>None of the following persons shall be qualified for appointment 
as auditor of a multi- State co- operative society-

<subsection><tid>1301149</tid>
<number>a</number>a body corporate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1804472</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer or employee of the multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257184</tid>
<number>c</number>a person who is a member, or who is in the employment, of an 
officer or employee of the multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1463377</tid>
<number>d</number>a person who is indebted to the multi- State co- operative society 
or who has given any guarantee or provided any security in connection 
with the indebtedness of any third person to the multi- State 
co- operative society for an amount exceeding one thous nd rupees.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>390609</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall also not be qualified for appointment as an auditor 
of a multi- State co- operative society if he is, by virtue of 
sub- section (2), disqualified for appointment as an auditor of any 
other body corporate or multi- State co- operative societ or 
co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>356535</tid>
<number>4</number>If an auditor becomes subject, after his appointment, to any of 
the disqualifications specified in sub- sections (2) and (3), he shall 
be deemed to have vacated his office as such.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1734220</tid>
<number> 73</number> Powers and duties of auditors.-
<section><tid>1658751</tid>
<number>1</number>Every auditor of a multi- State  
co- operative society shall have a right of access at all times to the 
books, accounts and vouchers of the multi- State co- operative society, 
whether kept at the head office of the multi State co- operative 
society or elsewhere, and shall be entitled to require from the 
officers or other employees of the multi- State co- operative society 
such information and explanations as the auditor may think necessary 
for the performance of his duties s an auditor.

</section>

<section><tid>1572625</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to provisions of sub- section (1), the auditor 
shall inquire,-

<subsection><tid>1984720</tid>
<number>a</number>whether loans and advances made by the multi- State co- operative 
society on the basis of security have been properly secured and 
whether the terms on which they have been made are not prejudicial to 
the interests of the multi- State co- operative societ or its members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>858743</tid>
<number>b</number>whether transactions of the multi- State co- operative society which 
are represented merely by book entries are not prejudicial to the 
interests of the multi- State co- operative society; (c) whether 
personal expenses have been charged to revenue account; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>307870</tid>
<number>d</number>where it is stated in the books and papers of the multi- State 
co- operative society that any shares have been allotted for cash, 
whether cash has actually been received in respect of such allotment, 
and if no cash has actually been so received, whethe the position as 
stated in the account books and the balance- sheet is correct, regular 
and not misleading.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1731203</tid>
<number>3</number>The auditor shall make a report to the members of the multi- State 
co- operative society on the accounts examined by him and on every 
balance- sheet and profit and loss account and on every other document 
required to be part of or annexed to the balance sheet or profit and 
loss account, which are laid before the multi- State co- operative 
society in general meeting during his tenure of office, and the report 
shall state whether, in his opinion and to the best of his information 
and according to the explan tions given to him, the said accounts give 
the information required by this Act in the manner so required and 
give a true and fair view,-

<subsection><tid>821349</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the balance- sheet, of the state of the multi- State 
co- operative society' s affairs as at the end of its financial year; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744536</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the profit and loss account, of the profit or loss 
for its financial year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>269081</tid>
<number>4</number>The auditors' report shall also state-

<subsection><tid>1716655</tid>
<number>a</number>whether he has obtained all the information and explanations which 
to the best of his knowledge and belief were necessary for the 
purposes of his audit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400820</tid>
<number>b</number>whether, in his opinion, proper books of account have been kept by 
the multi- State co- operative society so far as appears from his 
examination of those books, and proper returns adequate for the 
purposes of his audit have been received from branches r offices of 
the multi- State co- operative society not visited by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>526082</tid>
<number>c</number>whether the report on the accounts of any branch office audited by 
a person other than the multi- State co- operative society' s auditor has 
been forwarded to him and how he has dealt with the same in preparing 
the auditor' s report;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1999654</tid>
<number>d</number>whether the multi- State co- operative society' s balance- sheet and 
profit and loss account dealt with by the report are in agreement with 
the books of account and returns.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>105977</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any of the matters referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of 
sub- section (3) or in clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of sub- section (4) 
is answered in the negative or with a qualification, the auditor' s 
report shall state the reason for the answer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1506833</tid>
<number>74</number>Signature of audit report, etc.- Only the person appointed as an 
auditor of the multi- State co- operative society shall sign the 
auditor' s report, or sign or authenticate any other document of the 
multi- State co- operative society required by law to be igned or 
authenticated by the auditor.


</article>



<article><tid>252439</tid>
<number>75</number>Reading and inspection of auditor' s report.- The auditor' s report 
shall be read before the multi- State co- operative society in the 
general meeting and shall be open to inspection by any member of the 
multi- State co- operative society.


</article>



<article><tid>1482970</tid>
<number>76</number>Right of auditor to attend general meeting.- All notices of, and 
other communications relating to, any general meeting of a multi- State 
co- operative society, which any member of the multi- State co- operative 
society is entitled to have sent to him, sha l also be forwarded to 
the auditor of the multi- State co- operative society; and the auditor 
shall be entitled to attend any general meeting and to be heard at any 
general meeting which he attends on any part of the business which 
concerns him as auditor.


</article>



<article><tid>1699147</tid>
<number> 77</number> Power of Central Government to direct special audit in certain 
cases.-
<section><tid>1061659</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government is of the opinion- 

<subsection><tid>1161139</tid>
<number>a</number>that the affairs of any multi- State co- operative society are not 
being managed in accordance with self- help and mutual aid and 
co- operative principles or prudent commercial practices; or with 
sound business principles; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>795208</tid>
<number>b</number>that any multi- State co- operative society is being managed in a 
manner likely to cause serious injury or damage to the interests of 
the trade, industry or business to which it pertains; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1966872</tid>
<number>c</number>that the financial position of any multi- State co- operative 
society is such as to endanger its solvency,
the Central Government may at any time by order direct that a special 
audit of the multi- State co- operative society' s accounts for such 
period or periods as may be specified in the order, shall be conducted 
and may by the same or a different order appoin either a chartered 
accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of 
the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>) or the multi- State 
co- operative society' s auditor himself to conduct with special audit:

Provided that the Central Government shall not order for special audit 
of a multi- State co- operative society' s accounts if that Government or 
the State Government either by itself or both hold less than fifty- one 
per cent. of the paid- up share capital or of the shares in such 
multi- State co- operative society.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>795034</tid>
<number>2</number>The chartered accountant or the multi- State co- operative society' s 
auditor appointed under sub- section (1) to conduct a special audit as 
aforesaid is hereafter in this section referred to as the special 
auditor.

</section>

<section><tid>1789541</tid>
<number>3</number>The special auditor shall have the same powers and duties in 
relation to the special audit as an auditor of a multi- State 
co- operative society has under section 73:
Provided that the special auditor shall, instead of making his report 
to the members of the multi- State co- operative society, make the same 
to the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>312908</tid>
<number>4</number>The report of the special auditor shall, as far as may be, include 
all the matters required to be included in the auditors' report under 
section 73 and, if the Central Government so directs, shall also 
include a statement on any other matter which ma be referred to him by 
that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1837229</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may by order direct any person specified in 
the order to furnish to the special auditor within such time as may be 
specified therein such information or additional information as may be 
required by the special auditor in connec ion with the special audit.

</section>

<section><tid>569719</tid>
<number>6</number>On receipt of the report of the special auditor, the Central 
Government may take such action on the report as it considers 
necessary in accordance with the provisions of this Act or any other 
law for the time being in force: Provided that if the Central 
Government does not take any action on the report within four months 
from the date of its receipt, that Government shall send to the 
multi- State co- operative society either a copy of, or relevant extract 
from, the report with its comments thereon and require the multi- State 
co- operative society either to circulate that copy or those extracts 
to the members or to have such copy or extracts read before the 
multi- State co- operative society at its next general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>661697</tid>
<number>7</number>The expenses of, and incidental to, any special audit under this 
section (including the remuneration of the special auditor) shall be 
determined by the Central Government which determination shall be 
final and paid by the multi- State co- operative soc ety and in default 
of such payment, shall be recoverable from the multi- State 
co- operative society as an arrear of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>435442</tid>
<number> 78</number> Inquiry by Central Registrar.-
<section><tid>1219401</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Registrar may, on a  
request from a federal co- operative to which a multi- State 
co- operative society is affiliated or a creditor or not less than 
one- third of the members of the board or not less than one- ifth of 
the total number of members of a multi- State co- operative society hold 
an inquiry or direct some person authorised by him by order in writing 
in this behalf to hold an inquiry into the constitution, working and 
financial condition of a multi- Stat co- operative society: Provided 
that no inquiry under this sub- section shall be held unless a notice 
of not less than fifteen days has been given to the multi- State 
co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>1825631</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Registrar or the person authorised by him under 
sub- section (1) shall have the following powers, namely:-

<subsection><tid>890943</tid>
<number>a</number>he shall at all reasonable times have free access to the books, 
accounts, documents, securities, cash and other properties belonging 
to or in the custody of the multi- State co- operative society and may 
summon any person in possession or responsible f r the custody of any 
such books, accounts, documents, securities, cash or other properties 
to produce the same, at any place specified by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>167818</tid>
<number>b</number>he may, notwithstanding any bye- law specifying the period of 
notice for a general meeting of the multi- State co- operative society, 
require the officers of the society to call a general meeting of the 
society by giving notice of not less than seven da s at such time and 
place at the headquarters of the society to consider such matters, as 
may be directed by him; and where the officers of the society refuse 
or fail to call such a meeting, he shall have power to call it 
himself;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1628249</tid>
<number>c</number>he may summon any person who is reasonably believed by him to have 
any knowledge of the affairs of the multi- State co- operative society 
to appear before him at any place at the headquarters of the society 
or any branch thereof and may examine such pe son on oath.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1171644</tid>
<number>3</number>Any meeting called under clause (b) of sub- section (2) shall have 
all the powers of a general meeting of the society called under the 
bye- laws of the society and its proceedings shall be regulated by such 
bye- laws.

</section>

<section><tid>272041</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Registrar shall, within a period of three months of 
the date of receipt of the report, communicate the report of inquiry 
to the multi- State co- operative society, the financial institutions, 
if any, to which the society is affiliated, and o the person or 
authority, if any, at whose instance the inquiry is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297600</tid>
<number> 79</number> Inspection of multi- State co- operative societies.-
<section><tid>1642660</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Registrar may, on a request from a federal co- operative to which a 
multi- State co- operative society is affiliated or a creditor or not 
less than one- third of the members of the board o not less than 
one- fifth of the total number of members of a multi- State co- operative 
society by general or special order in writing in this behalf, inspect 
or direct any person authorised by him by order in writing in this 
behalf to make an inspection i to the constitution, working and 
financial condition of a multi- State co- operative society:
Provided that no inspection under this sub- section shall be made 
unless a notice of not less than fifteen days has been given to the 
multi- State co- operative society.


</section>

<section><tid>173757</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) For the purpose of inspection under sub- section (1), the 
Central Registrar or the person authorised by him under that 
sub- section shall at all times have access to all books, accounts, 
papers, vouchers, securities, stock and other property of tha society 
and may, in the event of serious irregularities discovered during 
inspection, take them into custody and shall have power to verify the 
cash balance of the society and subject to the general or special 
order of the Central Registrar to call a me ting of the board and also 
a general meeting of the society where such general meeting is, in his 
opinion, necessary.

<subsection><tid>919744</tid>
<number>b</number>Every officer or member of a multi- State co- operative society 
shall furnish such information with regard to the working of the 
society as the Central Registrar or the person making such inspection 
may require.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>599825</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the report of inspection under this section shall be 
communicated to the multi- State co- operative society within a period 
of three months from the date of completion of such inspection.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>901771</tid>
<number> 80</number> Inspection of books of indebted multi- State co- operative 
societies.-
<section><tid>803467</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Registrar shall, on the application of a  
creditor of a multi- State co- operative society, inspect, or direct 
some person authorised by him by order in writing in this ehalf to 
inspect, the books of the society: Provided that no such inspection 
shall be made unless the applicant-

<subsection><tid>1139154</tid>
<number>a</number>satisfies the Central Registrar that the debt is a sum then due, 
and that he has demanded payment thereof and has not received 
satisfaction within a reasonable time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205765</tid>
<number>b</number>deposits with the Central Registrar such sum as security for the 
costs of the proposed inspection as the Central Registrar may require.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>512219</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Registrar shall communicate the result of any such 
inspection to the creditor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1998197</tid>
<number> 81</number> Costs of inquiry and inspection.- Where an inquiry is held under 
section 78 or an inspection is made under section 79, the Central 
Registrar may apportion the costs, or such part of the costs, as he 
may think fit, between the multi- State co- operative ociety, the 
members or creditors demanding an inquiry or inspection, and the 
officers or former officers and the members or past members of that 
society:
Provided that-

<section><tid>1410306</tid>
<number>a</number>no order of apportionment of the costs shall be made under this 
section unless the society or the person liable to pay the costs 
thereunder has had a reasonable opportunity of being heard;

</section>

<section><tid>86010</tid>
<number>b</number>the Central Registrar shall state in writing under his own hand 
the grounds on which the costs are apportioned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1436355</tid>
<number>82</number>Recovery of costs.- Any sum awarded by way of costs under section 
 81 may be recovered, on application to a magistrate having 
jurisdiction in the place where the person, from whom the money is 
claimable, actually and voluntarily resides or carries on b siness, 
and such magistrate shall recover the same as if it were a fine 
imposed by himself.


</article>



<article><tid>1698637</tid>
<number> 83</number> Repayment, etc.-
<section><tid>300834</tid>
<number>1</number>If in the course of an audit, inquiry,  
inspection or the winding up of a multi- State co- operative society, it 
is found that any person, who is or was entrusted with the 
organisation or management of such society or who is or has a any time 
been an officer or an employee of the society, has made any payment 
contrary to this Act, or the bye- laws or has caused any deficiency in 
the assets of the society by breach of trust or wilful negligence or 
has misappropriated or fraudulently r tained any money or other 
property belonging to such society, the Central Registrar may, of his 
own motion or on the application of the board, liquidator or any 
creditor inquire himself or direct any person authorised by him, by an 
order in writing in th s behalf, to inquire into the conduct of such 
person within a period of two years from the date of the report of the 
audit, inspection or inquiry or the date of the order of winding up, 
as the case may be:
Provided that where the Central Registrar is satisfied that such 
inquiry could not be commenced during the period of two years 
aforesaid on account of fraud or concealment of facts, he may make or 
direct the inquiry to be made within such period not exce ding six 
years from the date of the report of the audit, inspection or inquiry 
or the date of the order of winding up, as he thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1062498</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an inquiry is made under sub- section (1), the Central 
Registrar may, after giving the person concerned a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard, make an order requiring him to repay or 
restore the money or property or any part thereof, with inte est at 
such rate, or to pay contribution and costs or compensation to such 
extent, as the Central Registrar may consider just and equitable.
CHAP

SETTLEMENT OF DISPUTES

CHAPTER IX

SETTLEMENT OF DISPUTES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>223290</tid>
<number> 84</number> Reference of disputes.-
<section><tid>19425</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
any other law for the time being in force, if any dispute[ other than 
a dispute regarding disciplinary action taken by a multi- State 
co- operative society against its paid employee or an industrial 
dispute as defined in clause (k) of section 2 of the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>)] touching the constitution, management 
or business of a multi- State co- operative society arises-

<subsection><tid>145632</tid>
<number>a</number>among members, past members and persons claiming through members, 
past members and deceased members, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1351455</tid>
<number>b</number>between a member, past members and persons claiming through a 
member, past member or deceased member and the multi- State 
co- operative society, its board or any officer, agent or employee of 
the multi- State co- operative society or liquidator, past or resent, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147669</tid>
<number>c</number>between the multi- State co- operative society or its board and any 
past board, any officer, agent or employee, or any past officer, past 
agent or past employee, heirs or legal representatives of any deceased 
officer, deceased agent or deceased employe of the multi- State 
co- operative society, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>389498</tid>
<number>d</number>between the multi- State co- operative society and any other 
multi- State co- operative society, between a multi- State co- operative 
society and liquidator of another multi- State co- operative society or 
between the liquidator of one multi- State co- operative society and the 
liquidator of another multi- State co- operative society,
such dispute shall be referred to arbitration.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>882970</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the following shall be deemed 
to be disputes touching the constitution, management or business of a 
multi- State co- operative society, namely:-

<subsection><tid>839728</tid>
<number>a</number>a claim by the multi- State co- operative society for any debt or 
demand due to it from a member or the nominee, heirs or legal 
representatives of a deceased member, whether such debt or demand be 
admitted or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1252982</tid>
<number>b</number>a claim by a surety against the principal debtor where the 
multi- State co- operative society has recovered from the surety any 
amount in respect of any debt or demand due to it from the principal 
debtor as a result of the default of the principal debt r, whether 
such debt or demand is admitted or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>207763</tid>
<number>c</number>any dispute arising in connection with the election of any officer 
of a multi- State co- operative society.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>982321</tid>
<number>3</number>If any question arises whether a dispute referred to arbitration 
under this section is or is not a dispute touching the constitution, 
management or business of a multi- State co- operative society, the 
decision thereon of the arbitrator shall be final nd shall not be 
called in question in any court.

</section>

<section><tid>701444</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a dispute has been referred to arbitration under sub- section 
 (1), the same shall be settled or decided by the arbitrator to be 
appointed by the Central Registrar.

</section>

<section><tid>1915711</tid>
<number>5</number>Save as otherwise provided under this Act, the provisions of the 
Arbitration and Conciliation Act, <year>1996</year> shall apply to all arbitration 
under this Act as if the proceedings for arbitration were referred for 
settlement or decision under the provisions f the Arbitration and 
Conciliation Act, <year>1996</year> (26 of <year>1996</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>764768</tid>
<number> 85</number> Limitation.-
<section><tid>1919758</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the  
Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36 of <year>1963</year>), but subject to the specific 
provisions made in this Act, the period of limitation in the case of a 
dispute referred to arbitration shall,-

<subsection><tid>1127527</tid>
<number>a</number>when the dispute relates to the recovery of any sum including 
interest thereon due to a multi- State co- operative society by a member 
thereof, be computed from the date on which such member dies or ceases 
to be a member of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1460457</tid>
<number>b</number>save as otherwise provided in clause (c), when the dispute relates 
to any act or omission on the part of any of the parties referred to 
in clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) of sub- section (1) of 
section 84, be six years from the date on which t e act or omission, 
with reference to which the dispute arose, took place;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>617130</tid>
<number>c</number>when the dispute is in respect of an election of an officer of a 
multi- State co- operative society, be one month from the date of the 
declaration of the result of the election.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1263944</tid>
<number>2</number>The period of limitation in the case of any dispute, except those 
mentioned in sub- section (1), which are required to be referred to 
arbitration shall be regulated by the provisions of the Limitation 
Act, <year>1963</year> (36 of <year>1963</year>), as if the dispute were a s it and the 
arbitrator a civil court.

</section>

<section><tid>1727012</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and (2), 
the arbitrator may admit a dispute after the expiry of the period of 
limitation, if the applicant satisfies the arbitrator that he had 
sufficient cause for not referring the dispute with n such period.
CHAP

WINDING UP OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETY

CHAPTER X

WINDING UP OF MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1711216</tid>
<number> 86</number> Winding up of multi- State co- operative societies.-
<section><tid>1565408</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
Central Registrar, after audit has been conducted under section 70 or 
special audit has been conducted under section 77 or an inquiry has 
been held under section 78 or an inspection has bee made under section 
79, is of opinion that the society ought to be wound up, he may, after 
giving the society a reasonable opportunity of making its 
representations by order, direct it to be wound up.

</section>

<section><tid>394412</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Registrar may, of his own motion and after giving the 
multi- State co- operative society a reasonable opportunity of making 
its representation, make an order directing the winding up of the 
multi- State co- operative society,-

<subsection><tid>239707</tid>
<number>a</number>where it is a condition of the registration of the society that 
the society shall consist of at least fifty members and the number of 
members has been reduced to less than fifty; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>402162</tid>
<number>b</number>where the multi- State co- operative society has not commenced 
working within a period of six months of the date of its registration 
or such extended period as the Central Registrar may allow in this 
behalf or has ceased to function in accordance with o- operative 
principles.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>803831</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Registrar may cancel an order for the winding up of a 
multi- State co- operative society, at any time, in any case where, in 
his opinion, the society should continue to exist.

</section>

<section><tid>1093917</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of such order shall be communicated by registered post to 
the multi- State co- operative society and to the financial 
institutions, if any, of which the society is a member.

</section>

<section><tid>1501085</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no 
co- operative bank shall be wound up except with the previous sanction, 
in writing of the Reserve Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>1344579</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the Central 
Registrar shall make an order for the winding up of a multi- State 
co- operative society, if the society, by a resolution passed by 
two- third majority of memebrs present and voting in a ge eral meeting 
decides for winding up of that society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>833291</tid>
<number>87</number>Winding up of co- operative bank at the direction of Reserve 
Bank.- Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained elsewhere in 
this Act, the Central Registrar shall make an order for the winding up 
of a co- operative bank, if so required by the Res rve Bank in the 
circumstances mentioned in section 13D of the Deposit Insurance and 
Credit Guarantee Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1257850</tid>
<number> 88</number> Reimbursement to the Deposit Insurance Corporation by 
liquidator.- Where a co- operative bank, being an insured bank within 
the meaning of the Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation 
Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>), is wound up and the Deposit Insura ce 
Corporation has become liable to the depositors of the insured bank 
under sub- section
<section><tid>1175726</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 16 of that Act, the Deposit Insurance  
Corporation shall be reimbursed by the liquidator or such other person 
in the circumstances, to the extent and i the manner provided in 
section 21 of that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1348635</tid>
<number> 89</number> Liquidator.-
<section><tid>1126237</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Registrar has made an order  
under section 86 for the winding up of a multi- State co- operative 
society, the Central Registrar may appoint a liquidator for the 
purpose and fix his remuneration.

</section>

<section><tid>1417391</tid>
<number>2</number>A liquidator shall, on appointment, take into his custody or under 
his control all the property, effects and actionable claims to which 
the multi- State co- operative society is or appears to be entitled and 
shall take such steps as he may deem necessa y or expedient to prevent 
loss or deterioration of, or damage to, such property, effects and 
claims and he may carry on the business of the multi- State 
co- operative society so far as may be necessary with the previous 
approval of the Central Registrar.

</section>

<section><tid>1665774</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an appeal is preferred under clause (f) of sub- section (1) 
of section 99, an order for the winding up of a multi- State 
co- operative society made under section 86 shall not operate 
thereafter until the order is confirmed in appeal: Provided that the 
liquidator shall continue to have custody or control of the property, 
effects and actionable claims mentioned in sub- section (2) and have 
authority to take the steps referred to in that sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>195402</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an order for the winding up of a multi- State co- operative 
society is set aside in appeal, the property, effects and actionable 
claims of the society shall re- vest in the society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1253419</tid>
<number> 90</number> Powers of liquidator.-
<section><tid>474850</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules made in this  
behalf, the whole of the assets of a multi- State co- operative society 
in respect of which an order for winding up has been made, shall vest 
in the liquidator appointed under section 89 from he date on which the 
order takes effect and the liquidator shall have power to realise such 
assets by sale or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>196768</tid>
<number>2</number>Such liquidator shall also have power, subject to the control of 
the Central Registrar-

<subsection><tid>1259967</tid>
<number>a</number>to institute and defend suits and other legal proceedings on 
behalf of the multi- State co- operative society by the name of his 
office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>130248</tid>
<number>b</number>to determine from time to time the contribution (including debts  
  due and costs of liquidation) to be made or remaining to be made by 
the members or past members or by the estates or nominees, heirs or 
legal representatives of the deceased members or y any officers or 
former officers, to the assets of the multi- State co- operative 
society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1070221</tid>
<number>c</number>to investigate all claims against the multi- State co- operative 
society and subject to the provisions of this Act, to decide questions 
of priority arising between claimants;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>114685</tid>
<number>d</number>to pay claims against the multi- State co- operative society, 
including interest up to the date of winding up according to their 
respective priorities, if any, in full or rateably, as the assets of 
the society may permit; and the surplus, if any, remai ing after 
payment of the claims being applied in payment of interest from the 
date of such order of winding up at a rate fixed by him but not 
exceeding the contract rate in any case;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1113211</tid>
<number>e</number>to determine by what persons and in what proportions the costs of 
the liquidation are to be borne;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>533996</tid>
<number>f</number>to determine whether any person is a member, past member or 
nominee of a deceased member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1734734</tid>
<number>g</number>to give such directions in regard to the collection and 
distribution of the assets of the multi- State co- operative society as 
may appear to him to be necessary for winding up the affairs of that 
society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1320110</tid>
<number>h</number>to carry on the business of the multi- State co- operative society 
so far as may be necessary for the beneficial winding up of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>385595</tid>
<number>i</number>to make any compromise or arrangement with creditors or persons 
claiming to be creditors or having or alleging to have any claim, 
present or future, whereby the multi- State co- operative society may be 
rendered liable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>272839</tid>
<number>j</number>to make any compromise or arrangement with any person between whom 
and the multi- State co- operative society there exists any dispute and 
to refer any such dispute for decision;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>38069</tid>
<number>k</number>after consulting the members of the multi- State co- operative 
society, to dispose of the surplus, if any, remaining after paying the 
claims against the society, in such manner as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147643</tid>
<number>l</number>to compromise all calls or liabilities to calls and debts and 
liabilities capable of resulting in debts, and all claims, present or 
future, certain or contingent, subsisting or alleged to be subsisting 
between the multi- State co- operative society and a contributory or 
other debtor or person apprehending liability to the multi- State 
co- operative society and all questions in any way relating to or 
affecting the assets or the winding up of the society on such terms as 
may be agreed and take any security for the discharge of any such 
call, liability, debt or claim and give a complete discharge in 
respect thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1026376</tid>
<number>3</number>When the affairs of a multi- State co- operative society have been 
wound up, the liquidator shall make a report to the Central Registrar 
and deposit the records of the society in such place as the Central 
Registrar may direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1298188</tid>
<number> 91</number> Disposal of surplus assets.- The surplus assets, as shown in the 
report of a liquidator of a multi- State co- operative society which is 
wound up,-
<section><tid>141808</tid>
<number>a</number>may, if the bye- laws of the multi- State co- operative society 
specify the purpose for which surplus shall be utilised, be utilised 
by the Central Registrar for the said purpose, and

</section>

<section><tid>417934</tid>
<number>b</number>if the bye- laws aforesaid do not specify the purpose, be divided 
by the Central Registrar with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, amongst the members of such multi- State co- operative 
society in such manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>24434</tid>
<number>92</number>Priority of contributions assessed by liquidator.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law relating to insolvency, the contribution 
assessed by a liquidator shall rank next to debts due to the Central 
Government or a State Government or a local uthority in accordance 
with the order of priority in insolvency proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>143358</tid>
<number> 93</number> Power of Central Registrar to cancel registration of a 
multi- State co- operative society.-
<section><tid>14448</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Registrar may, after  
considering the report of the liquidator made to him under sub- section 
 (3) of section 90, order the registration of the mult- State 
co- operative society to be cancelled and on such cancellation, that 
society shall stand dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>34223</tid>
<number>2</number>An order passed under sub- section (1) shall be communicated by 
registered post to the president or the chairperson, as the case may 
be, of the multi- State co- operative society and to the financial 
institutions, if any, of which the society was a memb r.
CHAP

EXECUTION OF DECREES, ORDERS AND DECISIONS

CHAPTER XI

EXECUTION OF DECREES, ORDERS AND DECISIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1016117</tid>
<number> 94</number> Execution of decisions, etc.- Every decision or order made under 
section 39 or section 40 or section 83 or section 99 or section 101 
shall, if not carried out,-
<section><tid>1332877</tid>
<number>a</number>on a certificate signed by the Central Registrar or any person 
authorised by him in writing in this behalf, be deemed to be a decree 
of a civil court and shall be executed in the same manner as if it 
were a decree of such court and such decree shall e executed by the 
Central Registrar or any person authorised by him in writing in this 
behalf, by attachment and sale or sale without attachment of any 
property of the person or a multi- State co- operative society against 
whom the decision or order has b en made; or

</section>

<section><tid>587334</tid>
<number>b</number>where the decision or order provides for the recovery of money, be 
executed according to law for the time being in force for the recovery 
of arrears of land revenue:
Provided that any application for the recovery of any sum shall be 
made in such manner-


<subsection><tid>1908698</tid>
<number>i</number>to the Collector and shall be accompanied by a certificate signed 
by the Central Registrar or by any person authorised by him in writing 
in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>957293</tid>
<number>ii</number>within twelve years from the date fixed in the decision or order 
and if no such date is fixed, from the date of decision or order, as 
the case may be; or

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>607223</tid>
<number>c</number>be executed by the Central Registrar or any person authorised by 
him in writing in this behalf, by attachment and sale or sale without 
attachment of any property of the person or a multi- State co- operative 
society against whom the decision or order h s been made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1556987</tid>
<number>95</number>Execution of orders of liquidator.- Every order made by the 
liquidator under section 90 shall be executed according to the law for 
the time being in force for the recovery of arrears of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>1825654</tid>
<number> 96</number> Attachment before award.-
<section><tid>1517368</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the arbitrator is satisfied  
that a party to any reference made to him under section 84 with intent 
to defeat or delay the execution of any decision that may be passed 
thereon is about to-

<subsection><tid>622765</tid>
<number>a</number>dispose of the whole or any part of the property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1326298</tid>
<number>b</number>remove the whole or any part of the property from its existing 
precincts, the arbitrator may, unless adequate security is furnished, 
direct conditional attachment of the said property or such part 
thereof as he deems necessary.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>431026</tid>
<number>2</number>The attachment under sub- section (1) shall be executed by a civil 
court having jurisdiction in the same way as an attachment order 
passed by itself and shall have the same effect as such order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1427547</tid>
<number>97</number>Central Registrar or arbitrator or person authorized to be civil 
court for certain purposes.- The Central Registrar or the arbitrator or 
any person authorised by him in writing in this behalf shall be 
deemed, when exercising any powers under this Act or the recovery of 
any amount by the attachment and sale or by sale without attachment of 
any property, or when passing any orders on any application made to 
him for such recovery or for taking a step- in- aid of such recovery, to 
be a civil court for the urposes of article 136 of the Schedule to the 
Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36 of <year>1963</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>311349</tid>
<number> 98</number> Recovery of sums due to Government.-
<section><tid>1291488</tid>
<number>1</number>All sums due from a  
multi- State co- operative society, or from an officer or member or past 
member of a multi- State co- operative society, to the Central 
Government or a State Government, including any cost award d to the 
Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, under 
any provision of this Act, may, on a certificate issued by the Central 
Registrar in this behalf, be recovered in the same manner as arrears 
of land revenue as first charge on he assets of such society or 
officer or member, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1529537</tid>
<number>2</number>Sums due from a multi- State co- operative society to the Central 
Government or a State Government and recoverable under sub- section (1) 
may be recovered firstly from the property of the society and secondly 
from the members, past members or the estate of deceased members, 
subject to the limit of their liability:
Provided that the liability of past members and the estate of deceased 
members shall in all cases be subject to the provisions of section 37.

CHAP

APPEALS AND REVIEW

CHAPTER XII

APPEALS AND REVIEW




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>230697</tid>
<number> 99</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>708546</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of section 100, an appeal  
shall lie under this section against-

<subsection><tid>943406</tid>
<number>a</number>an order made by the Central Registrar under sub- section (3) of 
section 7 refusing to register a multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1124728</tid>
<number>b</number>an order made by the Central Registrar under sub- section (9) of 
section 11 refusing to register an amendment of the bye- laws of a 
multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489359</tid>
<number>c</number>a decision of a multi- State co- operative society refusing or 
deemed to be refusing under sub- section (4) of section 25 to admit any 
person as a member of the society who is otherwise duly qualified for 
membership under the bye- laws of the society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918625</tid>
<number>d</number>an order made by the Central Registrar under section 81 
apportioning the costs of an inquiry held under section 78 or an 
inspection made under section 80;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1462126</tid>
<number>e</number>an order made by the Central Registrar under sub- section (2) of 
section 83;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>376406</tid>
<number>f</number>an order made by the Central Registrar under section 86 directing 
the winding up of a multi- State co- operative society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259644</tid>
<number>g</number>an order made by the liquidator of a multi- State co- operative 
society under section 90.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1957205</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal against any decision or order under sub- section (1) 
shall be made within sixty days from the date of such decision or 
order to the prescribed appellate authority.

</section>

<section><tid>163312</tid>
<number>3</number>The appellate authority may, if satisfied that the appellant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal within the 
period of sixty days, admit the appeal within such further period as 
that authority may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>22976</tid>
<number>4</number>In disposing of an appeal under this section, the appellate 
authority may, after giving the parties a reasonable opportunity of 
making their representation, pass such order thereon as that authority 
may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>749037</tid>
<number>5</number>The decision or order of the appellate authority on appeal shall 
be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>59121</tid>
<number> 100</number> No appeal in certain cases.- Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act, where, with the previous sanction in writing of, or on 
requisition by, the Reserve Bank, a co- operative bank-
<section><tid>1121324</tid>
<number>a</number>is being wound up; or

</section>

<section><tid>1274728</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of which a scheme of amalgamation or reorganisation is 
given effect to,
no appeal there against shall lie or be permissible, and the sanction 
or requisition of the Reserve Bank shall not be liable to be called in 
question.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1826575</tid>
<number> 101</number> Review.-
<section><tid>1185465</tid>
<number>1</number>The appellate authority referred to in section 99,  
may, on the application of any party, review its own order in any case 
and pass in reference thereto such order as it thinks fit:
Provided that no such application shall be entertained unless the 
appellate authority is satisfied that there has been a discovery of 
new and important matter or evidence which after exercise of due 
diligence was not within the knowledge of the applicant or could not 
be produced by him at the time when the order was made or that there 
has been some mistake or error apparent on the face of the record or 
for any other sufficient reason:

Provided further that no such order shall be made under this 
sub- section unless notice has been given to all interested parties and 
they have been afforded a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1015657</tid>
<number>2</number>An application for review under sub- section (1) by any party shall 
be made within thirty days from the date of communication of the order 
of the appellate authority sought to be reviewed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377344</tid>
<number>102</number>Interlocutory orders.- Where an appeal is made under section 99, 
the appellate authority may, in order to prevent the ends of justice 
being defeated, make such interlocutory orders, including an order of 
stay pending the decision of the appeal as suc authority may deem fit.
CHAP

SOCIETIES WHICH BECOME MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES CONSEQUENT 
ON 
REORGANISATION OF STATES

CHAPTER XIII

SOCIETIES WHICH BECOME MULTI- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES CONSEQUENT 
ON REORGANISATION OF STATES



</article>



<article><tid>902817</tid>
<number> 103</number> Co- operative societies functioning immediately before 
reorganization of States.-
<section><tid>1809899</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, by virtue of the provisions of  
Part II of the State Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>) or any 
other enactment relating to reorganisation of States, any co- perative 
society which immediately before the day on which the reorganisation 
takes place, had its objects confined to one State becomes, as from 
that day, a multi- State co- operative society, it shall be deemed to be 
a multi- State co- operative society re istered under the corresponding 
provisions of this Act and the bye- laws of such society shall, in so 
far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
continue to be in force until altered or rescinded.

</section>

<section><tid>2028</tid>
<number>2</number>If it appears to the Central Registrar or any officer authorised 
in this behalf by the Central Government (hereafter in this section  
  referred to as the authorised officer) that it is necessary or 
expedient to reconstitute or reorganise any society re erred to in 
sub- section (1), the Central Registrar or the authorised officer, as 
the case may be, may, with the previous approval of the Central 
Government, place before a meeting of the general body of that 
society, held in such manner as may be prescri ed, a scheme for the 
reconstitution or reorganisation, including proposals regarding-

<subsection><tid>746975</tid>
<number>a</number>the formation of new multi- State co- operative societies and the 
transfer thereto in whole or in part, of the assets and liabilities of 
that society; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1207362</tid>
<number>b</number>the transfer, in whole or in part, of the assets and liabilities 
of that society to any other multi- State co- operative society in 
existence immediately before the date of that meeting of the general 
body (hereafter in this section referred to as the xisting multi- State  
  co- operative society).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>457512</tid>
<number>3</number>If the scheme is sanctioned by a resolution passed by a majority 
of the members present at the said meeting, either without 
modifications or with modifications to which the Central Registrar or 
the authorised officer agrees, he shall certify the sche e and upon 
such certification, the scheme shall, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in any law, regulation or bye- laws for the time 
being in force, be binding on all the societies affected by the 
scheme, as well as the shareholders and cr ditors of all such 
societies.

</section>

<section><tid>1318930</tid>
<number>4</number>If the scheme is not sanctioned under sub- section (3), the Central 
Registrar or the authorised officer may refer the scheme to such Judge 
of the appropriate High Court, as may be nominated in this behalf by 
the Chief Justice thereof, and the decision of that Judge in regard to 
the scheme shall be final and shall be binding on all the societies 
affected by the scheme as well as the shareholders and creditors of 
all such societies.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," appropriate High 
Court" means the High Court within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction the principal place of business of the multi- State 
co- operative society is situated.


</section>

<section><tid>926641</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where a scheme 
under sub- section (2) includes any proposal regarding the transfer of 
the assets and liabilities of any multi- State co- operative society 
referred to in clause (b) thereof, the scheme hall not be binding on 
such multi- State co- operative society or the shareholders and 
creditors thereof, unless the proposal regarding such transfer is 
accepted by that multi- State co- operative society by a resolution 
passed by a majority of the members p esent at a meeting of its 
general body.
CHAP

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES

CHAPTER XIV

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>288248</tid>
<number> 104</number> Offences and penalties.-
<section><tid>1410251</tid>
<number>1</number>A multi- State co- operative society  
or an officer or member thereof wilfully making a false return or 
furnishing false information, or any person wilfully or without any 
reasonable excuse disobeying any summons, requisitio or lawful written 
order issued under the provisions of this Act, or wilfully not 
furnishing any information required from him by a person authorised in 
this behalf under the provisions of this Act, shall be punishable with 
fine which shall not be less t an two thousand rupees and which may 
extend to ten thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1386747</tid>
<number>2</number>Any employer who, without sufficient cause, fails to pay to a 
multi- State co- operative society the amount deducted by him under 
section 60 within a period of fourteen days from the date on which 
such deduction is made shall, without prejudice to any action that may 
be taken against him under any other law for the time being in force, 
be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1416649</tid>
<number>3</number>Any officer or custodian who wilfully fails to hand over custody 
of books, accounts, documents, records, cash, security and other 
property belonging to a multi- State co- operative society of which he 
is an officer or custodian, to a person entitled un er section 54, or 
section 70, or section 78, or section 79, or section 89 shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees and in 
the case of a continuing breach, with a further fine which may extend 
to five thousand rupees for every day during which the breach is 
continued after conviction for the first such breach.

</section>

<section><tid>474591</tid>
<number>4</number>Whoever, before, during or after the election of delegates under 
the proviso to sub- section (1) of section 38 or election of members of 
the board,-

<subsection><tid>263116</tid>
<number>a</number>fraudulently defaces or fraudulently destroys any nomination 
paper; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>986552</tid>
<number>b</number>fraudulently defaces, destroys or removes any list, notice or 
other document affixed by or under the authority of a returning 
officer; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>630331</tid>
<number>c</number>fraudulently defaces or fraudulently destroys any ballot paper or 
the official mark on any ballot paper or any declaration of identity; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1435307</tid>
<number>d</number>without due authority supplies any ballot paper to any person or 
receives any ballot paper from any person or is in possession of any 
ballot paper; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>426602</tid>
<number>e</number>fraudulently puts into any ballot box anything other than the 
ballot paper which he is authorised by law to put in; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1012368</tid>
<number>f</number>without due authority destroys, takes, opens or otherwise 
interferes, with any ballot box or ballot papers then in use for the 
purposes of the election; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>786544</tid>
<number>g</number>fraudulently or without due authority, as the case may be, 
attempts to do any of the foregoing acts or wilfully aids or abets the 
doing of any such acts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1677913</tid>
<number>h</number>offers any gift or promises to offer any gratification to any 
person with the object, directly or indirectly, of including-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>553531</tid>
<number>i</number>a person to stand or not to stand as, or to withdraw or not to 
withdraw from, being a candidate at an election; or

<subsubsection><tid>434408</tid>
<number>ii</number>a member to vote or refrain from voting at an election, or as a 
reward to a person for having so stood or not stood or for having 
withdrawn or not having withdrawn his candidature; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1927283</tid>
<number>iii</number>a member for having voted or refrained from voting, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months 
or with fine or with both.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>495862</tid>
<number> 105</number> Cognizance of offences.-
<section><tid>499788</tid>
<number>1</number>No court inferior to that of a  
Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class 
shall try any offence under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>589351</tid>
<number>2</number>No prosecution for offences under section 104 shall be instituted 
except on a complaint filed in writing by a member of a multi- State 
co- operative society or by the Central Registrar in the competent 
court.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER XV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1290096</tid>
<number>106</number>Copies of bye- laws, etc., to be open to inspection.- Every 
multi- State co- operative society shall keep a copy of the rules and 
its bye- laws and also a list of its members, open to inspection free 
of charge at all resonable times, at the registered ad ress of the 
society.


</article>



<article><tid>1331801</tid>
<number> 107</number> Place of keeping and inspection of, registers and returns.-
<section><tid>205542</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The register of members commencing from the date of the registration 
of multi- State co- operative society, the index of members, the 
register of debenture holders, and copies of all annua returns 
prepared together with the copies of certificates and documents, shall 
be kept at the registered office of the multi- State co- operative 
society.

</section>

<section><tid>1718860</tid>
<number>2</number>The registers, indexes, returns and copies of certificates and 
other documents referred to in sub- section (1) shall be open during 
business hours (subject to such reasonable restrictions, as the  
  hours in each day are allowed for inspection) to the inspection- 
multi- State co- operative society may impose, so that n t less than two

<subsection><tid>1340371</tid>
<number>a</number>of any member or debenture holder, without fee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1401013</tid>
<number>b</number>of any other person, on payment of such sum as may be prescribed 
for each inspection.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1667857</tid>
<number> 108</number> Inspection of books of account, etc., of multi- State 
co- operative society.-
<section><tid>302480</tid>
<number>1</number>The books of account and other books and  
papers of every multi- State co- operative society shall be open to 
inspection during business hours-

<subsection><tid>1519098</tid>
<number>i</number>by the Central Registrar, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>832244</tid>
<number>ii</number>by such officer of the Government as may be authorised by the 
Central Government in this behalf:
Provided that such inspection may be made without giving any previous 
notice to that society or any officer thereof;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126997</tid>
<number>iii</number>by the members of the multi- State co- operative society.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>948665</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of every director, other officer or employee 
of the multi- State co- operative society to produce to the person 
making inspection under sub- section (1), all such books of account and 
other books and papers of the multi- State co- ope ative society in his 
custody or control and to furnish him with any statement, information 
or explanation relating to the affairs of such society as the said 
person may require of him within such time and at such place as he may 
specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1919424</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall also be the duty of every director, other officer or 
employee of the multi- State co- operative society to give to the person 
making inspection under this section all assistance in connection with 
the inspection which the multi- State co- operat ve society may be 
reasonably expected to give.

</section>

<section><tid>662044</tid>
<number>4</number>The person making the inspection under this section may, during 
the course of inspection,-

<subsection><tid>1317335</tid>
<number>i</number>make or cause to be made copies of books of account and other 
books and papers, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1582460</tid>
<number>ii</number>place or cause to be placed any marks of identification thereon 
in token of the inspection having been made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>394615</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force or any contract to the contrary, the Central Registrar 
or an officer authorised under clause (ii) of sub- secion (1), making 
an inspection under this section shall have th same powers as are 
vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>832318</tid>
<number>i</number>the discovery and production of books of account and other 
documents, at such place and such time as may be specified by such 
person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1849260</tid>
<number>ii</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of persons and examining 
them on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1338224</tid>
<number>iii</number>inspection of any books, registers and other documents of the 
multi- State co- operative society at any place.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>683056</tid>
<number>6</number>Where an inspection of the books of account and other books and 
papers of the multi- State co- operative society has been made under 
this section, the Central Registrar or an officer authorised under 
clause (ii) of sub- section (1), making the inspecti n shall make a 
report to the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1113607</tid>
<number> 109</number> Annual accounts and balance- sheet.- At every annual general 
meeting of a multi- State co- operative society, the board shall lay 
before the multi- State co- operative society-
<section><tid>891063</tid>
<number>a</number>a balance- sheet as at the end of every co- operative year; and

</section>

<section><tid>724686</tid>
<number>b</number>a profit and loss account for that year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693130</tid>
<number> 110</number> Minutes of proceedings of general meetings and board and other 
meetings.-
<section><tid>101205</tid>
<number>1</number>Every multi- State co- operative society shall cause  
minutes of all proceedings of every general meeting and of all 
proceedings of every meeting of its board or of every com ittee of the 
board, to be kept by making within thirty days of the conclusion of 
every such meeting concerned, entries thereof in books kept for that 
purpose with their pages consecutively numbered.

</section>

<section><tid>348654</tid>
<number>2</number>Each page of every such book shall be initialed or signed and the 
last page of the record of proceedings of each meeting in such books 
shall be dated and signed-

<subsection><tid>1532352</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of minutes of proceedings of a meeting of the board or 
of a committee thereof, by the chairperson of the said meeting or the 
chairperson of the next succeeding meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>791946</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of minutes of proceedings of a general meeting, by the 
chairperson of the same meeting within the aforesaid period of thirty 
days or in the event of the death or inability of that chairperson 
within that period, by a member of the board uly authorised by the 
board for the purpose.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>682141</tid>
<number>3</number>In no case the minutes of proceedings of a meeting shall be 
attached to any such books as aforesaid by pasting or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>82208</tid>
<number>4</number>The minutes of each meeting shall contain a fair and correct 
summary of the proceedings thereat.

</section>

<section><tid>399314</tid>
<number>5</number>All appointments of officers made at any of the meetings aforesaid 
shall be included in the minutes of the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1727894</tid>
<number>6</number>In the case of a meeting of the board or of a committee of the 
board, the minutes shall also contain-

<subsection><tid>1205465</tid>
<number>a</number>the names of the members of the board present at the meeting; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>905337</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of each resolution passed at the meeting, the names of 
the members of the board, if any, dissenting from, or not concurring 
in, the resolution.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1026648</tid>
<number>7</number>Nothing contained in sub- sections (1) to (6) shall be deemed to 
require the inclusion in any such minutes of any matter which, in the 
opinion of the chairperson of the meeting-

<subsection><tid>567043</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or could reasonably be regarded as, defamatory of any person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1858359</tid>
<number>b</number>is irrelevant or immaterial to the proceedings; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1994383</tid>
<number>c</number>is detrimental to the interests of the multi- State co- operative 
society.
Explanation.- The chairperson shall exercise an absolute discretion in 
regard to the inclusion or non- inclusion of any matter in the minutes 
on the grounds specified in this sub- section.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476478</tid>
<number>111</number>Minutes to be evidence.- Minutes of meetings kept in accordance 
with the provisions of section 110 shall be evidence of the 
proceedings recorded therein.


</article>



<article><tid>336833</tid>
<number>112</number>Presumptions to be drawn where minutes duly drawn and 
signed.- Where minutes of the proceedings of any general meeting of the 
multi- State co- operative society or of any meeting of its board or a 
committee of the board have been kept in accordance wit the provisions 
of section 110, then, until the contrary is proved, the meeting shall 
be deemed to have been duly called and held, and all proceedings 
thereat to have duly taken place, and in particular, all appointments 
of directors or liquidators made at the meeting shall be deemed to be 
valid.


</article>



<article><tid>880057</tid>
<number> 113</number> Inspection of minutes book of general meetings.- The books 
containing the minutes of the proceedings of any general meeting of a 
multi- State co- operative society shall-
<section><tid>1164742</tid>
<number>a</number>be kept at the registered office of that society, and

</section>

<section><tid>700037</tid>
<number>b</number>be open, during business hours, to the inspection of any member of 
that society.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>263097</tid>
<number>114</number>Liquidator to be public servant.- Any person appointed as 
liquidator under the provisions of this Act shall be deemed to be a 
public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal 
Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1064965</tid>
<number>115</number>Notice necessary in suits.- No suit shall be instituted against a 
multi- State co- operative society or any of its officers in respect of 
any act touching the constitution, management or the business of the 
society until the expiration of ninety days n xt after notice in 
writing has been delivered to the Central Registrar or left at his 
office, stating the cause of action, the name, description and place 
of residence of the plaintiff and the relief which he claims, and the 
plaint shall contain a statem nt that such notice has been so 
delivered or left.


</article>



<article><tid>338213</tid>
<number> 116</number> Power to amend Second Schedule.-
<section><tid>690105</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is  
satisfied that any multi- State co- operative society should be 
designated as a national co- operative society or any national 
co- operative society specified in the Second Schedule shou d be 
omitted from the said Schedule, it may, by notification, amend the 
said Schedule so as to include therein such multi- State co- operative 
society or exclude therefrom such national co- operative society, and 
thereupon the said Schedule shall be deemed o have been amended 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1378073</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of every notification under sub- section (1) shall be laid 
before each House of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1403301</tid>
<number> 117</number> Bar of jurisdiction of courts.-
<section><tid>1367497</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in  
this Act, no court shall have jurisdiction in respect of-

<subsection><tid>205913</tid>
<number>a</number>the registration of a multi- State co- operative society or its 
bye- laws or of an amendment of the bye- laws;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819682</tid>
<number>b</number>any matter concerning the winding up and the dissolution of a 
multi- State co- operative society.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>304590</tid>
<number>2</number>While a multi- State co- operative society is being wound up, no 
suit or other legal proceedings relating to the business of such 
society shall be proceeded with or instituted against the liquidator 
or against the society or any member thereof, except y leave of the 
Central Registrar and subject to such terms and conditions as he may 
impose.

</section>

<section><tid>1016938</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, no decision or order made 
under this Act shall be questioned in any court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378250</tid>
<number>118</number>Indemnity.- No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall 
lie against the Central Registrar or, any person subordinate to him or 
acting on his authority or against any other person, in respect of 
anything in good faith done or purporting to h ve been done under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1751385</tid>
<number>119</number>Opening of branches.- Notwithstanding anything contained to the 
contrary in any law relating to co- operative societies in force in a 
State, a multi- State co- operative society, not being a co- operative 
bank, may open branches or places of business in ny place in India.


</article>



<article><tid>1488817</tid>
<number> 120</number> Filling of returns.- Every year within six months of the closure 
of the accounting year every multi- State co- operative society shall 
file the following returns with the Central Registrar, namely:-
<section><tid>1107785</tid>
<number>a</number>annual report of the activities;

</section>

<section><tid>562850</tid>
<number>b</number>audited statements of accounts;

</section>

<section><tid>1977673</tid>
<number>c</number>plan for surplus disposal as approved by the general body;

</section>

<section><tid>1639047</tid>
<number>d</number>list of amendments to the bye- laws of the multi- State co- operative 
society;

</section>

<section><tid>144517</tid>
<number>e</number>declaration regarding date of holding of general body meeting and 
conduct of elections where due;

</section>

<section><tid>1895278</tid>
<number>f</number>any other information required by the Central Registrar in 
pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>184697</tid>
<number> 121</number> Certain Acts not to apply.-
<section><tid>1471420</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of the Companies  
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) and the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade 
Practices Act, <year>1969</year> (54 of <year>1969</year>) shall not apply to the multi- State 
co- operative societies.

</section>

<section><tid>1446048</tid>
<number>2</number>The multi- State co- operative societies registered or deemed to be 
registered under the provisions of this Act shall not indulge in 
monopolistic and restrictive trade practices as defined in the 
Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, <year>1969</year> (54 of <year>1969</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171800</tid>
<number>122</number>Central Government' s power to give directions to specified 
multi- State co- operative societies in public interest.- If the Central 
Government is satisfied that in the public interest or for the 
purposes of securing proper implementation of co- operativ production 
and other developmental programmes approved or undetaken by the 
Central Government or to secure proper management of the business of 
the specified multi- State co- operative societies generally or for 
preventing the affairs of such society bein conducted in a manner 
detrimental to the interests of the members, any depositors or 
creditors thereof, it is necessary to issue directions to any class of 
specified multi- State co- operative societies generally or to any 
specified multi- State co- operati e society or societies in particular, 
the Central Government may issue directions to it or to them, from 
time to time, and all such specified multi- State co- operative society 
or the societies concerned, as the case may be, shall be bound to 
comply with s ch directions.


</article>



<article><tid>1290009</tid>
<number> 123</number> Supersession of board of specified multi- State co- operative 
society.-
<section><tid>1548723</tid>
<number>1</number>If in the opinion of the Central Government, the board of  
any specified multi- State co- operative society is persistently making 
default or is negligent in the performance of th duties imposed on it 
by this Act or the rules or the bye- laws or has committed any act 
which is prejudicial to the interests of the society or its members, 
or has omitted or failed to comply with any directions given to it 
under section 122 or that the e is a stalemate in the constitution or 
functions of the board, the Central Government may, after giving the 
board an opportunity to state its objections, if any, and considering 
the objections, if received, by order in writing, remove the board and 
appo nt one or more administrators, who need not be members of the 
society, to manage the affairs of the society for such period not 
exceeding six months, as may be specified in the order which period 
may, at the discretion of the Central Government, be exten ed from 
time to time; so, however, that the aggregate period does not exceed 
one year: Provided that in the case of a co- operative bank, the 
provisions of this sub- section shall have effect as if for the words 
" one year", the words" two years" had been substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>493196</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may fix such remuneration for the 
administrators, as it may think fit and the remuneration shall be paid 
out of the funds of the specified multi- State co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>1862786</tid>
<number>3</number>The administrator shall, subject to the control of the Central 
Government and to such instructions as it may from time to time give, 
have power to exercise all or any of the functions of the board or of 
any officer of the specified multi- State co- ope ative society and take 
all such actions as may be required in the interests of the society.

</section>

<section><tid>1345669</tid>
<number>4</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (5), the administrator 
shall, before the expiry of his term of office, arrange for the 
constitution of a new board in accordance with the bye- laws of the 
specified multi- State co- operative society.

</section>

<section><tid>218504</tid>
<number>5</number>If, at any time during the period the administrator is in office, 
the Central Government considers it necessary or expedient so to do, 
it may, by order in writing giving reasons therefor, direct the 
specified multi- State co- operative society in accordance with the 
bye- laws of such society and immediately on the constitution of such 
board, the administrator shall hand over the management of such 
society to such newly constituted boa administrator to arrange for the 
constitution of a ew board for such d and cease to function.

</section>

<section><tid>86424</tid>
<number>6</number>Where a specified multi- State co- operative society is indebted to 
any financial institution, the Central Government shall, before taking 
any action, under sub- section (1) in respect of that society, consult 
the financial institution.
Explanation.- For the purposes of sections 122 and 123," specified 
multi- State co- operative society" means any multi- State co- operative 
society in which not less than fifty- one per cent. of the paid- up 
share capital, or, of total shares, is held by the Ce tral Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365818</tid>
<number> 124</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1441798</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>933821</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1762</tid>
<number>a</number>the form to be used, the particulars to be given and the 
conditions to be complied with in making of applications under section 
 6 for the registration of a multi- State co- operative society and the 
procedure in the matter of such applications;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>817726</tid>
<number>b</number>the matters in respect of which a multi- State co- operative society 
may make bye- laws under sub- section (2) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>159669</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which the order of refusal to register any amendment 
of the bye- laws shall be communicated under sub- section (9) of section 
11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1253895</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which a multi- State co- operative society shall have 
a principal place of business and registered address under section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1323871</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure and conditions for change in the extent of the 
liability of a multi- State co- operative society under section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>740290</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which order of refusal to register an amendment of 
bye- laws shall be communicated under sub- section (4) of section 22;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>32949</tid>
<number>g</number>the classification of federal co- operative and other terms and 
conditions applicable to in under sub- section (3) of section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1098489</tid>
<number>h</number>the restriction on holding the share capital of the society other 
than a member referred to in section 33;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824194</tid>
<number>i</number>the constitution and powers of smaller body representing the 
general body under the proviso to sub- section (1) of section 38;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>598931</tid>
<number>j</number>the period within which annual general meeting be called and the 
procedure at such meetings and the powers to be exercised by such 
meeting under section 39;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>73760</tid>
<number>k</number>the election of members of the board under sub- section (2) of 
section 45 through secret ballot;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>195183</tid>
<number>l</number>the nomination of members under the second proviso to sub- section 
 (1) of section 48;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>170444</tid>
<number>m</number>the additional measures and acts which may be taken or, as the 
case may be, done by the board under section 49;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>565219</tid>
<number>n</number>the salary and allowances payable to and other terms and 
conditions of the Chief Executive under sub- section (3) of section 51;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>914412</tid>
<number>o</number>the conditions subject to which the board may constitute an 
Executive Committee and other committees or sub- committees under 
sub- section (1) of section 53;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488923</tid>
<number>p</number>the persons by whom and the form in which copies of entries in 
books of multi- State co- operative societies may be certified under 
section 58 and the charges to be levied for the supply of such copies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>819390</tid>
<number>q</number>providing aid to multi- State co- operative societies on certain 
terms and conditions under clause (g) of section 61;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>268861</tid>
<number>r</number>the conditions under which profits may be distributed to the 
members of a multi- State co- operative society and the maximum rate of 
dividend which may be paid by the multi- State co- operative societies 
under section 63;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940512</tid>
<number>s</number>establishment of contributory provident fund under sub- section (1) 
of section 69;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1088931</tid>
<number>t</number>the manner of disposing of the surplus under clause (k) of 
sub- section (2) of section 90;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1315243</tid>
<number>u</number>the manner in which surplus assets be divided by the Central 
Registrar with the previous sanction of the Central Government under 
clause (b) of section 91;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>855355</tid>
<number>v</number>the appellate authority to be specified under sub- section (2) of 
section 99;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>882306</tid>
<number>w</number>the procedure under section 103 for reconstitution and 
reorganisation of societies which became the multi- State co- operative 
societies consequent on reorganisation of States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1833613</tid>
<number>x</number>the inspection of records of the society on payment of fees under 
clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 107;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1306559</tid>
<number>y</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1740367</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessio s, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, a the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1487168</tid>
<number> 125</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1518301</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act s may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty: Provided that no order shall 
be made under this section after the expiry of two years from the 
commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>589150</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>28181</tid>
<number> 126</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1521377</tid>
<number>1</number>The Multi- State Co- operative Societies  
Act, <year>1984</year> (51 of <year>1984</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1699501</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in the General 
Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>) with respect to repeals, any 
notification, rule, order, requirement, registration, certificate, 
notice, decision, direction, approval, authorisation, consent, 
application, request or thing made, issued, given or done under the 
Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1984</year> (51 of <year>1984</year>) shall, if in 
force at the commencement of this Act, continue to be in force and 
have effect as if made, issued, given or done un er the corresponding 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1047347</tid>
<number>3</number>Every multi- State co- operative society, existing immediately 
before the commencement of this Act which has been registered under 
the Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>) or under any other 
Act relating to co- operative societies in force, in a y State or in 
pursuance of the provisions of the Multi- unit Co- operative Societies 
Act, <year>1942</year> (6 of <year>1942</year>) or the Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, 
 <year>1984</year> (51 of <year>1984</year>), shall be deemed to be registered under the 
corresponding provisions of this Act, an the bye- laws of such society 
shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of 
this Act, or the rules, continue to be in force until altered or 
rescinded.

</section>

<section><tid>1163091</tid>
<number>4</number>All appointments, rules and orders made, all notifications and 
notices issued and all suits and other proceedings instituted under 
any of the Acts referred to in sub- section (1) shall, in so far as 
they are not inconsistent with the provisions of thi Act, be deemed to 
have been respectively made, issued and instituted under this Act, 
save that an order made cancelling the registration of a multi- State 
co- operative society shall be deemed, unless the society has already 
been finally liquidated, to be an order made under section 86 for its 
being wound up.

</section>

<section><tid>897780</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions of this Act shall apply to-

<subsection><tid>1578853</tid>
<number>a</number>any application for registration of a multi- State co- operative 
society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>219783</tid>
<number>b</number>any application for registration of amendment of bye- laws of a 
multi- State co- operative society, pending at the commencement of this 
Act and to the proceedings consequent thereon and to any registration 
granted in pursuance thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1275137</tid>
<number>6</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, any legal proceeding 
pending in any court or before the Central Registrar or any other 
authority at the commencement of this Act shall be continued to be in 
that court or before the Central Registrar or that au hority as if 
this Act had not been passed.


</section>

</article>



 </act>