<act><title>

THE 
    delivery of books and newspaper 
    (public libraries) act, 1954</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Delivery of Books <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[and 
    Newspapers] (Public Libraries) Act, 1954.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir.
  













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “book” includes every volume, part or 
    division of a volume, and pamphlet, in any language and every sheet of 
    music, map, chart or plan separately printed or lithographed, but does not 
    include a newspaper published in conformity with the provisions of section 5 
    of the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>    
    ‘newspaper’ means any printed periodical work containing public news or 
    comments on public news published in conformity with the provisions of 
    section 5 of the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867;]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Public libraries” means the 
    National Library at Calcutta and any three other libraries1 which 
    may be specified by the Central Government in this behalf by notification in 
    the Official Gazette.
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Delivery of books to public libraries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any rule that may be made under this Act, but without prejudice 
    to the provisions contained in section 9 of the Press and Registration of 
    Books Act, 1867, the publisher of every book published in the territories to 
    which this Act extends after the commencement of this Act shall, 
    notwithstanding any agreement to the contrary, deliver at his own expense a 
    copy of the book to the National Library at Calcutta and one such copy to 
    each of the other three public libraries<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> within 
    thirty days from the date of its publication.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The copy 
    delivered to the National Library shall be a copy of the whole book with all 
    maps and illustrations belonging thereto, finished and coloured in the same 
    manner as the best copies of the same, and shall be bound, sewed or stitched 
    together, and on the best paper on which any copy of the book is printed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The copy 
    delivered to any other public library shall be on the paper on which the 
    largest number of copies of the book is printed for sale, and shall be in 
    the like condition as the books prepared for sale,
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing 
    contained in sub-section (1) shall apply to any second or subsequent edition 
    of a book in which edition no additions or alterations either in the 
    letter-press or in the maps, book-prints or other engravings, belonging to 
    the book have been made, and a copy of the first or some preceding edition 
    of which book has been delivered under this Act.





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> 
    Delivery of newspapers to public libraries.—Subject 
    to any rules that may be made under this Act, but without prejudice to the 
    provisions contained in the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867, the 
    publisher of every newspaper, published in the territories to which this Act 
    extends, shall deliver at his own expense one copy of each issue of such 
    newspaper as soon as it is published to each such public library as may be 
    notified in this behalf by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.]
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Receipt 
    for books delivered.—The person in 
    charge of a public library (whether called a librarian or by any other name) 
    or any other person authorized by him in this behalf to whom a copy of a 
    book is delivered under section 3 shall give to the publisher a receipt in 
    writing therefor.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Penalty.—Any 
    publisher who contravenes any provision of this Act or of any rule made 
    thereunder shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty rupees
    <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[and, 
    if the contravention is in respect of a book, shall also be punishable with 
    fine which shall be equivalent to the value of the book], and the Court 
    trying the offence may direct that the whole or any part of the fine 
    realised from him shall be paid, by way of compensation, to the public 
    library to which the book 
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[or 
    newspaper, as the case may be] ought to have been delivered.
  
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
    court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act save on 
    complaint made by an officer empowered in this behalf by the Central 
    Government by a General or Special order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No Court 
    inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first 
    class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> 
    Application of Act to books and newspapers published by Government.—This 
    Act shall also apply to books and newspapers published by or under the 
    authority of the Government but shall not apply to books meant for official 
    use only.]
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Power to make rules.—<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules2
    to carry out the 
    purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
    is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
    one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
    of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
    be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]
  
  




 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by the Delivery 
    of Books (Public Libraries) Amendment Act, 1956 (99 of 1956), sec. 3 
    (29-12-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   The Act has now been 
    extended to the Union territories of—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Clause (aa) was ins. by the 
    Delivery of Books (Public Libraries) Amendment Act, 1956 (99 of 1956), sec. 
    4 (29-12-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Delhi Public Library, S.P. 
    Mukherjee Marg, Delhi — Specified as Public Library — See Gazette of 
    India, dated 30-1-82, Pt. II, sec. 3(i), p. 262, G.S.R. 106/82.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Connemara Public 
    Library so notified—See Gazette of India, 17-9-1955, Pt. II. sec. 3, 
    p. 1808.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by the Delivery 
    of Books (Public Libraries) Amendment Act, 1956 (99 of 1956), sec. 5 
    (29-12-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. for the words “and 
    the value of the book” by the Delivery of Books (Public Libraries) Amendment 
    Act, 1956 (99 of 1956), sec. 6 (29-12-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins., ibid.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. for former section 7 
    by the Delivery of Books (Public Libraries) Amendment Act, 1956 (99 of 
    1956), sec. 7 (29-12-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Section 8 renumbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof and after sub-section (1) as so re-numbered,  
    sub-section (2) ins. by Act 4 of 2005, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 11-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   For Delivery of Books 
    (Public Libraries) Rules, 1955, see S.R.O. 587, dated 19-3-1955, Pt. 
    II, Sec. 3, p. 523.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>