<act><tid>897686</tid>
<title>THE WILD LIFE (PROTECTION) AMENDMENT ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 17th January, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Wild Life (Protection) Act, <year>1972</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>359086</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>475932</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Wild  
Life (Protection) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>92051</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>957474</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title.- In the Wild Life (Protection) Act, <year>1972</year> 
 (53 of <year>1972</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), for the 
long title, the following long title shall be substituted, namely:-
" An Act to provide for the protection of wild animals, birds and 
plants and for matters connected therewith or ancillary or incidental 
thereto with a view to ensuring the ecological and environmental 
security of the country.".



</article>



<article><tid>980368</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1987139</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (1), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (1)" animal" includes mammals, birds, reptiles, amphibians, fish, 
other chordates and invertebrates and also includes their young and 
eggs;';


</section>

<section><tid>947780</tid>
<number>b</number>for clause (4), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (4)" Board" means a State Board for Wild Life constituted under 
sub- section (1) of section 6;';


</section>

<section><tid>1490299</tid>
<number>c</number>clause (8) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1988391</tid>
<number>d</number>for clause (9), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (9)" Collector" means the chief officer- in- charge of the revenue 
administration of a district or any other officer not below the rank 
of a Deputy Collector as may be appointed by the State Government 
under section 18B in this behalf;';


</section>

<section><tid>707198</tid>
<number>e</number>for clause (11), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (11)" dealer" in relation to any captive animal, animal article, 
trophy, uncured trophy, meat or specified plant, means a person, who 
carries on the business of buying or selling any such animal or 
article, and includes a person who undertakes business n any single 
transaction;';


</section>

<section><tid>1689805</tid>
<number>f</number>for clause (12A), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (12A)" Forest officer" means the Forest officer appointed under 
clause (2) of section 2 of the Indian Forest Act, <year>1927</year> (16 of <year>1927</year>) or 
under any other Act for the time being in force in a State;


<subsection><tid>760238</tid>
<number>12B</number>" forest produce" shall have the same meaning as in sub- clause 
 (b) of clause (4) of section 2 of the Indian Forest Act, <year>1927</year> (16 of  
  <year>1927</year>);';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1089352</tid>
<number>g</number>in clause (16), for sub- clauses (a) and (b), the following 
sub- clauses shall be substituted, namely:-
" (a) killing or poisoning of any wild animal or captive animal and 
every attempt to do so;


</section>

<section><tid>947780</tid>
<number>b</number>capturing, coursing, snaring, trapping, driving or baiting any 
wild or captive animal and every attempt to do so;";

</section>

<section><tid>802259</tid>
<number>h</number>for clause (18A), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (18A)" livestock" means farm animals and includes buffaloes, bulls, 
bullocks, camels, cows, donkeys, goats, sheep, horses, mules, yaks, 
pigs, ducks, geese, poultry and their young but does not include any 
animal specified in Schedules I to V;';


</section>

<section><tid>1049601</tid>
<number>i</number>for clauses (19) and (20), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' (19)" manufacturer" means a person who manufactures articles from any 
animal or plant specified in Schedules I to V and VI, as the case may 
be;


<subsection><tid>901447</tid>
<number>20</number>" meat" includes blood, bones, sinew, eggs, shell or carapace, fat 
and flesh with or without skin, whether raw or cooked, of any wild 
animal or captive animal, other than a vermin;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1146594</tid>
<number>20A</number>" National Board" means the National Board for Wild Life 
constituted under section 5A;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>270184</tid>
<number>j</number>after clause (24), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (24A)" protected area" means a National Park, a sanctuary, a 
conservation reserve or a community reserve notified under sections 
18, 35, 36A and 36C of the Act;';


</section>

<section><tid>1011379</tid>
<number>k</number>for clauses (25B) and (26), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' (25B)" reserve forest" means the forest declared to be reserved by 
the State Government under section 20 of the Indian Forest Act, <year>1927</year> 
 (16 of <year>1927</year>), or declared as such under any other State Act;


<subsection><tid>839014</tid>
<number>26</number>" sanctuary" means an area declared as a sanctuary by notification 
under the provisions of Chapter IV of this Act and shall also include 
a deemed sanctuary under sub- section (4) of section 66;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>139386</tid>
<number>l</number>clause (28) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>248998</tid>
<number>m</number>for clause (30), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (30)" taxidermy", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, means the curing, preparation or preservation or mounting 
of trophies;';


</section>

<section><tid>1899985</tid>
<number>n</number>in clause (31), for sub- clause (b), the following sub- clause shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" (b) antler, bone, carapace, shell, horn, rhinoceros horn, hair, 
feather, nail, tooth, tusk, musk, eggs, nests and honeycomb;";


</section>

<section><tid>185253</tid>
<number>o</number>for clause (36), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (36)" wild animal" means any animal specified in Schedules I to IV 
and found wild in nature;';


</section>

<section><tid>1485806</tid>
<number>p</number>for clause (37), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (37)" wild life" includes any animal, aquatic or land vegetation 
which forms part of any habitat;';


</section>

<section><tid>754861</tid>
<number>q</number>in clause (39), for the words" but does not include a circus and 
an establishment", the words" and includes a circus and rescue centres 
but does not include an establishment" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>762923</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1435196</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), clause (b) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>845580</tid>
<number>ii</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (3) The officers and other employees appointed under this section 
shall be required to assist the Director.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1718712</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for clause (bb), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (bb) Honorary Wild Life Wardens;".



</article>



<article><tid>1289635</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new sections 5A to 5C.- After section 5 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 5A. Constitution of the National Board for Wild Life.- (1) The 
Central Government shall, within three months from the date of 
commencement of the Wild Life (Protection) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>, 
constitute the National Board for Wild Life consisting of the fo 
lowing members, namely:-

<section><tid>1958503</tid>
<number>a</number>the Prime Minister as Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>866276</tid>
<number>b</number>the Minister in- charge of Forests and Wild Life as 
Vice- Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>1332530</tid>
<number>c</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be from the House of 
the People and one from the Council of States;

</section>

<section><tid>1473883</tid>
<number>d</number>Member, Planning Commission in- charge of Forests and Wild Life;

</section>

<section><tid>1431687</tid>
<number>e</number>five persons to represent non- governmental organisations to be 
nominated by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>817486</tid>
<number>f</number>ten persons to be nominated by the Central Government from amongst 
eminent conservationists, ecologists and environmentalists;

</section>

<section><tid>457775</tid>
<number>g</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in- charge of the Ministry 
or Department of the Central Government dealing with Forests and Wild 
Life;

</section>

<section><tid>1113440</tid>
<number>h</number>the Chief of the Army Staff;

</section>

<section><tid>187220</tid>
<number>i</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in- charge of the Ministry 
of Defence;

</section>

<section><tid>982880</tid>
<number>j</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in- charge of the Ministry 
of Information and Broadcasting;

</section>

<section><tid>380838</tid>
<number>k</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in- charge of the 
Department of Expenditure, Ministry of Finance;

</section>

<section><tid>778500</tid>
<number>l</number>the Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of Tribal 
Welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>740891</tid>
<number>m</number>the Director- General of Forests in the Ministry or Department of 
the Central Government dealing with Forests and Wild Life;

</section>

<section><tid>1341349</tid>
<number>n</number>the Director- General of Tourism, Government of India;

</section>

<section><tid>521562</tid>
<number>o</number>the Director- General, Indian Council for Forestry Research and 
Education, Dehradun;

</section>

<section><tid>684840</tid>
<number>p</number>the Director, Wild Life Institute of India, Dehradun;

</section>

<section><tid>1889843</tid>
<number>q</number>the Director, Zoological Survey of India;

</section>

<section><tid>573949</tid>
<number>r</number>the Director, Botanical Survey of India;

</section>

<section><tid>1777676</tid>
<number>s</number>the Director, Indian Veterinary Research Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>589562</tid>
<number>t</number>the Member- Secretary, Central Zoo Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>1687437</tid>
<number>u</number>the Director, National Institute of Oceanography;

</section>

<section><tid>1952221</tid>
<number>v</number>one representative each from ten States and Union territories by 
rotation, to be nominated by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1420766</tid>
<number>w</number>the Director of Wild Life Preservation who shall be the 
Member- Secretary of the National Board.

<subsection><tid>1178509</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members other than those who are members 
ex officio, the manner of filling vacancies referred to in clauses 
 (e), (f) and (v) of sub- section (1), and the procedure to be followed 
in the discharge of their functions by the members of the National 
Board shall be such, as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411930</tid>
<number>3</number>The members (except members ex officio) shall be entitled to 
receive such allowances in respect of expenses incurred in the 
performance of their duties as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>679092</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, the office of a member of the National Board shall not 
be deemed to be an office of profit.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1532240</tid>
<number> 5B</number> Standing Committee of the National Board.-
<section><tid>370354</tid>
<number>1</number>The National Board  
may, in its discretion, constitute a Standing Committee for the 
purpose of exercising such powers and performing such duties as may be 
delegated to the Committee by the National Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1278434</tid>
<number>2</number>The Standing Committee shall consist of the Vice- Chairperson, the 
Member- Secretary, and not more than ten members to be nominated by the 
Vice- Chairperson from amongst the members of the National Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1848253</tid>
<number>3</number>The National Board may constitute committees, sub- committees or 
study groups, as may be necessary, from time to time in proper 
discharge of the functions assigned to it.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1609471</tid>
<number> 5C</number> Functions of the National Board.-
<section><tid>765799</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the  
National Board to promote the conservation and development of wild 
life and forests by such measures as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>989183</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, 
the measures referred to therein may provide for-

<subsection><tid>96674</tid>
<number>a</number>framing policies and advising the Central Government and the State 
Governments on the ways and means of promoting wild life conservation 
and effectively controlling poaching and illegal trade of wild life 
and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>739449</tid>
<number>b</number>making recommendations on the setting up of and management of 
national parks, sanctuaries and other protected areas and on matters 
relating to restriction of activities in those areas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1251236</tid>
<number>c</number>carrying out or causing to be carried out impact assessment of 
various projects and activities on wild life or its habitat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>134299</tid>
<number>d</number>reviewing from time to time, the progress in the field of wild 
life conservation in the country and suggesting measures for 
improvement thereto; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>286418</tid>
<number>e</number>preparing and publishing a status report at least once in two 
years on wild life in the country.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>480735</tid>
<number> 7</number> Substitution of new section for section 6.- For section 6 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 6. Constitution of State Board for Wild Life.- (1) The State 
Government shall, within a period of six months from the date of 
commencement of the Wild Life (Protection) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year> 
constitute a State Board for Wild Life consisting of the followin 
members, namely:-

<section><tid>1509047</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chief Minister of the State and in case of the Union 
territory, either Chief Minister or Administrator, as the case may be 
- Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>605523</tid>
<number>b</number>the Minister in- charge of Forests and Wild Life- 
Vice- Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>56191</tid>
<number>c</number>three members of the State Legislature or in the case of a Union 
territory with Legislature, two members of the Legislative Assembly of 
that Union territory;

</section>

<section><tid>1935304</tid>
<number>d</number>three persons to represent non- governmental organisations dealing 
with wild life to be nominated by the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>658707</tid>
<number>e</number>ten persons to be nominated by the State Government from amongst 
eminent conservationists, ecologists and environmentalists including 
at least two representatives of the Scheduled Tribes;

</section>

<section><tid>1795249</tid>
<number>f</number>the Secretary to the State Government or the Government of the 
Union territory, as the case may be, in- charge of Forests and Wild 
Life;

</section>

<section><tid>856563</tid>
<number>g</number>the Officer in- charge of the State Forest Department;

</section>

<section><tid>663487</tid>
<number>h</number>the Secretary to the State Government, Department of Tribal 
Welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>1916161</tid>
<number>i</number>the Managing Director, State Tourism Development Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>1436713</tid>
<number>j</number>an officer of the State Police Department not below the rank of 
Inspector- General;

</section>

<section><tid>1458173</tid>
<number>k</number>a representative of the Armed Forces not below the rank of a 
Brigadier to be nominated by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1329076</tid>
<number>l</number>the Director, Department of Animal Husbandry of the State;

</section>

<section><tid>1505100</tid>
<number>m</number>the Director, Department of Fisheries of the State;

</section>

<section><tid>176298</tid>
<number>n</number>an officer to be nominated by the Director, Wild Life 
Preservation;

</section>

<section><tid>42777</tid>
<number>o</number>a representative of the Wild Life Institute of India, Dehradun;

</section>

<section><tid>91647</tid>
<number>p</number>a representative of the Botanical Survey of India;

</section>

<section><tid>433421</tid>
<number>q</number>a representative of the Zoological Survey of India;

</section>

<section><tid>1911848</tid>
<number>r</number>the Chief Wild Life Warden, who shall be the Member- Secretary.

<subsection><tid>1827557</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members other than those who are members 
ex officio and the manner of filling vacancies referred to in clauses 
 (d) and (e) of sub- section (1) and procedure to be followed shall be 
such, as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1433990</tid>
<number>3</number>The member (except members ex officio) shall be entitled to 
receive such allowances in respect of expenses incurred in the 
performance of their duties as may be prescribed.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1394626</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 8.- In section 8 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1735031</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" the Wild Life Advisory Board", the words" State 
Board for Wild Life" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1754423</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (a) in the selection and management of areas to be declared as 
protected areas;".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>284510</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>99055</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), the following provisos and Explanation thereunder 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that no wild animal shall be ordered to be killed unless the 
Chief Wild Life Warden is satisfied that such animal cannot be 
captured, tranquilised or translocated:

Provided further that no such captured animal shall be kept in 
captivity unless the Chief Wild Life Warden is satisfied that such 
animal cannot be rehabilitated in the wild and the reasons for the 
same are recorded in writing.

Explanation.- For the purposes of clause (a), the process of capture or 
translocation, as the case may be, of such animal shall be made in 
such manner as to cause minimum trauma to the said animal.";


</section>

<section><tid>221287</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" such animal or cause such animal to 
be hunted", the words" such animal or group of animals in a specified 
area or cause such animal or group of animals in that specified area 
to be hunted" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1627867</tid>
<number>10</number>Substitution of heading of Chapter IV.- In Chapter IV of the 
principal Act, for the heading" SANCTUARIES, NATIONAL PARK AND CLOSED 
AREAS", the following heading shall be substituted, namely:-
" PROTECTED AREAS".



</article>



<article><tid>1523369</tid>
<number> 11</number> Insertion of new sections 18A and 18B.- After section 18 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 18A. Protection to sanctuaries.- (1) When the State Government 
declares its intention under sub- section (1) of section 18 to 
constitute any area, not comprised within any reserve forest or 
territorial waters under that sub- section, as a sanctuary, the pr 
visions of sections 27 to 33A (both inclusive) shall come into effect 
forthwith.

<section><tid>1868884</tid>
<number>2</number>Till such time as the rights of affected persons are finally 
settled under sections 19 to 24 (both inclusive), the State Government 
shall make alternative arrangements required for making available 
fuel, fodder and other forest produce to the person affected, in terms 
of their rights as per the Government records.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>162788</tid>
<number> 18B</number> Appointment of Collectors.- The State Government shall appoint, 
an officer to act as Collector under the Act, within ninety days of 
coming into force of the Wild Life (Protection) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>, 
or within thirty days of the issue of notificatio under section 18, to 
inquire into and determine the existence, nature and extent of rights 
of any person in or over the land comprised within the limits of the 
sanctuary which may be notified under sub- section
<section><tid>1134648</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 18.". 



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1024624</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 21.- In section 21 of the principal Act, 
after the words" the Collector shall", the words" within a period of 
sixty days," shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>1451125</tid>
<number> 13</number> Insertion of new section 25A.- After section 25 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 25A. Time- limit for completion of acquisition proceedings.- (1) The 
Collector shall, as far as possible, complete the proceedings under 
sections 19 to 25 (both inclusive), within a period of two years from 
the date of notification of declaration of sanc uary under section 18.

<section><tid>227811</tid>
<number>2</number>The notification shall not lapse if, for any reasons, the 
proceedings are not completed within a period of two years.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>460453</tid>
<number>14</number>Amendment of section 26A.- In section 26A of the principal Act, 
for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) No alteration of the boundaries of a sanctuary shall be made by 
the State Government except on a recommendation of the National 
Board.".



</article>



<article><tid>596077</tid>
<number>15</number>Substitution of new section for section 29.- For section 29 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 29. Destruction, etc., in a sanctuary prohibited without a 
permit.- No person shall destroy, exploit or remove any wild life 
including forest produce from a sanctuary or destroy or damage or 
divert the habitat of any wild animal by any act whatsoever or ivert, 
stop or enhance the flow of water into or outside the sanctuary, 
except under and in accordance with a permit granted by the Chief Wild 
Life Warden, and no such permit shall be granted unless the State 
Government being satisfied in consultation w th the Board that such 
removal of wild life from the sanctuary or the change in the flow of 
water into or outside the sanctuary is necessary for the improvement 
and better management of wild life therein, authorises the issue of 
such permit:

Provided that where the forest produce is removed from a sanctuary the 
same may be used for meeting the personal bona fide needs of the 
people living in and around the sanctuary and shall not be used for 
any commercial purpose. Explanation.- For the purposes of this 
section, grazing or movement of livestock permitted under clause (d) 
of section 33 shall not be deemed to be an act prohibited under this 
section.".



</article>



<article><tid>1691895</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of section 33.- In section 33 of the principal Act, 
after clause (a), the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that no construction of commercial tourist lodges, hotels, 
zoos and safari parks shall be undertaken inside a sanctuary except 
with the prior approval of the National Board;".



</article>



<article><tid>805908</tid>
<number> 17</number> Insertion of new section 33B.- After section 33A of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 33B. Advisory Committee.- (1) The State Government shall constitute 
an Advisory Committee consisting of the Chief Wild Life Warden or his 
nominee not below the rank of Conservator of Forests as its head and 
shall include a member of the State Legislature within whose 
constituency the sanctuary is situated, three representatives of 
Panchayati Raj Institutions, two representatives of non- governmental 
organisations and three individuals active in the field of wild life 
conservation, one representative each rom departments dealing with 
Home and Veterinary matters, Honorary Wild Life Warden, if any, and 
the officer- in- charge of the sanctuary as Member- Secretary.

<section><tid>69254</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall render advice on measures to be taken for 
better conservation and management of the sanctuary including 
participation of the people living within and around the sanctuary.

</section>

<section><tid>220307</tid>
<number>3</number>The Committee shall regulate its own procedure including quorum.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1352286</tid>
<number> 18</number> Insertion of new section 34A.- After section 34 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 34A. Power to remove encroachment.- (1) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, any officer 
not below the rank of an Assistant Conservator of Forests may,-

<section><tid>1852619</tid>
<number>a</number>evict any person from a sanctuary or National Park, who 
unauthorisedly occupies Government land in contravention of the 
provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>86854</tid>
<number>b</number>remove any unauthorised structures, buildings, or constructions 
erected on any Government land within any sanctuary or National Park 
and all the things, tools and effects belonging to such person shall 
be confiscated, by an order of an officer not be ow the rank of the 
Deputy Conservator of Forests:
Provided that no such order shall be passed unless the affected person 
is given an opportunity of being heard.


<subsection><tid>1964262</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this section shall apply notwithstanding any 
other penalty which may be inflicted for violation of any other 
provision of this Act.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>828724</tid>
<number> 19</number> Amendment of section 35.- In section 35 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1123961</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- sections (5) and (6), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (5) No alteration of the boundaries of a National Park by the State 
Government shall be made except on a recommendation of the National 
Board.


<subsection><tid>1175876</tid>
<number>6</number>No person shall destroy, exploit or remove any Wild Life including 
forest produce from a National Park or destroy or damage or divert the 
habitat of any wild animal by any act whatsoever or divert, stop or 
enhance the flow of water into or outside th National Park, except 
under and in accordance with a permit granted by the Chief Wild Life 
Warden, and no such permit shall be granted unless the State 
Government being satisfied in consultation with the National Board 
that such removal of wild life fro the National Park or the change in 
the flow of water into or outside the National Park is necessary for 
the improvement and better management of wild life therein, authorises 
the issue of such permit:
Provided that where the forest produce is removed from a National 
Park, the same may be used for meeting the personal bona fide needs of 
the people living in and around the National Park and shall not be 
used for any commercial purpose.";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1252164</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (8), the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, in case of an area, 
whether within a sanctuary or not, where the rights have been 
extinguished and the land has become vested in the State Government 
under any Act or otherwise, such area may be notified by it, by a 
notification, as a National Park and the proceedings under sections 19 
to 26 (both inclusive) and the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4) 
of this section shall not apply.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1444313</tid>
<number> 20</number> Insertion of new sections 36A to 36D.- After section 36 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 36A. Declaration and management of a conservation reserve.- (1) The 
State Government may, after having consultations with the local 
communities, declare any area owned by the Government, particularly 
the areas adjacent to National Parks and sanctuaries a d those areas 
which link one protected area with another, as a conservation reserve 
for protecting landscapes, seascapes, flora and fauna and their 
habitat:

Provided that where the conservation reserve includes any land owned 
by the Central Government, its prior concurrence shall be obtained 
before making such declaration.

<section><tid>1503977</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 18, sub- sections (2), 
 (3) and (4) of section 27, sections 30, 32 and clauses (b) and (c) of 
section 33 shall, as far as may be, apply in relation to a 
conservation reserve as they apply in relation to a sa ctuary.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>24602</tid>
<number> 36B</number> Conservation reserve management committee.-
<section><tid>646362</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government shall constitute a conservation reserve management 
committee to advise the Chief Wild Life Warden to conserve, manage and 
maintain the conservation reserve.

</section>

<section><tid>9389</tid>
<number>2</number>The committee shall consist of a representative of the forest or 
Wild Life Department, who shall be the Member- Secretary of the 
Committee, one representative of each Village Panchayat in whose 
jurisdiction the reserve is located, three representative of 
non- governmental organisations working in the field of wild life 
conservation and one representative each from the Department of 
Agriculture and Animal Husbandry.

</section>

<section><tid>1695426</tid>
<number>3</number>The Committee shall regulate its own procedure including the 
quorum.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1112040</tid>
<number> 36C</number> Declaration and management of community reserve.-
<section><tid>871040</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government may, where the community or an individual has volunteered 
to conserve wild life and its habitat, declare any private or 
community land not comprised within a National Park, sa ctuary or a 
conservation reserve, as a community reserve, for protecting fauna, 
flora and traditional or cultural conservation values and practices.

</section>

<section><tid>994439</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 18, sub- sections (2), 
 (3) and (4) of section 27, sections 30, 32 and clauses (b) and (c) of 
section 33 shall, as far as may be, apply in relation to a community 
reserve as they apply in relation to a sanct ary.

</section>

<section><tid>1962183</tid>
<number>3</number>After the issue of notification under sub- section (1), no change 
in the land use pattern shall be made within the community reserve, 
except in accordance with a resolution passed by the management 
committee and approval of the same by the State Gover ment.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248202</tid>
<number> 36D</number> Community reserve management committee.-
<section><tid>1029023</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
shall constitute a Community Reserve management committee, which shall 
be the authority responsible for conserving, maintaining and managing 
the community reserve.

</section>

<section><tid>1689029</tid>
<number>2</number>The committee shall consist of five representatives nominated by 
the Village Panchayat or where such Panchayat does not exist by the 
members of the Gram Sabha and one representative of the State Forests 
or Wild Life Department under whose jurisdictio the community reserve 
is located.

</section>

<section><tid>486693</tid>
<number>3</number>The committee shall be the competent authority to prepare and 
implement the management plan for the community reserve and to take 
steps to ensure the protection of wild life and its habitat in the 
reserve.

</section>

<section><tid>1788834</tid>
<number>4</number>The committee shall elect a Chairman who shall also be the 
Honorary Wild Life Warden on the community reserve.

</section>

<section><tid>25955</tid>
<number>5</number>The committee shall regulate its own procedure including the 
quorum.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377634</tid>
<number>21</number>Omission of section 37.- Section 37 of the principal Act shall be 
omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1265319</tid>
<number>22</number>Amendment of section 38B.- In section 38B of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after the words" every member", the words" other than 
the Member- Secretary" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>509643</tid>
<number>23</number>Amendment of section 38H.- In section 38H of the principal Act, 
after sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (1A) On and after the commencement of the Wild Life (Protection) 
Amendment Act, <year>2002</year> a zoo shall not be established without obtaining 
the prior approval of the Authority.".



</article>



<article><tid>1645661</tid>
<number> 24</number> Substitution of new section for section 38-I.- For section 38-I of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 38I. Acquisition of animals by a zoo.- (1) Subject to the other 
provisions of this Act, no zoo shall acquire, sell or transfer any 
wild animal or captive animal specified in Schedules I and II except 
with the previous permission of the Authority.

<section><tid>12511</tid>
<number>2</number>No zoo shall acquire, sell or transfer any wild or captive animal 
except from or to a recognised zoo.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1604821</tid>
<number> 25</number> Amendment of section 40.- In section 40 of principal Act,-
<section><tid>469266</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" or any uncured trophy", the 
words" or animal article, trophy or uncured trophy" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>693693</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (2A) No person other than a person having a certificate of ownership, 
shall, after the commencement of the Wild Life (Protection) Amendment 
Act, <year>2002</year> acquire, receive, keep in his control, custody or possession 
any captive animal, animal article, trophy or uncured trophy specified 
in Schedule I or Part II of Schedule II, except by way of inheritance.


<subsection><tid>553826</tid>
<number>2B</number>Every person inheriting any captive animal, animal article, 
trophy or uncured trophy under sub- section (2A) shall, within ninety 
days of such inheritance make a declaration to the Chief Wild Life 
 42 shall apply as if the declaration had been made under sub- section 
 (1) of section 40: Warden or the authorised officer and the 
provisions o sections 41 and
Provided that nothing in sub- sections (2A) and (2B) shall apply to the 
live elephant.".


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1453670</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (4), for the words" any animal article", the 
words" any animal or animal article" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1097349</tid>
<number> 26</number> Insertion of new section 40A.- After section 40 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 40A. Immunity in certain cases.- (1) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub- sections (2) and (4) of section 40 of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by notification, require any person to declare 
to the Chief Wild Life Warden or the authorised offi er, any captive 
animal, animal article, trophy or uncured trophy derived from animals 
specified in Schedule I or Part II of Schedule II in his control, 
custody or possession, in respect of which no declaration had been 
made under sub- section (1) or sub- ection (4) of section 40, in such 
form, in such manner and within such time as may be prescribed.

<section><tid>139221</tid>
<number>2</number>Any action taken or purported to be taken for violation of section 
 40 of this Act at any time before the commencement of the Wild Life 
 (Protection) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year> shall not be proceeded with and all 
pending proceedings shall stand abated.

</section>

<section><tid>1587832</tid>
<number>3</number>Any captive animal, animal article, trophy or uncured trophy 
declared under sub- section (1), shall be dealt with in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1069400</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of section 42.- In section 42 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be added, namely:-
" Provided that before issuing the certificate of ownership in respect 
of any captive animal, the Chief Wild Life Warden shall ensure that 
the applicant has adequate facilities for housing, maintenance and 
upkeep of the animal.".



</article>



<article><tid>1339897</tid>
<number> 28</number> Substitution of new section for section 43.- For section 43 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 43. Regulation of transfer of animal, etc.- (1) No person having in 
his possession captive animal, animal article, trophy or uncured 
trophy in respect of which he has a certificate of ownership shall 
transfer by way of sale or offer for sale or by any ot er mode of 
consideration of commercial nature, such animal or article or trophy 
or uncured trophy.

<section><tid>994144</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person transfers or transports from the State in which he 
resides to another State or acquires by transfer from outside the 
State, any such animal, animal article, trophy or uncured trophy in 
respect of which he has a certificate of ownership he shall, within 
thirty days of the transfer or transport, report the transfer or 
transport to the Chief Wild Life Warden or the authorised officer 
within whose jurisdiction the transfer or transport is effected.

</section>

<section><tid>1737064</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall apply-

<subsection><tid>1367134</tid>
<number>a</number>to tail feather of peacock and the animal article or trophies made 
therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1810896</tid>
<number>b</number>to transfer of captive animals between recognised zoos subject to 
the provisions of section 38-I, and transfer amongst zoos and public 
museums.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1369430</tid>
<number> 29</number> Amendment of section 50.- In section 50 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1589</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (3A), for the words" Wild Life Warden," the words 
" an Assistant Conservator of Forests" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1343093</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (4), the words" under intimation to the Chief Wild 
Life Warden or the officer authorised by him in this regard" shall be 
inserted at the end;

</section>

<section><tid>1907964</tid>
<number>iii</number>for sub- section (6), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (6) Where any meat, uncured trophy, specified plant or part or 
derivative thereof is seized under the provisions of this section, the 
Assistant Director of Wild Life Preservation or any other officer of a 
gazetted rank authorised by him in this behalf r the Chief Wild Life 
Warden or the authorised officer may arrange for the disposal of the 
same in such manner as may be prescribed.";


</section>

<section><tid>1776563</tid>
<number>iv</number>in sub- section (8), for the words" Wild Life Warden", the words 
" an officer not below the rank of Assistant Conservator of Forests 
authorised by the State Government in this behalf" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236121</tid>
<number> 30</number> Amendment of section 51.- In section 51 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1887776</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), for the first and second provisos, the 
following provisos shall be substituted, namely:-
" Provided that where the offence committed is in relation to any 
animal specified in Schedule I or Part II of Schedule II or meat of 
any such animal or animal article, trophy or uncured trophy derived 
from such animal or where the offence relates to hunt ng in a 
sanctuary or a National Park or altering the boundaries of a sanctuary 
or a National Park, such offence shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than three years but may extend to 
seven years and also with fine whi h shall not be less than ten 
thousand rupees:

Provided further that in the case of a second or subsequent offence of 
the nature mentioned in this sub- section, the term of the imprisonment 
shall not be less than three years but may extend to seven years and 
also with fine which shall not be less than twenty- five thousand 
rupees.";


</section>

<section><tid>1995586</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (1A), for the words" one year", the words" three 
years" and for the words" five thousand rupees", the words" ten 
thousand rupees" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1163447</tid>
<number> 31</number> Insertion of new section 51A.- After section 51 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 51A. Certain conditions to apply while granting bail.- When any 
person accused of, the commission of any offence relating to Schedule 
I or Part II of Schedule II or offences relating to hunting inside the 
boundaries of National Park or wild life sanctua y or altering the 
boundaries of such parks and sanctuaries, is arrested under the 
provisions of the Act, then notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>) no such person who had 
been previously convicted of an o fence under this Act shall, be 
released on bail unless-

<section><tid>1612050</tid>
<number>a</number>the Public Prosecutor has been given an opportunity of opposing 
the release on bail; and

</section>

<section><tid>1210423</tid>
<number>b</number>where the Public Prosecutor opposes the application, the Court is 
satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for believing that he is 
not guilty of such offence and that he is not likely to commit any 
offence while on bail.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297604</tid>
<number> 32</number> Substitution of new section for section 54.- For section 54 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 54. Power to compound offences.- (1) The Central Government may, by 
notification, empower the Director of Wild Life Preservation or any 
other officer not below the rank of Assistant Director of Wild Life 
Preservation and in the case of a State Government in the similar 
manner, empower the Chief Wild Life Warden or any officer of a rank 
not below the rank of a Deputy Conservator of Forests, to accept from 
any person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has 
committed an offence against this A t, payment of a sum of money by 
way of composition of the offence which such person is suspected to 
have committed.

<section><tid>1153037</tid>
<number>2</number>On payment of such sum of money to such officer, the suspected 
person, if in custody, shall be discharged and no further proceedings 
in respect of the offence shall be taken against such person.

</section>

<section><tid>329838</tid>
<number>3</number>The officer compounding any offence may order the cancellation of 
any licence or permit granted under this Act to the offender, or if 
not empowered to do so, may approach an officer so empowered, for the 
cancellation of such licence or permit.

</section>

<section><tid>913369</tid>
<number>4</number>The sum of money accepted or agreed to be accepted as composition 
under sub- section (1) shall, in no case, exceed the sum of twenty- five 
thousand rupees: Provided that no offence, for which a minimum period 
of imprisonment has been prescribed in section 51, shall be 
compounded.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>379112</tid>
<number> 33</number> Amendment of section 55.- In section 55 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>137625</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (a), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (aa) the Member- Secretary, Central Zoo Authority in matters relating 
to violation of the provisions of Chapter IVA; or";


</section>

<section><tid>427042</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), after the words" State Government", the words 
" subject to such conditions as may be specified by that Government" 
shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>318425</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (bb) the officer- in- charge of the zoo in respect of violation of 
provisions of section 38J; or".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1503350</tid>
<number>34</number>Insertion of new Chapter VIA.- After Chapter VI of the principal 
Act, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
' CHAPTER VI A

FORFEITURE OF PROPERTY DERIVED FROM ILLEGAL HUNTING AND TRADE

</article>



<article><tid>209767</tid>
<number> 58A</number> Application.- The provisions of this Chapter shall apply only to 
the following persons, namely:-
<section><tid>1570193</tid>
<number>a</number>every person who has been convicted of an offence punishable under 
this Act with imprisonment for a term of three years or more;

</section>

<section><tid>444298</tid>
<number>b</number>every associate of a person referred to in clause (a);

</section>

<section><tid>1612115</tid>
<number>c</number>any holder (hereafter in this clause referred to as the present  
  holder) of any property which was at any time previously held by a 
person referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) unless the present 
holder or, as the case may be, any one who held such roperty after 
such person and before the present holder, is or was a transferee in 
good faith for adequate consideration.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1044587</tid>
<number> 58B</number> Definitions.- In this Chapter, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1246093</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited 
Property constituted under section 58N;

</section>

<section><tid>686003</tid>
<number>b</number>" associate" in relation to a person whose property is liable to be 
forfeited under this Chapter, includes-

<subsection><tid>487207</tid>
<number>i</number>any individual who had been or is managing the affairs or keeping 
the accounts of such person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517562</tid>
<number>ii</number>any association of persons, body of individuals, partnership firm 
or private company within the meaning of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>) of which such person had been or is a member, partner or 
director;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1812349</tid>
<number>iii</number>any individual who had been or is a member, partner or director 
of an association of persons, body of individuals, partnership firm or 
private company referred to in sub- clause (ii) at any time when such 
person had been or is a member, partner or d rector of such 
association, body, partnership firm or private company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>229054</tid>
<number>iv</number>any person, who had been or is managing the affairs, or keeping 
the accounts of any association of persons, body of individuals, 
partnership firm or private company referred to in sub- clause (iii);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1469264</tid>
<number>v</number>the trustee of any trust, where,-

<subsubsection><tid>391118</tid>
<number>1</number>the trust has been created by such person; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>850291</tid>
<number>2</number>the value of the assets contributed by such person (including the  
  value of the assets, if any, contributed by him earlier) to the trust 
amounts on the date on which contribution is made, to not less than 
date; twenty per cent. of the value of the assets of the trust on 
that

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>560041</tid>
<number>vi</number>where the competent authority, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, considers that any properties of such person are held on his 
behalf by any other person, such other person;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>611157</tid>
<number>c</number>" competent authority" means an officer authorised under section 
58D;

</section>

<section><tid>1767850</tid>
<number>d</number>" concealment" means the concealment or disguise of the nature, 
source, disposition, movement or ownership of property and includes 
the movement or conversion of such property by electronic transmission 
or by any other means;

</section>

<section><tid>1901704</tid>
<number>e</number>" freezing" means temporarily prohibiting the transfer, conversion, 
disposition or movement of property by an order issued under section 
58F;

</section>

<section><tid>90207</tid>
<number>f</number>" identifying" includes establishment of proof that the property 
was derived from, or used in, the illegal hunting and trade of wild 
life and its products;

</section>

<section><tid>491137</tid>
<number>g</number>" illegally acquired property" in relation to any person to whom 
this Chapter applies, means,-

<subsection><tid>1700018</tid>
<number>i</number>any property acquired by such person, wholly or partly out of or 
by means of any income, earnings or assets derived or obtained from or 
attributable to illegal hunting and trade of wild life and its 
products and derivatives;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>824975</tid>
<number>ii</number>any property acquired by such person, for a consideration or by 
any means, wholly or partly traceable to any property referred to in 
sub- clause (i) or the income or earning from such property,
and includes-


<subsubsection><tid>1052544</tid>
<number>A</number>any property held by such person which would have been, in 
relation to any previous holder thereof, illegally acquired property 
under this clause if such previous holder had not ceased to hold it, 
unless such person or any other person who held the p operty at any 
time after such previous holder or, where there are two or more such 
previous holders, the last of such previous holders is or was a 
transferee in good faith for adequate consideration;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1887803</tid>
<number>B</number>any property acquired by such person, for a consideration, or by 
any means, wholly or partly traceable to any property falling under 
item (A), or the income or earnings therefrom;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>861330</tid>
<number>h</number>" property" means property and assets of every description, whether 
corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, tangible or intangible 
and deeds and instruments evidencing title to, or interest in, such 
property or assets, derived from the illegal hunting and trade of wild 
life and its products;

</section>

<section><tid>1037508</tid>
<number>i</number>" relative" means-

<subsection><tid>1077234</tid>
<number>1</number>spouse of the person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1684240</tid>
<number>2</number>brother or sister of the person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>271551</tid>
<number>3</number>brother or sister of the spouse of the person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>292453</tid>
<number>4</number>any lineal ascendant or descendant of the person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932738</tid>
<number>5</number>any lineal ascendant or descendant of the spouse of the person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>87761</tid>
<number>6</number>spouse of a person referred to in sub- clause (2), sub- clause (3), 
sub- clause (4) or sub- clause (5);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>220727</tid>
<number>7</number>any lineal descendant of a person referred to in sub- clause (2) or 
sub- clause (3);

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>976884</tid>
<number>j</number>" tracing" means determining the nature, source, disposition, 
movement, title or ownership of property;

</section>

<section><tid>1217124</tid>
<number>k</number>" trust" includes any other legal obligation.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>996205</tid>
<number> 58C</number> Prohibition of holding illegally acquired property.-
<section><tid>1055691</tid>
<number>1</number>From the  
date of commencement of this Chapter, it shall not be lawful for any 
person to whom this Chapter applies to hold any illegally acquired 
property either by himself or through any other erson on his behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>762915</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person holds such property in contravention of the 
provisions of sub- section (1), such property shall be liable to be 
forfeited to the State Government concerned in accordance with the 
provisions of this Chapter:
Provided that no property shall be forfeited under this Chapter if 
such property was acquired by a person to whom this Act applies before 
a period of six years from the date on which he was charged for an 
offence relating to illegal hunting and trade of ild life and its 
products.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1695028</tid>
<number>58D</number>Competent authority.- The State Government may, by order 
published in the Official Gazette, authorise any officer not below the 
rank of Chief Conservator of Forests to perform the functions of the 
competent authority under this Chapter in respect of uch persons or 
classes of persons as the State Government may, direct.
</article>



<article><tid>853255</tid>
<number> 58E</number> Identifying illegally acquired property.-
<section><tid>1976047</tid>
<number>1</number>An officer not  
below the rank of Deputy Inspector General of Police duly authorised 
by the Central Government or as the case may be, the State Government, 
shall, on receipt of a complaint from the compete t authority about 
any person having illegally acquired property, proceed to take all 
steps necessary for tracing and identifying any property illegally 
acquired by such person.

</section>

<section><tid>516307</tid>
<number>2</number>The steps referred to in sub- section (1) may include any inquiry, 
investigation or survey in respect of any person, place, property, 
assets, documents, books of account in any bank or financial 
institution or any other relevant step as may be necessa y.

</section>

<section><tid>1123167</tid>
<number>3</number>Any inquiry, investigation or survey referred to in sub- section 
 (2) shall be carried out by an officer mentioned in sub- section (1) in 
accordance with such directions or guidelines as the competent 
authority may make or issue in this behalf.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1882832</tid>
<number> 58F</number> Seizure or freezing of illegally acquired property.-
<section><tid>493807</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any officer conducting an inquiry or investigation under section 58E 
has reason to believe that any property in relation to which such 
inquiry or investigation is being conducted is an il egally acquired 
property and such property is likely to be concealed, transferred or 
dealt with in any manner which may result in frustrating any 
proceeding relating to forfeiture of such property under this Chapter, 
he may make an order for seizing such property and where it is not 
practicable to seize such property, he may make an order that such 
property shall not be transferred or otherwise dealt with, except with 
the prior permission of the officer making such order, or of the 
competent authority an a copy of such order shall be served on the 
person concerned:
Provided that a copy of such an order shall be sent to the competent 
authority within forty- eight hours of its being made.


</section>

<section><tid>447859</tid>
<number>2</number>Any order made under sub- section (1) shall have no effect unless 
the said order is confirmed by an order of the competent authority 
within a period of thirty days of its being made.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," transfer of property" 
means any disposition, conveyance, assignment, settlement, delivery, 
payment or other alienation of property and, without limiting the 
generality of the foregoing, includes-


<subsection><tid>700663</tid>
<number>a</number>the creation of a trust in property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1253056</tid>
<number>b</number>the grant or creation of any lease, mortgage, charge, easement, 
licence, power, partnership or interest in property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1057727</tid>
<number>c</number>the exercise of a power of appointment, of property vested in any 
person not the owner of the property, to determine its disposition in 
favour of any person other than the donee of the power; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444957</tid>
<number>d</number>any transaction entered into by any person with intent thereby to 
diminish directly or indirectly the value of his own property and to 
increase the value of the property of any other person.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>705135</tid>
<number> 58G</number> Management of properties seized or forfeited under this 
Chapter.-
<section><tid>1447007</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by order published in the  
Official Gazette, appoint as many of its officers (not below the rank  
  of Conservator of Forests) as it thinks fit, to perform th functions 
of an Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1435511</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator appointed under sub- section (1) shall receive 
and manage the property in relation to which an order has been made 
under sub- section (1) of section 58F or under section 58-I in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be pre cribed.

</section>

<section><tid>21617</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator shall also take such measures as the State 
Government may direct, to dispose of the property which is forfeited 
to the State Government.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>565723</tid>
<number> 58H</number> Notice of forfeiture of property.-
<section><tid>1160483</tid>
<number>1</number>If having regard to the  
value of the properties held by any person to whom this Chapter 
applies, either by himself or through any other person on his behalf, 
his known sources of income, earnings or assets, and ny other 
information or material available to it as a result of a report from 
any officer making an investigation under section 58E or otherwise, 
the competent authority for reasons to be recorded in writing believes 
that all or any of such properties ar illegally acquired properties, 
it may serve a notice upon such person (hereinafter referred to as the  
  person affected) calling upon him within a period of thirty days 
specified in the notice to show cause why all or any of such 
properties, as the case m y be, should not be declared to be illegally 
acquired properties and forfeited to the State Government under this 
Chapter and in support of his case indicate the sources of his income, 
earnings or assets, out of which or by means of which he has acquired 
such property, the evidence on which he relies and other relevant 
information and particulars.

</section>

<section><tid>865890</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a notice under sub- section (1) to any person specifies any 
property as being held on behalf of such person by any other person, a 
copy of the notice shall also be served upon such other person.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1641724</tid>
<number> 58I</number> Forfeiture of property in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1531397</tid>
<number>1</number>The competent  
authority may, after considering the explanation, if any, to the show 
cause notice issued under section 58H, and the materials available 
before it and after giving to the person affected an in a case where 
the person affected holds any property specified in the notice through 
any other person, to such other person, also a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard, by order, record a finding whether all or any of the 
properties in question are illegally acquired properties:
Provided that if the person affected (and in a case where the person  
affected holds any property specified in the notice through any other 
  person, such other person also), does not appear before the competent 
authority or represent his case before it wit in a period of thirty 
days specified in the show cause notice, the competent authority may 
proceed to record a finding under this sub- section ex parte on the 
basis of evidence available before it.


</section>

<section><tid>342746</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the competent authority is satisfied that some of the 
properties referred to in the show cause notice are illegally acquired 
properties but is not able to identify specifically such properties, 
then, it shall be lawful for the competent authori y to specify the 
properties which, to the best of its judgment, are illegally acquired 
properties and record a finding accordingly under sub- section (1) 
within a period of ninety days.

</section>

<section><tid>750188</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the competent authority records a finding under this section 
to the effect that any property is illegally acquired property, it 
shall declare that such property shall, subject to the provisions of 
this Chapter stand forfeited to the State Gover ment free from all 
encumbrances.

</section>

<section><tid>1146840</tid>
<number>4</number>In case the person affected establishes that the property 
specified in the notice issued under section 58H is not an illegally 
acquired property and therefore not liable to be forfeited under the 
Act, the said notice shall be withdrawn and the proper y shall be 
released forthwith.

</section>

<section><tid>1476661</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any shares in a company stand forfeited to the State 
Government under this Chapter, the company shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or the 
article of association of the company, forthwith register th State 
Government as the transferee of such shares.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1558465</tid>
<number>58J</number>Burden of proof.- In any proceedings under this Chapter, the 
burden of proving that any property specified in the notice served 
under section 58H is not illegally acquired property shall be on the 
person affected.
</article>



<article><tid>961986</tid>
<number> 58K</number> Fine in lieu of forfeiture.-
<section><tid>919356</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the competent authority  
makes a declaration that any property stands forfeited to the State 
Government under section 58-I and it is a case where the source of 
only a part of the illegally acquired property has n t been proved to 
the satisfaction of the competent authority, it shall make an order 
giving option to the person affected to pay, in lieu of forfeiture, a 
fine equal to the market value of such part.

</section>

<section><tid>213075</tid>
<number>2</number>Before making an order imposing a fine under sub- section (1), the 
person affected shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.

</section>

<section><tid>1772251</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the person affected pays the fine due under sub- section (1), 
within such time as may be allowed in that behalf, the competent 
authority may, by order revoke the declaration of forfeiture under 
section 58-I and thereupon such property shall stan released.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>279783</tid>
<number> 58L</number> Procedure in relation to certain trust properties.- In the case 
of any person referred to in sub- clause (vi) of clause (b) of section 
58B, if the competent authority, on the basis of the information and 
materials available to it, for reasons to be re orded in writing 
believes that any property held in trust is illegally acquired 
property, it may serve a notice upon the author of the trust, or as 
the case may be, the contributor of the assets out of or by means of 
which such property was acquired by t e trust and the trustees, 
calling upon them within a period of thirty days specified in the 
notice, to explain the source of money or other assets out of or by 
means of which such property was acquired or, as the case may be, the 
source of money or other assets which were contributed to the trust 
for acquiring such property and thereupon such notice shall be deemed 
to be a notice served under section 58H and all the other provisions 
of this Chapter shall apply accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section" illegally acquired 
property" in relation to any property held in trust, includes-

<section><tid>1353934</tid>
<number>i</number>any property which if it had continued to be held by the author of 
the trust or the contributor of such property to the trust would have 
been illegally acquired property in relation to such author or 
contributor;

</section>

<section><tid>180373</tid>
<number>ii</number>any property acquired by the trust out of any contributions made 
by any person which would have been illegally acquired property in 
relation to such person had such person acquired such property out of 
such contributions.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>66790</tid>
<number> 58M</number> Certain transfers to be null and void.- Where after the making of 
an order under sub- section
<section><tid>1371073</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 58F or the issue of a notice  
under section 58H or under section 58L, any property referred to in 
the said order or notice is transferred by an mode whatsoever, such 
transfer shall, for the purposes of the proceedings under this 
Chapter, be ignored and if such property is subsequently forfeited to 
the State Government under section 58-I, then, the transfer of such 
property shall be deemed to be null and void.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1630058</tid>
<number> 58N</number> Constitution of Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1171877</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Appellate 
Tribunal to be called the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property 
consisting of a Chairman, and such number of other members (being  
officers of the State Government not below the rank of a Principal 
  Secretary to the Government), as the State Government thinks fit, to 
be appointed by that Government for hearing appeals against the orders 
made under section 58F, section 8-I, sub- section (1) of section 58K or 
section 58L.

</section>

<section><tid>1026830</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal shall be a person who is or 
has been or is qualified to be a Judge of a High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1847089</tid>
<number>3</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other 
members shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>391479</tid>
<number> 58O</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>1540646</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an order of the competent  
authority made under section 58F, section 58-I, sub- section (1) of 
section 58K or section 58L may, within forty- five days from the date 
on which the order is served on him prefer an app al to the Appellate 
Tribunal:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the 
said period of forty- five days, but not after sixty days, from the 
date aforesaid if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from filing the appeal in tim.


</section>

<section><tid>1818047</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (1), the Appellate 
Tribunal may, after giving an opportunity of being heard to the 
appellant, if he so desires, and after making such further inquiry as 
it deems fit, confirm, modify or set aside the order ap ealed against.

</section>

<section><tid>162777</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Tribunal may regulate its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>1396949</tid>
<number>4</number>On application to the Appellate Tribunal and on payment of the 
prescribed fee, the Appellate Tribunal may allow a party to any appeal 
or any person authorised in this behalf by such party to inspect at 
any time during office hours, any relevant recor s and registers of 
the Appellate Tribunal and obtain a certified copy or any part 
thereof.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1880189</tid>
<number>58P</number>Notice or order not to be invalid for error in description.- No 
notice issued or served, no declaration made, and no order passed 
under this Chapter shall be deemed to be invalid by reason of any 
error in the description of the property or person men ioned therein 
if such property or person is identifiable from the description so 
mentioned.
</article>



<article><tid>1949319</tid>
<number>58Q</number>Bar of jurisdiction.- No order passed or declaration made under 
this Chapter shall be appealable except as provided therein and no 
civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the 
Appellate Tribunal or any competent authority is empowered by or under 
this Chapter to determine, and no injunction shall be granted by any 
court or other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken 
in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Chapter.
</article>



<article><tid>81507</tid>
<number> 58R</number> Competent Authority and Appellate Tribunal to have powers of 
civil court.- The competent authority and the Appellate Tribunal shall 
have all the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>) in respec of the following 
matters, namely:-
<section><tid>339854</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
him on oath;

</section>

<section><tid>594551</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</section>

<section><tid>895589</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</section>

<section><tid>795185</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any court or 
office;

</section>

<section><tid>1019110</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for examination of witnesses or documents;

</section>

<section><tid>293963</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1325556</tid>
<number> 58S</number> Information to competent authority.-
<section><tid>554090</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in any other law for the time being in force, the competent 
authority shall have power to require any officer or authority of the 
Central Government or a State Government or local authority to furnish 
information in relation to such persons, on points or matters as in 
the opinion of the competent authority will be useful for, or relevant 
to, the purposes of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>1701308</tid>
<number>2</number>Every officer referred to in section 58T may furnish suo motu any 
information available with him to the competent authority if in the 
opinion of the officer such information will be useful to the 
competent authority for the purposes of this Chapter.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>525690</tid>
<number> 58T</number> Certain officers to assist Administrator, competent authority 
and Appellate Tribunal.- For the purposes of any proceedings under this 
Chapter, the following officers shall render such assistance as may be 
necessary to the Administrator appointed unde section 58G, competent 
authority and the Appellate Tribunal, namely:-
<section><tid>1596438</tid>
<number>a</number>officers of Police;

</section>

<section><tid>964818</tid>
<number>b</number>officers of the State Forest Departments;

</section>

<section><tid>1619487</tid>
<number>c</number>officers of the Central Economic Intelligence Bureau;

</section>

<section><tid>1070378</tid>
<number>d</number>officers of the Directorate of Revenue Intelligence;

</section>

<section><tid>302948</tid>
<number>e</number>such other officers as specified by the State Government in this 
behalf by notification in the Official Gazette.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1107821</tid>
<number> 58U</number> Power to take possession.-
<section><tid>1821152</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any property has been  
declared to be forfeited to the State Government under this Chapter, 
or where the person affected has failed to pay the fine due under 
sub- section (1) of section 58K within the time allowed t erefor under 
sub- section (3) of that section, the competent authority may order the 
person affected as well as any other person who may be in possession 
of the property to surrender or deliver possession thereof to the 
Administrator appointed under sect on 58G or to any person duly 
authorised by him in this behalf within thirty days of the service of 
the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1595660</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person refuses or fails to comply with an order made under 
sub- section (1), the Administrator may take possession of the property 
and may for that purpose use such force as may be necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1444635</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
Administrator may, for the purpose of taking possession of any 
property referred to in sub- section (1) requisition the services of 
any police officer to assist him and it shall be the duty of such 
officer to comply with such requisition.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>813648</tid>
<number>58V</number>Rectification of mistakes.- With a view to rectifying any mistake 
apparent from record, the competent authority or the Appellate 
Tribunal, as the case may be, may amend any order made by it within a 
period of one year from the date of the order:
Provided that if any such amendment is likely to affect any person 
prejudicially and the mistake is not of a clerical nature, it shall 
not be made without giving to such person a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard.

</article>



<article><tid>604144</tid>
<number>58W</number>Findings under other laws not conclusive for proceedings under 
this Chapter.- No finding of any officer or authority under any other 
law shall be conclusive for the purposes of any proceedings under this 
Chapter.
</article>



<article><tid>997692</tid>
<number> 58X</number> Service of notices and orders.- Any notice or order issued or 
made under this Chapter shall be served,-
<section><tid>1293493</tid>
<number>a</number>by tendering the notice or order or sending it by registered post 
to the person for whom it is intended or to his agent;

</section>

<section><tid>180236</tid>
<number>b</number>if the notice or order cannot be served in the manner provided in 
clause (a), then, by affixing it on a conspicuous place in the 
property in relation to which the notice or order is issued or made or 
on some conspicuous part of the premises in which he person for whom 
it is intended is known to have last resided or carried on business or 
personally worked for gain.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>224987</tid>
<number>58Y</number>Punishment for acquiring property in relation to which 
proceedings have been taken under this Chapter.- Any person who 
knowingly acquires, by any mode whatsoever, any property in relation 
to which proceedings are pending under this Chapter shall be p 
nishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years 
and with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.'.


</article>



<article><tid>499515</tid>
<number> 35</number> Amendment of section 60A.- In section 60A of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1696159</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" twenty per cent. of such 
fine", the words" fifty per cent. of such fine" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1392200</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" twenty per cent. of such 
money", the words" fifty per cent. of such money" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>671620</tid>
<number>36</number>Insertion of new section 60B.- After section 60A of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 60B. Reward by State Government.- The State Government may empower 
the Chief Wild Life Warden to order payment of reward not exceeding 
ten thousand rupees to be paid to a person who renders assistance in 
the detection of the offence or the apprehension o the offender, from 
such fund and in such manner as may be prescribed.".



</article>



<article><tid>1847724</tid>
<number>37</number>Amendment of section 63.- In section 63 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (ai) the term of office of members other than those who are members 
ex officio; the manner of filling vacancies, the procedure to be 
followed by the National Board under sub- section (2) and allowances of 
those members under sub- section (3) of section 5A".



</article>



<article><tid>1248769</tid>
<number> 38</number> Amendment of section 64.- In section 64 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>678563</tid>
<number>i</number>for clauses (a) and (b), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) the term of office of members other than those who are members, 
ex officio, the manner of filling vacancies and the procedure to be 
followed by the Board under sub- section (2) of section 6;


<subsection><tid>1118485</tid>
<number>b</number>allowances referred to in sub- section (3) of section 6;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>524899</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (d), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (dd) the conditions subject to which the officers will be authorised 
to file cases in the court;";


</section>

<section><tid>400010</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (g), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ga) the manner and conditions subject to which the Administrator 
shall receive and manage the property under sub- section (2) of section 
58G;


<subsection><tid>750281</tid>
<number>gb</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other 
members under sub- section (3) of section 58N;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1190043</tid>
<number>gc</number>the fund from which and the manner in which payment of reward 
under section 60B shall be made;".
----

K. N. CHATURVEDI,

Additional Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>