<act> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 19911
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These Rules may be called the Public Liability Insurance Rules, 1991.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These Rules shall come 
into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these Rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Public 
Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991);
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  “Advisory Committee” means the 
committee constituted by the Central Government in accordance with section 21 of 
the Act called the Public Liability Insurance Advisory Committee (PLIAC);
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  “Authorised physician”, means 
any person registered under any Central Act or State Act providing for the 
maintenance of a register of medical practitioners or in any area where no such 
last mentioned Act is in force, any person declared by State Government by 
notification in the Official Gazette to be a qualified medical practitioner;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  

1[“Fund” means the Public Liability 
Insurance Fund established] and maintained by an owner in accordance with 
provision of sub-section (3) of section 4 of the Act;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  Words and expressions used in 
these Rules but not defined and defined in the Act shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for relief.—An 
application for claim for relief shall be made to the Collector in Form I.
 


</article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Documents that may be 
required.—The 
claim application shall be made to the Collector in Form I accompanied by such 
of the following documents as may be applicable:—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  Certificate of an authorised 
physician regarding disability or injury or illness caused by the accident;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  Death certificate and/or 
post-mortem report in the case of a fatal accident;
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  Certificate of the employer 
regarding loss of wages, due to temporary or partial disability, with proof of 
hospitalisation for a period exceeding three days and certificate about the date 
of birth or age of victim;
 </section><section>
        <number>iv</number>  Medical bills and receipts;
 </section><section>
         <number>v</number>  Certificate of cost of repairs 
or replacement of private property damaged by the accident;
 </section><section>
        <number>vi</number>  Any other documents which may 
have relevance to the claim.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Establishment and 
administration of Fund.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
An owner seeking exemption under sub-section (3) of section 4 of the Act, shall 
with the prior approval of the Central Government create and maintain a Fund for 
an amount of Rs. 5 crores or for an amount equal to the paid up capital of the 
undertaking handling hazardous substances, whichever is less, in the State Bank 
of India or any of its subsidiaries or any nationalised Bank, and which will be 
available readily for meeting the liability of that owner under the Act.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fund to be created 
shall be utilised for the purpose of meeting the liability arising out of any 
claim awarded against the owner who has created the fund and to discharge the 
amount awarded by the Collector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fund shall be 
operated by an Administrator to be nominated by the owner. The owner shall 
notify the nomination of the Administrator to the Central Government.
 
 



</section></article> 
 THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE RULES, 
1991
  
 <article><number>6</number> Establishment and 
administration of Fund.—1[
<section><number>1</number> An owner seeking exemption 
under sub-section (3) of section 4 of the Act, shall with the prior approval of 
the Central Government create and maintain a Fund for an amount of Rs. 5 crores 
or for an amount equal to the paid up capital of the undertaking handling 
hazardous substances, whichever is less, in the State Bank of India or any of 
its subsidiaries or any nationalised Bank, and which will be available readily 
for meeting the liability of that owner under the Act.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The fund to be created shall 
be utilised for the purpose of meeting the liability arising out of any claim 
awarded against the owner who has created the fund and to discharge the amount 
awarded by the Collector.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The fund shall be operated 
by an Administrator to be nominated by the owner. The owner shall notify the 
nomination of the Administrator to the Central Government.
  


</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Miscellaneous.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Collector shall maintain a register of the applications for relief or claim 
petitions, and, a register of awards and payment made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These Registers shall 
be kept open to the public inspection from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. and 2 p.m. to 5 
p.m. on every working day.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On a request from a 
concerned person, the Collector shall supply a copy of or extract from any 
particulars entered in the registers mentioned above to be a true copy or 
extract thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A copy of or extract 
from the register(s) of the Collector as certified under the hand of the 
Collector or any officer authorised to act in this behalf shall, in all legal 
proceedings, be admissible as evidence as of equal validity with the original.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8</number> Directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any direction issued under section 12 shall be in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The direction shall 
specify the nature of action to be taken and the time within which it shall be 
complied with by any owner, person, officer, authority or agency to whom such 
direction is given.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The owner, person, 
officer, authority or agency to whom any direction is sought to be issued, shall 
be served with a copy of the proposed direction and shall be given an 
opportunity of net less than fifteen days from the date of service of the notice 
to file, with an officer designated in this behalf the objections, if any, to 
the issue of the proposed direction.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Government shall, 
within a period of forty-five days from the date of receipt of the objections, 
or from the date up to which an opportunity is given to the owner, person, 
officer, authority or agency to file objections, whichever is earlier, after 
considering the objections, if any, received from the owner, person, officer, 
authority or an agency sought to be directed and for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, confirm, modify or decide not to issue the proposed direction.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In a case where the 
Government is of the opinion that in views of the likelihood of a grave injury 
to the public it is not expedient to provide an opportunity to file objections 
against the proposed direction, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
issue directions without providing such an opportunity.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every notice or 
direction required to be issued under this rule shall be deemed to be duly 
served—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  where the person to be served 
is a company, if the document is addressed in name of the company, at its 
registered office or at its principal office or place of business, and is 
either—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number>  sent by registered post; 
or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  delivered or affixed at 
some conspicuous part of the premises at its registered office or at the 
principal office or place of business;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  where the person to be served 
is an office serving in Government, if the document is addressed to the person 
and a copy thereof is endorsed to his Head of the Department and also to the 
Secretary to the Government, as the case may be, incharge of the Department in 
which, for the time being, the business relating to the Department, in which the 
officer is employed, is transacted and is either—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number>  sent by registered post; 
or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  is given or tendered to 
him;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  in any other case, if the 
document is addressed to the person to be served, and—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number>  is given or tendered to 
him; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  if such person cannot be 
found, is affixed on some conspicuous part of his last known place of residence 
or business, or is given or tendered to some adult member of his family or is 
affixed on some conspicuous part of the land or building, if any, to which it 
relates, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  is sent by registered 
post to that person.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule—
 <subsubsubsection>
         <number>a</number>  “company” means any body 
corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
         <number>b</number>  “a servant”, not a member of 
the family.
 
 



</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Manner of giving 
notice.—The 
manner of giving notice under clause (b) of section 18 shall be as follows:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  The notice shall be in writing 
in Form II.
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  The person giving notice may 
send a copy of the same to—
 <subsection>
               <number>i</number>  if the alleged offence 
has taken place in a Union Territory,—
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the Central Board or 
the Committee/person or body of persons delegated the powers of the Central 
Board under the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
1974), and the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981); 
and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>b</number>  Ministry of 
Environment and Forests (represented by the Secretary to the Government of 
India);
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
              <number>ii</number>  if the alleged offence 
has taken place in a State,—
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>a</number>  the State Board for 
the prevention and control of water pollution constituted under the Water 
(Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>b</number>  the Government of the 
State (represented by the Secretary to the State Government incharge of 
Environment); and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>c</number>  the Ministry of 
Environment and Forests (represented by the Secretary to the Government of 
India);
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  if the alleged offence 
has taken place in a District,— 
 
     the District 
Collector.
 
       *(c)  The notice shall be sent by 
registered post acknowledgement due; and
 
       *(d)  The period of sixty days 
mentioned on clause (b) of section 18 of the Act (6 of 1991) shall be reckoned 
from the date it is first received by one of the authorities mentioned above.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10</number> Extent of 
liability.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2A) of section 4 of 
the Act, the maximum aggregate liability of the insurer to pay relief under an 
award to the several claimants arising out of an accident shall not exceed 
rupees five crores and in case of more than one accident during the currency of 
the policy or one year, whichever is less, shall not exceed rupees fifteen 
crores in the aggregate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In awarding relief 
under the Act, the Collector shall ensure that the insurer's maximum liability 
under the insurance policy does not exceed the limits stipulated in sub-rule 
(1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any award for relief 
which exceeds the amount payable under the insurance policy shall be met from 
the relief fund and in case the award exceeds the total of the amount of 
insurance and the relief fund, the amount which falls short of such payable 
shall be met by the owner.
 

2[(4) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3), where an owner is exempted 
under sub-section (3) of section 4 of the Act, he shall be liable to discharge 
all the claims arising out of an accident.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Contribution of owner 
to the Environmental Relief Fund.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[An owner unless 
exempted under sub-section (3) of section 4 of the Act shall contribute] to the 
Environmental Relief Fund a sum equal to the premium payable to the insurer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every contribution to 
the Environmental Relief Fund under sub-rule (1) shall be payable to the 
insurer, together with the amount of premium.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The contribution 
received by the insurer shall be remitted as per the scheme under section 7A of 
the Act.]
 
 



</section></article><form>
 


THE PUBLIC LIABILITY INSURANCE 
RULES, 1991
 


 
 


FORM I
 


FORM OF APPLICATION FOR COMPENSATION
 


Shri/Shrimati/Kumari* ……………………….. Son 
of/Daughter of/Widow* of Shri …………………… who died/had sustained injuries in an 
accident on ……… at ………. Particulars in respect of accident and other information 
are given below:
 


       1.  Name and father's name of person 
injured/dead (husband's name in case of married woman of widow)
 


       2.  Address of the person 
injured/dead.
 


       3.  Age ………….. Date of birth……………..
 


       4.  Sex of the person injured/dead:
 


       5.  Place, date and time of the 
accident:
 


       6.  Occupation of the person 
injured/dead:
 


       7.  Nature of injuries sustained:
 


       8.  Name and address of Police Station 
in whose jurisdiction accident took place or was registered;
 


       9.  Name and address of the Medical 
Officer/Practitioner who attended on the injured/dead:
 


     10.  Name/s and address/es of the 
claimant/claimants:
 


     11.  Relationship with the deceased:
 


     12.  Any other information that may be 
considered necessary of helpful in the disposal of the claim:
 


I hereby swear and affirm that all the facts 
noted above are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 


*Strike out whichever is not applicable.
 


 Signature of the claimant
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>