<act> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Air Corporations Act, 1953.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  “aircraft” means any machine 
which can derive support in the atmosphere from reactions of the air and 
includes balloons, whether fixed or free, airships, kites, gliders and flying 
machines;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  “air transport service” means 
a service for the transport by air of persons, mails or any other thing, 
animate or inanimate, for any kind of remuneration whatsoever, whether such 
service consists of a single flight or a series of flights;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  “associate” in relation to 
either of the corporations means any subsidiary of the corporation or any 
person with whom the corporation has made an agreement in accordance with 
clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 7;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  “Corporations” means “Indian 
Airlines” and “Air India International” established under section 3, and 
“Corporation” means either of the Corporations;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  the expression “existing air 
companies” means the Air India Ltd., the Air Services of India Ltd., the 
Airways (India) Ltd., the Bharat Airways Ltd., the Deccan Airways Ltd., the 
Himalayan Aviation Ltd., the Indian National Airways Ltd., the Kalinga Airlines 
and the Air India International Ltd., and “existing air company” means any of 
the existing air companies;
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed 
by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
      <number>vii</number>  “regulations” means regulations 
made by either of the corporations under section 45;
 </section><section>
     <number>viii</number>  “scheduled air transport 
service” means an air transport service undertaken between the same two or more 
places and operated according to a published time table or with flights so 
regular or frequent that they constitute a recognisably systematic series, each 
flight being open to use by members of the public;
 </section><section>
       <number>ix</number>  “Tribunal” means the Tribunal 
constituted under section 25.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Incorporation of the 
Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established two Corporations to 
be known as “Indian Airlines” and “Air India International”.*
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the 
Corporations aforesaid shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession 
and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire 
and hold property, and may by its name sue and be sued.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Constitution of the 
Corporations.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and 
business of each of the Corporations shall vest in a Board of directors which 
may exercise all such powers and do all such acts and things as may be 
exercised or done by the Corporation under this Act.
 <subsection>
<number>lA</number> The Board of 
directors shall consist of a Chairman to be appointed by the Central 
Government, and not less than eight and not more than fourteen other directors 
to be appointed by the Central Government and the Chairman or any other 
director may be required to render whole-time or part-time service as the 
Central Government may direct:
 
Provided that—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  the same person may be appointed 
to be the Chairman of both the Corporations or Chairman of one and director of 
the other;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>b</number>  the same persons may be 
appointed to be directors of both the Corporations.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Before appointing a 
person to be a 

1[director] of 
either of the Corporations, the Central Government shall satisfy itself that 
person will have no such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
prejudicially the exercise or performance by him of his functions as a 

1[director] of the 
Corporation and the Central Government shall also satisfy itself from time to 
time with respect to every 

1[director] of the 
Corporation that he has no such interest; and any person who is, or whom the 
Central Government proposes to appoint and who has consented to be 

1[director] of the 
Corporation shall, whenever required by the Central Government so to do, 
furnish to it such information as the Central Government considers necessary 
for the performance of its duties under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 

1[director] of 
either of the Corporations who is in any way directly or indirectly interested 
in a contract made or proposed to be made by the Corporation, or in any 
contract made or proposed to be made by an associate of the Corporation which 
is brought up for consideration by the Corporation, shall, as soon as possible 
after the relevant circumstances have come to his knowledge, disclose the 
nature of his interest at a meeting of the Corporation; and the disclosure 
shall be recorded in the minutes of the Corporation, and the 

1[director] shall 
not take any part after the disclosure in any deliberation or decision of the 
Corporation with respect to that contract.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> During the temporary 
absence of the Chairman of either of the Corporation, the Central Government 
may appoint another person, whether a 

1[director] of the 
Corporation or not, to act as the Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in this section, nothing contained in this Act shall be deemed to 
disqualify the 

1[managing 
director] of either of the Corporations from being appointed to be a 

1[director] 
thereof.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Conditions of service 
of 

1[directors].—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman and other 

2[directors] of 
each of the Corporations shall ordinarily be entitled to hold office for the 
period specified in the order of appointment, unless the appointment is 
terminated earlier by the Central Government:
 
Provided that any 

2[director] may at 
any time by notice in writing addressed to the Central Government resign his 
office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
previous approval of the Central Government, each of the Corporations shall pay 
to every 

2[director] 
thereof in respect of his office as such, 

2[such 
remuneration by way of salary, allowances], fees or otherwise as may be 
determined by the Corporation, and to the Chairman in respect of his office as 
such, such remuneration, whether in addition to the remuneration to which he 
may be entitled in respect of his office as a 

2[director] or 
otherwise, as it may similarly determine.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Vacancy in Corporation 
not to invalidate proceedings.—No 
act or proceeding of either of the Corporations shall be deemed to be invalid 
by reason merely of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the 
Corporation.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Functions of the 
Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the rules, if any, made by the Central Government in this behalf, it 
shall be the function of each of the Corporations to provide safe, efficient, 
adequate, economical and properly co-ordinated air transport services, whether 
internal or international or both, and the Corporations shall so exercise their 
powers as to secure that the air transport services are developed to the best 
advantage and, in particular, so exercise those powers as to secure that the 
services are provided at reasonable charges.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of the powers conferred by sub-section (1), each of the 
Corporations shall, in particular, have power—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to operate any air transport 
service, or any flight by aircraft for a commercial or other purpose, and to 
carry out all forms of aerial work;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to provide for the instruction 
and training in matters connected with aircraft or flight by aircraft of 
persons employed, or desirous of being employed, either by the Corporation or 
by any other person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  with the previous approval of 
the Central Government, to promote any organization outside India for the 
purpose of engaging in any activity of a kind which the Corporation has power 
to carry on;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  to acquire, hold or dispose of 
any property, whether movable or immovable, or any air transport undertaking;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  to repair, overhaul, 
reconstruct, assemble or recondition aircraft, vehicles or other machines and 
parts, accessories and instruments thereof or therefore and also to manufacture 
such parts, accessories and instruments, whether the aircraft, vehicles or 
other machines are owned by the Corporation or by any other person;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  to enter into and perform all 
such contracts as are calculated to further the efficient performance of its 
duties and the exercise of its powers under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  to perform any functions as 
agent or contractor in relation to an air transport service operated by any 
other person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  with the previous approval of 
the Central Government, to enter into agreements with any person engaged in air 
transportation with a view to enabling such person to provide air transport 
services on behalf of or in association with the Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  with the previous approval of 
the Central Government, to determine and levy fares and freight rates and other 
charges for or in respect of the carriage of passengers and goods on air 
transport services operated by it;
 

        1[(ii)  to make such grants 
as it thinks fit as contribution or donation, in furtherance of the interests 
of the Corporation, to any fund established for a benevolent or charitable 
purpose:
 
                 Provided that nothing in 
this clause shall be construed as empowering the Corporation to make any such 
grant to any political party or for any political purpose to any individual or 
body;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  to take such steps as are 
calculated to extend the air transport services provided by the Corporation, 
whether within or without India, including the development of feeder services 
and the improvement of the types of aircraft used in air transport services;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  to take such steps as are 
calculated to promote the interests of the Corporation or to improve the 
services the Corporation may provide, 

2[including provisions of catering, 
hotels, restaurants, rest-rooms], goods-sheds, warehouses and transport by land 
or water in connection with any air transport service or any other amenity or 
facility;
 

      3[(kk)  to form one or more 
companies under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) to further the efficient 
performance of its duties and the exercise of its powers under this Act:
 
                 Provided that the paid up 
share capital of every company so formed shall be held exclusively by the 
Corporation;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  to take all such steps as may 
be necessary or convenient for, or may be incidental to, the exercise of any 
power, or the discharge of any function or duty conferred or imposed on it by 
this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
this section shall be construed as—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  authorising the disregard by the 
Corporation of any law for the time being in force, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  authorising any person to 
institute any proceeding in respect of a duty or liability to which either of 
the Corporations or its employees would not otherwise be subject.










</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Appointment of 
officers and other employees of the Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of enabling it efficiently to discharge its functions under 
this Act each of the Corporations shall appoint a 

1[managing 
director] and, subject to such rules as may be prescribed in this behalf, may 
also appoint such number of other officers and employees as it may think 
necessary:
 
Provided that the 
appointment of the 

1[managing 
director] and such other categories of officers as may be specified after 
consultation with the Chairman in such rules shall be subject to the approval 
of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of section 20, every person employed by each of the Corporations 
shall be subject to such conditions of service and shall be entitled to such 
remuneration and privileges as may be determined by regulations made by the 
Corporation by which he is employed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Neither the 

1[managing 
director] nor such other employee of either of the Corporations as may be 
specified in this behalf by the Central Government shall, during his service in 
the Corporation, be employed in any capacity whatsoever or directly or 
indirectly have any interest in any air transport undertaking other than an 
undertaking of either of the Corporations, or in any other undertaking which is 
interested in any contract with either of the Corporations.







</section></article> 
 The Air Corporations Act, 1953
  
 <article><number>9</number> Corporations to act on 
business principles.—In carrying out any of the 
duties vested in it by this Act, each of the Corporations shall act so far as 
may be on business principles.</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Capital of the 
Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All non-requiring expenditure incurred by the Central Government for, or in 
connection with, each of the Corporations up to the date of establishment of 
that Corporation and declared to be capital expenditure by that Government, 
shall be treated as capital provided by the Central Government to that 
Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
Government may provide any further capital that may be required by either of 
the Corporations for the carrying on of the business of the Corporation or for 
any purpose connected therewith on such terms and conditions as the Central 
Government may determine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Each of the 
Corporations may, with the consent of the Central Government, or in accordance 
with the terms of any general authority given to it by the Central Government—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  borrow money for all or any of 
the purposes of the Corporation, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  secure the payment of any money 
borrowed by it or any interest thereon by the issue of bonds, debentures, 
debenture-stock or any mortgage or charge or other security on the undertaking 
of the Corporation or any part of it or on any of its properties.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Vesting of properties 
in the Corporations.—All 
properties, assets and funds owned or acquired by the Central Government for 
the purpose of Indian Airlines or, as the case may be, Air-India International 
before the establishment of those Corporations shall, on such establishment, 
vest in the Corporation concerned.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Funds of the 
Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each of the Corporations shall have its own funds and all receipts of the 
Corporation shall be carried thereto and all payments for the Corporation shall 
be made therefrom.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the 
Corporations may keep in 

1[account] with 
any scheduled bank as defined in section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 
1934 (2 of 1934) or in any other bank approved by the Central Government in 
this behalf a sum of money not exceeding such amount as may be prescribed, but 
any moneys in excess of the said sum shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank of 
India or with the agents of the Reserve Bank of India or invested in such 
manner as may be approved by the Central Government.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Powers of the 
Corporations in regard to expenditure.—Each 
of the Corporations shall have power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to 
spend such sums as it thinks fit on objects or for purposes authorised by this 
Act and such sum shall be treated as expenditure out of the funds of that 
Corporation.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Corporation to assume 
obligations of Central Government in respect of certain matters.—All 
obligations incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with, or for the Central Government for any of the 
purposes of this Act before the establishment of either of the Corporations 
shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into or engaged to be done by, 
with or for Indian Airlines or, as the case may be, Air India International 
according as the obligations, contracts, matters and things relate to the 
purposes of the former Corporation or the latter.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporations shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
prepare an annual statement of accounts, including the profit and loss account 
and the balance sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the 
Corporations shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
of India and any 
expenditure incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by 
the Corporations to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in connection with the 
audit of the accounts of the Corporations shall have the same rights and 
privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, 
connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the 
offices of the Corporations.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the 
Corporations as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or 
any other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the audit report 
thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that 
Government shall cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15A</number> Audit of 
accounts of companies formed by Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the auditor of any company 
formed by either of the Corporations under clause (kk) of sub-section (2) of 
section 7 shall be appointed or re-appointed by the Corporation concerned on 
the advice of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in sub-section (1), in addition to the provisions contained in the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), relating to the audit of the accounts of any 
company, the following provisions shall apply to the audit of the accounts of 
any company referred to in sub-section (1), namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India shall have power to conduct a supplementary or test 
audit of the company’s accounts by such person or persons as he may authorise 
in this behalf; and for the purposes of such audit to require information to be 
furnished to any person or persons so authorised, on such matters, by such 
person or persons and in such form as the Comptroller and Auditor-General may, 
by general or special order, direct;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the auditor appointed or 
re-appointed under sub-section (1) shall submit a copy of his audit report to 
the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India who shall have the right to 
comment upon, or supplement, the audit report in such manner as he may think 
fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  any such comments upon, or 
supplement to, the audit report shall be placed before the annual general 
meeting of the company at the same time and in the same manner as the audit 
report.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Undertakings of 
existing air companies to vest in the Corporation.—On 
such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint (hereinafter referred to as “the appointed date”), there shall 
be transferred to and vest in—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Indian Airlines, the 
undertakings of all the existing air companies (other than Air India 
International Ltd.), and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Air India International, the 
undertaking of the Air India International Ltd.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> General effect of 
vesting of undertakings in the Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The undertaking of each of the existing air companies which is transferred to 
and which vests in either of the Corporations under section 16 shall, subject 
to the provisions of section 22, be deemed to include all assets, rights, 
powers, authorities and privileges and all property, movable and immovable, 
including lands, works, workshops, aircraft, cash balances, reserve funds, 
investments and book debts and all other rights and interests arising out of 
such property as were immediately before the appointed date in the ownership, 
possession or power of the existing air company in relation to the undertaking, 
whether within or without India, and all books of account and documents 
relating thereto, and, subject to the provisions contained in section 22, shall 
also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of 
whatever kind then subsisting of the existing air company in relation to the 
undertaking.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any lands, works, 
aircraft, assets or other property vesting in the Corporation under sub-section 
(1) shall by force of such vesting be freed and discharged from all trusts, 
obligations, mortgages, charges, liens and other encumbrances affecting it, and 
any attachment, injunction or any other order of a court restricting the use of 
such property in any manner shall be deemed to have been withdrawn.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to the other 
provisions contained in this Act, all contracts and working arrangements which 
are subsisting immediately before the appointed date and affecting any of the 
existing air companies shall, in so far as they relate to the undertaking of 
that company, cease to have effect or be enforceable against that company or 
any person who was surety or had guaranteed the performance thereof, and shall 
be of as full force and effect against or in favour of the Corporation in which 
the undertaking has vested by virtue of this Act and enforceable as fully and 
effectually as if, instead of the company, the Corporation had been named 
therein or had been a party thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to the other 
provisions contained in this Act, any proceeding or cause of action pending or 
existing immediately before the appointed date by or against any of the 
existing air companies in relation to its undertaking may as from that date be 
continued and enforced by or against the Corporation in which it has vested by 
virtue of this Act as it might have been enforced by or against that company if 
this Act had not been passed, and shall cease to be enforceable by or against 
that company, its surety or guarantor.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Reservation of 
scheduled air transport services to the Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the appointed date, it shall not be lawful for any person other than the 
Corporations or their associates to operate any scheduled air transport service 
from, to, in or across India:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this section shall restrict the right of any person,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  for the purpose of any air 
transport undertaking of which the principal place of business is in any 
country outside India, to operate an air transport service, in accordance with 
the terms of any agreement for the time being in force between the Government 
of India and the Government of that country; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to carry passengers for the sole 
purpose of instructing them in flying or on duties of aircrews; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  to carry passengers or goods for 
the sole purpose of providing an air ambulance service or a rescue or relief 
service during any natural calamity; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  to carry passengers or goods for 
the sole purpose of providing joy rides consisting of flights operated from and 
to the same aerodrome or place without any intermediate landing or for the 
purpose of aerial survey, fire fighting, crop-dusting, locust control or any 
other aerial work of a similar nature; 

1[or]
 

        1[(e)  to operate, with the 
previous permission of the Central Government for such period and subject to 
such terms and conditions as that Government may determine, any scheduled air 
transport service as aforesaid which is not provided by either of the 
Corporations or their associates.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person who 
operates a scheduled air transport service in contravention of the provisions 
of this section shall be liable in respect of each offence to a fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or to imprisonment which may extend to three 
months, or to both.
 
Explanation.—The 
operation of each flight shall constitute a separate offence for the purposes 
of this section.







</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Licences to cease to 
be valid.—With 
effect from the appointed date, all licences granted under the Indian Aircraft 
Act, 1934 (22 of 1934) or under the rules made thereunder for the operation of 
scheduled air transport services shall cease to be valid.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Provisions respecting 
officers and employees of existing air companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every officer or other employee of an existing air company (except a director, 
managing agent, manager or any other person entitled to manage the whole or a 
substantial part of the business and affairs of the company under a special 
agreement) employed by that company prior to the first day of July, 1952, and 
still in its employment immediately before the appointed date shall, in so far 
as such officer or other employee is employed in connection with the 
undertaking which has vested in either of the Corporations by virtue of this 
Act, become as from the appointed date an officer or other employee as the case 
may be, of the Corporation in which the undertaking has vested and shall hold 
his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and 
upon the same terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as 
to pension and gratuity and other matters as he would have held the same under 
the existing air company if its undertaking had not vested in the Corporation 
and shall continue to do so unless and until his employment in the Corporation 
is terminated or until his remuneration, terms or conditions are duly altered 
by the Corporation:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this section shall apply to any officer or other employee who has, 
by notice in writing given to the Corporation concerned prior to such date as 
may be fixed by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, 
intimated his intention of not becoming an officer or other employee of the 
Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1) the Central Government may direct either 
of the Corporations in which the undertaking of any existing air company has 
vested to take into its employment any officer or other employee who was 
employed by the existing air company prior to the first day of July, 1952, and 
who has been discharged from service in that company on or after the said date 
for reasons which, in the opinion of the Central Government, appear to be 
inadequate for the purpose, and where the Central Government issues any such 
direction, the provisions of sub-section (1) shall apply to such officer or 
other employee as they apply to any officer or other employee referred to 
therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> As from the appointed 
date the trustees of the provident funds and pension funds or pension schemes 
of each of the existing air companies shall transfer to the Corporation 
concerned the balances lying to the credit of each of the employees whose 
services have been transferred to that Corporation by virtue of this Act and 
also all other balances of the funds or schemes as shall remain after 
satisfying all demands and liabilities, and thereupon the trustees shall be 
discharged of the trusts by virtue of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act or in the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913) 
or in any other law for the time being in force or in any agreement entered 
into by an existing air company or in the articles of association of any such 
company, no director, managing agent, manager or any other person entitled to 
manage the whole or a substantial part of the business and affairs of the 
company shall be entitled to any compensation against any existing air company 
or against either of the Corporations for the loss of office or for the 
premature termination of any contract of management entered into by him with 
any existing air company and where any existing air company has, after the 
first day of July, 1952, and before the commencement of this Act, paid to any 
such person as is referred to in this sub-section any sum by way of 
compensation to which the person receiving such compensation would not have 
been entitled if this sub-section were in force at the time of such payment, 
the existing air company shall be entitled to claim refund of any sum so paid.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Duty to deliver up 
possession of property acquired and documents relating thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any property has vested in either of the Corporations under section 16, 
every person in whose possession or custody or under whose control the property 
may be, shall deliver up the property to the Corporation concerned forthwith.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person who on the 
appointed date has in his possession or under his control any books, documents 
or papers relating to any undertaking which has vested in either of the 
Corporations under this Act and which belong to an existing air company or 
would have so belonged if its undertaking had not so vested shall be liable to 
account for the said books, documents and papers to the Corporation in which 
the undertaking has vested and shall deliver them up to the Corporation or to 
such person as the Corporation may direct:
 
Provided that the 
Corporation shall produce for inspection by such companies or their authorized 
representatives the books of account and documents as relate to the affairs of 
the company for any period prior to the appointed date.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Without prejudice to 
the other provisions contained in this section, it shall be lawful for the 
Corporation and the Central Government to take all necessary steps for securing 
possession of all properties which have vested in the Corporation under section 
16.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Duty of existing air 
companies to supply particulars.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the undertaking of an existing air company vests in either of the 
Corporations under this Act, the existing air company shall, within thirty days 
from the appointed date or within such further time as the Corporation 
concerned may allow in any case, supply to the Corporation particulars of book 
debts and investments belonging to and all liabilities and obligations of the 
company subsisting immediately before the appointed date, and also of all 
agreements entered into by the existing air company and in force on the 
appointed date, including agreements, whether express or implied, relating to 
leave, pension, gratuity and other terms of service of any officer or other 
employee of the existing air company, under which by virtue of this Act the 
Corporations have or will or may have liabilities except such agreements as the 
Corporation may exclude either generally or in any particular case from the 
operation of this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any existing air 
company fails to supply to the Corporation concerned particulars of such book 
debts, liabilities and agreements within the time allowed to it for the purpose 
under sub-section (1), nothing contained in this Act shall have effect so as to 
transfer any such book debts, liabilities and agreements to or to vest the same 
in the Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Either Corporation 
may by notice in writing within a period of 

1[six months] 
after submission of the particulars referred to in sub-section (1) intimate to 
the existing air company submitting the particulars that such of the book debts 
and investments as are specified in the notice are not included in the 
properties vesting in the Corporation whereupon the compensation provided by 
section 25 of this Act and the Schedule thereto shall be reduced by the amount 
of such excluded book debts and investments but the right of such existing air 
company to recover and retain such excluded book debts shall remain unaffected 
by this Act.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Right of Corporations 
to disclaim certain agreements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where it appears to either of the Corporations that the making of any such 
agreements as is referred to in section 22 under which the Corporation has or 
will have or may have liabilities was not reasonably necessary for the purposes 
of the activities of the existing air company or has not been entered into in 
good faith, the Corporation may, within 

1[one year] from 
the appointed date, apply to the Tribunal for relief from such agreement, and 
the Tribunal, if satisfied after making such inquiry into the matter as it 
thinks fit that the agreement was not reasonably necessary for the purposes of 
the activities of the existing air company or has not been entered into in good 
faith, may make an order cancelling or varying the agreement on such terms as 
it may think fit to impose and the agreement shall thereupon have effect 
accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All the parties to 
the agreement which is sought to be cancelled or varied under this section 
shall be made parties to the proceeding.
 
 




</section></article> 
 The Air Corporations Act, 1953
  
 <article><number>24</number> Transactions resulting in 
dissipation of assets.—
<section><number>1</number> This section shall apply 
where any existing air company has, after the first day of July, 1952, and 
before the appointed date,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  made 
any payment to any person without consideration or for an inadequate 
consideration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  sold 
or disposed of any of its properties or rights without consideration or for an 
inadequate consideration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  
acquired any property or rights for an excessive consideration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  
entered into or varied any agreement so as to require an excessive consideration 
to be paid or given by the company;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  
entered into any other transaction of such an onerous nature as to cause a loss 
to or impose a liability on the company exceeding any benefit accruing to the 
company; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  sold or otherwise transferred any aircraft, equipment, machinery or 
other property of book value exceeding rupees ten thousand;
 and the 
payment, sale, disposal, acquisition, agreement or variation thereof, or other 
transaction or transfer, was not reasonably necessary for the purposes of the 
company or was made with an unreasonable lack of prudence on the part of the 
company, regard being had in either case to the circumstances at the 
time.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Either of the Corporations 
may, in the case of any such existing air company as is referred to in 
sub-section (1) the undertaking of which has vested in the Corporation under 
this Act, at any time within 1[one year] from the appointed 
date, apply for relief to the Tribunal in respect of any transaction to which in 
the opinion of the Corporation this section applies, and all parties to the 
transaction shall, unless the Tribunal otherwise directs, be made parties to the 
application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Tribunal is 
satisfied that a transaction in respect of which an application is made is a 
transaction to which this section applies, then, unless the Tribunal is also 
satisfied that the transaction was a proper transaction made in the ordinary 
course of business regard being had to the circumstances at the time and was not 
in any way connected with any provision, made by this Act or with any 
anticipation of the making of any such provision, the Tribunal shall make such 
order against any of the parties to the application as the Tribunal thinks just 
having regard to the extent to which those parties were respectively responsible 
for the transaction or benefited from it and all the circumstances of the 
case.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where an application is made 
to the Tribunal under this section in respect of any transaction and the 
application is determined in favour of the Corporation, the Tribunal shall have 
exclusive jurisdiction to determine any claims outstanding in respect of the 
transaction.
  


</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Compensation to be 
given for compulsory acquisition of undertaking.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the undertaking of any of the existing air companies has vested in either 
of the Corporations under this Act, compensation shall be given by the 
Corporation to that company in the manner specified in section 27 and the 
amount of such compensation shall be determined in accordance with the 
principles specified in the Schedule to this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding that 
separate valuations are calculated under the principles specified in the 
Schedule in respect of the several matters referred to therein, the amount of 
compensation to be given shall be deemed to be a single compensation to be 
given for the undertaking as a whole.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of the 
compensation to be given in accordance with the aforesaid principles shall be 
determined by the Corporation and if the amount so determined is approved by 
the Central Government, it shall be offered to the existing air company in full 
satisfaction of the compensation payable under this Act, and if the amount so 
offered is not acceptable to the existing air company, it may within such time 
as may be prescribed for the purpose have the matter referred to a Tribunal 
constituted for this purpose by the Central Government for decision.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Constitution of 
special Tribunal to determine compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Tribunal to be constituted under section 25 shall consist of three members 
appointed by the Central Government, one of whom shall be a person who is or 
has been a Judge of a High Court or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Tribunal may for 
the purpose of deciding any matter under this Act choose one or more persons 
possessing special knowledge of any matter relating to the case under inquiry 
to assist it in determining any compensation which is to be given under this 
Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Tribunal shall 
have the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (Act 5 of 1908) in respect of the following matters:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  summoning and enforcing the 
attendance of any person and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  requiring the discovery and 
production of documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  receiving evidence on 
affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  issuing commissions for the 
examination of witnesses or documents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Tribunal shall by 
a majority of its number regulate its own procedure and decide any matter 
within its competence and may review its decision in the event of there being a 
mistake on the face of the record or correct any arithmetical or clerical error 
therein but subject thereto the decision of the Tribunal on any matter within 
its jurisdiction shall be final and shall not be called in question in any 
court.


</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Mode of giving 
compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the amount of compensation to be given under this Act to an existing air 
company has been determined under section 25, the Corporation shall give to the 
company one or more bonds of the face value of the amount of compensation so 
determined less such portion thereof as is payable in cash under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Out of the 
compensation to be given to each of the existing air companies under this Act, 
there shall be paid in cash—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  ten per cent of the amount of 
compensation payable to each of such companies (which percentage shall be 
uniformly applicable to all existing air companies); or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the amount borrowed by any such 
company from any bank and outstanding on the 31st day of December, 1952, or on 
the appointed date, whichever amount is less; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  an amount equal to the cash of 
any such company, including cash in deposit with a bank, which has vested in 
the Corporation under this Act;
 
whichever of the amount specified in clauses (a), (b) and (c) is the greatest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The bonds aforesaid 
shall be issued by the Corporation with the previous approval of the Central 
Government and shall be negotiable and shall be redeemed at their face value by 
the Corporation concerned on the demand of the holder within one hundred and 
eighty days after the expiry of five years from the date of their issue and the 
redemption of the bonds and payment of all interest thereon shall be guaranteed 
by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If within the expiry 
of the said period of one hundred and eighty days, the holder of any bond fails 
to require payment of its face value from the Corporation concerned, the bond 
shall cease to be redeemable at the option of the holder:
 
Provided that in any case 
the Corporation may by notice require the holder of the bond to accept its face 
value in cash at any time whether before or after the expiry of the period of 
five years aforementioned.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The holder of the 
bond shall be entitled to receive from the Corporation interest on the bond at 
three-and-a-half per cent. per annum at such intervals as may be prescribed, 
with effect from the appointed date and until the bond is duly redeemed.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Bonds issued under 
this section shall, for the purpose of redemption and of computing interest, be 
deemed to have been issued on the appointed date.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any bond issued under 
the provisions of this section shall be deemed to be a security in which a 
trustee may invest trust monies within the meaning of section 20 of the Indian 
Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882).
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Winding up of 
existing company whose undertaking has been acquired.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, on the application of any existing air company or 
on the application of a majority in number representing three-fourths in value 
of its members holding ordinary shares, by order in writing, authorise the 
existing air company the undertaking of which has vested in either of the 
Corporations, to be wound up voluntarily in accordance with the provisions of 
the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913) relating to voluntary winding up:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the winding up of the company 
shall commence on the day on which the Central Government authorises the 
winding up without the passing by the company of any special or other 
resolution for winding up; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the directors of the existing 
company shall not be under an obligation to make any such statutory declaration 
as is required by section 207 of the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913); 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the winding up of the company 
shall be continued by the directors of the existing company in office at the 
time the Central Government authorises its winding up and they shall be deemed 
to be joint liquidators for the purpose of the said winding up with power to 
act by a majority of their number.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
winding up the affairs of any existing air company or for any other purpose 
necessary for enabling it to give effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, permit 
the existing air company to occupy, kept in its custody or utilise, as the case 
may be, for such period as it may allow any office, books, accounts and other 
documents and the services of any officers or other employees, which have been 
transferred to either of the Corporations under this Act, on such terms and 
conditions as may be agreed between the Corporation in which the undertaking 
has vested and the existing air company, or failing agreement, as may be 
determined by the Central Government.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Authorisation under 
section 28 may contain certain directions.—Any 
authorisation granted under section 28 may include a direction requiring an 
existing air company the voluntary winding up of which has been authorised 
under that section to distribute its net assets among the various classes of 
members of the company in such proportion as the Central Government may, having 
regard to the amount subscribed by each class of such members or having regard 
to the circumstances relating to the issue of the shares to the various classes 
of members, specify in the direction, and any such direction shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 
1913) or in the articles of association or resolution of the company or in any 
agreement, and every such company shall be bound to comply with any such 
direction.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Constitution of Air 
Transport Council.—1[
<section><number>1</number>]


2[The Central 
Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
constitute] an Air Transport Council consisting of a Chairman and such other 
number of members not exceeding eleven as the Central Government may appoint 
thereto:
 
Provided that amongst the 
members to be so appointed there shall at least be one person with experience 
in financial matters and one person who is an employee of either of the 
Corporations with experience in labour matters.
 

3[(2) If at any 
time the Central Government, is of opinion that the continued existence of an 
Air Transport Council is not necessary, it may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, declare that the Air Transport Council shall be dissolved with effect 
from such date as may be specified in the notification, and thereupon the Air 
Transport Council shall be deemed to be dissolved, accordingly.]
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Functions of the Air 
Transport Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the Air Transport Council to consider—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  at the request of either of the 
Corporations any matter of the kind referred to in section 38; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  any matter of importance which 
may be referred to it by the Director General of Civil Aviation or the Director 
General of Posts and Telegraphs relating to matters of common interest, between 
either of the Corporations and the Director General of Civil Aviation, or as 
the case may be, the Director General of Posts and Telegraphs, including rates 
for the carriage of postal articles by air, and to make recommendations thereon 
to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> At the request of the 
Central Government, the Air Transport Council shall investigate any matter 
relating to the fares, freight rates or other charges levied by either 
Corporation in respect of any service or facility provided by the Corporation 
and of the adequacy of efficiency of such service or facility and shall make 
recommendations thereon to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Council shall, if 
so required by the Central Government, tender advice to that Government in 
regard to financial and economic analysis, accounting, costing and statistical 
techniques and financial reporting relating to air transport and, in 
particular, advise in regard to the matters specified in the proviso to 
sub-section (2) of section 34.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
Government, after taking any recommendation made by the Air Transport Council 
under this section into consideration, may issue such directions in the matter 
as it thinks fit and such directions shall be binding on the Corporation 
concerned. 
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Staff of the Council.—The 
Council shall have a Secretary and such other employees as the Central 
Government may appoint, and the expenditure on the staff and other charges of 
the Council shall be borne by the Central Government.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Proceedings of the 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall regulate its own procedure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No proceeding of the 
Council shall be deemed to be invalid by reason merely of any vacancy in, or 
any defect in the constitution of, the Council.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Power of Central 
Government to give directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may give to either of the Corporations directions as to 
the exercise and performance by the Corporation of its functions, and the 
Corporation shall be bound to give effect to any such directions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
Government may, if it is of opinion that it is expedient in the national 
interest so to do, after consultation with the Corporation concerned, direct 
either of the Corporations—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to undertake any air transport 
service or other activity which the Corporation has power to undertake;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to discontinue or make any 
change in any scheduled air transport service or other activity which it is 
operating or carrying on;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  not to undertake any activity 
which it proposes to do:
 
Provided that, if at the 
direction of the Central Government, the Corporation establishes, alters or 
continues to maintain an air transport service or other activity and satisfies 
the Central Government that during the relevant financial year the Corporation 
has suffered on over-all loss in respect of the operation of all its air 
transport services and of all its other activities and also that the service or 
activity so established, altered or continued to be maintained in compliance 
with the directions of the Central Government as aforesaid has been operated at 
a loss in any financial year, then the Central Government shall reimburse the 
Corporation to the extent of the loss relatable to the operation of that 
particular service or activity.


</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Prior approval of 
Central Government necessary in certain cases.—Neither 
Corporation shall, without the previous approval of the Central Government—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  undertake any capital 
expenditure for the purchase or acquisition of any immovable property or 
aircraft or any other thing at a cost exceeding 

1[such amount as the Central 
Government may, from time to time, by order, fix in the behalf];
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  enter into a lease of any 
immovable property for a period exceeding 

2[ten years]; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  in any manner dispose of any 
property, right or privilege having an original or book value exceeding 

1[such amount as the Central 
Government may, from time to time, by order, fix in this behalf].
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Submission of 
programme of work for each year.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each of the Corporations shall prepare and submit to the Central Government, 
not less than 

1[two months] 
before the commencement of the financial year of the Corporation a statement 
showing the programme of operation and development of air transport services to 
be operated by the Corporation and its associates during the forthcoming 
financial year and its other activities as well as its financial estimates in 
respect thereof, including any proposed investment of capital and increase in 
the strength of its total staff.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, during any 
financial year, either of the Corporations engages or proposes to engage in any 
air transport service or ancillary activity in addition to those specified in 
the programme previously submitted under sub-section (1) and a substantial 
alteration of the financial estimates is likely to be involved thereby, the 
Corporation shall submit to the Central Government for approval a supplementary 
programme of such service or activity and a supplementary estimate of the 
expenditure and revenue to be incurred and received by the Corporation in 
respect thereof during the remainder of that period:
 
Provided that, to meet 
any unexpected traffic demand or other special situation, either of the 
Corporations may undertake any additional service or other ancillary activity 
not specified in the programme submitted under sub-section (1) or sub-section 
(2) and subsequently submit a report on the matter to the Central Government in 
the prescribed manner.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Submission of Annual 
Reports to Parliament.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each of the Corporations shall, as soon as may be after the end of each 
financial year prepare and submit to the Central Government in such form as may 
be prescribed a report giving an account of its activities during the previous 
financial year, and the report shall also give an account of the activities, if 
any, which are likely to be undertaken by the Corporation during the next 
financial year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
Government shall cause every such report to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament as soon as may be after it is submitted.
</section></article> 
 The Air Corporations Act, 1953
  
 <article><number>38</number> Corporations to act in 
mutual consultation.—It shall be the duty of each of 
the Corporations to enter into consultations with the other in matters of common 
interest to the two Corporations including, in particular, the operation of 
scheduled air transport services, the routes on which such services should be 
operated by each of the Corporations, the frequency of such services, the 
passenger fares and freight rates to be charged, the measures of economy to be 
adopted, the provision of any services in regard to overhaul and maintenance of 
aircraft or any other matter falling within the scope of the functions of either 
of the Corporations, and, generally, in regard to ensuring the fullest 
co-operation and co-ordination in respect of all such 
matters.</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Transfer of scheduled 
air transport services or assets from one Corporation to the other.—The 
Central Government may, for the purpose of improving the air transport services 
provided by either of the Corporations or for effecting better co-ordination in 
respect of such services, direct that with effect from such date as may be 
specified in the direction and subject to such conditions as may be similarly 
specified,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  any scheduled air transport 
service operated by one Corporation shall no longer be operated by that 
Corporation but shall be operated by the other Corporation, and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  any property belonging to one 
Corporation shall be transferred to the other Corporation.
</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Corporations may 
delegate their powers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each of the Corporations may appoint a Committee or Committees consisting of 
some or any of its 

1[directors] with 
or without the addition of any officer or employee of the Corporation and 
delegate any of the functions and powers of the Corporation to such Committee 
or Committees and may limit the exercise of such delegated authority to any 
specified area.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Either of the 
Corporations may, in relation to any particular matter or class of matters or 
to any particular area, by general or special order, direct that any of its 
officers or other employees may also exercise all or any of its powers under 
this Act (except the powers given to it by this section) to the extent to which 
the Corporation deems it necessary for the efficient running of its day-to-day 
administration.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Advisory and Labour 
Relations Committees.—1[***]
 

1[***] Each of the 
Corporations shall constitute in the prescribed manner a Labour Relations 
Committee consisting of representatives of the Corporations and of its 
employees, so however, that the number of representatives of the employees on 
the Committee shall not be less than the number of representatives of the 
Corporation, and it shall be the duty of the Labour Relations Committee to 
advise the Corporation on matters which relate to the welfare of the employees 
or which are likely to promote and secure amity and good relations between the 
two.
 
 




</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Meetings of the 
Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Meetings of the Corporation shall be held at such times and places and, subject 
to sub-sections (2) and (3), the proceedings of the Corporation shall be 
conducted in such manner as may be provided by the regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairman or in 
his absence any person chosen by the 

1[directors] 
present from amongst themselves shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At a meeting of the 
Corporation all questions shall be decided by a majority of votes of the 

1[directors] 
present, and for this purpose, each 

1[director] shall 
have one vote and in the case of equality of votes the Chairman or, in his 
absence, the person presiding at the meeting shall have a second or casting 
vote.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Penalty for wrongful 
withholding of property.—If 
a director, managing agent, manager or other officer or employee of an existing 
air company who wilfully withholds or fails to deliver to the Corporation as 
required by sub-section (2) of section 21 any books, documents or papers which 
may be in his possession or who wrongfully obtains possession of any property 
of any such company which has vested in either of the Corporations under this 
Act or having any such property in his possession wrongfully withholds it from 
the Corporation or wilfully applies it to purposes other than those expressed 
in, or authorised by, this Act shall, on the complaint of the Corporation 
concerned, be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and 
may be ordered by the Court trying the offence to deliver up or refund within a 
time to be fixed by the Court any such property improperly obtained or 
wrongfully withheld or wilfully misapplied or in default to suffer imprisonment 
which may extend to one year.
</article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Power to make rules—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
to give effect to the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the terms and conditions of 
service of the 

1[managing directors] of the two 
Corporations; and such other categories of officers as may be specified from 
time to time under sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the form in which the budget of 
the two Corporations shall be prepared and submitted to the Central Government; 
and the form and the manner in which the accounts of the two Corporations shall 
be maintained and in which any returns or statistics shall be furnished or 
submitted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the reports which should be 
submitted by the Corporations and the intervals within which they should be so 
submitted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the maintenance of books of 
account;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the establishment and 
maintenance of a fund by each of the Corporations for meeting any liability 
arising out of any act or omission in respect of which the Corporation may 
incur any liability to any third party;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the provision of 

2[***] reserve and other funds;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the prohibition of persons who 
are directly or indirectly interested in any subsisting contract with either of 
the Corporations from becoming or being employees of the Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the powers which may be 
exercised by either of the Corporations to facilitate the acquisition of any 
undertaking;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the issue of bonds by either of 
the Corporations to meet any compensation payable by it under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  the training of the employees 
of either of the Corporations or other persons and the fees which may in its 
discretion be charged therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number> the term of office and other 
conditions of service of members of the Air Transport Council constituted under 
section 30;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  the prohibition of any 
interference with any air transport service or with any property of the 
Corporation or of any interference with or obstruction of any officer or 
employee of the Corporation in the performance of his duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the punishment which shall not 
exceed imprisonment for three months or fine of rupees one thousand but which 
may consist of both such imprisonment and fine, in respect of any contravention 
of the provisions of any rules made under this section.
 

3[(3) Every rule 
made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before 
each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in 

4[two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid,] both Houses agree 
in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
anything previously done under that rule.]










</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Power of Corporations 
to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[Subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (3), each of the Corporations may], by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act or the 
rules made thereunder for the administration of the affairs of the Corporation 
and for carrying out its functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, any such 
regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the time and place of the 
meeting of the Corporation and the procedure to be followed for the transaction 
of business at such meetings;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the terms and conditions of 
service of officers and other employees of the Corporation other than the


2[managing director] and officers of 
any other categories referred to in section 44;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the issue of passes by the 
Corporation to its officers and other employees either free of cost or at 
concessional rates for travel on its air services and the conditions relating 
thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the authentication of orders and 
decisions of the Corporation and the instruments executed by it;
 

        3[(e)  the grant of refund in 
respect of any unused tickets and the issue of passes free of cost or at 
concessional rates;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the period after the expiry of 
which unclaimed goods may be disposed of and the manner of their disposal;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the conditions governing the 
carriage of persons or goods on its services.
 

4[(3) No 
regulation under clause (b) if sub-section (2) shall be made except with the 
previous approval of the Central Government.]
 

5[(4) Every 
regulation made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree 
in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that regulation.]
 
 








</subsection></section></article><form>
 

The Air Corporations Act, 1953
 

 
 

The Schedule 

 

(See section 25)
 

Principles for Determining Compensation Under this 
Act
 

Paragraph I.—The compensation which shall be given by Indian 
Air lines or Air India International, as the case may be, to any existing air 
company in respect of the vesting, in accordance with the provisions of this 
Act, of the undertaking of such company in that Corporation shall be the sum of 
the amounts computed in accordance with the provisions of paragraph II, 
less the sum of the amounts computed in accordance with the provisions of 
paragraph III.
 

Paragraph II.—(a) The aggregate written down value of all 
airframes of aircraft in respect of which there are certificates of 
airworthiness in force of which can be rendered fit or certificates of 
airworthiness if the Corporation concerned were to incur expenditure within the 
normal rates for rendering the airframes airworthy, plus—
 

                
A sum of Rs. 12,000 in respect of each airframe of a Dakota aircraft and a sum 
of Rs. 24,000 in respect of each airframe of a Viking aircraft in any case where 
the existing air company had obtained a certificate of airworthiness in respect 
of it within ninety days immediately preceding the appointed date or if a 
certificate of airworthiness had not actually been obtained within that period 
but the existing air company had incurred expenditure within that period for the 
purpose of rendering that airframe airworthy, the value of the spare parts used 
for the purpose subject to a maximum of Rs. 12,000 in the case of each airframe 
of a Dakota aircraft and Rs. 24,000 in the case of each airframe of a Viking 
aircraft.
 

Note.—In this Schedule, the expression “airframe” 
includes also the equipment of the aircraft, whether fixed or 
removable.
 

(b) the aggregate written down value of all such 
power plants, aero-engines, air screws, spare aero-engines, and spare air screws 
(all of which are in this Schedule collectively referred to as power plants) as 
are suitable for use in the airframes mentioned in sub-clause (a) and as are of 
an approved standard or can be rendered fit to be an approved standard if the 
Corporation concerned were to incur expenditure within the normal rates for such 
purposes, plus the following, namely:—
 

         
(i)  a sum of Rs. 6,000 in respect of each engine of a Dakota aircraft and 
a sum of Rs. 12,000 in respect of each engine of a Viking aircraft in any case 
where the existing air company had made it an approved engine within a period of 
ninety days immediately preceding the appointed date or if the engine had not 
been made completely fit to be an approved engine within that period but the 
existing air company had incurred expenditure within the said period for the 
purpose of making that engine an approved engine, then, the value of the spare 
parts used for that purpose subject to a maximum of Rs. 6,000 in the case of 
each engine of a Dakota aircraft and Rs. 12,000 in the case of each engine of a 
Viking aircraft; and
 

        
(ii)  a sum of Rs. 2,000 in respect of the air screws and accessories of 
the power plant of a Dakota aircraft and a sum of Rs. 4,000 in respect of the 
air screws and accessories of the powers plant of a Viking aircraft in any case 
where the air screws and accessories had been rendered completely fit for the 
approved standard within a period of ninety days immediately preceding the 
appointed date or if the same had not been rendered completely fit for that 
standard within that period but the existing air company had incurred 
expenditure within that period for the purpose of rendering the same fit for the 
approved standard, then, the value of the spare parts used for that purpose 
subject to a maximum of Rs. 2,000 in the case of air screws and accessories of a 
Dakota aircraft and Rs. 4,000 in the case of air screws and accessories of a 
Viking aircraft.
 

Note.—In this Schedule, the expression “approved 
standard” means such condition of efficiency of the power plant as satisfies the 
requirements laid down in Section E of Schedule III to the Indian Aircraft 
Rules, 1937.
 

(c) the cost of purchase of all serviceable general 
stores and all such other serviceable stores and spare parts (all of which are 
in this Schedule collectively referred to as stores and spare parts) belonging 
to the existing air company as are suitable for use in respect of the aircraft 
or power plants referred to in sub-clauses (a) and (b), reduced in each 
case by 20 per cent. of such cost of purchase:
 

Provided that the reduction shall be 10 per 
cent. in the case of stores and spare parts pertaining to Constellation and 
Skymaster aircraft.
 

Note.—In this Schedule—
 

        
(a)  stores shall be deemed to be serviceable if they are such as to 
satisfy the requirements laid down in section E of Schedule III to the Indian 
Aircraft Rules, 1937;
 

        
(b)  without prejudice to the clause immediately preceding, stores (other 
than general stores) and spare parts shall also be deemed to be serviceable if 
by incurring expenditure of an amount not exceeding half the cost of purchase of 
such stores and spare parts, they can be rendered suitable for use in respect of 
the aircraft or power plants;
 

        
(d)  the aggregate actual cost to the existing air company of all lands 
other than lease-holds;
 

        
(e)  the total amount of the premiums paid by the company in respect of all 
lease-holds reduced in the case of each such premium by an amount which 
bears to such premium the same proportion as the expired term on the appointed 
date of the lease in respect of which such premium shall have been paid bears to 
the total term of the lease;
 

         
(f)  the scrap value of all such aircraft, power plants, propellers and 
other accessories, spare parts and stores, not falling within any of the 
preceding sub-clauses, and all properties as have become obsolete on the 
appointed date, the scrap value for the purposes of this Act being one per cent. 
of the book value of the relevant item of property;
 

        
(g)  the price paid by the existing air company for any trustee security 
held by it; 
 

        
(h)  the value of any shares held by any existing air company in any other 
existing air company, the value being calculated on the basis of the valuation 
of the air transport undertaking of that other company in accordance with the 
provisions of this Schedule;
 

         
(i)  the market value on the appointed date or the purchase price whichever 
is less, of any other investments held by any existing air company in any 
concern other than another existing air company which, subject to the provisions 
of section 22, have vested in the Corporation;
 

         
(j)  the amount of cash held by any existing air company on the appointed 
date whether in deposit with a bank or otherwise;
 

        
(k)  the amount of debts other than bad debts due to any existing air 
company, to the extent to which they are reasonably considered to be 
recoverable, less the amount of the debts, if any, excluded from the 
transfer to the Corporation concerned under the provisions of section 
22;
 

         
(l)  the aggregate cost of all licence fees paid by the company under 
clause (c) sub-rule (1) of Rule 154 of the Indian Aircraft Rules, 1937, in 
respect of the licences granted to it for the operation of any scheduled air 
transport services and held by it on the appointed date and which but for the 
provisions of section 19 would continue to remain valid plus a sum of Rs. 
100 for each such licence; provided that the fees paid for each such licence 
shall be reduced by an amount which bears to such fees the same proportion as 
the period of the licence which shall have expired on the appointed date bears 
to the total period of the licence;
 

       (m)  the 
aggregate written down value of all tangible assets other than those falling 
within the preceding clauses;
 

        
(n)  an aggregate amount not exceeding ten thousand rupees as may be agreed 
upon between the Corporation and the existing air company concerned or, failing 
agreement, which may be assessed by the Tribunal, in respect of all such assets, 
intangible or otherwise, as do not fall within any of the preceding sub-clauses 
and in respect of the loss of any future profits which the existing air company 
might have earned but for the passing of this Act:
 

                  
Provided that in assessing any amount under this clause regard shall be had to 
the following circumstances, namely:—
 

               
(i)  the profits, if any, earned by it annually during the six years 
immediately preceding the appointed date on which income-tax has been 
paid.
 

              
(ii)  the subsidies, if any, given to that company by the Central 
Government during such period, and
 

             
(iii)  the probability or otherwise of the company earning future profits 
if it were allowed to continue its scheduled air transport services for the 
remaining period of the licence held by it after having due regard to the fact 
that the licences held by it did not confer any monopoly upon it in respect of 
the routes concerned and the fact that no subsidy would have been payable by the 
Central Government after the 31st day of December, 1952.
 

Explanation A.—For the purposes of this Schedule, the written 
down value in respect of each class of assets means the actual cost to the 
existing air company of such assets respectively, less the total 
depreciation calculated at the rates and in the manner following, 
namely:—
 

         
(i)  in respect of each airframe, depreciation shall be calculated at 15 
per cent. per annum for Constellation and Skymaster aircraft and 18 
per cent. per annum for other aircraft from the date on which the 
aircraft concerned was first used in revenue operations by the company till the 
31st day of December, 1952, the rates being applied as follows:—
 

                        
for the first year, on the actual cost of acquisition;
 

                        
for the second year, on an amount obtained by reducing from the actual cost of 
acquisition the amount of depreciation calculated as aforesaid for the first 
year;
 

                  
      for the third year, on an amount obtained by 
reducing from the actual cost of acquisition the aggregate amount of 
depreciation calculated as aforesaid for the preceding two years,
 

  and so on;
 

        
(ii)  in respect of power plants, the depreciation shall be calculated at 
20 per cent. per annum for Constellation and Skymaster aircraft and at 24 
per cent. per annum for other aircraft from the date on which the power 
plant concerned was first used in revenue operations by the company till the 
31st day of December, 1952, the rates being applied as follows:—
 

                        
for the first year, on the actual cost of acquisition;
 

                        
for the second year, on an amount obtained by reducing from the actual cost of 
acquisition the amount of depreciation calculated as aforesaid for the first 
year;
 

                        
for the third year, on an amount obtained by reducing from the actual cost of 
acquisition the aggregate amount of depreciation calculated as aforesaid for the 
preceding two years,
 

  and so on;
 

        
(iii)  in respect of all tangible assets falling within clause (m) of 
Paragraph II, depreciation shall be calculated at the normal annual rates for 
which provision is made in the Indian Income-tax Act, 1922 (11 of 1922) and in 
the manner provided therein, but excluding initial or other special 
depreciation, from the date such assets were acquired or created by the existing 
air company until the 31st day of December, 1952:
 

Provided that in respect of any such asset for 
which no provision has been made in the Indian Income-tax Act, 1922 (11 of 
1922), the rate of depreciation shall be 10 per cent. per 
annum:
 

Provided further that in respect of any such asset 
situate on leasehold land other than land rented from Government, the 
depreciation shall be either,—
 

        
(a)  as provided in the preceding provisions of this clause, or
 

        
(b)  equivalent to an amount which bears the same ratio to the total cost 
of acquisition or creation of the asset (situate on leasehold land) as the 
expired portion of the lease on the appointed date bears to the total period of 
the lease currently running, whichever is greater.
 

Explanation B.—For the purposes of this Schedule, the actual cost 
shall include, in the case of airframes, in addition to the cost of purchase or 
acquisition,—
 

         
(i)  the actual expenditure, if any, incurred by the existing air company 
for reconversion or reconstruction of the airframe in order to render it fit for 
civil air transport before it was first used in revenue operations by the 
company, plus
 

        
(ii)  the actual expenditure incurred in making the airframe airworthy 
before its first use in revenue operations.
 

Explanation C.—In the case of power plants, the actual cost shall 
include, in addition to the cost of purchase or acquisition, the cost incurred 
by the company for conversion or reconditioning, repairing or overhauling the 
power plant, in order to render it fit for the purposes of a certificate under 
paragraph 4 of Section E of Schedule III to the Indian Aircraft Rules, 1937, 
before the date of its first use in revenue operations.
 

Paragraph III.—Subject to the provisions of sections 22 and 23, 
all such liabilities as have been declared by the existing air company under the 
provisions of section 22:
 

Provided that if any liability so declared has been 
under-stated, the Corporation may recover the additional amount from the 
company.
 

 
 

—————
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>