<act><tid>72652</tid>
<title>THE COAL MINES (NATIONALISATION) ACT, <year>1973</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1973</year>
[ 30th May, <year>1973</year>.] BE

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the right, title 
and interest of the owners in respect of the coal mines specified in 
the Schedule with a view to re- organising and reconstructing such coal 
mines so as to ensure the rational, co- ordinated and scientific 
development and utilisation of coal resources consistent with the 
growing requirements of the country, in order that the ownership and 
control of such resources are vested in the State and thereby so 
distributed as best to subserve the common good, and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1538649</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>458265</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Act, <year>1973</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>992828</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 30 and 31 shall come into force at 
once and the remaining provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have 
come into force on the 1st day of May, <year>1973</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>285597</tid>
<number> 1A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Declaration as to expediency of Union control.
<section><tid>314591</tid>
<number>1</number>It is  
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
Union should take under its control the regulation and development of 
coal mines to the extent hereinafter provided in sub- sections (3) and 
 (4) of section 3 and sub- section (2) of section 30.

</section>

<section><tid>1146223</tid>
<number>2</number>The declaration contained in sub- section (1) is in addition 
to, and not in derogation, of the declaration contained in section 2 
of the Mines and Minerals (Regulation and Development) Act, <year>1957</year> (67  
  of <year>1957</year>).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>276070</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>130186</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of May, <year>1973</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>412138</tid>
<number>b</number>" coal mine" means a mine in which there exists one or 
more seams of coal;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>332</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 67 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 29- 4- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>761387</tid>
<number>c</number>" company" means a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and includes a 
foreign company within the meaning of section 591 of 
that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1629167</tid>
<number>d</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments 
appointed under section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>374171</tid>
<number>e</number>" Custodian" means the Custodian appointed under sub- 
section (2) of section 11, to take over, or carry on, 
the management of a coal mine;

</section>

<section><tid>1186422</tid>
<number>f</number>" Government company" has the meaning assigned to it by 
section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1932490</tid>
<number>g</number>" managing contractor" means the person, or body of 
persons, who, with the previous consent, in writing, of 
the State Government, has entered into an arrangement, 
contract or understanding, with the owner of a coal 
mine under which the operations of the coal mine are 
substantially controlled by such person or body of 
persons;

</section>

<section><tid>826565</tid>
<number>h</number>" mine" means any excavation where any operation for the 
purpose of searching for or obtaining minerals has been 
or is being carried on, and includes--

</section>

<section><tid>1078890</tid>
<number>i</number>all borings and bore holes;

<subsection><tid>1092192</tid>
<number>ii</number>all shafts, whether in the course of being 
sunk or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944572</tid>
<number>iii</number>all levels and inclined planes in the course 
of being driven;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>299655</tid>
<number>iv</number>all open cast workings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1342473</tid>
<number>v</number>all conveyors or aerial ropeways provided for 
bringing into or removal from a mine of minerals or 
other articles or for the removal of refuse therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>101629</tid>
<number>vi</number>all lands, buildings, works, adits, levels, 
planes, machinery and equipments, instruments, stores, 
vehicles, railways, tramways and sidings in, or 
adjacent to, a mine and used for the purposes of the 
mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>535594</tid>
<number>vii</number>all workshops (including buildings,  
machinery, instruments, stores, equipment of such 
  workshops and the lands on which such workshops stand) 
in, or adjacent to, a mine and used substantially for 
the purposes of the mine or a number of mines under the 
same management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>644667</tid>
<number>viii</number>all coal belonging to the owner of the 
mine, whether in stock or in transit, and all coal 
under production in a mine;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>333</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1308110</tid>
<number>ix</number>all power stations in a mine or operated 
primarily for supplying electricity for the purpose of 
working the mine or a number of mines under the same 
management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1486602</tid>
<number>x</number>all lands, buildings and equipments belonging 
to the owner of the mine, and in, adjacent to or 
situated on the surface of, the mine where the washing 
of coal obtained from the mine or manufacture, 
therefrom, of coke is carried on;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1919241</tid>
<number>xi</number>all lands and buildings[ other than those 
referred to in sub- clause (x)], wherever situated, if 
solely used for the location of the management, sale or 
liaison offices, or for the residence of officers and 
staff, of the mine;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1265062</tid>
<number>xii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> all other fixed assets, movable and 
immovable, belonging to the owner of a mine, wherever 
situated, and current assets, belonging to a mine, 
whether within its premises or outside.
Explanation.-- The expression" current assets" does 
not include,--


</section>

<section><tid>130186</tid>
<number>a</number>dues representing the sale of coal and coal 
products effected at any time before the appointed day 
and outstanding immediately before the said day;

</section>

<section><tid>412138</tid>
<number>b</number>dues from the Coal Board, established under 
section 4 of the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), prior to the 
repeal of the said Act, with respect to any period 
before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>761387</tid>
<number>c</number>dues from sundry debtors, loans and advances 
to other parties and investments, not being investments 
in the coal mine;

</section>

<section><tid>1629167</tid>
<number>d</number>security deposits made by the owners with the 
Coal Controller appointed by the Central Government or 
with the Railways for the fulfilment of contracts or 
with a State Electricity Board for the payment of 
bills;

</section>

<section><tid>374171</tid>
<number>e</number>earnest money deposited by the owners with the 
Railways for obtaining contracts;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>334</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 10, for the original sub- clause 
 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



<subsection><tid>262779</tid>
<number>i</number>" Mineral Concession Rules" means the rules, for the time 
being in force, made under the Mines and Minerals 
 (Regulation and Development) Act, <year>1957</year> (67 of <year>1957</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1513391</tid>
<number>j</number>" mining company" means a company owning a coal mine, and 
in relation to a foreign company within the meaning of 
section 591 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
the undertaking of that company in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1344577</tid>
<number>k</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1141269</tid>
<number>l</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>924741</tid>
<number>m</number>" specified date" means such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, for the purpose of any provision of 
this Act by notification, specify; and different dates 
may be specified for different provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>734254</tid>
<number>n</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), have the 
meanings, respectively, assigned to them in that Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735935</tid>
<number>o</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined in 
this Act or in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), but defined in 
the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>), have the meanings, 
respectively, assigned to them in the Mines Act, <year>1952</year>.
CHAP

ACQUISITION OF THE RIGHTS OF OWNERS OF COAL MINES

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE RIGHTS OF OWNERS OF COAL MINES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>956071</tid>
<number> 3</number> Acquisition of rights of owners in respect of coal mines.
<section><tid>271938</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On the appointed day, the right, title and interest of the owners in 
relation to the coal mines specified in the Schedule shall stand 
transferred to, and shall vest absolutely in the Central Government 
free from all incumbrances.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>335</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The specified date for the purpose of the different provisions 
of the Act is as indicated below:-- 
Provision of the Act Specified date Gazette reference 
Sub- section (3) of section 14 16- 6- <year>1973</year> G. S. R. 312 (E), 
dated 12- 6- <year>1973</year>.

Section 16 31- 12- <year>1973</year>- do-

Sub- section (3) of section 19 30- 11- <year>1974</year> G. S. R. 282 (E), 
dated 26- 6- <year>1974</year>.

Sub- section (4) of section 30- 11- <year>1974</year>- do- 
19 and the proviso thereto.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1405846</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> On and from the commencement of section 3 of the Coal 
Mines (Nationalisation) Amendment Act, <year>1976</year> (67 of <year>1976</year>),--

<subsection><tid>970380</tid>
<number>a</number>no person, other than--

<subsubsection><tid>1480829</tid>
<number>i</number>the Central Government or a Government, 
company or a corporation owned, managed or controlled 
by the Central Government, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1386145</tid>
<number>ii</number>a person to whom a sub- lease, referred to in 
the proviso to clause (c), has been granted by any such 
Government, company or corporation, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1141949</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a company engaged in--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1269889</tid>
<number>1</number>the production of iron and steel,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>847488</tid>
<number>2</number>generation of power,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>854159</tid>
<number>3</number>washing of coal obtained from a mine, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>653613</tid>
<number>4</number>such other end use as the Central 
Government may, by notification, specify,]
shall carry on coal mining operation, in India, in any form;


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1698277</tid>
<number>b</number>excepting the mining leases granted before such 
commencement in favour of the Government, company or 
corporation, referred to in clause (a), and any sub- 
lease granted by any such Government, company or 
corporation, all other mining leases and sub- leases in 
force immediately before such commencement, shall, in 
so far as they relate to the winning or mining of coal, 
stand terminated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>633028</tid>
<number>c</number>no lease for winning or mining coal shall be granted in 
favour of any person other than the Government, company 
or corporation, referred to in clause (a):
Provided that the Government, company or corporation to whom 
a lease for winning or mining coal has been granted may 
grant a sub- lease to any person in any area on such 
terms and conditions as may be specified in the 
instrument granting the sub- lease, if the Government, 
company or corporation is satisfied that--


<subsubsection><tid>403788</tid>
<number>i</number>the reserves of coal in the area are in 
isolated small pockets or are not sufficient for 
scientific and economical development in a co- ordinated 
and integrated manner, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>336</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 67 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 29- 4- <year>1976</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1993</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1365659</tid>
<number>ii</number>the coal produced by the sub- lessee will not 
be required to be transported by rail.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>548451</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a mining lease stands terminated under sub- section (3), 
it shall be lawful for the Central Government or a Government, company 
or corporation owned or controlled by the Central Government to 
obtain, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> xxx a prospecting licence or a mining lease in respect of 
the whole or part of the land covered by the mining lease which stands 
so terminated.]

</section>

<section><tid>33798</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If, after the appointed day, the Central Government is 
satisfied, whether from any information received by it or otherwise, 
that there has been any error, omission or misdescription in relation 
to the particulars of a coal mine included in the Schedule or the name 
and address of the owner of any such coal mine, it may, by 
notification, correct such error, omission or misdescription and on 
the issue of such notification, the relevant entries in the Schedule 
shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been, corrected 
accordingly:
Provided that no such correction in relation to the ownership of 
a coal mine shall be made where such ownership is in dispute.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>340185</tid>
<number> 4</number> Central Government to be the lessee of the State Government.

<section><tid>362603</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the rights of an owner under any mining lease granted, or  
deemed to have been granted, in relation to a coal mine, by a State 
Government or any other person, vest in the Central Government under 
section 3, the Central Government shall, on and from the date of such 
vesting, be deemed to have become the lessee of the State Government 
or such other person, as the case may be, in relation to such coal 
mine <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as if a fresh mining lease] in relation to such coal mine had 
been granted to the Central Government and the period of such lease 
shall be <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the maximum period] for which such lease could have been 
granted by the State Government or such other person under the Mineral 
Concession Rules, and thereupon all the rights under such mining 
lease, including surface, underground and other rights granted to the 
lessee shall be deemed to have been transferred to, and vested in, the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1837423</tid>
<number>2</number>On the expiry of the term of any lease, referred to in sub- 
section (1), such lease shall, if so desired by the Central 
Government, be renewed, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> xxx by the lessor, for the maximum period 
for which such lease can be renewed under the Mineral Concession 
Rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>708418</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of Central Government to direct vesting of rights in a 
Government company.
<section><tid>466815</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections  
 3 and 4, the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that a 
Government company is willing to comply, or has complied, with such 
terms and conditions as that Government may think fit to impose, 
direct, by an order in writing, that the right, title and interest of 
an owner in relation to a coal mine referred to in section 3, shall, 
instead of continuing to vest in the Central Government, vest in the 
Government company either on the date of publication of the direction 
or on such earlier or later date (not being a date earlier than the  
  appointed day), as may be specified in the direction.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>337</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 12, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
4 Omitted by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>136662</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the right, title and interest of an owner in relation 
to a coal mine vest in a Government company under sub- section (1), the 
Government company shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be 
deemed to have become the lessee in relation to such coal mine as if a 
mining lease in relation to the coal mine had been granted to the 
Government company and the period of such lease shall be the entire 
period for which such lease could have been granted under the Mineral 
Concession Rules; and all the rights and liabilities of the Central 
Government in relation to such coal mine shall, on and from the date 
of such vesting, be deemed to have become the rights and liabilities, 
respectively, of the Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>1081197</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 4 shall apply to 
a lease which vests in a Government company as they apply to a lease 
vested in the Central Government and references therein to the 
" Central Government" shall be construed as references to the 
Government company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1026166</tid>
<number> 6</number> Properties vested in the Central Government to be freed from 
mortgages, etc.
<section><tid>407987</tid>
<number>1</number>All property which vests in the Central Government  
or in a Government company under this Chapter shall, by force of such 
vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, 
charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting it and any 
attachment, injunction or decree or order of any court restricting the 
use of such property in any manner shall be deemed to have been 
withdrawn.

</section>

<section><tid>1664649</tid>
<number>2</number>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this 
Act in the Central Government or a Government company, and every 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in or in relation to 
any such property shall give, within such time and in such manner as 
may be prescribed, an intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, 
charge, lien or other interest.

</section>

<section><tid>422837</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (1) or any other 
person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation 
to any, such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with 
his rights and interests, payment of the mortgage money or other dues, 
in whole or in part, out of the amount specified in relation to such 
property in the Schedule, but no such mortgage, charge, lien or other 
interest shall be enforceable against any property which has vested in 
the Central Government or the Government company.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>338</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>11770</tid>
<number> 7</number> Central Government or Government company not to be liable for 
prior liabilites.
<section><tid>394734</tid>
<number>1</number>Every liability of the owner, agent, manager or  
managing contractor of a coal mine, in respect of any period prior to 
the appointed day, shall be the liability of such owner, agent, 
manager or managing contractor, as the case may be, and shall be 
enforceable against him and not against the Central Government or the 
Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>254552</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that--

<subsection><tid>694778</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise provided elsewhere in this Act, no 
claim for wages, bonus, royalty, rate, rent, taxes, 
provident fund, pension, gratuity or any other dues in 
relation to a coal mine in respect of any period prior 
to the appointed day, shall be enforceable against the 
Central Government or the Government company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>105739</tid>
<number>b</number>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or 
other authority in relation to any coal mine passed 
after the appointed day, but in relation to any matter, 
claim or dispute which arose before that day, shall be 
enforceable against the Central Government or the 
Government company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>787197</tid>
<number>c</number>no liability for the contravention, before the appointed 
day, of any provision of law for the time being in 
force, shall be enforceable against the Central 
Government or the Government company.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1345653</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment of amount to owners of coal mines. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>151309</tid>
<number>1</number>] The owner  
of every coal mine or group of coal mines specified in the second 
column of the Schedule, shall be given by the Central Government, in 
cash and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, for the vesting in it, 
under section 3, of the right, title and interest of the owner in 
relation to such coal mine or group of coal mines, an amount equal to 
the amount specified against it in the corresponding entry in the 
fifth column of the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>802082</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
amount specified in the fifth column of the Schedule against any coal 
mine or group of coal mines specified in the second column of the said 
Schedule and required to be given by the Central Government to its 
owner under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to include, and deemed 
always to have included, the amount required to be paid to such owner 
in respect of all coal in stock or other assets referred to in clause 
 (h) of section 2 on the date immediately before the appointed day and 
no further amount shall be payable to the owner in respect of such 
coal or other assets.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>243952</tid>
<number> 9</number> Payment of further amount.
<section><tid>861978</tid>
<number>1</number>In consideration of the  
retrospective operation of the provisions of sections 3, 4 and 5, 
there shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner 
of every coal mine or group of coal mines specified in the Schedule, 
an amount equal to the amount which would have been, but for the 
provisions of the said sections 3,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>339</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 13, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 4 and 5, payable to such owner under the Coal Mines (Taking Over of  
  Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of <year>1973</year>), for the period commencing on the 
 1st day of May, <year>1973</year>, and ending on the date on which this Act 
receives the assent of the President.


</section>

<section><tid>1852735</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the amount referred to in sub- section (1), 
there shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner 
of every coal mine or group of coal mines specified in the Schedule, 
simple interest at the rate of four per cent. per annum on the amount 
specified against such owner in the corresponding entry in the fifth 
column of the Schedule for the period commencing on the date on which 
this Act receives the assent of the President and ending on the date 
on which payment of such amount is made by the Central Government to 
the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>22922</tid>
<number>3</number>The amounts referred to in sub- section (1) and sub- section 
 (2) shall be in addition to the amount specified in the Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1732167</tid>
<number> 10</number> Income derived by the owners of coal mines after the 
appointed day to be refunded to the Central Government.
<section><tid>846924</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in  
pursuance of any decree, order or injunction of a court or otherwise, 
the Central Government or the Custodian appointed under the Coal Mines 
 (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of <year>1973</year>), was prevented 
from taking over the management of any coal mine, the owner of such 
coal mine shall render, within sixty days from the date on which 
management of the coal mine is delivered to the Central Government or 
Government company, as the case may be, accounts in relation to the 
period commencing on the date of commencement of the said Act and 
ending on the date of delivery of such management to the Central 
Government or the Government company, as the case may be, with regard 
to the--

<subsection><tid>989101</tid>
<number>a</number>assets and stores of the coal mine acquired or sold by 
him during the said period;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>985840</tid>
<number>b</number>coal sold or despatched during the said period;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>590776</tid>
<number>c</number>income derived by him from the coal mine during the said 
period.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1136919</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on examination of the accounts referred to in sub- section 
 (1), any income is found to have been derived by the owner from the 
coal mine during the period referred to in that sub- section, such 
income shall be recoverable by the Central Government from the amount 
payable under section 8 to the owner of such coal mine, and, the debt 
due to the Central Government on this account shall rank as an 
unsecured debt.

</section>

<section><tid>129171</tid>
<number>3</number>If no account is rendered by the owner of a coal mine within 
the period referred to in sub- section (1) or if the Central Government 
or the Government company has any reason to believe that the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>340</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

account rendered by such owner is incorrect or false in material 
particulars, the Central Government or the Government company may 
refer the matter to the Commissioner and thereupon the Commissioner 
shall determine the income derived by the owner from the coal mine 
during the period referred to in sub- section (1), and take steps to 
recover the said income from the amount payable to the owner of the 
coal mine under section 8, as if the debt due to the Central 
Government on this account were an unsecured debt.


</section>

<section><tid>716616</tid>
<number>4</number>No mortgage, charge, lien or other incumbrance in relation to 
a coal mine or any asset thereof shall be binding on the Central 
Government or the Government company if such mortgage, charge, lien or 
other incumbrance was created, at any time during the period in which 
the Central Government or the Custodian was prevented, by any decree, 
order or injunction of a court or otherwise, from taking over the 
management of the said coal mine.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF COAL MINES

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF COAL MINES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>155306</tid>
<number> 11</number> Management, etc., of coal mines.
<section><tid>885037</tid>
<number>1</number>The general  
superintendence, direction, control and management of the affairs and 
business of a coal mine, the right, title and interest of an owner in 
relation to which have vested in the Central Government under section 
3, shall,--

<subsection><tid>1579597</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a coal mine in relation to which a 
direction has been made by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) of section 5, vest in the Government 
company specified in such direction, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>265898</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a coal mine in relation to which no such 
direction has been made by the Central Government, vest 
in one or more Custodians appointed by the Central 
Government under sub- section (2),
and thereupon the Government company so specified or the Custodian so 
appointed, as the case may be, shall be entitled to exercise all such 
powers and do all such things as the owner of the coal mine is 
authorised to exercise and do.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1995566</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint an individual or a 
Government company as the Custodian of a coal mine in relation to 
which no direction has been made by it under sub- section (1) of 
section 5.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>341</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1430774</tid>
<number> 12</number> Duty of persons in charge of management of coal mines to 
deliver all assets, etc.
<section><tid>1391597</tid>
<number>1</number>On the vesting of the management of a  
coal mine in a Government company or on the appointment of a 
Custodian, all persons in charge of the management of such coal mine 
immediately before such vesting or appointment, shall be bound to 
deliver to the Government company or the Custodian, as the case may 
be, all assets, books of account, registers or other documents in 
their custody relating to the coal mine.

</section>

<section><tid>347235</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may 
deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the Government 
company or Custodian as to its or his powers and duties and the 
Government company or Custodian may also, if it or he so desires, 
apply to the Central Government at any time for instructions as to the 
manner in which the management of the coal mine shall be conducted by 
it or him or in relation to any other matter arising in the course of 
such management.

</section>

<section><tid>15464</tid>
<number>3</number>The Custodian shall receive from the funds of the coal mine, 
in relation to which he or it is the Custodian, such remuneration as 
the Central Government may fix and shall hold office during the 
pleasure of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>802052</tid>
<number>13</number>Accounts and audit. The Custodian of every coal mine shall 
maintain the accounts of such mine in such manner and under such 
conditions as may be prescribed.
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF COAL MINES

CHAPTER V

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF COAL MINES



</article>



<article><tid>703090</tid>
<number>14</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Liability of officer or other employee of a coal mine for 
transfer to any other coal mine. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law 
for the time being in force, the services of any officer or other 
employee employed in a coal mine shall be liable to be transferred to 
any other coal mine and such transfer shall not entitle such officer 
or other employee to any compensation under this Act or any other law 
for the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by 
any court, tribunal or other authority.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>342</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1777577</tid>
<number> 15</number> Provident and other funds.
<section><tid>1405305</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a coal mine has  
established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare or other fund 
for the benefit of its employees, the monies relatable to the 
employees, whose services have become transferred by or under this Act 
to the Central Government or a Government company shall, out of the 
monies standing, on the appointed day, to the credit of such provident 
fund, superannuation, welfare or other fund, stand transferred to, and 
vest in, the Central Government or the Government company, as the case 
may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1288572</tid>
<number>2</number>The monies which stand transferred, under sub- section (1), to 
the Central Government or a Government company shall be dealt

<pagefootnote><pagenum>343</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

with by that Government or company, as the case may be, in such manner 
as may be prescribed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1982982</tid>
<number>16</number>Superannuation fund, etc., to be distributed to employees 
whose employment becomes terminated under this Act. Where the 
employment of an employee stands terminated by reason of sub- section 
 (3) of section 14 and such employee is not employed by the owner of 
the coal mine in any of his other establishments, such owner shall pay 
to such employee the amount standing at his credit in the provident 
fund and also pay him the amounts due to him as superannuation, 
welfare and other benefits admissible to him as if the employee had 
superannuated or his service with the coal mine had terminated on the 
day immediately preceding the specified date.
CHAP

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS

CHAPTER VI

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS



</article>



<article><tid>1941399</tid>
<number> 17</number> Commissioner of Payments to be appointed.
<section><tid>1416958</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose  
of disbursing the amounts payable to the owner of each coal mine or 
group of coal mines, the Central Government shall appoint such person 
as it may think fit to be the Commissioner of Payments.

</section>

<section><tid>1076043</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it 
may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons to also 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act, 
and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>185153</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any 
powers may exercise those powers in the same manner and with the same 
effect as if they have been conferred on that person directly by this 
Act and not by way of authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>1409665</tid>
<number>4</number>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1884479</tid>
<number> 18</number> Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>1058511</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified 
date, pay, in cash, to the Commissioner for payment to the owner of a 
coal mine, an amount equal to the amount specified against the coal 
mine in the Schedule and shall also pay to the Commissioner such sums 
as may be due to the owner of a coal mine under section 9.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>344</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1694024</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the sum referred to in sub- section (1), the 
Central Government shall pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, such 
amount as may become due to the owner of a coal mine in relation to 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the period] during which the management of the coal mine remains 
vested in the Central Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, and simple interest at the rate 
of four per cent. per annum on such amount for the period commencing 
on the 1st day of July, <year>1975</year> and ending on the date of payment of such 
amount to the Commissioner].

</section>

<section><tid>50647</tid>
<number>3</number>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government, 
in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and 
every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be 
deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account in the 
Public Account of India, and thereafter the said deposit account shall 
be operated by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>516994</tid>
<number>4</number>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in 
respect of each coal mine in relation to which payments have been made 
to him under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1965777</tid>
<number>5</number>Interest accruing on the amounts standing to the credit of 
the deposit account referred to in sub- section (3) shall ensure to the 
benefit of the owners of coal mines <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and shall also be payable to 
the Commissioner in addition to the sum referred to in sub- section 
 (1)].

</section>

<section><tid>288482</tid>
<number>6</number>References in this section to the owner of a coal mine shall, 
in relation to a group of coal mines specified in the Schedule, be 
construed as references to the owner of that group of coal mines.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1947302</tid>
<number> 19</number> Statement of accounts in respect of the period of management 
by the Central Government, etc.
<section><tid>404162</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government or the  
Government company, as the case may be, shall cause the books in 
relation to each coal mine, the management of which has vested in it 
under the Coal Mines (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of  
  <year>1973</year>), to be closed and balanced as on the date immediately before the 
appointed day, and shall cause a statement of accounts, as on that 
day, to be prepared, within such time, in such form and in such manner 
as may be prescribed, in relation to each such mine in respect of the 
transactions effected by it during the period for which the management 
of such coal mine remained vested in it:
Provided that where two or more coal mines were owned, before the 
commencement of this Act, by the same owner, a consolidated statement 
of accounts may be prepared for all the coal mines owned by such 
owner.


</section>

<section><tid>419412</tid>
<number>2</number>All amounts received by the Central Government or the 
Government company after the closure of such accounts shall, where 
such accounts relate to transactions effected before the appointed 
day, be included in the said statement of accounts in respect of the 
coal mine to which the said receipt relates.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>345</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 11, for certain words. 
2 Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1956</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>310580</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government or the Government company in which the 
right, title and interest of coal mine stand vested shall be entitled 
to receive, up to the specified date, to the exclusion of all other 
persons, any money, due to the coal mine, realised after the appointed 
day notwithstanding that the realisations pertain to a period prior 
to the appointed day:
Provided that where such realisations have not been included in 
the statement of accounts as on the day immediately before the 
appointed day, a supplementary statement of accounts shall be prepared 
and furnished, at such intervals as may be prescribed, by the Central 
Government or the Government company to the owner of the coal mine.


</section>

<section><tid>523932</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The liabilities of the coal mine (not being liabilities  
arising out of advances made by the Central Government or the 
  Government company), which could not be discharged by the appointed 
day, may be discharged by the Central Government or the Government 
company up to the specified date out of the realisations effected 
before or after the appointed day or out of advances or borrowings 
made up to the specified date and every payment so made shall be 
included in the statement of accounts as on the date immediately 
before the appointed day indicating therein the period in relation to 
which the payments were made and the payments so made shall not be 
called in question in any court:
Provided that the liabilities in relation to the period prior to 
the appointed day, which have not been discharged on or before the 
specified date, shall be the liabilities of the owner of the coal 
mine.]


</section>

<section><tid>1205016</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of each statement of accounts prepared under this 
section shall be delivered by the Central Government or the Government 
company, as the case may be, to the Commissioner and also to the 
owner:
Provided that where the number of owners is more than one, only 
one copy of the statement of accounts shall be given to the owners for 
the benefit of all of them.


</section>

<section><tid>710198</tid>
<number>6</number>The statement of accounts prepared under this section shall 
be audited by a person who is qualified to be appointed as an auditor 
of a company under section 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), and the auditor so appointed shall receive from the funds of 
the coal mine, such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1447006</tid>
<number>7</number>The audit of the statement of accounts shall be conducted in 
such manner as the Central Government may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>133867</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The statement of accounts audited under sub- section (6) 
shall, unless the contrary is proved, be conclusive proof in respect 
of every matter entered therein.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," statement of 
accounts" means a statement in the form of receipts and payments, and 
does not include any statement that may be prepared as a result of the 
closing and balancing of the books for the preparation of the profit 
and loss account and balance- sheet or any statement prepared in 
accordance with the normal commercial practice.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1164050</tid>
<number> 19A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Validation of certain collections.
<section><tid>1667558</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 2, as amended by section 10 of the Coal 
Mines Nationalisation Laws
<pagefootnote><pagenum>346</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 16, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 12.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



<subsection><tid>532760</tid>
<number>Amendment</number>Act, <year>1978</year> (22 of <year>1978</year>), any money collected by the 
Central Government or the Government company during the period 
commencing on the appointed day and ending with the date specified 
under sub- section (3) of section 19 shall be deemed to have been 
validly collected by the Central Government or the Government company, 
as the case may be, and any such money shall be applied in accordance 
with the provisions of section 19.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>761276</tid>
<number>2</number>Any money collected as aforesaid shall not be called in 
question in any court of law.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1639029</tid>
<number> 20</number> Claims to be made to the commissioner. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>631411</tid>
<number>1</number>] Every person  
having a claim against the owner of a coal mine shall prefer such 
claim before the Commissioner within thirty days from the specified 
date:
Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant 
was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the 
said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a 
further period of thirty days but not thereafter.


</section>

<section><tid>1190842</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), 
claims in relation to a provident fund, pension fund, gratuity fund or 
any other fund established for the welfare of the persons employed by 
the owner of a coal mine or group of coal mines may be filed on behalf 
of the persons so employed by the Coal Mines Provident Fund 
Commissioner appointed by the Central Government under section 3C of 
the Coal Mines Provident Fund, Family Pension and Bonus Schemes Act, 
 <year>1948</year> (46 of <year>1948</year>); <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and claims in relation to any other matter may 
be filed on behalf of all or any of the persons so employed or any 
group of such persons, by any Trade Union, registered under the Trade 
Unions Act, <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>), or, where no such claim has been filed 
by any Trade Union, by the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) 
appointed by the Central Government or any officer subordinate to 
him;] and the claims so made shall be deemed to have been made by the 
persons having a claim against the owner of a coal mine or group of 
coal mines:
Provided that no such claim shall be made by the Coal Mines 
Provident Fund Commissioner <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or the Trade Union or the Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central) or any officer subordinate to him,] in relation 
to a person who has already made a claim under sub- section (1).]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>347</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Section 20 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 41 of 
<year>1973</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 6, ibid., (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1778727</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where any claim, not being a claim which was time- barred 
on the 31st day of January, <year>1973</year>, was preferred under sub- section (1) 
within the period specified therefor and was rejected merely on the 
ground that such claim was time- barred, such claim shall be deemed not 
to have been rejected and the Commissioner shall restore on his file 
such claim and shall deal with it in the manner specified in section 
23.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>292975</tid>
<number> 21</number> Priority of claims in relation to arrears of provident fund, 
etc.
<section><tid>1599424</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person employed by the owner of a coal mine or group of  
coal mines may make a claim to the Commissioner to the effect that the 
sums deducted under sub- section (4) of section 7 of the Coal Mines 
 (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of <year>1973</year>), are not 
sufficient to meet fully the amount of arrears due to him, on the 
appointed day within the meaning of that Act, from the owner of such 
coal mine or group of coal mines,--

<subsection><tid>132213</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to a provident fund, pension fund, gratuity 
fund or any other fund established for the welfare of 
the persons employed by the owner of a coal mine or 
group of coal mines, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>149836</tid>
<number>b</number>as wages,
and that a sum equal to the deficiency may be recovered from the 
amount specified in the Schedule against the owner of such coal mine 
or group of coal mines.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1942950</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a claim is made under sub- section (1), the Commissioner 
shall determine the extent of the deficiency and shall, after such 
determination, deduct in the first instance, out of the amount paid to 
him under section 8, a sum equal to the extent of the deficiency 
determined by him under this sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>1786119</tid>
<number>3</number>All sums deducted by the Commissioner under sub- section (2) 
shall, in accordance with such rules as may be made under this Act, be 
credited by the Commissioner to the relevant fund or be paid to the 
persons to whom such sums are due, and on such credit or payment, the 
liability of the owner in respect of all the amounts of arrears due as 
aforesaid shall stand discharged.

</section>

<section><tid>1469258</tid>
<number>4</number>The deductions made by the Commissioner under sub- section (2) 
shall have priority over all other debts, whether secured or 
unsecured.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>322387</tid>
<number> 22</number> Priority in relation to other claims.
<section><tid>964170</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise  
provided in section 21, every secured debt due from the owner of a 
coal mine or group of coal mines shall
<pagefootnote><pagenum>348</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


have priority over all other debts and shall be paid in accordance 
with the rights and interests of the secured creditors.


</section>

<section><tid>956866</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, there shall be paid in priority to all other 
unsecured debts, not being the amounts advanced by the Central 
Government or the Custodian appointed under the Coal Mines (Taking  
  Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of <year>1973</year>), for the management of the 
coal mine,--

<subsection><tid>800026</tid>
<number>a</number>all sums due to the State Government including royalty 
and dead rent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452533</tid>
<number>b</number>all amounts due in respect of any compensation or 
liability for compensation under the Workmen' s 
Compensation Act, <year>1923</year> (8 of <year>1923</year>), in respect of the 
death or disablement of any employee of the coal mine 
unless such mine has, under such contract with insurers 
as mentioned in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 14] of the said Act, rights 
capable of being transferred to and vested in, the 
workmen; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1860190</tid>
<number>c</number>all sums deducted by the employer from the salary or 
wages of any workman or other employee for credit to 
any provident fund, or any other fund established for 
the welfare of the employees of the coal mine but not 
deposited to the credit of the said fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1813069</tid>
<number>3</number>The debts specified in sub- section (2) shall rank equally 
among themselves and be paid in full, unless the assets are 
insufficient to meet them, in which case they shall abate in equal 
proportions and be paid accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1127088</tid>
<number> 23</number> Admission or rejection of claims.
<section><tid>914836</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner shall  
fix a certain date on or before which every claimant shall file the 
proof of his claim or be excluded from the benefit of the disbursement 
made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1200458</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in 
the English language and one issue of the daily newspaper in the 
regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every 
such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his 
claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the 
advertisement.

</section>

<section><tid>1958772</tid>
<number>3</number>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the time specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from 
the disbursements made by the Commissioner.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>349</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" section 15".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1953179</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary and after giving the owner of the coal mine 
an opportunity of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit or reject the 
claim in whole or in part.

</section>

<section><tid>907358</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions 
including the place or places at which he will hold his sittings and 
shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act, 
have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of 
the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>296177</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1695469</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other 
material object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>683794</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>297861</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witness.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>690201</tid>
<number>6</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter 
XXXV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1422488</tid>
<number>6A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Commissioner may, on receipt of a claim,--

<subsection><tid>474602</tid>
<number>a</number>elect to settle the claim himself; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>24401</tid>
<number>b</number>transfer the claim for settlement to a person authorised 
in this behalf under sub- section (2) of section 17; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549662</tid>
<number>c</number>withdraw the claim from the person referred to in clause 
 (b) and either settle the claim himself or transfer it 
for disposal to any other person who has been 
authorised in this behalf under sub- section (2) of 
section 17.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1127602</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> A claimant or owner who is dissatisfied with the decision 
of the Commissioner may prefer an appeal, within a period of sixty 
days from the date of the decision,] to the principal civil court of 
original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the coal mine is situated:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>350</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is 
appointed to be the Commissioner, such appeal shall lie to the High 
Court for the State in which the coal mine is situated, and such 
appeal shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of 
that High Court:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that any appeal which has not been preferred 
before the date on which the Coal Mines Nationalisation Laws 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1978</year> (22 of <year>1978</year>), receives the assent of the 
President, shall be preferred within a period of Sixty days from such 
date.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>681969</tid>
<number>23A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Application of sections 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act. 
The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36  
  of <year>1963</year>), shall, so far as may be, apply to appeals under section 23.]


</article>



<article><tid>1803601</tid>
<number>24</number>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner to claimants. 
Where, after meeting the claims admitted by him, of secured creditirs, 
and unsecured creditors having priority under sub- section (2) of 
section 22, the total amount of claims of other unsecured creditors 
admitted by the Commissioner, does not exceed the total amount of the 
money credited to the account of a coal mine, every such admitted 
claim shall be paid in full and the balance, if any, shall be paid to 
the owner, but where such amount is insufficient to meet in full the 
total amount of the admitted claims, all such claims shall abate in 
equal proportions and be paid accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1137028</tid>
<number>24A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Interest on admitted claims. Notwithstanding any award, 
decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority, passed 
before the appointed day, in relation to any coal mine, where any 
amount is payable in respect of a claim admitted under this Act, the 
interest payable on such amount for any period after the appointed day 
shall be at such rate not exceeding the rate of interest accruing on 
any amount deposited by the Commissioner under section 18.]


</article>



<article><tid>1911617</tid>
<number>25</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Recovery of excess payments made by Central Government or 
Custodian. Any amount in excess of payments over receipts in the 
statement of accounts prepared under section 19 shall be deemed to be 
an amount advanced by the Central Government or the Custodian, as the 
case may be, for the management of a coal mine during the period in 
which the management of such coal mine remained vested in the Central 
Government and the Central Government may make a claim to the 
Commissioner for such excess payment and such claim shall have 
priority over the claims of all other unsecured creditors of the coal 
mine, including those referred to in sub- section (2) of section 22.
Explanation.-- In this section." Custodian" means the Custodian 
appointed under the Coal Mines (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> 
 (15 of <year>1973</year>).']

<pagefootnote><pagenum>351</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 15, ibid., (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 16, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>920242</tid>
<number> 25A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notice to owners of coal mines and managing contractors, 
etc.
<section><tid>1907136</tid>
<number>1</number>After meeting the liabilities of persons whose claims have  
been admitted under this act, the Commissioner shall notify, in such 
manner as he may think fit, the amount of money available with him and 
specify in such notification a date within which the owners of the 
coal mines, the managing contractors and the owners of any machinery, 
equipment or other property which has vested in the Central Government 
or a Government company under this Act and which does not belong to 
the owners of the coal mines may apply to him for payment.

</section>

<section><tid>362907</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any application is made under sub- section (1), the 
Commissioner shall, after satisfying himself as to the right of the 
applicant to receive the whole or any part of the amount, pay the 
amount to the person concerned and in the event of there being a doubt 
or dispute as to the right of the person to receive the whole or any 
part of the amount, the Commissioner shall deal with the application 
in the manner specified in sub- section (2) of section 26.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1167779</tid>
<number> 26</number> Disbursement of amounts to the owners of coal mines.
<section><tid>1346414</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
out of the monies paid to him in relation to a coal mine or group of 
coal mines specified in the second column of the Schedule, there is a 
balance left after meeting the liabilities of all the secured and 
unsecured creditors, the Commissioner shall disburse such balance to 
the owner of such coal mine or group of coal mines.

</section>

<section><tid>58705</tid>
<number>2</number>Before making any payment to the owner of any coal mine or 
group of coal mines under sub- section (1), the Commissioner shall 
satisfy himself as to the right of such person to receive the whole or 
any part of such amount, and in the event of there being a doubt or 
dispute as to the right of the person to receive the whole or any part 
of the amount, referred to in sections 8 and 9, the Commissioner
<pagefootnote><pagenum>352</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall refer the matter to the court and make the disbursement in 
accordance with the decision of the court.


</section>

<section><tid>297066</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
entries in the fourth column of the Schedule shall not be deemed to be 
conclusive as to the right, title and interest of any person in 
relation to any coal mine specified in the corresponding entires in 
the second column of the Schedule and evidence shall be admissible to 
establish the right, title and interest of any person in relation to 
such coal mine.

</section>

<section><tid>30640</tid>
<number>4</number>In relation to a coal mine the operations of which were, 
immediately before the taking over of the management of such coal mine 
under the Coal Mines (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1973</year> (15 of  
  <year>1973</year>), under the control of a managing contractor, the amount 
specified in the fifth column of the Schedule against such coal mine 
shall be apportioned between the owner of the coal mine and such 
managing contractor in such proportions as may be agreed upon by or 
between the owner and such managing contractor, and in the event of 
there being no such agreement, in such proportions as may be 
determined by the court on a reference made to it by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>712825</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any machinery, equipment or other property in a coal 
mine has vested in the Central Government or a Government company 
under this Act, but such machinery, equipment or other property does 
not belong to the owner of such coal mine, the amount specified in the 
fifth column of the Schedule against such coal mine shall, on a 
reference made to it by the Commissioner, be apportioned by the court 
between the owner of such coal mine and the owner of such machinery, 
equipment or other property having due regard to the value of such 
machinery, equipment or other property on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>746435</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the amount specified in the fifth column of the 
Schedule is relatable to a group of coal mines, the Commissioner shall 
have power to apportion such amount among the owners of such group, 
and in making such apportionment, the Commissioner shall have regard 
to the highest annual production in the coal mine during the three 
years immediately preceding the appointed day.]
Explanation.-- In this section," court", in relation to a coal 
mine, means the principal civil court of original jurisdiction within 
the local limits of whose jurisdiction the coal mine is situated.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1458899</tid>
<number>27</number>Undisbursed of unclaimed amounts to be deposited to the 
general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which 
remains undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> three years from 
the day on which the last order for disbursement was made], shall be 
transferred by the Commissioner to the general revenue account of the 
Central Government; but a claim to any money so transferred may be 
preferred to the Central Government by the person entitled to
<pagefootnote><pagenum>353</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 57 of <year>1986</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1973</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 18, for certain words (w. e. f. 27- 5-  
  <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such payment and shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been 
made, the order, if any, for payment of the claim being treated as an 
order for the refund of revenue.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1984499</tid>
<number>28</number>Effect of this Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, or 
in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1050553</tid>
<number> 29</number> Contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by 
Government.
<section><tid>1215252</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract entered into by the owner or occupier  
of any coal mine for any service, sale or supply and in force 
immediately before the appointed day shall, on and from the expiry of 
one hundred and twenty days from the appointed day, cease to have 
effect unless such contract is, before the expiry of that period, 
ratified, in writing, by the Central Government and in ratifying such 
contract the Central Government may make such alterations or 
modifications therein as it may think fit:
Provided that the Central Government shall not omit to ratify a 
contract unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly onerous 
or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the 
interests of the coal mine.


</section>

<section><tid>246849</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall not omit to ratify a contract or 
make any alteration or modification therein except after giving to the 
parties to the contract a reasonable opportunity of being heard and 
except after recording in writing its reasons for refusal to ratify 
the contract.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1914327</tid>
<number> 30</number> Penalties. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>39850</tid>
<number>1</number>] Any person who,-- 

<subsection><tid>542278</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of the undertaking of any coal 
mine referred to in the Schedule wrongfully withholds 
such property from the Central Government or the 
Government company, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>354</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 30 was renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 67 
of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>544917</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any 
property forming part of the undertaking of any coal 
mine specified in the Schedule or wilfully withholds or 
fails to furnish to the Central Government or any 
person specified by that Government, any document 
relating to such coal mine which may be in his 
possession, custody or control or fails to deliver to 
the Custodian any assets, books of account, registers 
or other documents in his custody relating to the coal 
mine in respect of which a Custodian has been 
appointed, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1123824</tid>
<number>c</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property of any coal 
mine or prefers any claim under this Act which he knows 
or has reasonable cause to believe to be false or 
grossly inaccurate,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>202920</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any person who engages, or causes any other person to be 
engaged, in winning or mining coal from the whole or part of any land 
in respect of which no valid prospecting licence or mining lease or 
sub- lease is in force, shall be punishable <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to three years and also with fine which may 
extend to twenty thousand rupees.].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1920077</tid>
<number> 31</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>525040</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1053487</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any
<pagefootnote><pagenum>355</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 67 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 27- 5- <year>1976</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1978</year>, s. 19, for certain words (w. e. f. 27- 5-  
  <year>1978</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>36076</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1637393</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1883519</tid>
<number>32</number>Mining companies not to be wound up by the court. No 
proceeding for the winding up of a mining company, the right, title 
and interest in relation to the coal mine owned by which have vested 
in the Central Government or a Government company under this Act or 
for the appointment of a receiver in respect of the business of the 
company, shall lie in any court except with the consent of the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>687123</tid>
<number> 33</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>1422747</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act may also be exercised by any person or persons as may 
be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1340305</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1237145</tid>
<number> 34</number> 
<section><tid>1133811</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification, make rules  
to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>693874</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>490435</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the coal mine shall be managed by a 
Government company or a Custodian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312102</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which monies in any provident or other 
fund referred to in section 15 shall be dealt with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>283140</tid>
<number>c</number>the form and manner in which the statement of accounts 
referred to in section 19 shall be prepared;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472094</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>356</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1090390</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or successive sessions aforesaid, 
both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1155499</tid>
<number>35</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the appointed day.


</article>



 </act>