<act><title>THE TRANSPLANTATION OF HUMAN ORGANS RULES, 19951</title> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 19951
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Transplantation of Human Organs Act, 1994 (42 of 1994); 
 
 




</section><section><number>b</number> “Form” means a Form annexed to these Rules; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> “National Accreditation Board for Laboratories” (NABL) means a Board set up by the Quality Council of India (set up by the Government of India) for undertaking assessment and accreditation of testing and calibration of laboratories in accordance with the international standard ISO/IEC 17025 and ISO 15189;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>e</number> the Registered Medical Practitioner, as defined in clause (n) of  
    section 2 of Transplantation of Human Organs Act, 1994 includes an allopathic doctor with MBBS or equivalent degree under the Medical Council of India Act;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>f</number>] words and expressions used and not defined in these Rules, but defined in the Act, shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section></article> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
  
 <article><number>3</number> Authority for Removal of 
Human Organ.—Any donor may authorise 
the removal, before his death, of any human organ of his body for therapeutic 
purposes in the manner and on such conditions as specified in Form 1.
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Duties of the Medical Practitioner. </title>— <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> A registered medical practitioner shall, before removing a human organ from the body of a donor before his death, satisfy himself— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that the donor has given his authorization in appropriate Form 1(A) or 1(B) or 1(C); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that the donor is in proper state of health and is fit to donate the organ, and the registered medical practitioner shall sign a certificate as specified in Form 2; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> that the donor is a near relative of the recipient, as certified in 
    Form 3, who has signed Form 1(A) or 1(B) as applicable to the donor and that the donor has submitted an application in Form 10 jointly with the recipient and that the proposed donation has been approved by the concerned competent authority and that the necessary documents as prescribed and medical tests, if required, to determine the factum of near relationship, have been examined to the satisfaction of the registered medical practitioner, i.e., Incharge of transplant centre; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> that in case the recipient is spouse of the donor, the donor has given a statement to the effect that they are so related by signing a certificate in Form 1(B) and has submitted an application in Form 10 jointly with the recipient and that the proposed donation has been approved by the concerned competent authority under provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 4A; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in case of a donor who is other than a near relative and has signed Form 1(C) and submitted an application in Form 10 jointly with the recipient, the permission from the Authorisation Committee for the said donation has been obtained.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> A registered medical practitioner shall, before removing a human organ from the body of a person after his death, satisfy himself— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that the donor had, in the presence of two or more witnesses (at least one of whom is a near relative of such person), unequivocally authorised as specified in Form 5 before his death, the removal of the human organ of his body, after his death, for therapeutic purposes and there is no reason to believe that the donor had subsequently revoked the authority aforesaid; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>b</number> that the person lawfully in possession of the dead body has signed a certificate as specified in Form 6.] 
 </subsection>




</section><section><number>3</number> A registered medical practitioner shall, before removing a human organ from the body of a person in the event of his brain-stem death, satisfy himself— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that a certificate as specified in Form 8 has been signed by all the members of the Board of medical experts referred to in sub-section (6) of section 3 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that in the case of brain-stem death of a person of less than eighteen years of age, a certificate specified in Form 8 has been signed by all the members of the Board of medical experts referred to in sub-section (6) of section 3 of the Act and an authority as specified in Form 9 has been signed by either of the parents of such person. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Authorisation Committee. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The medical practitioner who will be part of the organ transplantation team for carrying out transplantation operation shall not be a member of the Authorisation Committee constituted under the provisions of clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-section (4) of section 9 of the Act. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where the proposed transplantation is between a married couple, the Registered Medical Practitioner,  i.e., Incharge of transplant centre must evaluate the factum and duration of marriage and ensure that documents such as marriage certificate, marriage photograph, etc., are kept for records along with the information on the number and age of children and family photograph depicting the entire immediate family, birth certificates of children containing particulars of parents. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> When the proposed donor or recipient or both are not Indian Nationals/citizens whether “near relatives” or otherwise, Authorisation Committees shall consider all such requests. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> When the proposed donor and the recipient are not “near relatives”, as defined under clause (i) of section 2 of the Act, the Authorisation Committee shall evaluate that,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> there is no commercial transaction between the recipient and the donor and that no payment or money or moneys worth as referred to in the Act, has been made to the donor or promised to be made to the donor or any other person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the following shall specifically be assessed by the Authorisation Committee:— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> an explanation of the link between them and the circumstances which led to the offer being made; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> reasons why the donor wishes to donate; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> documentary evidence of the link, e.g.,  proof that they have lived together, etc.; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> old photographs showing the donor and the recipient together; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> that there is no middleman or tout involved; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> that financial status of the donor and the recipient is probed by asking them to give appropriate evidence of their vocation and income for the previous three financial years. Any gross disparity between the status of the two must be evaluated in the backdrop of the objective of preventing commercial dealing; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> that the donor is not a drug addict or known person with criminal record; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> that the next of the kin of the proposed unrelated donor is interviewed regarding awareness about his or her intention to donate an organ, the authenticity of the link between the donor and the recipient and the reasons for donation. Any strong views or disagreement or objection of such kin shall also be recorded and taken note of.] 
</subsection>



</section></article> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
  
 <article><number>5</number> Preservation of Organs.—The 
organ removed shall be preserved according to current and accepted scientific 
methods in order to ensure viability for the purpose of transplantation.
 

1[Provided that the eye ball removed 
shall be preserved in the following three steps, namely:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>   short-term preservation;
 </section><section>       <number>ii</number>   medium-term preservation;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   long-term preservation,
 and suitable media shall be used for preservation.]
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6</number> </title>The donor and the recipient shall make jointly an application to grant approval for removal and transplantation of a human organ, to the concerned competent authority or Authorisation Committee as specified in Form 10. The Authorisation Committee shall take a decision on such application in accordance with the guidelines in the rule 6A.] 
  



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6A</number> Composition of Authorisation Committees. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be one State level Authorisation Committee. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Additional authorisation committees may be set up at various levels as per norms given below, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> no member from transplant team of the institution should be a member of the respective Authorisation Committee. All Foreign Nationals (related and unrelated) should go to “Authorisation Committee” as abundant precaution needs to be taken in such cases; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Authorisation Committee should be Hospital based in Metro and big cities if the number of transplants exceed 25 in a year at the respective transplantation centres. In smaller towns, there are State or District level Committees if transplants are less than 25 in a year in the respective districts. 
 
 <subsubsection><number>A</number> Composition of Hospital Based Authorisation Committees: (To be constituted by the State Government and in case of Union territory by the Central Government). 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> the senior most person officiating as Medical Director or Medical Superintendent of the Hospital; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> two senior medical practitioners from the same hospital who are not part of the transplant team; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number> two members being persons of high integrity, social standing and credibility, who have served in high ranking Government positions, such as in higher judiciary, senior cadre of police service or who have served as a reader or professor in University Grants Commission approved University or are self-employed professionals of repute such as lawyers, chartered accountants and doctors (of Indian Medical Association), etc.; and 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>d</number> Secretary (Health) or nominee and Director Health Services or nominee. 
</subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>B</number> Composition of State or District Level Authorisation Committees: (To be constituted by the State Government and in case of Union territory by the Central Government). 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> a Medical Practitioner officiating as Chief Medical Officer or any other equivalent post in the main/major Government Hospital of the District; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> two senior medical practitioners to be chosen from the pool of such medical practitioners who are residing in the concerned District and who are not part of any transplant team; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number> two senior citizens, non-medical background (one lady) of high reputation and integrity to be chosen from the pool of such citizens residing in the same district, who have served in high ranking Government positions, such as in higher judiciary, senior cadre of police service or who have served as a reader or professor in University Grants Commission approved University or are self-employed professionals of repute such as lawyers, chartered accountants and doctors (of Indian Medical Association), etc.; and 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>d</number> Secretary (Health) or nominee and Director Health Services or nominee; 
</subsubsubsection>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 ( <title>Note. </title>—Effort should be made to have most of the members' ex-officio so that the need to change the composition of committee is less frequent.). 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6B</number> </title>The State level committees shall be formed for the purpose of providing approval or no objection certificate to the respective donor and recipient to establish the legal and residential status as a domicile State. It is mandatory that if donor, recipient and place of transplantation are from different States, then the approval or “no-objection Certificate” from the respective domicile State Government should be necessary. The institution where the transplant is to be undertaken in such case the approval of Authorisation Committee is mandatory.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6C</number> </title>The quorum of the Authorisation Committee should be minimum four. However, quorum ought not to be considered as complete without the participation of the Chairman. The presence of Secretary (Health) or nominee and Director of Health Services or nominee is mandatory.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6D</number> </title>The format of the Authorisation Committee approval should be uniform in all the institutions in a State. The format may be notified by respective State Government.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6E</number> </title>Secretariat of the Committee shall circulate copies of all applications received from the proposed donors to all members of the Committee. Such applications should be circulated along with all annexures, which may have been filed along with the applications. At the time of the meeting, the Authorisation Committee should take note of all relevant contents and documents in the course of its decision making process and in the event any document or information is found to be inadequate or doubtful, explanation should be sought from  
the applicant and if it is considered necessary that any fact or information requires to be verified in order to confirm its veracity or correctness, the same be ascertained through the concerned officer(s) of the State/Union Territory Government.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>6F</number> </title>The Authorisation Committee shall focus its attention on the following, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Where the proposed transplant is between persons related genetically, Mother, Father, (Brother, Sister, Son or Daughter above the age of 18 years) the concerned competent authority shall evaluate— (i) results of tissue typing and other basic tests; 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> documentary evidence of relationship, e.g., relevant birth certificates and marriage certificate, certificate from Sub-Divisional Magistrate/Metropolitan Magistrate/or Sarpanch of the Panchayat; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> documentary evidence of identity and residence of the proposed donor, e.g.,  Ration Card or Voters Identity Card or Passport or Driving Licence or PAN Card or Bank Account and family photograph depicting the proposed donor and the proposed recipient along with another near relative; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> if in its opinion, the relationship is not conclusively established after evaluating the above evidence, it may in its discretion direct further medical tests as prescribed below: 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>a</number> the tests for Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA), Human Leukocyte Antigen-B alleles to be performed by the serological and/or Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) based Deoxyribonucleic Acid (DNA) methods. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> test for Human Leukocyte Antigen-DR beta genes to be performed using the Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) based Deoxyribonucleic Acid (DNA), methods. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the teste referred to in sub-rules (i) and (ii) shall be got done from a laboratory accredited with National Accreditation Board for Laboratories (NABL). 
 </section><section><number>d</number> where the tests referred to in sub-rules (i) to (iii) above do not establish a genetic relationship between the donor and the recipient, the same tests to be performed on both or at least one parent, preferably both parents. If parents are hot available, same tests to be performed on such relatives of donor and recipient as are available and are willing to be tested failing which, genetic relationship between the donor and the recipient will be deemed to have not been established. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> The papers for approval of transplantation would be processed by the registered medical practitioner and administrative division of the Institution for transplantation, while the approval will be granted by the Authorisation Committee. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Where the proposed transplant is between a married couple (except foreigners, whose cases should be dealt by Authorisation Committee): 
 The concerned competent authority or Authorisation Committee, as the case may be, must evaluate all available evidence to establish the factum and duration of marriage and ensure that documents such as marriages certificate, marriage photograph is placed before the Committee along with the information on the number and age of children and a family photograph depicting the entire immediate family, birth certificates of children containing the particulars of parents. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Where the proposed transplant is between individuals who are not “near relatives”, the Authorization Committee shall evaluate)— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> that there is no commercial transaction between the recipient and the donor. That no payment of money or moneys worth as referred to in the Act, has been made to the donor or promised to be made to the donor or any other person. In this connection the Authorisation Committee shall take into consideration— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> an explanation of the link between them and the circumstances which led to the offer being made; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> documentary evidence of the link, e.g.,  proof that they have lived together, etc.; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> reasons why the donor wishes to donate; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> old photographs showing the donor and the recipient together. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> that there is no middleman or tout involved; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> that financial status of the donor and the recipient is probed by asking them to give appropriate evidence of their vocation and income for the previous three financial years. Any gross disparity between the status of the two, must be evaluated in the backdrop of the objective of preventing commercial dealing; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> that the donor is not a drug addict or a known person with criminal record; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> that the next of kin of the proposed unrelated donor is interviewed regarding awareness about his/her intention to donate an organ, the authenticity of the link between the donor and the recipient and the reasons for donation. Any strong views or disagreement or objection of such kin may also be recorded and taken note of; and 
 </subsection>
</section><section><number>e</number> When the proposed donor or the recipient or both are foreigners— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a senior Embassy official of the country of origin has to certify the relationship between the donor and the recipient; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Authorisation Committee shall examine the cases of Indian donors consenting to donate organs to a foreign national (who is a near relative), including a foreign national of Indian origin, with greater caution. Such cases should be considered rarely on case to case basis. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number> In the course, of determining eligibility of the applicant to donate, the applicant should be personally interviewed by the Authorisation Committee and minutes of the interview should be recorded. Such interviews with the donors should be videographed. 
 </section><section><number>g</number> In case where the donor is a woman greater precautions ought to be taken. Her identity and independent consent should be confirmed by a person other than the recipient. Any document with regard to the proof of residence or domicile and particulars of parentage should be relatable to the photo identity of the applicant in order to ensure that the documents pertain to the same person, who is the proposed donor and in the event of any inadequate or doubtful information to this effect, the Authorisation Committee may in its discretion seek such other information or evidence as may be expedient and desirable in the peculiar facts of the case. 
 </section><section><number>h</number> The Authorisation Committee should state in writing its reason for rejecting/approving the application of the proposed donor and all approvals should be subject to the following conditions:— 
 
 
 </section><section><number>i</number> that the approved proposed donor would be subjected to all such medical tests as required at the relevant stages to determine his biological capacity and compatibility to donate the organ in question. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> further that the psychiatrist clearance would also be mandatory to certify his mental condition, awareness, absence of any overt or latent psychiatric disease and ability to give free consent. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> all prescribed forms have been and would be filled up by all relevant persons involved in the process of transplantation. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> all interviews to be video recorded. 
</subsection></section><section><number>i</number> The Authorisation Committee shall expedite its decision making process and use its discretion judiciously and pragmatically in all such cases where the patient requires immediate transplantation. 
 </section><section><number>j</number> Every authorised transplantation centre must have its own website. The Authorisation Committee is required to take final decision within 24 hours of holding the meeting for grant of permission or rejection for transplant. The decision of the Authorisation Committee should be displayed on the notice board of the hospital or institution immediately and should reflect on the website of the hospital or institution within 24 hours of taking the decision. Apart from this, the website of the hospital or institution must update its website regularly in respect of the total number of the transplantations done in that hospital or institution along with the details of each transplantation. The same data should be accessible for compilation, analysis and further use by respective State Governments and Central Government.] 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Registration of Hospital. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An application for registration shall be made to the Appropriate Authority as specified in Form 11. The application shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees one thousand payable to the Appropriate Authority by means of a bank draft or postal order. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Appropriate Authority shall, after holding an inquiry and after satisfying itself that the applicant has complied with all the requirements, grant a certificate of registration as specified in Form 12 and shall be valid for a period of five years from the date of its issue and shall be renewable. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum></title>[<number>3</number> Before a hospital is registered under the provisions of this rule, it shall be mandatory for the hospital to nominate a transplant coordinator.] 



</section></article> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
  
 <article><number>8</number> Renewal of Registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for the renewal of a certificate of registration shall be made to 
the Appropriate Authority within a period of three months prior to the date of 
expiry of the original certificate of registration and shall be accompanied by a 
fee of rupees five hundred payable to the Appropriate Authority by means of a 
bank draft or postal order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A renewal certificate of 
registration shall be as specified in Form 13 and shall be valid for a period of 
five years.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If, after an inquiry 
including inspection of the hospital and scrutiny of its past performance and 
after giving an opportunity to the applicant, the Appropriate Authority is 
satisfied that the applicant, since grant of certificate of registration under 
sub-rule (2) of Rule 7 has not complied with the requirements of this Act and 
the Rules made thereunder and conditions subject to which the certificate of 
registration has been granted, shall, for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
refuse to grant renewal of the certificate of registration.
</section></article> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
  
 <article><number>9</number> Conditions for grant of 
Certificate of Registration.—No 
hospital shall be granted a certificate of registration under this Act unless it 
fulfils the following requirement of manpower, equipment, specialised services 
and facilities as laid down below:—
 General Requirement
 <section><number>1</number>  Surgical Staff
 </section><section><number>2</number>  Cardiology Staff
 </section><section><number>3</number>  Nursing Staff
 </section><section><number>4</number>  Communication System
 </section><section><number>5</number>  Intensivist
 </section><section><number>6</number>  Medical Social Worker
 </section><section><number>7</number>  Perfusionist.
 

1[8.          Ophthalmologist
 </section></article><article><number>9</number>  Corneal Surgeons.]
 Various Departments
 <section><number>1</number>  Microbiology
 </section><section><number>2</number>  Mycology
 </section><section><number>3</number>  Pathology
 </section><section><number>4</number>  Virology
 </section><section><number>5</number>  Nephrology
 </section><section><number>6</number>  Neurology
 </section><section><number>7</number>  Psychology
 </section><section><number>8</number>  G.I. Surgery
 </section></article><article><number>9</number>  Anaesthesiology
 </article><article><number>10</number> Imaging Facilities
 </article><article><number>11</number> Paediatrics
 </article><article><number>12</number> Physiotherapy
 </article><article><number>13</number> Immunology
 </article><article><number>14</number> Haematology
 </article><article><number>15</number> Blood Bank
 </article><article><number>16</number> Clinical Chemistry
 </article><article><number>17</number> Cardiology.
 </article><article>

1[<number>18</number> Department of Ophthalmology.]
 Non-transplantation Programme Team
 <section><number>1</number>  Neurologist
 </section><section><number>2</number>  Neurosurgeon
 </section><section><number>3</number>  Medical Superintendent
 </section><section><number>4</number>  And Other Hospital Staff.
 

1[5.          Eye Donation Counsellor/Grief 
Counsellor.]
 Basic Equipment
 

2[1.]        Operating Room facilities 
for routine open heart surgery which includes heart lung machine and 
accessories.
 

1[2. Slit Lamp
 </section><section><number>3</number> Specular Microscope
 </section><section><number>4</number> Operating Microscope]
 Additional Equipment Required for Transplantation Programme
 </section><section><number>1</number> Cell Saver.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Assist devices like IABP, 
Centrifugal Pump and various assist devices, both pneumatic and electric 
operated.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Mobile C-arm, image 
intensifier for routine biopsies in the sterile operating room.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Eact/Alert System for early 
detection of any infection.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Radioimmunoassy for measuring 
Cyclosporin levels.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Routine Laboratory facilities 
for detection of HIV, Australia antigen, CMV, Toxoplasnosis and other Mycology 
Tests.
 

1[7. Autoclave (mandatory)
 </section><section><number>8</number> U. V. Lamp
 </section><section><number>9</number> Laminor Flow
 Experts
 <subsection><number>A</number> Kidney Transplantation
 </subsection><subsection><number>M</number>S. (Gen.) Surgery or 
equivalent qualification with three years post M.S. training in a recognised 
centre in India or abroad and having attended to adequate number of renal 
transplantation as an active member of team.
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> Transplantation of liver and 
other abdominal organs
 </subsection><subsection><number>M</number>S. (Gen.) Surgery or 
equivalent qualification with adequate post M.S. training in an established 
centre with a reasonable experience of performing liver transplantation as an 
active member of team.
 </subsection><subsection><number>C</number> Cardiac, Pulmonary, 
Cardio-Pulmonary Transplantation
 </subsection><subsection><number>M</number> Ch. Cardio-thorasic and 
vascular surgery or equivalent qualification in India or abroad with at least 3 
years experience as an active member of the team performing an adequate number 
of open heart operations per year and well-versed with Coronary by-pass surgery 
and Heart-valve surgery.
  



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
  
 <article><number>10</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by an order of the Authorisation Committee under 
sub-section (6) of section 9, or by an order of the Appropriate Authority under 
sub-section (2) of section 15 and section 16 of the Act, may, within thirty days 
from the date of receipt of the order, prefer an appeal to the Central 
Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal shall be in 
writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against.
</section></article><form>
 

The Transplantation of Human Organs Rules, 1995
 

 
 

Form 1
 

(See rule 3)
 

I,................................, 
aged................................s/o, d/o, w/o Shri 
.................................... resident of 
............................................. hereby authorise to remove for 
therapeutic purposes/consent to donate my organ, namely, 
.............................................to
 

(i) Shri/Smt./Km. 
..............................................s/o, d/o, w/o Shri. 
.................................. aged 
..................................resident of 
.................................................................................... 
who happens to be my near relative as defined in clause (i) of section 2 of the 
Act.
 

OR
 

(ii) Shri/Smt./Km...........................................s/o, 
d/o, w/o Shri......................................... 
aged...................................resident of 
............................................................................................ 
towards whom I possess special affection or attachments, or for any special 
reason (to be specified).
 

I certify that the above authority/consent has been given by 
me out of my own free will without any undue pressure, inducement, influence or 
allurement and that the purposes of the above authority/donation and of all 
possible complications, side-effects, consequences and options have been 
explained to me before giving this authority or consent or both.
 

Signature of the Donor
</form><form>
 

THE TRANSPLANTATION OF HUMAN ORGANS RULES, 1995
 

 
 

1[***]
 

--------
 

1. Ed. FORM 4 which was related to rule 4(1)(d) stands deleted as the said rule 4(1)(d) has been amended vide G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).
</form><form>
 

THE TRANSPLANTATION OF HUMAN ORGANS RULES, 1995
 

 
 

1[***]
 

--------
 

1. Form 7 omitted by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).
</form><form>
 

THE TRANSPLANTATION OF HUMAN ORGANS RULES, 19951
 

 
 

Form 9 
 

[ See rule 4(3)(b)] 
 

I, Shri/Smt. .................................................., S/o, W/o Shri ................................................  

  resident of ........................................hereby authorise removal of the organ/organs, namely, ...........................................................for therapeutic purpose from the deadbody of my son/daughter Shri/Km. .................................................. aged .................................................whose brain-stem death has been duly certified in accordance with the law. 
 

Signature ................................................... 
 

Name ......................................................... 
 

Place...................................... 
 

Date....................................... 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>Clause (d) renumbered as clause (f) thereof by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 
  4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 571(E), dated 31st July, 2008 (w.e.f. 4-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Existing entry 
numbered as entry 1 by G.S.R. 266(E), dated 8th April, 2002 (w.e.f. 9-4-2002).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>