<act> 
 The Research and Development cess Act, 1986
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Research and Development Cess Act, 1986.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on 
such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
  



</section></article> 
 The Research and Development cess Act, 1986
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
1[
<section><number>a</number>  
“Board” means the Technology Development Board constituted under the Technology 
Development Board Act, 1995 (44 of 1995);
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>  “cess” means the cess levied under section 3;]
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>  “import”, in relation to any technology, means 
the bringing into India of, such technology from a place outside India;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>  “industrial concern” has the meaning assigned 
to it in clause (c) of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank of India 
Act, 1964  
(18 of 1964), and includes any other person in whose favour a foreign 
collaboration involving the import of technology
2[is 
approved or automatically approved in accordance with the Industrial Policy of 
the Government of India in force from time to time];
 </section><section>         <number>f</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act;
 </section><section>        <number>g</number>  “specified agency” means—
 <subsection>              <number>i</number>  the Reserve Bank of India constituted 
under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); or
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>ii</number>  the State Bank of India constituted under 
the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955); or
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>iii</number>  such other bank or institution as may be 
specified in this behalf by the Central Government;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>h</number>  “technology” means any special or technical 
knowledge or any special service required for any purpose whatsoever by an 
industrial concern under any foreign collaboration, and includes designs, 
drawings, publications and technical personnel.
  




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Levy and 
    collection of cess on payments made towards import of technology.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be levied and collected, for the purposes of this Act, a cess at 
    such rate not exceeding five per cent. on all payments made towards the 
    import of technology, as the Central Government may, from time to time, 
    specify, by notification, in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The cess shall be 
    payable to the Central Government by an industrial concern which imports 
    technology on or before making any payments towards such import and shall be 
    paid by the industrial concern to any specified agency.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Crediting 
    proceeds of cess to Consolidated Fund of India.—The 
    proceeds of the cess levied and collected under section 3 shall first be 
    credited to the Consolidated Fund  of India and the Central Government 
    may, if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this behalf so provides, 
    pay to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Board], from time to time, from out of such proceeds 
    (after deducting the cost of collection), such sums of money as it may think 
    fit for being utilised for the purposes of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Board].
 

 








 



</article> 
 The Research and Development cess Act, 1986
  
 <article><number>5</number> Venture Capital Fund.—[Repealed 
by Act 45 of 1995, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
1-9-1996).]
  
</article> 
 The Research and Development cess Act, 1986
  
 <article><number>6</number> Application of Fund.—[Repealed 
by Act 45 of 1995, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
1-9-1996).]
  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of Central 
    Government to exempt.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is satisfied that 
    it is necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette and subject to such conditions, if any, 
    as may be specified therein, exempt any industrial concern from the payment 
    of the cess payable under this Act for the import of such technology as may 
    be specified in such notification.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to call for 
    information.—The 
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Board] 
    may require an industrial concern to furnish, for the purposes of this Act, 
    such statistical and other information in such form and within such period 
    as may be prescribed.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Penalty for 
    non-payment of cess.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
    cess payable by an industrial concern is not paid on or before making 
    payments towards the import of technology, it shall be deemed to be in 
    arrears and the same shall be recovered by the 
1[Board] 
    in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Board] 
    may, after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on the industrial concern, 
    which is in arrears under sub-section (l), a penalty not exceeding ten times 
    the amount in arrears:
 
Provided that before 
    imposing such penalty, such industrial concern shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard, and if, after such hearing, the 
1[Board] 
    is satisfied that the default was for any good and sufficient reason, no 
    penalty shall be imposed under this sub-section.
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 
The 
    Research and Development Cess Act, 1986
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power to make 
    rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out 
    the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
    without prejudice to the foregoing power, such rules may provide for the 
    following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
               
    <number>a</number>    the form in which and the period within which the 
    information under section 8 may be furnished;
 </subsection><subsection>
               
    <number>b</number>    the manner in which the arrears of cess may be 
    recovered under sub-section (1) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection>
               
    <number>c</number>    any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
    prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made 
    under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of  no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act, 
    45 of 1995, sec. 3, for "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act, 
    45 of 1995, sec. 3, for "Fund" (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by Act 45 
    of 1995, sec. 5, for "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 45 
    of 1995, sec. 5, for "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>