<act><title>


The Industrial Development Bank of India 
    (Appeal to the Central Government) Rules, 19951</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Industrial Development Bank of India (Appeal to the 
    Central Government) Rules, 1995.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Industrial Development 
    Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “authorised representative” means,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in relation to an appellant, a person 
    duly authorised by the appellant to present an appeal on his behalf to the 
    Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in relation to the Board, a person 
    duly appointed by the Board by resolution as authorised representative to 
    appear, plead and Act for the Board in any appeal under these rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    in relation to any other party to the 
    appeal, a person duly authorised by such party to appear, plead and Act on 
    his behalf;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Board” means the Board of Directors of 
    the Development Bank constituted under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the 
    Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Development Bank” means the Industrial 
    Development Bank of India established under section 3 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Form” means the form appended to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “party” means a person who files an 
    appeal before the Central Government and the respondent;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “Rules” means rules made under the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    other expressions which are not defined 
    here shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Form of 
    appeal.—Every appeal under 
    sub-section (3) of section 13D of the Act shall be preferred by any person 
    aggrieved by an order of refusal of the Board made under sub-section (2) of 
    section 13D, to the Central Government in the Form.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Time 
    within appeal is to be preferred.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An appeal shall be preferred by the aggrieved person within a period of 
    thirty days from the date of communication to him of the order of refusal of 
    the Board made under sub-section (2) of section 13D of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the 
    appeal is preferred after the expiry of the period of thirty days specified 
    sub-rule (1), it shall be accompanied by an application supported by an 
    affidavit setting forth the facts on which the appellant relies to satisfy 
    the Central Government that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the 
    appeal within the said period of 30 days:  
 
Provided that 
    if the Central Government is satisfied that the appellant had sufficient 
    cause for not preferring the appeal within the aforesaid period, it may, for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing, admit the appeal after the expiry of the 
    aforesaid period but before the expiry of forty-five days from the date of 
    communication to him of the order of refusal of the Board.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Payment 
    of fees.—
<section><number>1</number> Every memorandum of 
    appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 500.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount 
    of fees shall be deposited by means of a challan with any branch of the 
    State Bank of India under the head,—  
 
        
    0070—Other administrative service  
 
        
    60—Other services  
 
        
    800—Other receipts  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Contents 
    of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every appeal filed 
    under rule 3 shall be written in English or Hindi and shall set forth 
    concisely under distinct heads, the grounds of appeal which shall be 
    numbered consecutively.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    appeal shall be filed in the Form in duplicate and shall be accompanied by a 
    certified copy of the order of refusal of the Board appealed against, 
    affidavit and other documents to support the grounds of appeal.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Rights to 
    representation.—
<section><number>1</number> An appellant 
    and every other party to the appeal may appear before the Central Government 
    in person or through their authorised representatives.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    shall be represented before the Central Government through its authorised 
    representative.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Authorisation empowering a person to Act as an authorised representative 
    shall be filed with the Central Government before the commencement of the 
    hearing of the appeal.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Procedure 
    for filing appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> An appeal 
    shall be preferred either by the appellant in person or his authorised 
    representative to the Central Government and the same shall be addressed to 
    the Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Economic Affairs, 
    Ministry of Finance, New Delhi, by registered post.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal 
    under sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been preferred to the Central 
    Government on the date on which it is received in the office of the 
    Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Economic Affairs, 
    Ministry of Finance, New Delhi.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Furnishing of information/documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, before considering the appeal, require any party 
    to the appeal to furnish such further information and documents as it 
    considers necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The parties 
    shall furnish such information and documents within 30 days of such order or 
    such further period as may be granted by the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Date and 
    place of hearing of appeal to be communicated.—The 
    Central Government shall communicate, before considering the appeal, to the 
    parties concerned, the date and place of the hearing of the appeal and shall 
    also send a notice of the Board either before or with such communication.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Hearing 
    of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> On the day fixed or 
    on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the appellant shall 
    be heard in support of the appeal. The Central Government shall then, if 
    necessary, hear the authorised representative of the Board and any other 
    party to the appeal and in such case the appellant shall be entitled to 
    reply.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case the 
    appellant does not appear in person or through an authorised representative 
    when the appeal is called for hearing, the Central Government may dismiss 
    the appeal for default:  
 
Provided that 
    if the appellant on an application satisfies the Central Government, that 
    there was sufficient cause for his non-appearance when the appeal was called 
    for hearing, the Central Government shall make an order setting aside the 
    ex parte order and restore the appeal.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Orders 
    by the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may after considering the appeal and making such further 
    enquiry as it considers necessary, either dismiss the appeal, or—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    pass an order directing that the 
    transfer of shares shall be registered by the Board and the Board shall 
    comply with such order within thirty days of the receipt of the order; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    pass an order directing the 
    rectification of the register of the shareholders of the Development Bank; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    in its discretion, pass such others 
    orders as it may deem fit and just.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The order 
    passed under sub-rule (1) above shall be in writing and shall be signed and 
    dated and shall be communicated to the concerned parties.  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Industrial Development Bank of India (Appeal to the Central Government) 
    Rules, 1995
 



 



Form
 



    Industrial Development Bank of India
 


(Appeal to the Central Government)
 


(See rule 3)
 


Form of Appeal
 


From:
 


(Mention the name and address of the appellant 
    here)
 


To,
 


The Secretary to the Government of India,
 


Department of Economic Affairs,
 


Ministry of Finance,
 


New Delhi.
 


Sir,
 


The appellant named above, begs to prefer this 
    appeal under sub-section (3) section 13D of the Industrial Development Bank 
    of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964), against order of refusal of the Board of 
    the Development Bank passed under the said Act on the following facts and 
    grounds.
 


Facts:
 


(Mention briefly the facts of the case here. 
    Enclose certified copy of the order of refusal of the Board, an affidavit 
    and copies of other relevant documents, if any).
 


Grounds:
 


(Mention here the grounds on which the appeal 
    is made).
 


Prayer:
 


In the light of what is stated above, the 
    appellant prays that he/she/ it may be granted the following relief:
 


Relief sought:
 


(Specify the relief sought)
 


The amount of Rs................as fees for 
    this appeal has been deposited, vide Challan 
    No...........dated.......................with................branch of the 
    State Bank of India.
 

 
 



    ................................................
 


(Signature of the appellant or 
 


his authorised representative)
 


 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>