<act><title>


The Petroleum Rules, 20021</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called The Petroleum Rules, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  “Act” means the Petroleum Act, 1934 (30 of 1934);
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  “adequate”,—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  in relation to ventilation, means where the concentration of the 
inflammable gas in a gas-air mixture does not reach the lower inflammable limit, 
or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  where applied to provision of facilities for fire-fighting, means the 
facilities so provided are in accordance with the prevalent recognized standards 
or codes of safety;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  “approved”,—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  where applied to specification, means that the specification 
authorised by the Chief Controller, including the following Oil Industry Safety 
Directorates Standards: OISD-105, OISD-116, OISD-117, OISD-118, OISD-141 and 
OISD-156;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  where applied to an appliance or fitting, means that the appliance or 
fitting bears a label of a designated testing organization certifying conformity 
with a specification approved by the Chief Controller or with a laboratory test 
report accepted by the Chief Controller; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  where applied to any facility for petroleum, means that it conforms to 
these rules;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  “Chief Controller” means the Chief Controller of Explosives;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  “Controller” means Controller of Explosives and includes Joint Chief 
Controller of Explosives, Deputy Chief Controller of Explosives and Deputy 
Controller of Explosives;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  “competent person” means a person recognized by the Chief Controller 
to be a competent person, or a person who holds a certificate of competency for 
the job in respect of which competency is required from an institution 
recognized by the Chief Controller in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>vii</number>  “Conservator” includes any person acting under the authority of the 
officer or body of persons appointed to be Conservator of a port under section 7 
of the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908);
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>viii</number>  “container” means a receptacle for petroleum not exceeding 1,000 
litres in capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>ix</number>  “Defence Forces of the Union” includes General Reserve Engineering 
Forces under the Director-General, Border Roads, Assam Rifles, Central Reserve 
Police Force, Border Security Force and National Security Guard under the 
Ministry of Home Affairs and Special Security Bureau under the Cabinet 
Secretariat;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>x</number>  “District Authority” means—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  in towns having a Commissioner of Police, the Commissioner or a Deputy 
Commissioner of Police;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  in any other place, the District Magistrate;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       
<number>xi</number>  “District Magistrate” means and includes an Additional District 
Magistrate and in the States of Punjab and Haryana and in the Karaikal, Mahe and 
Yenam areas of the Union Territory of Pondicherry, also includes a 
Sub-divisional Magistrate;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      
<number>xii</number>  “electric apparatus” includes motors, starters, lamps, switches, 
junction boxes, fuses, cut-outs or any other appliance, equipment or fitting 
which operates on electricity;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      
<number>xiii</number>  “Form” means a Form in the First Schedule;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xiv</number>  “hot work” means any work which involves welding, burning, 
soldering, brazing sand blasting, chipping by spark-producing tools, use of 
certain power driven tools, non-flame proof electrical equipment or equipment 
with internal combustion engines and including any other work which is likely to 
produce sufficient heat, capable of igniting inflammable gases;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      
<number>xv</number>  “Inspector” means an officer authorized by the Central Government 
under sub-section (1) of section 13 of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xvi</number>  “installation” means any premises wherein any place has been 
specially prepared for the storage of petroleum in bulk, but does not include a 
well-head tank or a service station;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xvii</number>  “OISD” means “Oil Industry Safety Directorate” a technical body 
assisting the Safety Council constituted under the Ministry of Petroleum and 
Natural Gas;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xviii</number>  
“OISD Standard” means technical standards formulated by OISD and approved by 
Safety Council constituted under the Ministry of Petroleum and Natural Gas to 
ensure safety in Oil and Gas Industry, as amended from time to time; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xix</number>  “petroleum in bulk” means petroleum contained in a tank irrespective 
of the quantity of petroleum contained therein;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      
<number>xx</number>  “Protected Area” means the area necessary for the maintenance of the 
distance required under the conditions of the licence to be kept clear between 
any installation, service station or storage shed and any protected works;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xxi</number>  “Protected works” include—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  buildings in which persons dwell or assemble, docks, wharves, timber 
and coal yards, furnace, kiln or chimney and buildings or places used for 
storing petroleum or for any other purpose but does not include buildings or 
places forming part of an installation;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  any public road or a railway line which is used exclusively as an oil 
siding; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  overhead high-tension power lines;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xxii</number>  “Sampling officer” means an officer authorized by the Central 
Government under sub-section (1) of section 14 of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxiii</number>  
“Schedule” means a Schedule annexed to these rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxiv</number>  
“service station” means any premises specially prepared for the fuelling of 
motor vehicles and includes such places within the premises which have been 
specially approved by the licensing authority for the servicing of motor 
vehicles and for other purposes;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxv</number>  
“Storage Shed” means a building used for the storage of petroleum otherwise than 
in bulk, whether forming part of an installation or not, but does not include a 
building used for the storage of petroleum exempt from licence under section 7, 
8 or 9 of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxvi</number>  
“tank” means a receptacle for petroleum exceeding 1,000 litres in capacity;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxvii</number>  
“tank cart” means a hand-drawn or animal-drawn vehicle equipped with a tank;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxviii</number>  
“tank semi-trailer” means a tank trailer constructed in such a manner that when 
it is drawn by a tractor by means of fifth wheel connection, some part of the 
load rests on the towing vehicle;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxix</number>  
“tank trailer” means a vehicle with a tank mounted thereon or built as integral 
part thereof and constructed in such a manner that it has at least two axles and 
all its load rests on its own wheels;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     
<number>xxx</number>  “tank truck” means a single self-propelled vehicle with a tank 
mounted thereon;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxxi</number>  
“tank vehicle” means any vehicle, including a tank wagon with a tank of a 
capacity exceeding 1,000 litres mounted thereon and also includes refueller used 
for refuelling of air crafts or onsite fuelling of heavy 
vehicles/machineries/stationery equipments;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxii</number>  
“tank wagon” means a railway carriage with a tank mounted thereon;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxiii</number>  
“Testing officer” means an officer authorised by the Central Government to test 
petroleum under section 17 of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xxxiv</number>  
“vehicle” means all carriages, including animal-drawn carriages for the 
transportation of petroleum either in bulk or otherwise than in bulk;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxv</number>  
“well-head tank” means a tank into which crude petroleum flowing or being pumped 
from an oil well is first discharged.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The words and 
expressions used in these rules but not defined in sub-rule (1), shall have the 
respective meanings assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Restriction on 
delivery and dispatch of petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person, shall deliver or dispatch any petroleum to anyone in India other than 
the holder of a storage licence issued under these rules or his authorized agent 
or a port authority or railway administration or a person who is authorized 
under the Act to store petroleum without a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The petroleum 
delivered or dispatched under sub-rule (1) shall be of the class, and shall not 
exceed the quantity, which the person to whom it is delivered or dispatched is 
authorised to store with or without a licence under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2) petroleum Class B not exceeding 15,000 litres 
in quantity packed in sealed airtight approved containers may be dispatched to a 
person not holding a storage licence provided that the person dispatching the 
petroleum has satisfied himself that prior arrangements have been made by the 
person to whom the petroleum is dispatched for the immediate disposal in the 
original sealed packages or such quantity as in excess of 2,500 litres:
 
Provided that a dry 
chemical powder fire extinguisher as a means of fighting fire in emergency shall 
be carried in the case of the containers with more than 2,500 litres.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in sub-rules 
(1) and (2) shall apply to the delivery or dispatch of petroleum to the Defence 
Forces of the Union and to the delivery or dispatch of kerosene (petroleum Class 
B) to the person holding licence in Form XVIII for decantation into containers 
from tank vehicle:
 
Provided that the person 
dispatching the kerosene has satisfied himself that prior arrangements have been 
made by the person to whom the kerosene is dispatched for the immediate disposal 
into containers in lots of 2,500 litres or less.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Approval of 
containers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Containers exceeding one litre in capacity for petroleum Class A and five litres 
in capacity for petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C, shall be of a type 
approved by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the approval of 
the Chief Controller is sought to a type of container not previously approved, 
an application together with copies of drawings thereof to scale showing the 
design, materials to be used, the method of construction and capacity of the 
container together with two sample containers and a fee of rupees one thousand 
for scrutiny shall be submitted to the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in sub-rules 
(1) and (2) shall apply to containers in the possession of the Defence Forces of 
the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Containers for 
petroleum Class A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Containers for petroleum Class A shall be constructed of tinned, galvanized or 
externally rust proofed sheet iron or steel and be of a type approved by the 
Chief Controller:
 
Provided that glass 
bottles of a capacity not exceeding 2.5 litres and of a type approved by Chief 
Controller can be used as a container for laboratory chemicals classified as 
petroleum Class “A”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The containers shall 
be so constructed and secured as not to be liable except under circumstances of 
gross negligence or extraordinary accident to become defective, leaky or 
insecure in transit and they shall be kept in proper repair.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The containers shall 
have well-made filling aperture which shall be fitted with well-fitting and 
secure air tight screw plugs or screw caps or other caps.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Containers made of 
sheet iron or steel shall have the following thickness of metal namely:—
 
 
Capacity of Container 
  exclusive of the                                   
  Minimum thickness in mm.
 
 
free space prescribed in 
  sub-rule (6)                                        
  of sheet iron or steel
 
Not exceeding 10 litres                                                               
0.443 (27 BG)
 
Exceeding 10 but not 
exceeding 25 litres                                        
0.63 (24 BG)
 
Exceeding 25 but not 
exceeding 50 litres                                        
0.80 (22 BG)
 
Exceeding 50 but not 
exceeding 200 litres                                      
1.25 (18 BG)
 
 
Exceeding 200 but not 
  exceeding 300 litres                                     
  1.59 (16 BG)
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The capacity of any 
container, other than those approved by the Chief Controller for specified 
purposes, shall not exceed 300 litres.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> An air space of not 
less than 5 per cent. of its capacity shall be kept in each container.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The container shall 
bear a stamped, embossed or painted warning exhibiting in conspicuous characters 
the words “Petrol” or “Motor Spirit” or an equivalent warning of the highly 
inflammable nature of the petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Nothing in sub-rules 
(1), (3), (4), (5), (6) and (7), shall apply to containers in the possession of 
the Defence Forces of the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Containers for 
petroleum Class B and Class C.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Containers for petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C shall be constructed of 
steel or iron and be of a type approved by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An air space of not 
less than 5 per cent. of its capacity shall be kept in each container for 
petroleum Class B and not less than 3 per cent. of its capacity in each 
container for petroleum Class C.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to containers in the possession of the Defence Forces of the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Empty receptacles.—All 
empty tanks which had petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B and empty 
containers which had petroleum Class A shall, except when they are opened for 
the purpose of filling or cleaning and rendering them free from petroleum vapour, 
be kept securely closed until they have been thoroughly cleaned and freed from 
petroleum vapour.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Repairs to 
receptacles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall cause to be repaired or repair by the use of hot work any tank 
or container which had petroleum unless it has been thoroughly cleaned and freed 
from petroleum and petroleum vapour or otherwise prepared for safely carrying 
out such hot repair and certified, in writing, by a competent person to have 
been so repaired. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The certificate 
required under sub-rule (1) shall be preserved by the repairer for a period of 
at least three months and produced to an inspector on demand.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Prevention of escape 
of petroleum.—All 
due precautions shall be taken at all times to prevent escape of petroleum into 
any drain, sewer, and harbour, river or watercourse or over any public road or 
railway line.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Prohibition of 
employment of children and intoxicated persons.—No 
child under the age of eighteen years and no person who is in a state of 
intoxication shall be employed on the loading, unloading or transport of 
petroleum or in any premises licensed under these rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Prohibition of 
smoking, fires, lights, etc.—Unless 
expressly provided in these rules, no person shall smoke and no matches, fires, 
lights or articles or substances capable of causing ignition of petroleum shall 
be allowed, at any time in proximity to a place where petroleum is refined, 
stored or handled or in a vehicle’s carriage or vessel in which petroleum is 
transported.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Special precautions 
against accident.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall commit or attempt to commit any act, which may tend to cause a 
fire or explosion in or about any place where petroleum is refined, stored or 
handled, or any vehicle’s carriage or vessel in which petroleum is transported.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person storing 
petroleum and every person in charge of or engaged in the storage, handling or 
transport of petroleum shall at all times—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  comply with the provisions of these rules and conditions of any 
licence relating thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  observe all precautions for prevention of accident by fire or 
explosion; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  prevent any person from committing any act referred to in sub-rule 
(1).
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Payment of fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All fees payable under these rules to the Chief Controller shall be paid by a 
crossed bank draft drawn in favour of the Chief Controller of Explosives, Nagpur. 
The bank draft shall be drawn on any nationalized bank, payable at Nagpur. Fees 
upto Rupees one hundred in each case may be paid in cash at the office of the 
Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Fees payable to a 
Controller shall be paid by a crossed bank draft drawn in favour of the 
Controller of Explosives to whom the payment is made. The bank draft shall be 
drawn on any nationalized bank payable at the station where the office of the 
Controller to whom payment is to be made is located. Fees upto rupees one 
hundred in each case may also be paid in cash at the office of the Controller 
concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Fees payable to 
District Authority or any other authority under these rules shall be paid in 
such a manner as may be specified by that authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>(i) If an application 
for the grant, renewal or amendment of the licence is rejected, the fees paid by 
the applicant shall be refunded to him—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  by the licensing authority, if the fee has been paid in cash or by 
bank draft; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  if the fee has been paid into a treasury, by that treasury on the 
production of signed order from the licensing authority directing such refund;
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> The fees shall be 
refunded by the licensing authority preferably within six months of the 
realization. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Fees payable under 
these rules for purposes other than the grant, renewal, or amendment of licences 
shall not be refundable.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Licence for import 
of petroleum.—Petroleum, 
other than petroleum which may be stored without a licence under sections 7, 8 
and 9 of the Act, shall not be imported into India except under a licence 
granted under these rules:
 
Provided that, such 
petroleum products may also be imported by a person not having a licence if 
adequate advance arrangements are made by such person to receive and store the 
imported petroleum product in licensed premises.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Petroleum exempted.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Nothing in this chapter applies to petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C 
comprising in a ship’s stores and manifested as such.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in rules 14, 
19 and 26 shall apply to petroleum imported by the Defence Forces of the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Ports into which 
petroleum may be imported.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum shall not be imported into India by sea except through the ports which 
are duly approved for this purpose by the Ministry of Shipping, Government of 
India, in consultation with the Chief Controller and declared as Custom’s ports 
by the Commissioner of Customs.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Commissioner of Customs may, on the 
recommendation of the Chief Controller, allow import of petroleum Class B or 
petroleum Class C, otherwise than in bulk, through any other port.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Adequate fire fighting 
facilities as per OISD Standard-156 shall be provided at the ports handling 
petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Person(s) desirous of 
seeking approval in respect of proposed facilities for unloading of petroleum 
for the purpose of import under sub-rule (1) or of making modifications in the 
existing facilities shall submit to the Chief Controller an application 
alongwith—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  specifications and plans drawn to scale in quadruplicate, clearly 
indicating—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  surroundings and all protected works within 500 metres of the 
unloading facilities on all sides showing therein the location, available draft, 
navigation channel, turning circle, route of transfer pipeline(s);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  mooring or berthing facilities, service platform/berth, mode of 
unloading, fire fighting facilities, illumination arrangements, navigational 
facilities, control room, spill collection/containment arrangements etc.; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  piping and instrumentation diagram of the petroleum pipeline(s) at 
the unloading area;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  comprehensive project report elaborating the scheme and methodology of 
import, safety and security features including those mentioned in (a) (i), (ii) 
and (iii) of this sub-rule;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  Environment Impact Assessment and Risk Analysis Report indicating 
qualitative and quantitative risks, probable failure scenarios, Lower 
Flammability Limit (LFL) distances and consequent hazards and damages with 
damage distances and remedies recommended;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  scrutiny fee of rupees two thousand; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  copies of clearances obtained from the following authorities:—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  Ministry of Shipping or State Maritime Board, as the case may be,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  Ministry of Environment and Forests or State Pollution Control Board, 
as the case may be, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  Commissioner of Customs.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Unloading of petroleum 
in bulk shall be either by mechanized arm or by armoured hose as approved by 
Chief Controller. All hoses, pipes and other appliances used in unloading of 
petroleum shall be electrically and mechanically continuous and duly tested as 
per codes/standards.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Declaration by the 
master of the ship carrying petroleum or by the ship’s agent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The master of every ship carrying petroleum shall deliver to the pilot before 
entering any port approved under sub-rule (1) of rule 16, a written declaration 
in Form I under his signature:
 
Provided that no such 
declaration is necessary if the agent of the ship deliver such a declaration 
signed by him to the Conservator before the arrival of such ship.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The pilot shall make 
over the said declaration to the Conservator without delay and the Conservator 
shall forward the declaration to the Commissioner of Customs of the port with 
all convenient despatch.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Anchorage of ships 
carrying petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every ship having petroleum on board shall be anchored at such anchorage as the 
Conservator shall specify in this behalf and shall not leave such anchorage 
without the general or special order of the Conservator and subject to such 
conditions as may be specified in such order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The anchorage shall in 
no case be the same as that for vessel laden with explosives and shall be at 
such distance from the anchorage for vessels laden with explosives as to render 
it impossible for a fire originating at the former anchorage to affect vessels 
at the latter:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to ships having on board petroleum Class C. 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Production of 
certificate and licence for import.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person desiring to import petroleum shall furnish personally or through 
his agent to the Commissioner of Customs—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  certificate of storage accommodation in Form II signed by such person 
or his agent; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the licence or an authenticated copy of the licence for the import and 
storage of such petroleum:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to the importation, otherwise than in bulk, of petroleum 
exempted under sections 7, 8, 9 and 10 of the Act:
 
Provided further that the 
furnishing of a licence under clause (b) shall not be necessary for the 
importation of petroleum Class C in bulk in quantity exempted under section 7 of 
the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), a person may import petroleum Class A in 
bulk, even if—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  he is not holding a licence for storage at the port of importation; or

 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the storage accommodation in the premises licensed in his name is not 
sufficient to hold the quantity of petroleum intended to be imported:
 
Provided in both cases 
adequate advance arrangements to the satisfaction of the Conservator are made by 
the importer to distribute the petroleum from the port of import to premises 
licensed to store such petroleum.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Permission of 
Commissioner of Customs to land petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No imported petroleum shall be landed except with the permission of the 
Commissioner of Customs.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Commissioner of 
Customs after receiving—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  of the testing officer’s reports on the petroleum;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the certificate of storage accommodation in Form II if required under 
rule 19; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the licence or an authenticated copy of the licence if required under 
rule 19,
 
and after making such 
further inquiries, as he deems necessary, is satisfied that the petroleum can be 
lawfully imported and that there is suitable accommodation for it, he shall 
permit it to be landed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Commissioner of 
Customs is satisfied that any petroleum imported otherwise than in bulk is not 
intended to be stored in India but is intended to be dispatched immediately 
after landing to any place outside India, he may waive the requirements of rules 
14 and 19 and by written order permit subject to such conditions as he may 
specify such petroleum to be landed for the purpose of immediate dispatch to 
that place. The Commissioner of Customs shall ensure that the goods are 
immediately moved to the destination country. In the event of road breaches, 
etc., occurring maximum time of 30 days may be allowed from the date of landing 
of the goods upto the date of dispatch to the destinations outside of India.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall affect the power of the Commissioner of Customs to detain the petroleum 
under any other law or rule for the time being in force.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Landing of 
petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C in anticipation of the testing officer’s 
report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 20 where the consignee furnishes a 
guarantee to re-ship the petroleum if the testing officer’s report proves 
unfavourable, the Commissioner of Customs may in anticipation of the testing 
officer’s report permit any petroleum which he believes to be petroleum Class B 
or petroleum Class C to be discharged into boats or to be landed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The permission granted 
under sub-rule (1) shall be subject to the conditions that the boats into which 
the petroleum is discharged shall remain at such place as the Conservator may 
specify or that the petroleum shall be landed at a landing place duly specified 
for the purpose by him and stored in an installation licensed under these rules.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Unloading of 
petroleum in bulk.—Subject 
to the provisions of Part II of Chapter III, petroleum imported in bulk shall be 
discharged into storage tanks on shore either directly or by means of barges or 
lighters specially constructed for carrying petroleum in bulk and only at such 
places as the Conservator may by general or special order direct.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Unloading of 
petroleum otherwise than in bulk.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provision of Part II of Chapter III, petroleum imported otherwise 
than in bulk shall be landed either at jetties provided for the purpose, or in 
barges or lighters and only at such places as the Conservator shall direct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No petroleum contained 
in containers shall be landed unless such containers are free from leakage and 
are of such strength or construction as not to be liable to be broken or to leak 
except in cases of gross negligence or extraordinary accident:
 
Provided that petroleum 
contained in containers, which do not satisfy the requirements of this sub-rule, 
may subject to provisions of Part II of Chapter III and to such conditions as 
the Conservator may impose, be landed at separate landing place approved for the 
purpose.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Transhipment of 
petroleum.—Petroleum 
may be transhipped from one ship to another for conveyance to any other port, 
whether within or beyond the territory of India subject to the provisions of 
Part II of Chapter III.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Petroleum to be 
imported by land only at authorized places.—No 
petroleum shall be imported into India by land except at places specially 
authorized for the purpose by the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Declaration and 
certificate to be furnished and licence to be produced before importing 
Petroleum by land.—Every 
person desiring to import petroleum by land shall furnish to the Commissioner of 
Customs—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  a declaration in Form I signed by him or his agent;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  a certificate of storage accommodation in Form II signed by him or his 
agent; and 
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  the licence or an authenticated copy of the licence held for the 
importation and storage of such petroleum:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to the importation of petroleum exempted under sections 7, 
8 and 9 of the Act:
 
Provided further that the 
furnishing of licence under clause (c) shall not be necessary for the 
importation of petroleum Class C, in bulk, in quantity exempted under section 7 
of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Permission of the 
Commissioner of Customs to unload petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No petroleum shall be unloaded except with the permission of the Commissioner of 
Customs.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Commissioner of 
Customs, after receiving—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the testing officer’s report on the petroleum;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the certificate in Form II, if required by rule 26; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the licence, if required by rule 26,
 
and after making such 
further inquiries as he deems necessary, is satisfied that the petroleum can be 
lawfully imported and that there is suitable accommodation for it, he shall 
permit it to be unloaded.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Commissioner of 
Customs is satisfied that any petroleum imported is not intended to be stored in 
India but is intended to be dispatched immediately after unloading to any place 
outside India, he may waive the requirements of rules 14 and 26 and by written 
order permit, subject to such conditions as he may specify, such petroleum to be 
unloaded for the purpose of immediate dispatch to that place.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall affect the power of the Commissioner of Customs to detain petroleum under 
any other law or rule for the time being in force.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Restriction on 
leaky receptacles.—No 
leaky tank or container containing petroleum shall be tendered for transport.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Loading of 
containers.—Barrels, 
drums and other containers filled with petroleum shall be loaded with bung 
upwards.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Restriction on 
passengers, combustible and inflammable cargo.—Save 
as provided in rules 38, 39 and 52 and clause (b) of rule 60, no ship, vessel or 
vehicle shall carry petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B and Class C in bulk 
if it is carrying passengers or any combustible cargo other than petroleum:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall prohibit the use of dunnage for packing purposes in the case of 
coast wise transport of petroleum Class A otherwise than in bulk.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Prohibition of 
smoking, fires, lights.—No 
person while engaged in loading or unloading or transporting shall smoke or 
carry matches, lighters or other appliances capable of producing ignition or 
explosion.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Restriction on 
loading and unloading by night.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum shall not be loaded into, or unloaded from, any ship, vessel or 
vehicle between the hours of sunset and sunrise, unless—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  adequate electric lighting is provided at the place of loading or 
unloading and the provisions of Chapter IV are complied with; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  adequate fire-fighting facilities with personnel are kept ready at the 
place of loading for immediate use in the event of a fire.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to the refuelling of an aircraft by vessels or vehicles licensed 
under these rules in accordance with the provisions of the Indian Aircraft 
Rules, 1937, or to the refueling of an aircraft by the Defence Forces of the 
Union.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule the Chief Controller shall determine the adequacy or 
otherwise of the electric lighting and fire-fighting facilities.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Conditions of 
carriage of petroleum in bulk by water.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum in bulk shall not be carried by water, except in a ship or other 
vessel licensed for the carriage of petroleum in bulk by an officer appointed by 
the Central Government in this behalf (hereinafter in this Part referred to as 
the licensing authority) and the petroleum shall be stored in such part of the 
ship or other vessel and in such manner as may be approved by general or special 
order by the licensing authority after consultation with the Chief Controller:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  nothing in this rule shall apply to vessels registered in a country 
other than India importing petroleum;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  petroleum in tank vehicles may, with the permission, in writing, of 
the Chief Controller and subject to such conditions as he may specify, be 
transported across a river by a ferry.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The licence referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be granted in Form III, and shall remain in force for a 
period of one year from the date of its issue.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Requirement as to 
the construction of vessels.—Every 
ship or other vessel carrying petroleum in bulk, other than a ferry permitted to 
transport tank vehicles under clause (b) of the proviso of sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 
33, shall be made of iron or steel well and substantially constructed with 
scantlings of ample dimensions in proportion to the size of the vessel:
 
Provided that the 
licensing authority may, in special circumstances, allow use of such ships or 
other vessels constructed of materials other than iron or steel under such 
conditions as it may, in consultation with the Chief Controller, specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Tank fittings on 
ships or vessels.—The 
following provisions shall apply for the transport of petroleum other than 
petroleum Class C in ships or other vessels, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  all tanks shall be fitted with independent approved filling and 
suction pipes and valves, or with stand pipes with blank flanges, all pipes 
being carried down nearly to the bottom of the tanks, and no petroleum in bulk 
shall be taken on board or discharged except through such pipes and valves, 
unless otherwise permitted by the Chief Controller in writing;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  all tanks shall be fitted with manholes having screw-down cover with 
petroleum-tight joints and, in the case of tanks intended for use with petroleum 
Class A, with ventilators or relief valves of approved pattern properly 
protected with wire gauge of a mesh not less than 11 meshes to linear centimetre; 
and 
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  ventilators similarly protected shall be fitted to all spaces, around 
tanks.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Self propelled 
barges.—The 
following conditions shall be observed in self propelled barges transporting 
petroleum other than petroleum Class C, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  the whole of the machinery shall be at the stern of the barge and 
shall be entirely separated from the cargo by a cofferdam consisting of two 
transverse petroleum-proof bulkheads separated by a space of at least 15 
centimetres;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  each exhaust outlet from the machinery shall be fitted with an 
approved type of spark arrester;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  no petrol-driven engine shall be used either as main engine or for the 
purpose of driving any auxiliary machinery or pumps;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  a quick-action closing valve which can be operated from outside the 
machinery space, shall be fitted to each fuel feed pipe at its junctions with 
the fuel service tank;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  the barge shall be provided with a heavy wood belting; and 
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  suitable ventilators shall be fitted to the cargo space.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Petroleum in bulk 
on barges and flats.—Petroleum 
in bulk shall not be transported in a barge or flat unless the barge or flat is 
self-propelled or is in tow of or otherwise, attended by, a steamer or tug and 
carrier—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  at least four fire extinguishers suitable for extinguishing oil fires 
and a covered sand box, on deck, containing at least 0.20 cubic metres of dry 
sand;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  a suitable hammer of non-sparking metal; and 
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  a red flag.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Restriction on 
cargo or passengers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No ship or other vessel shall carry petroleum in bulk if it is carrying 
passengers, or any inflammable cargo other than petroleum or coal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> This rule shall not 
apply to petroleum Class C used as fuel and carried in cellular double bottoms 
under engine and boiler compartment and under ordinary holds; such fuel oil 
tanks and installations connected therewith shall comply with the provisions of 
the Indian Merchant Shipping (Construction and Survey of Passenger Steamers) 
Rules, 1956.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Petroleum carried 
as cargo in unberthed passenger ships.—Petroleum 
Class A shall not be transported as cargo by an unberthed passenger ship as 
defined in the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958):
 
Provided that the 
certifying officer referred to in section 243 of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 
(44 of 1958), may in cases where he is satisfied that no other means of 
transporting the petroleum are available, permit petroleum Class A in quantity 
not exceeding 1,250 litres to be transported otherwise than in bulk by an 
unberthed passenger ship subject to—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  the condition that no more persons shall be carried in the ship than 
can with safety be accommodated in the ship’s life-boats in case of an accident; 
and 
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  such other conditions as the certifying officer may, after 
consultation with the Chief Controller, impose:
 
Provided further that 
clause (a) of the first proviso shall not apply in the case of unberthed 
passenger ships engaged on voyages in the course of which they do not go beyond 
32 kilometres from land.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Prohibition of 
transport of petroleum Class A by country craft.—No 
country craft shall carry petroleum Class A if it is carrying passengers.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Restrictions on 
steamers or tugs employed in towing or attending a petroleum vessel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No steamer or tug employed in towing or otherwise attending a barge, flat or 
lighter carrying petroleum, other than petroleum Class C in bulk, shall at the 
same time tow or otherwise attend any other vessel carrying on inflammable cargo 
other than petroleum or coal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such steamer or tug 
shall carry any inflammable cargo other than petroleum or coal.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All such steamer or 
tugs shall be fitted with efficient spark arrestors.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Ventilations and 
cleaning of holds and tanks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before any petroleum is discharged from a ship or vessel, the holds of such 
vessels shall be thoroughly ventilated:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub-rule shall apply to any vessel carrying petroleum Class A not exceeding 
30 litres or petroleum Class B not exceeding 2,500 litres or petroleum Class C.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After all petroleum 
has been discharged from any such vessel, the holds, tanks and bilge’s of the 
vessel shall be rendered free from inflammable vapour.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Sub-rule (2) shall not 
apply to the tanks of a ship importing petroleum which leaves the port without 
delay after unloading of cargo or remains only for the purpose of taking on 
board bunkers, stores or ballast or for such other purpose as may be approved by 
the Conservator, if the tanks of every such ship are securely fastened down 
immediately after the discharge of the cargo.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Sub-rule (2) shall not 
apply to barges or lighters continuously engaged in the transport of petroleum 
in bulk, if—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  an interval of not more than 72 hours is likely to elapse between an 
operation of unloading and the next loading operation; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the tanks are securely fastened down immediately after unloading.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Sub-rule (2) shall not 
apply to specially constructed steel tank motor vessel approved by the Chief 
Controller which are engaged in the transport of petroleum in bulk on such 
rivers and on such ports thereof as may be approved by him in areas outside port 
limits, or by the Conservator within port limits, if the tanks of such vessels 
are securely fastened down immediately after unloading and the vessels depart 
not later than 12 hours after completion of unloading for their next place of 
loading.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> All ships or other 
vessels which by sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4) or sub-rule (5) are exempted from 
the application of sub-rule (2) shall until their holds and tanks have been 
rendered free from inflammable vapour, comply with all the rules applicable to 
ships or other vessels when carrying petroleum in bulk.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Master of vessels 
specially responsible.—The 
master or other officer-in-charge of any vessel which had carried petroleum on 
board whether as a cargo or as a fuel, or any vessel licensed under rule 33 
shall be responsible to see that—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  all due precautions are taken for the prevention of accidents due to 
ignition of petroleum or petroleum vapour;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  so long as there is petroleum or petroleum vapour in a tank, all 
openings from the tank to the atmosphere except the gas escape line are kept 
closed and locked or otherwise securely fastened; and when it is necessary to 
take dips or samples, the sludge plugs or sighting ports are closed immediately 
after such dips or samples are taken:
 
                 
Provided that subject to the provisions of clause (c) the master or officer 
in-charge may cause the necessary openings to be opened or unlocked for the 
purpose of taking on board or unloading petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C 
for cleaning the tanks or for other sufficient reason;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  no person enters a tank or an enclosed space which had, or is 
suspected to have contained petroleum without wearing a breathing apparatus of a 
type approved by the Chief Controller unless an officer appointed by the Central 
Government in this behalf has examined the tank or space with the aid of an 
approved petroleum vapour-testing instrument and has been certified by him in 
writing that the said tank or space is free from petroleum vapour;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  the vessel does not undergo repair by hot work to any of its tanks, 
part of fittings which are likely to contain petroleum vapour or petroleum 
unless each such tank, part of fittings, as the case may be, has been examined 
by an officer appointed under clause (c) with the aid of an approved petroleum 
vapour-test instrument and has been certified by him in writing that the tank, 
part or fittings is free from petroleum vapour or petroleum;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  the vessel used for the carriage of petroleum in bulk as a cargo is 
not taken among other ships or to a dry dock unless—
 <subsection>
             
<number>i</number>  the vessel is proceeding to an oil berth, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  a certificate from an officer appointed under clause (c) to the 
effect that he has examined all the tanks, cofferdams, pump rooms and such other 
parts as are deemed necessary with the aid of an approved petroleum vapour-testing 
instrument, and that such tanks, cofferdams, pump rooms and other parts are free 
from petroleum vapour; and declaration from the Master that to the best of his 
knowledge there is no petroleum vapour, present in other parts of the vessel not 
covered by the above certificate are produced;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  the officer granting certificate under clause (c) or clause (d) or 
clause (e) may specify such conditions and make such recommendations as are 
necessary to maintain gas-free conditions of tanks, space or parts certified;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number>  the certificate referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) shall be 
granted only on receipt of fee fixed by the Central Government from time to 
time;
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number>  the vessel or any steamer or tug towing or otherwise attending on such 
vessel exhibits conspicuously—
 </section><section>
             
<number>i</number>  from sunrise to sunset a red flag not less than 90 centimetres square 
with a white circular centre 15 centimetres in diameter if petroleum class A is 
carried and a red flag not less than 90 centimetres square if petroleum Class B 
is carried; and
 <subsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  from sunset to sunrise such warning lights as may be required by the 
Conservator.
 
Note.—The 
port authority concerned shall be the authority for the issue of final 
permission for the purpose of clauses (c), (d) and (e) even though Gas Free 
Certificates have been obtained from the officer concerned under clause (c) of 
this rule.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 
 
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>43A</number>
Agency undertaking ship breaking specially responsible.—The Agency, which
owns vessels meant for breaking or breaching, before undertaking breaking of
such vessels, called ship breaking, shall be responsible to see that— 
 
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
all due precautions are taken for the prevention of accidents due to
ignition of petroleum or petroleum vapour; 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
so long as there is petroleum vapour in a tank, all openings from the
tank to the atmosphere except the gas escape line are kept closed and locked or
otherwise securely fastened; and subject the provisions of clause (c), the
agency undertaking the ship breaking activities may cause the necessary openings
to be opened or unlocked for cleaning the tanks or for making the tank free from
petroleum vapour or for other sufficient reason; 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
no person enters a tank or an enclosed space which had, or is suspected
to have contained petroleum without wearing a breathing apparatus of a type
approved by the Chief Controller unless an officer appointed by the Central
Government in this behalf has examined the tank or space with the aid of an
approved petroleum vapour-testing instrument and has been certified by him in
writing that the said tank or space is free from petroleum vapour. 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
the vessel does not undergo breaking by hot work to any of its tanks,
part of fittings which are likely to contain petroleum vapour or petroleum
unless each such tank, part of fittings, as the case may be, has been examined
by an officer appointed under clause (c) with the aid of an approved petroleum
vapour-test instrument and has been certified by him in writing that the tank,
part of fittings are free from petroleum vapour or petroleum; 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
the vessel is not taken to ship breaking yard unless a certificate from
an officer appointed under clause (c); to the effect that he has examined all
the tanks, cofferdams, pump rooms and such other parts as are deemed necessary
with the aid of an approved petroleum vapour-testing instrument, and that such
tanks, cofferdams, pump room and other parts are free from petroleum vapour; and
declaration from the agency undertaking the ship breaking activities that to the
best of its knowledge there is no petroleum vapour, present in other parts of
the vessel not covered by the above certificate are produced; 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
the officer granting certificate under clause (c) or clause (d) or clause
(e) may specify such conditions and make such recommendations as are necessary
to maintain gas free conditions of tanks, space or parts certified; 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
the certificate referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) shall be granted
only on receipt of fee fixed by Central Government from time to time. 


 Note.—The
port authority concerned shall be the authority for the issue of final
permission for the purpose of clauses (c), and (e) even though Gas Free
Certificates have been obtained from the officer concerned under clause (c) of
this rule.]

  
  
  



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Loading and 
unloading of bulk petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum in bulk shall not be loaded or unloaded into or from any ship/barge at 
any place unless—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the location is notified or permitted by the Central Government and 
the facilities are approved by Chief Controller under rule 16, in case of 
import, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the location and facilities for loading or unloading are approved by 
the Chief Controller, in cases other than import.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Person(s) seeking 
approval under sub-rule (1)(b) of this rule shall submit to Chief Controller—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  specification and plans drawn to scale in quadruplicate, indicating—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  surroundings and all protected works within 500 metres of the loading 
or unloading facilities on all sides showing therein the location, size of the 
ship, available draft, navigation channel, turning circle, route of transfer 
pipeline(s),
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  mooring or berthing facilities, service platform/berth, mode of 
loading or unloading, fire fighting facilities, illumination arrangements, 
control room, spill collection/containment arrangements, etc., and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  piping and instrumentation diagram of the petroleum pipeline(s) at 
the loading or unloading area:
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  comprehensive project report elaborating the scheme and methodology of 
loading or unloading of petroleum, safety and security features including those 
mentioned in (a)(i), (ii) and (iii) of this sub-rule;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  Risk Analysis Report indicating qualitative and quantitative risks, 
probable failure scenarios and consequent hazards and damages with damage 
distances, etc., and remedies recommended;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  scrutiny fee of rupees two thousand; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  copies of clearances obtained from the following authorities:—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  Ministry of Shipping or State Maritime Board, as the case may be,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  Ministry of Environment and Forests or State Pollution Control Board, 
as the case may be.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Loading or unloading 
of petroleum in bulk shall be either by merchandised arm, or armoured hose metal 
pipe as approved by Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All hoses, pipes and 
other appliances used in loading or unloading of petroleum shall be electrically 
and mechanically continuous and duly tested as per codes/standards.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The hose and metal 
pipes used for loading and unloading of petroleum in bulk shall be subjected to 
periodic testing.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Precautions on 
suspension of loading or unloading.—When 
the loading or unloading of petroleum has commenced, such loading or unloading 
shall proceed with due diligence and, if it is discontinued, the tanks, and 
holds of the ships or other vessels concerned and all loading or unloading 
valves shall be closed immediately.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Prohibition of 
naked lights, fire and smoking on board a vessel.—No 
fire, naked light, fuses, matches or other appliances for producing ignition or 
explosion and no smoking shall be allowed on board any barge, flat or lighter 
carrying petroleum in bulk or on board any vessel used for the transport of 
petroleum Class A otherwise than in bulk or for the transhipment of petroleum to 
or from any vessel within the limits of any port:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall prevent the use on a self-propelled barge of the machinery or 
propulsion.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Prohibition of 
smoking, fire and lights, during loading or unloading.—At 
all times during loading or unloading of a ship or other vessel and until such 
time as all petroleum shall have been loaded into or unloaded from the holds or 
tanks and the holds or tanks shall have been securely closed down and, in the 
case of unloading rendered free from inflammable vapour, there shall be no fire 
or artificial light or smoking on board such ship or other vessel or within 30 
metres of the place where the petroleum is being loaded or unloaded:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  to the use of lamps, cookers or similar apparatus, electric or 
otherwise so designed, constructed and maintained as to be incapable of igniting 
inflammable vapour or in the case of petroleum Class C the use of gally fires;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  to the unloading or loading of a ship under conditions approved by 
the Conservator by means of steam from her own boilers or power generated by 
electric motors or internal combustion engines placed in a position away from 
cargo holds and pump rooms or by means of electric motors, so designed, 
constructed and maintained as to be incapable of igniting inflammable vapour and 
maintained in accordance with the requirements specified by Lloyds or other ship 
surveyors approved by the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Fire-extinguishing 
appliances to be ready for use.—Vessels 
unloading or loading petroleum shall have adequate fire-extinguishing appliances 
so disposed that they can be put into immediate use.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Restriction on the 
simultaneous conveyance of different classes of petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum Class A shall not be conveyed to the shore from, or loaded into the 
same vessel simultaneously with petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Controller 
may, by written order exempt specially any particular operation from the 
provisions of sub-rule (1) if separate and distinct pipelines and pumps are 
provided for loading or unloading of petroleum Class A simultaneously with 
petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Transport by sea of 
petroleum which has not been tested.—Petroleum 
which has been imported into any port approved under sub-rules 
<section><number>1</number> and (2) of 
rule 16 and which has not been tested at such port in accordance with the rules 
contained in Chapter X, shall not be transported to any port other than a port 
at which importation is permitted under sub-rule (1) of rule 16 and in 
accordance with the provisions of all the rules in Chapter II.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The rules in this Part apply only to the transport coastwise of Petroleum Class 
A otherwise than in bulk.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Unless otherwise 
expressly provided in this Part, nothing contained in Part II of this Chapter 
shall apply to any petroleum transported in accordance with this Part.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Conditions of 
transport by unberthed passenger ships.—Petroleum 
Class A may be transported otherwise than in bulk by an unberthed passenger ship 
as defined in the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958), in accordance with 
the provisions of rules 29, 30, 39 and 54 to 60 (both inclusive).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Maximum quantity 
allowed to be carried.—Petroleum 
Class A may be transported otherwise in bulk by a country craft or steam or 
motor vessel other than unberthed passenger ship as defined in the Merchant 
Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958) subject to the provisions of rules 29, 30, 39 
and 54 to 60 (both inclusive), if the quantity of petroleum does not exceed—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  in the case of country craft, the licensed carrying capacity of the 
vessel after taking into account the weight of barrels or tins in which the 
petroleum is carried; or 
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  in the case of steam or motor vessels, 15 tonnes.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Carriage below 
decks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum Class A shall not be carried below deck in decked vessels unless there 
are efficient ventilators in the hold.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Half of the 
ventilators referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be carried down nearly to the 
bottom of the holds and the other half of such ventilators terminated only a 
short distance below the deck, the short ventilators shall be labelled “Outlet 
or to Leeward” and the long ventilators shall be labelled “Inlet or to 
Windward”, such ventilators shall have large cowl heads, the openings being 
covered with double copper or non-corroding metal gauze not less than 11 meshes 
per linear centimeter.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Provisions of 
bulkhead.—In 
all vessels other than country craft, a solid gas-tight bulkhead without 
openings, and in country craft a solid bulkhead without openings, shall be 
between the hold and the afterdeck where the crew are accommodated, and in 
vessels fitted with a poop the bulkhead shall be placed immediately in front of 
the poop. In decked vessels the bulkhead shall reach up to the deck, in all 
other vessels it shall reach to within 15 centimetres of the gunwale.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Prohibition of 
fire, lights and smoking.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fire, naked light of any description and no smoking shall be allowed on any 
part of the vessel transporting petroleum Class A except abaft the solid 
bulkhead.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The navigational 
lights on any such vessel shall be carried abaft the bulkhead.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Provisions of fire 
extinguishers.—Fire 
extinguishers suitable for fighting oil fires shall be placed at convenient 
points on any vessel transporting petroleum Class A. Not less than two such 
fire-extinguishers shall be placed on the afterdeck.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Construction of 
steam or motor-vessels.—Steam 
or motor-vessels not specially constructed for the carriage of petroleum shall 
not carry petroleum unless they are constructed of iron or steel or any other 
material approved by the Chief Controller.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Transport in steam 
or motor-vessels.—On 
steam or motor vessels not specially constructed for the carriage of petroleum—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  any petroleum shall either be carried in separate compartments which 
shall be gas-tight and shall be effectively sealed, or in a hold in which there 
are efficient ventilators in accordance with sub-rule (2) of rule 54 or on deck 
in accordance with rule 60;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  petroleum Class A shall be packed in containers complying with the 
provisions of rules 4 and 5;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  special precautions shall be taken against smoking and the use of 
lights or fire of any kind while cargo is being loaded or unloaded or while the 
hatches are off, or any deck openings are uncovered, before any lights are used 
in compartment which contains petroleum. Precautions shall also be taken to 
ensure that the space is clear of vapour and all empty containers which have 
contained petroleum Class A are kept securely closed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Transport of deck.—Petroleum 
may be carried in deck in steamer or motor-vessels not specially built for the 
carriage of petroleum, subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  in cargo ships petroleum Class A shall not occupy more than 50 per 
cent. of the open deck area and shall be so stowed as not to interfere with the 
navigation of the ship or make it unseaworthy;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  in passenger ships a limited quantity of petroleum Class A may be 
carried provided that proper precautions are taken regarding stowage and keeping 
the packages away from passengers, promenade or deck space;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  the petroleum shall be protected from the direct rays of the sun by 
the use of canvas awnings or otherwise; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  conspicuous notices shall be posted up, drawing attention to the 
danger arising from smoking or striking matches near the deck cargo.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Conditions of 
transport by country craft.—No 
petroleum Class A shall be transported in a country craft unless the following 
conditions are satisfied, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  the petroleum shall be carried—
 <subsection>
             
<number>i</number>  in 200 litres capacity steel barrels, the screw bungs of such barrels 
being well fitting and sealed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  in 200 litres capacity sealed steel drums, not more than three tiers 
of which may be carried on any single vessel; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  in 10 litres capacity sealed tins, not more than six tiers of which 
may be carried on any single vessel; or
 </subsection></section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  all barrels or tins shall be carefully examined and no leaky barrel or 
tin shall be taken on board the craft;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  no barrels, drums or tins shall be placed within 1.2 metres of 
afterdeck where the crew are accommodated in the case of an undecked vessel or 
on deck in the case of a decked vessel; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  no passengers shall be carried on board the craft.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Application.—The 
provisions of this Part shall apply to the transport of petroleum on land by 
vehicles except transport of—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  petroleum Class A in quantity not exceeding 100 litres and petroleum 
of any other class, otherwise than in bulk, subject to the provisions of rule 
67;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  petroleum of any class transported by the Defence Forces of the Union.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Tank vehicles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every tank vehicle used for the transport of petroleum, in bulk on land shall be 
built, tested and maintained in accordance with the requirements laid down in 
the Third Schedule and be of a type approved in writing by the Chief Controller:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may under exceptional circumstances to be recorded in writing, waive 
any of the requirements of the third Schedule. This will, inter alia, 
include approvals for trials of better quality vehicles that will contribute to 
enhancement of safety of petroleum transportation by road under Indian 
conditions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The tank shall be 
fabricated and mounted on the vehicle chassis by a manufacturer approved by the 
Chief Controller. Such a manufacturer shall apply to the Chief Controller for 
approval with particulars of facilities and competent persons available with him 
and a scrutiny fee of rupee five hundred. The tank fabrication and mounting 
drawings in quadruplicate for each type of tank vehicle, along with scrutiny fee 
of rupee one hundred for each type of tank vehicles shall be submitted to the 
Chief Controller for approval. Such approval shall be valid for three years from 
the date of issue of approval and renewable for further period of 3 years on 
payment of fee of rupees five hundred.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Chief 
Controller, after receipt of the drawing under sub-rule (2) and after making 
such further inquiries as he deems necessary, is satisfied that the tank vehicle 
or the special safety fitting, as the case may be, meet with the requirements 
laid down in the Third Schedule, he shall approve the drawing and return to the 
applicant one copy thereof duly endorsed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to tank wagons for the carriage of petroleum by rail.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Tank capacity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Part, “the tank forming part of a tank vehicle” shall be deemed to 
include any number of tanks on the same chassis and any limitation herein 
specified on the capacity of a tank shall be construed so as to permit the tank 
containing the quantity specified under varying degrees of temperature.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The net carrying 
capacity of a tank shall be 97 per cent. of its gross carrying capacity in the 
case of petroleum Class A and petroleum Class B and 98 per cent. in the case of 
petroleum Class C.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The net carrying 
capacity of a tank truck or a tank semi-trailer shall not exceed 25 kilolitres 
of petroleum except in case of air-craft refueller in which case it should not 
exceed 50 kilolitres and the net carrying capacity of any tank trailer should 
not exceed 5 kilolitres of petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The maximum safe 
carrying capacity in weight of petroleum that can be carried in a tank vehicle 
shall not exceed the difference between the unladen weight of the vehicle and 
the maximum gross weight permitted for the class of vehicle under the 
appropriate transport regulations.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Restriction on 
other use.—Tank 
vehicle meant for the carriage of petroleum in bulk shall not be used for any 
other purpose except when so authorized by the Chief Controller in writing.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Trailers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A tank trailer not exclusively used for transporting petroleum shall not be 
attached to any vehicle for transporting petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A tank trailer 
transporting petroleum shall not be attached to any vehicle other than a vehicle 
used exclusively for transporting petroleum and not more than one trailer shall 
be so attached.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A tank trailer shall 
not be attached to a tank semi-trailer or a trailer. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A tank trailer or tank 
semi-trailer shall have reliable brakes on all wheels which shall be capable of 
efficient operation from driver’s seat of the vehicle towing the trailer.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The width of the tank 
trailer or a tank semi-trailer shall be less than the overall width of the 
towing vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A tank trailer shall 
be so connected to the towing vehicle as to cause the trailer to follow 
substantially the path of the towing vehicle and to prevent the tank trailer 
from whipping or swerving side to side dangerously.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If a tank trailer 
carrying petroleum Class A is attached to a vehicle carrying petroleum Class B 
or petroleum Class C, the towing vehicle shall comply with all the provisions of 
these rules relating to a vehicle for the transportation of petroleum Class A.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A trailer other than a 
tank trailer shall not be attached to any tank truck.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where a tank trailer 
is attached to a tank truck, the total quantity of petroleum transported in the 
tank trailer and the tank truck shall not exceed 15 kilolitres..
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> No tank trailer shall 
be attached to a tank truck having a net carrying capacity exceeding 12 
kilolitres of petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> No tank trailer 
attached to a tank truck shall be operated within a thickly populated area 
without the written permission of the district authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Vehicle for 
transport otherwise than in bulk.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every vehicle on which petroleum otherwise than in bulk is transported shall be 
strongly constructed and with sides and back of adequate height, and shall be 
maintained in good condition.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of 
animal-drawn vehicles, push carts and pedal carts, the requirements of sub-rule 
(1) regarding the sides and back of the vehicle shall not apply if the load is 
securely fastened to the vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All containers shall 
be so packed as not to project beyond the sides or back of the vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Petroleum Class A 
otherwise than in bulk shall not be transported in a trailer, attached to any 
vehicle.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Composite vehicle.—Petroleum 
in cans or in other containers shall not be transported by road on any tank 
vehicle used for transport of petroleum unless the vehicle is so constructed as 
to comply with the rules applicable to the transport of petroleum otherwise than 
in bulk as well as with the rules applicable to the transport of petroleum in 
bulk.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Carriage of other 
articles prohibited.—No 
vehicle shall carry any other article while it is carrying petroleum except when 
specially authorized in writing by the Chief Controller.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Engines of 
mechanically propelled vehicles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every mechanically propelled vehicle used for the transport by road of 
petroleum other than petroleum Class B otherwise than in bulk or petroleum Class 
C—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  the engine shall be diesel engine or an internal combustion engine;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the exhaust shall be wholly in front of the tank or the load, as the 
case may be and shall have ample clearance from fuel-system and combustible 
materials and shall not be exposed to leakage or spillage of the fuel or product 
or accumulations of grease or oil;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  the exhaust pipe shall be fitted with an approved spark arrestor;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  the muffler or silencer shall not be cut off from the exhaust system;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  the engine air intake shall be fitted with an effective 
flame-arrestor, or an air cleaner having effective flame-arrestor, 
characteristics, substantially installed and capable of preventing emission of 
flame from the side of the engine in the event of back firing;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  the cab of the vehicle shall be of all-metal construction and its 
rear window, if provided, shall be fully covered with wired glass; 
alternatively, the cab and the engine shall be separated from the tank or the 
load, as the case may be, by a fire-resisting shield which shall fully cover the 
tank or load.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The fuel tanks of 
every such vehicle, if installed behind the cab of vehicle, shall be—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  so designed, constructed and installed as to present no unusual 
hazard, and shall be so arranged as to permit drainage without removal from 
their mountings; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  protected against blows by stout steel guards and provided with a lock 
in the filling caps.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In every engine 
running on petroleum Class A, quick action cut-off valve shall be fitted to the 
fuel feed pipe in an easily accessible position which shall be clearly marked.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this rule, provisions of sub-rules (1) to (3) except 
clauses (i) and (iii) of sub-rule (1), shall not apply for transportation of 
petroleum Class A otherwise than in bulk exclusively used by helicopters and 
aeroplanes for aerial crops-spraying purposes only.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Electrical 
installation.—If 
electric light or instrument or any other electrically-operated equipment is 
employed on any vehicle including a trailer used in the transportation by road 
of petroleum other than petroleum Class C—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  the pressure of the electric circuit shall not exceed 24 volts;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  electric wiring shall—
 <subsection>
            
<number>a</number>  be heavily insulated and be adequate for maximum loads to be carried;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>b</number>  be provided with suitable over-current protection in the form of fuses 
or automatic circuit breakers and installed so as to be protected from physical 
damage and contact with possible product spill either by location or by being 
encased in metal conduct or other oil resistant protective covering; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>c</number>  have all junction boxes sealed;
 </subsection></section><section>
       
<number>iii</number>  the generator, battery, switches, fuses and circuit brackets shall 
be carried in the cab of the vehicle or in the engine compartment and the 
battery shall be in an easily accessible position with a heavy-duty switch close 
by to cut-off the battery;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  generators and motors and switches thereof which are not installed 
within the engine compartment shall be of the approved flame-proof type:
 
                 
Provided that where such generators or motors or switches thereof are installed 
in an enclosed space, adequate provision shall be made for air circulation to 
prevent overheating and possible accumulation of inflammable vapours:
 
                 
Provided further that the provisions of this rule except clause (i) and 
sub-clause (a) of clause (ii) shall not apply for transportation of petroleum 
Class A otherwise than in bulk exclusively used by helicopters and aeroplanes 
for aerial crop spraying purposes only.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Means of 
extinguishing fire to be carried.—A 
portable fire extinguisher (10 kg. dry chemical powder or equivalent) suitable 
for extinguishing petroleum fire shall be carried in an easily accessible and 
detachable position and away from the discharge faucets on every vehicle 
transporting petroleum by road. Additionally, one dry chemical powder type fire 
extinguisher of 1 kg. capacity shall be carried in the driver’s cabin of the 
vehicle.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Vehicles to be 
constantly attended.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every vehicle which is engaged in the transport of petroleum by road shall be 
constantly attended to by at least one person who shall be familiar with the 
rules in this Part:
 
Provided that such a 
vehicle, if its tanks or compartments are empty, but not free from petroleum 
vapour, may be left unattended in places previously approved for the purpose in 
writing by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every vehicle in which 
more than 5 kilolitres of petroleum, other than petroleum Class C, is being 
transported by road, or which, while transporting petroleum, other than 
petroleum Class C by road is being trailed by another vehicle, shall, so long as 
it is in motion, be attended to, by the driver and at least one more person both 
of whom shall be familiar with the rules in this Part.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Prohibition as to 
parking.—No 
vehicle carrying petroleum by road shall be parked on a public road or in any 
congested area or at a place within 9 metres of any source of fire.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Licence necessary 
for the transport in bulk of petroleum Classes A and B.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall transport petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B in bulk, by 
road except under and in accordance with the condition of a licence granted 
under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall apply to the transport by railway administration of petroleum which is in 
its possession in its capacity as a carrier or to the transport of petroleum in 
the refueller, licensed under these rules between places within the same 
aerodrome.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Restriction against 
loading and unloading of tank vehicles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall load or unload a tank vehicle with any class of petroleum except 
at a place which is situated within premises licensed under these rules and is 
approved in writing, for loading or unloading of such class of petroleum, by the 
Chief Controller:
 
Provided that petroleum 
Class C may be loaded or unloaded at a place where such petroleum is allowed to 
be stored without licence under sections 7 and 10 of the Act:
 
Provided further that—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  a tank wagon may be loaded or unloaded at railway sidings earmarked 
for the purpose; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  a tank vehicle may be unloaded at any other place with all due 
precautions against fire and under adequate supervision if such unloading is 
necessitated by an accident or breakdown.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every tank vehicle, 
while it is being loaded or unloaded and until its valves have been shut and 
filling pipe and discharge faucets closed, shall be attended to by a person who 
is familiar with the rules in this Part.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person shall under 
any circumstances allow filling or replenishment of the fuel tank of any motor 
vehicle or internal combustion engine directly from a tank vehicle:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub-rule shall restrict filling or replenishment of the fuel tank of an 
aircraft in accordance with the rule framed under Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 
1934).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Prohibition of 
loading of leaky or defective tank vehicles or unlicensed tank vehicles.—No 
person shall load—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  any class of petroleum in tank vehicle if any tank, compartment, 
valve, pipes or any safety fitting thereof becomes leaky or defective and until 
such leaks are repaired and defects rectified and, in the case of any leak in a 
tank or a compartment until all the tanks or compartment are re-tested in the 
manner laid down in para 5 of the Third Schedule and pass the test;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B in any tank vehicle other than 
a tank wagon which is not licensed under these rules.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Precautions against 
static charges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All petroleum pipelines entering any tank vehicle loading or unloading area 
shall be electrically continuous and be efficiently earthed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An earth boss with a 
flexible cable having robust clamping device shall be provided adjacent to the 
loading point.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Sound and electrically 
continuous hoses or metal pipes shall only be used for loading or unloading of a 
tank vehicle. Where stand pipes or metallic loading arms are provided, swivel 
joints shall be electrically continuous.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The tank, filling pipe 
and the chassis of the tank vehicle shall, during loading of a tank vehicle, be 
efficiently bonded and connected with the earth boss referred to in sub-rule (2) 
by means of a flexible metal wire or tape.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The bonding and 
earthing connections shall not be broken until loading of a tank vehicle has 
been completed and the filling and dip pipes thereof have been securely closed.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Dip rod, if used, 
shall be lowered into the tank or compartment before loading of petroleum 
starts; such a rod shall not be completely raised above the liquid level during 
or within one minute of the completion of such loading.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No tank vehicle shall 
be loaded at a rate exceeding one metre per second at the delivery end of the 
filling pipe until the filling pipe is completely submerged in petroleum and 
thereafter the loading rate may be gradually increased but it shall at no time 
exceed six metres per second at the delivery end of the filling pipe:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may specify a faster loading rate in respect of crude petroleum and 
petroleum products which have a relative higher conductivity rate.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> No tank or compartment 
of any tank vehicle which has last carried petroleum Class A, shall be filled 
with petroleum of any other class if the interior thereof has any floating 
non-conducting loose object or water. No tank vehicle shall be subjected to 
splash loading.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Precautions against 
electrical hazards and hazard of a running engine.—No 
mechanically propelled vehicle for the petroleum shall be loaded or unloaded 
until its engine has been stopped and battery is isolated from the electrical 
circuit. The engine shall not be restarted and the battery shall not be 
connected to the electrical circuit until tanks and valves have been securely 
closed:
 
Provided that this rule 
shall not apply in the case of unloading of a tank vehicle into the fuel tank of 
aircraft in accordance with the rules framed under the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 
1934) or in any other case as may be authorized, in writing, by the Chief 
Controller subject to such conditions as he may specify in that behalf.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Precautions against 
movements of vehicles during loading or unloading.—Petroleum 
shall not be loaded into or unloaded from a vehicle until its wheels have been 
secured by efficient brakes or by scotching and in the case of animal-drawn 
vehicle until the animals have been unhitched and removed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Precaution against 
product contamination.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall load or unload any tank vehicle unless he has selected the 
correct filling hose and otherwise satisfied himself that such loading or 
unloading will not result in any dangerous contamination of one class of 
petroleum with another class of petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A tank or compartment 
which carried petroleum Class A shall not be filled with any other class of 
petroleum until such tank or compartment has been completely drained of residual 
oil and its discharge faucet and emergency control valve have been closed 
firmly.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Filling discharge 
faucet and dip pipes to be kept closed.—Except 
during the operation of loading or emptying a tank vehicle, the filling pipe, 
discharge faucet and dip pipe all be kept securely closed. Where the filling 
pipes are not provided with a liquid seal, the covers shall be locked or sealed 
except during the operation of loading a tank vehicle and the keys shall not be 
carried on the vehicle or the trailer.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Restrictions on 
loading and unloading of petroleum at night.—Except 
where approved electric lights as specified in Chapter IV are exclusively used, 
the loading or unloading of tank vehicles, carrying petroleum shall be performed 
between the hours of sunrise and sunset.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Prohibition of 
fires and smoking.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fire or other artificial light capable of igniting inflammable vapour shall 
be allowed on any vehicle containing petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B and 
Class C in bulk.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall smoke 
while on or attending such a vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No article or 
substance capable of causing fire or explosion shall be carried on such a 
vehicle.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Repair of tank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No tank which has carried petroleum shall be repaired by welding, brazing, 
soldering or hot-riveting unless it has been examined by a competent responsible 
person and certified in writing by such person to be free from inflammable 
vapours or oil.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The certificate issued 
by the competent and responsible person under sub-rule (1) shall be preserved by 
the repairer for a period of at least three months and shall be produced for 
examination on demand by an Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All repairs to tanks 
which have contained petroleum shall be carried out by qualified and experienced 
persons.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All the compartments 
of the tank shall be tested after each repair in the manner laid down in para 5 
of the Third Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Special provisions 
for motor conveyances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No motor conveyance carrying passengers on hire shall carry petroleum other 
than—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  petroleum in the tank incorporated in the conveyance, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  petroleum not exceeding 100 litres in quantity intended to be used to 
generate motive power for the conveyance of that vehicle and kept in the manner 
provided in sub-section (2) of section 8 of the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> During the filling or 
replenishment of the fuel tank of a motor conveyance licensed for the carriage 
of more than six passengers on hire, the driver or other person in charge of 
such conveyance shall not allow any passenger to remain therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All petroleum 
containers carried in a motor conveyance carrying passengers on hire shall be 
free from leaks and be securely closed and shall be placed in a specially 
prepared receptacle which is not accessible to passengers in such conveyance and 
is not on the roof.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>87</number> Application.—The 
rules in this Part apply only to the transport of petroleum by means of 
pipelines other than those in any area in which operation for the winning of 
natural petroleum, or natural gas or both are carried on or within the limits of 
refineries and installations.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Right of way to be 
acquired.—No 
pipeline and installation connected with a pipeline, shall be constructed 
without acquiring the necessary land, leasements and right for the construction 
thereof and for the unhindered access thereto for inspection, maintenance, 
repairs, replacements and patrolling.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>89</number> Approval of the 
design and route of the pipeline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No pipeline shall be laid without the prior written approval of the Chief 
Controller of the route of the pipeline, and of the design, construction and 
working thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the approval of 
the Chief Controller is sought for the laying of a pipeline, the person desirous 
of laying the pipeline shall submit to the Chief Controller—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a comprehensive project report, accompanied by all necessary drawings, 
calculation giving references to recognize code or codes followed, giving full 
details of the design, construction and testing of the pipeline and its 
components, the route along which the pipeline will be laid and the manner of 
laying, the class or classes of petroleum proposed to be transported in the 
pipeline and provisions proposed to be made for the maintenance and patrolling 
of the pipeline;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>90</number> Design of pipeline 
and attachments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The pipeline shall be constructed of suitable steel which is safe for the 
conditions under which it is to be used.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The pipeline and its 
components shall be designed and constructed in accordance with a code 
recognised by the Chief Controller or OISD Standard-141 regarding design and 
construction requirements for cross country hydrocarbon pipelines and shall be 
capable of withstanding a pressure which shall not be less than the maximum 
working pressure thereof plus an allowance for surge pressure, as anticipated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Provision shall be 
made for thermal expansion or contraction of the pipeline and for the prevention 
of excessive stresses on the pipeline or its anchorages, guides and connections.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The pipeline shall be 
protected by a casing of steel pipe or by increasing the thickness of its wall 
or in any other manner approved by the Chief Controller and any other authority 
having jurisdiction to prevent damage to the pipeline from usual external 
conditions which may be encountered in railway crossings, road crossings, river 
or water course crossings, bridges, long self supported spans, unstable ground, 
vibrations, weight of special attachments or thermal forces.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> By-pass relief valves, 
pressure limiting stations or automatic shut down equipment of approved design 
shall be provided in the pipeline to prevent rising at any time of the pressure 
in the pipeline to a pressure which exceeds the designed internal pressure by 
more than ten per cent.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Isolation valves shall 
be installed at each of the following locations:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  on the suction end and the discharge end of the pump station in a 
manner that permits isolation of the pump station equipment in the event of an 
emergency;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  on each line entering or leaving the installation in a manner that 
permits isolation of the installation from other facilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  on each main line at locations along the pipeline system that will 
minimise damage from accidental product discharge, as appropriate for the 
terrain in open country or for the location near cities or other populated 
areas;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  on each lateral take off from a trunk line in a manner that permits 
shutting off the lateral without interrupting the flow in the trunk line;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  on each side of a water crossing that is more than 30 m wide from 
high-water mark to high-water mark;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>f</number>  on each side of a reservoir holding water for human consumption.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>91</number> Laying of pipeline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Pipeline shall be laid in the most favourable route, avoiding as far as 
possible, known obstructions and areas in which unusual external conditions 
prevail.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Pipeline shall be laid 
below the ground level except where laying thereof above the ground level is 
desirable for typographical, economic or other special reasons.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an underground 
pipeline has to cross any existing underground water or gas line, cable, drain 
or other services, the pipeline shall be laid at least thirty centimetres below 
such services in a manner that will not obstruct access to such services for 
inspection, repair, or maintenance.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The number of bends in 
the pipeline shall be kept to the minimum by proper grading of trenches or 
supports at crossing and other obstacles.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The route of 
underground sections of a pipeline shall be indicated by markers and not less 
than two such markers shall be visible from any point along the route.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>92</number> Protection against 
corrosion.—The 
pipeline shall be protected against corrosion by suitable coating, strapping and 
where necessary by cathodic protection.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>93</number> Hydrostatic testing 
of pipeline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before transporting petroleum for the first time, each pipeline or completed 
sections thereof shall be filled with water and the pressure in the line or 
section, as the case may be, raised to 1.1 times the design internal pressure 
and maintained for a period of at least 24 hours or as per procedure laid down 
in the relevant pipelines design code recognized by Chief Controller. A pipeline 
or a section thereof showing any significant drop of pressure during the period 
of testing shall not be used for transporting petroleum until necessary repairs 
have been carried out and satisfactory retest done.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The test specified in 
sub-rule (1) shall be carried out at least once every 12 months in each 
completed pipeline section which crosses an area where there is danger of water 
pollution by any leakage:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may, subject to such conditions as may be specified by him in this 
behalf, allow retesting of such sections of the pipelines as are protected by 
sleeves or otherwise—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  to contain or prevent leakage at longer intervals, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  by filling them with petroleum in place of water for the purposes of 
test.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of 
sub-rule (2) shall not apply to cross country pipelines, for which new 
technologies are available.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>94</number> Shut-down of 
pipelines.—Except 
when shut-down for maintenance work, a pipeline when not in operation shall be 
shut down under pressure and a careful record made of the pressure during the 
shut-down period. Any significant drop in pressure shall be deemed to render the 
pipeline unfit for transport of petroleum until it is repaired and tested in 
accordance with rule 98 and on significant drop in shut-down pressure is 
observed and it passes the test specified in rule 93.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>95</number> Patrolling of 
pipeline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The whole of every pipeline shall be efficiently patrolled by company owning the 
pipeline—
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Telegraph or telephone 
or radio communication facilities shall be provided at frequent intervals along 
the pipeline:
 
Provided that one such 
communication channel shall suffice for a series of parallel pipelines laid 
close to each other:
 
Provided further that 
nothing in this sub-rule shall apply to a pipeline if the length thereof does 
not exceed two kilometres.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>96</number> Checking of gauges.—Tank 
gauges or gauges at intermediate or booster pump stations shall be checked 
atleast once a year.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>97</number> Additions and 
alterations in the pipeline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No addition or alteration to a pipeline shall be carried out without the 
previous approval of the Chief Controller in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person desirous 
of carrying out any additions or alterations in any pipeline shall submit to the 
Chief Controller an application along with—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  three copies of a drawing to scale and a full descriptive note of the 
proposed additions and alterations and the purpose thereof, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of the 
drawings and fee under sub-rule (2) and after eliciting such additional 
information as may be required, the Chief Controller shall, if he is satisfied, 
approve the proposed additions or alterations subject to such conditions as he 
may deem fit.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>98</number> Repair and 
maintenance of pipeline.—No 
maintenance or repair involving cutting or rewelding of any pipeline shall be 
carried out except under following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  an experienced engineer shall inspect the section requiring 
maintenance or repair before the work is undertaken and issue a written permit 
specifying therein the precautions to be observed and the procedure to be 
followed for carrying out the work. The permit so issued shall be preserved by 
the owner of the pipeline for a period of six months;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  all work involving cutting or welding shall be carried out by an 
experienced person in accordance with the permit referred to in clause (i);
 </section><section>
       
<number>iii</number>  the section of the pipeline shall be isolated and drained before 
starting repairs or maintenance;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  only mechanical cutters shall be used for cutting the pipeline or any 
connection thereof unless the section of the pipeline and its connections have 
been purged with an inert gas;
 </section><section>
       
<number>v</number>  no hot work shall be carried out on any pipeline until the section 
thereof requiring repair has been isolated, drained and purged with inert gas or 
steam or kept filled with water or until such section has been prepared in a 
manner approved in writing by the experienced engineer;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  the section of the pipeline in which repairs or maintenance work has 
been carried out shall be used for transporting petroleum until such sections 
are replaced with hydrostatically pretested sections and the repaired weld 
joints pass the radiography test;
 </section><section>
      
<number>vii</number>  no section of any pipeline and no valve fitted to it shall be 
separated until an efficient electrical bond has been established between the 
parts to be so separated which shall not be broken until the separated parts 
have been rejoined.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>99</number> Relaying or repairs 
to a pipeline in public interest.—Where 
the Chief Controller is of the opinion that it is in the interest of public 
safety to do so, he may, by a notice in writing given to the owner of the 
pipeline, require such owner, to relay, renew or repair such pipeline in 
accordance with such requirements as may be specified in such notice.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>100</number> Power of 
inspection and examination.—The 
Chief Controller or Controller may at any time inspect and examine any pipeline, 
and the owner thereof or persons operating or using the pipeline and the person 
on whose land such pipeline is situated or his representative shall facilitate 
such inspection and examination and answer all inquiries put by the Chief 
Controller or Controller in regard to such pipeline.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>101</number> Reports of fire or 
major leakage.—The 
occurrence of any fire or major leakage in a pipeline and connected facilities 
thereof shall be reported immediately by the person for the time being incharge 
of the pipeline to the nearest Magistrate or office-in-charge of the nearest 
police station and to the Chief Controller by telephone/fax and also by telegram 
at his telegraphic address, namely “Explosives Nagpur”.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>102</number> Restriction on 
electric installation and apparatus.—Save 
as provided in this Chapter, no electric wiring shall be installed and no 
electric apparatus shall be used in any refinery, installation, storage shed, 
services station or in any other place where petroleum is refined, blended, 
stored, loaded or unloaded.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>103</number> Hazardous area.—For 
the purpose of this Chapter, an area shall be deemed to be a hazardous area, 
where—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  petroleum having flash point below 650 C 
or any inflammable gas or vapour in a concentration capable of ignitions is 
likely to be present;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  petroleum or any inflammable liquid having flash point above 65°C is 
likely to be refined, blended, handled or stored at above its flash point.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>104</number> Classification of 
hazardous area.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A hazardous area shall be deemed to be—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a zone “0” area, if inflammable gas or vapours are expected to be 
continuously present in the area; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a zone “1” area, if inflammable gases or vapours are likely to be 
present in the area under normal operating conditions; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  a zone “2” area, if inflammable gases or vapours are likely to be 
present in the area only under abnormal operating conditions or failure or 
rupture of an equipment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
as to whether hazardous area is a zone “0” area or a zone “1” or a zone “2” 
area, the decisions thereon of the Chief Controller shall be final.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>105</number> Extent of 
hazardous area.—The 
extent of hazardous area shall be as laid down in the Fourth Schedule:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may, increase or reduce the extent of hazardous area where there are 
special circumstances which, in his opinion, warrant such increase or reduction, 
and the persons affected shall be informed of his decision.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>106</number> Fixed electric 
apparatus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No electric apparatus shall be allowed in a zone “0” area:
 
Provided that this 
sub-rule shall not prohibit the use in a zone “0” area of an intrinsically safe 
apparatus of a type approved in writing by the Chief Controller and in 
connection with an intrinsically safe circuit, where use of such apparatus 
cannot be completely excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All electric apparatus 
installed or used in a zone “1” area shall be either—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a flame proof or intrinsically safe apparatus of a type or types 
approved in writing by the Chief Controller, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  an industrial-type apparatus house in an enclosure or a room which 
has been made safe by pressurizing or purging with a plenum of atmosphere free 
from significant concentration of any inflammable gas or vapour and so arranged 
and inter locked that in case of failure of the pressurizing or purging agent, 
the electricity supply is automatically cut off or a warning is automatically 
given to a person in attendance who shall take suitable measures to prevent a 
hazard.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All electric apparatus 
installed or used in a zone “2” area shall, be either—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  A non-sparking apparatus of a type approved by the Chief Controller; 
or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  an apparatus of any of the types permitted under sub-rule (2).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the approval of 
the Chief Controller is sought for any type of electric apparatus for use in 
hazardous area, the person desirous of manufacturing the apparatus shall submit 
to the Chief Controller—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a comprehensive report accompanied by all necessary drawings, 
calculations giving references to recognised code or codes followed, full 
details of design and construction and necessary test certificates from the 
recognised bodies in respect of the apparatus and its components;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>107</number> Fixed electric 
wiring.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
conductors of an intrinsically safe circuit in connection with an intrinsically 
safe apparatus installed in any hazardous area shall be so laid as to prevent 
invasion of such circuit by current arising from contact or electrostatic or 
electromagnetic induction from any other circuit. Conductors of intrinsically 
safe circuits shall be effectively protected against mechanical damage.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All electric wiring in 
a hazardous area, other than the conductors of an intrinsically safe circuit, 
shall be effectively sealed at all joints, mechanically protected and adequately 
supported throughout its length and shall consist of—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  approved armoured cable with correctly designed terminations, complete 
with armour clamps, the armouring being carried and electrical clamps to provide 
mechanical support to the cable and electrical continuity; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  approved metal sheathed cable with correctly designed and installed 
terminations; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  single or multicorde insulated cables accommodated in solid drawn 
heavy gauge screwed galvanized conduits used in conjunction with approved 
flameproof fittings, the conduit being sealed at both ends and installed in such 
a manner as to permit internal condensation to drain to a point or points from 
which it may be removed; where a conduit runs from a zone “1” area to zone “2” 
area or an area which is not hazardous area, an adequate seal shall be provided 
outside the boundary of zone “1” area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  single or multicored mineral insulated cable of approved type in 
conjunction with approved flame-proof type glands at all joints and 
terminations;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  bare conductors contained in an approved flameproof or forming part of 
an intrinsically safe circuit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Insulated cables 
without metallic sheathing or armouring but accommodated in a conduct shall not 
be buried in the open ground in any hazardous area.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The electric supply 
circuits of each electric pump in a hazardous area shall be—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  separately protected by a fuse or circuit breaker set to operate when 
the current in the circuit so exceeds the rated current for such a period of 
time as to involve danger; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  provided with an individual isolating switch at the main supply point 
for each electric pump including its integral lighting system, if any.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If the Chief 
Controller is satisfied that the requirements of sub-rules (1) and (2) may be 
modified or relaxed in any class of electric wiring, he may authorize such 
modification or relaxation for such period and subject to such conditions as he 
may think fit.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>108</number> Earthing and 
bonding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All electrical systems and equipments and all structures, plants and other 
non-current-carrying metallic parts of major electric apparatus or any major 
metallic object in any place where petroleum is refined, blended, stored, loaded 
or unloaded shall be efficiently earthed; the resistance value of and earthing 
system of the general mass of the earth, shall not be more than—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  4 ohms in the case of electrical systems and equipment or a valve that 
ensures the operation of the protective device in the electrical circuit, 
whichever is lower, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  10 ohms in the case of all non-current-carrying metallic parts of 
major electric apparatus or any major metallic object.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All joints in 
pipeline, valves, plants, storage tanks and associated facilities and equipments 
for petroleum shall be made electrically continuous by bonding or otherwise, the 
resistance value between each joint shall not exceed 1 ohm.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A piping which is not 
in electrical contact with the associated tank or vessel shall be efficiently 
connected to such tank or vessel by a flexible conductor and earthed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>109</number> Cathodic 
protection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Cathodic protection system where employed shall be designed and installed in 
accordance with the current recognized practice and so maintained as—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  not to affect adversely metallic bodies in the zone of protection; and

 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  to eliminate the danger of sparking in a hazardous area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The metallic 
structures, pipelines, valves, plants and associated equipments under cathodic 
protection shall not be broken for repair or maintenance unless a heavy gauge 
conducting cable is clamped to each side of the intended break for establishing 
between them an electrical bond and the cable shall remain clamped until repair 
or maintenance work is completed and the break rejoined.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>110</number> Protection against 
stray current.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where high values of stray currents are likely to exist, both the rails of spur 
lines shall be insulated from a railway siding which is used for the loading or 
unloading of tank wagons.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On electrified railway 
systems, live-contact rails and overhead electric lines shall be terminated 
outside the area where tank wagons are loaded or unloaded; such rails or 
overhead lines shall not be allowed within a refinery or an installation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No joint in a pipeline 
or associated equipments shall be broken save as provided in sub-rule (2) of 
rule 109.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>111</number> Portable electric 
apparatus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall instal or use in a hazardous area any portable electric lamp or 
apparatus other than a portable lamp or apparatus of a type approved by the 
Chief Controller after such examination and test and for such application as he 
may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No mains operated 
portable lamp shall be operated at a voltage exceeding 25 volts above the earth:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may, at his discretion, allow higher operating voltage not exceeding 
55 volts above earth.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All portable lamps or 
apparatus other than a self-contained lamp or apparatus shall be connected to 
the mains in such manner and used under such conditions as the Chief Controller 
may specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>112</number> Maintenance of 
approved electric apparatus and wiring.—All 
electric apparatus and wiring in a hazardous area shall at all times be so 
maintained as to retain the characteristic on which their approval has been 
granted.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>113</number> Repair and test 
work.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
flame-proof or intrinsically safe apparatus shall be opened and no work likely 
to impair the safety characteristics of such apparatus or electric wiring 
connected thereto shall be carried out until all voltage has been cut off from 
the said apparatus or wiring. The voltage shall not be restored thereto until 
the work has been completed and the safety characteristics provided in 
connection with the apparatus and wiring have been fully restored. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this rule, use of soldering apparatus or other means 
involving flame, fire or heat or use of industrial type apparatus in a zone “1” 
area shall be permitted for the purposes of effecting repairs and testing and 
alternations, provided that the area in which such apparatus or wiring has been 
installed, has first been made safe and certified by a competent person after 
testing with an approved gas-testing apparatus to be safe and free from 
inflammable vapours, gases or liquids and is maintained in such conditions, so 
long as the work is in progress.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>114</number> Certificate of 
electric installation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before engineering any electric circuit and any electric apparatus in hazardous 
area for the first time and after each repair, maintenance or alteration work 
carried out in such circuit or apparatus, a competent person shall issue a 
certificate under his signature to the effect that the circuit and the apparatus 
have the safety characteristics upon which their use in such area has been 
approved.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The certificate 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be preserved by the occupier of the premises 
and shall be produced to the Inspector on demand:
 
Provided that the 
certificate issued for each repair and maintenance work need not be preserved 
for a period exceeding six months.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>115</number> Precautions 
against corrosion.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where necessary, all electric apparatus and equipments and conduits carrying 
electric wiring in a hazardous area shall be regularly treated with a suitable 
protective paint.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The certification 
label indicating the flame-proof or intrinsically safe nature of the apparatus 
or equipment shall not be painted over or treated in any manner to impair the 
legibility of the particulars written, stamped or embossed on such label.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>116</number> Licence for 
storage.—Save 
as provided in sections 7, 8 and 9 of the Act no person shall store petroleum 
except under and in accordance with a licence granted under these rules:
 
Provided that no licence 
shall be necessary—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  for the storage of petroleum in well-headed tanks; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  for the storage of petroleum as transit cargo within the limits of a 
port subject to such conditions as may be specified by the Conservator.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>117</number> Precautions 
against fire.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall smoke in any installation, storage shed or service station save 
in places specifically authorized by the licensing authority for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall carry 
matches, fuses or other appliances capable of producing ignition or explosion in 
any installation or storage shed which is used for storage of petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No fire, furnace or 
other source of heat or light capable of igniting inflammable vapour shall be 
allowed in any installation, storage shed or service station save in places 
specially authorised by the licensing authority for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>(i) An adequate number 
of portable dry chemical powder or any other fire extinguisher capable of 
extinguishing oil fires shall always be kept in every storage shed and small 
Class B or C installations at strategic points and all persons employed at such 
locations shall be conversant with the use of such fire extinguishers.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Scale of fire 
fighting provided in other areas of installation should be as per the 
requirement given to OISD Standard-117 for all installations approved by the 
Chief Controller after publication of the original standard OISD-117. For 
installations existing prior to the publication of the standard the fire 
fighting facilities shall be improved to the extent feasible (keeping this 
standard in mind) and approved by the Chief Controller.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>118</number> Supervision of 
operations within an installation, service station or storage shed.—All 
operations within an installation, service station or storage shed shall be 
conducted under supervision of an experienced responsible agent or supervisor 
who is conversant with the terms and conditions of the licence held for the 
installation, service station or storage shed, as the case may be, and those 
persons should have proper safety training.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>119</number> Cleanliness of 
installation, service station or storage shed.—The 
ground in the interior of an installation or service station and the protected 
areas surrounding any installation, service station or storage shed shall be 
kept clean and free from all vegetation, waste material and rubbish.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>120</number> Drainage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All enclosures surrounding above ground tanks in an installation shall be 
provided with proper drainage facilities in such a way that no water is allowed 
to accumulate in the enclosure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No part of the 
enclosure referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be below the level of the 
surrounding ground within the protected area.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where drainage is 
effected by means of a pipe, the pipe shall be fitted with a valve which is 
capable of being operated from the outside of the enclosure or with any other 
arrangement approved in writing by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All valves and other 
opening for draining off water shall be kept closed except when water is being 
drained off.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The nature of the 
drainage arrangements and the position of all openings and valves therein shall 
be shown in the plan submitted with the application for a licence.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>121</number> Exclusion of 
unauthorized persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The protected area surrounding every installation and storage shed shall be 
surrounded by a wall or fence of at least 1.8 metres in height.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case of service 
station 1.2 metre high boundary wall or fence on sides other than the drive way 
shall be provided.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Precautions shall be 
taken to prevent unauthorised persons from having access to any storage shed or 
installation.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>122</number> Petroleum only to 
be stored.—No 
installation, service station or storage shed shall, without permission in 
writing from the Chief Controller be used for any purpose other than the storage 
and distribution of petroleum and for purpose directly connected therewith.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>123</number> Marking of 
capacity of tanks.—The 
capacity in litres or kilolitres of every above ground tank in an installation 
shall be conspicuously marked on the tank.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>124</number> Construction of 
tanks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every tank or receptacle for the storage of petroleum in bulk other than a 
well-head tank shall be constructed of iron or steel in accordance with the 
codes or specifications approved by the Indian Standards Institution or any 
other code or specifications approved in writing by the Chief Controller:
 
Provided that if the 
properties of petroleum to be stored so required or for any other reason it is 
necessary so to do, tanks or other receptacles may be built of materials other 
than iron or steel.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The tanks or other 
receptacles shall be erected on firm foundations or supports of non-combustible 
material in accordance with sound engineering practice.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The height of a 
storage tank shall not exceed one and a half times its diameter or twenty-metres, 
whichever is less.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub-rule, the height of a tank shall be the height from its 
bottom to top curb angles.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An air space of not 
less than five per cent. of the total capacity of the tank or the space 
prescribed in the code or specification to in sub-rule (1), whichever is less, 
shall be kept in each tank.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>125</number> Protection against 
corrosion.—All 
tanks or other receptacles for the storage of petroleum in bulk, other than 
well-head tanks installed on the ground or below the round, shall be protected 
against corrosion by the use of protective coatings or cathodic protection or by 
any other means approved by the licensing authority.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>126</number> Testing of tanks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Storage tanks or other receptacles for the storage of petroleum in bulk, other 
than well-head tanks, after being installed and secured in the final position or 
after undergoing re-installation or any major repair, shall, before being put 
into use, be tested by water pressure by a competent person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The water used for 
testing shall be free from petroleum and shall not be passed through any pipe or 
pump ordinarily used for the conveyance of petroleum:
 
Provided that where the 
licensing authority is satisfied that it is not reasonably possible to convey 
water by pipes or pumps other than those ordinarily used for conveyance of 
petroleum, he may permit use of a petroleum pipe or pump for the conveyance of 
water subject to such conditions as he may impose.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The competent person 
carrying out the test as required under sub-rule (1) shall issue a certificate 
in the proforma given below; the certificate so issued shall be submitted to the 
licensing authority along with the application for the grant or amendment of a 
licence, or, in the case of any major repair, after each such repair.
 
Proforma of Certificate 
of Tank Testing
 
[See rule 126]
 
In respect 
of........................................of 
size..................................... (number of tanks) (diameter and height 
or length of each tank) ................................ and 
capacity...................................respectively, installed within the 
installation/service station of..........................(delete words not 
applicable) ...................... (full name of occupier of 
installation/service station as the case may 
be)................................................. 
at..........................(Name of place, police station, District, State) 
covered by licence No........................
 
(To be filled in the 
case of amendment of licence or repair of tank)
 
Certified that I have in 
accordance with rule 126 of the Petroleum Rules, 2002, tested the tanks 
described above by water pressure after they had been installed and secured in 
the final position/repaired and found them free from leak and suitable for the 
storage of petroleum (delete words not applicable).
 
Date of 
test........................                                                                                               
................................................... 
 
Full signature of the 
competent person issuing the certificate
 
His recognized 
qualification.....................................................
 
His full name and postal 
address............................................
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>127</number> Earthing of tank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every tank or other receptacle for the storage of petroleum in bulk, other than 
a well head tank or tanks of less than 50,000 litres capacity containing 
petroleum Class C shall be electrically connected with the earth in an efficient 
manner by not less than two separate and distinct connections placed at the 
opposite extremities of such tank or receptacle. The roof and all metal 
connections of such tank or receptacle shall be in efficient electrical contact 
with the body of such tank or receptacle.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The connections and 
contacts required under sub-rule (1) shall have a few joints as possible. All 
joints shall be riveted, welded or bolted and also soldered to ensure both 
mechanical and electrical soundness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The resistance to 
earth shall not exceed 7 ohms and the resistance to any part of the fitting to 
the earth plate or to any other part of fitting shall not exceed 2 ohms.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>128</number> Testing of earth 
connections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The connections and contacts of the tank or receptacle required under rule 127 
shall be inspected and tested by a competent person at least once in every 
twelve months by means of a direct reading instrument, such as a Megar.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The testing instrument 
referred to in sub-rule (1), if capable of producing a spark, shall be so 
shielded as to be incapable of igniting petroleum vapour.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A record of such 
inspections and test shall be maintained by the licensee in the licensed 
premises and shall be produced on demand by any inspector.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>129</number> Night working.—No 
installation storage shed shall be open and no work in any installation or 
storage shed shall be permitted between sunset and sunrise except where approved 
electric lights conforming to the provisions of Chapter IV are exclusively used.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>130</number> Certificate of 
safety.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
certificate of safety in proforma given below this rule and signed by a 
competent person shall be furnished to the licensing authority before any 
petroleum is stored in an installation or a service station for the first time 
or whenever any additions or alterations to the enclosure walls and embankments 
are carried out or when any tank is installed or its position shifted.
 
Proforma of Certificate 
of Safety
 
[See rule 130]
 
I, 
.........................., hereby certify that I have inspected the petroleum 
service station/installation described below on...........(date) and it has been 
constructed as per plan approved by Chief Controller/Controller, vide 
letter No. ................ dated ................. and the service 
station/installation, in my opinion is safe for storage of petroleum.
 </section><section>
         
<number>1</number> Name and Address of occupier 
.............................................................
 </section><section>
         
<number>2</number>  Location of the service 
station/installation..............................................
 
              
(Plot No., Village/Town, District, State)
 </section><section>
         
<number>3</number>  Description of facilities of the service station/installation.
 <subsection>
              
<number>A</number>   Tanks:
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>   Aboveground tanks:
 <subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>a</number>  Identification No., size, capacity, product, class of petroleum
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>b</number>  Whether enclosure walls provided, if so, nature of enclosure walls, 
its capacity, provision of drain pipe and valve
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>c</number>  Nature and description of fittings provided
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>   Underground tanks:
 <subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>a</number>  Identification No., size, capacity, product, class of petroleum
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>b</number>  Nature of pit, soil cover, fastening arrangement
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>c</number>  Nature of top cover (whether soil/RCC)
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                      
<number>d</number>  Nature and description of fittings provided
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
              
<number>B</number>   Filling/storage shed:
 
              
Whether provided as per approved plan
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>C</number>   Tank lorry and/or Tank wagon loading/unloading:
 <subsubsection>
                  
<number>i</number>  Number of bays and points provided
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>ii</number>  Type of loading and unloading facilities
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
              
<number>D</number>   Pipelines:
 <subsubsection>
                  
<number>i</number>  Size and specification of pipeline(s)
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>ii</number>  Test pressure of pipeline............................kg/cm2
 
                       
(Tested by ......................... on...................)
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
              
<number>E</number>   Electrical fittings/equipments:
 <subsubsection>
                  
<number>i</number>  Pumps (specification, make and CCE approval reference for each)
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>ii</number>  Starters
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>iii</number>  Junction Box
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                
<number>iv</number>  Switches
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>v</number>  Light fittings
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                
<number>vi</number>  Others
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>F</number>   Earthing, bonding and electrical continuity:
 <subsubsection>
                  
<number>i</number>  Earthing of tanks, pumps, bulk loading/unloading facilities
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>ii</number>  Bonding of pipeline joints
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 
<number>iii</number>  Earthing resistance at each point
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>G</number>   Nature of Fencing/boundary wall:
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>H</number>   Description of fire fighting facilities provided:
 </subsection></section><section>
           
<number>4</number>   Remarks:
 
Place: 
..........................
 
Date: 
........................                                                                       
Signature of the competent person
 
 
 
Particulars of recognition 
by Chief Controller
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) Anybody intending 
to be recognised as competent person shall possess the qualification and 
experience prescribed in para (A) of Form XX and shall submit to the Chief 
Controller an application in the form prescribed in para (B) of the same form. 
Every application shall be accompanied by a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred. 
The Chief Controller shall register such application and within a period of 
sixty days of the date of receipt of the application, and after having satisfied 
himself with regard to competence and professional ethics either recognise the 
applicant as a competent person or reject the application specifying the reason 
therefor.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The Chief Controller 
may after giving an opportunity to such person to be heard revoke the 
recognition—
 <subsubsection>
       
<number>a</number>  if he has reason to believe that such person has violated any 
condition stipulated in the letter of recognition or has carried out a test, 
examination and inspection or has acted, in a manner inconsistent with the 
intent or the purpose of these rules; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       
<number>b</number>  for any other person to be recovered in writing.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>131</number> Prior approval of 
specifications and plans of premises proposed to be licensed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person desiring to obtain a licence to import and store petroleum in Form 
XIV, Form XV, Form XVI or in Special Form, as the case may be, shall submit to 
the licensing authority and application alongwith—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  specification and plans drawn to scale, in duplicate, clearly 
indicating—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  the manner in which the provisions prescribed in these rules will be 
complied with;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  the premises proposed to be licensed, the area of which shall be 
distinctly coloured or otherwise marked;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  the surroundings and all protected works lying within 100 metres of 
the edge of all facilities which are proposed to be licensed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>iv</number>  the position, capacity, materials of construction and ground and 
elevation view of all storage tanks, enclosures around tanks, all valves, 
filling and discharge points, vent pipes, dip pipes, storage and filling sheds, 
pumps, fire-fighting facilities and all other building and facilities forming 
part of the premises proposed to be licensed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>v</number>  the areas reserved for different classes of petroleum including 
petroleum exempted under section 11 of the Act; and 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees four hundred paid in the manner specified in 
rule 13.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Chief 
Controller, after scrutiny of the specification and plans and after making such 
enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that petroleum may be stored in the 
premises proposed to be licensed, he shall return to the applicant one copy each 
of the specifications and plans signed by him conveying his sanction subject to 
such conditions as he may specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>132</number> Pumping.—No 
internal combustion engine or electric motor in an installation shall be used 
for driving pumps for pumping petroleum save in a pump house or pumping area 
specially constructed for the purpose and approved by the Chief Controller.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>133</number> Identification 
mark on licensed premises.—Every 
installation, storage shed or service station under these rules shall have 
prominently marked thereon the number of the licence held for it.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>134</number> Posting up of rules and 
conditions.—An 
extract of rules 3 to 12, 102 to 115, 116 to 134, 146 to 148 and 152 to 160 and 
of the conditions of the licence shall be exhibited in a conspicuous place in 
every licensed installation, service station or storage 
shed.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>135</number> Petroleum in the 
possession of Defence Forces of the Union.—Nothing 
in rules 116, 121, 122, 125, 126, 127, 128, 130, 131, 133 and 134 shall apply to 
petroleum in the possession of the Defence Forces of the Union.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>136</number> Application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to petroleum Class C stored otherwise 
than under a licence as provided in section 7 of the Act but shall not apply to 
petroleum Class C in the possession of the Defence Forces of the Union.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
Chapter V shall not apply to petroleum Class C permitted to be stored without a 
licence under section 7 of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>137</number> Restriction of 
Storage.—Petroleum 
Class C shall not be stored together with any other class of petroleum except 
under and in accordance with a licence granted under these rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>138</number> Storage of 
exempted petroleum Class C in bulk.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Petroleum Class C in bulk shall be stored in a tank constructed of iron or steel 
or any other material approved in writing by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The tank referred to 
in sub-rule (1) shall be properly designed and erected and the tank with all its 
fittings shall be so constructed and maintained as to prevent any leakage of 
petroleum.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All tanks of capacity 
exceeding 5,000 litres for the storage of petroleum Class C shall be surrounded 
by an enclosure wall or placed inside a pit, so constructed and maintained as to 
be able to contain without leakage the maximum quantity of petroleum capable of 
being contained in largest tank within such enclosure or pit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A drainage pipe with a 
valve capable of being actuated from outside the enclosure wall shall be 
provided in the enclosure or pit referred to in sub-rule (3) and the valve shall 
be kept closed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A distance of not less 
than 1.5 metres shall be kept clear between protected works and the edge of such 
enclosure wall or pit.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>139</number> Storage of 
petroleum Class C in non-bulk.—Petroleum 
Class C which is not in bulk shall, if the quantity at any one time exceeds 2500 
litres be stored in a storage shed of which either—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  the doorways and openings shall be built up to a height of 30 
centimetres above the floor, or
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  the floor shall be sunk to a depth of 30 centimetres.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>140</number> Prior report of 
storage of petroleum Class C.—Every 
person intending to store petroleum Class C in quantity exceeding 5000 litres 
otherwise than under a licence shall submit the following to the Chief 
Controller before commencing storage:—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  plans drawn to scale of the storage facilities showing compliance of 
rule 138 and site plan of the storage premises and surroundings upto 100 metres 
identifying the locations of premises; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five hundred.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>141</number> Grant of licence.—Licences 
under these rules may be granted by the licensing authorities set forth in the 
First Schedule in the forms specified for the purpose and on payment of a fee 
specified therein.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>142</number> Period for which 
licences may be granted or renewed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence in Form III or form XVII may be granted for such period as the 
licensing authority may deem necessary subject to a maximum of one year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every other licence 
granted or renewed under these rules will remain in force until the 31st day of 
December of the year up to which the licence is granted or renewed subject to a 
maximum of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), the licensing authority 
where it is satisfied that a licence is required for a specific work or festival 
which is not likely to last up to the 31st day of December of the year up to 
which the licence is granted or renewed, may grant or renew a licence for such 
period as is actually necessary.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>143</number> Application for 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
person wishing to obtain or renew a licence under these rules shall submit an 
application in writing to the authority empowered to grant such a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application for the 
grant of a licence to transport petroleum in bulk by road in mechanically 
propelled vehicles shall be in Form VII and to transport petroleum Class A/B in 
bulk on land for onsite fuelling of aircrafts, heavy vehicles/machineries and 
stationary equipment by a mechanically propelled vehicle viz. refueller 
shall be in Form VIII. An application for licence to import and store petroleum 
shall be in Form IX and to decant Kerosene (Petroleum Class B) from mechanically 
propelled vehicles containers shall be in Form X.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>144</number> No-objection 
certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the licensing authority is the Chief Controller or the Controller, as the 
case may be, an applicant for a new licence other than a licence in Forms III, 
XI, XVII, XVIII or XIX shall apply to the District Authority with two copies of 
the site-plan showing the location of the premises proposed to be licensed for a 
certificate to the effect that there is no objection, to the applicant receiving 
a licence for the site proposed and the District Authority shall, if he sees no 
objection, grant such certificate to the applicant who shall forward it to the 
licensing authority with his application Form IX.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every certificate 
issued by the District Authority under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a 
copy of the plan of the proposed site duly endorsed by him under his official 
seal.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Controller 
or the Controller, as the case may be, may refer an application not accompanied 
by certificate granted under sub-rule (1) to the District Authority for his 
observations.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the District 
Authority, either on a reference being made to him or otherwise, intimates, to 
the Chief Controller or the Controller, as the case may be, that any licence 
which has been applied for should not, in his opinion, be granted, such licence 
shall not be issued without the sanction of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The District Authority 
shall complete his inquiry for issuing 
no objection certificate (NOC) under sub-rule (1) and shall complete the 
action for issue or refusal of the NOC, as the case may be, as expeditiously as 
possible but not later than three months from the date of receipt of application 
by him.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>145</number> Particulars of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall be held subject to the conditions 
specified therein and shall contain all the particulars which are contained in 
the Form specified under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> One copy of the plan 
or plans for the licensed premises signed in token of approval by the licensing 
authority shall be attached to the licence which shall form part of such licence, 
and an identical copy shall be filed for record in the office of the licensing 
authority, except in the case of licence in Form XVIII.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>146</number> Prior approval 
necessary for alterations in the licensed premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No alteration shall be carried out in the licensed premises until a drawing or 
drawings showing such alteration has been approved in writing by the licensing 
authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person wishing to 
carry out any alteration in the licensed premises shall submit to the licensing 
authority—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  three copies of a properly drawn plan of the licensed premises showing 
in distinct colour or colours the proposed alteration and the reasons therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a fee of rupees four hundred for scrutiny of the proposed alteration.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the licensing 
authority, after scrutiny of the plan showing the proposed alteration and after 
making such enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that the proposed alteration 
may be carried out, he shall return to the licensee one copy of the plan signed 
by him and conveying his sanction subject to such condition or conditions as he 
may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The holder of the 
licence, shall apply to the licensing authority for the amendment of the licence 
as soon as the sanctioned alteration has been carried out.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>147</number> Amendment of 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any licence granted under these rules may be amended by the authority empowered 
to grant such a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee for amendment 
of a licence shall be rupees five hundred plus the amount, if any, by which the 
fee that would have been payable if the licence had originally been issued in 
the amended form exceeds the fee originally paid for the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A licensee who desires 
to have his licence amended shall submit to the licensing authority—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  an application duly filled in and signed in Form VII if the licence 
has been granted for transport of petroleum in bulk by road, in Form VIII, if 
the licence has been granted for refueller in form XIX, in Form IX, if the 
licence is granted to import and store petroleum; and in Form X, if the licence 
is granted to decant kerosene (Petroleum Class B) from mechanically propelled 
vehicles in containers;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the licence sought to be amended together with the approved plans 
attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  where any alteration in the licensed premises has been carried out 
three copies of the properly drawn plan shown in the alteration sanctioned under 
rule 146 by the licensing authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  fee for the amendment of a licence as specified in sub-rule (2);
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  a certificate of testing of the tank or tanks, if required under rule 
126;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  a certificate of safety, if required under rule 130.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>148</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence may be renewed by the authority empowered to grant such a licence:
 
Provided that a licence 
which has been granted by the Chief Controller may be renewed without alteration 
by a Controller duly authorized by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence granted 
under these rules, other than a licence in Form III or Form XVII may be 
renewable for three calendar years where there has been no contravention of the 
Act or of the rules framed thereunder or of any conditions of the licence so 
renewed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a licence which 
has been renewed for more than one year, is surrendered before its expiry, the 
renewal fee paid for unexpired portion of the licence shall be refunded to the 
licensee provided that no refund of renewal fee shall be made for any calendar 
year during which—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the licensing authority receives the renewed licence for surrender, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  any petroleum is received or stored on the authority of the licence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every application 
under sub-rule (2) shall be made in Form VII, Form VIII, Form IX and Form X, as 
the case may be, and shall be accompanied by the licence which is to be renewed 
together with approved plans attached to the licence, wherever applicable and 
the renewal fee paid in the manner specified in rule 13.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application for 
the renewal of licence shall be made so as to reach the licensing authority at 
least thirty days before the date on which it expires, and if the application is 
so made, the licence shall be deemed to be in force until such date as the 
licensing authority renews the licence or until an intimation that the renewal 
of the licence is refused, has been communicated to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the renewal of a 
licence is refused, the fee paid for the renewal shall be refunded to the 
licensee after deducting therefrom the proportionate fee for the period 
beginning from the date from which the licence was to be renewed up to the date 
on which renewal thereof is refused.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>The same fee shall be 
charged for the renewal of licence for each calendar year as for the grant 
thereof:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  if the application with accompaniments required under sub-rule (4) is 
not received within the time specified in sub-rule (5), the licence shall be 
renewed only on payment of a fee amounting to twice the fee ordinarily payable;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  if such an application with accompaniments is received by the 
licensing authority after the date of expiry but not later than 30 days from the 
date of expiry, the licence may, without prejudice to any other action that may 
be taken in this behalf, be renewed on payment of twice the fee ordinarily 
payable:
 
Provided further that in 
case of an application for the renewal of a licence for a period of more than 
one calendar year at a time, the fee prescribed under clause (i) or clause (ii) 
of the first proviso, if payable, shall be paid only for the first calendar year 
of renewal.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> No licence shall be 
renewed if the application for renewal is received by the licensing authority 
after thirty days of the date of its expiry.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>149</number> Refusal of 
no-objection certificate.—A 
district authority refusing to grant a no-objection certificate under rule 144 
shall record, in writing, the reasons for such refusal and shall furnish to the 
applicant a copy of such order:
 
Provided that before 
refusing to grant a no-objection certificate, the applicant shall be given a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>150</number> Cancellation of 
no-objection certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A no-objection certificate granted under rule 144 shall be liable to be 
cancelled by the District Authority or the State Government, if the District 
Authority or the State Government is satisfied, that the licensee has ceased to 
have any right to use the site for storing petroleum:
 
Provided that before 
cancelling a no-objection certificate, the licensee shall be given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A District Authority 
or a State Government cancelling a no-objection certificate shall record, in 
writing, the reasons for such cancellation and shall immediately furnish to the 
licensee and to the licensing authority concerned, copy of the order cancelling 
the no-objection certificate.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>151</number> Refusal of licence.—A 
licensing authority refusing to grant, amend, renew or transfer a licence, shall 
record his reason for such refusal in writing.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>152</number> Suspension and 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  stand cancelled, if the licensee ceases to have any right to the site 
for storing petroleum;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  stand cancelled, if the no-objection certificate is cancelled by the 
District Authority or the State Government in accordance with sub-rule (1) of 
rule 150;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  be liable to be suspended or cancelled by an order of the licensing 
authority for any contravention of the Act or of any rule thereunder or of any 
condition contained in such licence, or by order of the Central Government, if 
it is satisfied that there are sufficient grounds for doing so:
 
              
Provided that—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  before suspending or cancelling a licence under this rule, the holder 
of the licence shall be given an opportunity of being heard;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  the maximum period of suspension shall not exceed three months; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  the suspension of a licence shall not debar the holder of the licence 
from applying for its renewal in accordance with the provisions of rule 148.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), an opportunity of being heard may not be 
given to the holder of a licence before his licence is suspended or cancelled in 
cases—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  where the licence is suspended by a licensing authority as an interim 
measure for violation of any of the provisions of the Act or these rules, or of 
any conditions contained in such licence and in his opinion such violations is 
likely to cause imminent danger to the public:
 
                 
Provided that where a licence is so suspended, the licensing authority shall 
give the holder of the licence an opportunity of being heard before the order of 
suspension is confirmed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  where the licence is suspended or cancelled by the Central Government, 
if that Government considers that in the public interest or in the interest of 
the security of the State, such opportunity should not be given.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A licensing authority 
or the Central Government suspending or cancelling a licence under sub-rule (1), 
shall record its reason for so doing in writing.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>153</number> Procedure on 
expiration, suspension or cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person licensed to store petroleum shall, on the expiration, suspension or 
cancellation of his licence, forthwith give notice to the District Authority of 
the class and quantity of petroleum in his possession and shall comply with any 
directions which the District Authority may, on the recommendation of the Chief 
Controller, gives in regard to its disposal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The District Authority 
may grant for a term not exceeding three months from the date of expiration, 
suspension or cancellation, as the case may be, a temporary licence for the 
storage of petroleum actually held at the time of the issue of the temporary 
licence:
 
Provided that where the 
expired, suspended or cancelled licence was granted by an authority, other than 
the District Authority, no temporary licence shall be granted without the 
previous consent of such other authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fee chargeable on 
a licence granted under sub-rule (2) shall bear the same proportion to the fee 
charged on the expired or cancelled or suspended licence as the period covered 
by the temporary licence bears to a full year.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>154</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie against any order refusing to grant, amend or renew a 
licence cancelling or suspending a licence to—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  the Central Government, where the order is passed by the Chief 
Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the Chief Controller, where the order is passed by a Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  the immediate official superior to the District Authority, where the 
order is passed by the District Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  the immediate official superior to officer appointed under rule 33 in 
the case of vessels licensed for the carriage of petroleum in bulk.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal against any 
order of the District Authority refusing to grant or cancelling a no-objection 
certificate shall lie to the authority which is immediately superior to the said 
District Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal shall be 
in writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and 
shall be presented within sixty days of the order passed.
 

1[(4) The Appellate 
Authority shall dispose of the appeal within 60 days of receipt of the appeal]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>155</number> Supply of 
rules.—With every 
licence granted for the storage of petroleum, an extract of rules 3 to 12, rules 
102 to 134, rules 146 to 148 and rules 151 to 159 shall be given free of charge 
to the licensee.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>156</number> Transfer of 
licence for storage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The holder of a licence, for the storage of petroleum may, at any time before 
the expiry of the licence, apply to the licensing authority to transfer the 
licence to another person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application for 
the transfer of a licence shall be accompanied by—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a letter signed by the holder of the licence indicating the full name 
and address of the person to whom he wishes to transfer the licence and give 
complete possession of the licensed premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the licence sought to be transferred together with the approved plan 
or plans attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  an application in Form IX duly filled in and signed by the person to 
whom the licence is sought to be transferred;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  a fee of rupees five hundred paid in the manner specified in rule 13.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensing 
authority on receipt of the documents and fee required under sub-rule (2) shall, 
if he approves the transfer, enter upon the licence, under his signature, an 
endorsement to the effect that the licence has been transferred to the person 
named.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person to whom the 
licence is so transferred shall enjoy the same power and be subject to the same 
obligations under the licence as the original licensee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>157</number> Procedure on death 
or disability of licensee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a licensee dies or becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is otherwise 
disabled, the person carrying on the business of such licensee shall not be 
liable to any penalty or confiscation under the Act or these rules of exercising 
the powers granted to the licensee during such time as may reasonably be 
required to allow him to make an application for a new licence in his own name 
for the unexpired portion of the original licence in respect of the year in 
which the licensee dies or becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is 
otherwise disabled:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub-rule shall be deemed to authorize the exercise of any power under this 
sub-rule by any person after the expiry of the period of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application for a 
new licence for the unexpired portion of the original licence shall be 
accompanied by a no-objection certificate issued by the District Authority in 
favour to the person applying for such licence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A fee of rupees two 
hundred shall be charged for a new licence for the unexpired portion of the 
original licence granted to any person applying for it under this rule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>158</number> Loss of licence.—Where 
a licence granted under these rules is lost or accidentally destroyed a 
duplicate may be granted on submission of a copy of plan or plans identical with 
those attached to the licence and on payment of a fee of rupees two hundred.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>159</number> Production of 
licence on demand.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person holding or acting under a licence granted under these rules shall 
produce it, or an authenticated copy of it, at the place to which the licence 
applies, when called upon to do so by any Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Copies of any licence 
may, for the purpose of this rule, be authenticated by the authority which 
granted the licence—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  on payment of a fee of rupees fifty for each authenticated copy; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  on the submission of a copy or copies of the plans identical with the 
approved plan or plans attached to the licence.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>160</number> Procedure on 
reports of infringement.—The 
District Authority shall inform the Chief Controller of the action taken by him 
on any reports of infringements of the Act or of these rules which the Chief 
Controller may make to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>161</number> Executive control 
over authorities.—Every 
authority other than the Central Government, acting under this Chapter shall 
perform its duties subject to the control of the Central Government:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall be deemed to affect the powers of executive control of the Chief 
Controller over the officer subordinate to him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>162</number> Approval of 
refinery.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall refine, crack, reform or blend petroleum unless the project 
report with specifications and plans showing the general arrangements of tanks, 
stills, furnaces, electrical installations, pump houses, arrangement for 
drainage treatment and disposal of effluents, arrangement for fighting fire, 
fencing gates and all plants and buildings at the place where it is proposed to 
refine, crack, reform or blend petroleum (hereinafter in this Chapter referred 
to as the refinery) has been approved by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The design and layout 
of the various block/facilities/process units in new crude oil refineries shall 
be as per design philosophy given in OISD Standard-118. This will apply to new 
crude oil refineries/gas processing installations approved by the Chief 
Controller after publication of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person desiring to 
refine, crack, reform or blend petroleum shall submit to the Chief Controller an 
application along with—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  a copy of the project report and specifications and plans referred to 
in sub-rule (1) in triplicate, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees five thousand paid in the manner specified 
in rule 13.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chief Controller 
on receiving the project report with specifications and plans may require 
submission of such further particulars as he may specify after satisfying 
himself that petroleum can be so refined, cracked, reformed or blended, shall 
return to the applicant one set of the specifications and plans signed by him 
and conveying his sanction subject to such conditions as he may specify.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>163</number> Retention of plans 
and specifications.—A 
copy each of the approved plans and specifications and containing any 
alterations sanctioned under rule 164 from time to time shall be kept at the 
refinery.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>164</number> Alterations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No alterations in refinery involving the general arrangements or the design of 
tanks, stills, furnaces, plants, pump-houses, electric installation or 
fire-fighting facilities shall be carried out without the previous sanction in 
writing of the Chief Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The occupier of a 
refinery wishing to carry out any of the alterations referred to in sub-rule (1) 
shall submit to the Chief Controller an application along with—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  specifications and plans, in triplicate, showing proposed alterations 
together with reason therefor, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  a scrutiny fee of rupees one thousand paid in the manner prescribed 
in rule 13.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Controller 
on receiving the specifications and plans for the alterations and reasons 
therefor, may require submission of such further particulars as he may specify 
and after satisfying himself that the proposed alterations can be carried out, 
return to the applicant one copy of the specifications and plans signed by him 
and conveying his approval subject to such conditions as he may prescribe.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>165</number> Use of fire-proof 
materials.—All 
buildings and facilities in which petroleum is handled shall be built of 
fire-proof materials.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>166</number> Situations of 
storage tanks.—No 
storage tanks for petroleum shall be situated nearer than 90 metres to any 
still, boiler or furnace:
 
Provided that this rule 
shall not apply to a storage tank containing petroleum Class C for use as a fuel 
for a boiler and such a storage tank shall not be larger than is necessary to 
conserve 24 hours fuel for the fire which it services.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>167</number> Situation of 
storage tanks and facilities for liquefied petroleum gases.—No 
storage tank or filling facility for liquefied petroleum gases shall be nearer 
than 90 metres to any still, boiler or furnace or nearer than 30 metres to any 
storage tank, pump-house or any facility for the blending or filling of 
petroleum or to any protected work.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>168</number> Situation of 
flare.—No flare 
shall be situated nearer than 90 metres to any tank, still, pump-house or any 
facility for the refining, cracking, reforming, blending, storage or handling of 
petroleum or liquefied petroleum gas, other than knockout drum and condensate 
recovery pump attached to such flare.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>169</number> Drainage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Adequate arrangements shall be made to ensure that effluents and drainage 
passing from the refinery does not cause pollution of rivers, irrigation 
channels, water reservoirs or foreshore and does not harmfully affect animal or 
vegetable life in any way.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Effluent drainage from 
pump-houses and all other points where oil may be entrained shall be passed 
through an efficient oil interceptor system of adequate size.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All chemical waste 
shall be rendered harmless before they leave the refinery area.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The whole of the 
sewerage shall be independent of other drainage systems.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All drains shall have 
adequate capacity to prevent any flooding or backing-up and be of such 
construction as to prevent leakage from them to the surrounding grounds.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Drains for carrying 
waste chemicals shall be of a type which is not affected by the chemicals in 
question.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Trash racks shall be 
fitted to the drains where there is a possibility of rubbish being carried 
forward and forming a plug.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Manholes shall be 
provided in closed drains where there is an abrupt change of directions and also 
at reasonable intervals in straight sections to permit rodding.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> When vents are 
provided to release gases separated from contaminated effluents in closed 
drains, they shall be sited where they are unlikely to cause danger or 
annoyance.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> All drains shall be 
fitted with fire traps/water seals at suitable points to prevent the passage of 
flame.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Where gas traps are 
provided in the drains they shall be constructed on the upstream side of the oil 
interceptors and such gas traps shall be fitted with vents to liberate the gas 
at such a height that danger or annoyance is not caused.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>170</number> Fire and Smoking.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fire furnace, source of heat or light capable of igniting inflammable vapours 
shall be allowed except in the firing space of stills and boilers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No smoking shall be 
allowed except in spaces or buildings specially approved for the purpose by the 
Chief Controller.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>171</number> Permits to carry 
out maintenance and repair work.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No maintenance or repair work and no entry into confined spaces including a 
closed drain or manhole shall be permitted except under and in accordance with 
the conditions of a written permit as per OISD Standard-105 issued by a 
competent person authorised by the occupier of the refinery.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The competent person 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall, before issuing the permit, satisfy himself by 
inspecting and testing, whenever necessary, that the conditions of the vessel, 
site or equipment are entirely safe for the work which is to be undertaken and 
shall specify on the permit the conditions under which the work can be carried 
out safely.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Permits for carrying 
out maintenance or repair work shall be issued for limited and stated period 
during which known conditions will remain safe and such permits shall not be 
renewed without re-inspection and re-testing of the vessel, site or equipment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All gas tests for the 
purpose of issuing a permit shall be carried out by suitably trained persons by 
an instrument which is calibrated and checked at such intervals as are 
recommended in this behalf by the manufacturers of such instruments in the 
manual of instruction pertaining thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the case of vessels 
which had contained products blended with leaded fluid, the regulations laid 
down by the suppliers of the fluid shall be fully observed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>172</number> Fire Control.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every crude oil refinery shall be fully protected against fire by a well 
organised and trained fire fighting service with necessary materials and fixed, 
mobile and portable equipments for fighting fires in line with the Oil Industry 
Safety Directorate’s Standard-116. This will apply to new crude oil 
refineries/gas processing installation approved by the Chief Controller after 
publication of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An adequate supply of 
water shall be available at all strategic points in the refinery by means of an 
independent ring main or grid provided with isolating valves. The main shall be 
kept constantly pressurized by two or more boosting pumps of adequate capacity 
preferably working automatically as any significant loss of pressure in the main 
occurs. At least one of the boosting pumps shall be independent of the normal 
power supply.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All mains shall be 
fitted with hydrants at convenient places not more than thirty metres apart in 
hazardous areas and not more than 45 metres apart in non-hazardous area. Such 
hydrants shall be of design suitable for operating conditions and for connecting 
mobile pumps.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Static water supply of 
adequate capacity shall be provided where mains water supply may be subject to 
interference.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All refinery personnel 
shall be practiced in the use of first-aid, fire-fighting appliances and 
selected refinery personnel shall be trained in all aspects of fire-fighting.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chief Controller 
may relax any of the provisions of sub-rules (1) to (5) or require additional 
fire-fighting provisions to be made if he deems such relaxation or additional 
fire-fighting provisions necessary in respect of any class of refinery.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>173</number> Removal of 
Petroleum.—All 
petroleum as it leaves the stills with the exception of such quantities as may 
be pumped direct to service tanks for fuel, shall at once be pumped out into the 
refinery storage tanks and shall not be stored in the immediate neighbourhood of 
stills and boilers:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller may permit petroleum to be disposed of otherwise.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>174</number> Prevention of 
danger from static electricity.—Adequate 
provision shall be made to prevent accumulation of dangerous static charge of 
electricity.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>175</number> Warning notices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Warning notices regarding prevention of unauthorised person, naked lights, 
smoking and other hazards shall be displayed prominently at strategic locations 
in the refinery.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No fireworks of any 
kind shall be carried out within a radius of one kilometre from the refinery 
except with the prior permission of District Magistrate.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>176</number> Marking of 
pipelines and cables.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All above-ground pipelines and cables shall be identified by taping, stenciling, 
colouring distinctively or by any other suitable methods.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All overhead pipelines 
and cables crossing roads shall be adequately protected against accidental 
damage.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Pipelines and valves 
at loading and discharging berths shall be prominently marked to identify the 
product.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The route of all 
underground cables shall be marked by prominent markers. At least two such 
markers shall be visible from any point on the route of the cable.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The route of all 
underground pipelines shall be marked by prominent markers or by any other 
effective means to prevent accidental damage to the pipelines.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>177</number> Inspections.—All 
plants, instruments and equipments including fire-fighting equipment shall be 
inspected and tested at intervals, the frequency depending on practical or other 
relevant factors, and records of all such inspections shall be maintained.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>178</number> Safe operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All operators employed in a refinery shall be adequately trained in the safe 
operation of plants and equipment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Written procedures 
shall be established for operators to start up, shut down and gas-free plants or 
sections of plants safely and to take safe action under emergency conditions.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Checks shall be made 
at all stages of the operations by supervisors to ensure that vessels and 
equipments are properly isolated or connected up, as required, and to ensure 
that safety facilities are commissioned as the operation proceeds.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>179</number> Report of fire.—The 
occurrence of any fire in refinery shall be reported immediately by the person 
in-charge of the refinery for the time being to the Chief Controller and to the 
nearest police station.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>180</number> Closing of 
refinery.—If 
refinery is closed down, the area within the fence surrounding it shall be 
cleared of all petroleum having flash point below 93 degree C as soon as 
possible.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>181</number> Additions of Tetra 
Ethyl Lead Mixture.—Tetra 
Ethyl Lead shall not be bended with petroleum except in an equipment approved in 
writing by the Chief Controller and in such proportions and under such 
conditions as may from time to time be determined by him.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>182</number> Additions of Tetra 
Ethyl Lead Mixture.—Tetra 
Ethyl Lead shall not be blended except in an equipment approved in writing by 
the Chief Controller and in quantities not exceeding the limits specified in the 
relevant Indian Standards Specifications.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>183</number> Prescription of 
special conditions.—The 
Chief Controller may from time to time by a written order prescribe special 
conditions which shall be observed during mixing of petroleum with ethyl fluid, 
handling of leaded petroleum or cleaning or repair of storage tanks which have 
contained leaded petroleum.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>184</number> Colouration of 
leaded petroleum.—Every 
mixture of petroleum and Tetra Ethyl Lead shall be distinctively coloured before 
being supplied to the public.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>185</number> Marking of 
receptacles.—All 
receptacles other than tank containing a mixture of petroleum and Tetra Ethyl 
Lead shall, except when they are in possession of the Defence Forces of the 
Union, bear a warning in the following terms, namely:—
 


“Warning”
 


This spirit contains lead and Shall be used  
as a motor fuel only
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>186</number> Drawing of sample.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In all cases, the sampling officer shall personally superintend the drawing of 
the sample and the sample shall be drawn in the presence of at least one 
witness. Where the sample is drawn from an original unopened receptacle 
containing petroleum otherwise than in bulk the opening shall be sufficient to 
admit of the sample being rapidly transferred from the receptacle.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Two bottles, each of a 
capacity of 1 litre shall be filled to nine-tenths of their capacity with the 
sample and corked. The corks shall be driven home and cut-off level with the 
neck; and melted sealing wax shall be worked into the corks and the bottles 
shall be efficiently sealed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of 
petroleum imported into India the bottles containing the samples shall, after 
being sealed, be labelled with the name of the consignee, particulars of the 
ship or vehicle by which it is imported and such other distinguishing marks as 
may be necessary.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>187</number> Forwarding and 
retention of samples.—One 
of the bottles referred to in sub-rule (2) or rule 186 shall be preserved for 
reference in case of need and the other shall be forwarded to the testing 
officer.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>188</number> Procedure of 
delivery of samples.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the master of, or the agent for, a ship or the agent of the importer has 
made the declaration required under rule 17 or rule 26, the sampling officer 
shall obtain samples of all the petroleum which is intended to land at the port 
or place of import. If the importer so desires, the sampling officer shall also 
take samples of all the petroleum which is intended to land at any other port or 
place of import in India:
 
Provided that no sample 
need be taken of petroleum if it is declared to be the petroleum Class A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The master of ship or 
the person for the time being in-charge of the vehicle by which petroleum is 
imported shall deliver to the sampling officer, without charge, samples of every 
variety of petroleum comprised in the petroleum of which samples are to be taken 
under sub-rule (1). Such samples shall, if the sampling officer so requires, be 
taken from the particular receptacles indicated by him:
 
Provided that when the 
petroleum is in cases, samples shall be taken as the landing proceeds.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>189</number> Selection of 
samples from imported cargo.—The 
minimum number of samples to be selected from each brand or quality contained in 
the cargo to the imported shall be as follows:
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  in cases-one sample for every 10,000 cases or part thereof;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  in casks or drums, declared to be uniform quality—one sample for 
every 600 kilolitres or part thereof;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iii</number>  in bulk or in tanks—one sample from each tank or tank compartment.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>190</number> Standard test 
apparatus.—The 
standard test apparatus shall—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  agree in every respect with the Indian Standard Specification No. 
IS-1448 (Part I): (P 20) or (P 21) as applicable and for the unit being in 
force; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  have been tested and certified by an officer appointed by the Central 
Government under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>191</number> Certification of 
apparatus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any apparatus for determining the flash point of petroleum is submitted to 
the officer appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act for 
comparison with the standard test apparatus, the officer shall examine the 
apparatus including the thermometers and the barometers or aneroid.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No certificate shall 
be granted under section 16 of the Act if the apparatus, any thermometer or 
barometer is in any respect outside the tolerances laid down or variations 
permitted under the Indian Standard Specification No. IS-1448 (Part-1): (P 20) 
or (P 21), as applicable, and for the time being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A certificate in Form 
IV shall be granted in respect of any apparatus which has been found to agree 
with the standard test apparatus within the limits specified in IS-1448 (Part I) 
(P 20) (P 21) was applicable and for the time being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A certificate granted 
under this rule shall be valid for a period of three years.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>192</number> Register of 
certificates.—A 
register of all certificates granted under rule 191 shall be maintained in Form 
V by the officer appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 15 of Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>193</number> Method of test.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The testing officer shall test the samples in the manner laid down in the Indian 
Standard Specification No. IS-1448 (Part I); (P 20) or (P 21), as applicable, 
and for the time being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In all cases at least 
three samples shall be separately tested, the average of the three readings 
being corrected for the thermometer correction, if any, and for the barometric 
correction in case of dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the average flash 
point is not lower than 23°C, the whole of the petroleum represented by the 
samples shall be deemed to be petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C according 
to the average flash point determined by the test.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the petroleum to be 
tested is viscous or solid or contains sediments or thickening ingredients, such 
petroleum shall be tested in accordance with the methods specified in the Fifth 
Schedule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>194</number> Procedure when 
tests show want of uniformity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the testing officer after testing samples taken from an imported cargo, 
considers further testing necessary to satisfy himself that none of the 
petroleum is petroleum Class A, he shall report to the Commissioner of Customs 
accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of a report 
under sub-rule (1)—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  when the consignment is imported in cases or casks or drums, the 
Commissioner of Customs shall cause the petroleum in question to be landed and 
stacked in lots of not more than 1,500 cases or casks or drums each, or to be 
discharged into boats each containing not more than 1,500 cases, casks or drums, 
and the sampling officer shall select and deliver to the testing officer one 
sample from each lot.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  when the consignment is imported in bulk, the sampling officer shall 
forward a second sample and Commissioner of Customs may, until the receipt of 
the testing officer’s further report, prevent the landing of any portion of the 
contents of the tank in question or may permit it to be landed as provided under 
rule 21.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  if the petroleum has already been landed and stored under rule 21—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  if it is otherwise than in bulk it shall be divided into lots, and 
samples of each lot shall be selected as provided in clause (a);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  if it is in bulk, samples shall be drawn from each separate storage 
tank containing the petroleum.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>195</number> Certificate of 
tests.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
testing officer shall, as soon as practicable, and ordinarily within twenty-four 
hours after receipt of samples make out a certificate in Form VI and shall 
forward it in the case of samples, of petroleum taken on board a ship or a 
vehicle by which petroleum is imported to the Commissioner of Customs and in the 
case of other samples to the officer submitting the sample.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The testing officer 
shall, at the request of any person concerned furnish him with a certified copy 
of the certificate in Form VI on payment of a fee of rupees two hundred.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>196</number> Fee for inspection 
and comparison.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee for each inspection of the standard test apparatus shall be rupees one 
hundred.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee for comparing 
a privately owned test apparatus with the standard test apparatus shall be as 
follows:—
 
                                             
(in Rupees)
 
Test apparatus                              
800
 
Barometer                                     
200
 
Thermometer                                 
100
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>197</number> Fee for testing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee for testing each sample of petroleum shall be rupees five hundred:
 
Provided that the 
aggregate fees chargeable under this sub-rule shall not, in the case of any 
single consignment of petroleum in any one ship, other vessel, train or place, 
exceed rupees one thousand.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee for re-testing 
each sample under section 20 of the Act shall be rupees one thousand. It shall 
be refunded if the original test is proved to be erroneous.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>198</number> Power to enter, 
inspect, search and seize.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any, officer, specified in column (1) of the table below may within the 
jurisdiction specified in the corresponding entry in column 2 of the said table—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  enter, inspect and search any place where he has reason to believe 
that any petroleum is being imported, transported, stored, produced, refined or 
blended or is under transport and inspect all receptacles, plants and appliances 
used in connection therewith in order to ascertain if they are in accordance 
with provisions of the Act and of these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  search for petroleum therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  take samples for testing of any petroleum found therein and make 
payments by cash for value of samples taken; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  seize, detain and remove any petroleum or any material suspected to be 
petroleum or any equipment or appliances used therein together with connected 
documents thereof in respect of which he has reasons to believe that any of the 
provisions of the act or of these rules have been contravened.
 

Table
 
 
Designation of the 
  Officer                                                   
  Unit or Jurisdiction
 
 <subsubsection>
           
  <number>1</number>                                                                               
  (2)
 
Chief Controller &amp; 
Controller                                                
Whole of India
 
All District Magistrates                                                       
Their respective Districts
 
All Magistrates 
subordinate to                                             
Their respective Jurisdiction
 
District Magistrate                           

 
Police Officer not below 
the                                                
The area over which their
 
 
rank of an Inspector                                                          
  authority extends
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>2</number> Whenever any officer 
other than the Chief Controller, seizes, detains or removes any petroleum or any 
material connected therewith or any connected documents thereof under this rule, 
he shall forthwith report the fact by telegram to the Chief Controller and 
Controller having jurisdiction over the place where seizure, etc., has taken 
place and whenever any officer not being the district authority seizes, detains 
or removes any petroleum or any material connected therewith or any connected 
documents thereof under this rule, he shall intimate the facts of the case to 
the Chief Controller and the Controller having jurisdiction.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>3</number> Whenever any samples 
are taken in accordance with this rule, they shall be tested in accordance with 
the relevant provisions of Chapter X of these rules.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>4</number> Whenever any petroleum 
is seized under this rule, it shall be stored, under adequate guard until 
examination by Chief Controller or Controller and receipt of instructions from 
him as to its disposal.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>5</number> Whenever searches are 
made under this rule the same shall be carried out in accordance with the 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). All officers of 
the police and district authorities shall assist the Chief Controller in the 
execution of the Act and rules.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>6</number> Whenever any person by 
himself or any person in his employment voluntarily obstructs or offers any 
resistance to or otherwise interferes with or refuses or fails to give or 
wilfully gives false or misleading information to the officer duly appointed 
under this rule who is acting in accordance with his duty thereunder such person 
shall be deemed to have committed an offence under the Act.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>199</number> Destruction of 
petroleum.—The 
Chief Controller or Controller may destroy any petroleum or any material or 
equipment connected in respect of which the Chief Controller or Controller has 
reason to believe that any of the provisions of the Act or of these rules have 
been contravened or which in his opinion is no longer fit for storage, transport 
or use. The petroleum shall be destroyed at the expenses of the licensee or the 
occupier of the premises, as the case may be.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>200</number> Notice of 
accident.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The notice of an accident required to be given under section 27 of the Act shall 
be given forthwith—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  to the Chief Controller by telephone/fax and also by telegram 
[telegraphic address—‘Explosives Nagpur’] followed within 24 hours by a letter 
giving particulars of the occurrence; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police station by the quickest 
means of communication.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Pending the visit of 
the Chief Controller or his representative, or until instruction is received 
from the Chief Controller that he does not wish any further investigation or 
inquiry to be made, all wreckage and debris shall be left untouched except in so 
far as its removal may be necessary for the rescue of persons injured and 
recovery of the bodies of any persons killed by the accident or in the case of 
Railways for the restoration through communication.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<title><number>201</number> Power to exempt.—</title>The Central Government may, on the recommendation of the Chief Controller, in exceptional cases, by order exempt any class or classes of petroleum from all or any of the provisions of these rules, on such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>202</number> Repeal and 
savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Petroleum Rules, 1976, are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  all licences or duplicates granted or renewed under the said rules and 
all fees imposed or levied shall be deemed to have been granted, renewed or 
imposed or levied, as the case may be under the corresponding provisions of 
these rules, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all approvals given and all powers conferred by or under any 
notification or rule shall, so far as they are consistent with the Act and these 
rules be deemed to have been given or conferred by or under these rules.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>202</number> Repeal and 
savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Petroleum Rules, 1976, are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  all licences or duplicates granted or renewed under the said rules and 
all fees imposed or levied shall be deemed to have been granted, renewed or 
imposed or levied, as the case may be under the corresponding provisions of 
these rules, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  all approvals given and all powers conferred by or under any 
notification or rule shall, so far as they are consistent with the Act and these 
rules be deemed to have been given or conferred by or under these rules.
 
 
</subsection></section></article><form>
 




The Petroleum Rules, 2002
 


 
 



Fifth Schedule
 


(See rule 193)
 



Method of testing 
viscous or solid Forms of Petroleum
 


If the sample of petroleum to be 
tested is viscous or solid or contains sediments or thickening ingredients, such 
petroleum shall be tested in the ABEL apparatus in the following 
manner:—
 


The solid mixture must be cut into 
cylinders 38.1 mm in diameter by means of a cork borer or other similar cutter 
having the correct internal diametre. These cylinders are to be placed in the 
petroleum cup of the testing apparatus in a vertical position in such number as 
will completely fill the cup. The cylinders must be in contact with one another 
but must not be so tightly packed and so be deformed in shape.
 


Five or six of the cylinders in the 
centre of the cup must be shortened to 127 mm to allow space for the thermometer 
bulb.
 


The petroleum which is viscous or 
contains sediment or thickening ingredient shall be filled in the petroleum cup 
of the testing apparatus in a vertical position so that it completely fills the 
cup.
 


The air bath of the testing 
apparatus must be filled to a depth of 38.1 mm with water. The water bath must 
then be raised to, and maintained at a temperature of about 80oF.
 


The cup must then be placed in 
the air bath, and temperature of the sample must be allowed to rise until the 
thermometer in the oil-cup show 75oF 
then test flame must be applied.
 


If no flash is obtained, this 
temperature must be maintained constant in the oil-cup for one hour at the 
expiration of which time the test flame must again be applied.
 


If a flash is obtained, the solid 
mixture will be subjected to the provisions of the Petroleum Act, 1934.
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 61(E), dated 2nd February, 2007 (w.e.f. 2-2-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 4(E), dated 4th January, 2005 (w.e.f. 4-1-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>