<act> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Manner of Recovery of Excess Deductions) Rules, 1966
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
application and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Wages (Manner of Recovery of Excess 
Deductions) Rules, 1966.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules shall 
apply to the persons employed on railways, mines, oil-fields and air transport 
services.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They extend to the 
whole of India, except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Manner of Recovery of Excess Deductions) Rules, 1966
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means the Payment of Wages 
Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  ‘section’ means a section of the 
Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Manner of Recovery of Excess Deductions) Rules, 1966
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Manner of recovery of 
amount of deductions in excess of limits prescribed under sub-section (3) of 
section 7.—Where 
the total amount of deductions which have to be made under sub-section (2) of 
section 7 of the Act in any wage-period from the wages of any employed person 
exeeds the limit specified in clause 
<section><number>i</number> or, as the case may be, clause (ii) of 
sub-section (3) of that section, the excess shall be carried forward and 
recovered from the wages for the succeeding wage-period in such number of 
instalments, not exceeding six, as may be necessary to enable the deductions to 
be made in compliance with the said limits.
 <subsection>
Illustration.—The 
wages of a monthly-rated employed person for January are one hundred rupees and 
deductions (which include deductions on account of dues of a co-operative 
society) amount to ninety rupees. His maximum deduction from the wage for 
January will be seventy-five rupees. The excess amount of fifteen rupees will be 
carried forward and recovered in not more than six instalments by limiting other 
deductions for those months so that the total deduction does not exceed 
seventy-five rupees in any month.
  
</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>