<act><title>

THE DOCK WORKERS (SAFETY, HEALTH 
    AND WELFARE) RULES, 19901</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


     <number>1</number> Short title, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Dock Workers (Safety, Health and Welfare) 
    Rules, 1990. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> They shall apply to all major ports in India as defined in the Major 
    Ports Act, 1963 (38 of 1963). 
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> They shall come into force after expiry of 30 days from the date of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise require,— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Dock Workers (Safety, Health and Welfare) Act, 1986 
    (54 of 1986); 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   “Regulations” means the Dock Workers (Safety, Health and Welfare) 
    Regulations, 1989; and, 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   all the words used in these rules and not defined but defined in the 
    Act or the regulations shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
    in the Act and the regulations. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>3</number> Inspection procedure.—An 
    Inspector shall exercise the powers conferred upon him under the Act and the 
    regulations. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>4</number> Notice to employer.—The 
    Inspector shall, after every inspection visit, as may be deemed necessary, 
    issue an improvement notice or a prohibition notice pointing out the 
    non-compliance of provisions of the Act or the regulations to the owner or 
    master or officer-in-charge of the ship or their agent or the employer of 
    the dock workers in Form IX appended to the regulations. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>5</number> Compliance of previous inspection reports.—An 
    Inspector shall, at each inspection, ascertain to what extent any 
    shortcomings notified at a previous inspection have been rectified and the 
    notices previously issued have been complied with. His findings and any 
    shortcomings which may come to light during the inspection, together with 
    any order passed by him under the Act or the regulations shall be recorded 
    in an inspection register required to be maintained for the purpose. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>6</number> Notice to whom served.—Any 
    notice or order required or intended to be served under the Act or the 
    regulations, may be served: 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   on any person by delivering it to him, or by leaving it at, or sending 
    it by registered post to the ship, premises or registered office as the case 
    may be. 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   on any firm by delivering it to any partner of the firm or by leaving 
    it at, or sending it by registered post to the office of the firm. 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   on any company by delivering it to any of the directors or the person 
    in charge of operation in the dock premises or by sending it by registered 
    post to the office of the company. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>7</number> Show-cause notice.—An 
    Inspector may, as deemed necessary, issue show-cause notice and prohibition 
    order and prosecute the port authority, firm or company, who by himself or 
    through his agent is responsible for non-compliance of the provisions under 
    the Act and the regulations. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>8</number> Inquiry into causes of accidents.—An 
    Inspector shall conduct inquiry into causes of any accident or dangerous 
    occurrence, which he has reason to believe was caused as a result of 
    collapse or failure of lifting appliance, loose gear, transport equipment, 
    etc., or non-compliance with any of the provisions of the Act or the 
    regulations. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>9</number> Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Advisory Committee under section 9 of the Act shall consist of the 
    following nine members to be appointed by the Central Government, namely:— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   The Chief Inspector and other two members representing the Central 
    Government. 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   Three members representing organisation of employers of dock workers 
    as the Central Government may consider appropriate. 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iii</number>   Three members representing organisations of dock workers, as the 
    Central Government may consider appropriate: 
 

    Provided that any vacancy occurring in the Advisory Committee shall, as soon 
    as possible, be filled by the Central Government by appointing new members 
    representing the organisations as provided in this sub-rule: 
 

    Provided further that the Central Government may remove any member from the 
    Advisory Committee, without assigning any reasons. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>b</number> The Chief Inspector shall be Chairman of the Advisory Committee. 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number> The members of the Committee shall be appointed for a period of three 
    years. 
 </section><section>

    <number>d</number> An Official of the organisation of the Chief Inspector shall function as 
    the Secretary to the Advisory Committee and shall be entitled to attend and 
    take part in the meetings of the Committee. He shall not have a right to 
    vote. 
 </section><section>

    <number>e</number>   (i)   The Chairman shall convene meetings of the Advisory 
    Committee, as often as considered necessary, by giving notice of at least 15 
    days. The Chairman shall also forward to the members the agenda for the 
    meeting before the meeting is held. 
 <subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   The decisions taken by the Committee shall be forwarded by the 
    Chairman to the Central Government, along with comments and recommendations 
    on the action to be taken thereon. 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iii</number>   A report of the action taken on the decisions of the Advisory 
    Committee shall be presented to the Committee by the Chairman at its next 
    meeting. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>10</number> 

    Any competent person appointed by the Central Government for the purposes of 
    inquiring into the causes of any accident, diseases connected with the dock 
    work under the provision of section 10 of the Act shall make the inquiry in 
    the following manner:— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   date, time and place of holding the inquiry shall be fixed and may be 
    varied, notice of which shall be given not less than 30 days in writing of 
    such date, time and place to every person entitled to appear at the inquiry 
    whose name and address are known to the competent person : 
 

    Provided that,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   with the consent of all such persons, the competent person may give 
    such lesser period of notice as shall be agreed to with those persons; and 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   where it becomes necessary or advisable to vary the time or place 
    fixed for the inquiry, the competent person shall give such notice of the 
    variation as may appear to it to be reasonable in the circumstances. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>b</number>   The notice given under paragraph (a) of this rule shall state the name 
    of the competent person and the names of assessors, if any, appointed to 
    assist the competent person in the inquiry. 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this rule, the 
    competent person shall also for the purpose of notifying to the persons who 
    may in any way be concerned with the subject-matter of the inquiry, take one 
    or more of the following steps, namely:— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   publish notice of the inquiry in one or more newspapers, including 
    where appropriate, newspapers circulating in the locality/area in which the 
    subject-matter of the inquiry arose; and 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   give such other notice of the inquiry as appears to the competent 
    person to be appropriate;  
 

    and the requirements as to the period of notice contained in paragraph (a) 
    of this rule shall not apply to any such notices. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>11</number> Persons to appear at inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The person entitled to appear at the inquiry shall be—
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   any competent person under regulation 2 (a); 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   any enforcing authority concerned; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   any employers’ association or trade union of employees; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   any person who was injured or suffered damage as a result of the 
    accident, occurrence, situation, disease or other matter which is the 
    subject of the inquiry, or his representative; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>   the owner of any premises in which the accident, occurrence, situation 
    or other matter occurred or arose; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>   any person carrying on dock work giving rise to the accident, 
    occurrence, situation or other matter which is the subject of the inquiry; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>g</number>   any other person at the discretion of the appointed competent person. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The following shall represent at the inquiry:— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   a corporate body may be represented by its secretary or by any other 
    officer appointed for the purpose, or by counsel or solicitor; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   a Government department, an employers’ association or a trade union 
    may be represented by a counsel or a solicitor; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   where there are two or more persons having a similar interest in the 
    matter under inquiry, the competent person may allow one or more persons to 
    appear for the benefit of some or all persons so interested. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>3</number> The competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 
    10 of the Act, may, either of his own motion or on the application of any 
    person entitled or permitted to appear, cause to be served on any person 
    appearing to him to be likely to be able to give material evidence or to 
    produce any document likely to be material evidence, a notice requiring that 
    person to attend at the inquiry at the time and place specified in the 
    notice to give evidence or produce the document. 
 </section><section>

    <number>4</number> A person on whom a notice is served under sub-rule (3) may apply to the 
    competent person either at or before the inquiry to vary or set aside the 
    requirement, and where he does so before the inquiry, he shall give notice 
    of his application to the person, if any, who applied for the notice under 
    sub-rule (3) to be served. 
 </section><section>

    <number>5</number> Except as otherwise provided in these rules, the procedure at and in 
    connection with an inquiry shall be at the discretion of the competent 
    person who shall state at the commencement of the hearing the procedure 
    which, subject to consideration of any submission by the persons appearing 
    at the inquiry, he proposed to adopt and shall inform those persons what he 
    proposes as regards any site inspection arising out of the hearing. 
 </section><section>

    <number>6</number> Except as provided in sub-rule (1) of rule 12, the inquiry shall be held 
    in public.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
 

THE DOCK WORKERS (SAFETY, HEALTH  
    AND WELFARE) RULES, 1990
 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Inquiry in public.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 10 of 
    the Act shall conduct the inquiry under rule 10 in public, unless,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   the Central Government is of the opinion that the matters of the 
    inquiry or any part of it are of such nature that it would be against the 
    interest of national security to hold the inquiry in public and directs the 
    competent person to hold the inquiry in camera; or 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   on an application made to him by any party to the inquiry, decides to 
    hold the inquiry or such part of it in camera, if he is of the 
    opinion that the holding of public inquiry will lead to disclosure of 
    information relating to a trade secret. 
 

    Information disclosed to any person by the hearing of evidence in the 
    circumstances mentioned in sub-paragraphs (a) or (b) above shall not be 
    disclosed by him except for the purposes of the inquiry. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> Persons entitled or permitted to appear shall be heard in such order as 
    the competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 10 of 
    the Act, may determine. 
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> Persons entitled to appear shall be entitled to make an opening 
    statement, to call evidence and to cross-examine persons giving evidence, 
    but any other person appearing at the inquiry may do so only to the extent 
    permitted by the competent person appointed by the Central Government under 
    section 10 of the Act. 
 </section><section>

    <number>4</number> Where the competent person appointed by the Central Government under 
    section 10 of the Act, so requires, witnesses shall give evidence on oath, 
    and for that purpose he may administer an oath in due form. 
 </section><section>

    <number>5</number> Any evidence may be admitted at the discretion of the competent person 
    appointed by the Central Government under section 10 of the Act, who may 
    direct that documents to be tendered in evidence may be inspected by any 
    person entitled or permitted to appear at the inquiry and that facilities be 
    afforded to him to take or obtain copies thereof. 
 </section><section>

    <number>6</number> The competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 
    10 of the Act, shall be entitled (subject to disclosure thereof at the 
    inquiry and making available copies thereof to the persons appearing at the 
    inquiry) to take into account any written representation or statement 
    received by him before the inquiry from any person. 
 </section><section>

    <number>7</number> The competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 
    10 of the Act, may from time to time, adjourn the inquiry and where he does 
    so shall give reasonable notice to every person entitled or permitted to 
    appear at the inquiry of the date, time and place of the adjourned inquiry. 
    Provided that where the date, time and place of the adjourned inquiry are 
    announced at the inquiry, no further notice shall be required. 
 </section><section>

    <number>8</number> The competent person appointed by the Central Government under section 
    10 of the Act, and any person appointed to assist him in the inquiry may, 
    where necessary for the purpose of the inquiry, at any reasonable time enter 
    and make an inspection of any ship/premises to which the inquiry relates and 
    anything in them. 
 </section><section>

    <number>9</number> (a) The competent person appointed by the Central Government under 
    section 10 of the Act shall after the close of the inquiry make a report in 
    writing to the Central Government, which shall include the findings of the 
    facts and his recommendations, if any, or his reasons for making any 
    recommendation. 
 <subsection>

    <number>b</number> Except where the said report is to be published, in whole or in part, 
    the Central Government shall send to any person who appeared at the inquiry 
    a copy of the report or so much of it as the competent person appointed by 
    the Central Government under section 10 of the Act thinks fit. 
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>