<act><title>


The Patents rules, 20031</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Patents Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date2 on 
which the Patents (Amendment) Act, 2002 comes into force.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “appropriate 
office” means the appropriate office of the patent office as specified in rule 
4; 
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “article” 
includes any substance or material, and any plant, machinery or apparatus, 
whether affixed to land or not;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “Form” means 
a Form specified in the Second Schedule;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “Schedule” 
means Schedule to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act; 
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  words and 
expressions used, but not defined in these rules, shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Prescribed 
particulars.—Save 
as otherwise provided in these rules, the particulars contained in a Form are 
hereby prescribed as the particulars, if any, required under the relevant 
provision or provisions of the Act.
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Appropriate office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The appropriate office of the patent office shall—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  for all the 
proceedings under the Act, 

1[***] be the head 
office of the patent office or the branch office, as the case may be, within 
whose territorial limits—
 <subsubsection>


<number>a</number>  the applicant or 
first mentioned applicant in case of joint applicants for a patent, normally 
resides or has his domicile or has a place of business or the place from where 
the invention actually originated; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>b</number>  the 
applicant for a patent or party in a proceeding if he has no place of business 
or domicile in India, the address for service in India given by such applicant 
or party is situated; and
 
 

2[***]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The appropriate office 
once decided in respect of any proceedings under the Act shall not ordinarily be 
changed.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Address for service.—Every 
person, concerned in any proceedings to which the Act or these rules relate and 
every patentee, shall furnish to the Controller an address for service in India 
and that address may be treated for all purposes connected with such proceedings 
or patent as the address of the person concerned in the proceedings or of the 
patentee. Unless such an address is given, the Controller shall be under no 
obligation either to proceed or deal with any proceeding, or patent or to send 
any notice that may be required to be given under the Act or these rules 

1[and the 
Controller may take suo motu decision in the matter].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Leaving and serving 
documents.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Any application, notice or other document authorised or required to be filed, 
left, made or given at the patent office, or to the Controller or to any other 
person under the Act or these rules, may be tendered by hand or sent by a letter 
addressed to the Controller at the appropriate office or to that person through 
post or registered post or speed post or courier service or by electronic 
transmission duly authenticated. If it is sent by post or registered post or 
speed post or courier service or by electronic transmission duly authenticated, 
it shall be deemed to have been filed, left, made or given at the time when the 
mail containing the same would have been delivered in the ordinary course of 
post or registered post or speed post or courier service, or by electronic 
transmission duly authenticated, as the case may be. In proving such sending, it 
shall be sufficient to show that the mail was properly addressed and 
transmitted:
 

2[***]]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any written 
communication addressed to a patentee at his address as it appears on the 
register of patents or at his address for service given under rule 5, or to any 
applicant or opponent in any proceedings under the Act or these rules, at the 
address appearing on the application or notice of opposition, or given for 
service, shall be deemed to be properly addressed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All notices and all 
written communications addressed to a patentee, or to any applicant or opponent 
in any proceedings under the Act or these rules, and all documents forwarded to 
the patentee or to the said applicant or opponent, shall, except when they are 
sent by special messenger, be sent by registered post or speed post or courier 
service or by electronic transmission duly authenticated.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The date of a notice 
or a written communication addressed to a patentee or to any applicant or 
opponent in any proceedings under the Act and these rules shall be the date of 
dispatch of the said notice or written communication, by registered post or 
speed post or courier or fax or electronic transmission duly authenticated, as 
the case may be, unless otherwise specified under the Act or these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In case of delay in 
receipt of a document or a communication sent by the patent office to a party to 
any proceedings under the Act or these rules, the delay in transmitting or 
resubmitting a document to the patent office or doing any act by the party may 
be condoned by the Controller if a petition for such condonation of delay is 
made by the party to the Controller immediately after the receipt of the 
document or a communication along with a statement regarding the circumstances 
of the fact and evidence in support of the statement: 
 
Provided that the delay 
condoned by the Controller shall not exceed the period between the date on which 
the party was supposed to have received the document or communication by 
ordinary course of mail or electronic transmission and the actual date of 
receipt of the same.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees payable under section 142 in respect of the grant of patents and 
applications therefor, and in respect of other matters for which fees are 
required to be payable under the Act shall be as specified in the First 
Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
(a) The fees, 
payable under the Act may either be paid in cash 

1[or through 
electronic means] or may be sent by bank draft or cheque payable to the 
Controller of Patents and drawn on a scheduled bank at the place where the 
appropriate office is situated. If the draft or cheque is sent by post, the fees 
shall be deemed to have been paid on the date on which the draft or cheque would 
have reached the Controller in the ordinary course of mail.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Cheques or drafts not 
including the correct amount of commission and cheques on which the full value 
specified therein cannot be collected in cash 

2[***] shall be 
accepted only at the discretion of the Controller.
 

3[(c) Where a fee 
is payable in respect of a document, the entire fee shall accompany the 
document.]
 
Provided that the 
Controller may accept the fee in part and allow remaining part of the fee to be 
paid at any time within one month from the date of filing of the document 
notwithstanding the expiry of the due date for filing of such document and on 
such payment, the document shall be taken on record from the date of its filing.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In case an application 
processed by a natural person is fully or partly transferred to a person other 
than a natural person, the difference, if any, in the scale of fee(s) between 
the fee(s) charged from a natural person and the fee(s) chargeable from the 
person other than the natural person in the same matter shall be paid by the new 
applicant with the request for transfer.
 

4[(4) Fees once 
paid in respect of any proceeding shall not ordinarily be refunded irrespective 
of whether the proceeding has taken place or not.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (i) Subject to the 
approval of the Controller, any person may deposit money in advance and request 
the Controller to realise any fee payable by him from the said deposit and in 
such case the date of the receipt of the request to realise the fee or the date 
on which the request to realise the fee is deemed to have been received, 
whichever is earlier, shall be taken as the date of payment of the fee:
 
Provided that the 
requisite amount of money is available at the credit of the person making such 
request.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Subject to the 
approval of the Controller, any person may discontinue the deposit of money in 
advance and in such case the balance, if any, shall be refunded.
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Forms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Forms set forth in the Second Schedule with such variations as the 
circumstances of each case may require shall be used for the purposes mentioned 
therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where no Form is so 
specified for any purpose, the applicant may adopt any Form specified in the 
Second Schedule with such modifications and variations as may be required.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Size, etc., 
of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All documents and copies of documents, except affidavits and drawings, sent to 
or left at the patent office or otherwise furnished to the Controller shall be 
written or typewritten or printed either in Hindi or in English language (unless 
otherwise directed or allowed by the Controller) in large and legible characters 
with deep indelible ink with lines widely spaced upon one side only of strong 
white paper of a size A4 of approximately 29.7 centimetres by 21 centimetres 
with a margin of at least 4 centimetres on the top and left hand part and 3cm on 
the bottom and right hand part thereof. Any signature which is not legible or 
which is written in a script other than Hindi or English shall be accompanied by 
a transcription of the name either in Hindi or in English in block letters:
 
Provided that any document 
including drawing, if any, may also be filed in electronic form along with a 
copy of it on white paper:
 
Provided further that in 
case the application for patent discloses sequence listing of nucleotides and/or 
amino acides, the same shall be filed in electronic form.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Additional copies of 
all documents shall be filed at the appropriate office, if required by the 
Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Names and addresses of 
applicants and other persons shall be given in full together with their 
nationality and such other particulars, if any, as are necessary for 
identification.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Period within which 
proof of the right under section 7(2) to make the application shall be 
furnished.—
Where, in an application for a patent made by virtue of an assignment of the 
right to apply for the patent for the invention, if the proof of the right to 
make the application is not furnished with the application, the applicant shall 
within a period of 

1[six months] after 
the filing of such application furnish such proof.­
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, the 

1[six months] 
period in case of an application corresponding to an international application 
in which India is designated shall be reckoned from the actual date on which the 
corresponding application is filed in India.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Order of recording 
applications.—The 
applications filed in a year shall constitute a series identified by the year of 
such filing. In case of an application filed corresponding to an international 
application in which India is designated, such application shall constitute a 
series distinct from the rest of the applications identified by the year of 
filing of corresponding applications in India.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Statement and 
undertaking regarding foreign applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The statement and undertaking required to be filed by an applicant for a patent 
under sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be made in Form 3.
 

1[(1A). The period 
within which the applicant shall file the statement and undertaking under 
sub‑section (1) of section 8 shall be 

2[six months] from 
the date of filing the application.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule, the period of 

2[six months] in 
case of an application corresponding to an international application in which 
India is designated shall be reckoned from the actual date on which the 
corresponding application is filed in India.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The time within which 
the applicant for a patent shall keep the Controller informed of the details in 
respect of other applications filed in any country in the undertaking to be 
given by him under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be 

3[six months] from 
the date of such filing.
 

4[(3) When so 
required by the Controller under sub‑section (2) of section 8, the applicant 
shall furnish information relating to objections, if any, in respect of novelty 
and patentability of the invention and any other particulars as the Controller 
may require which may include claims of application allowed within 

3[six months] from 
the date of such communication by the Controller.]
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Specifications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every specification, whether provisional or complete, shall be made in Form 2.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> A specification in 
respect of a divisional application under section 16 shall contain specific 
reference to the number of the original application from which the divisional 
application is made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A specification in 
respect of a patent of addition under section 54 shall contain a specific 
reference to the number of the main patent, or the application for the main 
patent, as the case may be, and a definite statement that the invention 
comprises an improvement in, or a modification of, the invention claimed in the 
specification of the main patent granted or applied for.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the invention 
requires explanation through drawings, such drawings shall be prepared in 
accordance with the provisions of rule 15 and shall be supplied with, and 
referred to in detail, in the specification:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a complete specification, if the applicant desires to adopt the drawings 
filed with his provisional specification as the drawings or part of the drawings 
for the complete specification, it shall be sufficient to refer to them in the 
complete specification as those left with the provisional specification.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Irrelevant or other 
matter, not necessary, in the opinion of the Controller, for elucidation of the 
invention, shall be excluded from the title, description, claims and drawings.
 

1[(6) Except in the 
case of an application (other than a convention application or an application 
filed under the Patent Cooperation Treaty designating India) which is 
accompanied by a complete specification, a declaration as to the inventorship of 
the invention shall be filed in Form 5 with the complete specification or at any 
time before the expiration of one month from the date of filing of the complete 
specification, as the Controller may allow on an application made in Form 4.]
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, the date of filing of the complete specification with 
respect to an application corresponding to an international application in which 
India is designated shall be reckoned from the actual date on which the 
corresponding application is filed in India.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> (a) The abstract as 
specified under clause (d) of sub-section (4) of section 10, accompanying the 
specification shall commence with the title of the invention. The title of the 
invention shall disclose the specific features of the invention normally in not 
more than fifteen words.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The abstract shall 
contain a concise summary of the matter contained in the specification. The 
summary shall indicate clearly the technical field to which the invention 
belongs, technical problem to which the invention relates and the solution to 
the problem through the invention and principal use or uses of the invention. 
Where necessary, the abstract shall contain the chemical formula, which 
characterises the invention.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The abstract may not 
contain more than one hundred and fifty words.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> If the specification 
contains any drawing, the applicant shall indicate on the abstract the figure, 
or exceptionally, the figures of the drawings which may accompany the abstract 
when published. Each main feature mentioned in the abstract and illustrated by a 
drawing shall be followed by the reference sign used in that drawing.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> The abstract shall be 
so drafted that it constitutes an efficient instrument for the purposes of 
searching in the particular technical field, in particular by making it possible 
to assess whether there is a need to consult the specification itself.
 

2[(8) The period 
within which reference to the deposit shall be made in the specification under 
sub-clause (A) of clause (ii) of sub-section (4) of section 10 shall be three 
months from the date of filing of the application.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> Amendments 
to specifications.—
<section><number>1</number> When a provisional or complete specification or any 
drawing accompanying it has been received by the applicant or his agent for 
amendment, and amendment is duly made thereon, the page incorporating such 
amendment shall be retyped and submitted to form a continuous document. 
Amendments shall not be made by slips pasted on, or as footnotes or by writing 
in the margin of any of the said documents.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amended documents 
shall be returned to the Controller together with the superseded pages or 
drawings, if any, duly marked, cancelled and initialed by the applicant or his 
agent. Copies of any pages that have been retyped or added and of any drawing 
that has been added or substantially amended shall be sent in duplicate.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Drawings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Drawings, when furnished under section 10 by the applicants otherwise than on 
requisition made by the Controller, shall accompany the specifications to which 
they relate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No drawings or sketch, 
which would require a special illustration of the specification, shall appear in 
the specification itself.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At least one copy of 
the drawing shall be prepared neatly and clearly on a durable paper sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Drawings shall be on 
standard A4 size sheets with a clear margin of at least 4 cm on the top and left 
hand and 3cm at the bottom and right hand of every sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Drawings shall be on a 
scale sufficiently large to show the inventions clearly and dimensions shall not 
be marked on the drawings.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Drawings shall be 
sequentially or systematically numbered and shall bear—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  in the left 
hand top corner, the name of the applicant;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in the right 
hand top corner, the number of the sheets of drawings, and the consecutive 
number of each sheet; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  in the 
right hand bottom corner, the signature of the applicant or his agent.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> No descriptive matter 
shall appear on the drawings except in the flow diagrams.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Models.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Models or samples shall be furnished under section 10 only when required by the 
Controller.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Definitions.—In 
this Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Article” 
means an Article of the Treaty;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Treaty” or 
“PCT” means the Patent Cooperation Treaty.
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  All other 
words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the PCT shall 
have the same meaning as assigned to them in that Treaty.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appropriate office 
in relation to international applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The receiving office, designated office and elected office for the purposes of 
international applications filed under the Treaty shall be the appropriate 
office in accordance with rule 4.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The head office of the 
patent office shall be the appropriate office for dealing with the International 
Bureau of the World Intellectual Property Organisation, International Searching 
Authorities and International Preliminary Examining Authorities.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An international 
application under the Treaty shall be filed at and processed by the appropriate 
office in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter, the Treaty and the 
regulations established under the PCT.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2), on receipt of an international application, 
the appropriate office shall transmit one copy as record copy of such 
application to International Bureau of the World Intellectual Property 
Organisation and another copy as search copy to Competent International 
Searching Authority. The appropriate office shall simultaneously furnish 
complete details of such application to the head office of the patent offices.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> International 
applications filed with appropriate office as receiving office.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
An international application shall be filed with the appropriate office in 
triplicate either in English or in Hindi language.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fees payable in 
respect of an international application filed with the appropriate office shall 
be, in addition to the fees as specified in the regulations under the Treaty, 
the fees as specified in the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an international 
application filed with the appropriate office has not been filed as specified 
under sub-rule (1) and the applicant desires that the appropriate office should 
prepare the additional copies required, the fee for making such copies shall be 
paid by the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of a 
request from the applicant and on payment of the prescribed fee by him, the 
appropriate office shall prepare a certified copy of the priority document and 
promptly transmit the same to the International Bureau of the World Intellectual 
Property Organisation for the purpose of an international application filed with 
the appropriate office with an intimation to the applicant and the head office.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> International 
applications designating or designating and electing India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application corresponding to an international application under the Patent 
Cooperation Treaty under section 7(1A) may be made in 

1[Form 1].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Patent Office 
shall not commence processing of an application filed corresponding to 
international application designating India before the expiration of the time 
limit prescribed under 

2[sub-rule (4)(i)].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An applicant in 
respect of an international application designating India shall, before the time 
limit prescribed in 

2[sub-rule (4)(i)],—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  pay the 
prescribed national fee and other fees to the patent office in the manner 
prescribed under these rules and under the regulations made under the Treaty;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  and where the 
international application was either not filed or has not been published in 
English, file with the patent office, a translation of the application in 
English, duly verified by the applicant 

3[or the person 
duly authorised by him] that the contents thereof are correct and complete.
 

4[(4) (i) The time 
limit referred to in sub‑rule (2) shall be thirty one months from the priority 
date as referred to in Article 2(xi);
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in clause (i), the Patent Office may, on the express request 
filed in Form 18 along with the fee specified in First Schedule, process or 
examine the application at any time before thirty one months.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The translation of the 
international application referred to in sub-rule (3) shall include a 
translation in English of,—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  the 
description;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the claims 
as filed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  any text 
matter of the drawings;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  the abstract; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number>  in case the 
applicant has not elected India and if the claims have been amended under 
Article 19, then the amended claims together with any statement filed under the 
said Article;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  in case the 
applicant has elected India and any amendments to the description, the claims 
and text matter of the drawings that are annexed to the international 
preliminary examination report.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> If the applicant fails 
to file a translation of the amended claims and annexures referred to in 
sub-rule (5), even after invitation from the appropriate office to do so, within 
a time limit as may be fixed by that office having regard to the time left for 
meeting the requirements, the amended claims and annexures shall be disregarded 
in the course of further processing the application by the appropriate office.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The applicant in 
respect of an international application designating India shall when complying 
with sub-rule (3), preferably use Forms set out in the Second Schedule before 
the appropriate office as designated office.
 
 






</section></article> 
 
 


  THE PATENTS RULES, 2003
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Filing of 
  priority document.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Where the applicant in respect of an international application designating 
  India has not complied with the requirements of paragraph 
<subsection><number>a</number> or paragraph (b) 
  of rule 17.1 of the regulations under the Treaty, the applicant shall file 
  with the patent office the priority document referred to in that rule before 
  the expiration of the time limit referred to in sub-rule (4) of rule 20.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where priority 
  document referred to in sub-rule (1) is not in the English language, an 
  English translation thereof duly verified by the applicant 

  1[or the person 
  duly authorised by him] shall be filed within the time limit specified in 
  sub-rule (4) of rule 20.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the applicant 
  does not comply with the requirements of sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), the 
  appropriate office shall invite the applicant to file the priority document or 
  the translation thereof, as the case may be, within three months from the date 
  of such invitation, and if the applicant fails to do so, the claim of the 
  applicant for the priority shall be disregarded for the purposes of the Act.
 
 
</section></article>
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Effect of 
non-compliance with certain requirements.—An 
international application designating India shall be deemed to be withdrawn if 
the applicant does not comply with the requirements of rule 20.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> The requirements 
under this Chapter to be supplemental of the regulations, etc., under the 
Treaty.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
provisions of this Chapter shall be supplemental to the PCT and the regulation 
and the administrative instructions made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case of a conflict 
between any provisions of the rules contained in this Chapter and provisions of 
the Treaty and the regulations and the administrative instructions made 
thereunder, the provisions of the Treaty and the regulations and administrative 
instructions made thereunder shall apply in relation to international 
applications.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>24</number> 
Publication of application.—The period for which an application for patent 
shall not ordinarily be open to public under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 11A 
shall be eighteen months from the date of filing of application or the date of 
priority of the application, whichever is earlier.]
 

2[Provided that the 
period within which the Controller shall publish the application in the Journal 
shall ordinarily be one month from the date of expiry of said period, or one 
month from the date of request for publication under rule 24A.]
 
 








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24A</number> Request for 
publication.—A 
request for publication under sub‑section (2) of section 11A shall be made in 
Form 9.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24B</number> Examination of 
application.—
<section><number>1</number>(i) 
A request for examination under section 11 B shall be made in Form 18 

1[within 
forty-eight months] from the date of priority of the application or from the 
date of filing of the application, whichever is earlier;
 

2[(ii) The period 
within which the request for examination under sub­-section (3) of section 11B 
to be made shall be forty-eight months from the date of priority if applicable, 
or forty-eight months from the date of filing of the application;]
 

3[(iii) The request 
for examination under sub‑section (4) of section 11B shall be made within 
forty-eight months from the date of priority or from the date of filing of the 
application, or within six months from the date of revocation of the secrecy 
direction, whichever is later;]
 

4[(iv) The request 
for examination of application as filed according to the ‘Explanation’ under 
sub‑section (3) of section 16 shall be made within forty-eight months from the 
date of filing of the application or from the date of priority of the first 
mentioned application or within six months from the date of filing of the 
further application, whichever is later;]
 <subsection>
<number>v</number> The period for making 
request for examination under section 11B, of the applications filed before the 
1st day of January, 2005 shall be 

5[the period 
specified under the section 11B before the commencement of the Patents 
(Amendment) Act, 2005 or] the period specified under these rules, whichever 
expires later.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 

6[(i) The period 
within which the Controller shall refer the application and specification and 
other documents to the examiner in respect of the applications where the request 
for examination has been received shall ordinarily be one month from the date 
its publication or one month from the date of the request for examination 
whichever is later:
 
Provided that such 
reference shall be made in order in which the request is filed under sub-rule 
(1).]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The period within 
which the examiner shall make the report under sub‑section (2) of section 12, 
shall ordinarily be one month but not exceeding three months from the date of 
reference of the application to him by the Controller;
 

7[(iii) the period 
within which the Controller shall dispose off the report of the examiner shall 
ordinarily be one month from the date of the receipt of the such report by the 
Controller.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A first examination 
report along with the application and specification shall be sent to the 
applicant or 

8[his authorised 
agent ordinarily within six months from the date of the request for examination 
or six months from date of publication whichever is later.] In case other 
interested person files the request for examination, an intimation of such 
examination may be sent to such interested person.
 

6[(4) The time for 
putting an application in order for grant under section 21 shall be twelve 
months from the date on which the first statement of objection is issued to the 
applicant to comply with the requirements.]]
 
 










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Identification of 
published applications.—Publication 
of application under sub-sections (2) and (5) of section 11A shall be identified 
by the letter ‘A’ along with the number of application.
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Request for 
withdrawal.—1[***] 
A request for withdrawing the application under sub-section (4) of section 11B 
shall be made in writing.
 

2[***]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>27</number> Inspection 
and supply of published documents.—After the date of publication of the 
application under section 11A, the application together with the complete 
specification and provisional specification, if any, the drawing, if any, and 
the abstract filed in respect of the application may be inspected at the 
appropriate office by making a written request to the Controller on payment of 
the fee in that behalf and copies thereof may be obtained on payment of fees 
specified in the First Schedule.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Procedure in case 
of anticipation by prior publication.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Controller is satisfied after investigation under section 13 that the 
invention so far as claimed in any claim of the complete specification has been 
published in any specification or other document referred to in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of the said section, the Controller shall 
communicate the gist of specific objections and the basis thereof to the 
applicant and the applicant shall be afforded an opportunity to amend his 
specification.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the applicant 
contests any of the objections communicated to him by the Controller under 
sub-rule (1), or if he refiles his specification along with his observations as 
to whether or not the specification is to be amended, he shall be given an 
opportunity to be heard in the matter if he so requests:
 
Provided that such request 
shall be made on a date earlier than ten days of the final date of the period


1[referred to] 
under sub-section (1) of section 21:
 
Provided further that a 
request for hearing may be allowed to be filed within such shorter period as the 
Controller may deem fit in the circumstances of the case.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the applicant 
requests for a hearing under sub-rule (2) within a period of one month from the 
date of communication of the gist of objections, or, the Controller, considers 
it desirable to do so, whether or not the applicant has refiled his application, 
he shall forthwith fix a date and time for hearing having regard to the period 
remaining for putting the application in order or to the other circumstances of 
the case.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The applicant shall be 
given ten days’ notice of any such hearing or such shorter notice as appears to 
the Controller to be reasonable in the circumstances of the case and the 
applicant shall, as soon as possible, notify the Controller whether he will 
attend the hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After hearing the 
applicant, or without a hearing if the applicant has not attended or has 
notified that he does not desire to be heard, the Controller may specify or 
permit such amendment of the specification as he thinks fit to be made and may 
refuse to 

2[grant the patent] 
unless the amendment so specified or permitted is made within such period as may 
be fixed.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>28A</number> Procedure 
in relation to consideration of report of examiner under section 14.—In case 
the applicant contests any of the objections communicated to him, the procedure 
specified under rule 28 may apply.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Procedure in case 
of anticipation by prior claiming.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When it is found that the invention so far as claimed in any claim of the 
complete specification, is claimed in any claim of any other specification 
falling within clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 13, the applicant shall 
be so informed and shall be afforded an opportunity to amend his specification.
 

1[(2) If the 
applicant’s specification is otherwise in order for grant and an objection under 
clause (b) of sub‑section (1) of section 13 is outstanding, the Controller may 
postpone the grant of patent and allow a period of two months for removing the 
objection.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Amendment of the 
complete specification in case of anticipation.—If 
the applicant so requests at any time, or if the Controller is satisfied that 
the objection has not been removed within the period referred to in sub-rule (2) 
of rule 29, a date for hearing the applicant shall be fixed forthwith and the 
applicant shall be given at least ten days’ notice of the date so fixed. The 
applicant shall, as soon as possible, notify the Controller whether he will 
attend the hearing.
 <section>
<number>2</number> After hearing the 
applicant, or without a hearing if the applicant has not attended or has 
notified that he does not desire to be heard, the Controller may specify or 
permit such amendment of the specification as will be to his satisfaction to be 
made and may direct that reference to such other specification, as he shall 
mention shall be inserted in the applicant’s specification unless the amendment 
is made or agreed to within such period as he may fix.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Form of reference 
to another specification.—When 
in pursuance of rule 30, the Controller directs that a reference to another 
specification shall be inserted in the applicant’s complete specification, such 
reference shall be inserted after the claims and shall be in the following form, 
namely:
 
“Reference has been 
directed, in pursuance of section 18(2) of the Patents Act, 1970, to the 
specification filed in pursuance of application No..……..”
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Procedure in case 
of potential infringement.—If 
in consequence of an investigation made under section 13 

1[***], it appears 
to the Controller that the applicant’s invention cannot be performed without 
substantial risk of infringement of a claim of another patent, the applicant 
shall be so informed and the procedure provided in rule 29 shall, so far as may 
be necessary, be applicable.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Form of reference 
to another patent.—Where 
the Controller directs that a reference to another patent shall be inserted in 
the applicant’s complete specification under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 19, such 
reference shall be inserted after the claims in the following form, namely:
 
“Reference has been 
directed, in pursuance of section 19(1) of the Patents Act, 1970, to Patent 
No..................”
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Manner in which a 
claim under section 20
<section><number>1</number> shall be made.—(1) 
A claim under sub-section (1) of section 20 shall be made in Form 6.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The original 
assignment or agreement or an official copy or notarized copy thereof shall also 
be produced for the Controller’s inspection and the Controller may call for such 
other proof of title or written consent as he may require.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Manner in which a 
request may be made under section 20(4).—
<section><number>1</number> 
A request under sub-section (4) of section 20 shall be made in Form 6.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The request shall be 
accompanied by proof of death of the joint applicant and a certified copy of the 
probate of the will of the deceased or letters of administration in respect of 
his estate or any other document to prove that the person who gives the consent 
is the legal representative of the deceased applicant.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Manner of 
application under section 20(5).—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under sub-section (5) of section 20 shall be made in Form 6 in 
duplicate and shall be accompanied by a statement setting out fully the facts 
upon which the applicant relies and the directions which he seeks.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the 
application and statement shall be sent by the Controller to every other joint 
applicant.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>37</number> Numbering 
of applications on the grant of patent.—On the grant of a patent, the 
application shall be accorded a number (called serial number) in the series of 
numbers accorded to patents under the Indian Patents and Designs Act, 1911 (2 of 
1911), which shall be the number of the patent so granted.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 






 

 
 
 

1[***]
 





 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>55</number>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Opposition
to the patent].—
<section><number>1</number>
Representation for opposition under sub-section <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[(1)
of section 25 shall be filed at the appropriate office and shall include a
statement and evidence, if any, in support of the representation and a request
for hearing if so desired.
 


 </section><section><number>1A</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), no patent shall be granted
before the expiry of a period of six months from the date of publication of the
application under section 11A.]
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Controller shall consider such representation only when a request for
examination of the application has been filed.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
On consideration of the representation if the Controller is of the opinion that
application for patent shall be refused or the complete specification requires
amendment, he shall give a notice to the applicant to that <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[effect
alongwith a copy of such representation].
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
On receiving the notice under sub-rule (3), the applicant shall, if he so
desires, file his statement and evidence, if any in support of his application
within <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[three
months] from the date of the notice.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
On consideration of the statement and evidence filed by the applicant, the
Controller may either refuse to grant a patent on the application or require the
complete specification to be amended to his satisfaction before the patent is
granted.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
After considering the representation and submission made during the hearing if
so requested, the Controller shall proceed further simultaneously either
rejecting the representation and granting the patent or accepting the
representation and refusing the grant of patent on that application, ordinarily
within one month from the completion of above proceedings] 


   


   


   












</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55A</number> Filing of notice 
of opposition.—The 
notice of opposition to be given under 

1[sub‑section (2) 
of section 25] shall be made in Form 7 and sent to the Controller in duplicate 
at the appropriate office.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Constitution of 
Opposition Board and its proceeding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of 

1[notice of 
opposition under rule 55A], the Controller shall, by order, constitute an 
Opposition Board consisting of three members and nominate one of the members as 
the Chairman of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An examiner appointed 
under sub‑section (2) of section 73 shall be eligible to be a member of the 
Opposition Board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The examiner, who has 
dealt with the application for patent during the proceeding for grant of patent 
thereon shall not be eligible as member of Opposition Board as specified in 
sub‑rule (2) for that application.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Opposition Board 
shall conduct the examination of the notice of opposition along with documents 
filed under rules 57 to 60 referred to under 

2[sub‑section (3) 
of section 25], submit a report with reasons on each ground taken in the notice 
of opposition with its joint recommendation within three months from the date on 
which the documents were forwarded to them.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Filing of written 
statement of opposition and evidence.—The 
opponent shall send a written statement in duplicate setting out the nature of 
the opponent’s interest, the facts upon which he bases his case and relief which 
he seeks and evidence, if any, along with notice of opposition and shall deliver 
to the patentee a copy of the statement and the evidence, if any.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Filing of reply 
statement and evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the 

1[patentee] desires 
to contest the opposition, he shall leave at the appropriate office a reply 
statement setting out fully the grounds upon which the opposition is contested 
and evidence if any, in support of his case within a period of two months from 
the date of receipt of the copy of the written statement and opponent’s 
evidence, if any by him under rule 57 and deliver to the opponent a copy 
thereof.
 

2[(2) If the 
patentee does not desire to contest or leave his reply and evidence within the 
period as specified in sub‑rule (1), the patent shall be deemed to have been 
revoked.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Filing of reply 
evidence by opponent.—The 
opponent may, within one month from the date of delivery to him of a copy of the


1[patentee’s] reply 
statement and evidence under rule 58, leave at the appropriate office evidence 
in reply strictly confined to matters in the 

1[patentee’s] 
evidence and shall deliver to the 

2[patentee] a copy 
of such evidence.
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Further evidence to 
be left with the leave of the Controller.—No 
further evidence shall be delivered by either party except with the leave or 
directions of the Controller:
 
Provided that such leave 
or direction is prayed before the Controller has fixed the hearing under rule 
62.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Copies of documents 
to be supplied.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Copies of all documents referred to in the notice of opposition or in any 
statement or evidence filed in connection with the opposition and authenticated 
to the satisfaction of the Controller, shall be simultaneously furnished in 
duplicate unless the Controller otherwise directs.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a specification 
or other document in a language other than English is referred to in the notice, 
statement or evidence, an attested translation thereof, in duplicate, in English 
shall be furnished along with such notice, statement or evidence, as the case 
may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Hearing.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
On the completion of the presentation of evidence, if any, and on receiving the 
recommendation of Opposition Board or at such other time as the Controller may 
think fit, he shall fix a date and time for the hearing of the opposition and 
shall give the parties not less than ten days’ notice of such hearing and may 
require members of Opposition Board to be present in the hearing.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If either party to the 
proceeding desires to be heard, he shall inform the Controller by a notice along 
with the fee as specified in the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Controller may 
refuse to hear any party who has not given notice under sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If either party 
intends to rely on any publication at the hearing not already mentioned in the 
notice, statement or evidence, he shall give to the other party and to the 
Controller not less than five days’ notice of his intention, together with 
details of such publication.
 

2[(5) After hearing 
the party or parties desirous of being heard, or if neither party desires to be 
heard, then without a hearing, and after taking into consideration the 
recommendation of Opposition Board, the Controller shall decide the opposition 
and notify his decision to the parties giving reasons therefor.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>63</number> 
Determination of costs.—If the patentee notifies the Controller that he 
desires to withdraw the patent after notice of opposition is given, the 
Controller, depending on the merits of the case, may decide whether costs should 
be awarded to the opponent.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>63A</number> Request 
made under section 26
<section><number>1</number>.—Request under section 26(1) shall be made on Form 
12 within three months from the date of the order of the Controller and shall be 
accompanied by a statement setting out the facts upon which the petitioner 
relies and relief he claims.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 

 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Form of making a 
request under section 28(2).—A 
request under sub-section (2) of section 28 shall be made in Form 8.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Form of making a 
claim under section 28(3).—
<section><number>1</number> 
A claim under sub-section (3) of section 28 shall be made in Form 8, and shall 
be accompanied by a statement setting out the circumstances under which the 
claim is made.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the claim 
and the statement shall be sent by the Controller to every applicant for the 
patent (not being the claimant) and to any other person whom the Controller may 
consider to be interested.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Form of application 
to be made under section 28(7).—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under sub-section (7) of section 28 shall be made in Form 8 and 
shall be accompanied by a statement setting out the circumstances under which 
the application is made.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the 
application and the statement shall be sent by the Controller to each patentee 
or the applicant for patent, as the case may be, and to any other person whom 
the Controller may consider to be interested.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>69</number> Procedure 
for the hearing of claim or an application under section 28.—The procedure 
specified in rules 55A and 57 to 63 relating to the filing of notice of 
opposition, written statement, reply statement, leaving evidence, hearing and 
cost shall, so far as may be, apply to the hearing of a claim or an application 
under section 28 as they apply to the opposition proceedings subject to the 
modification that reference to patentee shall be construed as the person making 
the claim, or an application, as the case may be.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Mention of 
inventor.—Any 
mention of the inventor under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 28 shall be made in the 
relevant documents in the following form namely:—
 
“The inventor of this 
invention/substantial part of this invention within the meaning of section 28 of 
the Patents Act, 1970, is................of...................”.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>71</number> Permission 
for making patent application outside India under section 39.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
request for permission for making patent application outside India shall be made 
in Form 25.
 

2[(2) The time 
within which the Controller dispose of the request made under sub-rule (1), 
except in case of inventions relating to defence and atomic energy applications, 
shall ordinarily be within a period of twenty one days from the date of filing 
of such request.]]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Communication of 
result of reconsideration under section 36(2).— 

<section><number>1</number> The result of every reconsideration under sub-section (1) of section 36 
shall be communicated to the applicant for patent within fifteen days of the 
receipt of the notice by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Extension of time 
on revocation of secrecy directions under section 38.—The extension of time 
to be given for doing anything required or authorised to be done under section 
38 shall not exceed the period for which directions given by the Central 
Government under sub-section (1) of section 35 were in force.
 
 
</section></article> 

   


   


 [***] 


   


   







 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>74</number> Form of 
patent.—
<section><number>1</number> A patent shall be in the form as specified in the Third Schedule 
with such modifications as the circumstances of each case may require and shall 
bear the number accorded to the application under rule 37.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The patent certificate 
shall ordinarily be issued within seven days from the date of grant of patent 
uner section 43.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>74A</number>
Inspection of documents related to grant of patent.—After the date of publication
of a grant of a patent, the application together with the complete specification
and provisional specification, if any, the drawing if any, abstract and other
documents related thereto may be inspected at the appropriate office by making a
written request to the Controller and on payment of fee and may obtain copies on
payment of fee specified in the First Schedule.]
 


   




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Amendment of patent 
under section 44.—An 
application under section 44 for the amendment of a patent shall be made in Form 
10 along with substantiating evidence and be accompanied by the patent.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Manner of applying 
for direction under section 51
<section><number>1</number>.—(1) 
An application for directions under sub-section (1) of section 51 shall be made 
in Form 11 and shall be accompanied by a statement setting out the facts upon 
which the applicant relies.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the 
application and of the statement shall be sent by the Controller to every other 
person registered as grantee or proprietor of the patent.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Manner of 
application under section 51(2).—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for directions under sub-section (2) of section 51 shall be made 
in Form 11 and shall be accompanied by a statement setting out the facts upon 
which the applicant relies.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the 
application and statement shall be sent by the Controller to the person in 
default.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>78</number> Procedure 
for the hearing of proceedings under section 51.—The procedure specified in 
rules 55A and 57 to 63 relating to the filing of notice of opposition, written 
statement, reply statement, leaving evidence, hearing and costs shall, so far as 
may be, apply to the hearing of an application under section 51 as they apply to 
the hearing of an opposition proceeding.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Request under 
section 52(2).—
<section><number>1</number> 
A request under sub-section (2) of section 52 shall be made in Form 12 within 
three months from the date of the order of the 

1[Appellate Board 
or] court referred to in sub-section (1) of the said section and shall be 
accompanied by a statement setting out the facts upon which the petitioner 
relies and the relief he claims and a certified copy of the order of the 

1[Appellate Board 
or] court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 

1[Appellate Board 
or] court has ordered the grant of patent to the applicant only for a part of 
the invention, the new patent granted shall be accorded a number in the same 
series of numbers accorded to the complete specifications accepted on the same 
day as the patent is granted.
 
 



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>80</number>
Renewal fees under section 53.—
<section><number>1</number>
To keep a patent in force, the renewal fees specified in the First Schedule
shall be payable at the expiration of the second year from the date of the
patent or of any succeeding year and the same shall be remitted to the patent
office before the expiration of the second or the succeeding year.
 


 </section><section><footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number>
The period for payment of renewal fees so specified in sub‑rule (1) may be
extended to such period not being more than six months if the request for such
extension of time is made in Form 4 with the fee specified in the First
Schedule.]
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
While paying the renewal fee, the number and date of the patent concerned and
the year in respect of which the fee is paid shall be quoted.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The annual renewal fees payable in respect of two or more years may be paid in
advance.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Controller shall, after making such enquiry as he may deem necessary, credit
any renewal fee and issue a certificate that the fee has been paid. 


   




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Amendment of 
application, specification or any document relating thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under section 57 for the amendment of an application for a patent 
or a complete specification or any document related thereto shall be made in 
Form 13.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the application for 
amendment under sub-rule (1) relates to an application for a patent which has 
not been 

1[granted], the 
Controller shall determine whether and subject to what conditions, if any, the 
amendment shall be allowed.
 

2[3(a) If the 
application for amendment under sub‑rule (1) is made after grant of patent and 
the nature of the proposed amendment is substantive, the application shall be 
published.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any person interested 
in opposing the application for amendment shall give a notice of opposition in 
Form 14 within three months from the date of publication of the application.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The procedure 
specified in rules 57 to 63 relating to the filing of written statement, reply 
statement, leaving evidence, hearing and costs shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the hearing of the opposition under section 57 as they apply to the hearing of 
an opposition proceeding.]
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Preparation of 
amended specifications, etc.—Where 
the Controller allows the application for a patent or the complete specification 
or any other document to be amended, the applicant shall, if the Controller so 
requires and within the time to be specified by him, leave at the appropriate 
office an amended application or the specification or the other document, as the 
case may be, in accordance with the provisions of these rules.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>83</number> 
Publication of the amendment allowed.—The amendments allowed after a patent 
has been granted, shall be published.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Restoration of 
patents.— 
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for the restoration of a patent under section 60 shall be made in 
Form 15.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Controller 
is satisfied that a prima facie case for the restoration of any patent 
has not been made out, he shall intimate the applicant accordingly and unless 
the applicant makes a request to be heard in the matter within one month from 
the date of such intimation, the Controller shall refuse the application.
 

1[(3) Where 
applicant requests for a hearing within the time allowed and the Controller, 
after giving the applicant such a hearing, is prima facie satisfied that 
the failure to pay the renewal fees was unintentional, he shall publish the 
application.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>85</number> Opposition 
to restoration under section 61.—
<section><number>1</number> At any time, within two months from the 
date of publication of the application under sub‑rule (3) of rule 84, any person 
interested may give notice of opposition thereto in Form 14.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the notice 
of opposition shall be sent by the Controller to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The procedure 
specified in rules 57 to 63 relating to the filing of written statement, reply 
statement, leaving evidence, hearing and costs shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the hearing of the opposition under section 60 as they apply to the hearing in 
the opposition proceeding.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Payment of unpaid 
renewal fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Controller decides in favour of the applicant, the applicant shall pay 
the unpaid renewal fees and the additional fee specified in the First Schedule, 
within a month from the date of the order of the Controller allowing the 
application for restoration.
 

1[(2) The 
Controller shall publish his decision.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>87</number> Surrender 
of Patents.—
<section><number>1</number> The Controller shall publish the notice of an offer given 
under section 63.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person interested 
may, within three months from the date of publication of the notice, give notice 
of opposition to the Controller in Form 14 in duplicate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The procedure 
specified in rules 57 to 63 relating to the filing of written statement, reply 
statement, leaving evidence, hearing and costs shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the hearing of the opposition under section 63 as they apply to the hearing in 
opposition proceeding.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the Controller 
accepts the patentee’s offer to surrender the patent, he may direct the patentee 
to return the patent, and on receipt of such patent, the Controller shall by 
order revoke it and publish the revocation of the patent.]
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Register of patents 
under section 67.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon the 

1[grant] of a 
patent, the Controller shall enter in the register of patents at each 
appropriate office, the name, address and nationality of the grantee as the 
patentee thereof, the title of the invention (including the categories to which 
the invention relates), the date of the patent and the date of 

1[grant] thereof 
together with the address for service of the patentee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller shall 
also enter in the register of patents particulars regarding proceedings under 
the Act before the 

2[Controller or 
Appellate Board or the courts] in respect of every patent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the register of 
patents or any part thereof is in computer floppies, diskettes or any other 
electronic form it shall be maintained and accessed only by the person who is 
duly authorised by the Controller and no entry or alteration of any entry or 
rectification of any entry in the said register shall be made by any person who 
is not so authorised by the Controller.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 

 
 
 <article>
<number>90</number> Registration of 
title and interest in patents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 69 
shall be made in 

1[Form 16].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application for an 
entry in the register of patents of any other document purporting to affect the 
proprietorship of the patent by the person benefiting under the document shall 
be made in 

1[Form 16].
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>91</number> Presentation of 
assignment, etc., of patent to Controller.—Every 
assignment and every other document giving effect to or being evidence of the 
transfer of a patent or affecting the proprietorship thereof or creating an 
interest therein as claimed in such application, shall, unless the Controller 
otherwise directs, be presented to him together with the application which shall 
be accompanied by two copies of the assignment or other document certified to be 
true copies by the applicant or his agent and the Controller may call for such 
other proof of title or written consent as he may require.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>92</number> Registration of 
title or interest in a patent.—After 
the receipt of an application under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (2) of 
section 69, the Controller shall register the title of the person concerned or 
his interest in a patent, as the case may be, and an entry in the following form 
shall be made in the register, namely:—
 
“In pursuance of an 
application received on the ................................... Proprietor 
......................... Assignment ................... registered as 
.................. licencee ......................... by virtue of 
..................... licence ........................... Mortgagee etc. 
........................ Mortgage deed, etc. ........................... 
dated..................... and made between .......................... of the 
one part and .......................... of the other part.”
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>93</number> Entry of renewal 
fee.—Upon 
receipt of the payment of the prescribed renewal fee in respect of a patent, the 
Controller shall enter in the register of patents the fact that the fee has been 
paid and the date of payment of such fee and issue a certificate of the payment.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>94</number> Alteration of 
address.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
patentee may make a request in writing along with fee payable to the Controller 
for the alteration of his name, nationality, address or address for service as 
entered in the register of patents in respect of any patent granted to him. The 
Controller may require such proof of the alteration as he may think fit before 
acting on a request to alter the name or nationality.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Controller 
allows a request made under sub-rule (1), he shall cause the entries in the 
register to be altered accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a patentee makes a 
request in writing along with fee payable for entering an additional address for 
service in India and if the Controller is satisfied that the request should be 
allowed, he shall have the additional address for service entered in the 
register.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>95</number> Inspection of 
register of patents under section 72 and fees payable therefor.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The register of patents shall be open for public inspection during office hours 
on payment of the fees specified therefor in the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When register of 
patents or any part thereof is in computer floppies, diskettes or any other 
electronic form the person authorised by the Controller under sub-rule (3) of 
rule 88 shall provide access to the computer floppies, diskettes or other 
electronic form or printouts of the records thereof.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>96</number> 
Application for compulsory licence etc.—An application to the Controller for 
an order under section 84, section 85, section 91 or section 92 or section 92A 
shall be in Form 17, or Form 19, as the case may be. Except in the case of an 
application made by the Central Government, the application shall set out the 
nature of the applicant’s interest and terms and conditions of the licence the 
applicant is willing to accept.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>97</number> When a prima 
facie case is not made out.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, upon consideration of the evidence, the Controller is satisfied that a 
prima facie case has not been made out for the making of an order under any 
of the sections referred to in rule 96, he shall notify the applicant 
accordingly, and unless the applicant requests to be heard in the matter, within 
one month from the date of such notification, the Controller shall refuse the 
application.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the applicant 
requests for a hearing within the time allowed under sub-rule (1), the 
Controller shall, after giving the applicant an opportunity of being heard, 
determine whether the application may be proceeded with or whether it shall be 
refused.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>98</number> Notice of 
opposition under section 87(2).—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notice of opposition under sub-section (2) of section 87 shall be given in 
Form 14 and shall be sent to the Controller within two months from the date of 
the 

1[publication] of 
the application under sub-section (1) of the said section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice of 
opposition referred to in sub-rule (1) shall include the terms and conditions of 
the licence, if any, the opponent is prepared to grant to the applicant and 
shall be accompanied by evidence in support of the opposition.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The opponent shall 
serve a copy of his notice of opposition and evidence on the applicant and 
notify the Controller when such service has been effected.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No further statement 
or evidence shall be delivered by either party except with the leave of or on 
requisition by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Controller shall 
forthwith fix a date and time for the hearing of the case and shall give the 
parties not less than ten days’ notice of such hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The procedure 
specified in sub-rules (2) to (5) of rule 62, shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the procedure for hearing under this rule as they apply to the hearing 

2[in opposition 
proceedings].
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>99</number> Manner of 
publication of the revocation order.—The Controller shall publish the order 
made by him under sub‑section (3) of section 85 revoking a patent.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>100</number> Application under 
section 88(4).—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under sub-section (4) of section 88 for the revision of the terms 
and conditions of a licence which have been settled by the Controller shall be 
in 

1[Form 20] and 
shall state the facts relied upon by the applicant and the relief he seeks and 
shall be accompanied by evidence in support of the application.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Controller is 
satisfied that a prima facie case has not been made out for the revision 
of the terms and conditions of the licence, he may notify the applicant 
accordingly and unless within a month the applicant requests to be heard in the 
matter, the Controller may refuse the application.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Controller, after 
giving the applicant an opportunity of being heard, shall determine whether the 
application shall be proceeded with or whether the application shall be refused.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>101</number> Procedure to be 
followed in case of applications under section 88(4).—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Controller allows the application to be proceeded with, he shall direct 
the applicant to serve copies of the application and of the evidence in support 
thereof upon the patentee or any other person appearing in the register to be 
interested in the patent or upon any other person on whom, in his opinion such 
copies should be so served.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The applicant shall 
inform the Controller the date on which the service of copies of application and 
of the evidence on the patentee and other persons referred to in sub-rule (1) 
has been effected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The patentee or any 
other person on whom copies of the application and of the evidence have been 
served, may give to the Controller notice of opposition in Form 14 within one 
month from the date of such service. Such notice shall contain the grounds 
relied upon by the opponent and shall be accompanied by evidence in support of 
the opposition.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The opponent shall 
serve copies of the notice of opposition and his evidence on the applicant and 
inform the Controller the date on which such service has been effected.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No further evidence or 
statement shall be filed by either party except with special leave of or on 
requisition by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> On completion of the 
above proceedings, the Controller shall forthwith fix a date and the time for 
the hearing of the case and shall give the parties not less than ten days’ 
notice of such hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The procedure 
specified in sub-rules (2) to (5) of rule 62 shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the procedure for hearing under this rule as they apply to the hearing 

1[in opposition 
proceedings].
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If the Controller 
decides to revise the terms and conditions of licence he shall forthwith amend 
the licence granted to the applicant in such manner, as he may deem necessary.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>102</number> Application for 
termination of compulsory licence under section 94.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for termination of compulsory licence under section 94(1) shall 
be made in 

1[Form 21] by the 
patentee or any other person deriving title or interest in the patent. The 
application shall be accompanied by the evidence in support of the application.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The applicant shall 
serve a copy of the application and evidence on the holder of the compulsory 
licence and shall inform the Controller the date on which the service has been 
effected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The holder of the 
compulsory licence may file his objection along with evidence, if any, to the 
application within one month from the date of receipt of the application and 
evidence by him to the Controller and serve a copy thereof to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No further evidence or 
statement shall be filed by either party except with special leave of or on 
requisition by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On completion of the 
above proceedings, the Controller shall forthwith fix a date and the time for 
the hearing of the case and shall give the parties not less than ten day’s 
notice of such hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The procedure 
specified in sub-rules (2) to (5) of rule 62 so far as may be, apply to the 
procedure for hearing under this rule as they apply to the hearing 

2[in opposition 
proceedings].
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If the Controller 
decides to terminate the compulsory licence he shall forthwith issue an order 
giving terms and conditions, if any, of such termination and serve copies of the 
order to both the parties.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>103</number> Roll of scientific 
advisers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Controller shall maintain a roll of scientific advisers for the purpose of 
section 115. The roll shall be updated annually. The roll shall contain the


1[names, addresses, 
specimen signatures and photographs] of scientific advisers, their designations, 
information regarding their educational qualifications, the disciplines of their 
specialisation and their technical, practical and research experience.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person shall be 
qualified to have his name entered in the roll of scientific advisers, if he—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  holds a 
degree in science, engineering or technology or equivalent;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  has at least 
fifteen years’ practical or research experience; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  he holds or 
has held a responsible post in a scientific or technical department of the 
Central or State Government or in any organisation.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>104</number> Manner of 
application for inclusion in the roll of scientific advisers.—Any 
interested person may apply to the Controller for inclusion of his name in the 
roll of scientific advisers furnishing his bio-data.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>105</number> Inclusion of the 
name of any other person in the roll of scientific advisers.—The 
Controller may, notwithstanding anything contained in rules 103 and 104, enter 
the name of any person in the roll of scientific advisers, if he is of the 
opinion after such inquiry as he deems fit, that such person should be entered 
in the roll of scientific advisers.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>106</number> Power to relax.—Where 
the Controller is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, he 
may, by order, for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax any of the 
qualifications specified in sub-rule (2) of rule 103 with respect to any person, 
if such person is otherwise well qualified.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>107</number> Removal of names 
from the roll of scientific advisers.—The 
Controller may remove the name of any person from the roll of scientific 
advisers, if—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  such person 
makes a request for such removal; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the 
Controller is satisfied that his name has been entered in the roll by error or 
on account of misrepresentation or suppression of any material fact; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  such person 
has been convicted of an offence and sentenced to a term of imprisonment or has 
been guilty of misconduct in his professional capacity and the Controller is of 
the opinion that his name should be removed from the roll:
 
Provided that, before 
removing the name of any person from the roll of scientific advisers under this 
rule, such person shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>108</number> Particulars to be 
contained in the register of patent agents.—The 
register of patent agents maintained under section 125 shall contain the name, 
nationality, address of the principal place of business, addresses of branch 
offices, if any, the qualifications and the date of registration of every 
registered patent agent.
 <section>
<number>2</number> Where the register of 
patent agents is in computer floppies, diskettes or any other electronic form, 
it shall be maintained and accessed only by the person who is duly authorised by 
the Controller and no entry or alteration of any entry or rectification of any 
entry in the said register shall be made by any person who is not so authorised 
by the Controller.
 

1[(3) (i) Copies of 
register of patent agents shall be maintained in each of the branch offices;
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The register of 
patent agents shall also contain specimen signatures and photographs of the 
persons registered as patent agents.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>109</number> Application for 
registration of patent agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person who desires to be registered as a patent agent shall make an 
application in 

1[Form 22].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The applicant shall 
furnish such other information as may be required by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person desirous to 
appear in the qualifying examination under rule 110 shall make a request to the 
Controller along with the fee as specified in the First Schedule.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>110</number> Particulars of the 
qualifying examination for patent agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The qualifying examination referred to in clause (c)(ii) of sub-section (1) of 
section 126 shall consist of a written test and a viva voce examination.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The qualifying 
examination shall consist of the following papers and marks, namely:
 
Paper I —Patents Act and 
Rules                                       100
 
Paper II—Drafting and 
interpretation of patent
 
 specifications and other 
documents                                  100
 
Viva Voce 

                                                                    100
 

1[(3) The 
qualifying marks for each written paper and for the viva voce examination 
shall be fifty per cent. each, of total marks and a candidate shall be declared 
to have passed the examination only if he obtains an aggregate of sixty per 
cent. of the total marks.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>111</number> Registration of 
patent agents.—After 
a candidate passes the qualifying examination specified in rule 110 and after 
obtaining any further information which the Controller considers necessary he 
shall, on receipt of the fee specified therefor in the First Schedule, enter the 
candidate’s name in the register of patent agents and issue to him a certificate 
of registration as a patent agent.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>111A</number> Issue of 
duplicate certificate of patent agents.—The Controller may issue a duplicate 
certificate of registration as patent agent on a request made by the person so 
registered as patent agent along with fee specified in the First Schedule and 
contain a statement setting out the circumstances in which the original 
certificate issued under rule 111 was lost, destroyed and cannot be produced.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>112</number> Details to be 
included in an application for the registration of a patent agent.—An 
application by a person entitled to be registered as a patent agent under 
sub-section (2) of section 126 shall also be made in 

1[Form 22].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>113</number> Registration of 
patent agents under section 126 (2).—On 
receipt of an application for the registration of a person as a patent agent 
under rule 112, the Controller may if he is satisfied that the said person 
fulfils the conditions specified in sub-section (2) of section 126 enter his 
name in the register of patent agents.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>114</number> Disqualifications 
for registration as a patent agent.—A 
person shall not be eligible to be registered as a patent agent, if he—
 <section>
         <number>i</number>  has been 
adjudged by a competent court to be of unsound mind;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  is an 
undischarged insolvent;
 </section><section>
        <number>iii</number>  being a 
discharged insolvent, has not obtained from the court a certificate to the 
effect that his insolvency was caused by misfortune without any misconduct on 
his part;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  has been 
convicted by a competent court, whether within or outside India of an offence to 
undergo a term of imprisonment, unless the offence of which he has been 
convicted has been pardoned or unless on an application made by him, the Central 
Government has, by order in this behalf, removed the disability;
 </section><section>
        <number>v</number>  being a legal 
practitioner has been guilty of professional misconduct; or
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  being a 
chartered accountant, has been guilty of negligence or misconduct.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>115</number> Payment of fees.—The 
continuance of a person’s name in the register of patent agents shall be subject 
to the payment of the fees specified therefor in the First Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>116</number> Removal of a name 
from the register of patent agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Controller may delete from the register of patent agents, the name of any 
patent agent—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  from whom a 
request has been received to that effect; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  when he is 
dead; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  when the 
Controller has removed the name of a person under sub-section (1) of section 
130; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  if he has 
defaulted in the payment of fees specified in rule 115, by more than three 
months after they are due.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The removal of the 
name of any person from the register of patent agents 

1[shall be 
published] and shall be, where relevant forthwith communicated to the person 
concerned.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>117</number> Restoration of 
name of persons removed from the register of patent agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for the restoration of the name of any person removed from the 
register of patent agents under sub-section (2) of section 130 shall be made in


1[Form 23] within 
two months from the date of such removal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the name of a 
person is restored to the register of patent agents, his name shall be continued 
therein for a period of one year from the date on which his last annual fee 
became due.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The restoration of a 
name to the register of patent agents 

2[shall be 
published] and communicated to the person concerned.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>118</number> Alteration of 
names, etc., in the register of patent agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A patent agent may apply for the alteration of his name, address of the 
principal place of business and branch offices, if any, or the qualifications 
entered in the register of patent agents. On receipt of such application and the 
fee specified therefor in the First Schedule, the Controller shall cause the 
necessary alterations to be made in the register of patent agents.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every alteration made 
in the register of patent agents 

1[shall be 
published].
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>119</number> Refusal to 
recognise as patent agent.—If 
the Controller is of the opinion that any person should not be recognised as a 
patent agent in respect of any business under the Act as provided in sub-section 

<section><number>1</number> of section 131 thereof, he shall communicate his reasons to that person and 
direct him to show cause why he should not refuse to recognise him as such 
agent, within such time as he may allow, and after considering the reply, if 
any, of that person and giving him an opportunity of being heard, the Controller 
may pass such orders as he may deem fit.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>120</number> Publication of the 
names of patent agents, registered under the Act.—The 
names and addresses of persons registered as patent agents shall from time to 
time be published 

1[***].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>121</number> Period 
within which copies of specification etc. are to be filed.—The period within 
which copies of specification or corresponding documents to be filed by the 
applicant under sub­-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 138 shall be three months from the 
date of communication by the Controller.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>121A</number> Address 
of Communications.—All communications in relation to any proceeding under 
the Act or these rules shall be addressed to the Controller at the appropriate 
office.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>122</number> Correction of 
clerical errors.—A 
request for the correction of a clerical error in any document referred to in 
section 78 shall be accompanied by a copy of the document highlighting the 
corrections clearly along with the fees payable therefor as specified in the 
First Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>123</number> Manner of 
advertisement of the proposed correction of any error.—Where 
the Controller requires a notice of the nature of the proposed correction to be 
advertised, the request and the nature of the proposed correction shall be 
published 

1[***] and the 
person making the request shall also serve copies of the request and the copies 
of the document showing the proposed corrections to such persons who, in the 
opinion of the Controller, may be interested.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>124</number> Manner and time of 
opposition to the making of corrections.— 

<section><number>1</number> Any person interested may, at any time, within three months from the date of 
the advertisement of the request for correction 

1[***] give notice 
of opposition to the Controller in Form 14 in duplicate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such notice of 
opposition shall be accompanied by a statement in duplicate setting out the 
nature of the opponent’s interest, the facts on which he relies and the relief 
which he seeks.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the notice 
and of the statement shall be sent by the Controller to the person making the 
request.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The procedure 
specified in rules 58 to 63 relating to the filing of reply statement, leaving 
evidence and hearing and costs shall, so far as may be, apply to the hearing of 
the opposition under section 78 as they apply 

2[in the hearing of 
the opposition proceeding].
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>125</number> Notification of 
corrections.—The 
Controller shall notify the person making a request for the correction and the 
opponent, if any, of the corrections made in the relevant document.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>126</number> Form, etc., of 
affidavits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The affidavits required by the Act or these rules to be filed at the patent 
office or furnished to the Controller shall be duly sworn to in the manner as 
prescribed in sub-rule (3).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Affidavits shall be 
confined to such facts as the deponent is able, of his own knowledge, to prove 
except in interlocutory matters, where statements of belief of the deponent may 
be admitted, provided that the grounds thereof are given.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Affidavits shall be 
sworn to as follows:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  in 
India—before any court or person having by law authority to receive evidence, or 
before any officer empowered by such court as aforesaid to administer oaths or 
to take affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  in any 
country or place outside India—before a diplomatic or consular officer, within 
the meaning of the Diplomatic and Consular Officers (Oaths and Fees) Act, 1948 
(41 of 1948) in such country or place or before a notary of the country or 
place, recognised by the Central Government under section 14 of the Notaries 
Act, 1952 (53 of 1952), or before a judge or magistrate of the country or place.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Alterations and 
interlineations shall, before an affidavit is sworn to or affirmed be 
authenticated by the initials of the person before whom the affidavit is sworn 
to.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>127</number> Exhibits.—Where 
there are exhibits to be filed in an opposition or any other proceedings, a copy 
or impression of each exhibit shall be supplied to the other party at his 
request and expense; if copies or impressions of the exhibits cannot 
conveniently be furnished, the originals shall be left with the Controller for 
inspection by the person interested by prior appointment. The exhibits in 
original if not already left with the Controller shall be produced at the 
hearing.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>128</number> Directions not 
otherwise prescribed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where for the proper prosecution or completion of any proceedings under the Act 
or these rules, the Controller is of the opinion that it is necessary for a 
party to such proceedings to perform an act, file a document or produce 
evidence, for which provision has not been made in the Act or these rules, he 
may, by notice in writing, require such party to perform the act, file the 
document or produce the evidence specified in such notice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an applicant or 
a party to a proceeding desires to be heard or not heard, the Controller may, at 
any time, require him to submit his statement in writing giving such information 
as the Controller may deem necessary within the time specified by him.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>129</number> Exercise 
of discretionary power by the Controller.—Before exercising any 
discretionary power under the Act or these rules which is likely to affect an 
applicant for a patent or a party to a proceeding adversely, the Controller 
shall give such applicant or party, a hearing, after giving him or them, ten 
days notice of such hearing ordinarily.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>130</number> Application for 
review of decisions or setting aside of orders of the Controller.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application to the Controller for the review of his decision under clause (f) 
of sub-section (1) of section 77 shall be made in 

1[Form 24] within 
one month from the date of communication of such decision to the applicant or 
within such further period not exceeding one month thereafter as the Controller 
may on a request made in Form 4 allow and shall be accompanied by a statement 
setting forth the grounds on which the review is sought. Where the decision in 
question concerns any other person in addition to the applicant, the Controller 
shall forthwith transmit a copy of each of the application and the statement to 
the other person concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application to the 
Controller for setting aside an order passed by him ex parte under clause 
(g) of sub-section (1) of section 77 shall be made in 

2[Form 24] within 
one month from the date of communication of such order to the applicant or 
within such further period not exceeding one month as the Controller may on a 
request made in Form 4 allow and shall be accompanied by a statement setting 
forth the grounds on which the application is based. Where the order concerns 
any other person in addition to the applicant, the Controller shall, forthwith 
transmit a copy each of the application and the statement to the other person 
concerned.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>131</number> Form and manner in 
which statements required under section 146(2) to be furnished.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The statements which shall be furnished by every patentee and every licensee 
under sub-section (2) of section 146 in 

1[Form 27] which 
shall be duly verified by the patentee or the licencee or his authorised agent.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The statements 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be furnished in respect of every calendar year 
within three months of the end of each year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Controller may 
publish the information received by him under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
of section 146 

2[***].
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>132</number> Form of 
application for the issue of duplicate patent.—An 
application for the issue of a duplicate patent under section 154 shall contain 
a statement setting out the circumstances in which the patent was lost or 
destroyed or cannot be produced together with the fee as specified therefor in 
the First Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>133</number> Supply of 
certified copies and certificates under sections 72 and 147.—Certified 
copies of any entry in the register, or certificates of, or extracts from 
patents, specifications and other public documents in the patent office, or from 
registers and other records including records in computer floppies, diskettes or 
any other electronic form kept there, may be furnished by the Controller on a 
request therefor made to him and on payment of the fee specified therefor in the 
First Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>134</number> Request for 
information under section 153.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A request for information in respect of the following matters relating to any 
patent or application for patent shall be admissible, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  as to when a 
complete specification following a provisional specification has been filed or 
an application for patent has been deemed to have been abandoned;
 
 

1[(aa)  as to when 
the information under section 8 has been filed.]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  as to when 
publication of application has been made under section 11A;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  as to when an 
application has been withdrawn under section 11B;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  as to when a 
request for examination has been made under section 11B;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  as to when 
the examination report has been issued under section 12;
 
 

2[(f)  as to when 
an application for patent has been refused;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  as to when a 
patent has been granted;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  as to when a 
renewal fee has been paid;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  as to when 
the term of a patent has expired or shall expire;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  as to when 
an entry has been made in the register or application has been made for the 
making of such entry; or
 
 

3[(k)  as to when 
any application is made or action taken involving an entry in the register, 
publication in the 

4[Official Journal] 
or otherwise, if the nature of the application or action is specified in the 
request.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Separate request shall 
be made in respect of each item of information required.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fee payable on a 
request to be made under section 153 shall be as set out in the First Schedule.
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>135</number> Agency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The authorisation of an agent for the purposes of the Act and these rules shall 
be in Form 26 or in the form of a power of attorney.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
authorisation has been made under sub-rule (1), service upon the agent of any 
document relating to any proceeding or matter under the Act or these rules shall 
be deemed to be service upon the person so authorising him and all 
communications directed to be made to a person in respect of any proceeding or 
matter may be addressed to such agent, and all appearances before the Controller 
relating thereto may be made by or through such agent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1) and (2), the Controller may, if it is 
considered necessary, require the personal signature or presence of an 
applicant, opponent or party to such proceeding or matter.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>136</number> Scale of costs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In all proceedings before the Controller, he may, subject to rule 63, award 
costs as he considers reasonable, having regard to all the circumstances of the 
case: 
 
Provided that the amount 
of costs awarded in respect of any matter set forth in the Fourth Schedule shall 
not exceed the amount specified therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Controller may, in his discretion award 
a compensatory cost in any proceeding before him which in his opinion is false 
or vexatious.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>137</number> Powers of 
Controller generally.—Any 
document for the amendment of which no special provision is made in the Act may 
be amended and any irregularity in procedure which in the opinion of the 
Controller may be obviated without detriment to the interests of any person, may 
be corrected if the Controller thinks fit and upon such terms as he may direct.
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>138</number> Power to 
extend time prescribed.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided 

2[in the rules 24B, 
sub-rule (4) of rule 55 and sub-rule (1A) of rule 80], the time prescribed by 
these rules for doing of any act or the taking of any proceeding thereunder may 
be extended by the Controller for a period of one month, if he thinks it fit to 
do so and upon such terms as he may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any request for 
extension of time made under these rules shall be made before the expiry of 
prescribed period.]
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>139</number> Hearing before the 
Controller to be in public in certain cases.—Where 
the hearing before the Controller of any dispute between two or more parties 
relating to an application for a patent or to any matter in connection with a 
patent takes place after the date of the publication of the complete 
specification, the hearing of the dispute shall be in public unless the 
Controller, after consultation with the parties to the dispute who appear in 
person or are represented at the hearing, otherwise directs.
  
  
</article><form>
 

The Patents rules, 2003
 





 



1[The 
Third Schedule
 


(Refer rule 74)
 




Form of Patent
 



Government of India
 




 


Patent No. 
...........................................
 


Application No. 
.................................
 


Date of 
filing.......................................
 


Patentee...............................................................................................................................................
 


Inventor(s) (Where 
applicable).......................................................................................................
 


It is hereby certified that 
a patent has been granted to the patentee for an invention 
entitled................................................................................................... 
as disclosed in the above mentioned application for the term of 20 years from 
the............... day of.................20....... in accordance with the 
provisions of the Patents Act, 1970.
 


 
 


Date of 
Grant..................     Controller of Patents
 


Seal of the Office)
 


Note.—The 
fees for renewal of this patent, if it is to be maintained will fall due 
on..................... day of ....................20...... and on the same day 
in every year thereafter.]
 


 
 


—————
 

   1.  
Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004, for the Heading “Opposition
to The Grant of Patents” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005) and again substituted by
S.O. 657(E), dated 5h May, 2006, for “Opposition
Proceedings” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rules “55.
Filing of notice of opposition.—The notice of opposition to be given under
sub-section (1) of section 25 shall be made in Form 7 and sent to the Controller
in duplicate.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “Opposition by
representation against the grant of patent” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “(1) Representation for
opposition under sub‑section (1) of section 25 shall be filed at the
appropriate office within a period not exceeding three months from the date of
publication of the application under section 11 A of the Act, or before the
grant of patent, whichever is later and shall include a statement and evidence,
if any, in support of the representation and a request for hearing if so
desired” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “effect” (w.e.f.
5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “one month” (w.e.f.
5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “sub-section (3) of section 25” (w.e.f. 
5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “notice of opposition” (w.e.f. 
5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “sub-section (4) of section 25” (w.e.f. 
5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “applicant” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(2) If the applicant does not 
desire to contest or leave his reply and evidence within the period as specified 
in sub-rule (1), the application for patent shall be deemed to have been 
abandoned.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “applicant’s” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “applicant” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(1) On the completion of the 
presentation of evidence, if any, or at such other time as the Controller may 
think fit, he shall forthwith fix a date and time for the hearing of the 
opposition and shall give the parties not less than ten days’ notice of such 
hearing.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(5) After hearing the party or 
parties desirous of being heard, or if neither party desires to be heard, then 
without a hearing, the Controller shall forthwith decide the opposition and 
notify his decision to the parties giving reasons therefor.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “63. Determination of costs.—If 
the applicant notifies the Controller that he does not desire to proceed with 
the application after notice of opposition is given, the Controller, depending 
on the merits of the case, may decide whether costs should be awarded to the 
opponent.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Ins. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Rule “64. Time 
within which complete specification is to be amended under section 27.—The 
time within which an applicant shall amend his complete specification to the 
satisfaction of the Controller under section 27 shall be two months from the 
date of such intimation by the Controller” omitted by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th 
December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Rule “65. 
Procedure to be followed.—(1) If the specification has not been amended to 
the satisfaction of the Controller within the time allowed under rule 64, he 
shall forthwith fix a date and time for hearing and the applicant shall be given 
at least ten days’ notice of such date of hearing.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “69. Procedure for the hearing of 
claim or an application under section 28.—The procedure specified in rules 
55 and 57 to 63 relating to the filing of notice of opposition, written 
statement, reply statement, leaving evidence hearing and cost shall, so far as 
may be, apply to the hearing of a claim or an application under section 28 as 
they apply to the proceedings in opposition to the grant of patents subject to 
the modification that reference to applicant shall be construed as the person 
making the claim or an application as the case may be.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “71. Permission for making patent 
application outside  
India under section 39 .—Request 
for permission for making patent application outside India shall be made on Form 
30.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “(2) The request made under sub‑rule (1) shall 
be disposed of by the Controller ordinarily within a period of three months from 
the date of filing of such request” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>
Rule “73. Sealing of patents.—(1) A request for the sealing of
a patent under sub-section (1) of section 43 shall be made in Form 9.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “74. Form of patent.—A patent shall be 
in the form as specified in the Third Schedule with such modifications as the 
circumstances of each case may require and shall bear the number accorded to the 
application under rule 37” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Subs. by S.O. 657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “74.
Form of patent.—A patent shall be in the
form as specified in the Third Schedule with such modifications as the
circumstances of each case may require and shall bear the number accorded to the
application under rule 37” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Sub. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “78. Procedure for the hearing of 
proceedings under section 51.—The procedure specified in rules 55 and 57 to 
63 relating to the filing of notice of opposition, written statement, reply 
statement, leaving evidence, hearing and costs shall, so far as may be, apply to 
the hearing of an application under section 51 as they apply to the hearing of 
an opposition to the grant of patents.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Ins. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>
Ins. by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “accepted” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(3) (a) If the application for 
amendment under sub-rule (1) is made after the acceptance of the complete 
specification and the nature of the proposed amendment is substantive, the 
application shall be advertised in the Official Gazette.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “83. Advertisement of the amendments 
allowed.—The amendments allowed after a complete specification has been 
accepted, shall be advertised in the Official Gazette.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(3) Where applicant requests for a 
hearing within the time allowed and the Controller, after giving the applicant 
such a hearing, is prima facie satisfied that the failure to pay the 
renewal fees was unintentional, he shall advertise the application in the 
Official Gazette.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “85. Opposition to restoration under 
section 61.—(1) At any time within two months from the date of advertisement 
of the application in the Official Gazette under sub-rule (3) of rule 84, any 
person interested may give notice of opposition thereto in Form 14.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(2) The Controller shall advertise 
his decision in the Official Gazette.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “87. Surrender of patents.—(1) 
The Controller shall advertise the notice of an offer given under section 63 in 
the Official Gazette.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “sealing” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Controller or the courts” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>  Rule “89. 
Registration of documents under section 68.—An application for the 
registration of a document under section 68 shall be made in Form 16.” omitted 
by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 17” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “96. Application for compulsory 
licence, etc.—(1) An application to the Controller for an order under 
section 84, section 85, section 91 or section 92 shall be in Form 18, or in Form 
20, as the case may be. Except in the case of an application made by the Central 
Government, the application shall set out the nature of the applicant’s interest 
and terms and conditions of the licence the applicant is willing to accept.” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “advertisement” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “ of opposition to the grant of patents” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “99. Manner of advertisement of the 
revocation order.—The Controller shall advertise in the Official Gazette the 
order made by him under sub-section (3) of section 85 revoking a patent.” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 21” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “of opposition to the grant of patents” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 22” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “of opposition to the grant of patent” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “names and addresses” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>  Ins. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 23” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for sub-rule “(3) The qualifying marks for each 
written paper and for the viva voce examination shall be fifty per 
cent. each, and a candidate shall be declared to have passed the examination 
only if he obtains an aggregate of sixty per cent. of the qualifying marks.” (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>  Ins. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 23” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “shall be notified in the Official Gazette” 
(w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 24” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “shall be notified by the Controller in the 
Official Gazette” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “shall be notified in the Official Gazette” 
(w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>  The words “in the 
Official Gazette, and in such other manner as the Controller may deem fit” 
omitted by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “121. Address of communications.—All 
communications in relation to any proceeding under the Act or these rules shall 
be addressed to the Controller at the appropriate office.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “121. Address of communications.—All 
communications in relation to any proceeding under the Act or these rules shall 
be addressed to the Controller at the appropriate office.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number>  The words “in the 
Official Gazette” omitted by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>  The words “in the 
Official Gazette” omitted by S.O. 1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 
1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “to the hearing of the opposition to the 
grant of patents” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “129. Exercise of discretionary 
power by the Controller.—Before exercising any discretionary power under the 
Act or these rules adversely to an applicant for a patent or a party to a 
proceeding the Controller shall give such applicant or party, a hearing, after 
giving him at least ten day’s notice of such hearing.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 25” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 25” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for “Form 29” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>  The words “in the 
Official Gazette and in such other manner as he may deem fit” omitted by S.O. 
1418 (E), dated 28th December, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number>  Ins. by S.O. 657(E), 
dated 5th May, 2006, (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for clauses “ (f) as to when a complete 
specification has been accepted or when an application for patent has been 
refused;</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for clause “(k) as to when any application is 
made or action taken involving an entry in the register or advertisement in the 
Official Gazette, if the nature of the application or action is specified in the 
request.” (w.e.f. 1-1-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “Official Gazette” (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number>  Subs. by S.O. 1418 
(E), dated 28th December, 2004, for rule “138. Power to extend time 
prescribed.—(1) The time prescribed by these rules for doing of any act or 
the taking of any proceeding thereunder may be extended by the Controller 
normally not more than three months, if he thinks it fit to do so and upon such 
terms as he may direct:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
657(E), dated 5th May, 2006, for “in the rules 24, 55 and 80(1A)” (w.e.f. 
5-5-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>