<act><title>


The Public Liability 
    Insurance Act, 1991</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This 
    Act may be called the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint.
 
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>   
    “accident” means an accident involving a fortuitous or sudden or unintended 
    occurrence while handling any hazardous substance resulting in continuous or 
    intermittent or repeated exposure to death of, or injury to, any person or 
    damage to any property but does not include an accident by reason only of 
    war or radio-activity;] 
    2[(a) “accident” means an accident involving a 
    fortuitous or sudden or unintended occurrence while handling any hazardous 
    substance resulting in continuous or intermittent or repeated exposure to 
    death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any property but does not 
    include an accident by reason only of war or radio-activity;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Collector” means the Collector having 
    jurisdiction over the area in which the accident occurs; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “handling”, in relation to any hazardous 
    substance, means the manufacture, processing, treatment, package, storage, 
    transportation by vehicle, use, collection, destruction, conversion, 
    offering for sale, transfer or the like of such hazardous substance; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “hazardous substance” means any 
    substance or preparation which is defined as hazardous substance under the 
    Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986), and exceeding such 
    quantity* as may be specified, by notification, by the Central Government; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “insurance” means insurance against 
    liability under sub-section (1) of section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 

1[(g)   
    “owner” means a person who owns, or has control over handling, any hazardous 
    substance at the time of accident and includes— 
    2[(g) “owner” means a person who owns, or has control 
    over handling, any hazardous substance at the time of accident and 
    includes—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   in the case of a firm, any of its 
    partners; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in the case of an association, any of 
    its members; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   in the case of a company, any of its 
    directors, managers, secretaries or other officers who is directly in charge 
    of, and is responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of 
    the company;] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>h</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 

2[(ha)   
    “Relief Fund” means the Environmental Relief Fund established under section 
    7A;] 
    1[(ha) “Relief Fund” means the Environmental Relief 
    Fund established under section 7A;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “rules” means rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “vehicle” means any mode of surface 
    transport other than railways. 
 
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Liability to give relief in certain cases on principle of no fault.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where death or injury to any person (other than a workman) or damage to any 
    property has resulted from an accident, the owner shall be liable to give 
    such relief as is specified in the Schedule for such death, injury or 
    damage.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In any 
    claim for relief under sub-section (1) (hereinafter referred to in this Act 
    as claim for relief), the claimant shall not be required to plead and 
    establish that the death, injury or damage in respect of which the claim has 
    been made was due to any wrongful act, neglect or default of any person. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   “workman” has the meaning assigned to it 
    in the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   “injury” includes permanent total or 
    permanent partial disability or sickness resulting out of an accident. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Duty of 
    owner to take out insurance policies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every owner shall take out, before he starts handling any hazardous 
    substance, one or more insurance policies providing for contracts of 
    insurance whereby he is insured against liability to give relief under 
    sub-section (1) of section 3: 
 
Provided that 
    any owner handling any hazardous substance immediately before the 
    commencement of this Act shall take out such insurance policy or policies as 
    soon as may be and in any case within a period of one year from such 
    commencement. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    owner shall get the insurance policy, referred to in sub-section (1), 
    renewed from time to time before the expiry of the period of validity 
    thereof so that the insurance policies may remain in force throughout the 
    period during which such handling is continued. 
 


    1[(2A) No insurance 
    policy taken out or renewed by an owner shall be for an amount less than the 
    amount of the paid-up capital of the undertaking handling any hazardous 
    substance and owned or controlled by that owner, and more than the amount, 
    not exceeding fifty crore rupees, as may be prescribed. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “paid-up capital” means, in the case of an owner not being 
    a company, the market value of all assets and stocks of the undertaking on 
    the date of contract of insurance. 
 </section><section>
<number>2B</number> The 
    liability of the insurer under one insurance policy shall not exceed the 
    amount specified in the terms of the contract of insurance in that insurance 
    policy. 
 </section><section>
<number>2C</number> Every 
    owner shall also, together with the amount of premium, pay to the insurer, 
    for being credited to the Relief Fund established under section 7A, such 
    further amount, not exceeding the sum equivalent to the amount of premium, 
    as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2D</number> The 
    insurer shall remit to the authority specified in sub-section (3) of section 
    7A the amount received from the owner under sub-section (2C) for being 
    credited to the Relief Fund in such manner and within such period as may be 
    prescribed and where the insurer fails to so remit that amount, it shall be 
    recoverable from the insurer as arrears of land revenue or of public 
    demand.] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification, exempt from the operation of 
    sub-section (1) any owner, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any State Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any corporation owned or controlled by 
    the Central Government or a State Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   any local authority: 
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall be made in relation to such owner unless a fund has been 
    established and is maintained by that owner in accordance with the rules 
    made in this behalf for meeting any liability under sub-section (1) of 
    section 3. 
 
 

 
 

 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Verification and publication of accident by Collector.—Whenever 
    it comes to the notice of the Collector that an accident has occurred at any 
    place within his jurisdiction, he shall verify the occurrence of such 
    accident and cause publicity to be given in such manner as he deems fit for 
    inviting applications under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Application for claim for relief.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for claim for relief may be made— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   by the person who has sustained the 
    injury; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   by the owner of the property to which 
    the damage has been caused; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   where death has resulted from the 
    accident, by all or any of the legal representatives of the deceased; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   by any agent duly authorised by such 
    person or owner of such property or all or any of the legal representatives 
    of the deceased, as the case may be: 
 
Provided that 
    where all the legal representatives of the deceased have not joined in any 
    such application for relief, the application shall be made on behalf of or 
    for the benefit of all the legal representatives of the deceased and the 
    legal representatives who have not so joined shall be impleaded as 
    respondents to the application. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    application under sub-section (1) shall be made to the Collector and shall 
    be in such form, contain such particulars and shall be accompanied by such 
    documents as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    application for relief shall be entertained unless it is made within five 
    years of the occurrence of the accident. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Award of 
    relief.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an 
    application under sub-section (1) of section 6, the Collector shall, after 
    giving notice of the application to the owner and after giving the parties 
    an opportunity of being heard, hold an inquiry into the claim or, each of 
    the claims, and may make an award determining the amount of relief which 
    appears to him to be just and specifying the person or persons to whom such 
    amount of relief shall be paid. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Collector shall arrange to deliver copies of the award to the parties 
    concerned expeditiously and in any case within a period of fifteen days from 
    the date of the award. 
 


    1[(3) When an award is 
    made under this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the insurer, who is required to pay any 
    amount in terms of such award and to the extent specified in sub-section 
    (2B) of section 4, shall, within a period of thirty days of the date of 
    announcement of the award, deposit that amount in such manner as the 
    Collector may direct; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the Collector shall arrange to pay from 
    the Relief Fund, in terms of such award and in accordance with the scheme 
    under section 7A, to the person or persons referred to in sub-section (1) 
    such amount as may be specified in that scheme; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the owner shall, within such period, 
    deposit such amount in such manner as the Collector may direct.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> In holding 
    any inquiry under sub-section (1), the Collector may, subject to any rules 
    made in this behalf, follow such summary procedure as he thinks fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Collector shall have all the powers of a Civil Court for the purpose of 
    taking evidence on oath and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and of 
    compelling the discovery and production of documents and material objects 
    and for such other purposes as may be prescribed; and the Collector shall be 
    deemed to be a Civil Court for all the purposes of section 195 and Chapter 
    XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    insurer or the owner against whom the award is made under sub-section (1) 
    fails to deposit the amount of such award within the period specified under 
    sub-section (3), such amount shall be recoverable from the owner, or as the 
    case may be, the insurer as arrears of land revenue or of public demand. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A claim 
    for relief in respect of death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any 
    property shall be disposed of as expeditiously as possible and every 
    endeavour shall be made to dispose of such claim within three months of the 
    receipt of the application for relief under sub-section (1) of section 6. 
 


    2[(8) Where an owner 
    is likely to remove or dispose of his property with the object of evading 
    payment by him of any amount of the award, the Collector may, in accordance 
    with the provisions of rules 1 to 4 of Order XXXIX of the First Schedule to 
    the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), grant a temporary injunction 
    to restrain such act.] 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>7A</number> Establishment of 
    Environmental Relief Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, establish a fund to be known as 
    the Environmental Relief Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Relief 
    Fund shall be utilised for paying, in accordance with the provisions of this 
    Act and the scheme made under sub-section (3), relief under the award made 
    by the Collector under section 7. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification, make a scheme specifying the 
    authority in which the Relief Fund shall vest, the manner in which the 
    Relief Fund shall be administered, the form and the manner in which money 
    shall be drawn from the Relief Fund and for all other matters connected with 
    or incidental to the administration of the Relief Fund and the payment of 
    relief therefrom.] 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Provisions as to other right to claim compensation for death, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The right to claim relief under sub-section (1) of section 3 in respect of 
    death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any property shall be in 
    addition to any other right to claim compensation in respect thereof under 
    any other law for the time being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where in respect of 
    death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any property, the owner, 
    liable to give claim for relief, is also liable to pay compensation under 
    any other law, the amount of such compensation shall be reduced by the 
    amount of relief paid under this Act. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    call for information.—Any person 
    authorised by the Central Government may, for the purposes of ascertaining 
    whether any requirements of this Act or of any rule or of any direction 
    given under this Act have been complied with, require any owner to submit to 
    that person such information as that person may reasonably think necessary. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power 
    of entry and inspection.—Any 
    person, authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, shall have a 
    right to enter, at all reasonable times with such assistance as he considers 
    necessary, any place, premises or vehicle, where hazardous substance is 
    handled for the purpose of determining whether any provisions of this Act or 
    of any rule or of any direction given under this Act is being or has been 
    complied with and such owner is bound to render all assistance to such 
    person.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Power 
    of search and seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> If a 
    person, authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, has reason to 
    believe that handling of any hazardous substance is taking place in any 
    place, premises or vehicle, in contravention of sub-section (1) of section 
    4, he may enter into and search such place, premises or vehicle for such 
    handling of hazardous substance.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, as 
    a result of any search under sub-section (1) any handling of hazardous 
    substance has been found in relation to which contravention of sub-section 
    (1) of section 4 has taken place, he may seize such hazardous substance and 
    other things which, in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any 
    proceeding under this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    where it is not practicable to seize any such substance or thing, he may 
    serve on the owner an order that the owner shall not remove, part with or 
    otherwise deal with, the hazardous substance and such other things except 
    with the previous permission of that person. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> He may, if 
    he has reason to believe that it is expedient to do to prevent an accident 
    dispose of the hazardous substance seized under sub-section (2) immediately 
    in such manner as he may deem fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    expenses incurred by him in the disposal of hazardous substances under 
    sub-section (3) shall be recoverable from the owner as arrears of land revenue 
    or of public demand. 
 

 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power 
    to give directions.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law but subject to the provisions of this 
    Act, the Central Government may, in exercise of its powers and performance 
    of its functions under this Act, issue such directions in writing as it may 
    deem fit for the purposes of this Act to any owner or any person, officer, 
    authority or agency and such owner, person, officer, authority or agency 
    shall be bound to comply with such directions. 
 

    Explanation.— For the removal of 
    doubts, it is hereby declared that the power to issue directions under this 
    section includes the power to direct— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   prohibition or regulation of the 
    handling of any hazardous substance; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   stoppage or regulation of the supply of 
    electricity, water or any other service. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Power 
    to make application to Courts for restraining owner from handling hazardous 
    substances.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Central 
    Government or any person authorised* by that Government in this behalf has 
    reason to believe that any owner has been handling any hazardous substance 
    in contravention of any of the provisions of this Act, that Government or, 
    as the case may be, that person may make an application to a Court not 
    inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of 
    first class for restraining such owner from such handling. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of the application under sub-section (1), the Court may make such order as 
    it deems fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    under sub-section (2), the Court makes an order restraining any owner from 
    handling hazardous substance, it may, in that order—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   direct such owner to desist from such 
    handling; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   authorise the Central Government or, as 
    the case may be, the person referred to in sub-section (1), if the direction 
    under clause (a) is not complied with by the owner to whom such direction is 
    issued, to implement the direction in such manner as may be specified by the 
    Court. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    expenses incurred by the Central Government, or as the case may be, the 
    person in implementing the directions of Court under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (3), shall be recoverable from the owner as arrears of land 
    revenue or of public demand. 
 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 The Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991
  
 <article><number>14</number> Penalty for contravention of 

1[sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (2) 
or sub-section (2A) or sub-section (2C)] of section 4 or failure to comply with 
directions under section 12.—(1) Whoever contravenes any of the provisions 
of 

1[sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) or 
sub-section (2A) or sub-section (2C)] of section 4 or fails to comply with any 
direction issued under section 12, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
a term which shall not be less than one year and six months but which may extend 
to six years, or with fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees, or with 
both.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, having already been 
convicted of an offence under sub-section (1), is convicted for the second 
offence or any offence subsequent to the second offence, he shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two years but which 
may extend to seven years and with fine which shall not be less than one lakh 
rupees.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in section 
360 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), or in the Probation of 
Offenders Act, 1958 (20 of 1958), shall apply to a person convicted of an 
offence under this Act unless such person is under eighteen years of age.









</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Penalty 
    for failure to comply with direction under section 9 or order under section 
    11 or obstructing any person in discharge of his functions under section 10 
    or 11.—If any owner fails to 
    comply with direction issued under section 9 or fails to comply with order 
    issued under sub-section (2) of section 11, or obstructs any person in 
    discharge of his functions under section 10 or sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or 
    sub-section (3) of section 11, he shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to ten 
    thousand rupees, or with both. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
    who, at the time the offence was committed, was directly in charge of, and 
    was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
    company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence 
    and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Offences by Government Departments.—Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of 
    Government, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this section shall render such Head of the Department 
    liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without 
    his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Cognizance of offence.—No court 
    shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a complaint 
    made by— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the Central Government or any authority 
    or officer authorised* in this behalf by that Government; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any person who has given notice of not 
    less than sixty days in the manner prescribed, of the alleged offence and of 
    his intention to make a complaint, to the Central Government or the 
    authority or officer authorised as aforesaid. 
 
 

 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Power 
    to delegate.—The Central 
    Government may, by notification, delegate, subject to such conditions and 
    limitations as may be specified in the notification, such of its powers and 
    functions under this Act (except the power under section 23) as it may deem 
    necessary or expedient to any person (including any officer, authority or 
    other agency). 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government 
    or the person, officer, authority or other agency in respect of anything 
    which is done or intended to be done in good faith in pursuance of this Act 
    or the rules made or orders or directions issued thereunder. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, constitute an Advisory Committee 
    on the matters relating to the insurance policy under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Advisory Committee shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   three officers representing the Central 
    Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   two persons representing the insurers; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   two persons representing the owners; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   two persons from amongst the experts of 
    insurance or hazardous substances, to be appointed by the Central 
    Government. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman of the Advisory Committee shall be one of the members representing 
    the Central Government, nominated in this behalf by that Government.
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Effect 
    of other laws.—The provisions of 
    this Act and any rules made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding 
    anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of 
    this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 

1[(a)   
    the maximum amount for which an insurance policy may be taken out by an 
    owner under sub-section (2A) of section 4; 
 <subsection>
<number>aa</number>   the amount required to be paid by every 
    owner for being credited, to the Relief Fund under sub-section (2C) of 
    section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ab</number>   the manner in which and the period 
    within which the amount received from the owner is required to be remitted 
    by the insurer under sub-section (2D) of section 4;] 
 

2[(ac)]   
    establishment and maintenance of fund under sub-section (3) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the form of application and the 
    particulars to be given therein and the documents to accompany such 
    application under sub-section (2) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the procedure for holding an inquiry 
    under sub-section (4) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the purposes for which the Collector 
    shall have powers of a Civil Court under sub-section (5) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the manner in which notice of the 
    offence and of the intention to make a complaint to the Central Government 
    shall be given under clause (b) of section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every 

    3[rule or scheme] made 
    under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the 

    3[rule or scheme] or 
    both Houses agree that the 

    3[rule or scheme] 
    should not be made, the 

    3[rule or scheme] 
    shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
    as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
    shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
    that 

    3[rule or scheme]. 
 
 
  








 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Public Liability 
    Insurance Act, 1991
 

 
 

 
 


THE SCHEDULE
 


[See section 3(1)]
 


(i) Reimbursement of medical expenses incurred 
    up to a maximum of Rs. 12,500 in each case.
 


(ii) For fatal accidents the relief will be Rs. 
    25,000 per person in addition to reimbursement of medical expenses, if any, 
    incurred on the victim up to a maximum of Rs. 12,500.
 


(iii) For permanent total or permanent partial 
    disability or other injury or sickness, the relief will be (a) reimbursement 
    of medical expenses incurred, if any, up to a maximum of Rs. 12,500 in each 
    case and (b) cash relief on the basis of percentage of disablement as 
    certified by an authorised physician. The relief for total permanent 
    disability will be Rs. 25,000.
 


(iv) For loss of wages due to temporary 
    partial disability which reduces the earning capacity of the victim, there 
    will be a fixed monthly relief not exceeding Rs. 1,000 per month up to a 
    maximum of 3 months : provided the victim has been hospitalised for a period 
    exceeding 3 days and is above 16 years of age.
 


(v) Up to Rs. 6,000 depending on the actual 
    damage, for any damage to private property. 

 
 




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>