<act><tid>1831584</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 1 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 31st December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1100631</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1196353</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Companies (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>23401</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>827457</tid>
<number>2</number>Insertion of new Part IXA.- In the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
after Part IX, the following Part shall be inserted, namely:-
' PART IXA

CHAPTER I

PRODUCER COMPANIES

</article>



<article><tid>660363</tid>
<number> 581A</number> Definitions.- In this Part, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>944930</tid>
<number>a</number>" active Member" means a member who fulfils the quantum and period 
of patronage of the Producer Company as may be required by the 
articles;

</section>

<section><tid>1703360</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chief Executive" means an individual appointed as such under 
sub- section (1) of section 581W;

</section>

<section><tid>1305153</tid>
<number>c</number>" limited return" means the maximum dividend as may be specified by 
the articles;

</section>

<section><tid>949058</tid>
<number>d</number>" Member" means a person or Producer institution (whether  
  incorporated or not) admitted as a Member of a Producer Company and 
who retains the qualifications necessary for continuance as such;

</section>

<section><tid>66600</tid>
<number>e</number>" inter- State co- operative society" means a multi- State 
co- operative society as defined in clause (p) of section 3 of the 
Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, <year>2002</year> (39 of <year>2002</year>) and includes 
any co- operative society registered under any other law fo the time 
being in force, which has, subsequent to its formation, extended any 
of its objects to more than one State by enlisting the participation 
of persons or by extending any of its activities outside the State, 
whether directly or indirectly or thro gh an institution of which it 
is a constituent;

</section>

<section><tid>1142096</tid>
<number>f</number>" mutual assistance principles" means the principles set out in 
sub- section (2) of section 581G;

</section>

<section><tid>66144</tid>
<number>g</number>" officer" includes any director or Chief Executive or Secretary or 
any person in accordance with whose directions or instructions part or 
whole of the business of the Producer Company is carried on;

</section>

<section><tid>559663</tid>
<number>h</number>" patronage" means the use of services offered by the Producer 
Company to its Members by participation in its business activities;

</section>

<section><tid>1888982</tid>
<number>i</number>" patronage bonus" means payments made by a Producer Company out of 
its surplus income to the Members in proportion to their respective 
patronage;

</section>

<section><tid>1263373</tid>
<number>j</number>" primary produce" means-

<subsection><tid>497497</tid>
<number>i</number>produce of farmers, arising from agriculture (including animal  
husbandry, horticulture, floriculture, pisciculture, viticulture, 
forestry, forest products, re- vegetation, bee raising and farming 
  plantation products), or from any other primary activit or service 
which promotes the interest of the farmers or consumers; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108817</tid>
<number>ii</number>produce of persons engaged in handloom, handicraft and other 
cottage industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>115454</tid>
<number>iii</number>any product resulting from any of the above activities, 
including by- products of such products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>100068</tid>
<number>iv</number>any product resulting from an ancillary activity that would 
assist or promote any of the aforesaid activities or anything 
ancillary thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>702935</tid>
<number>v</number>any activity which is intended to increase the production of 
anything referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (iv) or improve the quality 
thereof;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1501236</tid>
<number>k</number>" producer" means any person engaged in any activity connected with 
or relatable to any primary produce;

</section>

<section><tid>159038</tid>
<number>l</number>" Producer Company" means a body corporate having objects or 
activities specified in section 581B and registered as Producer 
Company under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1231499</tid>
<number>m</number>" Producer institution" means a Producer Company or any other 
institution having only producer or producers or Producer Company or 
Producer Companies as its member whether incorporated or not having 
any of the objects referred to in section 581B and w ich agrees to 
make use of the services of the Producer Company or Producer Companies 
as provided in its articles.

</section>

<section><tid>563972</tid>
<number>n</number>" withheld price" means part of the price due and payable for goods 
supplied by any Member to the Producer Company; and as withheld by 
the Producer Company for payment on a subsequent date.
CHAPTER II

INCORPORATION OF PRODUCER COMPANIES AND OTHER MATTERS


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>676747</tid>
<number> 581B</number> Objects of Producer Company.-
<section><tid>1958624</tid>
<number>1</number>The objects of the Producer  
Company shall relate to all or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1350791</tid>
<number>a</number>production, harvesting, procurement, grading, pooling, handling, 
marketing, selling, export of primary produce of the Members or import 
of goods or services for their benefit:
Provided that the Producer Company may carry on any of the activities 
specified in this clause either by itself or through other 
institution;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>475560</tid>
<number>b</number>processing including preserving, drying, distilling, brewing, 
vinting, canning and packaging of produce of its Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>509967</tid>
<number>c</number>manufacture, sale or supply of machinery, equipment or consumables 
mainly to its Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>51005</tid>
<number>d</number>providing education on the mutual assistance principles to its 
Members and others;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1632803</tid>
<number>e</number>rendering technical services, consultancy services, training, 
research and development and all other activities for the promotion of 
the interests of its Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>872592</tid>
<number>f</number>generation, transmission and distribution of power, revitalisation 
of land and water resources, their use, conservation and communication 
relatable to primary produce;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1936181</tid>
<number>g</number>insurance of producers or their primary produce;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944452</tid>
<number>h</number>promoting techniques of mutuality and mutual assistance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>799997</tid>
<number>i</number>welfare measures or facilities for the benefit of Members as may 
be decided by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183634</tid>
<number>j</number>any other activity, ancillary or incidental to any of the 
activities referred to in clauses (a) to (i) or other activities which 
may promote the principles of mutuality and mutual assistance amongst 
the Members in any other manner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1086581</tid>
<number>k</number>financing of procurement, processing, marketing or other 
activities specified in clauses (a) to (j) which include extending of 
credit facilities or any other financial services to its Members.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>541254</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Producer Company shall deal primarily with the produce of 
its active Members for carrying out any of its objects specified in 
this section.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242647</tid>
<number> 581C</number> Formation of Producer Company and its registration.-
<section><tid>1490692</tid>
<number>1</number>Any ten  
or more individuals, each of them being a producer or any two or more 
Producer institutions, or a combination of ten or more individuals and 
Producer institutions, desirous of forming a Producer Company having 
its objects specified in section 581B and otherwise complying with the 
requirements of this Part and the provisions of this Act in respect of 
registration, may form an incorporated Company as a Producer Company 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1692166</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Registrar is satisfied that all the requirements of this 
Act have been complied with in respect of registration and matters 
precedent and incidental thereto, he shall, within thirty days of the 
memorandum, the articles and other documents, if any, and issue a 
certificate of incorporation under this Act. receipt of the documents 
required for registratio, register the

</section>

<section><tid>1772696</tid>
<number>3</number>A Producer Company so formed shall have the liability of its 
Members limited by the memorandum to the amount, if any, unpaid on the 
shares respectively held by them and be termed a company limited by 
shares.

</section>

<section><tid>352682</tid>
<number>4</number>The Producer Company may reimburse to its promoters all other 
direct costs associated with the promotion and registration of the 
company including registration, legal fees, printing of a memorandum 
and articles and the payment thereof shall be subje t to the approval 
at its first general meeting of the Members.

</section>

<section><tid>430971</tid>
<number>5</number>On registration under sub- section (1), the Producer Company shall 
become a body corporate as if it is a private limited company to which 
the provisions contained in this Part apply, without, however, any 
limit to the number of Members thereof, and t e Producer Company shall 
not, under any circumstance, whatsoever, become or be deemed to become 
a public limited company under this Act.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>208239</tid>
<number> 581D</number> Membership and voting rights of Members of Producer 
Company.-
<section><tid>1669821</tid>
<number>1</number> (a) In a case where the membership consists solely of  
individual members, the voting rights shall be based on a single vote 
for every Member, irrespective of his shareholding or patro age of the 
Producer Company.

<subsection><tid>558534</tid>
<number>b</number>In a case where the membership consists of Producer institutions 
only, the voting rights of such Producer institutions shall be 
determined on the basis of their participation in the business of the 
Producer Company in the previous year, as may be sp cified by 
articles:
Provided that during the first year of registration of a Producer 
Company, the voting rights shall be determined on the basis of the 
shareholding by such Producer institutions.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1185653</tid>
<number>c</number>In a case where the membership consists of individuals and 
Producer institutions, the voting rights shall be computed on the 
basis of a single vote for every Member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1776915</tid>
<number>2</number>The articles of any Producer Company may provide for the 
conditions, subject to which a Member may continue to retain his 
membership, and the manner in which voting rights shall be exercised 
by the Members.

</section>

<section><tid>1571173</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2), any Producer Company may, if so authorised by its 
articles, restrict the voting rights to active Members, in any special 
or general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>795764</tid>
<number>4</number>No person, who has any business interest which is in conflict with 
business of the Producer Company, shall become a Member of that 
Company.

</section>

<section><tid>894597</tid>
<number>5</number>A Member, who acquires any business interest which is in conflict 
with the business of the Producer Company, shall cease to be a Member 
of that Company and be removed as a Member in accordance with 
articles.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1572204</tid>
<number> 581E</number> Benefits to Members.-
<section><tid>1862875</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions made in  
articles, every Member shall initially receive only such value for the 
produce or products pooled and supplied as the Board of Producer 
Company may determine, and the withheld price may be disbursed later 
in cash or in kind or by allotment of equity shares, in proportion to 
the produce supplied to the Producer Company during the financial year 
to such extent and in such manner and subject to such conditions as 
may be decided by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1973504</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Member shall, on the share capital contributed, receive only 
a limited return:
Provided that every such Member may be allotted bonus shares in 
accordance with the provisions contained in section 581ZJ.


</section>

<section><tid>1710307</tid>
<number>3</number>The surplus if any, remaining after making provision for payment 
of limited return and reserves referred to in section 581ZI, may be 
disbursed as patronage bonus, amongst the Members, in proportion to 
their participation in the business of the Produc r Company, either in 
cash or by way of allotment of equity shares, or both, as may be 
decided by the Members at the general meeting.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>241512</tid>
<number> 581F</number> Memorandum of Producer Company.- The memorandum of association 
of every Producer Company shall state-
<section><tid>1580522</tid>
<number>a</number>the name of the company with" Producer Company Limited" as the 
last words of the name of such Company;

</section>

<section><tid>747628</tid>
<number>b</number>the State in which the registered office of the Producer Company 
is to situate;

</section>

<section><tid>1956114</tid>
<number>c</number>the main objects of the Producer Company shall be one or more of 
the objects specified in section 581B;

</section>

<section><tid>1924314</tid>
<number>d</number>the names and addresses of the persons who have subscribed to the 
memorandum;

</section>

<section><tid>656706</tid>
<number>e</number>the amount of share capital with which the Producer Company is to 
be registered and division thereof into shares of a fixed amount;

</section>

<section><tid>26518</tid>
<number>f</number>the names, addresses and occupations of the subscribers being 
producers, who shall act as the first directors in accordance with 
sub- section (2) of section 581J;

</section>

<section><tid>996841</tid>
<number>g</number>that the liability of its members is limited;

</section>

<section><tid>103563</tid>
<number>h</number>opposite to the subscriber' s name the number of shares each 
subscriber takes:
Provided that no subscriber shall take less than one share;


</section>

<section><tid>974078</tid>
<number>i</number>in case the objects of the Producer Company are not confined to 
one State, the States to whose territories the objects extend.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>689948</tid>
<number> 581G</number> Articles of association.-
<section><tid>984096</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be presented, for  
registration to the Registrar of the State to which the registered 
office of the Producer Company is, stated by the memorandum of 
association, to be situate-

<subsection><tid>1760881</tid>
<number>a</number>memorandum of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>528346</tid>
<number>b</number>its articles duly signed by the subscribers to the memorandum.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>446792</tid>
<number>2</number>The articles shall contain the following mutual assistance 
principles, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1299818</tid>
<number>a</number>the membership shall be voluntary and available, to all eligible 
persons who, can participate or avail of the facilities or services of 
the Producer Company, and are willing to accept the duties of 
membership;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>106199</tid>
<number>b</number>each Member shall, save as otherwise provided in this Part, have 
only a single vote irrespective of the share holding;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1624229</tid>
<number>c</number>the Producer Company shall be administered by a Board consisting 
of persons elected or appointed as directors in the manner consistent 
with the provisions of this Part and the Board shall be accountable to 
the Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>491670</tid>
<number>d</number>save as provided in this Part, there shall be limited return on 
share capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>689460</tid>
<number>e</number>the surplus arising out of the operations of the Producer Company 
shall be distributed in an equitable manner by-

<subsubsection><tid>910072</tid>
<number>i</number>providing for the development of the business of the Producer 
Company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>234566</tid>
<number>ii</number>providing for common facilities; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1818464</tid>
<number>iii</number>distributing amongst the Members, as may be admissible in 
proportion to their respective participation in the business;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>569133</tid>
<number>f</number>provision shall be made for the education of Members, employees 
and others, on the principles of mutuality and techniques of mutual 
assistance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21436</tid>
<number>g</number>the Producer Company shall actively co- operate with other Producer 
Companies (and other organisations following similar principles) at 
local, national or international level so as to best serve the 
interest of their Members and the communities it pur orts to serve.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>928206</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions of 
sub- sections (1) and (2), the articles shall contain the following 
provisions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1827841</tid>
<number>a</number>the qualifications for membership, the conditions for continuance 
or cancellation of membership and the terms, conditions and procedure 
for transfer of shares;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1067734</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner of ascertaining the patronage and voting right based on 
patronage;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1367509</tid>
<number>c</number>subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) of section 
581N, the manner of constitution of the Board, its powers and duties, 
the minimum and maximum number of directors, manner of election and 
appointment of directors and retirement by rot tion, qualifications 
for being elected or continuance as such and the terms of office of 
the said directors, their powers and duties, conditions for election 
or co- option of directors, method of removal of directors and the 
filling up of vacancies on the Board, and the manner and the terms of 
appointment of the Chief Executive;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>880007</tid>
<number>d</number>the election of the Chairman, term of office of directors and the 
Chairman, manner of voting at the general or special meetings of 
Members, procedure for voting, by directors at meetings of the Board, 
powers of the Chairman and the circumstances unde which the Chairman 
may exercise a casting vote.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>15595</tid>
<number>e</number>the circumstances under which, and the manner in which, the 
withheld price is to be determined and distributed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866267</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner of disbursement of patronage bonus in cash or by issue 
of equity shares, or both;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444606</tid>
<number>g</number>the contribution to be shared and related matters referred to in 
sub- section (2) of section 581ZI;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1782941</tid>
<number>h</number>the matters relating to issue of bonus shares out of general 
reserves as set out in section 581ZJ;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274875</tid>
<number>i</number>the basis and manner of allotment of equity shares of the Producer 
Company in lieu of the whole or part of the sale proceeds of produce 
or products supplied by the Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1140813</tid>
<number>j</number>the amount of reserves, sources from which funds may be raised, 
limitation on raising of funds, restriction on the use of such funds 
and the extent of debt that may be contracted and the conditions 
thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>529965</tid>
<number>k</number>the credit, loans or advances which may be granted to a Member and 
the conditions for the grant of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>862523</tid>
<number>l</number>the right of any Member to obtain information relating to general 
business of the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1898741</tid>
<number>m</number>the basis and manner of distribution and disposal of funds 
available after meeting liabilities in the event of dissolution or 
liquidation of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>818596</tid>
<number>n</number>the authorisation for division, amalgamation, merger, creation of 
subsidiaries and the entering into joint ventures and other matters 
connected therewith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911874</tid>
<number>o</number>laying of the memorandum and articles of the Producer Company 
before a special general meeting to be held within ninety days of its 
registration;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>803984</tid>
<number>p</number>any other provision, which the Members may, by special resolution 
recommend to be included in articles.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>466947</tid>
<number> 581H</number> Amendment of memorandum.-
<section><tid>895409</tid>
<number>1</number>A Producer Company shall not alter  
the conditions contained in its memorandum except in the cases, by the 
mode and to the extent for which express provision is made in this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>536062</tid>
<number>2</number>A Producer Company may, by special resolution, not inconsistent 
with section 581B, alter its objects specified in its memorandum.

</section>

<section><tid>1827650</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the amended memorandum, together with a copy of the 
special resolution duly certified by two directors, shall be filed 
with the Registrar within thirty days from the date of adoption of any 
resolution referred to in sub- section (2):
Provided that in the case of transfer of the registered office of a 
Producer Company from the jurisdiction of one Registrar to another, 
certified copies of the special resolution certified by two directors 
shall be filed with both the Registrars within t irty days, and each 
Registrar shall record the same, and thereupon the Registrar from 
whose jurisdiction the office is transferred, shall forthwith forward 
to the other Registrar all documents relating to the Producer Company.


</section>

<section><tid>449116</tid>
<number>4</number>The alteration of the provisions of memorandum relating to the 
change of the place of its registered office from one State to another 
shall not take effect unless it is confirmed by the Company Law Board 
on petition.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643033</tid>
<number> 581I</number> Amendment of articles.-
<section><tid>13137</tid>
<number>1</number>Any amendment of the articles shall  
be proposed by not less than two- third of the elected directors or by 
not less than one- third of the Members of the Producer Company, and 
adopted by the Members by a special resolution

</section>

<section><tid>140608</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the amended articles together with the copy of the 
special resolution, both duly certified by two directors, shall be 
filed with the Registrar within thirty days from the date of its 
adoption.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1517573</tid>
<number> 581J</number> Option to inter- State co- operative societies to become Producer 
Companies.-
<section><tid>1902959</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1)  
of section 581C, any inter- State co- operative society with objects not 
confined to one State may make an applicatio to the Registrar for 
registration as Producer Company under this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>854062</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall be accompanied by-

<subsection><tid>1256571</tid>
<number>a</number>a copy of the special resolution, of not less than two- third of 
total members of inter- State co- operative society, for its 
incorporation as a Producer Company under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>997071</tid>
<number>b</number>a statement showing-

<subsubsection><tid>343331</tid>
<number>i</number>names and addresses or the occupation of the directors and Chief 
Executive, if any, by whatever name called, of such co- operative; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>994562</tid>
<number>ii</number>list of members of such inter- State co- operative society;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>116173</tid>
<number>c</number>a statement indicating that the inter- State co- operative society 
is engaged in any one or more of the objects specified in section 
581B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>169095</tid>
<number>d</number>a declaration by two or more directors of the inter- State 
co- operative society certifying that particulars given in clauses (a) 
to (c) are correct.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>198142</tid>
<number>3</number>When an inter- State co- operative society is registered as a 
Producer Company, the words" Producer Company Limited" shall form part 
of its name with any word or expression to show its identity preceding 
it.

</section>

<section><tid>365458</tid>
<number>4</number>On compliance with the requirements of sub- sections (1) to (3), 
the Registrar shall, within a period of thirty days of the receipt of 
application, certify under his hand that the inter- State co- operative 
society applying for registration is registere and thereby 
incorporated as a Producer Company under this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>1200223</tid>
<number>5</number>A co- operative society formed by producers, by federation or union 
of co- operative societies of producers or co- operatives of producers, 
registered under any law for the time being in force which has 
extended its objects outside the State, either directly or through a 
union or federation of co- operatives of which it is a c nstituent, as 
the case may be, and any federation or union of such co- operatives, 
which has so extended any of its objects or activities outside the 
State, shall be eligible to make an application under sub- section (1) 
and to obtain registration as a Pro ucer Company under this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>725027</tid>
<number>6</number>The inter- State co- operative society shall, upon registration 
under sub- section (1), stand transformed into a Producer Company, and 
thereafter shall be governed by the provisions of this Part to the 
exclusion of the law by which it was earlier govern d, save in so far 
as anything done or omitted to be done before its registration as a 
Producer Company, and notwithstanding anything contained in any other 
law for the time being in force, no person shall have any claim 
against the co- operative instituti n or the company by reason of such 
conversion or transformation.

</section>

<section><tid>887700</tid>
<number>7</number>Upon registration as a Producer Company, the Registrar of 
Companies who registers the company shall forthwith intimate the 
Registrar with whom the erstwhile inter- State co- operative society was 
register. earlier registered for appropriate deletion of the socie y 
from its

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>761163</tid>
<number> 581K</number> Effect of incorporation of Producer Company.- Every shareholder 
of the inter- State co- operative society immediately before the date of 
registration of Producer Company (hereafter referred to as the  
  transformation date) shall be deemed to be register d on and from that 
date as a shareholder of the Producer Company to the extent of the 
face value of the shares held by such shareholder. 581L. Vesting of 
undertaking in Producer Company.-
<section><tid>684671</tid>
<number>1</number>All properties and assets,  
movable and immovable, of, or belonging to, the inter- State 
co- operative society as on the transformation date, shall vest in the 
Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1444819</tid>
<number>2</number>All the rights, debts, liabilities, interests, privileges and 
obligations of the inter- State co- operative society as on the 
transformation date shall stand transferred to, and be the rights, 
debts, liabilities, interests, privileges and obligations f, the 
Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>145379</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section (2), 
all debts, liabilities and obligations incurred, all contracts entered 
into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or for, 
the society as on the transformation date for or in connection with 
their purposes, shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into, 
or engaged to be done by, with or for, the Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>421842</tid>
<number>4</number>All sums of money due to the inter- State co- operative society 
immediately before the transformation date, shall be deemed to be due 
to the Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>86929</tid>
<number>5</number>Every organisation, which was being managed immediately before the 
transformation date by the inter- State co- operative society shall be 
managed by the Producer Company for such period, to such extent and in 
such manner as the circumstances may requir.

</section>

<section><tid>921096</tid>
<number>6</number>Every organisation which was getting financial, managerial or 
technical assistance from the inter- State co- operative society, 
immediately before the transformation date, may continue to be given 
financial, managerial or technical assistance, as the ase may be, by 
the Producer Company, for such period, to such extent and in such 
manner as that company may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>589039</tid>
<number>7</number>The amount representing the capital of the erstwhile inter- State 
co- operative society shall form part of the capital of the Producer 
Company.

</section>

<section><tid>938856</tid>
<number>8</number>Any reference to the inter- State co- operative society in any law 
other than this Act or in any contract or other instrument, shall be 
deemed to be reference to the Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1827384</tid>
<number>9</number>If, on the transformation date, there is pending any suit, 
arbitration, appeal or other legal proceeding of whatever nature by or 
against the inter- State co- operative society, the same shall not 
abate, be discontinued or be in any way prejudicially a fected by 
reason of the incorporation of the Producer Company under section 581C 
or transformation of the inter- State co- operative society as a 
Producer Company under section 581J, as the case may be, but the suit, 
arbitration, appeal or other proceeding may be continued, prosecuted 
and enforced by or against the Producer Company in the same manner and 
to the same extent as it would have, or may have been continued, 
prosecuted and enforced by or against the inter- State co- operative 
society as if the pro isions contained in this Part had not come into 
force.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1288840</tid>
<number>581M</number>Concession, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to Producer 
Company.- With effect from the transformation date, all fiscal and 
other concessions, licences, benefits, privileges and exemptions 
granted to the inter- State co- operative society in co nection with the 
affairs and business of the inter- State co- operative society under any 
law for the time being in force shall be deemed to have been granted 
to the Producer Company.
</article>



<article><tid>1255303</tid>
<number> 581N</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of 
inter- State co- operative society.-
<section><tid>996907</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in section 581-O, all the directors in the inter- State 
co- operative society before the incorporation of the Producer C mpany 
shall continue in office for a period of one year from the 
transformation date and in accordance with the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1586255</tid>
<number>2</number>Every officer or other employee of the inter- State co- operative 
society (except a director of the Board, Chairman or Managing  
  Director) serving in its employment immediately before the 
transformation date shall, in so far as such officer or other emp oyee 
is employed in connection with the inter- State co- operative society 
which has vested in the Producer Company by virtue of this Act, 
become, as from the transformation date, an officer or, as the case 
may be, other employee of the Producer Company an shall hold his 
office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same 
remuneration, upon the same terms and conditions, with the same 
obligations and with the same rights and privileges as to leave, leave 
travel concession, welfare scheme, medical be efit scheme, insurance, 
provident fund, other funds, retirement, voluntary retirement, 
gratuity and other benefits as he would have held under the erstwhile 
inter- State co- operative society if its undertaking had not vested in 
the Producer Company and sh ll continue to do so as an officer or, as 
the case may be, other employee of the Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1126043</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an officer or other employee of the inter- State co- operative 
society opts under sub- section (2) not to be in employment or service 
of the Producer Company, such officer or other employee shall be 
deemed to have resigned.

</section>

<section><tid>456225</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
transfer of the services of any officer or other employee of the 
inter- State co- operative society to the Produce Company shall not 
entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation under this 
Act or under any other law for the time being in force and no such 
claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>33016</tid>
<number>5</number>The officers and other employees who have retired before the 
transformation date from the service of the inter- State co- operative 
society and are entitled to any benefits, rights or privileges, shall 
be entitled to receive the same benefits, rights o privileges from the 
Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1503926</tid>
<number>6</number>The trusts of the provident fund or the gratuity fund of the 
inter- State co- operative society and any other bodies created for the 
welfare of officers or employees shall continue to discharge functions 
in the Producer Company as was being done hither o in the inter- State 
co- operative society and any tax exemption granted to the provident 
fund or the gratuity fund would continue to be applied to the Producer 
Company.

</section>

<section><tid>246057</tid>
<number>7</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law 
for the time being in force or in the regulations of the inter- State 
co- operative society, no director of the Board, Chairman, Managing 
Director or any other person entitled to manage the whole or 
substantial part of the business and affairs of the 
inter- Stateco- operative society shall be entitled to any compensation 
against the inter- Stateco- operative society or the Producer Company 
contract of management entered into by him with the inter- State 
co- operative society. for the loss of office or for the premature 
termin tion of any
CHAPTER III

MANAGEMENT OF PRODUCER COMPANY


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1716581</tid>
<number>581O</number>Number of directors.- Every Producer Company shall have at 
least five and not more than fifteen directors:
Provided that in the case of an inter- State co- operative society 
incorporated as a Producer Company, such company may have more than 
fifteen directors for a period of one year from the date of its 
incorporation as a Producer Company.

</article>



<article><tid>949249</tid>
<number> 581P</number> Appointment of directors.-
<section><tid>1933263</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as provided in section 581N,  
the Members who sign the memorandum and the articles may designate 
therein the Board of directors (not less than five) who shall govern 
the affairs of the Producer Company until the d rectors are elected in 
accordance with the provisions of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1163788</tid>
<number>2</number>The election of directors shall be conducted within a period of 
ninety days of the registration of the Producer Company:
Provided that in the case of an inter- State co- operative society which 
has been registered as a Producer Company under sub- section (4) of 
section 581J in which at least five directors[ including the directors 
continuing in office under sub- section (1) of section 581N] hold 
office as such on the date of registration of such company, the 
provisions of this sub- section shall have effect as if for the words 
" ninety days", the words" three hundred and sixty- five days" had been 
substituted.


</section>

<section><tid>621011</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person shall hold office of a director for a period not less 
than one year but not exceeding five years as may be specified in the 
articles.

</section>

<section><tid>1417098</tid>
<number>4</number>Every director, who retires in accordance with the articles, shall 
be eligible for re- appointment as a director.

</section>

<section><tid>1641405</tid>
<number>5</number>Save as provided in sub- section (2), the directors of the Board 
shall be elected or appointed by the Members in the annual general 
meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1873013</tid>
<number>6</number>The Board may co- opt one or more expert directors or an additional 
director not exceeding one- fifth of the total number of directors or 
appoint any other person as additional director for such period as the 
Board may deem fit:
Provided that the expert directors shall not have the right to vote in 
the election of the Chairman but shall be eligible to be elected as 
Chairman, if so provided by its articles:

Provided further that the maximum period, for which the expert 
director or the additional director holds office, shall not exceed 
such period as may be specified in the articles.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1122774</tid>
<number> 581Q</number> Vacation of office by directors.-
<section><tid>1185169</tid>
<number>1</number>The office of the director  
of a Producer Company shall become vacant if-

<subsection><tid>1612014</tid>
<number>a</number>he is convicted by a court of any offence involving moral 
turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment for not 
less than six months;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>713690</tid>
<number>b</number>the Producer Company, in which he is a director, has made a 
default in repayment of any advances or loans taken from any company 
or institution or any other person and such default continues for 
ninety days;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>330585</tid>
<number>c</number>he has made a default in repayment of any advances or loans taken 
from the Producer Company in which he is a director;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>686242</tid>
<number>d</number>the Producer Company, in which he is a director-

<subsubsection><tid>217234</tid>
<number>i</number>has not filed the annual accounts and annual return for any 
continuous three financial years commencing on or after the 1st day of 
April, <year>2002</year>; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1679638</tid>
<number>ii</number>has failed to, repay its deposit or withheld price or patronage 
bonus or interest thereon on due date, or pay dividend and such 
failure continues for one year or more;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1361138</tid>
<number>e</number>default is made in holding election for the office of director, in 
the Producer Company in which he is a director, in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act and articles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>141481</tid>
<number>f</number>the annual general meeting or extraordinary general meeting of the 
Producer Company, in which he is a director, is not called in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act except due to natural 
calamity or such other reason.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1071170</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall, as far as may be, apply 
to the director of a Producer institution which is a member of a 
Producer Company.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98233</tid>
<number> 581R</number> Powers and functions of Board.-
<section><tid>281355</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act and articles, the Board of directors of a Producer Company 
shall exercise all such powers and to do all such acts and things, as 
that company is authorised so to do.

</section>

<section><tid>1375519</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such powers may include all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>978300</tid>
<number>a</number>determination of the dividend payable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>617734</tid>
<number>b</number>determination of the quantum of withheld price and recommend 
patronage to be approved at general meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>732258</tid>
<number>c</number>admission of new Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1449036</tid>
<number>d</number>pursue and formulate the organisational policy, objectives, 
establish specific long- term and annual objectives, and approve 
corporate strategies and financial plans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>363767</tid>
<number>e</number>appointment of a Chief Executive and such other officers of the 
Producer Company, as may be specified in the articles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1251548</tid>
<number>f</number>exercise superintendence, direction and control over Chief 
Executive and other officers appointed by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1321998</tid>
<number>g</number>cause proper books of account to be maintained; prepare annual 
accounts to be placed before the annual general meeting with the 
auditor' s report and the replies on qualifications, if any, made by 
the auditors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330406</tid>
<number>h</number>acquisition or disposal of property of the Producer Company in its 
ordinary course of business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1714211</tid>
<number>i</number>investment of the funds of the Producer Company in the ordinary 
course of its business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1343874</tid>
<number>j</number>sanction any loan or advance, in connection with the business 
activities of the Producer Company to any Member, not being a director 
or his relative;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1410836</tid>
<number>k</number>take such other measures or do such other acts as may be required 
in the discharge of its functions or exercise of its powers.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1506577</tid>
<number>3</number>All the powers specified in sub- sections (1) and (2) shall be 
exercised by the Board, by means of resolution passed at its meeting 
on behalf of the Producer Company.
Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that a 
director or a group of directors, who do not constitute the Board, 
shall not exercise any of the powers exercisable by it.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>857357</tid>
<number> 581S</number> Matters to be transacted at general meeting.- The Board of 
directors of a Producer Company shall exercise the following powers on 
behalf of that company, and it shall do so only by means of 
resolutions passed at the annual general meeting of its Mem ers, 
namely:-
<section><tid>1821658</tid>
<number>a</number>approval of budget and adoption of annual accounts of the Producer 
Company;

</section>

<section><tid>1383694</tid>
<number>b</number>approval of patronage bonus;

</section>

<section><tid>619163</tid>
<number>c</number>issue of bonus shares;

</section>

<section><tid>949972</tid>
<number>d</number>declaration of limited return and decision on the distribution of 
patronage;

</section>

<section><tid>1473962</tid>
<number>e</number>specify the conditions and limits of loans that may be given by 
the Board to any director; and

</section>

<section><tid>581475</tid>
<number>f</number>approval of any transaction of the nature as is to be reserved in 
the articles for approval by the Members.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>781792</tid>
<number> 581T</number> Liability of directors.-
<section><tid>1101631</tid>
<number>1</number>When the directors vote for a  
resolution, or approve by any other means, anything done in 
contravention of the provisions of this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force or articles, they shall be jointly and s verally 
liable to make good any loss or damage suffered by the Producer 
Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1824946</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section (1), 
the Producer Company shall have the right to recover from its 
director-

<subsection><tid>1825996</tid>
<number>a</number>where such director has made any profit as a result of the 
contravention specified in sub- section (1), an amount equal to the 
profit so made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1092626</tid>
<number>b</number>where the Producer Company incurred a loss or damage as a result 
of the contravention specified in sub- section (1), an amount equal to 
that loss or damage;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1156057</tid>
<number>3</number>The liability imposed under this section shall be in addition to 
and not in derogation of a liability imposed on a director under this 
Act or any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1929298</tid>
<number> 581U</number> Committee of directors.-
<section><tid>112452</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may constitute such  
number of committees as it may deem fit for the purpose of assisting 
the Board in the efficient discharge of its functions:
Provided that the Board shall not delegate any of its powers or assign 
the powers of the Chief Executive, to any committee.


</section>

<section><tid>29395</tid>
<number>2</number>A committee constituted under sub- section (1) may, with the 
approval of the Board, co- opt such number of persons as it deems fit 
as members of the committee:
Provided that the Chief Executive appointed under section 581W or a 
director of the Producer Company shall be a member of such committee.


</section>

<section><tid>860185</tid>
<number>3</number>Every such committee shall function under the general 
superintendence, direction and control of the Board, for such 
duration, and in such manner as the Board may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>675148</tid>
<number>4</number>The fee and allowances to be paid to the members of the committee 
shall be such as may be determined by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1137440</tid>
<number>5</number>The minutes of each meeting of the committee shall be placed 
before the Board at its next meeting.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>361396</tid>
<number> 581V</number> Meetings of Board and quorum.-
<section><tid>1684018</tid>
<number>1</number>A meeting of the Board shall  
be held not less than once in every three months and at least four 
such meetings shall be held in every year.

</section>

<section><tid>505640</tid>
<number>2</number>Notice of every meeting of the Board of directors shall be given 
in writing to every director for the time being in India, and at his 
usual address in India to every other director.

</section>

<section><tid>1416680</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Executive shall give notice as aforesaid not less than 
seven days prior to the date of the meeting of the Board and if he 
fails to do so, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
one thousand rupees:
Provided that a meeting of the Board may be called at shorter notice 
and the reasons thereof shall be recorded in writing by the Board.


</section>

<section><tid>1910089</tid>
<number>4</number>The quorum for a meeting of the Board shall be one- third of the 
total strength of directors, subject to a minimum of three.

</section>

<section><tid>1336533</tid>
<number>5</number>Save as provided in the articles, directors including the co- opted 
director, may be paid such fees and allowances for attendance at the 
meetings of the Board, as may be decided by the Members in the general 
meeting.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>340282</tid>
<number> 581W</number> Chief Executive and his functions.-
<section><tid>274422</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Producer Company  
shall have a full time Chief Executive, by whatever name called, to be 
appointed by the Board from amongst persons other than Members.

</section>

<section><tid>1471299</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive shall be ex officio director of the Board and 
such director shall not retire by rotation.

</section>

<section><tid>1897606</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in articles, the qualifications, 
experience and the terms and conditions of service of the Chief 
Executive shall be such as may be determined by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>71449</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chief Executive shall be entrusted with substantial powers of 
management as the Board may determine.

</section>

<section><tid>6614</tid>
<number>5</number>Without prejudice to the generality of sub- section (4), the Chief 
Executive may exercise the powers and discharge the functions, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1951365</tid>
<number>a</number>do administrative acts of a routine nature including managing the 
day- to- day affairs of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>369666</tid>
<number>b</number>operate bank accounts or authorise any person, subject to the 
general or special approval of the Board in this behalf, to operate 
the bank account;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1039915</tid>
<number>c</number>make arrangements for safe custody of cash and other assets of the 
Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1674065</tid>
<number>d</number>sign such documents as may be authorised by the Board, for and on 
behalf of the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1196887</tid>
<number>e</number>maintain proper books of account; prepare annual accounts and 
audit thereof; place the audited accounts before the Board and in the 
annual general meeting of the Members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1346179</tid>
<number>f</number>furnish Members with periodic information to appraise them of the 
operation and functions of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1831386</tid>
<number>g</number>make appointments to posts in accordance with the powers delegated 
to him by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>448830</tid>
<number>h</number>assist the Board in the formulation of goals, objectives, 
strategies, plans and policies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>890956</tid>
<number>i</number>advise the Board with respect to legal and regulatory matters 
concerning the proposed and on going activities and take necessary 
action in respect thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1314247</tid>
<number>j</number>exercise the powers as may be necessary in the ordinary course of 
business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824437</tid>
<number>k</number>discharge such other functions, and exercise such other powers, as 
may be delegated by the Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1118618</tid>
<number>6</number>The Chief Executive shall manage the affairs of the Producer 
Company under the general superintendence, direction and control of 
the Board and be accountable for the performance of the Producer 
Company.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>539526</tid>
<number> 581X</number> Secretary of Producer Company.-
<section><tid>1125812</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Producer Company  
having an average annual turnover exceeding five crore rupees in each 
of three consecutive financial years shall have a whole- time 
secretary.

</section>

<section><tid>827156</tid>
<number>2</number>No individual shall be appointed as whole- time secretary unless he 
possesses membership of the Institute of Company Secretaries of India 
constituted under the Company Secretaries Act, <year>1980</year> (56 of <year>1980</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>651288</tid>
<number>3</number>If a Producer Company fails to comply with the provisions of 
sub- section (1), the company and every officer of the company who is 
in default, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees for every day during which the default continues:
Provided that in any proceedings against a person in respect of an 
offence under this sub- section, it shall be a defence to prove that 
all reasonable efforts to comply with the provisions of sub- section 
 (1) were taken or that the financial position of th company was such 
that it was beyond its capacity to engage a whole- time secretary.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1646813</tid>
<number>581Y</number>Quorum.- Unless the articles require a larger number, one- fourth 
of the total membership shall constitute the quorum at a general 
meeting.
</article>



<article><tid>1798765</tid>
<number> 581Z</number> Voting rights.- Save as otherwise provided in sub- sections
<section><tid>1282224</tid>
<number>1</number> 
and (3) of section 581D, every Member shall have one vote and in the 
case of equality of votes, the Chairman or the person presiding shall 
have a casting vote except in the case of elect on of the Chairman.
CHAPTER IV

GENERAL MEETINGS


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1674550</tid>
<number> 581ZA</number> Annual general meetings.-
<section><tid>961672</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Producer Company shall in  
each year, hold, in addition to any other meetings, a general meeting, 
as its annual general meeting and shall specify the meeting as such in 
the notices calling it, and not more than ifteen months shall elapse 
between the date of one annual general meeting of a Producer Company 
and that of the next: Provided that the Registrar may, for any 
special reason, permit extension of the time for holding any annual 
general meeting (not being the first annual general meeting) by a 
period not exceeding three months.

</section>

<section><tid>377458</tid>
<number>2</number>A Producer Company shall hold its first annual general meeting 
within a period of ninety days from the date of its incorporation.

</section>

<section><tid>301957</tid>
<number>3</number>The Members shall adopt the articles of the Producer Company and 
appoint directors of its Board in the annual general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1985569</tid>
<number>4</number>The notice calling the annual general meeting shall be accompanied 
by the following documents, namely:-

<subsection><tid>384391</tid>
<number>a</number>the agenda of the annual general meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>822229</tid>
<number>b</number>the minutes of the previous annual general meeting or the 
extra- ordinary general meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>289606</tid>
<number>c</number>the names of candidates for election, if any, to the office of 
director including a statement of qualifications in respect of each 
candidate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747689</tid>
<number>d</number>the audited balance- sheet and profit and loss accounts of the 
Producer Company and its subsidiary, if any, together with a report of 
the Board of Directors of such Company with respect to-

<subsubsection><tid>1382385</tid>
<number>i</number>the state of affairs of the Producer Company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1009693</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount proposed to be carried to reserve;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>520671</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount to be paid as limited return on share capital;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1748352</tid>
<number>iv</number>the amount proposed to be disbursed as patronage bonus;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>41541</tid>
<number>v</number>the material changes and commitments, if any, affecting the 
financial position of the Producer Company and its subsidiary, which 
have occurred in between the date of the annual accounts of the 
Producer Company to which the balance- sheet relates and he date of the 
report of the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>446765</tid>
<number>vi</number>any other matter of importance relating to energy conservation, 
environmental protection, expenditure or earnings in foreign 
exchanges;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>902500</tid>
<number>vii</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, specified 
by the Board;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1771387</tid>
<number>e</number>the text of the draft resolution for appointment of auditors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>386007</tid>
<number>f</number>the text of any draft resolution proposing amendment to the 
memorandum or articles to be considered at the general meeting, along 
with the recommendations of the Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>19111</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board of Directors shall, on the requisition made in writing, 
duly signed and setting out the matters for the consideration, made by 
one- third of the Members entitled to vote in any general meeting, 
proceed to call an extraordinary general meetin in accordance with the 
provisions contained in sections 169 to 186 of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>322669</tid>
<number>6</number>Every annual general meeting shall be called, for a time during 
business hours, on a day that is not a public holiday and shall be 
held at the registered office of the Producer Company or at some other 
place within the city, town or village in whic the registered office 
of the Company is situate.

</section>

<section><tid>1312706</tid>
<number>7</number>A general meeting of the Producer Company shall be called by 
giving not less than fourteen days prior notice in writing.

</section>

<section><tid>1252274</tid>
<number>8</number>The notice of the general meeting indicating the date, time and 
place of the meeting shall be sent to every Member and auditor of the 
Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>130638</tid>
<number>9</number>Unless the articles of the Producer Company provide for a larger 
number, one- fourth of the total number of members of the Producer 
Company shall be the quorum for its annual general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>702623</tid>
<number>10</number>The proceedings of every annual general meeting along with the 
Directors' Report, the audited balance- sheet and the profit and loss 
account shall be filed with the Registrar within sixty days of the 
date on which the annual general meeting is held, with an annual 
return along with the filing fees as applicable under the Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1240113</tid>
<number>11</number>In the case where a Producer Company is formed by Producer 
institutions, such institutions shall be represented in the general 
body through the Chairman or the Chief Executive thereof who shall be 
competent to act on its behalf: Provided that a Producer institution 
shall not be represented if such institution makes a default or 
failure referred to in clauses (d) to (f) of sub- section (1) of 
section 581Q.
CHAPTER V

SHARE CAPITAL AND MEMBERS RIGHTS


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1390552</tid>
<number> 581ZB</number> Share capital.-
<section><tid>626168</tid>
<number>1</number>The share capital of a Producer Company  
shall consist of equity shares only.

</section>

<section><tid>765519</tid>
<number>2</number>The shares held by a Member in a Producer Company, shall as far as 
may be, be in proportion to the patronage of that company.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>337369</tid>
<number> 581ZC</number> Special user rights.-
<section><tid>457654</tid>
<number>1</number>The producers, who are active Members  
may, if so provided in the articles, have special rights and the 
Producer Company may issue appropriate instruments to them in respect 
of such special rights.

</section>

<section><tid>1686750</tid>
<number>2</number>The instruments of the Producer Company issued under sub- section 
 (1) shall, after obtaining approval of the Board in that behalf, be 
transferable to any other active Member of that Producer Company.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expression" special 
right" means any right relating to supply of additional produce by the 
active Member or any other right relating to his produce which may be 
conferred upon him by the Board.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>848458</tid>
<number> 581ZD</number> Transferability of shares and attendant rights.-
<section><tid>738655</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise provided in sub- sections (2) to (4), the shares of a Member 
of a Producer Company shall not be transferable.

</section>

<section><tid>1289887</tid>
<number>2</number>A Member of a Producer Company may, after obtaining the previous 
approval of the Board, transfer the whole or part of his shares along 
with any special rights, to an active Member at par value.

</section>

<section><tid>895149</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Member shall, within three months of his becoming a Member 
in the Producer Company, nominate, in the manner specified in 
articles, a person to whom his shares in the Producer Company shall 
vest in the event of his death.

</section>

<section><tid>1298291</tid>
<number>4</number>The nominee shall, on the death of the Member, become entitled to 
all the rights in the shares of the Producer Company and the Board of 
that Company shall transfer the shares of the deceased Member to his 
nominee:
Provided that in a case where such nominee is not a producer, the 
Board shall direct the surrender of shares together with special 
rights, if any, to the Producer Company at par value or such other 
value as may be determined by the Board.


</section>

<section><tid>710055</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Board of a Producer Company is satisfied that-

<subsection><tid>1075406</tid>
<number>a</number>any Member has ceased to be a primary producer; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1051085</tid>
<number>b</number>any Member has failed to retain his qualifications to be a Member 
as specified in articles,
the Board shall direct the surrender of shares together with special 
rights, if any, to the Producer Company at par value or such other 
value as may be determined by the Board:

Provided that the Board shall not direct such surrender of shares 
unless the Member has been served with a written notice and given an 
opportunity of being heard.

CHAPTER VI

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1925555</tid>
<number> 581ZE</number> Books of account.-
<section><tid>198600</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Producer Company shall keep at its  
registered office proper books of account with respect to-

<subsection><tid>1954316</tid>
<number>a</number>all sums of money received and expended by the Producer Company 
and the matters in respect of which the receipts and expenditure take 
place;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1553347</tid>
<number>b</number>all sales and purchase of goods by the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>609549</tid>
<number>c</number>the instruments of liability executed by or on behalf of the 
Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1333971</tid>
<number>d</number>the assets and liabilities of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1923874</tid>
<number>e</number>in case of a Producer Company engaged in production, processing 
and manufacturing, the particulars relating to utilisation of 
materials or labour or other items of costs.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1292088</tid>
<number>2</number>The balance- sheet and profit and loss account of the Producer 
Company shall be prepared, as far as may be, in accordance with the 
provisions contained in section 211.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>518360</tid>
<number> 581ZF</number> Internal audit.- Every Producer Company shall have internal 
audit of its accounts carried out, at such interval and in such manner 
as may be specified in articles, by a chartered accountant as defined 
in clause (b) of sub- section
<section><tid>811674</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 2 f the Institute of  
Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>897795</tid>
<number> 581ZG</number> Duties of auditor under this Part.- Without prejudice to the 
provisions contained in section 227, the auditor shall report on the 
following additional matters relating to the Producer Company, 
namely:-
<section><tid>637581</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of debts due along with particulars of bad debts if 
any;

</section>

<section><tid>1633538</tid>
<number>b</number>the verification of cash balance and securities;

</section>

<section><tid>654334</tid>
<number>c</number>the details of assets and liabilities;

</section>

<section><tid>4623</tid>
<number>d</number>all transactions which appear to be contrary to the provisions of 
this Part;

</section>

<section><tid>1488454</tid>
<number>e</number>the loans given by the Producer Company to the directors;

</section>

<section><tid>549603</tid>
<number>f</number>the donations or subscriptions given by the Producer Company;

</section>

<section><tid>356929</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter as may be considered necessary by the auditor.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>119580</tid>
<number> 581ZH</number> Donations or subscription by Producer Company.- A Producer 
Company may, by special resolution, make donation or subscription to 
any institution or individual for the purposes of-
<section><tid>1292800</tid>
<number>a</number>promoting the social and economic welfare of Producer Members or 
producers or general public; or

</section>

<section><tid>1137078</tid>
<number>b</number>promoting the mutual assistance principles:
Provided that the aggregate amount of all such donation and 
subscription in any financial year shall not exceed three per cent. 
of the net profit of the Producer Company in the financial year 
immediately preceding the financial year in which the donatio or 
subscription was made:

Provided further that no Producer Company shall make directly or 
indirectly to any political party or for any political purpose to any 
person any contribution or subscription or make available any 
facilities including personnel or material.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1576814</tid>
<number> 581ZI</number> General and other reserves.-
<section><tid>1907505</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Producer Company shall  
maintain a general reserve in every financial year, in addition to any 
reserve maintained by it as may be specified in articles.

</section>

<section><tid>914806</tid>
<number>2</number>In a case where the Producer Company does not have sufficient 
funds in any financial year for transfer to maintain the reserves as 
may be specified in articles, the contribution to the reserve shall be 
shared amongst the Members in proportion to thei patronage in the 
business of that company in that year.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1202333</tid>
<number>581ZJ</number>Issue of bonus shares.- Any Producer Company may, upon 
recommendation of the Board and passing of resolution in the general 
meeting, issue bonus shares by capitalisation of amounts from general 
reserves referred to in section 581ZI in proportion to the shares held 
by the Members on the date of the issue of such shares.
CHAPTER VII

LOANS TO MEMBERS AND INVESTMENTS

</article>



<article><tid>1517505</tid>
<number> 581ZK</number> Loan, etc., to Members.- The Board may, subject to the 
provisions made in articles, provide financial assistance to the 
Members of the Producer Company by way of-
<section><tid>1367202</tid>
<number>a</number>credit facility, to any Member, in connection with the business of 
the Producer Company, for a period not exceeding six months;

</section>

<section><tid>1510910</tid>
<number>b</number>loans and advances, against security specified in articles to any 
Member, repayable within a period exceeding three months but not 
exceeding seven years from the date of disbursement of such loan or 
advances:
Provided that any loan or advance to any director or his relative 
shall be granted only after the approval by the Members in general 
meeting.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>652395</tid>
<number> 581ZL</number> Investment in other companies, formation of subsidiaries, 
etc.-
<section><tid>1060884</tid>
<number>1</number>The general reserves of any Producer Company shall be  
invested to secure the highest returns available from approved 
securities, fixed deposits, units, bonds issued by the Governm nt or 
co- operative or scheduled bank or in such other mode as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1825210</tid>
<number>2</number>Any Producer Company may, for promotion of its objectives acquire 
the shares of another Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>235467</tid>
<number>3</number>Any Producer Company may subscribe to the share capital of, or 
enter into any agreement or other arrangement, whether by way of 
formation of its subsidiary company, joint venture or in any other 
manner with any body corporate, for the purpose of prom ting the 
objects of the Producer Company by special resolution in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>588573</tid>
<number>4</number>Any Producer Company, either by itself or together with its 
subsidiaries, may invest, by way of subscription, purchase or 
otherwise, shares in any other company, other than a Producer Company, 
specified under sub- section (2), or subscription of capit l under 
sub- section (3), for an amount not exceeding thirty per cent. of the 
aggregate of its paid- up capital and free reserves: Provided that a 
Producer Company may, by special resolution passed in its general 
meeting and with prior approval of the Central Government, invest in 
excess of the limits specified in this section.

</section>

<section><tid>433784</tid>
<number>5</number>All investments by a Producer Company may be made if such 
investments are consistent with the objects of the Producer Company.

</section>

<section><tid>928974</tid>
<number>6</number>The Board of a Producer Company may, with the previous approval of 
Members by a special resolution, dispose of any of its investments 
referred to in sub- sections (3) and (4).

</section>

<section><tid>1473278</tid>
<number>7</number>Every Producer Company shall maintain a register containing 
particulars of all the investments, showing the names of the companies 
in which shares have been acquired, number and value of shares; the 
date of acquisition; and the manner and price at wh ch any of the 
shares have been subsequently disposed of.

</section>

<section><tid>1636064</tid>
<number>8</number>The register referred to in sub- section (7) shall be kept at the 
registered office of the Producer Company and the same shall be open 
to inspection by any Member who may take extracts therefrom.
CHAPTER VIII

PENALTIES


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1725953</tid>
<number> 581ZM</number> Penalty for contravention.-
<section><tid>1709483</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person, other than a  
Producer Company registered under this Part, carries on business under 
any name which contains the words" Producer Company Limited", he shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to t n thousand rupees for 
every day during which such name has been used by him.

</section>

<section><tid>1009744</tid>
<number>2</number>If a director or an officer of a Producer Company, who wilfully 
fails to furnish any information relating to the affairs of the 
Producer Company required by a Member or a person duly authorised in 
this behalf, he shall be liable to imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to six months and with fine equivalent to five per cent. of 
the turnover of that company during preceding financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>330681</tid>
<number>3</number>If a director or officer of a Producer Company-

<subsection><tid>191445</tid>
<number>a</number>makes a default in handing over the custody of books of account 
and other documents or property in his custody to the Producer Company 
of which he is a director or officer; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>217595</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to convene annual general meeting or other general meetings, 
he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, 
and in the case of a continuing default or failure, with an additional 
fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees for every day during 
which such default or failure continues.
CHAPTER IX

AMALGAMATION, MERGER OR DIVISION


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>391718</tid>
<number> 581ZN</number> Amalgamation, merger or division, etc., to form new Producer 
Companies.-
<section><tid>1591356</tid>
<number>1</number>A Producer Company may, by a resolution passed at its  
general meeting,-

<subsection><tid>1262100</tid>
<number>a</number>decide to transfer its assets and liabilities, in whole or in 
part, to any other Producer Company, which agrees to such transfer by 
a resolution passed at its general meeting, for any of the objects 
specified in section 581B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>54949</tid>
<number>b</number>divide itself into two or more new Producer Companies.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1339250</tid>
<number>2</number>Any two or more Producer Companies may, by a resolution passed at 
any general or special meetings of its Members, decide to-

<subsection><tid>1670866</tid>
<number>a</number>amalgamate and form a new Producer Company; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488160</tid>
<number>b</number>merge one Producer Company (hereafter referred to as" merging  
  company") with another Producer Company (hereafter referred to as  
 " merged company").

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>309555</tid>
<number>3</number>Every resolution of a Producer Company under this section shall be 
passed at its general meeting by a majority of total Members, with 
right of vote not less than two- thirds of its Members present and 
voting and such resolution shall contain all parti ulars of the 
transfer of assets and liabilities, or division, amalgamation, or 
merger, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>473585</tid>
<number>4</number>Before passing a resolution under this section, the Producer 
Company shall give notice thereof in writing together with a copy of 
the proposed resolution to all the Members and creditors who may give 
their consent.

</section>

<section><tid>244190</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in articles or in any contract 
to the contrary, any Member, or any creditor not consenting to the 
resolution shall, during the period of one month of the date of 
service of the notice on him, have the option,-

<subsection><tid>337054</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any such Member, to transfer his shares with the 
approval of the Board to any active Member thereby ceasing to continue 
as a Member of that company; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>894028</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a creditor, to withdraw his deposit or loan or 
advance, as the case may be.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1523526</tid>
<number>6</number>Any Member or creditor, who does not exercise his option within 
the period specified in sub- section (5), shall be deemed to have 
consented to the resolution.

</section>

<section><tid>1346632</tid>
<number>7</number>A resolution passed by a Producer Company under this section shall 
not take effect until the expiry of one month or until the assent 
thereto of all the Members and creditors has been obtained, whichever 
is earlier.

</section>

<section><tid>1300559</tid>
<number>8</number>The resolution referred to in this section shall provide for-

<subsection><tid>645990</tid>
<number>a</number>the regulation of conduct of the Producer Company' s affairs in the 
future;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1715118</tid>
<number>b</number>the purchase of shares or interest of any Members of the Producer 
Company by other Members or by the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1208329</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of purchase of shares of one Producer Company by 
another Producer Company, the consequent reduction of its share 
capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>56378</tid>
<number>d</number>termination, setting aside or modification of any agreement, 
howsoever arrived between the company on the one hand and the 
directors, secretaries and managers on the other hand, apart from such 
terms and conditions as may, in the opinion of the major ty of 
shareholders, be just and equitable in the circumstances of the case;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1283627</tid>
<number>e</number>termination, setting aside or modification of any agreement 
between the Producer Company and any person not referred to in clause 
 (d): Provided that no such agreement shall be terminated, set aside 
or modified except after giving due notice to the party concerned:
Provided further that no such agreement shall be modified except after 
obtaining the consent of the party concerned;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1170266</tid>
<number>f</number>the setting aside of any transfer, delivery of goods, payment, 
execution or other act relating to property, made or done by or 
against the Producer Company within three months before the date of 
passing of the resolution, which would if made or done gainst any 
individual, be deemed in his insolvency to be a fraudulent preference;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1635610</tid>
<number>g</number>the transfer to the merged company of the whole or any part of the 
undertaking, property or liability of the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1796812</tid>
<number>h</number>the allotment or appropriation by the merged company of any 
shares, debentures, policies, or other like interests in the merged 
company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859962</tid>
<number>i</number>the continuation by or against the merged company of any legal 
proceedings pending by or against any Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>356643</tid>
<number>j</number>the dissolution, without winding- up, of any Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>614043</tid>
<number>k</number>the provision to be made for the Members or creditors who make 
dissent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>990221</tid>
<number>l</number>the taxes if any, to be paid by the Producer Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>602509</tid>
<number>m</number>such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as are 
necessary to secure that the division, amalgamation or merger shall be 
fully and effectively carried out.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>747272</tid>
<number>9</number>When a resolution passed by a Producer Company under this section 
takes effect, the resolution shall be a sufficient conveyance to vest 
the assets and liabilities in the transferee.

</section>

<section><tid>1323819</tid>
<number>10</number>The Producer Company shall make arrangements for meeting in full 
or otherwise satisfying all claims of the Members and the creditors 
who exercise the option, within the period specified in sub- section 
 (5), not to continue as the Member or creditor, s the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>263499</tid>
<number>11</number>Where the whole of the assets and liabilities of a Producer 
Company are transferred to another Producer Company in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- section (9), or where there is merger under 
sub- section (2), the registration of the first menti ned Company or 
the merging company, as the case may be, shall stand cancelled and 
that Company shall be deemed to have been dissolved and shall cease to 
exist forthwith as a corporate body.

</section>

<section><tid>1066819</tid>
<number>12</number>Where two or more Producer Companies are amalgamated into a new 
Producer Company in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (2) 
and the Producer Company so formed is duly registered by the 
Registrar, the registration of each of the amalgamatin companies shall 
stand cancelled forthwith on such registration and each of the 
Companies shall thereupon cease to exist as a corporate body.

</section>

<section><tid>412728</tid>
<number>13</number>Where a Producer Company divides itself into two or more Producer 
Companies in accordance with the provisions of clause (b) of 
sub- section (1) and the new Producer Companies are registered in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (8), the re istration of 
the erstwhile Producer Company shall stand cancelled forthwith and 
that Company shall be deemed to have been dissolved and cease to exist 
as a corporate body.

</section>

<section><tid>193215</tid>
<number>14</number>The amalgamation, merger or division of companies under the 
foregoing sub- sections shall not in any manner whatsoever affect the 
pre- existing rights or obligations and any legal proceedings that 
might have been continued or commenced by or against a y erstwhile 
company before the amalgamation, merger or division, may be continued 
or commenced by, or against, the concerned resulting company, or 
merged company, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1913137</tid>
<number>15</number>The Registrar shall strike off the names of every Producer 
Company deemed to have been dissolved under sub- sections (11) to (14).

</section>

<section><tid>112204</tid>
<number>16</number>Any member or creditor or employee aggrieved by the transfer of 
assets, division, amalgamation or merger may, within thirty days of 
the passing of the resolution, prefer an appeal to the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>8172</tid>
<number>17</number>The High Court shall, after giving a reasonable opportunity to 
the person concerned, pass such orders thereon as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1063633</tid>
<number>18</number>Where an appeal has been filed under sub- section (16), the 
transfer of assets, division, amalgamation or merger of the Producer 
Company shall be subject to the decision of the High Court.
CHAPTER X

RESOLUTION OF DISPUTES


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1351137</tid>
<number> 581ZO</number> Disputes.-
<section><tid>956988</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any dispute relating to the formation,  
management or business of a Producer Company arises-

<subsection><tid>1933548</tid>
<number>a</number>amongst Members, former Members or persons claiming to be Members 
or nominees of deceased Members; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>377664</tid>
<number>b</number>between a Member, former Member or a person claiming to be a 
Member, or nominee of deceased Member and the Producer Company, its 
Board of directors, office- bearers, or liquidator, past or present; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743795</tid>
<number>c</number>between the Producer Company or its Board, and any director, 
office- bearer or any former director, or the nominee, heir or legal 
representative of any deceased director of the Producer Company,
such dispute shall be settled by conciliation or by arbitration as 
provided under the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, <year>1996</year> (26 of <year>1996</year>) 
as if the parties to the dispute have consented in writing for 
the provisions of the said Act shall apply accordingly. determination 
of such disputes by conciliation or by arbitration and

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, a dispute shall 
include-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1933548</tid>
<number>a</number>a claim for any debt or other amount due;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>377664</tid>
<number>b</number>a claim by surety against the principal debtor, where the Producer 
Company has recovered from the surety amount in respect of any debtor 
or other amount due to it from the principal debtor as a result of the 
default of the principal debtor whether su h debt or amount due be 
admitted or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743795</tid>
<number>c</number>a claim by Producer Company against a Member for failure to supply 
produce as required of him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871815</tid>
<number>d</number>a claim by a Member against the Producer Company for not taking 
goods supplied by him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>4446</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether the dispute relates to formation, 
management or business of the Producer Company, the question shall be 
referred to the arbitrator, whose decision thereon shall be final.
CHAPTER XI

MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>270936</tid>
<number> 581ZP</number> Strike off name of Producer Company.-
<section><tid>1320837</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a Producer  
Company fails to commence business within one year of its registration 
or ceases to transact business with the Members or if the Registrar is 
satisfied, after making such inquiry as he thin s fit, that the 
Producer Company is no longer carrying on any of its objects specified 
in section 581B, he shall make an order striking off the name of the 
Producer Company, which shall thereupon cease to exist forthwith:
Provided that no such order cancelling the registration as aforesaid 
shall be passed until a notice to show cause has been given by the 
Registrar to the Producer Company with a copy to all its directors on 
the proposed action and reasonable opportunity t represent its case 
has been given.


</section>

<section><tid>146681</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Registrar has reasonable cause to believe that a 
Producer Company is not maintaining any of the mutual assistance 
principles specified, he shall strike its name off the register in 
accordance with the provisions contained in section 560 of his Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1277998</tid>
<number>3</number>Any Member of a Producer Company, who is aggrieved by an order 
made under sub- section (1), may appeal to the Company Law Board within 
sixty days of the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1447948</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an appeal is filed under sub- section (3), the order striking 
off the name shall not take effect until the appeal is disposed of.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>206526</tid>
<number>581ZQ</number>Provisions of this Part to override other laws.- The provisions 
of this Part shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent 
therewith contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force or any instrument having effect by vir ue of any such law; but 
the provisions of any such Act or law or instrument in so far as the 
same are not varied by, or are inconsistent with, the provisions of 
this Part shall apply to the Producer Company.
</article>



<article><tid>1865868</tid>
<number>581ZR</number>Application of provisions relating to private companies.- All 
the limitations, restrictions and provisions of this Act, other than 
those specified in this Part, applicable to a private company, shall, 
as far as may be, apply to a Producer Company, as if it is a private 
limited company under this Act in so far as they are not in conflict 
with the provisions of this Part.
CHAPTER XII

RECONVERSION OF PRODUCER COMPANY TO INTER- STATE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETY

</article>



<article><tid>370273</tid>
<number> 581ZS</number> Reconversion of Producer Company to inter- State co- operative 
society.-
<section><tid>1157978</tid>
<number>1</number>Any Producer Company, being an erstwhile inter- State  
co- operative society, formed and registered under this Part, may make 
an application-

<subsection><tid>44085</tid>
<number>a</number>after passing a resolution in the general meeting by not less than 
two- third of its Members present and voting; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1306135</tid>
<number>b</number>on request by its creditors representing three- fourth value of its 
total creditors,
to the High Court for its re- conversion to the inter- State 
co- operative society.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>261741</tid>
<number>2</number>The High Court shall, on the application made under sub- section 
 (1), direct holding meeting of its Members or such creditors, as the 
case may be, to be conducted in such manner as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1315637</tid>
<number>3</number>If a majority in number representing three- fourths in value of the 
creditors, or Members, as the case may be, present and voting in 
person at the meeting conducted in pursuance of the directions of the 
High Court under sub- section (2), agree for re- c nversion, if 
sanctioned by the High Court, be binding on all the Members and all 
the creditors, as the case may be, and also on the company which is 
being converted:
Provided that no order sanctioning re- conversion shall be made by the 
Court unless the Court is satisfied that the company or any other 
person by whom an application has been made under sub- section (1) has 
disclosed to the Court, by affidavit or otherwis, all material facts 
relating to the company, such as the latest financial position of the 
company, the latest auditor' s report on the accounts of the company, 
the pendency of any investigation proceedings in relation to the 
company under sections 235 to 251, and the like.


</section>

<section><tid>873244</tid>
<number>4</number>An order made by the Court under sub- section (3) shall have no 
effect until a certified copy of the order has been filed with the 
Registrar.

</section>

<section><tid>1107161</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of every such order shall be annexed to every copy of the 
memorandum of the company issued after the certified copy of the order 
has been filed as aforesaid, or in the case of a company not having a 
memorandum, to every copy so issued of the i strument constituting or 
defining the constitution of the company.

</section>

<section><tid>1524309</tid>
<number>6</number>If default is made in complying with sub- section (4), the company, 
and every officer of the company who is in default, shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, for each 
copy in respect of which default is made.

</section>

<section><tid>1261435</tid>
<number>7</number>The Court may, at any time after an application has been made to 
it under this section, stay the commencement or continuation of any 
suit or proceeding against the company on such terms as the Court 
thinks fit, until the application is finally dispos d of.

</section>

<section><tid>869199</tid>
<number>8</number>Every Producer Company which has been sanctioned re- conversion by 
the High Court, shall make an application, under the Multi- State 
Co- operative Societies Act, <year>2002</year> (39 of <year>2002</year>) or any other law for the 
time being in force for its registration as mult- State co- operative 
society or co- operative society, as the case may be, within six months 
of sanction by the High Court and file a report thereof to the High 
Court and the Registrar of companies and to the Registrar of the 
co- operative societies under w ich it has been registered as a 
multi- State co- operative society or co- operative society, as the case 
may be.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1093371</tid>
<number> 581ZT</number> Power to modify Act in its application to Producer 
Companies.-
<section><tid>1428629</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the  
Official Gazette, direct that any of the provisions of this Act (other  
  than those contained in this Part) specified in the said no ification-

<subsection><tid>33101</tid>
<number>a</number>shall not apply to the Producer Companies or any class or category 
thereof; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142612</tid>
<number>b</number>shall apply to the Producer Companies or any class or category 
thereof with such exception or adaptation as may be specified in the 
notification.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>192972</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under 
sub- section (1), shall be laid in draft before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more succes ive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the notification or both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the notifica ion, the 
notification shall not be issued or, as the case may be, shall be 
issued only in such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the 
Houses.'.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>