<act><title>


    THE TRANSFER OF PROPERTY ACT, 1882</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Transfer of Property Act, 1882.
 <section>

<number>Commencement</number>—It 
    shall come into force on the first day of July, 1882.
 </section><section>


    <number>Extent</number>—1[It 
    extends2 in 
    the first instance to the whole of India except 

    3[the 
    territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised 
    in Part B States or in the States of] Bombay, Punjab and Delhi.]
 


    4[But 
    this Act or any part thereof may by notification in the Official Gazette be 
    extended to the whole or any part of the 

    5[said 
    territories] by the 

    6[State 
    Government] concerned.]
 


    7[And 
    any 

    6[State 
    Government] may 

    8[***] 
    from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt, either 
    retrospectively or prospectively, any part of the territories administered 
    by such State Government from all or any of the following provisions, 
    namely:—
 

Section 54, paragraph 
    2 and sections 3, 59, 107 and 123.]
 


    9[Notwithstanding 
    anything in the foregoing part of this section, section 54, paragraphs 2 and 
    3, and sections 59, 107 and 123 shall not extend or be extended to any 
    district or tract of country for the time being excluded from the operation 
    of the Indian Registration Act, 

    10[1908], 
    (16 of 1908), under the power conferred by the first section of that Act or 
    otherwise.]
 

 



















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>2</number> Repeal of Acts.—Saving 
    of certain enactments, incidents, rights, liabilities, etc.—In the 
    territories to which this Act extends for the time being the enactments 
    specified in the Schedule hereto annexed shall be repealed to the extent 
    therein mentioned.  But nothing herein contained shall be deemed to affect—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    the provisions of any enactment not hereby expressly repealed;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     
    any terms or incidents of any contract or constitution of property which are 
    consistent with the provisions of this Act, and are allowed by the law for 
    the time being in force;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     
    any right or liability arising out of a legal relation constituted before 
    this Act comes into force, or any relief in respect of any such right or 
    liability; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     
    save as provided by section 57 and Chapter IV of this Act, any transfer by 
    operation of law or by, or in execution of, a decree or order of a Court of 
    competent jurisdiction,
 

and nothing  in  the  second Chapter of this Act shall be 
    deemed to affect any rule of 

    1[***] Muhammadan 

    2[***] law.
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>2</number> Repeal of Acts.—Saving 
    of certain enactments, incidents, rights, liabilities, etc.—In the 
    territories to which this Act extends for the time being the enactments 
    specified in the Schedule hereto annexed shall be repealed to the extent 
    therein mentioned.  But nothing herein contained shall be deemed to affect—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    the provisions of any enactment not hereby expressly repealed;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     
    any terms or incidents of any contract or constitution of property which are 
    consistent with the provisions of this Act, and are allowed by the law for 
    the time being in force;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     
    any right or liability arising out of a legal relation constituted before 
    this Act comes into force, or any relief in respect of any such right or 
    liability; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     
    save as provided by section 57 and Chapter IV of this Act, any transfer by 
    operation of law or by, or in execution of, a decree or order of a Court of 
    competent jurisdiction,
 

and nothing  in  the  second Chapter of this Act shall be 
    deemed to affect any rule of 

    1[***] Muhammadan 

    2[***] law.
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>3</number> Interpretation 
    clause.—In 
    this Act, unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context,—
 

    
    “immoveable property” does not include standing timber, growing crops or 
    grass;
 

    
    ‘‘instrument” means a non-testamentary instrument;
 

    
    1[“attested”, 
    in relation to an instrument, means and shall be deemed always to have meant 
    attested by two or more witnesses each of whom has seen the executant sign 
    or affix his mark to the instrument, or has seen some other person sign the 
    instrument in the presence and by the direction of the executant, or has 
    received from the executant a personal acknowledgement of his signature or 
    mark, or of the signature of such other person, and each of whom has signed 
    the instrument in the presence of the executant; but it shall not be 
    necessary that more than one of such witnesses shall have been present at 
    the same time, and no particular form of attestation shall be necessary;]
 

    “registered” means registered in 


    2[3[any 
    part of the territories] to which this Act extends] under the law4 for 
    the time being in force regulating the registration of documents;
 

    
    “attached to the earth” means—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    rooted in the earth, as in the case of trees and shrubs;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     
    imbedded in the earth, as in the case of walls or buildings; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     
    attached to what is so imbedded for the permanent beneficial enjoyment of 
    that to which it is attached;
 

          
    5[“actionable 
    claim” means a claim to any debt, other than a debt secured by mortgage of 
    immoveable property or by hypothecation or pledge of moveable property, or 
    to any beneficial interest in moveable property not in the possession, 
    either actual or constructive, of the claimant, which the Civil Courts 
    recognise as affording grounds for relief, whether such debt or beneficial 
    interest be existent, accruing, conditional or contingent;]
 

          
    6[“a 
    person is said to have notice” of a fact when he actually knows that fact, 
    or when, but for wilful abstention from an enquiry or search which he ought 
    to have made, or gross negligence, he would have known it.
 

Explanation I.—Where 
    any transaction relating to immoveable property is required by law to be and 
    has been effected by a registered instrument, any person acquiring such 
    property or any part of, or share or interest in, such property shall be 
    deemed to have notice of such instrument as from the date of registration 
    or, where the property is not all situated in one sub-district, or where the 
    registered instrument has been registered under sub-section (2) of section 
    30 of the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908), from the earliest date 
    on which any memorandum of such registered instrument has been filed by any 
    Sub-Registrar within whose sub-district any part of the property which is 
    being acquired, or of the property wherein a share or interest is being 
    acquired, is situated:]
 

Provided that—
 <subsection>

<number>1</number> the instrument 
    has been registered and its registration completed in the manner prescribed 
    by the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908), and the rules made 
    thereunder,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>2</number> the instrument or 
    memorandum has been duly entered or filed, as the case may be, in books kept 
    under section 51 of that Act, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>3</number> the particulars 
    regarding the transaction to which the instrument relates have been 
    correctly entered in the indexes kept under section 55 of that Act.
 

Explanation II.—Any 
    person acquiring any immovable property or any share or interest in any such 
    property shall be deemed to have notice of the title, if any, of any person 
    who is for the time being in actual possession thereof.
 

Explanation III.—A 
    person shall be deemed to have had notice of any fact if his agent acquires 
    notice thereof whilst acting on his behalf in the course of business to 
    which that fact is material:
 

Provided that, if the 
    agent fraudulently conceals the fact, the principal shall not be charged 
    with notice thereof as against any person who was a party to or otherwise 
    cognizant of the fraud.
 
 

 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>4</number> Enactments 
    relating to contracts to be taken as part of Contract Act and supplemental 
    to the Registration Act.—The 
    Chapters and sections of this Act which relate to contracts shall be taken 
    as part of the Indian Contract Act, 1872  
    (9 of 1872).
 


    1[And 
    section 54, paragraphs 2 and 3, and sections 59, 107 and 123 shall be read 
    as supplemental to the Indian Registration Act, 

    2[1908 
    (16 of 1908)].]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>5</number> 
    “Transfer of property” defined.—In 
    the following sections “transfer of property” means an act by which a living 
    person conveys property, in present or in future, to one or more other 
    living persons, or to himself, 
    1[or 
    to himself] and one or more other living persons; and “to transfer property” 
    is to perform such act.
 


    1[In 
    this section “living person” includes a company or association or body of 
    individuals, whether incorporated or not, but nothing herein contained shall 
    affect any law for the time being in force relating to transfer of property 
    to or by companies, associations or bodies of individuals.]
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>5</number> 
    “Transfer of property” defined.—In 
    the following sections “transfer of property” means an act by which a living 
    person conveys property, in present or in future, to one or more other 
    living persons, or to himself, 
    1[or 
    to himself] and one or more other living persons; and “to transfer property” 
    is to perform such act.
 


    1[In 
    this section “living person” includes a company or association or body of 
    individuals, whether incorporated or not, but nothing herein contained shall 
    affect any law for the time being in force relating to transfer of property 
    to or by companies, associations or bodies of individuals.]
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>6</number> What may be 
    transferred.—Property 
    of any kind may be transferred, except as otherwise provided by this Act or 
    by any other law for the time being in force,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    The chance of an heir-apparent succeeding to an estate, the chance of a 
    relation obtaining a legacy on the death of a kinsman, or any other mere 
    possibility of a like nature, cannot be transferred;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     A 
    mere right of re-entry for breach of a condition subsequent cannot be 
    transferred to any one except the owner of the property affected thereby;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     An 
    easement cannot be transferred apart from the dominant heritage;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     
    All interest in property restricted in its enjoyment to the owner personally 
    cannot be transferred by him;
 


    1[(dd)     A right 
    to future maintenance, in whatsoever manner arising, secured or determined, 
    cannot be transferred;]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> 
        A mere right to sue 

    2[***] cannot be 
    transferred;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>     
    A   public office cannot be transferred, nor can the salary of a public 
    officer, whether before or after it has become payable;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> 
        Stipends allowed to military 

    3[naval], 

    4[air-force] and 
    civil pensioners of the 

    5[Government] and 
    political pensions cannot be transferred;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> 
        No transfer can be made (1) in so far as it is opposed to the nature of 
    the interest affected thereby, or (2) 

    6[for an unlawful 
    object or consideration within the meaning of section 23 of the Indian 
    Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872)], or (3) to a person legally disqualified to 
    be transferee;
 


    7[(i)     Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to authorise a tenant having an 
    untransferable right of occupancy, the farmer of an estate in respect of 
    which default has been made in paying revenue, or the lessee of an estate, 
    under the management of a Court of Wards, to assign his interest as such 
    tenant, farmer or lessee.]
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>7</number> Persons competent 
    to transfer.—Every 
    person competent to contract and entitled to transferable property, or 
    authorised to dispose of transferable property not his own, is competent to 
    transfer such property either wholly or in part, and either absolutely or 
    conditionally, in the circumstances, to the extent and in the manner, 
    allowed and prescribed by any law for the time being in force.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>8</number> Operation of 
    transfer.—Unless 
    a different intention is expressed or necessarily implied, a transfer of 
    property passes forthwith to the transferee all the interest which the 
    transferor is then capable of passing in the property and in the legal 
    incidents thereof.
 

Such incidents 
    include, where the property is land, the easements annexed thereto, the 
    rents and profits thereof accruing after the transfer, and all things 
    attached to the earth;
 

and, where the 
    property is machinery attached to the earth, the moveable parts thereof;
 

and, where the 
    property is a house, the easements annexed thereto, the rent thereof 
    accruing after the transfer, and the locks, keys, bars, doors, windows, and 
    all other things provided for permanent use therewith;
 

and, where the 
    property is a debt or other actionable claim, the securities therefor 
    (except where they are also for other debts or claims not transferred to the 
    transferee), but not arrears of interest accrued before the transfer;
 

and, where the 
    property is money or other property yielding income, the interest or income 
    thereof accruing after the transfer takes effect.
 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>9</number> Oral transfer.—A 
    transfer of property may be made without writing in every case in which a 
    writing is not expressly required by law.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>10</number> Condition 
    restraining alienation.—Where 
    property is transferred subject to a condition or limitation absolutely 
    restraining the transferee or any person claiming under him from parting 
    with or disposing of his interest in the property, the condition or 
    limitation is void, except in the case of a lease where the condition is for 
    the benefit of the lessor or those claiming under him: provided that 
    property may be transferred to or for the benefit of a women (not being a 
    Hindu, Muhammadan or Buddhist), so that she shall not have power during her 
    marriage to transfer or charge the same or her beneficial interest therein.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>11</number> Restriction 
    repugnant to interest created.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created absolutely in 
    favour of any person, but the terms of the transfer direct that such 
    interest shall be applied or enjoyed by him in a particular manner, he shall 
    be entitled to receive and dispose of such interest as if there were no such 
    direction.
 


    1[Where 
    any such direction has been made in respect of one piece of immoveable 
    property for the purpose of securing the beneficial enjoyment of another 
    piece of such property, nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect 
    any right which the transferor may have to enforce such direction or any 
    remedy which he may have in respect of a breach thereof.]
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>12</number> Condition making 
    interest determinable on insolvency or attempted alienation.—Where 
    property is transferred subject to a condition or limitation making any 
    interest therein, reserved or given to or for the benefit of any person, to 
    cease on his becoming insolvent or endeavouring to transfer or dispose of 
    the same, such condition or limitation is void.
 

Nothing in this 
    section applies to a condition in a lease for the benefit of the lessor or 
    those claiming under him.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>13</number> Transfer for 
    benefit of unborn person.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created for the benefit of 
    a person not in existence at the date of the transfer, subject to a prior 
    interest created by the same transfer, the interest created for the benefit 
    of such person shall not take effect, unless it extends to the whole of the 
    remaining interest of the transferor in the property.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
       transfers property of which he is the 
      owner to B in trust for A and his intended wife successively 
      for their lives, and, after the death of the survivor, for the eldest son 
      of the intended marriage for life, and after his death for A’s 
      second son.  The interest so created for the benefit of the eldest son 
      does not take effect, because it does not extend to the whole of A’s 
      remaining interest in the property.

 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>14</number> Rule against 
    perpetuity.—No 
    transfer of property can operate to create an interest which is to take 
    effect after the life-time of one or more persons living at the date of such 
    transfer, and the minority of some person who shall be in existence at the 
    expiration of that period, and to whom, if he attains full age, the interest 
    created is to belong.
 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>15</number> 
    Transfer to class some of whom come under sections 13 and 14.—If, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created for the benefit of 
    a class of persons with regard to some of whom such interest fails by reason 
    of any of the rules contained in sections 13 and 14, such interest fails
    

    1[in 
    regard to those persons only and not in regard to the whole class].
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>16</number> 
    Transfer to take effect on failure of prior interest.—Where, by reason 
    of any of the rules contained in sections 13 and 14, an interest created for 
    the benefit of a person or of a class of persons fails in regard to such 
    person  or  the whole of  such class, any interest created in the same 
    transaction and intended to take effect after or upon failure of such prior 
    interest also fails.
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>17</number> Direction for 
    accumulation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the terms of a transfer of property direct that the income arising 
    from the property shall be accumulated either wholly or in part during a 
    period longer than—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     
    the life of the transferor, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     a 
    period of eighteen years from the date of transfer,
 

such direction shall, 
    save as hereinafter provided, be void to the extent to which the period 
    during which the accumulation is directed exceeds the longer of the 
    aforesaid periods, and at the end of such last-mentioned period the property 
    and the income thereof shall be disposed of as if the period during which 
    the accumulation has been directed to be made had elapsed.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> This section 
    shall not affect any direction for accumulation for the purpose of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>     
    the payment of the debts of the transferor or any other person taking any 
    interest under the transferor; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>     
    the provision of portions for children or remoter issue of the transferor or 
    of any other person taking any interest under the transfer; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>     
    the preservation or maintenance of the property transferred,
 

and such direction 
    may be made accordingly.
 

 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>18</number> Transfer in 
    perpetuity for benefit of public.—The 
    restrictions in sections 14, 16 and 17 shall not apply in the case of a 
    transfer of property for the benefit of the public in the advancement of 
    religion, knowledge, commerce, health, safety or any other object beneficial 
    to mankind.]
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>19</number> Vested interest.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created in favour of a 
    person without specifying the time when it is to take effect, or in terms 
    specifying that it is to take effect forthwith or on the happening of an 
    event which must happen, such interest is vested, unless a contrary 
    intention appears from the terms of the transfer.
 

A vested interest is 
    not defeated by the death of the transferee before he obtains possession.
 

Explanation.—An 
    intention that an interest shall not be vested is not to be inferred merely 
    from a provision whereby the enjoyment thereof is postponed, or whereby a 
    prior interest in the same property is given or reserved to some other 
    person, or whereby income arising from the property is directed to be 
    accumulated until the time of enjoyment arrives, or from a provision that if 
    a particular event shall happen the interest shall pass to another person.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>20</number> When unborn  
    person  acquires vested interest on transfer for his benefit.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created for the benefit of 
    a person not then living, he acquires upon his birth, unless a contrary 
    intention appears from the terms of the transfer, a vested interest, 
    although he may not be entitled to the enjoyment thereof immediately on his 
    birth.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>21</number> Contingent 
    interest.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created in favour of a 
    person to take effect only on the happening of a specified uncertain event, 
    or if a specified uncertain event shall not happen, such person thereby 
    acquires a contingent interest in the property.  Such interest becomes a 
    vested interest, in the former case, on the happening of the event, in the 
    latter, when the happening of the event becomes impossible.
 <section>

<number>Exception</number>—Where, 
    under a transfer of property, a person becomes entitled to an interest 
    therein upon attaining a particular age, and the transferor also gives to 
    him absolutely the income to arise from such interest before he reaches that 
    age, or directs the income or so much thereof as may be necessary to be 
    applied for his benefit, such interest is not contingent.
 

 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>22</number> Transfer to 
    members of a class who attain a particular age.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created in favour of such 
    members only of a class as shall attain a particular age, such interest does 
    not vest in any member of the class who has not attained that age.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>23</number> Transfer 
    contingent on happening of specified uncertain event.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is to accrue to a specified 
    person if a specified uncertain event shall happen, and no time is mentioned 
    for the occurrence of that event, the interest fails unless such event 
    happens before, or at the same time as, the intermediate or precedent 
    interest ceases to exist.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>24</number> Transfer to such 
    of certain persons as survive at some period not specified.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is to accrue to such of 
    certain persons as shall be surviving at some period, but the exact period 
    is not specified, the interest shall go to such of them as shall be alive 
    when the intermediate or precedent interest ceases to exist, unless a 
    contrary intention appears from the terms of the transfer.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      transfers property to B for life, and after his death to C 
      and D, equally to be divided between them, or to the survivor of 
      them.  C dies during the life of B.  D survives B. 
      At B’s death the property passes to D.
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>25</number> Conditional 
    transfer.—An 
    interest created on a transfer of property and dependent upon a condition 
    fails if the fulfilment of the condition is impossible, or is forbidden by 
    law, or is of such a nature that, if permitted, it would defeat the 
    provisions of any law, or is fraudulent, or involves or implies injury to 
    the person or property of another, or the Court regards it as immoral or 
    opposed to public policy.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number> A lets a farm to B 
      on condition that he shall walk a hundred miles in an hour.  The lease is 
      void.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> A  gives Rs. 500 to B 
      on condition that he shall marry A’s daughter C.  At the 
      date of the transfer C was dead.  The transfer is void.
 </section><section>

      <number>c</number> A transfers Rs. 500 to B 
      on condition that she shall murder C. The transfer is void.
 </section><section>

      <number>d</number> A transfers Rs. 500 to his 
      niece C, if she will desert her husband. The transfer is void.
</section>
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>26</number> Fulfilment of 
    condition precedent.—Where 
    the terms of a transfer of property impose a condition to be fulfilled 
    before a person can take an interest in the property, the condition shall be 
    deemed to have been fulfilled if it has been substantially complied with.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number> A transfers Rs. 5,000 to 
      B on condition that he shall marry with the consent  of C, D  
      and E. E  dies. B marries with the consent of C and
      D.  B is deemed to have fulfilled the condition.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> A transfers Rs. 5,000 to 
      B on condition that he shall marry with the consent of C, D and
      E.  B marries without the consent of C, D and E, 
      but obtains their consent after the marriage.  B has not fulfilled 
      the condition.
 

 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>27</number> Conditional 
    transfer to one person coupled with transfer to another on failure of prior 
    disposition.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created in favour of one 
    person, and by the same transaction an ulterior disposition of the same 
    interest is made in favour of another, if the prior disposition under the 
    transfer shall fail, the ulterior disposition shall take effect upon the 
    failure of the prior disposition, although the failure may not have occurred 
    in the manner contemplated by the transferor.
 

But, where the 
    intention of the parties to the transaction is that the ulterior disposition 
    shall take effect only in the event of the prior disposition failing in a  
    particular manner, the ulterior disposition shall not take effect unless the 
    prior disposition fails in that manner.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number> A transfers Rs. 500 to B 
      on condition that he shall execute a certain lease within three months 
      after A’s death, and, if he should neglect to do so, to C. B 
      dies in A’s life-time. The disposition in favour of C takes 
      effect.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> A transfers property to his 
      wife; but, in case she should die in his life-time, transfer to  B  
      that which he had transferred to her.  A and his wife perish 
      together, under circumstances which make it impossible to prove that she 
      died before him.  The disposition in favour of B does not take 
      effect.
 

 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>28</number> Ulterior transfer 
    conditional on happening or not happening of specified event.—On 
    a transfer of property an interest therein may be created to accrue to any 
    person with the condition superadded that in case a specified uncertain 
    event shall happen such interest shall pass to another person, or that in 
    case a specified uncertain event shall not happen such interest shall pass 
    to another person. In each case the dispositions are subject to the rules 
    contained in sections 10, 12, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25 and 27.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>29</number> Fulfilment of 
    condition subsequent.—An 
    ulterior disposition of the kind contemplated by the last preceding section 
    cannot, take effect unless the condition is strictly fulfilled.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      transfers Rs. 500 to B, to be paid to him on his attaining his 
      majority or marrying, with a proviso that, if B dies as minor or 
      marries without C’s consent, the Rs. 500 shall go to D.  B 
      marries when only 17 years of age, without C’s consent.  The 
      transfer to D takes effect.
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>30</number> Prior disposition 
    not affected by invalidity of ulterior disposition.—If 
    the ulterior disposition is not valid, the prior disposition is not affected 
    by it.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      transfers a farm to B for her life, and, if she does not desert her 
      husband to C. B is entitled to the farm during her life as 
      if no condition had been inserted.
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>31</number> Condition that 
    transfer shall cease to have effect in case specified uncertain event 
    happens or does not happen.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 12, on a transfer of property an interest 
    therein may be created with the condition superadded that it shall cease to 
    exist in case a specified uncertain event shall happen, or in case a 
    specified uncertain event shall not happen.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number> A transfers a farm to B 
      for his life, with a proviso that, in case B cuts down a certain 
      wood, the transfer shall cease to have any effect.  B cuts down the 
      wood.  He loses his life-interest in the farm.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> A transfers a farm to B, 
      provided that, if B shall not go to England within three years 
      after the date of the transfer, his interest in the farm shall cease.  
      B does not go to England within the term prescribed.  His interest in 
      the farm ceases.
 

 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>32</number> Such condition 
    must not be invalid.—In 
    order that a condition that an interest shall cease to exist may be valid, 
    it is necessary that the event to which it relates be one which could 
    legally constitute the condition of the creation of an interest.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>33</number> Transfer 
    conditional on performance of act, no time being specified for performance.—Where, 
    on a transfer of property, an interest therein is created subject to a 
    condition that the person taking it shall perform a certain act, but no time 
    is specified for the performance of the act, the condition is broken when he 
    renders impossible, permanently or for an indefinite period, the performance 
    of the act.
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>34</number> Transfer 
    conditional on performance of act, time being specified.—Where 
    an act is to be performed by a person either as a condition to be fulfilled 
    before an interest created on a transfer of property is enjoyed by him, or 
    as a condition on the non-fulfilment of which the interest is to pass from 
    him to another person, and a time is specified for the performance of the 
    act, if such performance within the specified time is prevented by the fraud 
    of a person who would be directly benefited by non-fulfilment of the 
    condition, such further time shall as against him be allowed for performing 
    the act as shall be requisite to make up for the delay caused by such 
    fraud.  But if no time is specified for the performance of the act, then, if 
    its performance is by the fraud of a person interested in the non-fulfilment 
    of the condition rendered impossible or indefinitely postponed, the 
    condition shall as against him be deemed to have been fulfilled.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>35</number> Election when 
    necessary.—Where 
    a person professes to transfer property which he has no right to transfer, 
    and as part of the same transaction confers any benefit on the owner of the 
    property, such owner must elect either to confirm such transfer or to 
    dissent from it; and in the latter case he shall relinquish the benefit so 
    conferred, and the benefit so relinquished shall revert to the transferor or 
    his representative as if it had not been disposed of,
 

subject nevertheless,
 

where the transfer is 
    gratuitous, and the transferor has, before the election, died or otherwise 
    become incapable of making a fresh transfer,
 

and in all cases 
    where the transfer is for consideration,
 

to the charge of 
    making good to the disappointed transferee the amount or value of the 
    property attempted to be transferred to him.
 
 

Illustrations
 

      The farm of Sultanpur is the property 
      of C and worth Rs. 800. A by an instrument of gift professes 
      to transfer it to B,  giving by the same instrument Rs. 1,000 to 
      C. C elects to retain the farm. He forfeits the gift of Rs. 
      1,000.
 

      In the same case, A dies  
      before  the  election.  His representative must out of the Rs. 1,000 pay 
      Rs. 800 to B.
 

The rule in the 
      first paragraph of this section applies whether the transferor does or 
      does not believe that which he professes to transfer to be his own.
 

A person taking no 
      benefit directly under a transaction, but deriving a benefit under it 
      indirectly, need not elect.
 

A person who in his 
      one capacity takes a benefit under the transaction may in another dissent 
      therefrom.

 

Exception to the last 
    preceding four rules.—Where 
    a particular benefit is expressed to be conferred on the owner of the 
    property which the transferor professes to transfer, and such benefit is 
    expressed to be in lieu of that property, if such owner claims the property, 
    he must relinquish the particular benefit, but he is not bound to relinquish 
    any other benefit conferred upon him by the same transaction.
 

Acceptance of the 
    benefit by the person on whom it is conferred constitutes an election by him 
    to confirm the transfer, if he is aware of his duty to elect and of those 
    circumstances which would influence the judgment of a reasonable man in 
    making an election, or if he waives enquiry into the circumstances.
 

Such knowledge or 
    waiver shall, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, be presumed, if 
    the person on whom the benefit has been conferred has enjoyed it for two 
    years without doing any act to express dissent.
 

Such knowledge or 
    waiver may be inferred from any act of his which renders it impossible to 
    place the persons interested in the property professed to be transferred in 
    the same condition as if such act had not been done.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      transfers to B an estate to which C is entitled, and as part 
      of the same transaction gives C a coal-mine. C takes 
      possession of the mine and exhausts it.  He has thereby confirmed the 
      transfer of the estate to B.
 

If he does not 
      within one year after the date of the transfer signify to the transferor 
      or his representatives his intention to confirm or to dissent from the 
      transfer, the transferor or his representative may, upon the expiration of 
      that period, require him to make his election; and, if he does not comply 
      with such requisition within a reasonable time after he has received it, 
      he shall be deemed to have elected to confirm the transfer.
 

In case of 
      disability, the election shall be postponed until the disability ceases, 
      or until the election is made by some competent authority.
 

 

COMMENTS
 
When question of election 
      arises
 

      A case of election arises only when 
      the transferee takes a benefit directly under a transaction.  When the 
      transferee derives any  benefit  indirectly, no question of election 
      arises, as he, in that case, cannot be said to take under the deed; 
      Valliammai v. Nagappa, AIR 1967 SC 1153.

  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>36</number> Apportionment of 
    periodical payments on determination of interest of person entitled.—In 
    the absence of a contract or local usage to the contrary, all rents 
    annuities, pensions, dividends and other periodical payments in the nature 
    of income shall, upon the transfer of the interest of the person entitled to 
    receive such payments, be deemed, as between the transferor and the 
    transferee, to accrue due from day to day, and to be apportionable 
    accordingly, but to be payable on the days appointed for the payment 
    thereof.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>37</number> Apportionment of 
    benefit of obligation on severance.—When, 
    in consequence of a transfer, property is divided and held in several 
    shares, and thereupon the benefit of any obligation relating to the property 
    as a whole passes from one to several owners of the property, the 
    corresponding duty shall, in the absence of a contract, to the contrary 
    amongst the owners, be performed in favour of each of such owners in 
    proportion to the value of his share in the property, provided that the duty 
    can be severed and that the severance does not substantially increase the 
    burden of the obligation; but if the duty cannot be severed, or if the 
    severance would substantially increase the burden of the obligation the duty 
    shall be performed for the benefit of such one of the several owners as they 
    shall jointly designate for that purpose:
 

Provided that no 
    person on whom the burden of the obligation lies shall be answerable for 
    failure to discharge it in manner provided by this section, unless and until 
    he has had reasonable notice of the severance.
 

Nothing in this 
    section applies to leases for agricultural purposes unless and until the 
    State Government by notification in the Official Gazette so directs.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number>  A sells to B, C and
      D a house situated in a village and leased to E at an annual 
      rent of Rs. 30 and delivery of one fat sheep, B having provided 
      half the purchase-money and C and D one quarter each. E, 
      having notice of this, must pay Rs. 15 to B, Rs. 7.50 to C, 
      and Rs. 7.50 to D and must deliver the sheep according to the joint 
      direction of B, C and D.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> In the same case, each house in 
      the village being bound to provide ten days’ labour each year on a dyke to 
      prevent inundation. E had agreed as a term of his lease to perform 
      this work for A. B, C and D severally require E to 
      perform the ten days’ work due on account of the house of each. E 
      is not bound to do more than ten days’ work in all, according to such 
      directions as B, C and D may join in giving.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>38</number> Transfer by 
    person authorised only under certain circumstances to transfer.—Where 
    any person, authorised only under circumstances in their nature variable to 
    dispose of immoveable property, transfers such property for consideration, 
    alleging the existence of such circumstances,  they shall, as between the 
    transferee on the one part and the transferor and other persons (if any) 
    affected by the transfer on the other part, be deemed to have existed, if 
    the transferee, after using reasonable care to ascertain the existence of 
    such circumstances, has acted in good faith.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A, 
      a Hindu widow, whose husband has left collateral heirs, alleging that the 
      property held by her as such is insufficient for her maintenance, agrees, 
      for purposes neither religious nor charitable to sell a field, part of 
      such property, to B.  B satisfies himself by reasonable enquiry 
      that the income of the property is insufficient for A’s 
      maintenance, and that the sale of the field is necessary, and acting in 
      good faith, buys the field from A. As between B on the one 
      part and  A  and the collateral heirs on the other part, a 
      necessity for the sale shall be deemed to have existed.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>39</number> 
    Transfer where third person is entitled to maintenance.—Where 
    a third person has a right to receive maintenance, or a provision for 
    advancement or marriage, from the profits of immoveable property, and such 
    property is transferred, 

    1[***] 
    the right may be enforced against the transferee, if he has  notice 


    2[thereof] 
    or if  the  transfer is gratuitous; but not against a transferee for 
    consideration and without notice of the right, nor against such property in 
    his hands.
 


    3[* 
    * *]
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>40</number> 
    Burden of obligation imposing restriction on use of land.—Where, 
    for the more beneficial enjoyment of his own immoveable property, a third 
    person has, independently of any interest in the  immoveable  property  of 
    another or of any easement thereon, a right to restrain the enjoyment 


    1[in 
    a particular manner of the latter property], or
 

Or of obligation 
    annexed to ownership but not amounting to interest or easement.—Where 
    a third person is entitled to the benefit of an obligation arising out of 
    contract and annexed to the ownership of immoveable property, but not 
    amounting to an interest therein or easement thereon,
 

such right or 
    obligation may be enforced against a transferee with notice thereof or a 
    gratuitous transferee of the property affected thereby, but not against a 
    transferee for consideration and without notice of the right or obligation, 
    not against such property in his hands.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      contracts to sell Sultanpur to B. While the contract is still in 
      force he sells Sultanpur to C, who has notice of the contract.  
      B may enforce the contract against C to the same extent as 
      against A.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>41</number> Transfer by 
    ostensible owner.—Where, 
    with the consent, express or implied, of the persons interested in 
    immoveable property, a person is the ostensible owner of such property and 
    transfers the same for consideration, the transfer shall not be voidable on 
    the ground that the transferor was not authorised to make it: provided that 
    the transferee, after taking reasonable care to ascertain that the 
    transferor had power to make the transfer, has acted in good faith.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>42</number> Transfer by 
    person having authority to revoke former transfer.—Where 
    a person transfers any immoveable property, reserving power to revoke the 
    transfer, and subsequently transfers the property for consideration to 
    another transferee, such transfer operates in favour of such transferee 
    (subject to any condition attached to the exercise of the power) as a 
    revocation of the former transfer to the extent of the power.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      lets a house to B, and reserves power to revoke the lease if, in 
      the opinion of a specified surveyor, B should make a use of it 
      detrimental to its value.  Afterwards A, thinking that such a use 
      has been made, lets the house to C.  This operates as a revocation 
      of B’s lease subject to the opinion of the surveyor as to B’s 
      use of the house having been detrimental to its value.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>43</number> 
    Transfer by unauthorised person who subsequently acquires interest in 
    property transferred.—Where 
    a person 

    1[fraudulently 
    or] erroneously represents that he is authorised to transfer certain 
    immoveable property and professes to transfer such property for 
    consideration, such transfer shall, at the option of the transferee, operate 
    on any interest which the transferor may acquire in such property at any 
    time during which the contract of transfer subsists.
 

Nothing in this 
    section shall impair the right of transferees in good faith for 
    consideration without notice of the existence of the said option.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A, 
      a Hindu who has separated from his father B, sells to C 
      three fields, X, Y and Z, representing that A is 
      authorised to transfer the same.  Of these fields Z does not belong 
      to A, it having been retained by B on the partition; but on
      B’s dying A as heir obtains Z. C, not having 
      rescinded the contract of sale, may require A to deliver Z 
      to him.
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>44</number> Transfer by one 
    co-owner.—Where 
    one of two or more co-owners of immoveable property legally competent in 
    that behalf transfers his share of such property or any interest therein, 
    the transferee acquires as to such share or interest, and so far as is 
    necessary to give, effect to the transfer, the transferor’s right to joint 
    possession or other common or part enjoyment of the property, and to enforce 
    a partition of the same, but subject to the conditions and liabilities 
    affecting at the date of the transfer, the share or interest so transferred.
 

Where the transferee 
    of a share of a dwelling-house belonging to an undivided family is not a 
    member of the family, nothing in this section shall be deemed to entitle him 
    to joint possession or other common or part enjoyment of the house.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>45</number> Joint transfer 
    for consideration.—Where 
    immoveable property is transferred for consideration to two or more persons 
    and such consideration is paid out of a fund belonging to them in common, 
    they are, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, respectively 
    entitled to interests in such property identical, as nearly as may be, with 
    the interests to which they were respectively entitled in the fund; and, 
    where such consideration is paid out of separate funds belonging to them 
    respectively, they are, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, 
    respectively entitled to interests in such property in proportion to the 
    shares of the consideration which they respectively advanced.
 

In the absence of 
    evidence as to the interests in the fund to which they were respectively 
    entitled, or as to the shares which they respectively advanced, such persons 
    shall be presumed to be equally interested in the property.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>46</number> Transfer for 
    consideration by persons having distinct interests.—Where 
    immoveable property is transferred for consideration by persons having 
    distinct interests therein, the transferors are,  in the absence of a 
    contract to the contrary, entitled to share in the consideration equally, 
    where their interests in the property were of equal value, and, where such 
    interests were of unequal value, proportionately to the value of their 
    respective interests.
 
 

      Illustration
 <section>

      <number>a</number> A, owing a moiety, and B 
      and C, each a quarter share, of mauza Sultanpur, exchange an eighth 
      share of that mauza for a quarter  share of mauza.  There being no 
      agreement to the contrary,  A is entitled to an eighth share in 
      Lalpura, and B and C each to a sixteenth share in the mauza.
 </section><section>

      <number>b</number> A, being entitled to a 
      life-interest in mauza Atrali and B and C to the reversion, 
      sell the mauza for Rs. 1,000.  A’s life-interest is ascertained to 
      be worth Rs. 600, the reversion Rs. 400.  A is entitled to receive 
      Rs. 600 out of the purchase-money. B and C to receive Rs. 
      400.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>47</number> Transfer  by  
    co-owners of share in common property.—Where  
    several  co-owners of immoveable property transfer a share therein without 
    specifying that the transfer is to take effect on any particular share or 
    shares of the transferors, the transfer, as among such transferors, takes 
    effect on such shares equally where the shares were equal, and, where they 
    were unequal, proportionately to the extent of such shares.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A, 
      the owner of an eight-anna share, and B and C, each the 
      owner of a four-anna share, in mauza Sultanpur, transfer a two-anna share 
      in the mauza to D, without specifying from which of their several 
      shares the transfer is made. To give effect to the transfer one-anna share 
      is taken from the share of A, and half-an-anna share from each of 
      the shares of B and C.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>48</number> Priority of 
    rights created by transfer.—Where 
    a person purports to create by transfer at different times rights in or over 
    the same immoveable property, and such rights cannot all exist or be 
    exercised to their full extent together, each later created right shall, in 
    the absence of a special contract or reservation binding the earlier 
    transferees, be subject to the rights previously created.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>49</number> Transferee’s 
    right under policy.—Where 
    immoveable property is transferred for consideration, and such property or 
    any part thereof is at the date of the transfer insured against loss or 
    damage by fire, the transferee, in case of such loss or damage, may, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, require any money which the 
    transferor actually receives under the policy, or so much thereof as may be 
    necessary, to be applied in reinstating the property.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>49</number> Transferee’s 
    right under policy.—Where 
    immoveable property is transferred for consideration, and such property or 
    any part thereof is at the date of the transfer insured against loss or 
    damage by fire, the transferee, in case of such loss or damage, may, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, require any money which the 
    transferor actually receives under the policy, or so much thereof as may be 
    necessary, to be applied in reinstating the property.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>50</number> Rent bona fide 
    paid to holder under defective title.—No 
    person shall be chargeable with any rents or profits of any immoveable 
    property, which he has in good faith paid or delivered to any person of whom 
    he in good faith held such property, notwithstanding it may afterwards 
    appear that the person to whom such payment or delivery was made had no 
    right to receive such rents or profits.
 
 

      Illustration
 

      A 
      lets a field to B at a rent of Rs. 50, and then transfers the field 
      to C.  B, having no notice of the transfer, in good faith pays the 
      rent to A. B is not chargeable with the rent so paid.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>51</number> Improvements made 
    by bona fide holders under defective titles.—When 
    the transferee of immoveable property makes any improvement on the property, 
    believing in good faith that he is absolutely entitled thereto, and he 
    subsequently evicted therefrom by any person having a better title, the 
    transferee has a right to require the person causing the eviction either to 
    have the value of the improvement estimated and paid or secured to the 
    transferee, or to sell interest in the property to the transferee at the 
    then market value thereof, irrespective of the value of such improvement.
 

The amount to be paid 
    or secured in respect of such improvement shall be the estimated value 
    thereof at the time of the eviction.
 

When, under the 
    circumstances aforesaid, the transferee has planted or sown on the property 
    crops which are growing when he is evicted therefrom, he is entitled to such 
    crops and to free ingress and egress to gather and carry them.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>52</number> 
    Transfer of property pending suit relating thereto.—During 
    the 

    1[pendency] 
    in any Court having authority 

    2[3[within 
    the limits of India excluding the State of Jammu and Kashmir] or established 
    beyond such limits] by 

    4[the 
    Central Government] 

    5[* 
    * *]  of 

    6[any] 
    suit or proceedings which  is not collusive and in which any right to 
    immoveable property is directly and specifically in question, the property 
    cannot be transferred or otherwise dealt with by any party to the suit or 
    proceeding so as to affect the rights of any other party thereto under any 
    decree or order which may be made therein, except under the authority of the 
    Court and on such terms as it may impose.
 


    7[Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, the pendency of a suit or proceeding shall be 
    deemed to commence from the date of the presentation of the plaint or the 
    institution of the proceeding in a Court of competent jurisdiction, and to 
    continue until the suit or proceeding has been disposed of by a final decree 
    or order and complete satisfaction or discharge of such decree or order has 
    been obtained, or has become unobtainable by reason of the expiration of any 
    period of limitation prescribed for the execution thereof by any law for the 
    time being in force.]
 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>53</number> 
    Fraudulent transfer.—
<section><number>1</number> Every transfer of immoveable property made with 
    intent to defeat or delay the creditors of the transferor shall be voidable 
    at the option of any creditor so defeated or delayed.
 

Nothing in this 
    sub-section shall impair the rights of a transferee in good faith and for 
    consideration.
 

Nothing in this 
    sub-section shall affect any law for the time being in force relating to 
    insolvency.
 

A suit instituted by 
    a creditor (which term includes a decree-holder whether he has or has not 
    applied for execution of his decree) to avoid a transfer on the ground that 
    it has been made with intent to defeat or delay the creditors of the 
    transferor shall be instituted on behalf of, or for the benefit of, all the 
    creditors.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every transfer of 
    immoveable property made without consideration with intent to defraud a 
    subsequent transferee shall be voidable at the option of such transferee.
 

For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, no transfer made without consideration shall be deemed to 
    have been made with intent to defraud by reason only that a subsequent 
    transfer for consideration was made.]
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>53A</number> 
    Part performance.—Where any person contracts to transfer for 
    consideration any immoveable property by writing signed by him or on his 
    behalf from which the terms necessary to constitute the transfer can be 
    ascertained with reasonable certainty,
 

and the transferee 
    has, in part performance of the contract, taken possession of the property 
    or any part thereof, or the transferee, being already in possession, 
    continues in possession in part performance of the contract and has done 
    some act in furtherance of the contract,
 

and the transferee 
    has performed or is willing to perform his part of the contract,
 

then, notwithstanding that 

    2[***] 
    where there is an instrument of transfer, that the transfer has not been 
    completed in the manner prescribed therefor by the law for the time being in 
    force, the transferor or any person claiming under him shall be debarred 
    from enforcing against the transferee and persons claiming under him any 
    right in respect of the property of which the transferee has taken or 
    continued in possession, other than a right expressly provided by the terms 
    of the contract:
 

Provided that nothing 
    in this section shall affect the rights of a transferee for consideration 
    who has no notice of the contract or of the part performance thereof.]
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>54</number> “Sale” defined.—‘‘Sale” 
    is a transfer of ownership in exchange for a price paid or promised or 
    part-paid and part-promised.
 

Sale 
    how  made.—3Such 
    transfer, in the case of tangible immoveable property of the value of one 
    hundred rupees and upwards, or in the case of a reversion or other 
    intangible thing, can be made only by a registered instrument.
 


    1In 
    the case of tangible immoveable property of a value less than one hundred 
    rupees, such transfer may be made either by a registered instrument or by 
    delivery of the property.
 

Delivery of tangible 
    immoveable property takes place when the seller places the buyer, or such 
    person as he directs, in possession of the property.
 

Contract for sale.—A 
    contract for the sale of immoveable property is a contract that a sale of 
    such property shall take place on terms settled between the parties.
 

It does not, of 
    itself, create any interest in or charge on such property.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>54</number> “Sale” defined.—‘‘Sale” 
    is a transfer of ownership in exchange for a price paid or promised or 
    part-paid and part-promised.
 

Sale 
    how  made.—3Such 
    transfer, in the case of tangible immoveable property of the value of one 
    hundred rupees and upwards, or in the case of a reversion or other 
    intangible thing, can be made only by a registered instrument.
 


    1In 
    the case of tangible immoveable property of a value less than one hundred 
    rupees, such transfer may be made either by a registered instrument or by 
    delivery of the property.
 

Delivery of tangible 
    immoveable property takes place when the seller places the buyer, or such 
    person as he directs, in possession of the property.
 

Contract for sale.—A 
    contract for the sale of immoveable property is a contract that a sale of 
    such property shall take place on terms settled between the parties.
 

It does not, of 
    itself, create any interest in or charge on such property.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>55</number> Rights and 
    liabilities of buyer and seller.—In 
    the absence of a contract to the contrary, the buyer and the seller of 
    immoveable property respectively are subject to the liabilities, and have 
    the rights, mentioned in the rules next following, or such of them as are 
    applicable to the property sold:—
 <section>

<number>1</number> The seller is 
    bound—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
        to disclose to the buyer any material defect in the property 

    1[or in the 
    seller’s title thereto] of which the seller is, and the buyer is not, aware, 
    and which the buyer could not with ordinary care discover;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     to 
    produce to the buyer on his request for examination all documents of title 
    relating to the property which are in the seller’s possession or power;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>     to 
    answer to the best of his information all relevant questions put to him by 
    the buyer in respect to the property or the title thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>     on 
    payment or tender of the amount due in respect of the price, to execute a 
    proper conveyance of the property when the buyer tenders it to him for 
    execution at a proper time and place;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>     
    between the date of the contract of sale and the delivery of the property, 
    to take as much care of the property and all documents of title relating 
    thereto which are in his possession as an owner of ordinary prudence would 
    take of such property and documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>     to 
    give, on being so required, the buyer, or such person as he directs, such 
    possession of the property as its nature admits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>     to 
    pay all public charges and rent accrued due in respect of the property up to 
    the date of the sale, the interest on all encumbrances on such property due 
    on such date, and, except where the property is sold subject to 
    encumbrances, to discharge all encumbrances  on  the property then existing.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> The seller shall 
    be deemed to contract with the buyer that the interest which the seller 
    professes to transfer to the buyer subsists and that he has power to 
    transfer the same:
 

Provided that, where 
    the sale is made by a person in a fiduciary character, he shall be deemed to 
    contract with the buyer that the seller has done no act whereby the property 
    is encumbered or whereby he is hindered from transferring it.
 

The benefit of the 
    contract mentioned in this rule shall be annexed to, and shall go with, the 
    interest of the transferee as such, and may be enforced by every person in 
    whom that interest is for the whole or any part thereof from time to time 
    vested.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Where the whole 
    of the purchase-money has been paid to the seller, he is also bound to 
    deliver to the buyer all documents of title relating to the property which 
    are in the seller’s possession or power :
 

Provided that, (a) 
    where the seller retains any part of the property comprised in such 
    documents, he is entitled to retain them all, and, (b) where the whole of 
    such property is sold to different buyers, the buye of the lot of greatest 
    value is entitled to such documents.  But in case (a) the seller, and in 
    case (b) the buyer, of the lot of greatest value, is bound, upon every 
    reasonable request by the buyer, or by any of the other buyers, as the case 
    may be, and at the cost of the person making the request, to produce the 
    said documents and furnish such true copies thereof or extracts therefrom as 
    he may require; and in the meantime, the seller, or the buyer of the lot of 
    greatest value, as the case may be, shall keep the said documents safe, 
    uncancelled and undefaced, unless prevented from so doing by fire or other 
    inevitable accident.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The seller is 
    entitled—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     to 
    the rents and profits of the property till the ownership thereof passes to 
    the buyer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
        where the ownership of the property has passed to the buyer before 
    payment of the whole of the purchase-money, to a charge upon the property in 
    the hands of the buyer, 

    1[any transferee 
    without consideration or any transferee with notice of the non-payment], for 
    the amount of the purchase-money, or any part thereof remaining unpaid, and 
    for interest on such amount or part 

    1[from the date on 
    which possession has been delivered].
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>5</number> The buyer is 
    bound—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     to 
    disclose to the seller any fact as to the nature or extent of the seller’s 
    interest in the property of which the buyer is aware, but of which he has 
    reason to believe that the seller is not aware, and which materially 
    increases the value of such interest;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     to 
    pay or tender, at the time and place of completing the sale, the 
    purchase-money to the seller or such person as he directs: provided that, 
    where the property is sold free from encumbrances, the buyer may retain out 
    of the purchase-money the amount of any encumbrances on the property 
    existing at the date of the sale, and shall pay the amount so retained to 
    the persons entitled thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>     
    where the ownership of the property has passed to the buyer, to bear any 
    loss arising from the destruction, injury or decrease in value of the 
    property not caused by the seller;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>     
    where the ownership of the property has passed to the buyer, as between 
    himself and the seller, to pay all public charges and rent which may become 
    payable in respect of the property, the principal moneys due on any 
    encumbrances subject to which the property is sold, and the interest thereon 
    afterwards accruing due.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>6</number> The buyer is 
    entitled—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     
    where the ownership of the property has passed to him, to the benefit of any 
    improvement in, or increase in value of, the property, and to the rents and 
    profits thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
        unless he has improperly declined to accept delivery of the property, to 
    a charge on the property, as against the seller and all persons claiming 
    under him, 

    2[* * *] to the 
    extent of the seller’s interest in the property, for the amount of any 
    purchase-money properly paid by the buyer in anticipation of the delivery 
    and for interest on such amount; and, when he properly declines to accept 
    the delivery, also for the earnest (if any) and for the costs (if any) 
    awarded to him of a suit to compel specific performance of the contract or 
    to obtain a decree for its rescission.
 

An omission to make 
    such disclosures as are mentioned in this section, paragraph (1), clause 
    (a), and paragraph (5), clause (a), is fraudulent.
 

 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>56</number> 
    Marshalling by subsequent purchaser.—If the owner of two or more 
    properties mortgages them to one person and then sells one or more of the 
    properties to another person, the buyer is, in the absence of a contract to 
    the contrary, entitled to have the mortgaged-debt satisfied out of the 
    property or properties not sold to him, so far as the same will extend, but 
    not so as to prejudice the rights of the mortgagee or persons claiming under 
    him or of any other person who has for consideration acquired an interest in 
    any of the properties.]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>57</number> Provision by 
    Court for encumbrances and sale freed therefrom.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Where immoveable property subject to any encumbrances, whether immediately 
    payable or not, is sold by the court or in execution of a decree, or out of 
    court, the court may, if it thinks fit, on the application of any party to 
    the sale, direct or allow payment into Court,—
 <subsection>

<number>1</number> in case of an 
    annual or monthly sum charged on the property, or of a capital sum charged 
    on a determinable interest in the property—of such amount as, when invested 
    in securities of the Central Government, the Court considers  will be 
    sufficient, by  means  of  the  interest  thereof,  to  keep  down  or  
    otherwise  provide  for  that charge, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>2</number> in any other case 
    of a capital sum charged on the property—of the amount sufficient to meet 
    the encumbrance and any interest due thereon.
 

But in either case 
    there shall also be paid into court such additional amount as the Court 
    considers will be sufficient to meet the contingency of further costs, 
    expenses and interest, and any other contingency, except depreciation of 
    investment, not exceeding one-tenth part of the original amount to be paid 
    in, unless the Court for special reasons (which it shall record) thinks fit 
    to require a large additional amount.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>b</number> Thereupon the 
    Court may, if it thinks fit, and after notice to the encumbrance, unless the 
    Court, for reasons to be recorded  in writing, thinks fit to dispense with 
    such notice, declare the property to be freed from the encumbrance, and make 
    any order for conveyance, or vesting order, proper for giving effect to the 
    sale, and give directions for the retention and investment of the money in 
    Court.
 </section><section>

<number>c</number> After notice 
    served on the persons interested in or entitled to the money or fund in 
    Court, the Court may direct payment or transfer thereof to the persons 
    entitled to receive or give a discharge for the same, and generally may give 
    directions respecting the application or distribution of the capital or 
    income thereof.
 </section><section>

<number>d</number> An appeal shall 
    lie from any declaration, order or direction under this section as if the 
    same were a decree.
 </section><section>

<number>e</number> In this section 
    “Court” means (1) a High Court in the exercise of its ordinary or 
    extraordinary original civil jurisdiction, (2) the Court of a District Judge 
    within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the property or any part 
    thereof is situate, (3) any other Court which the State Government may, from 
    time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
    competent to exercise the jurisdiction conferred by this section.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>58</number> “Mortgage”,  
    “mortgagor”,  “mortgagee”,  “mortgage-money” and “mortgage-deed”  defined.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    A mortgage is the transfer of an interest in specific immoveable property 
    for the purpose of securing the payment of money advanced or to be advanced 
    by way of loan, an existing or future debt, or the performance of an 
    engagement which may give rise to a pecuniary liability.
 

The transferor is 
    called a mortgagor, the transferee a mortgagee; the principal money and 
    interest of which payment is secured for the time being are called the 
    mortgage-money, and the instrument (if any) by which the transfer is 
    effected is called a mortgage-deed.
 </section><section>

<number>b</number> Simple 
    mortgage.—Where, without delivering possession of the mortgaged 
    property, the mortgagor binds himself personally to pay the mortgage-money, 
    and agrees, expressly or impliedly, that, in the event of his failing to pay 
    according to his contract, the mortgagee shall have a right to cause the 
    mortgaged property to be sold and the proceeds of sale to be applied, so far 
    as may be necessary, in payment of the mortgage-money, the transaction is 
    called a simple mortgage and the mortgagee a simple mortgagee.
 </section><section>

<number>c</number> Mortgage by 
    conditional sale.—Where, the mortgagor ostensibly sells the mortgaged 
    property—
 

on condition that on 
    default of payment of the mortgage-money on a certain date the sale shall 
    become absolute, or
 

on condition that on 
    such payment being made the sale shall become void, or
 

on condition that on 
    such payment being made the buyer shall transfer the property to the seller,
 

the transaction is 
    called mortgage by conditional sale and the mortgagee a mortgagee by 
    conditional sale:
 


    1[Provided 
    that no such transaction shall be deemed to be a mortgage, unless the 
    condition is embodied in the document which effects or purports to effect 
    the sale.]
 </section><section>

<number>d</number> Usufructuary mortgage.—Where the mortgagor 
    delivers possession 

    1[or 
    expressly or by implication binds himself to deliver possession] of the 
    mortgaged property to the mortgagee, and authorises him to retain such 
    possession until payment of the mortgage-money, and to receive the rents and 
    profits  accruing  from the property 

    2[or 
    any part of such rents and profits and to appropriate the same] in lieu of 
    interest, or in payment of the mortgage-money, or partly in lieu of interest
    

    3[or] 
    partly in payment of the mortgage-money, the transaction is called an 
    usufructuary mortgage and the mortgagee an usufructuary mortgagee. 

 </section><section>

<number>e</number> English 
    mortgage.—Where the mortgagor binds himself to repay the mortgage-money 
    on a certain date, and transfers the mortgaged property absolutely to the 
    mortgagee, but subject to a proviso that he will re-transfer it to the 
    mortgagor upon payment of the mortgage-money as agreed, the transaction is 
    called an English mortgage.
 


    4[(f) 
    Mortgage by deposit of title-deeds.—Where a person in any of the 
    following towns, namely, the towns of Calcutta, Madras, 

    5[and 
    Bombay], 

    6[* 
    * *] and in any other town7 
    
 which the 

    8[State 
    Government concerned] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify 
    in this behalf, delivers to a creditor or his agent documents of title to 
    immoveable property, with intent to create a security thereon, the 
    transaction is called a mortgage by deposit of title-deeds.
 </section><section>

<number>g</number> Anomalous 
    mortgage.—A mortgage which is not a simple mortgage, a mortgage by 
    conditional sale, an usufructuary mortgage, an English mortgage or a 
    mortgage by deposit of title-deeds within the meaning of this section is 
    called an anomalous mortgage.]
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>58</number> “Mortgage”,  
    “mortgagor”,  “mortgagee”,  “mortgage-money” and “mortgage-deed”  defined.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    A mortgage is the transfer of an interest in specific immoveable property 
    for the purpose of securing the payment of money advanced or to be advanced 
    by way of loan, an existing or future debt, or the performance of an 
    engagement which may give rise to a pecuniary liability.
 

The transferor is 
    called a mortgagor, the transferee a mortgagee; the principal money and 
    interest of which payment is secured for the time being are called the 
    mortgage-money, and the instrument (if any) by which the transfer is 
    effected is called a mortgage-deed.
 </section><section>

<number>b</number> Simple 
    mortgage.—Where, without delivering possession of the mortgaged 
    property, the mortgagor binds himself personally to pay the mortgage-money, 
    and agrees, expressly or impliedly, that, in the event of his failing to pay 
    according to his contract, the mortgagee shall have a right to cause the 
    mortgaged property to be sold and the proceeds of sale to be applied, so far 
    as may be necessary, in payment of the mortgage-money, the transaction is 
    called a simple mortgage and the mortgagee a simple mortgagee.
 </section><section>

<number>c</number> Mortgage by 
    conditional sale.—Where, the mortgagor ostensibly sells the mortgaged 
    property—
 

on condition that on 
    default of payment of the mortgage-money on a certain date the sale shall 
    become absolute, or
 

on condition that on 
    such payment being made the sale shall become void, or
 

on condition that on 
    such payment being made the buyer shall transfer the property to the seller,
 

the transaction is 
    called mortgage by conditional sale and the mortgagee a mortgagee by 
    conditional sale:
 


    1[Provided 
    that no such transaction shall be deemed to be a mortgage, unless the 
    condition is embodied in the document which effects or purports to effect 
    the sale.]
 </section><section>

<number>d</number> Usufructuary mortgage.—Where the mortgagor 
    delivers possession 

    1[or 
    expressly or by implication binds himself to deliver possession] of the 
    mortgaged property to the mortgagee, and authorises him to retain such 
    possession until payment of the mortgage-money, and to receive the rents and 
    profits  accruing  from the property 

    2[or 
    any part of such rents and profits and to appropriate the same] in lieu of 
    interest, or in payment of the mortgage-money, or partly in lieu of interest
    

    3[or] 
    partly in payment of the mortgage-money, the transaction is called an 
    usufructuary mortgage and the mortgagee an usufructuary mortgagee. 

 </section><section>

<number>e</number> English 
    mortgage.—Where the mortgagor binds himself to repay the mortgage-money 
    on a certain date, and transfers the mortgaged property absolutely to the 
    mortgagee, but subject to a proviso that he will re-transfer it to the 
    mortgagor upon payment of the mortgage-money as agreed, the transaction is 
    called an English mortgage.
 


    4[(f) 
    Mortgage by deposit of title-deeds.—Where a person in any of the 
    following towns, namely, the towns of Calcutta, Madras, 

    5[and 
    Bombay], 

    6[* 
    * *] and in any other town7 
    
 which the 

    8[State 
    Government concerned] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify 
    in this behalf, delivers to a creditor or his agent documents of title to 
    immoveable property, with intent to create a security thereon, the 
    transaction is called a mortgage by deposit of title-deeds.
 </section><section>

<number>g</number> Anomalous 
    mortgage.—A mortgage which is not a simple mortgage, a mortgage by 
    conditional sale, an usufructuary mortgage, an English mortgage or a 
    mortgage by deposit of title-deeds within the meaning of this section is 
    called an anomalous mortgage.]
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>59A</number> 
    References to mortgagors and mortgagees to include persons deriving title 
    from them.—Unless otherwise expressly provided, references in this 
    Chapter to mortgagors and mortgagees shall be deemed to include references 
    to persons deriving title from them respectively.]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>60</number> 
    Right of mortgagor to redeem.—At 
    any time after the principal money has become 

    1[due], 
    the mortgagor has a right, on payment or tender, at a proper time and place, 
    of the mortgage-money, to require the mortgagee 
<section><number>a</number> to deliver 


    2[to 
    the mortgagor the mortgage-deed and all documents relating to the mortgaged 
    property which are in the possession or power of the mortgagee], (b) where 
    the mortgagee is in possession of the mortgaged property, to deliver 
    possession thereof to the mortgagor, and 
    (c) at the cost of the mortgagor either to re-transfer the mortgaged 
    property to him or to such third person as he may direct, or to execute and 
    (where the mortgage has been effected by a registered instrument) to 
    have registered an acknowledgement in writing that any right in derogation 
    of his interest transferred to the mortgagee has been extinguished:
 

Provided that the right conferred by this section has not 
    been extinguished by act of the parties or by 

    3[decree] 
    of a Court.
 

The right conferred 
    by this section is called a right to redeem and a suit to enforce it is 
    called a suit for redemption.
 

Nothing in this 
    section shall be deemed to render invalid any provision to the effect that, 
    if the time fixed for payment of the principal money has been allowed to 
    pass or no such time has been fixed, the mortgagee shall be entitled to 
    reasonable notice before payment or tender of such money.
 
 


    Redemption of portion of mortgaged property.—Nothing 
    in this section shall entitle a person interested in a  share only of the 
    mortgaged property to redeem his own share only, on payment of a 
    proportionate part of the amount remaining due on the mortgage, except
    

    4[only] 
    where a mortgagee, or, if there are more mortgagees than one, all such 
    mortgagees, has or have acquired, in whole or in part, the share of a 
    mortgagor.
 

 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>60A</number> 
    Obligation to transfer to third party instead of re-transference to 
    mortgagor.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a mortgagor is entitled to redemption, then, on the 
    fulfilment of any conditions on the fulfilment of which he would be entitled 
    to require a re-transfer, he may require the mortgagee, instead of 
    re-transferring the property, to assign the mortgage-debt and transfer the 
    mortgaged property to such third person as the mortgagor may direct; and the 
    mortgagee shall be bound to assign and transfer accordingly.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The rights 
    conferred by this section belong to and may be enforced by the mortgagor or 
    by any encumbrancer notwithstanding an intermediate encumbrance; but the 
    requisition of any encumbrance shall prevail over a requisition of the 
    mortgagor and, as between encumbrancers, the requisition of a prior 
    encumbrancer shall prevail over that of a subsequent encumbrancer.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The provisions of 
    this section do not apply in the case of a mortgagee who is or has been in 
    possession.
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>60B</number> Right to 
    inspection and production of documents.—A 
    mortgagor, as long as his right of redemption subsists, shall be entitled  
    at  all reasonable times, at his request and at his own cost, and on payment 
    of the mortgagee’s costs and expenses in this behalf, to inspect and make 
    copies or abstracts of, or extracts from, documents of title relating to the 
    mortgaged property which are in the custody or power of the mortgagee.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>61</number> 
    Right to redeem separately or simultaneously.—A mortgagor who has 
    executed two or more mortgages in favour of the same mortgagee shall, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, when the principal money of any two 
    or more of the mortgages has become due, be entitled to redeem any one such 
    mortgage separately, or any two or more of such mortgages together.]
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>62</number> 
    Right of usufructuary mortgagor to recover possession.—In 
    the case of a usufructuary mortgage, the mortgagor has a right to recover 
    possession of the property 

    1[together 
    with the mortgage-deed and all documents relating to the mortgaged property 
    which are in the possession or power of the mortgagee],—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    where the mortgagee is authorized to pay himself the mortgage-money from the 
    rents and profits of the property,—when such money is paid;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> 
        where the mortgagee is authorised to pay himself from such rents and 
    profits 

    2[or any part 
    thereof a part only of the mortgage-money],—when the term (if any) 
    prescribed for the payment of the mortgage-money has expired and the 
    mortgagor pays or tenders to the mortgagee 

    3[the 
    mortgage-money or the balance thereof] or deposits it in Court as 
    hereinafter provided.
 

 
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>63</number> Accession to 
    mortgaged property.—Where 
    mortgaged property in possession of the mortgagee has, during the 
    continuance of the mortgage, received any accession, the mortgagor, upon 
    redemption shall, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, be entitled 
    as against the mortgagee to such accession.
 


    Accession acquired in virtue of transferred ownership.—Where 
    such accession has been acquired at the expense of the mortgagee, and is 
    capable of separate possession or enjoyment without detriment to the 
    principal property, the mortgagor desiring to take the accession must pay to 
    the mortgagee the expense of acquiring it.  If such separate possession or 
    enjoyment is not possible, the accession must be delivered with the 
    property; the mortgagor being liable, in the case of an acquisition 
    necessary to preserve the property from destruction, forfeiture or sale, or 
    made with his assent, to pay the proper cost thereof, as an addition to the 
    principal money, 

    1[with 
    interest at the same rate as is payable on the principal, or, where no such 
    rate is fixed, at the rate of nine per cent per annum].
 

In the case last 
    mentioned the profits, if any, arising from the accession shall be credited 
    to the mortgagor.
 

Where the mortgage is 
    usufructuary and the accession has been acquired at the expense of the 
    mortgagee, the profits, if any, arising from the accession shall, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, be set off against interest, if any, 
    payable on the money so expended.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>63A</number> 
    Improvements  to mortgaged property.—
<section><number>1</number> Where mortgaged property in 
    possession of the mortgagee has, during the  continuance of the mortgage, 
    been improved, the mortgagor, upon redemption, shall, in the absence of a 
    contract to the contrary, be entitled to the improvement; and the mortgagor 
    shall not, save only in cases provided for in sub-section (2), be liable to 
    pay the cost thereof.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Where any such 
    improvement was effected at the cost of the mortgagee and was necessary to 
    preserve the property from destruction or deterioration or was necessary to 
    prevent the security from becoming insufficient, or was made in compliance 
    with the lawful order of any public servant or public authority, the 
    mortgagor shall, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, be liable to 
    pay the proper cost thereof as an addition to the principal money with 
    interest at the same rate as is payable on the principal, or, where no such 
    rate is fixed, at the rate of nine per cent per annum, and the profits, if 
    any, accruing by reason of the improvement shall be credited to the 
    mortgagor.]
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>64</number> 
    Renewal of  mortgaged  lease.—Where 
    the mortgaged   property   is  a  lease 

    1[***], and the mortgagee obtains a renewal of the lease, the mortgagor, upon 
    redemption, shall, in the absence of a contract by him to the contrary, have 
    the benefit of the new lease.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>65</number> Implied contracts 
    by mortgagor.—In 
    the absence of a contract to the contrary, the mortgagor shall be deemed to 
    contract with the mortgagee,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     
    that the interest which the mortgagor professes to transfer to the mortgagee 
    subsists, and that the mortgagor has power to transfer the same;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     
    that the mortgagor will defend, or, if the mortgagee be in possession of the 
    mortgaged property, enable him to defend, the mortgagor’s title thereto;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     
    that the mortgagor will, so long as the mortgagee is not in possession of 
    the mortgaged property, pay all public charges accruing due in respect of 
    the property;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> 
        and, where the mortgaged property is a lease 

    1[***], that the 
    rent payable under  the lease, the conditions contained therein, and the 
    contracts binding on the lessee have been paid, performed and observed down 
    to the commencement of the mortgage; and that the mortgagor will, so long as 
    the security exists and the mortgagee is not in possession of the mortgaged 
    property, pay the rent reserved by the lease, or, if the lease be renewed, 
    the renewed lease, perform the conditions contained therein and observe the 
    contracts binding on the lessee, and indemnify the mortgagee against all the 
    claims sustained by reason of the non-payment of the said rent or the 
    non-performance or non-observance of the said conditions and contracts;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     
    and, where the mortgage is a second or subsequent encumbrance on the 
    property, that the mortgagor will pay the interest from time to time 
    accruing due on each prior encumbrance as and when it becomes due, and will 
    at the proper time discharge the principal money due on such prior 
    incumbrance.
 


    2[***]
 

The benefit of the 
    contracts mentioned in this section shall be annexed to and shall go with 
    the interest of the mortgagee as such, and may be enforced by every person 
    in whom that interest is for the whole or any part thereof from time to time 
    vested.
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>65A</number> 
    Mortgagor’s power to lease.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section 
    (2), a mortgagor, while lawfully in possession of the mortgaged property, 
    shall have power to make leases thereof which shall be binding on the 
    mortgagee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) 
    Every such lease shall be such as would be made in the ordinary course of 
    management of the property concerned, and in accordance with any local law, 
    custom or usage,
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> 
    Every such lease shall reserve the best rent that can reasonably be 
    obtained, and no premium shall be paid or promised and no rent shall be 
    payable in advance,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> No 
    such lease shall contain a covenant for renewal,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
    Every such lease shall take effect from a date not later than six months 
    from the date on which it is made,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> In 
    the case of a lease of buildings, whether leased with or without the land on 
    which they stand, the duration of the lease shall in no case exceed three 
    years, and the lease shall contain a covenant  for payment of the rent and a 
    condition of re-entry on the rent not being paid with a time therein 
    specified.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (1) apply only if and as far as a contrary 
    intention is not expressed in the mortgage-deed; and the provisions of 
    sub-section (2) may be varied or extended by the mortgage-deed and, as so 
    varied and extended, shall, as far as may be, operate in like manner and 
    with all like incidents, effects and consequences, as if such variations or 
    extensions were contained in that sub-section.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>65A</number> 
    Mortgagor’s power to lease.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section 
    (2), a mortgagor, while lawfully in possession of the mortgaged property, 
    shall have power to make leases thereof which shall be binding on the 
    mortgagee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) 
    Every such lease shall be such as would be made in the ordinary course of 
    management of the property concerned, and in accordance with any local law, 
    custom or usage,
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> 
    Every such lease shall reserve the best rent that can reasonably be 
    obtained, and no premium shall be paid or promised and no rent shall be 
    payable in advance,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> No 
    such lease shall contain a covenant for renewal,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
    Every such lease shall take effect from a date not later than six months 
    from the date on which it is made,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> In 
    the case of a lease of buildings, whether leased with or without the land on 
    which they stand, the duration of the lease shall in no case exceed three 
    years, and the lease shall contain a covenant  for payment of the rent and a 
    condition of re-entry on the rent not being paid with a time therein 
    specified.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (1) apply only if and as far as a contrary 
    intention is not expressed in the mortgage-deed; and the provisions of 
    sub-section (2) may be varied or extended by the mortgage-deed and, as so 
    varied and extended, shall, as far as may be, operate in like manner and 
    with all like incidents, effects and consequences, as if such variations or 
    extensions were contained in that sub-section.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Waste by mortgagor in possession.—A 
    mortgagor in possession of the mortgaged property is not liable to the 
    mortgagee for allowing the property to deteriorate; but he must not commit 
    any act which is destructive or permanently injurious thereto, if the 
    security  is  insufficient  or   will be rendered insufficient by such act.
 

    Explanation.—A 
    security is insufficient within the meaning of this section unless the value 
    of the mortgaged property exceeds by one-third, or, if consisting of  
    buildings, exceeds by one-half, the amount for the time being due on the 
    mortgage.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    Right to fore-closure or sale.—In 
    the absence of a contract to the contrary, the mortgagee has, at any time 
    after the mortgage-money has become 

    1[due] 
    to him, and before a decree has been made for the redemption of the 
    mortgaged property, or the mortgage-money has been paid or deposited as 
    hereinafter provided, a right to obtain from the Court 

    2[a 
    decree] that the mortgagor shall be absolutely debarred of his right to 
    redeem the property, or 

    2[a 
    decree] that the property be sold.
 
A suit 
    to obtain 

    2[a 
    decree] that a mortgagor shall be absolutely debarred of his right to redeem 
    the mortgaged property is called a suit for foreclosure.
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed—
 

    3[
<section><number>a</number>     to 
    authorise any mortgagee other than a mortgagee by conditional sale or a 
    mortgagee under an anomalous mortgage by the terms of which he is entitled 
    to foreclose, to institute a suit for foreclosure, or an usufructuary 
    mortgagee as such or a mortgagee by conditional sale as such to institute a 
    suit for sale; or]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     to authorise a 
    mortgagor who holds the mortgagee’s rights as his trustee or legal 
    representative, and who may sue for a sale of the property, to institute a 
    suit for foreclosure; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     to authorise the 
    mortgagee of a railway, canal, or other work in the maintenance of which the 
    public are interested, to institute a suit for foreclosure or sale; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     to authorise a 
    person interested in part only of the mortgage-money to institute a suit 
    relating only to a corresponding part of the mortgaged property, unless the 
    mortgagees have, with the consent of the mortgagor, severed their interests 
    under the mortgage.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>67A</number> 
    Mortgagee when bound to bring one suit on several mortgages.—A mortgagee 
    who holds two or more mortgages executed by the same mortgagor in respect of 
    each of which he has a right to obtain the same kind of decree under section 
    67, and who sues to obtain such decree on any one of the mortgages, shall, 
    in the absence of a contract to the contrary, be bound to sue on all the 
    mortgages in respect of which the mortgage-money has become due.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>68</number> 
    Right to sue for mortgage-money.—
<section><number>1</number> The mortgagee has a right to sue 
    for the mortgage-money in the following cases and no others, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     where the 
    mortgagor binds himself to repay the same;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     where, by any 
    cause other than the wrongful act or default of the mortgagor or mortgagee, 
    the mortgaged property is wholly or partially destroyed or the security is 
    rendered insufficient within the meaning of section 66, and the mortgagee 
    has given the mortgagor a reasonable opportunity of providing further 
    security enough to render the whole security sufficient, and the mortgagor 
    has failed to do so;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>     where the 
    mortgagee is deprived of the whole or part of his security by or in 
    consequence of the wrongful act or default of the mortgagor;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>     where, the 
    mortgagee being entitled to possession of the mortgaged property, the 
    mortgagor fails to deliver the same to him, or to secure the possession 
    thereof to him without disturbance by the mortgagor or any person claiming 
    under a title superior to that of the mortgagor :
 

    Provided that, in the case referred to in clause (a), a transferee from the 
    mortgagor or from his legal representative shall not be liable to be sued 
    for the mortgage-money.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a suit is brought under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (1), 
    the Court may, at its discretion, stay the suit and all proceedings therein, 
    notwithstanding any contract to the  contrary, until the mortgagee has 
    exhausted all his available remedies against the mortgaged property or what 
    remains of it, unless the mortgagee abandons his security and, if necessary, 
    re-transfers the mortgaged property.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Power of sale when valid.—1[
<section><number>1</number>]


    2[3[***] A mortgagee, or any person acting on his behalf, shall, subject to the 
    provisions of this section have power to sell or concur in selling the 
    mortgaged property or any part thereof, in default of payment of the 
    mortgage-money, without the intervention of the court, in the following 
    cases and in no others, namely:—]
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     where the mortgage 
    is an English mortgage, and neither the mortgagor nor the mortgagee is a 
    Hindu, Muhammadan or Buddhist 

    4[or a member of 
    any other race, sect, tribe or class from time to time specified in this 
    behalf by 

    5[the State 
    Government], in the Official Gazette];
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     where 


    6[a power of sale 
    without the intervention of the court is expressly conferred on the 
    mortgagee by the mortgage-deed and] the mortgagee is 

    7[the Government];
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>     where 


    6[a power of sale 
    without the intervention of the court is expressly conferred on the 
    mortgagee by the mortgage-deed and] the mortgaged property or any part 
    thereof 

    8[was, on the date 
    of the execution of the mortgage-deed], situate within the towns of 
    Calcutta, Madras, Bombay, 

    9[***] 


    10[or in any other  
    town11
      or area which the 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
    this behalf.]
 

    12[(2)]
    

    13[***] No such power shall be exercised unless and until—
 

    14[(a)]     notice 
    in writing requiring payment of the principal money has been served on the 
    mortgagor, or on one of several mortgagors, and default has been made in 
    payment of the principal money, or of part thereof, for three months after 
    such service; or
 

    15[(b)]     some 
    interest under the mortgage amounting at least to five hundred rupees is in 
    arrear and unpaid for three months after becoming due.
 

    16[(3)] 
    When a sale has been made in professed exercise of such a power, the title 
    of the purchaser shall not be impeachable on the ground that no case had 
    arisen to authorise the sale, or that due notice was not given, or that the 
    power was otherwise improperly or irregularly exercised; but any person 
    damnified by an unauthorised or improper or irregular exercise or the power 
    shall have his remedy in damages against the person exercising the power.
 

    17[(4)] 
    The money which is received by the mortgagee, arising from the sale, after 
    discharge of prior encumbrances, if any, to which the sale is not made 
    subject, or after payment into Court under section 57 of a sum to meet any 
    prior encumbrance, shall, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, be 
    held by him in trust to be applied by him, first, in payment of  all costs, 
    charges and expenses properly incurred by him as incident to the sale or any 
    attempted sale; and, secondly, in discharge of the mortgage-money and costs 
    and other money, if any, due under the mortgage; and the residue of the 
    money so received shall be paid to the person entitled to the mortgaged 
    property, or authorised to give receipts for the proceeds of the sale 
    thereof.
 

    18[(5) 
    Nothing in this section or in section 69A applies to powers conferred before 
    the first day of July, 1882.]
 

    19[***]
 



























 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>69A</number> 
    Appointment of receiver.—
<section><number>1</number> A mortgagee having the right to exercise a 
    power of sale under section 69 shall, subject to the provisions of 
    sub-section (2), be entitled to appoint, by writing signed by him or on his 
    behalf, a receiver of the income of the mortgaged property or any part 
    thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    person who has been named in the mortgage-deed and is willing and able to 
    act as receiver may be appointed by the mortgagee.
 
If no 
    person has been so named, or if all persons named are unable or unwilling 
    to act, or are dead, the mortgagee may appoint any person to whose 
    appointment the mortgagor agrees; failing such agreement, the mortgagee 
    shall be entitled to apply to the Court for the appointment of a receiver, 
    and any person appointed by the Court shall be deemed to have been duly 
    appointed by the mortgagee.
 
A 
    receiver may at any time be removed by writing signed by or on behalf of the 
    mortgagee and the mortgagor, or by the court on application made by either 
    party and on due cause shown.
 
A 
    vacancy in the office of receiver may be filled in accordance with the 
    provisions of this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    receiver appointed under the powers conferred by this section shall be 
    deemed to be the agent of the mortgagor; and the mortgagor shall be solely 
    responsible for the receiver’s act or defaults, unless the mortgage-deed 
    otherwise provides or unless such acts or defaults are due to the improper 
    intervention of the mortgagee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    receiver shall have power to demand and recover all the income of which he 
    is appointed receiver, by suit, execution or otherwise, in the name either 
    of the mortgagor or of the mortgagee to the full extent of the interest 
    which the mortgagor could dispose of, and to give valid receipts accordingly 
    for the same, and to exercise any powers which may have been delegated to 
    him by the mortgagee, in accordance with the provisions of this section.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    person paying money to the receiver shall not be concerned to inquire if the 
    appointment of the receiver was valid or not.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    receiver shall be entitled to retain out of any money received by him, for 
    his remuneration, and  in  satisfaction of all costs, charges and expenses 
    incurred by him as receiver, a commission at such rate not exceeding five 
    per cent, on the gross amount of all money received as is specified in his 
    appointment, and, if no rate is so specified, then at the rate of five per 
    cent. on that gross amount, or at such other rate as the court thinks fit to 
    allow, on application made by him for that purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    receiver shall, if so directed in writing by the mortgagee, insure to the 
    extent, if any, to which the mortgagee might have insured, and keep insured 
    against loss or damage by fire, out of the money received by him, the 
    mortgaged property or any part thereof being of an insurable nature.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act as to the application of insurance 
    money, the receiver shall apply all money received by him as follows, 
    namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>     in discharge of 
    all rents, taxes, land revenue, rates and outgoings whatever affecting the 
    mortgaged property;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>     in keeping down 
    all annual sums or other payments, and the interest on all principal sums, 
    having priority to the mortgage in right whereof he is receiver;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>     in payment of 
    his commission, and of the premiums on fire, life or other insurances,  if 
    any,  properly payable under  the mortgage-deed or under this Act, and the 
    cost of executing necessary or proper repairs directed in writing by the 
    mortgagee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>     in payment of the 
    interest falling due under the mortgage;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>     in or towards 
    discharge of the principal money, if so directed in writing by the 
    mortgagee,
 
and 
    shall  pay  the residue, of any, of the money received by him to the person 
    who, but for the possession of the receiver, would have been entitled to 
    receive the income of which he is appointed receiver, or who is otherwise 
    entitled to the mortgaged property.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (1) apply only if and as far as a contrary 
    intention is not expressed in the mortgage-deed; and the provisions of 
    sub-sections (3) to (8) inclusive may be varied or extended by the 
    mortgage-deed; and, as so varied or extended, shall, as far as may be, 
    operate in like manner and with all the like incidents, effects and 
    consequences, as if such variations or extensions were contained in the said 
    sub-sections.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> 
    Application may be made, without the institution of a suit, to the court for 
    its opinion, advice or direction on any present question respecting the 
    management or administration of the mortgaged property, other than questions 
    of difficulty or importance not proper in the opinion of the court for 
    summary disposal.  A copy of such application shall be served upon, and the 
    hearing thereof may be attended by, such of the persons interested in the 
    application as the Court may think fit.
 
The 
    costs of every application under this sub-section shall be in the discretion 
    of the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> In 
    this section, “the Court” means the Court which would have jurisdiction in a 
    suit to enforce the mortgage.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Accession to mortgaged property.—If, 
    after the date of a mortgage, any accession is made to the mortgaged 
    property, the mortgagee, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, 
    shall, for the purposes of the security, be entitled to such accession.
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A 
      mortgages to B a certain field bordering on a river.  The field is 
      increased by alluvion.  For the purposes of his security, B is 
      entitled to the increase.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A 
      mortgages a certain plot of building land to B and afterwards 
      erects a house on the plot.  For the purposes of his security, B is 
      entitled to the house as well as the plot.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Renewal of  mortgaged  lease.—When  
    the  mortgaged  property is a lease 

    1[***] and the mortgagor obtains a renewal of the lease, the mortgagee, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, shall, for the purposes of the 
    security, be entitled to the new lease.
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Right of mortgagee in possession.—1[A 
    mortgagee] may spend such money as is necessary—
 

    2[***]
 <section>
<number>b</number>     for 

    3[the preservation 
    of the mortgaged property] from destruction, forfeiture or sale;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     for supporting the 
    mortgagor’s title to the property;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     for making his own 
    title thereto good against the mortgagor; and
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     when the mortgaged 
    property is a renewable lease-hold, for the renewal of the lease,
 
and 
    may, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, add such money to the 
    principal money, at the rate of interest payable on the principal, and, 
    where no such rate is fixed, at the rate of nine per cent. per annum:
 

    4[Provided 
    that the expenditure of money by the mortgagee under clause (b) or clause 
    (c) shall not be deemed to be necessary unless the mortgagor has been called 
    upon and has failed to take proper and timely steps to preserve the property 
    or to support the title.]
 
Where 
    the property is by its nature insurable, the mortgagee may also, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, insure and keep insured against loss 
    or damage by fire the whole or any part of such property, and the premiums 
    paid for any such insurance shall be 

    5[added 
    to the principal money with interest at the same rate as is payable on the 
    principal money or, where no such rate is fixed, at the rate of nine per 
    cent. per annum].  But the amount of such insurance shall not exceed the 
    amount specified in this behalf   in the mortgage-deed or (if no such amount 
    is therein specified) two-thirds of the amount that would be required in 
    case of total destruction to reinstate the property insured.
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to authorise the mortgagee to insure when an 
    insurance of the property is kept up by or on behalf of the mortgagor to the 
    amount in which the mortgagee is hereby authorised to insure.
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>73</number> 
    Right to proceeds of revenue sale or compensation on acquisition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the mortgaged property or any part thereof or any interest therein is 
    sold owing to failure to pay arrears of revenue or other charges of a public 
    nature or rent due in respect of such property, and such failure did not 
    arise from any default of the mortgagee, the mortgagee shall be entitled to 
    claim payment of the mortgage-money, in whole or in part, out of any surplus 
    of the sale-proceeds remaining after payment of the arrears and of all 
    charges and deductions directed by law.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the mortgaged property or any part thereof or any interest therein is 
    acquired under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894); or any other 
    enactment for the time being in force providing for the compulsory 
    acquisition of immoveable property, the mortgagee shall be entitled to claim 
    payment of the mortgage-money, in whole or in part, out of the amount due to 
    the mortgagor as compensation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Such claims shall prevail against all other claims except those of prior 
    encumbrancers, and may be enforced notwithstanding  that  the principal 
    money on the mortgage has not become due.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> 
    Right of subsequent mortgagee to pay off prior mortgagee.—[Rep. 
    by the Transfer of Property (Amendment) Act, 1929 (20 of 1929), sec. 39.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Rights of mesne mortgagee against prior and subsequent mortgagees.—[Rep. 
    by the Transfer of Property (Amendment) Act, 1929 (20 of 1929), sec. 39.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Liabilities of mortgagee in possession.—When, 
    during the continuance of the mortgage, the mortgagee takes possession of 
    the mortgaged property,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     he must manage the 
    property as a person of ordinary prudence would manage it if it were his 
    own;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     he must use his 
    best endeavours to collect the rents and profits thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     he must, in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, out of the income of the property, 
    pay the Government revenue, all other charges of a public nature 


    1[and all rent] 
    accruing due in respect thereof during such possession, and any arrears of 
    rent in default of payment of which the property may be summarily sold;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     he must in the 
    absence of a contract to the contrary, make such necessary repairs of the 
    property as he can pay for out of the rents and profits thereof after 
    deducting from such rents and profits the payments mentioned in clause (c) 
    and the interest on the principal money;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     he must not commit 
    any act which is destructive or permanently injurious to the property;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>     where he has 
    insured the whole or any part of the property against loss or damage by 
    fire, he must, in case of such loss or damage, apply any money which he 
    actually receives under the policy or so much thereof as may be necessary, 
    in reinstating the property, or, if the mortgagor so directs, in reduction 
    or discharge of the mortgage-money;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>     he must keep 
    clear, full and accurate accounts of all sums received and spent by him as 
    mortgagee, and, at any time during the continuance of the mortgage, give the 
    mortgagor, at his request and cost, true copies of such accounts and of the 
    vouchers by which they are supported;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>     his receipts from 
    the mortgaged property, or, where such property is personally occupied by 
    him, a fair occupation-rent in respect thereof, shall, after deducting the 
    expenses 

    1[properly incurred 
    for the management of the property and the collection of rents and profits 
    and the other expenses] mentioned in clauses (c) and (d), and interest 
    thereon, be debited against him in reduction of the amount (if any) from 
    time to time due to him on account of interest 

    2[***] and, so 
    far as such receipts exceed any interest due, in reduction or discharge of 
    the mortgage-money; the surplus, if any, shall be paid to the mortgagor;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>     when the mortgagor 
    tenders, or deposits in the manner hereinafter provided, the amount for the 
    time being due on the mortgage, the mortgagee must, notwithstanding the 
    provisions in the other clauses of this section, account for his 


    3[***] receipts 
    from the mortgaged property from the date of the tender or from the earliest 
    time when he could take such amount out of court, as the case may be 


    1[and shall not be 
    entitled to deduct any amount therefrom on account of any expenses incurred 
    after such date or time in connection with the mortgaged property].
 
Loss 
    occasioned by his default.—If 
    the mortgagee fails to perform any of the duties imposed upon him by this 
    section, he may, when accounts are taken in pursuance of a decree made under 
    this Chapter, be debited with the loss, if any, occasioned by such failure.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Receipts in lieu of interest.—Nothing 
    in section 76, clauses (b), (d), (g) and (h), applies to cases where there 
    is a contract between the mortgagee and the mortgagor that the receipts from 
    the mortgaged property shall, so long as the mortgagee is in possession of 
    the property, be taken in lieu of interest on the principal money, or in 
    lieu of such interest and defined portions of the principal.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Postponement of prior mortgagee.—Where, 
    through the fraud, misrepresentation or gross neglect of prior mortgagee, 
    another person has been induced to advance money on the security of the 
    mortgaged property, the prior mortgagee shall be postponed to the subsequent 
    mortgagee.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Mortgage to secure uncertain amount when maximum is expressed.—If 
    a mortgage made to secure future advances, the performance of an engagement 
    or the balance of a running account, expresses the maximum to be secured 
    thereby, a subsequent mortgage of the same property shall, if made with 
    notice of the prior mortgage, be postponed to the prior mortgage in respect 
    of all advances or debits not exceeding the maximum, though made or allowed 
    with notice of the subsequent mortgage.
 
 

Illustration
 
A 
      mortgages  Sultanpur to his bankers, B &amp; Co., to secure the balance 
      of his account with them to the extent of Rs.10,000. A then 
      mortgages Sultanpur to C, to secure Rs.10,000, C having 
      notice of the mortgage to B &amp; Co., and C gives notice to 
      B &amp; Co.  of the second mortgage.  At the date of the second mortgage, 
      the balance due to B &amp; Co. does not exceed Rs. 5,000. B &amp; 
Co. 
      subsequently advance to  A  sums making the balance of the account 
      against him exceed the sum of Rs.10,000.  B &amp; 
Co. 
      are entitled, to the extent of Rs.10,000, to priority over C.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Tacking abolished.—[Rep. 
    by the Transfer of Property (Amendment) Act, 1929 (20 of 1929), sec. 41.]
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>81</number> 
    Marshalling, securities.—If the owner of two or more properties 
    mortgages them to one person and then mortgages one or more of the 
    properties to another person, the subsequent mortgagee is, in the absence of 
    a contract to the contrary, entitled to have the prior mortgage-debt 
    satisfied out of the property or properties not mortgaged to him, so far as 
    the same will extend, but not so as to prejudice the rights of the prior 
    mortgagee or of any other person who has for consideration acquired an 
    interest in any of the properties.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Contribution to mortgage-debt.—1[Where 
    property subject to a mortgage belongs to two or more persons having 
    distinct and separate rights of ownership therein, the different shares in 
    or parts of such property owned by such persons are, in the absence of a 
    contract to the contrary, liable to contribute rateably to the debt secured 
    by the mortgage, and, for the purpose of determining the rate at which each 
    such share or part shall contribute, the value thereof shall be deemed to be 
    its value at the date of the mortgage after deduction of the amount of any 
    other mortgage or charge to which it may have been subject on that date.]
 
Where, 
    of  two properties belonging to the same owner, one is mortgaged to secure 
    one debt and then both are mortgaged to secure another debt, and the former 
    debt is paid out of the former property, each property is, in the absence of 
    a contract to the contrary, liable to contribute rateably to the latter debt 
    after deducting the amount of the former debt from the value of the property 
    out of which it has been paid.
 
Nothing 
    in this section applies to a property liable under section 81 to the claim 
    of the 

    2[subsequent] 
    mortgagee.
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Power to deposit in Court money due on mortgage.—At 
    any time after the principal money 

    1[payable 
    in respect of any mortgage has become due] and before a suit for redemption 
    of the mortgaged property is barred, the mortgagor, or any other person 
    entitled to institute such suit, may deposit, in any court in which he might 
    have instituted such suit, to the account of the mortgagee, the amount 
    remaining due on the mortgage.
 

    Right to money deposited by mortgagor.—The 
    court shall thereupon cause written notice of the deposit to be served on 
    the mortgagee, and the mortgagee may, on presenting a petition (verified in 
    manner prescribed by law2  
    for the verification of  plaints) stating the amount then due on the 
    mortgage, and his willingness to accept the money so deposited in full 
    discharge of such amount, and on depositing in the same Court the 
    mortgage-deed 

    3[and 
    all documents in his possession or power relating to the mortgaged 
    property], apply for and receive the money, and  the mortgage-deed, 


    4[and 
    all such other documents] so deposited shall be delivered to the mortgagor 
    or such other person as aforesaid.
 

    5[Where 
    the mortgagee is in possession of the mortgaged property, the court shall, 
    before paying to him the amount so deposited, direct him to deliver 
    possession thereof to the mortgagor and at the cost of the mortgagor either 
    to re-transfer the mortgaged property to the mortgagor or to such third 
    person as the mortgagor may direct or to execute and (where the mortgage has 
    been effected by a registered instrument) have registered an acknowledgement 
    in writing that any right in derogation of the mortgagor’s interest 
    transferred to the mortgagee has been extinguished.]
 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Cessation of interest.—When 
    the mortgagor or such other person as aforesaid has tendered or deposited in 
    Court under section 83 the amount remaining due  on  the mortgage, interest 
    on the principal money shall cease from the date of the tender or 


    1[in 
    the case of a deposit, where no previous tender of such amount has been 
    made] as soon as the mortgagor or such other person as aforesaid has done 
    all that has to be done by him to enable the mortgagee to take such amount 
    out of Court, 

    2[and 
    the notice required by section 83 has been served on the mortgagee:
 

    Provided that, where the mortgagor has deposited such amount without having 
    made a previous  tender  thereof and  has  subsequently  withdrawn the same 
    or any part thereof, interest on the principal money shall be payable from 
    the date of such withdrawal.]
 
Nothing 
    in this section or in section 83 shall be deemed to deprive the mortgagee of 
    his right to interest when there exists a contract that he shall be entitled 
    to reasonable notice before payment or tender of the mortgage-money 


    3[and 
    such notice has not been given before the making of the tender or deposit, 
    as the case may be].
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Parties to suits for foreclosure, sale and redemption.—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>86</number>—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>87</number>—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>88</number>—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>89</number>—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>90</number>—[Rep. 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>91</number> 
    Persons who may sue for redemption.—Besides the mortgagor, any of the 
    following persons may redeem, or institute a suit for redemption of, the 
    mortgaged property, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     any person (other 
    than the mortgagee of the interest sought to be redeemed) who has any 
    interest in, or charge upon, the property mortgaged or in or upon the right 
    to redeem the same;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     any surety for the 
    payment of the mortgage-debt or any part thereof; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     any creditor of 
    the mortgagor who has in a suit for the administration of his estate 
    obtained a decree for sale of the mortgaged property.]
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>92</number> 
    Subrogation.—Any of the persons referred  to  in  section 91 (other  
    than  the mortgagor) and any co-mortgagor shall, on redeeming property 
    subject to the mortgage, have, so far as regards redemption, foreclosure or 
    sale of such property, the same rights as the mortgagee whose mortgage he 
    redeems may have against the mortgagor or any other mortgagee.
 

The right conferred 
    by this section is called the right of subrogation, and a person acquiring 
    the same is said to be subrogated to the rights of the mortgagee whose 
    mortgage he redeems.
 

A person who has 
    advanced to a mortgagor money with which the mortgage has been redeemed 
    shall be subrogated to the rights of the mortgagee whose mortgage has been 
    redeemed, if the mortgagor has by a registered instrument agreed that such 
    persons shall be so subrogated.
 

Nothing in this 
    section shall be deemed to confer a right of subrogation on any person 
    unless the mortgage in respect of which the right is claimed has been 
    redeemed in full.]
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>93</number> Prohibition of  
    tacking.—No 
    mortgagee paying off a prior mortgage,whether with or without notice of an 
    intermediate mortgage, shall thereby acquire any priority in respect of his 
    original security; and, except in the case provided for by section 79, no 
    mortgagee making a subsequent advance to the mortgagor, whether with or 
    without notice of an intermediate mortgage, shall thereby acquire any 
    priority in respect of his security for such subsequent advance.]
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>94</number> Rights of 
    mesne mortgagee.—Where 
    a property is mortgaged for successive debts to successive mortgagees, a 
    mesne mortgagee has the same rights against mortgagees posterior to 
    himself as he has against the mortgagor.]
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>95</number> 
    Right of redeeming co-mortgagor to expenses.—Where one of several 
    mortgagors redeems the mortgaged property, he shall, in enforcing his right 
    of subrogation under section 92 against his co-mortgagors, be entitled to 
    add to the mortgage money recoverable from them such proportion of the 
    expenses properly incurred in such redemption as is attributable to their 
    share in the property.]
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>96</number> Mortgage by 
    deposit of title-deeds.—The 
    provisions hereinbefore contained which apply to a simple mortgage shall, so 
    far as may be, apply to a mortgage by deposit of title-deeds.]
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>97</number> 
    Application of proceeds.—[Rep. by the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec. 156 and Sch. V.]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>98</number> 
    Rights and liabilities of parties to anomalous mortgages.—In 
    the case of 

    1[an 
    anomalous mortgage] the rights and liabilities of the parties shall be 
    determined by their contract as evidenced in the mortgage-deed, and, so far 
    as such contract does not extend, by local usage.
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>99</number> 
    Attachment of mortgaged property.—[Rep. by the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), sec.156 and Sch. V.]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>100</number> 
    Charges.—Where 
    immoveable property of one person is by act of parties or operation of law 
    made security for the payment of money to another, and the transaction does 
    not amount to a mortgage, the latter person is said to have a charge on the 
    property; and all the provisions hereinbefore contained 

    1[which 
    apply to a simple mortgage shall, so far as may be, apply to such charge].
 

Nothing in this section applies to the charge of a trustee on 
    the trust-property for expenses properly incurred in the execution of his 
    trust, 

    2[and, 
    save as otherwise expressly provided by any law for the time being in force, 
    no charge shall be enforced against any property in the hands of a person to 
    whom such property has been transferred for consideration and without notice 
    of the charge].
 

 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>101</number> 
    No merger in case of subsequent encumbrance.—Any mortgagee of, or person 
    having a charge upon, immoveable property, or any transferee from such 
    mortgagee or charge-holder, may purchase or otherwise acquire the rights in 
    the property of the mortgagor or owner, as the case may be, without thereby 
    causing the mortgage or charge to be merged as between himself and any 
    subsequent mortgagee of, or person having a subsequent charge upon, the same 
    property; and no such subsequent mortgagee or charge-holder shall be 
    entitled to foreclose or sell such property without redeeming the prior 
    mortgage or charge, or otherwise than subject thereto.]
 

 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>102</number> Service or 
    tender on or to agent.—Where 
    the person on or to whom any notice or tender is to be served or made under 
    this Chapter does not reside in the district in which the mortgaged property 
    or some part thereof is situate, service or tender on or to an agent holding 
    a general power-of-attorney from such person or otherwise duly authorised to 
    accept such service or tender shall be deemed sufficient.
 


    1[Where 
    no person or agent on whom such notice should be served can be found or is 
    known] to the person required to serve the notice, the latter person may 
    apply to any court in which a suit might be brought for redemption of the 
    mortgaged property, and such court shall direct in what manner such notice 
    shall be served, and any notice served in compliance with such direction 
    shall be deemed sufficient:
 


    2[Provided 
    that, in the case of a notice required by section 83, in the case of a 
    deposit, the application  shall  be  made  to  the court  in  which  the  
    deposit  has  been made.]
 


    3[Where 
    no person or agent to whom such tender should be made can be found or is 
    known] to the person desiring to make the tender, the latter person may 
    deposit 

    4[in 
    any Court in which a suit might be brought for redemption of the mortgaged 
    property] the amount sought to be tendered, and such deposit shall have the 
    effect of a tender of such amount.
 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>103</number> 
    Notice, etc., to or by person incompetent to contract.—Where, 
    under the provisions of this Chapter, a notice is to be served on or by, or 
    a tender or deposit made or accepted or taken out of court by, any person 
    incompetent to contract, such notice may be served 

    1[on 
    or by] or tender or deposit made, accepted or taken, by the legal curator of 
    the property of such person; but where there is no such curator, and it is 
    requisite or desirable in the interest of such person that a notice should 
    be served or a tender or deposit made under the provisions of this Chapter, 
    application may be made to any court in which a suit might be brought for 
    the redemption of the mortgage to appoint a guardian ad litem  for 
    the purpose of serving or receiving service of such notice, or making or 
    accepting such tender, or making or taking out of court such deposit, and 
    for the performance of all consequential acts which could or ought to be 
    done by such person if he were competent to contract2; 
    and the provisions of 

    3[order 
    XXXII in the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
    1908)] shall, so far as may be, apply to such application and to parties 
    thereto and to the guardian appointed thereunder.
 

 
 

 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>104</number> Power to make 
    rules.—The 
    High Court may, from time to time, make rules consistent with this Act for 
    carrying out, in itself and in the Courts of Civil Judicature subject to its 
    superintendence, the provisions contained in this Chapter.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>105</number> Lease defined.—A 
    lease of immoveable property is a transfer of a right to enjoy such 
    property, made for a certain time, express or implied, or in perpetuity, in 
    consideration of a price paid or promised, or of money, a share of crops, 
    service or any other thing of value, to be rendered periodically or on 
    specified occasions to the transferor by the transferee, who accepts the 
    transfer on such terms.
 

Lessor, lessee,  
    premium and rent defined.—The 
    transferor is called the lessor, the transferee is called the lessee, the 
    price is called the premium, and the money, share, service or other thing to 
    be so rendered is called the rent.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>106</number> 
    Duration of certain leases in absence of written contract or local usage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the absence of a contract or local law or usage to the contrary, a lease 
    of immovable property for agricultural or manufacturing purposes shall be 
    deemed to be a lease from year to year, terminable, on the part of either 
    lessor or lessee, by six months' notice; and a lease of immovable property 
    for any other purpose shall be deemed to be a lease from month to month, 
    terminable, on the part of either lessor or lessee, by fifteen days' notice.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in  any other law for the time being in force, the period 
    mentioned in sub-section (1) shall commence from the date of receipt of 
    notice.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> A notice under 
    sub-section (1) shall not be deemed to be invalid merely because the period 
    mentioned therein falls short of the period specified under that 
    sub-section, where a suit or proceeding is filed after the expiry of the 
    period mentioned in that sub-section.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> Every notice 
    under sub-section (1) must be in writing, signed by or on behalf of the 
    person giving it, and either be sent by post to the party who is intended to 
    be bound by it or be tendered or delivered personally to such party, or to 
    one of his family or servants at his residence, or (if such tender or 
    delivery is not practicable) affixed to a conspicuous part of the property.]
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>108</number> Rights and 
    liabilities of lessor and lessee.—In 
    the absence of a contract or local usage to the contrary, the lessor and the 
    lessee of immoveable property, as against one another, respectively, possess 
    the rights and are subject to the liabilities mentioned in the rules next 
    following, or such of them as are applicable to the property leased:—
 <section>

<number>A</number> Rights and 
    Liabilities of the Lessor
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>     The lessor is bound to disclose to the lessee any material defect in 
    the property, with reference to its intended use, of which the former is and 
    the latter is not aware, and which the latter could not with ordinary care 
    discover;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>     the lessor is bound on the lessee’s request to put him in possession 
    of the property;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>     the lessor shall be deemed to contract with the lessee that, if the 
    latter pays the rent reserved by the lease and performs the contracts 
    binding on the lessee, he may hold the property during the time limited by 
    the lease without interruption.
 

The benefit of such 
    contract shall be annexed to and go with the lessee’s interest as such, and 
    may be enforced by every person in whom that interest is for the whole or 
    any part thereof from time to time vested.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>B</number>  Rights and 
    Liabilities of the Lessee
 <subsection>
<number>d</number>     If during the continuance of the lease any accession is made to the 
    property, such accession (subject to the law relating to alluvion for the 
    time being in force) shall be deemed to be comprised in the lease;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>     if by fire, 
    tempest or flood, or violence of an army or of a mob, or other irresistible 
    force, any material part of the property be wholly destroyed or rendered 
    substantially and permanently unfit for the purposes for which it was let, 
    the lease shall, at the option of the lessee, be void:
 
Provided that, if the injury be occasioned by 
    the wrongful act or default of the lessee, he shall not be entitled to avail 
    himself of the benefit of this provision;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>     if the lessor neglects to make, within a reasonable time after 
    notice, any repairs which he is bound to make to the property, the lessee 
    may make the same himself, and deduct the expense of such repairs with 
    interest from the rent, or otherwise recover it from the lessor;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>     if the lessor neglects to make any payment which he is bound to 
    make, and which, if not made by him, is recoverable from the lessee or 
    against the property, the lessee may make such payment himself, and deduct 
    it with interest from the rent, or otherwise recover it from the lessor;
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>h</number>     the lessee may 

    1[even after the 
    determination of the lease] remove, at any time 

    2[whilst he is in 
    possession of the property leased but not afterwards] all things which he 
    has attached to the earth; provided he leaves the property in the state in 
    which he received it;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> 
        when a lease of uncertain duration determines by any means except the 
    fault of the lessee, he or his legal representative is entitled to all the 
    crops planted or sown by the lessee and growing upon the property when the 
    lease determines, and to free ingress and egress to gather and carry them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>     the lessee may 
    transfer absolutely or by way of mortgage or sub-lease the whole or any part 
    of his interest in the property, and any transferee of such interest or part 
    may again transfer it.  The lessee shall not, by reason only of such 
    transfer, cease to be subject to any of the liabilities attaching to the 
    lease;
 
Nothing in this clause shall be deemed to authorise a 
    tenant having an untransferable right of occupancy, the farmer of an estate 
    in respect of which default has been made in paying revenue, or the lessee 
    of an estate under the management of a Court of Wards, to assign his 
    interest as such tenant, farmer or lessee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>     the lessee is bound to disclose to the lessor any fact as to the 
    nature or extent of the interest which the lessee is about to take, of which 
    the lessee is, and the lessor is not, aware, and which materially increases 
    the value of such interest;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>     the lessee is bound to pay or tender, at the proper time and place, 
    the premium or rent to the lessor or his agent in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> 
        the lessee is bound to keep, and on the termination of the lease to 
    restore, the property in as good condition as it was in at the time when he 
    was put in possession, subject only to the changes caused by reasonable wear 
    and tear or irresistible force, and to allow the lessor and his agents, at 
    all reasonable times during the term, to enter upon the property and inspect 
    the condition thereof and give or leave notice of any defect in such 
    condition; and, when such defect has been caused by any act or default on 
    the part of the lessee, his servants or agents, he is bound to make it good 
    within three months after such notice has been given or left;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>     if the lessee becomes aware of any proceeding to recover the 
    property or any part thereof, or of any encroachment made upon, or any 
    interference with, the lessor’s rights concerning such property, he is bound 
    to give, with reasonable diligence, notice thereof to the lessor;
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>o</number>     the lessee may use the property and its products (if any) as 
    a person of ordinary prudence would use them if they were his own; but he 
    must not use, or permit another to use, the property for a purpose other 
    than that for which it was leased, or fell 

    3[or  sell] 
    timber, pull down or damage buildings 

    3[belonging to the 
    lessor, or] work mines or quarries not open when the lease was granted, or 
    commit any other act which is destructive or permanently injurious thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>     he must not, without the lessor’s consent, erect on the property any 
    permanent structure, except for agricultural purposes;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>     on the determination of the lease, the lessee is bound to put the lessor into possession of the property.
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>109</number> Rights of 
    lessor’s transferee.—If 
    the lessor transfers the property leased, or any part thereof, or any part 
    of his interest therein, the transferee, in the absence of a contract to the 
    contrary, shall possess all the rights, and, if the lessee so elects, be 
    subject to all the liabilities of the lessor as to the property or part 
    transferred so long as he is the owner of it; but the lessor shall not, by 
    reason only of such transfer cease to be subject to any of the liabilities 
    imposed upon him by the lease, unless the lessee elects to treat the 
    transferee as the person liable to him:
 

Provided that the 
    transferee is not entitled to arrears of rent due before the transfer, and 
    that, if the lessee, not having reason to believe that such transfer has 
    been made, pays rent to the lessor, the lessee shall not be liable to pay 
    such rent over again to the transferee.
 


    The lessor, the transferee and the lessee may determine what proportion of 
    the premium or rent reserved by the lease is payable in respect of the part 
    so transferred, 
    and, in case they disagree, such determination may be made by any Court 
    having jurisdiction to entertain a suit for the possession of the property 
    leased.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>109</number> Rights of 
    lessor’s transferee.—If 
    the lessor transfers the property leased, or any part thereof, or any part 
    of his interest therein, the transferee, in the absence of a contract to the 
    contrary, shall possess all the rights, and, if the lessee so elects, be 
    subject to all the liabilities of the lessor as to the property or part 
    transferred so long as he is the owner of it; but the lessor shall not, by 
    reason only of such transfer cease to be subject to any of the liabilities 
    imposed upon him by the lease, unless the lessee elects to treat the 
    transferee as the person liable to him:
 

Provided that the 
    transferee is not entitled to arrears of rent due before the transfer, and 
    that, if the lessee, not having reason to believe that such transfer has 
    been made, pays rent to the lessor, the lessee shall not be liable to pay 
    such rent over again to the transferee.
 


    The lessor, the transferee and the lessee may determine what proportion of 
    the premium or rent reserved by the lease is payable in respect of the part 
    so transferred, 
    and, in case they disagree, such determination may be made by any Court 
    having jurisdiction to entertain a suit for the possession of the property 
    leased.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>110</number> Exclusion of day 
    on which term commences.—Where 
    the time limited by a lease of immoveable property is expressed as 
    commencing from a particular day, in computing that time such day shall be 
    excluded. Where no day of commencement is named, the time so limited begins 
    from the making of the lease.
 

Duration of lease for 
    a year.—Where 
    the time so limited is a year or a number of years, in the absence of an 
    express agreement to the contrary, the lease shall last during the whole 
    anniversary of the day from which such time commences.
 

Option to determine 
    lease.—Where 
    the time so limited is expressed to be terminable before its expiration, and 
    the lease omits to mention at whose option it is so terminable, the lessee, 
    and not the lessor, shall have such option.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>111</number> Determination of 
    lease.—A 
    lease of immoveable property determines—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     by efflux of the 
    time limited thereby;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     where such time is limited  conditionally  on  the  happening  of  
    some  
    event—by the happening of such event;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     where the interest of the lessor in the property terminates on, or 
    his power to dispose of the same extends only to, the happening of any 
    event—by the happening of such event;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>     in case the interests of the lessee and the lessor in the whole of 
    the property become vested at the same time in one person in the same right;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     by express surrender; that is to say, in case the lessee yields up 
    his interest under the lease to the lessor, by mutual agreement between 
    them;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>     by implied 
    surrender;
 </section><section>

    <number>g</number>     by forfeiture; that is to say, (1) in case the lessee breaks 
    an express condition which provides that, on breach thereof, the lessor may 
    re-enter 

    1[* * *]; or (2) 
    in case the lessee renounces his character as such by setting up a title in 
    a third person or by claiming title in himself; 

    2[or (3) the 
    lessee is adjudicated an insolvent and the lease provides that the lessor 
    may re-enter on the happening of such event]; and in 

    3[any of these 
    cases] the lessor or his transferee 

    4[gives notice in 
    writing to the lessee of] his intention to determine the lease;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>     on  the  
    expiration of a notice to determine the lease, or to quit, or of intention 
    to quit, the property leased, duly given by one party to the other.
 
 
Illustration to clause (f)
 
A lessee 
    accepts from his lessor a new lease of the property leased, to take effect 
    during the continuance of the existing lease.  This is an implied surrender 
    of the former lease, and such lease determines thereupon.
 
COMMENTS
 
Doctrine of merger
 
The 
    doctrine of merger is attracted when a leasehold and revision coincide.  If 
    the lessee purchases the lessor’s interest, the lease is relinquished as the 
    same person cannot at the same time be both landlord and tenant.  The 
    doctrine of merger is based on the principle of union of two conflicting 
    interests which cannot be held by one person at the same time.  Therefore, 
    the leasehold rights in favour of the appellants stand extinguished; 
    Ramesh Kumar Jhambh  v.  Official Assignee, High Court Bombay, 
    AIR 1993 Bom 374. 
 
Implied surrender
 
There can 
    be implied surrender, if the lessor grants a new lease to a third person 
    with the assent of the lessee under the existing lease who delivers the 
    possession to such person or where the lessee directs his sub-tenant to pay 
    the rent directly to the lessor.  Since the respondents had by executing the 
    agreement impliedly surrendered their leasehold rights, they were no longer 
    lessees; P.M.C. Kunhiraman Nair  v.  C.R. Nagaratha Iyer, AIR 
    1993 SC 307.
 
Clause (1) 
    of section 111(g) has no application as there was no covenant prohibiting 
    sale or on its breach, of the right of re-entry.  Clause (2) of section 
    111(g) is also of no avail to the landlord for forfeiture because there is 
    no unequivocal and clear disclaimer of title of the landlord.  Therefore 
    neither clause (1) nor (2) of section 111(g) are of any avail for 
    forfeiture;  Guru Amarjit Singh  v.  Rattan Chand, AIR 1994 SC 
    227.
 
The 
    statement by the tenant that he was not aware of as to who was his landlord 
    cannot be held to be denial of title of landlord and no eviction decree by 
    forfeiture was granted; Munisami Naidu  v.  C. Ranganathan, 
    AIR 1991 SC 492.
 
It has 
    been held that the Board was entitled to institute proceedings against the 
    tenant as the notice period had expired; Vasant Kumar Radhakishan Vora  
    v. The Board of Trustees of the Port of Bombay, 
    AIR 1991 SC 14.

 

 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>112</number> Waiver  of   
    forfeiture.—A 
    forfeiture under section 111, clause (g) is waived by acceptance of rent 
    which has become due since the forfeiture, or by distress for such rent, or 
    by any other act on the part of the lessor showing an intention to treat the 
    lease as subsisting:
 

Provided that the 
    lessor is aware that the forfeiture has been incurred:
 

Provided also that, 
    where rent is accepted after the institution of a suit to eject the lessee 
    on the ground of forfeiture, such acceptance is not a waiver.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>113</number> Waiver of notice 
    to quit.—A 
    notice given under section 111, clause (h), is waived, with the express or 
    implied consent of the person to whom it is given, by any act on the part of 
    the person giving it showing an intention to treat the lease as subsisting.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number>  A, 
    the lessor, gives B, the lessee, notice to quit the property leased.  
    The notice expires.  B tenders and A accepts, rent which has 
    become due in respect of the property since the expiration of the notice.  
    The notice is waived.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  A, 
    the lessor, gives B, the lessee; notice to quit the property leased.  
    The notice expires, and B remains in possession. A gives to 
    B as lessee a second notice to quit.  The first notice is waived.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>114</number> Relief against 
    forfeiture for non-payment of rent.—Where 
    a lease of immoveable property has determined by forfeiture for non-payment 
    of rent, and the lessor sues to eject the lessee, if, at the hearing of the 
    suit, the lessee pays or tenders to the lessor the rent in arrear, together 
    with interest thereon and his full costs of the suit, or gives such security 
    as the Court thinks sufficient for making such payment within fifteen days, 
    the Court may, in lieu of making a decree for ejectment, pass an order 
    relieving the lessee against the forfeiture; and thereupon the lessee shall 
    hold the property leased as if the forfeiture had not occurred.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>114A</number> 
    Relief against forfeiture in certain other cases.—Where a lease of 
    immoveable property has determined by forfeiture for a breach of an express 
    condition which provides that on breach thereof the lessor may re-enter, no 
    suit for ejectment shall lie unless and until the lessor has served on the 
    lessee a notice in writing—
 <section>
<number>a</number>     specifying the 
    particular breach complained of; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>     if the breach is 
    capable of remedy, requiring the lessee to remedy the breach, and the lessee 
    fails, within a reasonable time from the date of the service of the notice, 
    to remedy the breach, if it is capable of remedy.
 

Nothing in this 
    section shall apply to an express condition against the assigning, 
    under-letting, parting with the possession, or disposing, of the property 
    leased, or to an express condition relating to forfeiture in case of 
    non-payment of rent.]
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>115</number> Effect of 
    surrender and forfeiture on under-leases.—The 
    surrender, express or implied, of a lease of immoveable property does not 
    prejudice an under-lease of the property or any part thereof previously 
    granted by the lessee, on terms and conditions substantially the same 
    (except as regards the amount of rent) as those of the original lease; but, 
    unless the surrender is made for the purpose of obtaining a new lease, the 
    rent payable by, and the contracts binding on, the under-lessee shall be 
    respectively payable to and enforceable by the lessor.
 

The forfeiture of 
    such a lease annuls all such under-leases, except where such forfeiture  
    has  been  procured  by  the  lessor  in  fraud  of  the  under-lessees, or 
    relief against the forfeiture is granted under section 114.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>116</number> Effect of 
    holding over.—If 
    a lessee or under-lessee of property remains in possession thereof after the 
    determination of the lease granted to the lessee, and the lessor or his 
    legal representative accepts rent from the lessee or under-lessee, or 
    otherwise assents to his continuing in possession, the lease is, in the 
    absence of an agreement to the contrary, renewed from year to year, or from 
    month to month, according to the purpose for which the property is leased, 
    as specified in section 106.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A 
     lets a house to B for five years. B underlets the house to 
    C at a monthly rent of  Rs. 100. The five years expire, but C 
    continues in possession of the house and pays the rent to A. C’s 
    lease is renewed from month to month.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A 
    lets a farm to B for the life of C. C dies, but B 
    continues in possession with A’s assent. B’s lease is renewed 
    from year to year. 
 

 
COMMENTS
 
Tenant at sufferance
 
A person 
    who is a tenant at sufferance has no estate or interest in the leasehold 
    property. A tenant holding after the expiry of his term is a tenant at 
    sufferance, which is a term useful to distinguish a possession rightful in 
    its inception but wrongful in its continuance from a trespass which is 
    wrongful both in its inception and in its continuance. A co-owner can 
    maintain a suit by himself in ejectment of a trespasser or a tenant at 
    sufferance; B. Valsala v. Sundram Nadar Bhaskaran, AIR 1994 
    Ker 164.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>117</number> 
    Exemption of leases for agricultural purposes.—None 
    of the provisions of this Chapter apply to leases for agricultural purposes, 
    except in so far as the State Government 

    1[***] may by notification published in the Official Gazette declare all or  
    any of such provisions to be so applicable 

    2[in 
    the case of all or any of such leases], together with, or subject to, those 
    of the local law, if any, for the time being in force.
 

Such notification 
    shall not take effect until the expiry of six months from the date of its 
    publication.
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>118</number> “Exchange” 
    defined.—When 
    two persons mutually transfer the ownership of one thing for the ownership 
    of another, neither thing or both things being money only, the transaction 
    is called an “exchange”.
 

A transfer of 
    property in completion of an exchange can be made only in manner provided 
    for the transfer of such property by sale.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>118</number> “Exchange” 
    defined.—When 
    two persons mutually transfer the ownership of one thing for the ownership 
    of another, neither thing or both things being money only, the transaction 
    is called an “exchange”.
 

A transfer of 
    property in completion of an exchange can be made only in manner provided 
    for the transfer of such property by sale.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>119</number> 
    Right of party deprived of thing received in exchange.—If any party to 
    an exchange or any person claiming through or under such party is by reason 
    of any defect  in  the  title of the other party deprived of the thing or 
    any part of the thing received by him in exchange, then, unless a contrary 
    intention appears from the terms of the exchange, such other party is liable 
    to him or any person claiming through or under him for loss caused thereby, 
    or at the option of the person so deprived, for the return of the thing 
    transferred, if still in the possession of such other party or his legal 
    representative or a transferee from him without consideration.]
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>120</number> Rights and 
    liabilities of parties.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in this Chapter, each party has the rights and is 
    subject to the liabilities of a seller as to that which he gives, and has 
    the rights and is subject to the liabilities of a buyer as to that which he 
    takes.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>121</number> Exchange of 
    money.—On 
    an exchange of money, each party thereby warrants the genuineness of the 
    money given by him.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>122</number> “Gift” defined.—“Gift” 
    is the transfer of certain existing moveable or immoveable property made 
    voluntarily and without consideration, by one person, called the donor, to 
    another, called the donee, and accepted by or on behalf of the donee.
 

Acceptance when to be 
    made.—Such 
    acceptance must be made during the lifetime of the donor and while he is 
    still capable of giving. 
 

If the donee dies 
    before acceptance, the gift is void.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>122</number> “Gift” defined.—“Gift” 
    is the transfer of certain existing moveable or immoveable property made 
    voluntarily and without consideration, by one person, called the donor, to 
    another, called the donee, and accepted by or on behalf of the donee.
 

Acceptance when to be 
    made.—Such 
    acceptance must be made during the lifetime of the donor and while he is 
    still capable of giving. 
 

If the donee dies 
    before acceptance, the gift is void.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>124</number> Gift of existing 
    and future property.—A 
    gift comprising both existing and future property is void as to the latter.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>125</number> Gift to several 
    of whom one does not accept.—A 
    gift of a thing to two or more donees, of whom one does not accept it, is 
    void as to the interest which he would have taken had he accepted.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>126</number> When gift may be 
    suspended or revoked.—The 
    donor and donee may agree that on the happening of any specified event which 
    does not depend on the will of the donor a gift shall be suspended or 
    revoked; but a gift which the parties agree shall be revocable wholly or in 
    part, at the mere will of the donor, is void wholly or in part, as the case 
    may be.
 

A gift may also be 
    revoked in any of the cases (save want or failure of consideration) in 
    which, if it were a contract, it might be rescinded.
 

Save as aforesaid, a 
    gift cannot be revoked.
 

Nothing contained in 
    this section shall be deemed to affect the rights of transferees for 
    consideration without notice.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A 
    gives a field to B, reserving to himself, with B’s assent, the 
    right to take back the field in case B and his descendants die before
    A.  B  dies without descendants in  A’s  lifetime.  A 
     may take back the field.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A 
    gives a lakh of rupees to B, reserving to himself, with B’s 
    assent, the right to take back at pleasure Rs. 10,000 out of the lakh. The 
    gift holds goods as to Rs. 90,000, but is void as to Rs. 10,000, which 
    continue to belong to A.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>127</number> Onerous gifts.—Where 
    a gift is in the form of a single transfer to the same person of several 
    things of which one is, and the others are not burdened by an obligation, 
    the donee can take nothing by the gift unless he accepts it fully.
 

Where a gift is in 
    the form of two or more separate and independent transfers to the same 
    person of several things, the doneee is at liberty to accept one of them and 
    refuse the others, although the former may be beneficial and the latter 
    onerous.
 

Onerous gift to 
    disqualified person.—A 
    donee not competent to contract and  accepting property burdened by any 
    obligation is not bound by his acceptance. But if, after becoming competent 
    to contract and being aware of the obligation, he retains the property 
    given, he becomes so bound.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A 
    shares in X, prosperous joint stock company, and also shares in Y, 
    a joint stock company in difficulties. Heavy calls are expected in respect 
    of the shares in Y. A gives B all his shares in joint stock 
    companies. B refuses to accept the shares in Y. He cannot take 
    the shares in X.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, 
    having a lease for a term of years of a house at a rent which he and his 
    representatives are bound to pay during the term, and which is more than the 
    house can be let for, gives to B the lease, and also, as a separate 
    and independent transaction, a sum of money. B refuses to accept the 
    lease. He does not by this refusal forfeit the money.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>128</number> 
    Universal donee.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 127, where a gift consists of the donor’s whole 
    property, the donee is personally liable for all the debts due by 


    1[and 
    liabilities of] the donor at the time of the gift to the extent of the 
    property comprised therein.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>129</number> 
    Saving of donations mortis causa and Muhammadan Law.—Nothing 
    in this Chapter relates to gifts of moveable property made in contemplation 
    of death, or shall be deemed to affect any rule of Muhammadan law 


    1[***].
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


<number>130</number> Transfer of actionable claim.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The transfer of an actionable claim 

    1[whether 
    with or without consideration] shall be effected only by the execution of an 
    instrument in writing signed by the transferor or his duly authorised agent,
    

    2[***] shall be complete and effectual upon the execution of such instruments, 
    and thereupon all the rights and remedies of the transferor, whether by way 
    of damages or otherwise, shall vest in the transferee, whether such notice 
    of the transfer as is hereinafter provided be given or not:
 

Provided that every 
    dealing with the debt or other actionable claim by the debtor or other 
    person from or against whom the transferor would, but for such instrument of 
    transfer as aforesaid, have been entitled to recover or enforce such debt or 
    other actionable claim, shall (save where the debtor or other person is a 
    party to the transfer or has received express notice thereof as hereinafter 
    provided) be valid as against such transfer.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The transferee of 
    an actionable claim may, upon the execution of such instrument of transfer 
    as aforesaid, sue or institute proceedings for the same in his own name 
    without obtaining the transferor’s consent to such suit or proceeding and 
    without making him a party thereto.
 <subsection>


    <number>Exception</number>—Nothing 
    in this section applies to the transfer of a marine or fire policy of 
    insurance 

    3[or 
    affects the provisions of section 38 of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 
    1938)].
 
 

Illustrations
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> A 
    owes money to B, who transfers the debt to C. B then demands 
    the debt from A, who, not having received notice of the transfer, as 
    prescribed in section 131, pays B. The payment is valid, and C 
    cannot sue A for the debt.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> A 
    effects a policy on his own life with an Insurance Company and assigns it to 
    a Bank for securing the payment of an existing or future debt. If A 
    dies, the Bank is entitled to receive the amount of the policy and to sue on 
    it without the concurrence of A’s executor, subject to the proviso in 
    sub-section (1) of section 130 and to provisions of section 132.
 



</subsubsection>








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>130A</number> 
    Transfer of policy of marine insurance.—[Rep. by the Marine Insurance 
    Act, 1963 (11 of 1963), sec. 92 (w.e.f. 
1-8-1963)].]
    
 

 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>131</number> Notice to be in 
    writing, signed.—Every 
    notice of transfer of an actionable claim shall be in writing, signed by the 
    transferor or his agent duly authorised in this behalf, or, in case the 
    transferor refuses to sign, by the transferee or his agent, and shall state 
    the name and address of the transferee.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>132</number> Liability of 
    transferee of actionable claim.—The 
    transferee of an actionable claim shall take it subject to all the 
    liabilities and equities and to which the transferor was subject in respect 
    thereof at the date of the transfer.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>i</number> A 
    transfers to C a debt due to him by B,  A being then indebted 
    to B. C sues B for the debt due by B to A. 
    In such suit B is entitled to set off the debt due by A  to 
    him; although C was unaware of it at the date of such transfer.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> A 
    executed a bond in favour of B under circumstances entitling the 
    former to have it delivered up and cancelled.  B assigns the bond to
    C for value and without notice of such circumstances. C cannot 
    enforce the bond against A.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>133</number> Warranty of 
    solvency of debtor.—Where 
    the transferor of a debt warrants the solvency of the debtor, the warranty, 
    in the absence of a contract to the contrary, applies only to his solvency 
    at the time of the transfer, and is limited, where the transfer is made for 
    consideration, to the amount or value of such consideration.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>134</number> Mortgaged debt.—Where 
    a debt is transferred for the purpose of securing an existing or future 
    debt, the debt so transferred, if received by the transferor or recovered by 
    the transferee, is applicable, first, in payment of the costs of such 
    recovery; secondly, in or towards satisfaction of the amount for the time 
    being secured by the transfer; and the residue, if any, belongs to the 
    transferor or other person entitled to receive the same.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>135</number> 
    Assignment of rights under policy of insurance against fire.—Every 
    assignee by endorsement or other writing, of a policy of insurance against 
    fire, in whom the property in the subject insured shall be absolutely vested 
    at the date of the assignment, shall have transferred and vested in him all 
    rights of suit as if the contract contained in the policy has been made with 
    himself.]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>135A</number> 
    Assignment of rights under policy of marine insurance.—[Rep. by the 
    Marine Insurance Act, 1963 (11 of 1963), sec.92, (w.e.f. 

    1-8-1963)].]
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>136</number> Incapacity of officers connected with 
    Courts of Justice.—No judge, 
    legal practitioner or officer connected with any Court of Justice shall buy 
    or traffic in, or stipulate for, or agree to receive any share of, or 
    interest in, any actionable claim, and no Court of Justice shall enforce, at 
    his instance, or at the instance of any person claiming by or through him, 
    any actionable claim so dealt with by him as aforesaid.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>

<number>137</number> Saving of negotiable instruments, etc.—Nothing 
    in the foregoing sections of this Chapter applies to stocks, shares or 
    debentures, or to instruments which are for the time being, by law or 
    custom, negotiable, or to any mercantile document of title to goods.
 

Explanation.—The 
    expression “mercantile document of title to goods” includes a bill of 
    lading, dock-warrant, warehouse-keeper’s certificate, railway receipt, 
    warrant or order for the delivery of goods, and any other document used in 
    the ordinary course of business as proof of the possession or control of 
    goods, or authorising or purporting to authorise, either by endorsement or 
    by delivery, the possessor of the document to transfer or receive goods 
    thereby represented.
 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
  
 
 




    THE TRANSFER OF PROPERTY ACT, 1882
 

 
 




    THE SCHEDULE
 



(A) 
    STATUTES
 
 
  

 
 Year and 
        Chapter
 Subject
 Extent of repeal

 
  

 
 27 Hen. VIII c. 10
 Uses
 The Whole.

 
 13 Eliz., c. 5
 Fraudulent conveyances
 The Whole.

 
 27 Eliz., c. 4
 Fraudulent conveyances
 The Whole.

 
 4 Wm and marry, c. 16
 Clandestine mortgages
 The Whole.

 
  

 
  
  
  


 

 
 



(B) 
    ACT OF THE GOVERNOR GENERAL IN COUNCIL
 
 
  

 
 Number and Year
 Subject
 Extent of repeal

 
  

 
 X of 1842
 Lease and re-lease
 The Whole

 
 XXXI of 1854
 Modes of conveying land
 Section117

 
 XI of 1855
 Mesne profit and 
        improvement
 Section 1; in the title, 
        the word "to mesne profits and", and in the preamble "to limit 
        the liability for mesne profits and"

 
 XXVII of 1866
 Indian Trustee Act
 Section 31.

 
 V of 1872
 Punjab Laws Act
 So fas as it related to 
        Bengal Regulations 1 of 1798 and XVII of 1806

 
 XX of 1875
 Central Provinvces Laws 
        Act
 So fas as it related to 
        Bengal Regulations 1 of 1798 and XVII of 1806

 
 XVIII of 1876
 Oudh Laws Act
 So fas as it related to 
        Bengal Regulations XVII of 1806

 
 1 of 1877
 Specific Relief
 In section 35 and 36, the 
        word "in writing".

 
  

 
  
  
  


 

 
 



(C)  
    REGULATIONS
 
 
  

 
 Number and years
 Subject
 Extent of repeal

 
  

 
 Bengal Regulation 1 of 
        1798
 Conditional Sale
 The Whole Regulation

 
  

 
 Bengal Regulation XVII of 
        1806
 Redemption
 The Whole Regulation

 
 Bombay Regulation V of 
        1827
 Acknowledgement of debts; 
        interest;
  

 
  
 Mortgagees in possession
 Section 15

 
  

 
  
  
  



  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 47. Original sections 93 were repealed 
    by Act 5 of 1908, sec. 156 and Sch.V.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 47. Original sections 94 were repealed 
    by Act 5 of 1908, sec. 156 and Sch.V.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 48, for the original section 95. 
    Original section 96 was repealed by Act 5 of 1908, sec. 156 and Sch.V.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 48, for the original section 95. 
    Original section 96 was repealed by Act 5 of 1908, sec. 156 and Sch.V.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> For the repealed provisions as re-enacted, see  the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), Sch. I, Order XXXIV, rules 12 and 13.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 49, for “a mortgage, not being a simple 
    mortgage, a mortgage by conditional sale, an usufructuary mortgage or an 
    English mortgage or a combination of the first and third, or the second and 
    third, of such forms”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> For the repealed provisions as re-enacted, see  the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), Sch. I, Order XXXIV, rule 14.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 50, for “as to a 
    mortgagor shall, so far as may be, apply to the owner of such property, and 
    the provisions of sections 81 and 82 shall, so far as may be, apply to the 
    person having such charge”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 51, for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Act  20  of 1929, sec. 52,  for “Where the person or agent 
    on whom such notice should be served cannot be found in the said district, 
    or is unknown”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 53.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 2003, 
    sec. 2, for section 106 (w.e.f. 31-12-2002). Section 106, before 
    substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> As to limitation to the territorial operation of section 107, see
    section 1, supra, section 107 extends to every cantonment—see
    section 287 of the Cantonments Act, 1924 (2 of 1924).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 56.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   The words “or the lease shall become void” omitted by Act 20 of 1929, 
    sec. 57.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 58.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   The words “with the previous sanction of the Governor General in 
    Council” omitted by Act 38 of 1920, sec. 2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Subs. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 59, for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> As to limitation to the territorial operation of section 123, see
    section 1, supra, section 123 extends to every cantonment—see
    section 287 of the Cantonments Act, 1924 (2 of 1924).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 60.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> The words and figures “or, save as provided by section 123, any rule 
    of Hindu or Buddhist law” omitted by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 61.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 1929, sec. 62.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 1944, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs. by Act 6 of 1944, sec. 3, for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Section 135A ins. by Act 6 of 1944, sec. 4.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>