<act><title>

    THE EXPLOSIVES ACT, 1884</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the 

    1[***] Explosives Act, 
    1884; and—(1) 
    This Act may be called the 

    3[***] Explosives Act, 
    1884; and"
 
Local 
    extent.—(2) 
    It extends to the whole of India 

    2[***].—(2) 
    It extends to the whole of India 

    4[***]."
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act shall come into force on such day1 as 
    the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoints.—(1) 
    This Act shall come into force on such day5 as 
    the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoints." 
 


    2[***] 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Repeal of portions of Act 12 of 1875.—[Rep. 
    by the Indian Ports Act, 1889 (10 of 1889)1,
    sec. 2 and Sch. II.]—[Rep. 
    by the Indian Ports Act, 1889 (10 of 1889)7,
    sec. 2 and Sch. II.]" 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “aircraft” means any machine which can 
    derive support in the atmosphere from the reactions of the air, other than 
    the reactions of the air against the earth’s surface, and includes baloons, 
    whether fixed or free, airships, kites, gliders and flying machines; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “carriage” includes any carriage, 
    wagon, cart, truck, vehicle or other means of conveying goods or passengers 
    by land, in whatever manner the same may be propelled; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “District Magistrate”, in relation to 
    any area for which a Commissioner of Police has been appointed, means the 
    Commissioner of Police thereof and includes— 
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>    any such Deputy Commissioner of Police, 
    exercising jurisdiction over the whole or any part of such area, as may be 
    specified by the State Government in this behalf in relation to such area or 
    part; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    an Additional District Magistrate; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “explosive” means gunpowder, 
    nitroglycerine, nitroglycol, gun-cotton, di-nitro-toluene, 
    tri-nitro-toluene, picric acid, di-nitro-phenol, tri-nitro-resorcinol (styphnic 
    acid), cyclo-trimethylene-tri-nitramine, penta-erythritol-tetranitrate, 
    tetryl, nitro-guanidine, lead azide, lead styphynate, fulminate of mercury 
    or any other metal, diazo-di-nitro-phenol, coloured fires or any other 
    substance whether a single chemical compound or a mixture of substances, 
    whether solid or liquid or gaseous used or manufactured with a view to 
    produce a practical effect by explosion or pyrotechnic effect; and includes 
    fog-signals, fireworks, fuses, rockets, percussion-caps, detonators, 
    cartridges, ammunition of all descriptions and every adaptation or 
    preparation of an explosive as defined in this clause; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “export” means taking out of India to a 
    place outside India by land, sea or air; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “import” means to bring into India from 
    a place outside India by land, sea or air; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “master”,— 
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>    in relation to any vessel or aircraft 
    means any person, other than a pilot, harbour master, assistant harbour 
    master or berthing master, having for the time being the charge or control 
    of such vessel or aircraft, as the case may be; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in relation to any boat belonging to a 
    ship, means the master of that ship; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “manufacture” in relation to an 
    explosive includes the process of— 
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>    dividing the explosive into its 
    component parts or otherwise breaking up or unmaking the explosive, or 
    making fit for use any damaged explosive; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>    re-making, altering or repairing the 
    explosive; 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>j</number>    “vessel” includes any ship, boat, 
    sailing vessel, or other description of vessel used in navigation whether 
    propelled by oars or otherwise and anything made for the conveyance, mainly 
    by water, of human beings or of goods and a caisson.] 
 
 




 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Power to make rules as to licensing of the manufacture, 
      possession, use, sale, transport, import and export of 
      explosives.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, for any part of 
      1[India] 2 
      [***] make 
      rules3 consistent with this Act to 
      regulate or prohibit, except under and in accordance with the conditions 
      of a licence granted as provided by those rules, the manufacture, 
      possession, use, sale, 4[transport, import and export] of 
      explosives, or any specified class of explosives.—(1) 
    The Central Government may, for any part of 

    1[India] 


    2 [***] make rules3 consistent 
    with this Act to regulate or prohibit, except under and in accordance with 
    the conditions of a licence granted as provided by those rules, the 
    manufacture, possession, use, sale, 

    4[transport, import 
    and export] of explosives, or any specified class of explosives." 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Rules under this section may provide for all 
      or any of the following, among other matters, that is to say:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    the 
      authority by which licences may be granted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    the fees to 
      be charged for licences, and the other sums (if any) to be paid for 
      expenses by applicants for licences; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    the manner 
      in which applications for licenses must be made, and the matters to be 
      specified in such applications; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    the form in 
      which, and the conditions on and subject to which, licences must be 
      granted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>    the 
      period for which licences are to remain in force; 5[***]
5[***]" 
 6[(ee)    the authority to which appeals may be 
      preferred under section 6F, the procedure to be followed by such authority 
      and the period within which appeals shall be preferred, the fees to be 
      paid in respect of such appeals and the circumstances under which such 
      fees may be refunded; 6[(ee) 
    the authority to which appeals may be preferred under section 6F, the 
    procedure to be followed by such authority and the period within which 
    appeals shall be preferred, the fees to be paid in respect of such appeals 
    and the circumstances under which such fees may be refunded;" 
 </subsection><subsection><number>eea</number>    the total 
      quantity of explosives that a licensee can purchase in a given period of 
      time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>eeb</number>    the fees 
      to be charged by the Chief Controller of Explosives or any officer 
      authorised by him in this behalf, for services rendered in connection with 
      the manufacture, transport, import or export of explosives;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>    the 
      exemption absolutely or subject to conditions of any explosives 
      6[or any person or class of persons] from the operation of the 
rules.6[or 
    any person or class of persons] from the operation of the rules." 
 7[***] 
 










 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>5A</number> Persons 
    already in business in respect of certain explosives to carry on such 
    business without licence for a certain period.—Notwithstanding anything 
    in section 5 or in the rules made thereunder where, immediately before the 
    commencement of the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 1978 (32 of 1978), 
    any person was carrying on the business of manufacture, sale, transport, 
    import or export of any explosive [for which no licence was required under 
    this Act before its amendment by the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 
    1978], then, such person shall be entitled to continue to carry on such 
    business without licence in respect of such explosive— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for a period of three months from the 
    date of such commencement; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if before the expiry of the said period 
    of three months, such person has made an application for grant of licence 
    under this Act for such business in such explosive, until the final disposal 
    of his application, 
 
    whichever is later.]
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Power for Central Government to prohibit the 
      manufacture, possession or importation of specially dangerous 
      explosives.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
      anything in the rules under the last foregoing section, the Central 
      Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official 
      Gazette,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
      prohibit, either absolutely or subject to conditions, the manufacture, 
      possession or importation of any explosive which is of so dangerous a 
      character that, in the opinion of the Central Government, it is expedient 
      for the public safety to issue the notification; 1[***]
2[***]" 
 1[***] 
 2[(2) The Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 
      1962) shall have effect in relation to any explosive with regard to the 
      importation of which a notification has been issued under this section and 
      the vessel, carriage or aircraft containing such explosive as that Act has 
      in relation to any article the importation of which is prohibited or 
      regulated thereunder and the vessel, carriage or aircraft containing such 
      article.] 
 3[***] 
 







 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>6A</number> Prohibition of manufacture, 
      possession, sale or transport of explosives by young persons and certain 
      other persons.—Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing provisions of 
      this Act,— 
 <section><number>a</number>    no person,— 
 <subsection><number>i</number>    who has not 
      completed the age of eighteen years, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    who has 
      been sentenced on conviction of any offence involving violence or moral 
      turpitude for a term of not less than six months, at any time during a 
      period of five years after the expiration of the sentence, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    who has 
      been ordered to execute under Chapter VIII of the Code of Criminal 
      Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), a bond for keeping the peace or for good 
      behaviour, at any time during the term of the bond, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>    whose 
      licence under this Act has been cancelled, whether before or after the 
      commencement of the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 1978 (32 of 1978), 
      for contravention of the provisions of this Act or of the rules made 
      thereunder, at any time during a period of five years from the date of 
      cancellation of such licence, 
 shall,— 
 <subsubsection><number>1</number>    manufacture, 
      sell, transport, import or export any explosive, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number>    possess any 
      such explosive as the Central Government may, having regard to the nature 
      thereof, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify; 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>b</number>    no person 
      shall sell, deliver or despatch any explosive to a person whom he knows or 
      has reason to believe at the time of such sale, delivery or despatch,— 
 <subsection><number>i</number>    to be 
      prohibited under clause (a) to manufacture, sell, transport, import, 
      export or possess such explosive, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    to be of 
      unsound mind.] 
 
  




 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6B</number> Grant of 
    licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a person makes an application for licence under section 5, the 
    authority prescribed in the rules made under that section for grant of 
    licences (hereinafter referred to in this Act as the licensing authority), 
    after making such inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, shall, 
    subject to the other provisions of this Act, by order in writing either 
    grant the licence or refuse to grant the same.1[6B. 
    Grant of licences.—(1) 
    Where a person makes an application for licence under section 5, the 
    authority prescribed in the rules made under that section for grant of 
    licences (hereinafter referred to in this Act as the licensing authority), 
    after making such inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, shall, 
    subject to the other provisions of this Act, by order in writing either 
    grant the licence or refuse to grant the same." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    licensing authority shall grant a licence— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where it is required for the purpose of 
    manufacture of explosives if the licensing authority is satisfied that the 
    person by whom licence is required— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    possesses technical know-how and 
    experience in the manufacture of explosives; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    has in his employment or undertakes to 
    employ a person or persons possessing such technical know-how and 
    experience; or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where it is required for any other 
    purpose, if the licensing authority is satisfied that the person by whom 
    licence is required has a good reason for obtaining the same.] 
 
 



 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6C</number> Refusal of 
    licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6B, the licensing authority 
    shall refuse to grant a licence—1[6C. 
    Refusal of licences.—(1) 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6B, the licensing authority 
    shall refuse to grant a licence—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where such licence is required in 
    respect of any prohibited explosives; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where such licence is required by a 
    person whom the licensing authority has reason to believe— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    to be prohibited by this Act or by any 
    other law for the time being in force to manufacture, possess, sell, 
    transport, import or export any explosive, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    to be of unsound mind, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    to be for any reason unfit for a 
    licence under this Act; or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where the licensing authority deems it 
    necessary for the security of the public peace or for public safety to 
    refuse to grant such licence. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    licensing authority refuses to grant a licence to any person it shall record 
    in writing the reasons for such refusal and furnish to that person on demand 
    a brief statement of the same unless in any case the licensing authority is 
    of opinion that it will not be in the public interest to furnish such 
    statement.] 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6D</number> Licensing 
    authority competent to impose conditions in addition to prescribed 
    conditions.—A 
    licence granted under section 6B may contain in addition to prescribed 
    conditions such other conditions as may be considered necessary by the 
    licensing authority in any particular case.]1[6D. 
    Licensing authority competent to impose conditions in addition to prescribed 
    conditions.—A 
    licence granted under section 6B may contain in addition to prescribed 
    conditions such other conditions as may be considered necessary by the 
    licensing authority in any particular case.]" 
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6E</number> Variation, 
    suspension and revocation of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The licensing authority may vary the conditions subject to which a licence 
    has been granted except such of them as have been prescribed and may for 
    that purpose require the holder of licence by notice in writing to 
    deliver-up the licence to it within such time as may be specified in the 
    notice.1[6E. 
    Variation, suspension and revocation of licences.—(1) 
    The licensing authority may vary the conditions subject to which a licence 
    has been granted except such of them as have been prescribed and may for 
    that purpose require the holder of licence by notice in writing to 
    deliver-up the licence to it within such time as may be specified in the 
    notice." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    licensing authority may, on the application of the holder of a licence, also 
    vary the conditions of the licence except such of them as have been 
    prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    licensing authority may, by order in writing, suspend a licence for such 
    period as it thinks fit or revoke a licence,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if the licensing authority is satisfied 
    that the holder of the licence is prohibited by this Act or by any other law 
    for the time being in force to manufacture, possess, sell, transport, import 
    or export any explosive, or is of unsound mind, or is for any reason unfit 
    for a licence under this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if the licensing authority deems it 
    necessary for the security of the public peace or for public safety to 
    suspend or revoke the licence; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    if the licence was obtained by the 
    suppression of material information or on the basis of wrong information 
    provided by the holder of the licence or any other person on his behalf at 
    the time of applying for the licence; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    if any of the conditions of the licence 
    has been contravened; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    if the holder of the licence has failed 
    to comply with a notice under sub-section (1) requiring him to deliver-up 
    the licence. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    licensing authority may also revoke a licence on the application of the 
    holder thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    licensing authority makes an order varying the conditions of a licence under 
    sub-section (1) or an order suspending or revoking a licence under 
    sub-section (3), it shall record in writing the reasons therefor and furnish 
    to the holder of the licence on demand a brief statement of the same unless 
    in any case the licensing authority is of the opinion that it will not be in 
    the public interest to furnish such statement. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A court 
    convicting the holder of a licence of any offence under this Act or the 
    rules made thereunder may also suspend or revoke a licence: 
 
Provided that 
    if the conviction is set aside on appeal or otherwise, the suspension or 
    revocation shall become void. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> An order 
    of suspension or revocation under sub-section (6) may also be made by an 
    appellate court or by the High Court when exercising its powers of revision. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Central Government may, by order in the Official Gazette, suspend or revoke, 
    or direct any licensing authority to suspend or revoke, all or any licences 
    granted under this Act throughout India or any part thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> On the 
    suspension or revocation of a licence under this section the holder thereof 
    shall without delay surrender the licence to the authority by whom it has 
    been suspended or revoked or to such other authority as may be specified in 
    this behalf in the order of suspension or revocation.] 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6F</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the licensing authority refusing to 
    grant a licence or varying the conditions of a licence or by an order of the 
    licensing authority suspending or revoking a licence may prefer an appeal 
    against that order to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the 
    appellate authority) and within such period as may be prescribed:1[6F. 
    Appeals.—(1) 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the licensing authority refusing to 
    grant a licence or varying the conditions of a licence or by an order of the 
    licensing authority suspending or revoking a licence may prefer an appeal 
    against that order to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the 
    appellate authority) and within such period as may be prescribed\:" 
 
Provided that 
    no appeal shall lie against an order made by, or under the direction of the 
    Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal 
    shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period 
    prescribed therefor: 
 
Provided that 
    an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor 
    if the appellant satisfies the appellate authority that he had sufficient 
    cause for not preferring the appeal within that period. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The period 
    prescribed for an appeal shall be computed in accordance with the provisions 
    of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), with respect to the computation of 
    periods of limitation thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    appeal under this section shall be made by a petition in writing and shall 
    be accompanied by a brief statement of the reasons for the order appealed 
    against where such statement has been furnished to the appellant and by such 
    fee as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    disposing of an appeal the appellate authority shall follow such procedure 
    as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    no appeal shall be disposed of unless the appellant has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The order 
    appealed against shall, unless the appellate authority conditionally or 
    unconditionally directs otherwise, be in force pending the disposal of the 
    appeal against such order. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every 
    order of the appellate authority confirming, modifying or reversing the 
    order appealed against shall be final.] 
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Power to make rules conferring powers of inspection, search, seizure, 
    detention and removal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government 

    1[***] may make rules 
    consistent with this Act authorising any officer, either by name or in 
    virtue of his office——(1) 
    The Central Government 

    2[***] may make rules 
    consistent with this Act authorising any officer, either by name or in 
    virtue of his office—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to enter, inspect and examine
    2[any 
    place, aircraft, carriage or vessel] in which an explosive is being 
    manufactured, possessed, used, sold, 
2[transported, 
    imported or exported] under a licence granted under this Act, or in which he 
    has reason to believe that an explosive has been or is being manufactured, 
    possessed, used, sold, 
3[transported, 
    imported or exported] in contravention of this Act or of the rules made 
    under this Act;1[any 
    place, aircraft, carriage or vessel] in which an explosive is being 
    manufactured, possessed, used, sold, 
2[transported, 
    imported or exported] under a licence granted under this Act, or in which he 
    has reason to believe that an explosive has been or is being manufactured, 
    possessed, used, sold, 
2[transported, 
    imported or exported] in contravention of this Act or of the rules made 
    under this Act;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to search for explosives therein; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to make samples of any explosive found 
    therein on payment of the value thereof; and 
 

4[(d)    
    to seize, detain and remove any explosive or ingredient thereof found 
    therein and, if necessary, also destroy such explosive or ingredient.] 3[(d) 
    to seize, detain and remove any explosive or ingredient thereof found 
    therein and, if necessary, also destroy such explosive or ingredient.]" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of the 

    5[Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] relating to searches under that Code shall, so 
    far as the same are applicable, apply to searches by officers authorised by 
    rules under this section. 
 
 

 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Notice of accidents.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    Whenever there occurs in or about, or in connection with, any place in which 
    an explosive is manufactured, possessed or used, or 

    2[any aircraft, 
    carriage or vessel] either conveying an explosive or on or from which an 
    explosive is being loaded or unloaded, any accident by explosion or by fire 
    attended with loss of human life or serious injury to person or property, or 
    of a description usually attended with such loss or injury, the occupier of 
    the place, or 

    3[the master of the 
    aircraft or vessel], or the person in charge of the carriage, as the case 
    may be, shall 

    4[within such time and 
    in such manner as may be by rule prescribed give notice thereof and of the 
    attendant loss of human life or personal injury, if any, to the 


    5[Chief Controller of 
    Explosives] and] to the officer in charge of the nearest police station.
 


    6[***] 
 
 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>9</number> Inquiry into 
    accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any accident such as is referred to in section 8 
    occurs in or about or in connection with 

    2[any place, aircraft, 
    carriage or vessel] under the control of any of 

    3[Armed Forces of the 
    Union], an inquiry into the causes of the accident shall be held by the 
    naval, military, or air force authority concerned, and where any such 
    accident occurs in any other circumstances, the District Magistrate 


    4[***] shall, in cases 
    attended by loss of human life, or may, in any other case, hold or direct a 
    Magistrate subordinate to him to hold, such an inquiry. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    person holding an inquiry under this section shall have all the powers of a 
    Magistrate in holding an inquiry into an offence under the 

    5[Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] and may exercise such of the powers conferred 
    on any officer by rules under section 7 as he may think it necessary or 
    expedient to exercise for the purposes of the inquiry. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The person 
    holding an inquiry under this section shall make a report to the Central 
    Government stating the causes of the accident and its circumstances. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government may make rules— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to regulate the procedure at inquiries 
    under this section; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to enable the 
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] to be present or represented at any such inquiry;
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] to be present or represented at any such inquiry;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to permit the 
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] or his representative to examine any witnesses at 
    the inquiry;
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] or his representative to examine any witnesses at 
    the inquiry;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    to provide that where the 
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] is not present or represented at any such inquiry, 
    a report of the proceedings thereof shall be sent to him;
6[Chief 
    Controller of Explosives] is not present or represented at any such inquiry, 
    a report of the proceedings thereof shall be sent to him;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    to prescribe the manner in which and 
    the time within which notices referred to in section 8 shall be given.] 
 
 
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 <title></title>
 THE EXPLOSIVES ACT, 1884
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>9A</number> Inquiry into more serious accidents. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, where it is of opinion, whether or not it has received the report of an inquiry under section 9, that an inquiry of more formal character should be held into the causes of an accident such as is referred to in section 8, appoint the 8 [Chief Controller of Explosives] or any other competent person to hold such inquiry, and may also appoint one or more persons possessing legal or special knowledge to act as assessors in such inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the Central Government orders an inquiry under this section, it may also direct that any inquiry under section 9 pending at the time shall be discontinued. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The person appointed to hold an inquiry under this section shall have all the powers of a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the purposes of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and compelling the production of documents and material objects; and every person required by such person as aforesaid to furnish any information shall be deemed to be legally bound so to do within the meaning of section 176 of the Indian Penal Code  
  (45 of 1860). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any person holding an inquiry under this section may exercise such of the powers conferred on any officer by rules under section 7 as he may think it necessary or expedient to exercise for the purposes of the inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The person holding an inquiry under this section shall make a report to the Central Government stating the causes of the accident and its circumstances, and adding any observations which he or any of the assessors may think fit to make; and the Central Government shall cause every report so made to be published at such time and in such manner as it may think fit. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government may make rules for regulating the procedure at inquiries under this section.] 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum><title>[<number>9B</number> Punishment for certain offences.</title> — 1) Whoever, in contravention of rules made under section 5 or of the conditions of a licence granted under the said rules— 
 <section> <number>a</number> manufactures, imports or exports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term, which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> possesses, uses, sells or transports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to three thousand rupees or with both; and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> in any other case, with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> Whoever in contravention of a notification issued under section 6 manufactures, possesses or imports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both; and in the case of importation by water, the owner and master of the vessel or in the case of importation by air, the owner and the master of the aircraft, in which the explosive is imported shall, in the absence of reasonable excuse, each be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>3</number> Whoever,— 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> manufactures, sells, transports, imports, exports or possesses any explosive in contravention of the provisions of clause (a) of section 6A; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> sells, delivers or despatches any explosive in contravention of the provisions of clause (b) of that section, 
 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with both; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> in contravention of the provisions of section 8 fails to give notice of any accident shall be punishable,— 
 <subsubsubsection><number>i</number> with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection> <number>ii</number>  if the accident is attended by loss of human life, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine or with both.] 




</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <title>[<number>9C</number> Offences by companies. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, or was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment under this Act if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge and that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against the punished accordingly. 
 Explanation. —For the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “company” means any body corporate, and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.] 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Forfeiture of explosives.—When a 
    person is convicted of an offence punishable under this Act or the rules 
    made under this Act, the court before which he is convicted may direct that 
    the explosive, or ingredient of the explosive, or the substance (if any) in 
    respect of which the offence has been committed, or any part of that 
    explosive, ingredient or substance, shall, with the receptacles containing 
    the same, be forfeited. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11</number> Distress of 
    aircraft or vessel.—Where the owner or master of any aircraft or vessel 
    is adjudged under this Act to pay a fine for any offence committed with, or 
    in relation to, that aircraft or vessel, the Court may, in addition to any 
    power it may have for the purpose of compelling payment of the fine, direct 
    it to be levied by distress and sale of,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the aircraft and its furniture or so 
    much of the furniture, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the vessel and the tackle, apparel and 
    furniture of such vessel or so much of the tackle, apparel and furniture 
    thereof, 
 
as is necessary for the payment of the fine.]
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Abetment and attempts.—Whoever 
    abets, within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), the 
    commission of an offence punishable under this Act, or the rules made under 
    this Act, attempts to Act, or commit any such offence and in such attempt 
    does any act towards the commission of the same, shall be punished as if he 
    had committed the offence. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Power to arrest without warrant persons committing dangerous offences.—Whoever 
    is found committing any act for which he is punishable under this Act or the 
    rules under this Act, and which tends to cause explosion or fire in or about 
    any place where an explosive is manufactured or stored, or any railway or 
    port, or any carriage, 

    1[aircraft or vessel], 
    may be apprehended without a warrant by a police officer, or by the occupier 
    of, or the agent or servant of, or other person authorised by the occupier 
    of, that place, or by any agent or servant of, or other person authorised 
    by, the railway administration or 

    2[conservator of the 
    port or officer in charge of the airport], and be removed from the place 
    where he is arrested and conveyed as soon as conveniently may be before a 
    Magistrate.—Whoever 
    is found committing any act for which he is punishable under this Act or the 
    rules under this Act, and which tends to cause explosion or fire in or about 
    any place where an explosive is manufactured or stored, or any railway or 
    port, or any carriage, 

    2[aircraft or vessel], 
    may be apprehended without a warrant by a police officer, or by the occupier 
    of, or the agent or servant of, or other person authorised by the occupier 
    of, that place, or by any agent or servant of, or other person authorised 
    by, the railway administration or 

    3[conservator of the 
    port or officer in charge of the airport], and be removed from the place 
    where he is arrested and conveyed as soon as conveniently may be before a 
    Magistrate." 
 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>14</number> Saving and 
    power to exempt.—
<section><number>1</number> Nothing in this Act, except sections 8, 9 and 9A 
    shall apply to the manufacture, possession, use, transport or importation of 
    any explosive— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by any of the 
2[Armed 
    Forces of the Union, and Ordnance factories or other establishments of such 
    Forces] in accordance with rules or regulations made by 
3[***] 
    the Central Government;
2[Armed 
    Forces of the Union, and Ordnance factories or other establishments of such 
    Forces] in accordance with rules or regulations made by 
3[***] 
    the Central Government;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by any person employed under
    4[the 
    Central Government or under a State Government] in execution of this Act.
4[the 
    Central Government or under a State Government] in execution of this Act." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette exempt, 
    absolutely or subject to any such conditions as it may think fit to impose,
    

    5[any explosive and 
    any person or class of persons from all or any of the provisions of this Act 
    or the rules made thereunder]. 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Saving of Arms Act, 1959.—Nothing in this Act shall affect 
      the provisions of the 1[Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 
      1959)]:—Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the provisions of the 

    6[Arms Act, 1959 (54 
    of 1959)]\:" 
 Provided that an authority granting a licence under this Act for 
      the manufacture, possession, sale, transport or importation of an 
      explosive may, if empowered in this behalf by the rules under which the 
      licence is granted, direct by an order written on the licence that it 
      shall have the effect of a like licence granted under the said 
      2[***] Arms Act. 
 
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Saving 
    as to liability under other law.—Nothing 
    in this Act or the rules under this Act shall prevent any person from being 
    prosecuted under any other law for any act or omission which constitutes an 
    offence against this Act or those rules, or from being liable under that 
    other law to any other or higher punishment or penalty than that provided by 
    this Act or those rules: 
 
Provided that 
    a person shall not be punished twice for the same offence. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Extension of definition of “explosive” to other explosive substances.—The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, declare that any substance which appears to the Central Government 
    to be specially dangerous to life or property, by reason either of its 
    explosive properties or of any process in the manufacture thereof being 
    liable to explosion, shall be deemed to be an explosive within the meaning 
    of this Act, and the provisions of this Act (subject to such exceptions, 
    limitations and restrictions as may be specified in the notification) shall 
    accordingly extend to that substance in like manner as if it were included 
    in the definition of the term “explosive” in this Act. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Extension of definition of “explosive” to other explosive substances.—The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, declare that any substance which appears to the Central Government 
    to be specially dangerous to life or property, by reason either of its 
    explosive properties or of any process in the manufacture thereof being 
    liable to explosion, shall be deemed to be an explosive within the meaning 
    of this Act, and the provisions of this Act (subject to such exceptions, 
    limitations and restrictions as may be specified in the notification) shall 
    accordingly extend to that substance in like manner as if it were included 
    in the definition of the term “explosive” in this Act. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>17A</number> Power to 
    delegate.—The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, direct that any power or function which may be exercised or 
    performed by it under this Act other than the power under sections 5, 6, 6A, 
    14 and 17 may, in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, 
    if any, as it may specify in the notification, be exercised or performed 
    also by— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    such officer or authority subordinate 
    to the Central Government, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    such State Government or such officer 
    or authority subordinate to the State Government.] 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Procedure for making, publication and confirmation of rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An authority making rules under this Act shall, before making the rules, 
    publish a draft of the proposed rules for the information of persons likely 
    to be affected thereby. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    publication shall be made in such manner as the Central Government, from 
    time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette prescribes1. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> There 
    shall be published with the draft a notice specifying a date at or after 
    which the draft will be taken into consideration. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    authority making the rules shall receive and consider any objection or 
    suggestion which may be made by any person with respect to the draft before 
    the date so specified. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    rule made under this Act shall not take effect 

    2[***] until it has 
    been published in the Official Gazette 

    2[***]. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    publication in the Official Gazette of a rule purporting to be made under 
    this Act shall be conclusive evidence that it has been duly made, and, if it 
    requires sanction, that it has been duly sanctioned. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All powers 
    to make rules conferred by this Act may be exercised from time to time as 
    occasion requires. 
 


    3[(8) Every rule made 
    under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.] 
  








 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Ordinance 18 of 1945, sec. 3, for section 9A.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 32 of 1978, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 32 of 1978, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 
    1978, sec. 14, for section 11 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983). tc " 
    1. Subs. by Act 32 of 1978, sec. 14, for section 11 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 
    1978, sec. 15, for “ship or boat” (w.e.f. 2-3-1983). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 32 of 1978, sec. 15, for “ship or boat” (w.e.f. 
    2-3-1983)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Ordinance 18 
    of 1945, sec. 4, for section 14. tc " 1. Subs. by 
    Ordinance 18 of 1945, sec. 4, for section 14."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 
      1978, sec. 17, for “Indian Arms Act, 1878 (11 of 1878)” (w.e.f. 2-3-1983). tc 
    " 6. Subs. by Act 32 of 1978, sec. 17, for “Indian Arms Act, 1878 (11 of 
    1878)” (w.e.f. 2-3-1983)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 32 of 
    1978, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983). tc " 1. Ins. by Act 
    32 of 1978, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 2-3-1983)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   For mode prescribed 
    see Gazette of India, 1927, Pt. I, p. 769. tc " 2. 
    For mode prescribed see Gazette of India, 1927, Pt. I, p. 769."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>