<act> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 19781
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Iron Ore Mines 

2[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Rules, 1978.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st day of September, 1978.
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>1</number> ‘Act’ means the Iron Ore Mines
1[, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Act, 1976 (61 of 
1976);
 </section><section>       <number>2</number> ‘Advisory Committee’ means an Advisory Committee 
constituted under section 5 of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>3</number> ‘Central Advisory Committee’ means a Central 
Advisory Committee constituted under section 6 of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>4</number> ‘Chairman’ means the Chairman of an Advisory 
Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be;
 </section><section>       <number>5</number> ‘Committee’ means the Advisory Committee or the 
Central Advisory Committee;
 </section><section>       <number>6</number> ‘Form’ means a Form in Schedule VI;
 </section><section>       <number>7</number> ‘Fund’ means the Iron Ore Mines
1[, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund formed under 
section 3;
 </section><section>       <number>8</number> ‘Member’ means a member of an Advisory Committee 
or the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be, and include the Chairman 
and Vice-Chairman of such Committee;
 </section><section>       <number>9</number> ‘Schedule’ means a Schedule appended to these 
rules;
 </section><section>      <number>10</number> ‘section’ means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>      <number>11</number> ‘Treasury’ means any Government treasury or 
sub-treasury;
 </section><section>      <number>12</number> ‘Welfare Commissioner’ means a Welfare 
Commissioner appointed under section 8.
  


</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>3</number> Composition of the Central 
Advisory Committee and State Advisory Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The Central Advisory Committee shall consist 
of the following persons to be appointed by the Central Government, 
namely:—
          
1[(i)  Chairman;
 <subsubsection>        <number>ii</number>  an 
officer of the Central Government who shall be the Vice-Chairman, ex 
officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>iii</number>  two officers 
of the Central Government to be nominated by the Government, ex 
officio;
        
2[(iv)  three Welfare Commissioners, to be nominated by the Central 
Government, ex officio;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>v</number>  such number of 
persons to represent the owners of iron ore mines, manganese ore mines and 
chrome ore mines as are equal in number to the aggregate of those provided in 
sub-clauses (ii) to (iv) to be appointed, after consultation with such 
organisations, if any, of the owners, as may be recognised by the Central 
Government in this behalf;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>vi</number>  such number of 
persons, of whom one shall be a woman, to represent the persons employed in iron 
ore mines, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines as are equal in number to 
those provided in sub-clause (v) to be appointed, after consultation with such 
organisations, if any, of persons so employed, as may be recognised by the 
Central Government in this behalf;]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The Central Government shall 
appoint one of its officers as the Secretary of the Central Advisory Committee 
and the Secretary so appointed shall be entitled to attend and take part in the 
meetings of the Central Advisory Committee, but shall not be entitled to 
vote.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> (a) Each Advisory Committee 
shall consist of the following persons, to be appointed by the Central 
Government, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the 
Chairman;
         
3[(ii)  Vice-Chairman;]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  4[two officers] of 
the Central Government, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  a member of 
the Legislative Assembly of the State concerned appointed in consultation with 
the Government of such State;
         
5[(v)  Three persons to represent the owners of Iron Ore Mines, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines to be appointed after consultation with 
such organisation, if any, of the owners of such mines as may be recognised by 
the Central Government in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>  Three persons 
to represent the persons employed in the Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore Mines and 
Chrome Ore Mines to be appointed after consultation with the organisation of the 
persons so employed as may be recognised by the Central Government in this 
behalf.]
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  a woman, if no 
woman has been appointed under sub-clause (v) or sub-clause (vi). 
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> An officer of the Iron Ore 
6[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour 
Welfare] Organisation in the State concerned shall be appointed as the Secretary 
of the Advisory Committee and the Secretary so appointed shall be entitled to 
attend and take part in the meetings of the Advisory Committee, but shall not be 
entitled to vote.
  






</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>3</number> Composition of the Central 
Advisory Committee and State Advisory Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> The Central Advisory Committee shall consist of the following persons to be 
appointed by the Central Government, namely:—
 
         1[(i)  
Chairman;
 <subsubsection>        <number>ii</number>  an officer of the Central Government who shall 
be the Vice-Chairman, ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>iii</number>  two officers of the Central Government to be 
nominated by the Government, ex officio;
 
       2[(iv)  
three Welfare Commissioners, to be nominated by the Central Government, ex 
officio;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>v</number>  such number of persons to represent the owners 
of iron ore mines, manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines as are equal in 
number to the aggregate of those provided in sub-clauses (ii) to (iv) to be 
appointed, after consultation with such organisations, if any, of the owners, as 
may be recognised by the Central Government in this behalf;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>vi</number>  such number of persons, of whom one shall be a 
woman, to represent the persons employed in iron ore mines, manganese ore mines 
and chrome ore mines as are equal in number to those provided in sub-clause (v) 
to be appointed, after consultation with such organisations, if any, of persons 
so employed, as may be recognised by the Central Government in this behalf;]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The Central Government shall 
appoint one of its officers as the Secretary of the Central Advisory Committee 
and the Secretary so appointed shall be entitled to attend and take part in the 
meetings of the Central Advisory Committee, but shall not be entitled to vote.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> (a) Each Advisory Committee 
shall consist of the following persons, to be appointed by the Central 
Government, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the Chairman;
 
        3[(ii)  
Vice-Chairman;]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> 
4[two 
officers] of the Central Government, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  a member of the Legislative Assembly of the 
State concerned appointed in consultation with the Government of such State;
 
        5[(v)  
Three persons to represent the owners of Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore Mines and 
Chrome Ore Mines to be appointed after consultation with such organisation, if 
any, of the owners of such mines as may be recognised by the Central Government 
in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>  Three persons to represent the persons employed 
in the Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines to be appointed 
after consultation with the organisation of the persons so employed as may be 
recognised by the Central Government in this behalf.]
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  a woman, if no woman has been appointed under 
sub-clause (v) or sub-clause (vi). 
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> An officer of the Iron Ore


6[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines Labour Welfare] Organisation in the State concerned shall be appointed as 
the Secretary of the Advisory Committee and the Secretary so appointed shall be 
entitled to attend and take part in the meetings of the Advisory Committee, but 
shall not be entitled to vote.
  







</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>4</number> Term of office of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> A member (other than an ex officio member) shall, unless he resigns 
his office, or dies or otherwise vacants his office at an earlier date, hold 
office for a period not exceeding three years, as may be specified by the 
Central Government in each case while making the appointment, from the date of 
publication in the Official Gazette of the notification appointing him as such 
member and shall be eligible for reappointment:
 Provided that an outgoing member 
shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is notified in 
the Official Gazette.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> An ex officio member 
shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A member appointed to fill a 
casual vacancy shall hold office for as long as the member, whose place he 
fills, would have been entitled to hold office if the vacancy had not occurred.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If a member is unable to 
attend a meeting of the Central Committee or Advisory Committee, as the case may 
be, then in the case of a member appointed under sub-clause (iv) or sub-clause 
(v) of clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 or sub-clause (v) or sub-clause (vi) 
of clause (a) or sub-clause (a) of sub-rule (2) of that rule, the body which is 
represented by him in the Central Advisory Committee or the Advisory Committee, 
as the case may be, may, by notice in writing signed on its behalf and by the 
said member, addressed to the Chairman concerned depute, and in other cases the 
Central Government may nominate, a substitute in his place to attend the meeting 
and such deputed or nominated member shall have all the rights of a member in 
respect of that meeting.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>5</number> Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A non-official member other than the Chairman may resign his office by writing 
under his hand addressed to the Chairman.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairman may resign his 
office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The resignation shall take 
effect from the date of its acceptance or on the expiry of thirty days from the 
date of its receipt by the Chairman or, as the case may be, the Central 
Government, whichever is earlier.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>6</number> Absence from India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before a non-official member leaves India he shall intimate to the Chairman the 
date of his departure from and the date of his expected return to India, and if 
he intends to be absent from India for a period longer than six months, he shall 
tender his resignation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any such member leaves 
India without intimation as required under sub-rule (1), he shall be deemed to 
have resigned with effect from the date of his departure from India.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>7</number> Vacation of office.—A 
non-official member shall be deemed to have vacated his office—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  if he becomes of unsound mind or is declared 
insolvent; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  if he is convicted for any offences which, in 
the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  if he is absent from three consecutive meetings 
of the Committee without leave of absence from the Chairman; or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  if, in the opinion of the Central Government, it 
is not desirable that he should continue to be a member;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  in the case of a member of a Legislative 
Assembly on his ceasing to be a member of such Legislative Assembly; or
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  if he ceases to represent the interest for 
representing which he was appointed.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article>

1[<number>8</number> Allowances payable to members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every non-official member shall be entitled to receive travelling allowance, 
daily allowance and conveyance allowance in accordance with the instructions 
contained in the Ministry of Finance, O.M. No. F.6(26)-EIV/59, dated 5th 
September, 1960, as for the time being in force.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The allowance under this 
rule shall be admissible only on production of a certificate by the non-official 
members to the effect that they have not claimed or drawn travelling, daily or 
conveyance allowance in respect of journeys and halts from any other source.]
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>9</number> Disposal of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every question which the Committee is required to take into consideration shall 
be considered either at a meeting or, if the Chairman so directs, by sending the 
necessary papers to every member for opinion:
 Provided that the papers shall 
be sent to each member by registered post with acknowledgment due and with the 
request that the views of the member should reach the office of the Committee 
within the period specified in the notice:
 Provided further that the papers 
need not be sent to a member who is absent from India.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a question is referred 
to the Committee for opinion, any member may request that the question be 
considered at a meeting of the Committee and thereupon the Chairman may, and, if 
the request is made by three or more members, shall, direct that it be so 
considered.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If not less than three 
members of the Committee request the Chairman to refer any matter to the 
Committee, the Chairman shall refer that matter to it accordingly.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>10</number> Time, place and date of 
meetings.—The Committee shall meet at 
such place and on such date and at such time as may be appointed by the 
Chairman.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>11</number> Notice of meetings and 
list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice shall be 
given to every member present in India of the time and place fixed for each 
ordinary meeting at least fifteen days before such meeting and every member 
shall be furnished with a list of business to be considered at the meeting.
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) An emergency meeting of 
the Committee may be called by the Chairman to discuss matters on which a 
decision has to be taken immediately.
 <subsection><number>b</number> Notice shall be given either 
by registered post or by telegram or in person, to every member present in 
India, of the place, time and date of an emergency meeting at least four days 
before such meeting and every member shall be furnished with a list of business 
to be considered at the meeting.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> No business which is not 
included in the list of business shall be considered at a meeting without the 
permission of the Chairman.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>12</number> Presiding at meetings.—The 
Chairman shall preside at every meeting at which he is present and, in his 
absence, the Vice-Chairman shall preside.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>13</number> Quorum.—No 
business shall be transacted at a meeting (whether ordinary or emergent) of the 
Committee unless at least one-third of the total number of members of the 
Committee having the right to vote are present and at least one of the members 
so present is the Chairman or the Vice-Chairman:
 Provided that if at any meeting, 
less than one-third of the total number of members are present the Chairman or, 
in his absence, the Vice-Chairman may adjourn the meeting to a date not later 
than seven days from the date of the meeting informing the members present and 
sending registered notice to the other members that he proposes to dispose of 
the business at the adjourned meeting whether there is quorum or not.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>14</number> Recommendation by 
majority.—
<section><number>1</number> Every question at a 
meeting of the Committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members 
present and voting on that question, but the minority shall in all cases have 
the right of requiring their dissent to be noted.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every question referred to 
the members for opinion shall, unless the Chairman in pursuance of sub-rule (2) 
of rule 9 reserves it for consideration at a meeting, be decided in accordance 
with the opinion of the majority of members recording opinion within the time 
specified.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of an equal 
division of votes or opinion, the Chairman shall have an additional or casting 
vote whether the matter is considered at a meeting of the Committee or by 
sending the papers for the opinion of members.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>15</number> Minutes of meetings.—The 
proceedings of each meeting of the Committee shall be circulated to all members 
present in India, as soon as may be after the meeting and shall be read out and 
confirmed at the next meeting of the Committee and signed by the Chairman, or, 
as the case may be, the Vice-Chairman, presiding at such next meeting and shall 
thereafter be recorded in a minute book, which shall be kept for permanent 
record.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>16</number> Headquarters of the Central 
Advisory Committee or an Advisory Committee.—The Headquarters of the Central Advisory Committee 
shall be in New Delhi and the headquarters of an Advisory Committee shall be at 
such place as may be fixed by the Central Government.
  </article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>16</number> Headquarters of the 
Central Advisory Committee or an Advisory Committee.—The 
Headquarters of the Central Advisory Committee shall be in New Delhi and the 
headquarters of an Advisory Committee shall be at such place as may be fixed by 
the Central Government.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>17</number> Chief Executive of an 
Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Welfare 
Commissioner shall be Chief Executive of an Advisory Committee and exercise the 
executive functions of the Advisory Committee on its behalf.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Secretary of an Advisory 
Committee shall carry out routine duties and shall exercise such powers and 
discharge such duties as the Welfare Commissioner, may, with the approval of the 
Central Government, delegate to him.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Welfare Commissioner may 
authorise the staff of the Advisory Committee to give assistance to any member 
of an Advisory Committee or of a sub-committee of the Advisory Committee or to 
any other authority exercising executive or advisory functions in connection 
with the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>18</number> Conditions of service of 
persons appointed under section 8.—Persons 
appointed under section 8 shall be governed by such rules relating to the terms 
and conditions of service as are applicable to Central Government servants.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>19</number> Power of Welfare 
Commissioner to incur expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Welfare Commissioner shall have power, subject to the provisions in the 
sanctioned budget, to incur expenditure on administrative staff and welfare 
schemes:
 Provided that—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  he 
shall have no powers to sanction any scheme, if it involves expenditure 
exceeding Rs. 50,000 non-recurring and Rs. 5,000 recurring in a year; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  in the 
case of a new scheme, the approval of the Finance Sub-Committee of the Advisory 
Committee concerned shall have to be obtained before it is sanctioned by the 
Welfare Commissioner or any expenditure on it is incurred.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Welfare Commissioner may 
sanction, without reference to the Advisory Committee, expenditure on 
contingencies, supplies and services and purchases of articles required for the 
running of the organisation under him subject to financial provision in the 
sanctioned budget and subject to the condition that the expenditure on any 
single object shall not exceed Rs. 2,000 non-recurring and Rs. 400 recurring.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>20</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The annual budget as prepared by the Welfare Commissioner in consultation with 
the Finance Sub-Committee shall be considered by the Advisory Committee 
concerned each year and thereafter a copy of the budget, as approved by the 
Advisory Committee, shall be forwarded not later than the 1st day of October 
each year for sanction to the Central Government which may make such alterations 
therein as it considers necessary before according its sanction.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The budget to be forwarded 
to the Central Government shall be accompanied by detailed self-contained notes 
explaining new schemes included therein.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>21</number> Other matters to be 
considered by an Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An Advisory Committee shall, besides carrying out its other duties, consider and 
advice upon any matter arising out of the administration of these rules which 
may be referred to it by the Central Government or the State Government for 
advice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An Advisory Committee may 
also consider any other matter that may be placed before it by the Welfare 
Commissioner with the prior permission of the Chairman.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>22</number> Committee to be informed 
of expenditure.—A memorandum setting 
forth any grant made of expenditure incurred since the last meeting shall be 
laid at each meeting of an Advisory Committee.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>23</number> Finance Sub-Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An Advisory Committee shall elect from among its members two persons of whom one 
shall be a person to represent owners of the iron ore mines or manganese ore 
mines or both and the other to represent the persons employed in the iron ore 
mines or manganese ore mines or both to constitute a Finance Sub-Committee of 
which the Welfare Commissioner shall be an additional member and Chairman.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An Advisory Committee may at 
any time co-opt a person or persons to the Finance Sub-Committee and any person 
so co-opted shall exercise all the powers and functions of a member of the 
Finance Sub-Committee, but shall not be entitled to vote and shall not solely by 
reason of being co-opted as a number of the Finance Sub-Committee be a member of 
the Advisory Committee.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notice of every meeting of 
the Finance Sub-Committee shall be sent to the Chairman of the Advisory 
Committee who may attend such meeting if he so desires, and if he does so 
attend, he shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), preside at 
the meeting and shall be entitled to vote.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>24</number> Duties of the Finance 
Sub-Committee.—The duties of the 
Finance Sub-Committee shall be to frame schemes of expenditure, to advice on the 
budget drawn up by the executive of the Advisory Committee and on the accounts 
of the Advisory Committee and also in regard to all expenditure and to consider 
all schemes referred to in clause (ii) of the proviso to rule 19.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>25</number> Other Sub-Committees.—An 
Advisory Committee may, as and when considered necessary, constitute from among 
its members as many sub-committees as it may deem necessary for considering and 
reporting on such matters as may be specifically referred to it.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>26</number> Meetings of 
Sub-Committees.—The meetings and 
proceeding of the Finance Sub-Committee and any other sub-committee which may be 
constituted under rule 25 shall, mutatis mutandis, be governed by the 
provisions herein contained for regulating the meetings and proceedings of an 
Advisory Committee.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>27</number> Grants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In each case in which a grant is made by or with the approval of the Central 
Government to a State Government, a local authority or the owner of an iron ore 
mine or a manganese ore mine, in aid of any scheme, approved by the Central 
Government, for the purposes of the Act, the Central Government may impose 
conditions necessary for ensuring,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  that the work 
for which the grant is made is duly and promptly executed and the money is 
actually utilised for the purpose for which it is granted;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  that the data 
on which the grant is calculated are in accordance with facts;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  that any 
particulars which the Central Government may from time to time require for the 
proper discharge of its responsibilities are promptly supplied;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  that all 
necessary facilities for inspection are accorded to persons duly authorised by 
the Central Government for the purpose of satisfying itself that the provisions 
of clause (a) are complied with or for checking the correctness of any 
particulars supplied under clause (c) or for the collection of such particulars;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  that proper 
accounts of the money granted are kept and are submitted for audit by such 
persons as the Central Government may authorise in this behalf.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  that an 
additional statement of accounts together with a certificate of a Registered 
Accountant or other recognised body of auditors to the effect that the accounts 
are correct, is furnished by the grantee, and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  that the 
labour employed on regular basis and that employed on contract basis are given 
same welfare facilities.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Before making grant to a 
local authority, or to the owner of an iron ore mine or manganese ore mine the 
Central Government shall require such local authority or owner to execute a bond 
for the fulfilment of the conditions imposed by the Central Government under 
sub-rule (1).
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be a condition of 
every bond executed under sub-rule (2) that in the event of the local authority 
or owner of the mine violating any condition imposed under sub-rule (1) such 
local authority or owner shall be liable to pay to the Central Government a sum 
not exceeding the amount paid as grant by way of penalty in addition to the 
refund or the entire remaining grant; and where the amount of penalty and the 
remaining grant aid is huge payment may be allowed to be made in two or three 
instalments.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>28</number> Standard of dispensary 
and hospital services.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
standard of dispensary or hospital services to be provided by owners of iron ore 
mines or manganese ore mines 

1[and chrome ore mines] for the purpose 
of getting the grant-in-aid under clause (c) of section 4 shall be as specified 
in Schedule II or Schedule III, as the case may be (hereafter in this rule and 
in rules 29 and 31 referred to as the prescribed standard).
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be maintained an 
independent dispensary or hospital at the site of each iron ore or manganese ore 
mine according to the prescribed standard:
 Provided that a common main 
dispensary or hospital may be maintained for several iron ore mines or manganese 
ore mines 

1[and chrome ore mines] with branch 
dispensaries or hospitals attached to each iron ore mine or manganese ore mine 
subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the 
common main dispensary or hospital shall maintain the standards prescribed for 
the aggregate number of workers of all the iron ore or manganese ore mines
1[and 
chrome ore mines] served by it or the standard maintained by it during the year 
1975, whichever is higher;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  every 
branch dispensary or hospital shall have a qualified doctor and a qualified 
compounder (pharmacist);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  the common 
main dispensary or hospital shall be so situated that none of the iron ore or 
manganese ore mines
1[and 
chrome ore mines] served by it is more than fifteen kilometers away from it; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  the common 
main dispensary or hospital shall maintain an ambulance van for taking serious 
cases of injury and sickness from the branch dispensary or hospital to the 
common main dispensary or hospital.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Welfare Commissioner 
may, if he is satisfied that any dispensary or hospital is being efficiently run 
and serves the purpose for which it is established for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, waive any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard:
 Provided that no such dispensary 
or hospital shall contain any room other than a store room which is less than 
four meters by three metres in area:
 Provided further that a medical 
licentiate may be appointed to be incharge of a dispensary or hospital catering 
to more than 250 workers only if he has ten years experience as a medical 
officer in independent charge of a main dispensary.
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article>

1[<number>29</number> Inspection of dispensary or 
hospital.—The dispensary or hospital 
services maintained by owners of iron ore mines or manganese ore mines 

2[or chrome ore mines] shall be inspected 
at intervals not exceeding one year by such medical or other officer as may be 
authorised by the Welfare Commissioner for the purpose or by the Welfare 
Commissioner himself whenever he considers it necessary and the inspecting 
officer or the Welfare Commissioner, as the case may be, shall if the dispensary 
or hospital conforms to the prescribed standard, issue a certificate in Form A 
which shall be valid for a period of one year from the date of the issue.]
  




</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>30</number> Submission of periodic 
returns.—Every owner of an iron ore 
mine or manganese ore mine who maintains a dispensary or hospital service 
according to the prescribed standard shall submit to the Welfare Commissioner:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  in 
January and July of each year a statement showing the total amount of iron ore 
or manganese ore produced in his mine during the preceding six months; and
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  in 
January of each year a certified statement of expenditure incurred on the 
dispensary or hospital during the preceding twelve months.
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>31</number> Standard of maternity 
centre.—
<section><number>1</number> The standard of maternity 
centre to be provided by owners of iron ore mines or manganese ore mines 

1[and chrome ore mines] for the purpose 
of getting the grants-in-aid under clause (c) of section 4, shall be as 
specified in Schedule IV (hereafter in this rule and in rules 32, 33 and 34 
referred to as the prescribed standard).
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be maintained an 
independent maternity centre at the site of each iron ore or manganese ore mines


1[and chrome ore mines] according to the 
prescribed standards:
 Provided that a common main 
maternity centre may be maintained for several iron ore or manganese ore mines


1[and chrome ore mines] with branch 
maternity centres attached to each iron ore or manganese ore mine subject to the 
following conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the 
common main maternity centre shall maintain the prescribed standard for the 
aggregate number of workers of all iron ore or manganese ore mines
1[and 
chrome ore mines] served by it or the standard maintained by it during the year 
1975, whichever is higher;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  every 
branch maternity centre shall have a qualified doctor and a qualified compounder 
(pharmacist);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  the common 
main maternity centre shall be so situated that none of the iron ore or 
manganese ore mines
1[and 
chrome ore mines] served by it is more than fifteen kilometres away from it; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  the common 
main maternity centre shall maintain an ambulance van for taking serious cases 
from the branch maternity centres to the common maternity centre.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Welfare Commissioner 
may, if he is satisfied that a maternity centre is being efficiently run and 
serves the purpose for which it is established, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, waive any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard:
 Provided that the functions of a 
lady health visitor may be performed by a fully qualified and registered 
mid-wife who has not less then ten years’ experience as a mid-wife:
 Provided further that a lady 
medical licentiate may be appointed to be incharge of a maternity centre 
catering to more than 1,000 workers if she has ten years’ experience as medical 
officer in independent charge of a mine maternity centre.
  


</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article>

1[<number>32</number> Inspection of maternity centre.—The 
maternity centre maintained by owners of iron ore or manganese ore mines 

2[and chrome ore mines] shall be 
inspected at intervals not exceeding one year by such medical or other officer 
as may be authorised by the Welfare Commissioner for the purpose or by the 
Welfare Commissioner himself whenever he considers it necessary and the 
Inspecting Officer or the Welfare Commissioner, as the case may be, shall, if 
the centre conforms to the prescribed standard, issue a certificate in Form ‘B’ 
which shall be valid for a period of one year from the date of issue.]
  




</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>33</number> Submission of periodic 
returns.—Every owner of an iron ore 
or a manganese ore mine who maintains a maternity centre according to the 
prescribed standard shall submit to the Welfare Commissioner in January of each 
year a certified statement of the expenditure incurred on the maternity centre 
during the preceding twelve months.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>34</number> Extent of grant-in-aid.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every owner of an iron ore mine or a manganese ore mine who maintains a 
dispensary, hospital or a maternity centre for the benefit of labour employed in 
his mine which conforms to the prescribed standard under rule 28 or rule 31, as 
the case may be, and is subject to inspection under rule 29 or 32, as the case 
may be, shall, if he desires to carry on improvement of the 

1[existing facilities] be eligible for 
grant-in-aid in respect of non-recurring expenditure on such improvement as the 
Central Government may decide, subject to the condition that it shall not exceed 
50 per cent. of the said expenditure.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every owner of an iron ore 
mine or a manganese ore mine who maintains a dispensary, hospital or maternity 
centre for the benefit of the labour employed in his mine shall, if the Welfare 
Commissioner is of opinion that the dispensary, hospital or maternity-centre 
conforms to the prescribed standard, be eligible to a grant-in-aid which shall 
not exceed,—
 
2[(i)  
the amount of duty at the rate of five paise per tonne recovered in respect of 
iron ore or manganese ore produced by the mine less the proportionate cost of 
recovery; or]
 <subsection>        <number>ii</number>  75 per 
cent of the amount spent by the owner of the mine on the maintenance of the 
dispensary, hospital or maternity centre as determined by the Welfare 
Commissioner whichever is less.
 Provided that in the case of a 
dispensary, hospital or maternity centre which serves other workers and the 
members of the public, the amount spent by the owner of the mine on the 
maintenance of the dispensary, hospital or maternity centre service for the 
purpose of this clause may, if separate expenditure figures are not available, 
be determined by the Chairman on proportionate basis.
  




</subsection></section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>35</number> Standard of facilities 
for education and recreation.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
standard of facilities for education and recreation of workers to be provided by 
owners of iron ore mines or manganese ore mines 

1[and chrome ore mines] for the purpose 
of getting grants-in-aid under clause (c) of section 4 shall be as specified in 
Schedule V, (hereafter in this rule and in rules 36, 37 and 38 referred to as 
the prescribed standard).
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be maintained an 
independent welfare centre at the site of each iron ore mine or manganese ore 
mine according to the prescribed standard.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Welfare Commissioner 
may, if he is satisfied that the centre is being efficiently maintained and 
serves the purpose for which it is established, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, waive any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard.
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>36</number> Inspection.—The 
welfare centre maintained by owners of iron ore mines or manganese ore mines


1[and chrome ore mines] shall be 
inspected at intervals not exceeding one year by such officer as may be 
authorised by the Welfare Commissioner for the purpose or by the Welfare 
Commissioner himself wherever he considers it necessary and the inspecting 
officer or the Welfare Commissioner, as the case may be, shall, if the centre 
conforms to the prescribed standard, issue a certificate in Form C which shall 
be valid for a period of one year from the date of issue.
  



</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>37</number> Submission of periodic 
returns.—Every owner of an iron ore 
mine or manganese ore mine who maintains a welfare centre according to the 
prescribed standard shall submit to the Welfare Commissioner—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  
immediately on the establishment of the Welfare Centre, adequate proof to the 
satisfaction of the Welfare Commissioner showing the capital expenditure 
incurred on the construction and equipment of the Welfare Centre; and
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  in 
January each year a certified statement of the expenditure incurred on the 
welfare centre during the preceding twelve months:
 Provided that the statement 
shall not include expenditure, if any, incurred on repairs and replacements.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>38</number> Extent of grant-in-aid.—Every 
owner of an iron ore mine or a manganese ore mine who maintains a welfare centre 
for the benefit of the labour employed in his mine which conforms to the 
prescribed standard and is subject to inspection under rule 36 shall be eligible 
to a grant-in-aid which shall not exceed 50 per cent of the amount spent by the 
owner of the mine in construction and equipment of the welfare centre subject to 
a maximum of Rs. 10,000.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>39</number> Statistics and other 
information.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent or 
manager of an iron ore mine or manganese ore mine or the occupier of the 
metallurgical factory, as the case may be, shall furnish such statistics or 
other information as the Central Government or any person authorised by that 
Government may, by written order, require for the purposes of the Act in Form 
‘D’ and within such time (being not less than thirty days from the date on which 
the order is served on to the persons concerned) and in such manner as may be 
specified in the order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any owner, agent or manager 
of an iron ore mine or manganese ore mine or the occupier of a metallurgical 
factory, as the case may be, who, without reasonable excuse, fails to furnish 
the statistics or other information required under sub-rule (1) or furnishes 
statistics or other information containing a statement, entry or detail which is 
not, to the best of his knowledge or belief, true, shall be punishable with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees.
  
</section></article><form>
 

The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
 

 
 



1[***]
 

—————
 

     1.   Schedule I omitted by the Iron Ore Mines, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Fund (Second Amendment) 
Rules, 1989 (w.e.f. 21-4-1990).
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
 

 
 




Schedule V
 




Standard of Facilities For  Education and  

recreation welfare centre
 


(See 
rule 35)
 



Welfare centre
 


I. Accommodation
 


(a)  1. One hall of 45 
square metres.
 


      2. Two rooms of 15 
square metres each
 


      3. Covered Verandah 
18 square metres
 


      4. One Lavatory for 
men
 


      5. One Lavatory for 
women
 


      6. One bath room for 
children
 


(b)  Play ground of the 
size of 36 metres x 18 metres
 


(c)  Children’s Park 
equipments—
 


(i)   
Swing                                                                                              
1 set
 


(ii)  Ocean 
wave                                                                                    
1
 


(iii) Sea 
Saw                                                                                          
1
 


(iv) 
Slides                                                                                              
1
 


II. Staff
 


1.   Adult Education 
Instructor-cum-Games Supervisor
 


2.   Sevika
 


III. Furniture &amp; Equipment
 


1.  
Table                                                                                                  
1
 


2.  
Chair                                                                                                  
2
 


3.  Chair Steel 
folding                                                                              
6
 


4.  Notice 
Board                                                                                       
1
 


5.  
Benches                                                                                             
2
 


6.  Black 
Board                                                                                        
1
 


7. Steel Almirah                                                                                      
1
 


8. Coir mat 15 metres x 1 
metre                                                            1
 


9. Radio with loud 
speaker                                                                     1
 


10. Slates, Slate Pencils, 
Chalk, etc.                                                       As necessary
 


11. Books, charts, maps, 
etc.                                                                  As 
necessary
 


12. Petromax (if no 
electricity is available)                                              1
 


13. Dholak                                                                                              
1
 


14. Jhals                                                                                                 
4 pairs
 


15. Volley ball court 
equipment, ball etc.                                                1 set
 


16. Tennikoit 
set                                                                                     
1
 


17. Carrom 
Board                                                                                   
2
 


18. 
Chess                                                                                               
2
 


19. Ludo                                                                                                 
3
 


20. Newspapers and 
Periodicals                                                             As 
necessary
 


21. Sewing 
machine                                                                                
1
 


22. 
                                                                                                         
Scissors          1 pair
 


23. 
Tape                                                                                                 
1
 


24. Knitting and crochet 
needles                                                            As necessary
 


25. Raw 
materials                                                                                   
As necessary
 


26. 
                                                                                                         
Gong  1
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese 
Ore Mines and chrome ore mines labour welfare fund rules, 1978
 

 
 




Schedule VI
 




Form A
 


(See 
rule 29)
 




Certificate  of  Inspection
 


Inspection report of 
the...................................Dispensary or hospital 
at.......................by the.......................for the 
year.....................ending.............20.......
 


1.   Name of Iron Ore 
Mine/Manganese Ore Mine 

1[/Chrome Ore Mine] 
served by Dispensary or hospital.
 


2.   Number of workers for 
which it caters
 


3.   Date and hour of 
Inspection
 


4.   Date of last 
Inspection
 


5.   Dispensary or hospital 
buildings
 


(a)  Condition of 
Dispensary or hospital building.
 


(b)  Does the accommodation 
provided conform to the prescribed standard?
 


6.   Medicines—
 


(a)  Is the supply 
sufficient and according to the prescribed scale?
 


(b)  Are the poisons 
labelled and kept separately under lock and key?
 


7.   Surgical instruments 
and equipments—
 


      Are they sufficient 
and in good order?
 


8.   Staff Acquittance 
Rolls—Are they in order and upto date?
 


9.   Registers and 
Returns—Are these properly kept and regularly submitted?
 


10. Establishment.
 


(a) Officer-in-charge
 


(i)   Part time/whole time.
 


(ii)  Name and 
qualifications.
 


(b)  Designation and pay of 
staff
 


(i)     Medical Graduate
 


(ii)    Medical Licentiate
 


(iii)   Lady Doctor
 


(iv)   Nurse
 


(v)    Compounder
 


(vi)   Auxiliary Nurse 
Midwife
 


(vii)  Male Dresser
 


(viii)  Female Dresser
 


(ix)   Sweeper
 


(x)    Chowkidar
 


(xi)   Peon.
 


(c)  Attendance Register—Do 
the staff attend regularly?
 


11. Annual expenditure on—
 


(a)  Establishment
 


(b)  Medicines.
 


12. Out-patients—
 


(a)  Number seen at the 
time of visit
 


(b)  Total number of new 
patients treated in current year up-to-date
 


(c)  Total number of old 
patients treated in current year up-to-date
 


(d)  Total treated during 
the last year.
 


(e)  Do the entries on 
tickets of patients present tally with the entries on the registers
 


(f)   Are there any 
arrangements for treating women apart from men?
 


13. In-patients—
 


(a)  Number seen at the 
time of visit
 


(b)  Total number of 
patients in current year up-to-date
 


14. Are you satisfied with 
the working of the dispensary or hospital? If not, what suggestions can be made 
for its improvements?
 


I certify that I have 
inspected the dispensary or hospital noted above and that it conforms/does not 
conform in the following respects* to the  standards laid down in the Iron Ore 
Mines 

2[, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Fund Rules, 1978].
 



                                                Signature of Inspecting Officer 
with date
 



                                                Counter signature of 
Commissioner with date
 


*Give details below:
 


Note.—The 
counter signature of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner 
himself is the Inspecting Authority.
 




Form B
 


(See 
rule 32)
 




Certificate  of  Inspection
 


Inspection report of the 
Maternity Centre at.................................by 
the.......................... for the year................... 
ending.............20.....
 


1.   Name of Iron Ore 
Mine/Manganese Ore Mine 

3[/Chrome Ore Mine] 
served by the Maternity Centre.
 


2.   Number of workers for 
which it caters.
 


3.   Date and hour of 
Inspection.
 


4.   Date of last 
inspection
 


5.   Maternity Centre 
Buildings.—
 


(a)  Condition of Maternity 
Centre Buildings.
 


(b)  Does the accommodation 
provided conform to the prescribed standard?
 


6.   Medicines—
 


(a)  Is the supply 
sufficient and according to the prescribed scale?
 


(b)  Are the poison 
labelled and kept separately under lock and key?
 


7.   Surgical Instruments 
and equipments—
 


      Are they sufficient 
and in good order?
 


8.   Staff Acquittance 
Rolls—
 


      Are they in order and 
up-to-date?
 


9.   Registers and Returns—
 


      Are these properly 
kept and regularly submitted?
 


10. Establishment—
 


(a)  Officer-in-Charge.
 


(i)     
Part-time/whole-time
 


(ii)    Name and 
qualifications
 


(b)  Designation and Pay of 
Staff—
 


(i)     Medical Graduate
 


(ii)    Medical Licentiate
 


(iii)    Lady Doctor
 


(iv)   Compounder
 


(v)    Nurse
 


(vi)   Midwife
 


(vii)   Ayah
 


(viii)  Sweeper
 


(ix)   Ward Attendant
 


(x)    Cook.
 


(c)  Attendance Registers—
 


      Do the staff attend 
regularly?
 


11. Annual expenditure on—
 


(a)  Establishment
 


(b)  Medicines
 


12. Out patients—
 


(a)  Number seen at the 
time of visit
 


(b)  Total number of new 
patients treated in current year up-to-date
 


(c)  Total number of old 
patients treated in current year up-to-date
 


(d)  Total treated during 
the last year
 


(e)  Do the entries on 
tickets of patients present tally with the entries on the register?
 


13. Are you satisfied with 
the working of the Maternity Centre? If not what suggestions can you make for 
its improvements?
 


I certify that I have 
inspected the Maternity Centre noted above and that conform/does not conform in 
the following respects* to the standards laid down in the Iron Ore Mines 

4[, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Rules, 1978.
 


Signature of the Inspecting 
Officer with date 
 


Counter Signature of 
Commissioner with date
 


*Give details below.
 


Note.—The 
counter signature of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner 
himself is the Inspecting Authority.
 




Form C
 


(See
rule 36)
 




Certificate of Inspection of the Welfare Centre
 


Inspection report of 
the............................... Welfare Centre 
at............................... by the ........................ for the 
year..................ending.......................20.........
 


1.   Name of Iron Ore 
Mine/Manganese Ore Mine 

5[/Chrome Ore Mine] 
served by the Centre.
 


2.   Number of workers for 
which it caters.
 


3.   Date and hour of 
inspection.
 


4.   Date of last 
inspection.
 


5.   Centre Building—
 


      (a) Condition of the 
building.
 


      (b) Does the 
accommodation provided conform to the prescribed standard?
 


6.   Equipment—
 


      (a) Are the 
equipments provided according to the prescribed standard?
 


      (b) Is timely 
repairs/replacement done where necessary?
 


      (c) Are the 
equipments all in serviceable condition?
 


7.   Establishments—
 


      (a) 
Officer-in-Charge—
 


           (i)   
Part-time/whole-time
 


           (ii)  Name and 
qualification
 


      (b) Designation and 
pay of staff—
 


           (i)   Adult 
Education Instructor
 


           (ii)  Sevika
 


           (iii)  Sweeper
 


      (c) Attendance 
Register—
 


           Do the staff 
attend regularly?
 


8.   Annual expenditure—
 


      (a) Establishments.
 


      (b) Repairs and 
replacements of of equipments.
 


9.   Activities—
 


      (a) Total number of 
rolls attending the centre
 


      (b) Number seen at 
the time of inspection
 


      (c) Number of adults 
attending literacy classes
 


      (d) Number of women 
attending craft classes
 


      (e) Number of adults 
participating in games and sports
 


10. Are you satisfied with 
the working of the centre? If not, what suggestion can  

be made for its improvements?
 


I certify that I have 
inspected the Welfare Centre noted above and that it conforms/does not conform 
in the following respects* to the standard laid down in the Iron Ore Mines


6[, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Rules, 1978.
 



                                            Signature of Inspecting Officer with 
date 
 



                                            Counter Signature of Commissioner 
with date.
 


*Give details below.
 


Note.—The 
counter Signature of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner 
himself is the Inspecting Authority.
 




Form D
 


(See 
rule 39)
 




Statistics  and  Other  Information
 


1.   Name of 
Mine/Metallurgical Factory
 


2.   Location and full 
address of mine/metallurgical factory
 


3.   Name of owner/manager 
of mine/occupier of factory
 


4.   Number of persons 
employed in the mine/metallurgical factory from.......20 
........to........20.....
 


(a)  Male
 


(b)  Female
 


(c)  Children
 


Total..............
 


5.   Details of welfare 
facilities provided by the mine/metallurgical factory to the persons employed in 
the mine/metallurgical factory.
 


(a)  Housing
 


(b)  Medical
 


(c)  Water supply
 


(d)  Recreation
 


(e)  Any other activities
 


6.   Quantum of Cess paid 
by the owner of mine/occupier of metallurgical factory under the Iron Ore Mines 
and Manganese Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Act, 1976, (61 of 1976) during the 
period from................ 20........ to ...... 20...
 


      Certified that the 
above paticular are true to the best of my knowledge and belief and are based on 
the records maintained in mine/factory.
 


 
 



No                                                                                      
Owner/Agent/Manager of Mine/
 



Date......................                                                             
Occupier of factory
 


Place......................
 


 
 


-----------------
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
535(E),  dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
535(E), dated  28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


   3.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
535(E), dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


   4.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
535(E), dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


   5.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
535(E), dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


   6.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
535(E), dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).
 


 
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>