<act><title>The
Banking Regulation (Co-operative Societies) Rules, 19661

</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Banking (Co-operative Societies) Rules, 1966.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number> “the Act” means the Banking
Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949); 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “commencement
of these rules” means— 
 
 


 <subsection>
<number>i</number> in
the case of a Co-operative Society which at the commencement of the Banking Laws
(Application to Co-operative Societies) Act, 1965 (23 of 1965) is a Co-operative
Bank and is carrying on the business of banking, the date on which these rules
come into force; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> in
the case of a Co-operative Society which becomes a Co-operative Bank or which
commences banking business as a Co-operative Bank after the commencement of the
Banking Laws (Application to Co-operative Societies) Act, 1965 (23 of 1965) the
date on which these rules come into force or the date on which the Co-operative
Society so becomes a Co-operative Bank or so commences banking business,
whichever is later; 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> “Form”
means a form appended to these rules; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “place
of business” of a Co-operative Bank includes any sub-office, pay-office,
sub-pay-office and any place of business, at which deposits are received,
cheques cashed, moneys lent, or any other form of business referred to in
sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act is transacted; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number> “principal
office of the Co-operative Bank” means the office of the Co-operative Bank
which will be responsible for the submission of the returns prescribed under the
Act or these rules; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>f</number>
“principal office of the Reserve Bank” means,— 
 
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
in relation to a primary Co-operative Bank, the office of the Urban Banks
Department of the Reserve Bank; and 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
in relation to a Central Co-operative Bank or a State Co-operative Bank,
the office of the Rural Planning and Credit Department of the Reserve Bank—to
which the returns prescribed under the Act or these rules are required to be
submitted;] 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>g</number> “quarter”
means a period of three months ending on the last day of March, June, September
or December of any year; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>h</number> all
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall
have the same meanings as assigned to them under the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section>

<number>i</number> references in these rules to
sections of the Act shall means references to those sections as applied to or in
relation to co-operative societies by section 56 of the Act.

   




</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>3</number>
Submission of returns.—
<section><number>1</number>
A return prescribed under the Act or these rules shall be submitted in the form
prescribed for the purpose or as near thereto as circumstances admit.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Such return shall be submitted by the principal office of a Co-operative Bank to
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Principal
office] of the Reserve Bank situated in the State in which the Co-operative Bank
has its principal office or to such other office of the Reserve Bank as may be
specified by the Reserve Bank on an application to be made <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[in
this behalf—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> by
a primary Co-operative Bank to the Reserve Bank of India, Central Office, Urban
Bank Department, Bombay; and 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> by
a Central Co-operative Bank or a State co-operative to the Reserve Bank of
India, Central Office, Rural Planning and Credit Department, Bombay.] 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
A Co-operative Bank shall intimate to the principal office of the Reserve Bank,
the address of its principal office within one month from the commencement of
these rules and any change in such address within one month of such change.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2), the Reserve Bank may, at any
time, direct that the returns prescribed under the Act or these rules shall be
submitted from any other specified office of a Co-operative Bank to any other
specified office of the Reserve Bank.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Wherever a return prescribed under the Act or these rules relates to a
particular day or date, the return shall be prepared on the basis of the figures
of that day or date in respect of offices working on that day or date, date and
the preceding working day’s figures in respect of offices where that day or
date is a holiday.



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>4</number>
List of Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> A Co-operative
Bank shall, not later than one month from the commencement of these rules, send
to the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[office
specified in sub-rule (2)] a written statement containing a list of—
 


 <subsection> <number>a</number>
the names, the official designations and specimen signatures of the
officers authorised to sign on behalf of the Co-operative Bank returns required
to be submitted under the Act or these rules, and 
 

 </subsection><subsection> <number>b</number>
the names and addresses of the Directors of the Co-operative Bank or the
members of the committee of management of the Co-operative Bank. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
The statement containing the lists referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of
sub-rule (1) shall be sent by a primary Co-operative Bank to the principal
office of the Reserve Bank and by a Central Co-operative Bank and a State
Co-operative Bank to the principal office of the Reserve Bank, and also to the
office of the National Bank situated in the State in which the Co-operative Bank
has its principal office or to such other office of the National Bank as may be
specified by the National Bank.]
 


 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>]
Any change in the list referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be intimated to the
principal office of the Reserve Bank <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[and,
in the case of a Central Co-operative Bank and a State Co-operative Bank, also
to the office of the National Banks as specified under sub-rule (2)] within one
month from the occurrence of such change. 


   









</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>5</number>
Form of statement of liabilities and cash reserve and other assets.—The
return to be submitted under section 18 and sub-section (3) of section 24 of the
Act shall be in Form I and the return to be submitted under sub-section (2) of
section 20 of the Act shall be in Form II.] 


  










</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>6</number>
Licensing of co-operative societies.—A Co-operative Society or a bank
desiring to have a licence under section 22 of the Act shall apply to the
principal office of the Reserve Bnk in the Form specified below, namely:—
 


 <section>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> in the case of a
Co-operative Society desiring to commence banking business after the
commencement of the Banking Laws (Application to Co-operative Societies) Act,
1965 (23 of 1965),— 
 
 


 <subsection>
<number>1</number> as a primary Co-operative Bank,
in Form IIIA, 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number> as a Central Co-operative Bank,
in Form IIIB, and 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> as a State Co-operative Bank, in
Form IIIC]; 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>b</number> in the case of a Co-operative Society, which at the commencement of
the Banking Laws (Application to Co-operative Societies) Act, 1965 (23 of 1965),
was carrying on business as a Co-operative Bank, or a Co-operative Bank which
has come into existence as a result of the division of any other Co-operative
Society carrying on business as a Co-operative Bank, or the amalgamation of two
or more co-operative societies carrying on banking business or a primary credit
society which becomes a primary Co-operative Bank after such commencement, and
desires to carry on banking business, in Form IV.] 


   










</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>7</number>
Opening of new places of business.—An application by a Co-operative Bank
for permission to open a new place of business or change the location of an
existing place of business under section 23 of the Act shall be submitted <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[in 
Form V—
 <section> 
 
<number>a</number> in the case of a primary Co-operative
Bank to the principal office of the Reserve Bank; and 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
in the case of a Central Co-operative Bank or a State Co-operative Bank
to the office of the National Bank situated in the State in which the
co-operative has its principal office or to such other office of the National
Bank as may be specified by the National Bank, and an advance copy of the
application be submitted directly to the principal office of the Reserve Bank.] 










</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>8</number>
A list relating to the offices of a Co-operative Bank shall be sent, within a
period of one month from the close of every quarter, in Form VI,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
by a primary Co-operative Bank to the principal office of the Reserve
Bank; and 
 
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
by a Central Co-operative Bank or a State Co-operative Bank to the
principal office of the Reserve Bank and also to such office of the National
Bank as may be specified by the National Bank.]


</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>9</number>
Other returns.—The returns to be
submitted under section 26 and sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 27 shall be in Form
VIII and Form IX respectively].



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>10</number>
Manner of publication of accounts and balance-sheet.—The
balance-sheet and profit and loss account prepared in pursuance of section 29 of
the Act together with the auditor’s report shall be published within a period
of nine months from the end of the period to which they relate in a newspaper
which is in circulation at the place where the Co-operative Bank has its
principal office.
 


 Explanation
1.—For the purposes of this rule,
the expression “newspaper” means any newspaper or journal published at least
once a week but does not include a journal other than a banking, commercial,
financial or economic journal.
 


 <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Explanation
2.—In the case of a Co-operative Bank the deposit liabilities of which as
at the end of the period to which the accounts and balance-sheet relate do not
exceed <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[twenty]
lakhs of rupees, a display, in a conspicuous place at the principal office, and
at every place of business of such bank, of a copy of the balance-sheet and
profit and loss account with the auditor’s report shall be deemed to
constitute compliance with the provision of this rule.]
 


   






</article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>
Manner of holding inquiries.—
<section><number>1</number> For
the purpose of holding an inquiry under sub-section (2) of section 47A of the
Act, the Reserve Bank shall appoint in writing one of its officers (hereinafter
referred to as the said Officer) for holding the inquiry and shall also
authorise him to exercise the powers conferred on the Reserve Bank under
sub-section (3) of the said section 47A.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The said office shall send by registered post to the co-operative bank at its
Registered office or principal office, a statement giving sufficient particulars
of the contravention or default of the nature referred to in sub-section (3) or
sub-section (4) of section 46 of the Act.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A Co-operative Bank to which a statement is addressed under sub-rule (2), shall,
before the expiry of 30 days from the receipt of such statement, send in writing
to the said officer its answer to the said statement together with particulars
of the documentary or other evidence on which it proposes to rely.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The said officer shall appoint a date and place for holding the inquiry and
intimate the same by registered post to the Co-operative Bank at its Registered
office or principal office and the date so appointed shall not be earlier than
thirty days from the date of issue of the statement to the Co-operative Bank.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
At the inquiry, the Co-operative Bank shall be entitled to be represented by any
of its Directors or officers as its authorised representative but shall not be
entitled to be represented by a legal practitioner.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
At the inquiry, an officer of the Reserve Bank, not being the officer conducting
the inquiry, shall present the case for the Reserve Bank including evidence on
the matter. Thereafter, the authorised representative of the Co-operative Bank
shall present its case including the evidence in relation thereto.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
On the date appointed for the purpose under sub-rule (4), the Co-operative Bank
shall be represented at the inquiry by its authorised representative and the
said officer shall commence the inquiry on the same day, unless, for reasons to
be recorded in writing and communicated to the Co-operative Bank in person or by
registered post, he adjourns the hearing to a later date. Such date shall not be
earlier than fifteen days from the date of issue of such communication to the
Co-operative Bank.
 


 </section><section><number>8</number>
In case the authorised representative of the Co-operative Bank fails to appear
before the said officer on the appointed date or such adjourned date, as the
case may be, without sufficient cause, the said officer shall proceed with the
inquiry ex parte and give his findings on the basis of the evidence
placed before him by the officer of the Reserve Bank presenting the case.
 


 </section><section><number>9</number>
Once the inquiry has commenced, it shall be continued on day-to-day basis,
including holidays, until all the witness for the Reserve Bank and the
Co-operative Bank have been examined, unless the said officer, for reasons to be
recorded in writing, decides that adjournment of the inquiry is necessary beyond
the following day.
 


 </section><section><number>10</number>
The authorised representative of the Co-operative Bank and the officer of the
Reserve Bank presenting the case may cross-examine the witnesses other than a
witness produced by the representative of the Co-operative Bank or, as the case
may be, by the officer of the Reserve Bank presenting the case.
 


 </section><section><number>11</number>
After the conclusion of the inquiry, the said officer shall record his findings
and submit the entire record to the Reserve Bank.]




</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>12</number>]
Banking Companies Rules, 1949, not to apply.—Nothing
contained in the Banking Companies Rules, 1949, shall apply to co-operative
societies.



</article><form>
 

The
Banking Regulation (Co-operative Societies) Rules, 19661 


 

  


 

[FORM VII]1
 

 
 

----------
 

1.
forms VII omitted by S.O. 1326, dated 23rd May, 1974 (w.e.f. 1-6-1974)
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by S.O. 269 (E),
dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Ins. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Sub-rule (2) renumbered as sub-rule (3) by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th
March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1326, dated 23rd May, 1974 (w.e.f. 1-6-1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by S.O. 269 (E),
dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Subs. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Subs. by S.O. 269 (E), dated 29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 29-3-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1326, dated 23rd May, 1974 (w.e.f. 1-6-1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 209, dated 30th October, 1969 (w.e.f. 7-2-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by S.O. 700, dated
31st January, 1979 (w.e.f. 24-2-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 271, dated
17th February, 1983 (w.e.f. 2-4-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>
Rule 11 renumbered as rule 12 by G.S.R. 271, dated 17th February, 1983 (w.e.f.
2-4-1983).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>