<act><tid>196539</tid>
<title>THE HIGH COURT JUDGES (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 28 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 20th May, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to regulate certain conditions of service of the Judges of 
High Courts <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>691030</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the High Court Judges 
 (Conditions of Service) Act, <year>1954</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1589226</tid>
<number> 2</number> 
<section><tid>1527492</tid>
<number>1</number>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires,-

<subsection><tid>1999885</tid>
<number>a</number>" acting Chief Justice" means a Judge appointed under 
article 223 of the Constitution to perform the duties of the 
Chief Justice;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1369342</tid>
<number>b</number>" acting Judge" means a person <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appointed to act 
as a Judge under sub- section (2) of section 222 of the 
Government of India Act, <year>1935</year> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or under clause (2) of 
article 224 of the Constitution];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1751219</tid>
<number>c</number>" actual service" includes-

<subsubsection><tid>1006517</tid>
<number>i</number>time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge or in the 
performance of such other functions as he may, at the 
request of the President of India, undertake to 
discharge;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1795555</tid>
<number>ii</number>vacations, excluding any time during which the 
Judge is absent on leave;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1354430</tid>
<number>iii</number>Joining time on transfer from a High Court to 
the Supreme Court or from one High Court to another or 
from the Supreme Court to a High Court;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>897006</tid>
<number>iv</number>time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge of a for- 
mer Indian High Court;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1902264</tid>
<number>v</number>time spent by a Judge to attend the sittings of 
the Supreme Court as an ad hoc Judge under article 
 127 of the Constitution; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words and letter" in Part A States" omitted by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" who was" omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Added, ibid.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>104032</tid>
<number>vi</number>vacation (excluding any time during which the  
  Judge was absent on leave) taken by a Judge as a Judge 
of a former Indian High Court;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1959589</tid>
<number>d</number>" additional Judge" means a person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appointed as 
an additional Judge under sub- section (3) of section 222 of 
the Government of India Act, <year>1935</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or under clause (1) of 
article 224 of the Constitution];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>105021</tid>
<number>e</number>" former Indian High Court" means the High Court at 
Rangoon, the High Court at Lahore, the Chief Court of Sind or 
the Judicial Commissioner' s Court of North- West Frontier 
Province;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>250999</tid>
<number>f</number>" High Court" means a High Court <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> for a State] and 
includes a High Court which was exercising Jurisdiction <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in 
a Part A State or] in the corresponding Province before the 
commencement of the Constitution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1609750</tid>
<number>g</number>" Judge" means a Judge of a High Court and includes the 
Chief Justice <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> an acting Chief Justice, an additional 
Judge and an acting Judge of the High Court];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>538658</tid>
<number>gg</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" pension" means a pension of any kind whatsoever 
payable to or in respect of a Judge, and includes any 
gratuity or other sum or sums so payable by way of death or 
retirement benefits;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>839112</tid>
<number>h</number>" service for pension" includes-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1521707</tid>
<number>i</number>actual service;

<subsubsection><tid>100074</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the amount, actually taken, of each period of 
leave on full allowances at a rate equal to the monthly 
rate of the salary;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1552018</tid>
<number>iii</number>joining time on return from leave out of 
India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1928603</tid>
<number>i</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>714923</tid>
<number>2</number>In the calculation of service for the purposes of this Act, 
previous service for any period or periods as acting Judge or 
additional Judge or as a Judge of a former Indian High Court shall be 
reckoned as service as a Judge but, save as otherwise expressly 
provided, previous service as an acting Chief Justice shall not be 
reckoned as service as Chief Justice.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" who was" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) 
Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Added, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs:, ibid., for" in any Part A State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Sub. by Act 46 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2, for" and acting Chief 
 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins by Act 50 of <year>1961</year>. s. 2 (retrospectively).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1980</year> s. 2, for sub- clause (ii).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1729142</tid>
<number>3</number>Any period of leave taken by a Judge before the commencement 
of this Act under the rules then applicable to him as an acting Judge, 
additional Judge or a Judge shall, for the purposes of this Act, be 
treated as if it were leave taken by him under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>873439</tid>
<number>4</number>Any period of leave taken by a Judge while serving as a Judge 
of a former Indian High Court before his appointment to a High Court 
shall for the purposes of this Act be treated as if it were leave 
taken by him under this Act.
CHAP

LEAVE

CHAPTER II

LEAVE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1033303</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1599369</tid>
<number>1</number>Kinds of leave admissible to a judge. Subject to the  
provisions of this Act, leave granted to a Judge may be at his option 
either-

<subsection><tid>540936</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> leave on full allowances (including commuted leave on  
half allowances into leave or full allowances on medical 
  certificate); or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1243690</tid>
<number>b</number>leave on half allowances; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1840427</tid>
<number>c</number>leave partly on full allowances and partly on half 
allowances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>560962</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this Chapter, any period of leave on 
full allowances shall be reckoned as double that period of leave on 
half allowances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1384684</tid>
<number> 4</number> 
<section><tid>170800</tid>
<number>1</number>Leave account showing the amount of leave due. A leave  
account shall be kept for each Judge showing therein the amount of 
leave due to him in terms of leave on half allowances.

</section>

<section><tid>361707</tid>
<number>2</number>In the leave account of a Judge-

<subsection><tid>1076727</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be credited to him-

<subsubsection><tid>266149</tid>
<number>i</number>one- fourth of the time spent by him on actual 
service;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1832425</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the Judge, by reason of his having been 
detained for the performance of duties not connected with 
the High Court, cannot enjoy any vacation which 
would otherwise have been entitled to enjoy had he not 
been so detained, as compensation for the vacation not 
enjoyed, a period equal to double the period by which 
the vacation enjoyed by him in any year falls short of 
one month; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>470779</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> where the Judge had, prior to his appointment as 
such, held any pensionable post under the Union or a 
State, the period of leave earned by him in the said 
post, so, however, that such period shall not exceed two 
hundred and forty days in terms of leave on full 
allowance; and.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1279481</tid>
<number>b</number>there shall be debited to him all leave with all by 
him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1971</year>, s. 3, for clause (a)  (w. e. f. 15. 1. <year>1972</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted and ins. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977</tid>
<number> 5</number> 
<section><tid>191101</tid>
<number>1</number>Aggregate amount of leave which may be granted. The  
aggregate amount of leave which may be granted to a Judge during 
the whole period of his service as such shall not exceed in terms of 
leave on half allowances three years together with the aggregate of 
the periods, if any, credited to his leave account under sub- section (2) 
 (a)  (ii) of section 4 as compensation for vacation not enjoyed.

</section>

<section><tid>877244</tid>
<number>2</number>The aggregate amount of leave on full allowances which may 
be granted to a Judge during the whole period of his service as such 
shall not exceed one- twenty- fourth of the period spent by him on 
actual service together with one- half of the aggregate periods, if 
any, credited to his leave account under sub- section 2 a ii of 
section 4 as compensation for vacation not enjoyed.

</section>

<section><tid>253692</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 
5A, the maximum period of leave which may be granted] at one time 
shall be, in the case of leave on full allowances, five months and in 
the case of leave with allowances of any kind, sixteen months.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>749016</tid>
<number> 6</number> Grant of leave not due. Subject to the maximum limit specified 
in sub- section 1 of section 5, leave on half allowances may be 
granted to a Judge in excess of the amount at his credit-
<section><tid>1736879</tid>
<number>i</number>on medical certificate; or

</section>

<section><tid>1792253</tid>
<number>ii</number>otherwise than on medical certificate, for not more 
than six months <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> for for two or more periods, not exceeding 
in the aggregate, six months] during the whole period of his 
service as a Judge;
Provided that no such leave shall be granted if the Judge is not 
expected to return to duty at the end of such leave and earn the leave 
granted.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1963799</tid>
<number>7</number>Special disability leave. The rules for the time being in force 
with respect to the grant of special disability leave in relation to 
an officer of the Central Civil

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1971</year>, s. 4, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1958</year>, s. 3. for" and not more than once" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Services, Class I who has entered service on or after the 16th July, 
 <year>1931</year> and who may be disabled by injury caused in, or in consequence 
of, the due performance of his official duties or in consequence of 
his official position, shall apply in relation to a Judge.



</article>



<article><tid>1974231</tid>
<number>8</number>Extraordinary leave. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Extraordinary leave may be granted to a 
Judge for a period not exceeding six months, or for two or more 
periods, not exceeding in the aggregate, six months] during the whole 
period of his service as a Judge in excess of any leave permissible 
under the foregoing provisions of this Chapter, but no salary or 
allowances shall be payable during, or in respect of, such leave.


</article>



<article><tid>584980</tid>
<number> 9</number> 
<section><tid>749389</tid>
<number>1</number>Leave allowances. The monthly rate of leave allowances  
payable to a Judge while on leave on full allowances shall be <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for 
the first forty- five days of such level a rate equal to the 
monthly rate of his salary, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and thereafter in the case of the 
Chief Justice, fifty- five per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary 
and in the case of each of the other Judges, sixty per cent. of the 
monthly rate of his salary];
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that where leave on full allowances is granted to a 
Judge on medical certificate, the monthly rate of leave allowances 
shall, for the first one hundred and twenty days of such leave, be a 
rate' equal to the monthly rate of his salary.]


</section>

<section><tid>1997846</tid>
<number>2</number>The monthly rate of leave allowances payable to a Judge 
while on leave on half allowances shall be <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in the case of the Chief 
Justice, twenty seven and a half per cent. of the monthly rate of his 
salary and in the case of each of the other Judges, thirty per cent. 
of the monthly rate of his salary"].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>930493</tid>
<number>10</number>Allowances for joining time. There shall be payable to a Judge 
in respect of joining time on his return from leave out of India an 
allowance at the rate of one thousand one hundred and ten rupees a 
month in lieu of salary.


</article>



<article><tid>1407453</tid>
<number> 11</number> Combining leave with vacation. A Judge may be permitted to 
combine vacation on full salary with leave, if.-
<section><tid>118268</tid>
<number>a</number>where the vacation consists of one continuous period, 
the leave is taken either at the commencement or at the end 
of the vacation but not a both;

</section>

<section><tid>806610</tid>
<number>b</number>where the vacation is divided into two separate 
periods, the leave is taken for the interval, or part of the 
interval, between the two periods of that vacation, or for 
the interval, or part of the interval, between the second 
period of that
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1958</year>, s. 4, for" Extraordinary leave not 
exceeding six Months in duration may be granted to a Judge not more 
than once" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1971</year>. s. 6 for certain words (w. e. f.  
  15- 1- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Added by Act 57 of <year>1980</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1986</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


vacation and the commencement of the next ensuing vacation:

Provided that no such permission to combine vacation with leave 
shall be granted if it becomes necessary to appoint an acting Chief 
Justice during the period of vacation or if the Judge is not expected 
to return to duty at the end of such leave.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1680391</tid>
<number>12</number>Consequences of overstaying leave or vacation. If a Judge 
overstays his leave or any vacation, whether combined with leave or 
not, he shall receive no salary for the period of his absence in 
excess of leave granted to him or beyond the end of the vacation, as 
the case may be:
Provided that if such absence is due to circumstances beyond his 
control, the period thereof may be treated as leave and may be debited 
to his leave account.



</article>



<article><tid>1129815</tid>
<number>13</number>Authority competent to grant leave, etc. The authority 
competent to grant or refuse leave to a Judge or revoke or curtail 
leave granted to a Judge shall be the Governor of the State in which 
the principal seat of the High Court is situate, after consultation 
with the Chief Justice of that High Court.
CHAP

PENSIONS

CHAPTER III

PENSIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1681393</tid>
<number> 14</number> Pension payable to Judges. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, every Judge shall, on his retirement, be paid a pension in 
accordance with the scale and provisions in Part I of the First 
Schedule:
Provided that no such pension shall be payable to a Judge unless-

<section><tid>1714509</tid>
<number>a</number>he has completed not less than twelve years of service 
for pension; or

</section>

<section><tid>333815</tid>
<number>b</number>he has attained the age of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> sixty- two years, and, in 
the case of a Judge holding office on the 5th day of October, 
<year>1963</year>, sixty years]; or

</section>

<section><tid>420411</tid>
<number>c</number>his retirement is medically certified to be 
necessitated by ill- health:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that if a Judge at the time of his appointment 
is in receipt of a pension (other than a disability or wound pension) 
in respect of any previous service in the Union or a State, the 
pension payable under this Act shall be in lieu of, and not in 
addition to, that pension.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub. by Act 27 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for" sixty years".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1958</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>),


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Explanation.- In this section' Judge' means a Judge who is not 
member of the Indian Civil Service or has not held any other 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pensionable post] under the Union or a State and includes a Judge 
who being a member of the Indian Civil Service or having held any 
other <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pension able post] under the Union or a State has elected to 
receive the pension payable under Part I of the First Schedule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1228375</tid>
<number> 15</number> Special provision of pension in respect of Judges who are 
members of service. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1968386</tid>
<number>1</number>] Every Judge- 

<subsection><tid>1610874</tid>
<number>a</number>who is a member of the Indian Civil Service shall, on 
his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance with the 
scale and provisions in Part 11 of the First Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200470</tid>
<number>b</number>who is not a member of the Indian Civil Service but has 
held any other <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pensionable post] under the Union or a 
State, shall on his retirement, be paid a pension in 
accordance with the scale and provisions in Part III of the 
First Schedule;
Provided that every such Judge shall elect to receive the pension 
payable to him either under Part I of the First Schedule or, as the 
case may be, Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, and the 
pension payable to him shall be calculated accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>632074</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), any 
Judge to whom that sub- section applies and who is in service on or 
after the 1st day of October, <year>1974</year>, may, if he has elected under the 
proviso to that sub- section to receive the pension payable to him 
under Part 11 or, as the case may be, Part III of the First Schedule 
before the date on which the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service) 
Amendment Act, <year>1976</year>, (35 of <year>1976</year>.) receives the assent of the 
President, cancel such election and elect afresh to receive the 
pension payable to him under Part I of the First Schedule and any such 
Judge who dies before the date of such assent shall be deemed to have 
elected afresh to be governed by the provisions of the said Part I if 
the provisions of that Part are more favourable in his case.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>671755</tid>
<number>16</number>Power of President to add to the service for pension. The 
President of India may for special reasons direct that any period not 
exceeding three months shall be added to the service for pension of 
a Judge:
Provided that the period so added shall be disregarded in 
calculating any additional pension under Part I or Part II or Part III 
of the First Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1980</year>, s. 4, for the words" pensionable civil 
post". 
2 S. 15 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 35 
of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1486032</tid>
<number> 17</number> Extraordinary pensions. The rules for the time being in force 
with respect to the grant of extraordinary pensions and gratuities in 
relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Class I who has 
entered service on or after the 1st April, <year>1937</year> and who may suffer 
injury or die as a result of violence, shall apply in relation to a 
Judge, subject, however, to the modification that references in those 
rules to tables of injury, gratuities and pensions and of family 
gratuities and pensions, shall be construed as references to the 
tables in the Second Schedule.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 17Family pensions and gratuities. (1) Where a Judge who, being 
in service on or after the commencement of the High Court and Supreme 
Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, <year>1986</year>, dies, 
whether before or after retirement in circumstances to which section 
 17 does- not apply, family pension calculated at the rate of fifty per 
cent of the pension admissible to him on the date of his death shall 
be payable to the person or persons entitled thereto and the amount so 
payable shall be paid from the day following the date of death of the 
Judge for a period of seven years or for a period up to the date on 
which the Judge would have attained the age of sixty- five years, had 
he survived, whichever is earlier, and thereafter at the rate of half 
of the family pension so admissible subject to a minimum of three 
hundred and seventy- five rupees per months.

Explanation.- For the purposes of determining the person or 
persons entitled to family pension tinder this sub- section,-

<section><tid>681895</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to a Judge who elects or is eligible to 
receive pension under Part I of the First Schedule, the 
rules, notifications and orders for the time being in force 
with regard to the person or persons entitled to family 
pension in relation to an officer of the Central Civil 
Services, Group' A', shall apply;

</section>

<section><tid>1254235</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to a Judge who elects to receive pension 
under Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, the ordinary 
rules of his service if be had not been appointed a Judge 
with respect to the person or persons entitled to family 
pension shall apply and his service as a Judge being treated 
as service therein.

<subsection><tid>1379694</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any Judge, who has elected to receive the pension 
payable to him under Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, 
retires, or dies in circumstances to which section 17 does not apply, 
gratuity, if any, shall be payable to the person or persons entitled 
thereto under the ordinary rules of his service if he had not been 
appointed a Judge, this service as a Judge being treated as service 
therein for the purpose of calculating that gratuity.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>152891</tid>
<number>3</number>The rules, notifications and orders for the time being in 
force with respect to the grant of death- cum- retirement gratuity bene- 
fit to or in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Cl- 
ass I (including the provisions relating to deductions from pension  
  for the purpose) shall apply to or in relation to the grant of 
death- cum- retirement gratuity benefit to or in relation to a Judge who, 
being in service on or after the 1st day of October, <year>1974</year>, retires, or 
dies in circumstances to which section 17 does not apply, subject to 
the modifications that-

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>681895</tid>
<number>i</number>the minimum qualifying service for the purpose of 
entitlement to the gratuity shall be two years and six months;

</section>

<section><tid>1254235</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount of gratuity shall be calculated on the basis 
of twenty days' salary for each completed year of service as 
a Judge;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Omitted by ACt 20 of <year>1988</year>, s 2, (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- In sub- section (3)] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the expression" Judge" has the 
same meaning as in section 14.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977635</tid>
<number>18</number>Conversion of sterling pension into rupees. Pensions expressed 
in sterling only shall, if paid in India, be converted into rupees at 
such rate of exchange as the Central Government may, from time to 
time, specify in this behalf.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>145399</tid>
<number>19</number>Commutation of pensions. The Civil Pensions (Commutation) 
Rules for the time being in force shall, with necessary modifications, 
apply to Judges.


</article>



<article><tid>78191</tid>
<number>20</number>Provident Fund. Every Judge shall be entitled to subscribe to 
the General Provident Fund (Central Services):
Provided that a Judge who is a member of the Indian Civil Service 
or has held any other pensionable civil post under the Union or a 
State shall continue to subscribe to the Provident Fund to which he 
was subscribing before his appointment as a Judge:

Provided further that a Judge who was appointed before the com- 
mencement of this Act may continue to subscribe to the Provident Fund 
to which he was subscribing immediately before such commencement.



</article>



<article><tid>811189</tid>
<number>21</number>Authority competent to grant pension. Save as may be otherwise 
expressly provided in the relevant rules relating to the grant of 
extraordinary pensions and gratuities, the authority competent to 
grant pension to a Judge under the provisions of this Act shall be the 
President of India.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>674911</tid>
<number>22</number>Travelling allowances to a Judge. Every Judge shall receive 
such reasonable allowances to reimburse him for expenses incurred in 
travelling on duty within the territory of India and shall be afforded 
such reasonable facilities in connection with travelling as may, from 
time to time, be prescribed.
</article>



<article><tid>130167</tid>
<number> 22A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Facility of rentfree houses.
<section><tid>1913179</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Judge shall be  
entitled without payment of rent to the use of an official residence 
in accordance with such rules as may, from time to time, be made in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1124763</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a Judge does not avail himself of the use of an 
official residence, he may be paid every month an allowance of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> two 
thousand five hundred rupees].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Proviso omitted by Act 46 of <year>1958</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1974</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 4 ibid. (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1977</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>607296</tid>
<number>22B</number>Conveyance facilities. Every Judge shall be entitled to a 
staff car and one hundred and fifty liters of petrol every month or 
the actual consumption of Petrol per month, whichever- is less.


</article>



<article><tid>1514577</tid>
<number>22C</number>Sumptuary allowance. The Chief Justice and each of the other 
Judges of every High Court shall be entitled to a sumptuary allowance 
of five hundred rupees per month and three hundred rupees per month, 
respectively"].


</article>



<article><tid>982343</tid>
<number> 22D</number> Exemption from liability to pay income- tax on certain 
perquisites received by a Judge. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>.-
<section><tid>1795950</tid>
<number>a</number>the value of rent- free official residence provided to a 
Judge under sub- section (1) of section 22A or the allowance 
paid to him under sub- section (2) of that section;

</section>

<section><tid>1104261</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of the conveyance facilities provided to a 
Judge under section 22B;

</section>

<section><tid>480645</tid>
<number>c</number>the sumptuary allowance provided to a Judge under 
section 22C,

</section>

<section><tid>549268</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the value of leave travel concession provided to a judge 
and members of his family"].
shall not be included in the computation of his income 
chargeable under the head" Salaries" under section 15: of the Income- 
tax Act <year>1961</year>.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>391768</tid>
<number> 23</number> Facilities for medical treatment and other conditions of 
service.
<section><tid>1347314</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Judge and the members of his family shall be  
entitled to such facilities for medical treatment and for 
accommodation in hospitals as may, from time to time, be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>481947</tid>
<number>2</number>The conditions of service of a Judge for which no express 
provision has been made in this Act shall be such as may be determined 
by rules made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>231884</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall be deemed to have come into force on the 
 26th January, <year>1950</year> and any rule made under this section may be made so 
as to be retrospective to any date not earlier than the commencement 
of this section.





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>167306</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>769818</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, bynotification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out 
thepurposes of this Act.-------------------



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>345259</tid>
<number> 25</number> Savings.[
<section><tid>188586</tid>
<number>1</number>] Nothing contained in this Act shall have effect  
so as to give to a Judge who is serving as such at the commencement of 
this Act less favourable terms in respect of his allowances or his 
rights in respect of leave of absence (including leave allowances) or 
pension than those to which he would be entitled if this Act had not 
been passed.
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[ (2) Nothing contained in this Act, as amended by the High 
Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, <year>1958</year>, (46 of  
  <year>1958</year>), shall have effect so as to give to a Chief Justice or a Judge of 
a former High Court in a Part B State less favourable terms in respect 
of his allowances or his rights in respect of leave of absence 
 (including the leave allowances) or pension than those to which he 
would be entitled under the High Court Judges (Part B States) Order, 
<year>1953</year>, or any other order or rule then


<pagefootnote><pagenum>42A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1976</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>S. 25 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 46 
of <year>1958</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 9, ibid., (w. e. f, 1- 11- <year>1956</year>),



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

applicable to him, if he had continued as a Judge of that High Court, 
his service as a Judge on or after the 1st day of November, <year>1956</year>, 
being treated as service in that High Court.]



</section>

</article>



 </act>