<act><tid>1724879</tid>
<title>THE PROVIDENT FUNDS ACT, <year>1925</year></title>

ACT NO. 19 OF <year>1925</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 27th August, <year>1925</year>.]

An Act to amend and consolidate the law relating to Government and 
other Provident Funds.

WHEREAS it is expedient to amend and consolidate the law relating 
to Government and other Provident Funds:

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>439317</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1615568</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>366915</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>495496</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1336401</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1485126</tid>
<number>a</number>" compulsory deposit" means a subscription to, or deposit 
in, a Provident Fund which, under the rules of the 
Fund, is not, until the happening of some specified 
contingency, repayable on demand otherwise than for the 
purpose of the payment of premia in respect of a policy 
of life insurance, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or the payment of subscriptions 
or premia in respect of a family pension fund], and 
includes any contribution <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> and any interest or 
increment which has accrued under the rules
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For Statement of Objects and Reasons, see Gazette of India, <year>1924</year>, 
Pt. V, p. 122.

This Act has been declared to be in force in- the district of 
khondmals by Regulation 4 of <year>1936</year>, s, 3 and Sch.; and the district of 
Angul by Regulation 5 of <year>1936</year>, s. 3 and Sch; also partially extended 
to Berar by C. P. and Berar Act 4 of <year>1941</year>; amended partially in U. P. 
by U. P. Act 19 of <year>1953</year>.

The Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and diu by Regulation 12 
of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch; to Pondicherry (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>) by Regulation 
7 of <year>1963</year>. s. 3 and Sch. I, to Dadra and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1965</year>) by Regulation 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, and to Laccadive, 
Minicoy and amindivi Islands (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>) by Regulation 8 of 
<year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>. s. 3 and Sch; for" except part B States". 
3. The words" including British Baluchistan" omitted by the A. O. 
<year>1948</year>. 
4.  1st April, <year>1926</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1925</year>, Pt. I, p. 1182. 
5. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2. 
6. The words" credited in respect of any such subscription or 
deposit" omitted by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the fund on any such subscription, deposit or 
contribution, and also any such subscription, deposit, 
contribution, interest or increment remaining to the 
credit of the subscriber or depositor after the 
happening of any such contingency;


</section>

<section><tid>729025</tid>
<number>b</number>" contribution" means any amount credited in a Provident 
Fund, by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any authority administering the Fund], by 
way of addition to, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a subscription to or deposit or 
balance at the credit of an individual account in,] the 
Fund; and" contributory Provident Fund" means a 
Provident Fund the rules of which provide for the 
crediting of contributions;

</section>

<section><tid>1141802</tid>
<number>c</number>" dependant" means any of the following relatives of a 
deceased subscriber to, or a depositor in, a Provident 
Fund, namely, a wife, husband, parent, child, minor 
brother, unmarried sister and a deceased son' s widow 
and child, and, where no parent of the subscriber or 
depositor is alive, a paternal grand- parent;

</section>

<section><tid>1456814</tid>
<number>d</number>" Government Provident Fund" means a Provident Fund, 
other than a Railway Provident Fund, constituted by the 
authority of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Secretary of State, the Central 
Government, the Crown Representative or any State 
Government] for any class or classes of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> persons in 
the service of the Government] or <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> of persons 
employed in educational institutions or employed by 
bodies existing solely for educational purposes], 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> and references in this Act to the Government shall 
be construed accordingly];

</section>

<section><tid>720335</tid>
<number>e</number>" Provident Fund" means a fund in which subscription or 
deposits of any class or classes of employees are 
received an held on their individual accounts, and 
includes any contributions <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> and any interest or 
increment accruing on such subscriptions, deposits or 
contributions under the rules of the Fund;

</section>

<section><tid>1674657</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>" Railway administration" means--

<subsection><tid>1819929</tid>
<number>i</number>any company administering a railway or 
tramway in <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> any part of India] either under a 
special Act of Parliament
<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2, for" the authority by which the 
Fund has been constituted". 
2. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2, for" or otherwise in respect of, a 
subscription to, or deposit in." 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Government". 
4. Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1942</year>, s. 3 and Sch. Ii, for" its employees". 
5. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2, for" for teachers in educational 
institutions". 
6. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
7. The words" credited in respect of such subscriptions or deposits" 
omitted by Act 1 of <year>1930</year>. s. 2. 
8. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original cl. (f). 
9. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" a part A State or a 
Part C State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of the United Kingdom] or an Indian law, or 
under contract with the Government, or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921112</tid>
<number>ii</number>the manager of any railway or tramway 
administered by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] of by a 
State Government,
and includes, in any case referred to in sub- clause 
 (ii), the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] or the State 
Government, as the case may be']


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>241949</tid>
<number>g</number>" Railway Provident Fund" means a Provident Fund 
constituted by the authority of a railway 
administration for any class or classes of its 
employees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1010442</tid>
<number> 3</number> Protection of compulsory deposits.
<section><tid>313829</tid>
<number>1</number>A compulsory deposit in  
any Government or Railway Provident Fund shall not in any way be 
capable of being assigned or charged and shall not be liable to 
attachment under any decree or order of any Civil, Revenue or Criminal 
Court in respect of any debt or liability incurred by the subscriber 
or depositor, and neither the Official Assignee nor any receiver 
appointed under the Provincial Insolvency Act, <year>1920</year>, (5 of <year>1920</year>.) 
shall be entitled to, or have nay claim on, any such compulsory 
deposit.

</section>

<section><tid>647654</tid>
<number>2</number>Any sum standing to the credit of any subscriber to, or 
depositor in, any such Fund at the time of his decease and payable 
under the rules of the Fund to any dependant of the subscriber or 
depositor, or to such person as may be authorised by law to receive 
payment on his behalf, shall, subject to any deduction authorised by 
this Act and, save where the dependant is the widow or child of the 
subscriber or depositor, subject also to the rights of an assignee 
under an assignment made before the commencement of this Act, vest in 
the dependant, and shall, subject as afore- said, be free from any debt 
or other liability incurred by the deceased or incurred by the 
dependant before the death of the subscriber or depositor,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1240815</tid>
<number> 4</number> Provisions regarding re- payments.
<section><tid>1232775</tid>
<number>1</number>When under the rules of  
any Government or Railway Provident Fund the sum standing to the 
credit of any subscriber or depositor, or the balance thereof after 
the making of any deduction authorised by this Act, has become 
payable, the officer whose duty it is to make the payment shall pay 
the or balance, as the case may be, to the subscriber or depositor, 
or, if he is dead, shall--

<subsection><tid>574712</tid>
<number>a</number>if the sum or balance, or any part thereof, vests in a 
dependant under the provisions of section 3, pay the 
same to the dependant or to such person as may be 
authorised by law to receive payment on his behalf; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" Federal Railway Authority".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>310301</tid>
<number>b</number>if the whole sum or balance, as the case may be, does 
not exceed five thousand rupees, pay the same, or any 
part thereof, which is not payable under clause (a), to 
any person nominated to receive it under the rules of 
the Funds, or, if no person is so nominated, to any 
person appearing to him to be otherwise entitled to 
receive it; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177726</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of any sum or balance, or any part thereof, 
which is not payable to any person under clause (a) or 
clause (b) pay the same,--

<subsubsection><tid>423129</tid>
<number>i</number>to any person nominated to receive it 
under the rules of the Fund on production by such 
person of probate of letters of administration 
evidencing the grant to him of administration to 
the estate of the deceased or a certificate 
granted under the Succession Certificate Act, <year>1889</year> 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, (7 of <year>1889</year>.) or under the Bombay Regulation 
VIII of <year>1827</year>, entitling the holder thereof to 
receive payment of such sum, balance or part, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>885165</tid>
<number>ii</number>where no person is so nominated, to any 
person who produces such probate, letters or 
certificate:
Provided that, where the whole or any part of any sum standing to 
the credit of the subscriber or depositor has been assigned to any 
other person before the commencement of this Act, and notice in 
writing of the assignment has been received by the officer from the 
assignee, the officer shall after making any deduction authorised by 
this Act and any payment due under clause (a) to or on behalf of the 
widow or children of the subscriber or depositor--


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>423129</tid>
<number>i</number>if the subscriber or depositor or, if he is dead, the 
person to whom in the absence of any valid assignment 
the sum or balance would be payable under this sub- 
section gives his consent in writing, pay the sum or 
part or the balance thereof, as the case may be, to the 
assignee, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>885165</tid>
<number>ii</number>if such consent is not forthcoming, withhold payment of 
the sum, part or balance, as the case may be, pending a 
decision of a competent Civil Court as to the person 
entitled to receive it.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1257335</tid>
<number>2</number>The making of any payment authorised by sub- section (1) shall 
be a full discharge to the Government or the railway administration, 
as the case may be, from all liability in respect of so much of the 
sum standing to the credit of the subscriber or depositor as is 
equivalent to the amount so paid.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293035</tid>
<number> 5</number> Rights of nominees. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>182682</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained  
in any law for the time being in force or in any disposition, whether 
testamentary or otherwise, by a subscriber to, or depositor in, a 
Government or Railway Provident Fund of the sum standing to his credit 
in the Fund, or of any part thereof, where any nomination, duly made 
in accordance with the rules of the Fund, purports to confer upon any 
person the right to receive the whole or any part of such sum on the 
death of the subscriber or depositor occurring before the sum has 
become payable or before the sum, having become payable, has been 
paid, the said person shall, on the death as aforesaid of the 
subscriber or depositor, become entitled, to the exclusion of all 
other persons, to receive such sum or part thereof, as the case may 
be, unless--

<subsection><tid>1163027</tid>
<number>a</number>such nomination is at any time varied by another 
nomination made in like manner or expressly cancelled 
by notice given in the manner and to the authority 
prescribed by those rules, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>872666</tid>
<number>b</number>such nomination at any time becomes invalid by reason of 
the happening of some contingency specified therein,--
and if the said person predeceases the subscriber or depositor, the 
nomination shall, so far as it relates to the right conferred upon the 
said person, become void and of no effect:

Provided that where provision has been duly made in the 
nomination in accordance with the rules of the Fund, conferring upon 
some other person such right in the stead of the person deceased, such 
right shall, upon the decease as aforesaid of the said person, pass to 
such other person.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>579577</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Indian 
Succession Act, <year>1925</year>], (39 of <year>1925</year>.) or the Bombay Regulation VIII of 
<year>1827</year>, any <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> person, who becomes entitled as aforesaid, may be 
granted] a certificate under that Act, or that Regulation, as the case 
may be, entitling him to receive payment of such sum or part, and such 
certificate shall not be deemed to be invalidated or superseded by any 
grant to any other person of probate or letters of administration to 
the estate of the deceased.

</section>

<section><tid>1447546</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The provisions of this section as amended by sub- section 
 (1) of section 2 of the Provident Funds (Amendment) Act, <year>1946</year>, (11 of  
  <year>1946</year>.) shall apply also to all such nominations made before the date 
of the commencement of that Act:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1946</year>, s. 2, for the original sub- section. 
2. Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1950</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" the Succession 
Certificate Act, <year>1889</year>". 
3. Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1946</year>, s. 2. for" such person shall, on the 
death of the subscriber or depositor, be entitled to the grant of". 
4. Added by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the provisions of this section as so amended shall 
not operate to affect any case, in which before the said date any sum 
has been paid, or has under the rules of the Fund become payable in 
pursuance of any nomination duly made in accordance with those rules.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>207513</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to make deductions. When the sum standing to the credit 
of any subscriber or depositor in any Government or Railway Provident 
Fund which is a contributory Provident Fund becomes payable, there 
may, if the authority <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> specified in this behalf in the rules of the 
Fund] so directs, be deducted therefrom and paid to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government or 
the Railway administration, as the case may be,]--
<section><tid>541074</tid>
<number>a</number>any amount due under a liability incurred by the 
subscriber or depositor to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government or the Railway 
administration], but not exceeding in any case the 
total amount of any contributions credited to the 
account of the subscriber or depositor and of any 
interest or increment which has accrued on such 
contributions; or

</section>

<section><tid>1431822</tid>
<number>b</number>where the subscriber or depositor has been dismissed 
from <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> his employment] for any reasons specified in 
this behalf in the rules of the Fund, or where he has 
resigned such employment within five years of the 
commencement thereof, the whole or any part of the 
amount of any such contributions, interest and 
increment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1473827</tid>
<number> 6A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Withholding or recovery of Government contributions in 
case of Central Government officers taking up, without prior 
permission, commercial employment within two years of their 
retirement.
<section><tid>762077</tid>
<number>1</number>In this section, unless the context otherwise  
requires,--

<subsection><tid>1825482</tid>
<number>a</number>" Central Government officer" means a subscriber to, or 
depositor in, a contributory provident fund constituted 
by the Central Government, who, immediately before his 
retirement, is a member of a Central Service Class I, 
but does not include an officer appointed under a 
contract of service for a specified term;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1019584</tid>
<number>b</number>" commercial employment" means employment in any capacity 
[ including that of an agent] under any company, co- 
operative society, firm or individual engaged in 
trading, commercial, industrial, financial or 
Professional business and includes also--

<subsubsection><tid>1591265</tid>
<number>i</number>a directorship of a company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1800253</tid>
<number>ii</number>the holding of any office, whether 
elective or other wise, such as that of president, 
chairman, manager, secretary, treasurer, by 
whatever name called in a co- operative society; 
and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1925</year>, s. 3, for" by which the Fund has been 
constituted". 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" that authority". 
3. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" the employment of that authority". 
4. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 7- 2- <year>1977</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>298309</tid>
<number>iii</number>the setting up of practice, either 
independently or as partner of a firm, as adviser 
of consultant in matters in respect of which the 
Central Government officer,--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1227778</tid>
<number>A</number>has no professional qualifications and 
the matters in respect of which the practice is to 
be set up or is carried on are relatable to his 
official knowledge or experience, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1903487</tid>
<number>B</number>has professional qualification, but the 
matters in respect of which such practice is to be 
set up are such as are likely to give his clients 
an unfair advantage by reason of the posts held by 
him under the Central Government, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1686921</tid>
<number>C</number>has to undertake work involving liaison 
or contact with the offices or officers of Central 
Government,
but does not include employment in or under a 
corporation or company wholly or substantially owned or 
controlled by Government or employment in or under a 
body controlled or financed wholly or substantially by 
Government;


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1229845</tid>
<number>c</number>" Government contributions" means contributions made 
after the commencement of the Provident Funds 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1975</year>, (46 of <year>1975</year>.) in respect of any 
period after such commencement, by the Central 
Government or by a State Government or by a local 
authority within the meaning of the Local Authorities 
Loans Act, <year>1914</year> (9 of <year>1914</year>.);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1644931</tid>
<number>d</number>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the 
Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>546806</tid>
<number>2</number>No Central Government officer shall have any right to the 
Government contributions made to his credit in a contributory 
provident fund in any case where he takes up commercial employment at 
any time before the expiry of two years from the date of his 
retirement without the prior permission of the Central Government.
Explanation 1.-- For the purposes of this sub- section and sub- 
section (7)," date of retirement" in relation to a Central Government 
officer re- employed after retirement without any break either in the 
same or any other Class I post under the Central Government or any 
other equivalent post under a State Government, shall mean the date on 
which such Central Government officer finally ceases to be re- employed 
in Government service.

Explanation 2.-- A Central Government officer permitted by the 
Central Government to take up a particular commercial employment 
during his


<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

leave preparatory to retirement shall be deemed, for the purposes of 
this sub- section, to have obtained prior permission of the Central 
Government for his continuance in such employment after retirement.


</section>

<section><tid>1387880</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (4), the Central 
Government may, by order in writing, on an application made in the 
prescribed form by a Central Government officer, grant, subject to 
such conditions, if any, as it may deem necessary, permission, or 
refuse, for reasons to be recorded in the order, permission, to such 
officer to take up the commercial employment specified in the 
application.

</section>

<section><tid>570022</tid>
<number>4</number>In granting or refusing permission under this section to a 
Central Government officer for taking up any commercial employment, 
the Central Government shall have regard to the following factors, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1893300</tid>
<number>a</number>the nature of the employment proposed to be taken up and 
the antecedents of the employer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687916</tid>
<number>b</number>whether his duties in the employment which he proposes 
to take up might be such as to bring him into conflict 
with Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>494013</tid>
<number>c</number>whether the officer while in service had any such 
dealing with the employer under whom he proposes to 
seek employment as might afford a reasonable basis for 
the suspicion that such officer had shown favours to 
such employer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1084944</tid>
<number>d</number>any other relevant factors which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>967437</tid>
<number>5</number>Where within a period of sixty days of the date of receipt of 
an application under sub- section (3), the Central Government does not 
refuse to grant the permission applied for or does not communicate the 
refusal to the applicant, the Central Government shall be deemed to 
have granted the permission applied for.

</section>

<section><tid>877890</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the Central Government grants the permission applied 
for subject to any conditions or refuses such permission, the 
applicant may, within thirty days of the receipt of the order of the 
Central Government to that effect, make a representation against any 
such condition or refusal and the Central Government may make such 
orders thereon as it deems fit:
Provided that no order other than an order cancelling such 
condition or granting such permission without any conditions shall be 
made under this sub- section without giving the person making the 
representation an opportunity to show cause against the order proposed 
to be made.


</section>

<section><tid>56442</tid>
<number>7</number>If any Central Government officer takes up any commercial 
employment at any time before the expiry of two years from the date of 
his retirement without the prior permission of the Central Government 
or commits a breach of any condition subject to which permission to 
take up

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any commercial employment has been granted to him under this section, 
it shall be competent for the Central Government to declare by order 
in writing and for reasons to be recorded therein that he shall not be 
entitled to such part of the Government contributions made in relation 
to such officer as may be specified in the order and if he has 
received payment thereof, to direct that he shall refund to the 
Central Government an amount equivalent to such part of the Government 
contributions:

Provided that no such order shall be made without giving the 
officer concerned an opportunity of showing cause against such 
declaration or direction:

Provided further that in making any order under this sub- section, 
the Central Government shall have regard to the following factors, 
namely:--


<subsection><tid>1291718</tid>
<number>i</number>the financial circumstances of the officer concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422551</tid>
<number>ii</number>the nature of, and the emoluments from, the commercial 
employment taken up by the officer concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1395844</tid>
<number>iii</number>such other relevant factors as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1219670</tid>
<number>8</number>Any amount required to be refunded by an order under sub- 
section (7) may, if it is not refunded within the prescribed period, 
be recovered as arrears of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>7124</tid>
<number>9</number>Every order passed by the Central Government under this 
section shall be communicated to the officer concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1808446</tid>
<number>10</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other 
provision of this Act or the rules applicable to any contributory 
provident fund.

</section>

<section><tid>413969</tid>
<number>11</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>114793</tid>
<number>7</number>Protection for acts done in good faith. No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against any person in respect of anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>479790</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to apply the Act to other Provident Funds. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1759453</tid>
<number>1</number>] The  
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that the provisions of this Act <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (except section 
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The original s. 8 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section 
by Act 1 of <year>1930</year>. s. 3. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
3. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 7- 2- <year>1977</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  6A)] shall apply to any Provident Fund established for the benefit of 
its employees by any local authority within the meaning of the Local 
Authorities Loans Act, <year>1914</year>, (9 of <year>1914</year>.) and, on the making of such 
declaration, this Act shall apply accordingly, as if such Provident 
Fund were a Government Provident Fund and such local authority were 
the Government.


</section>

<section><tid>22757</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of this Act <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (except  
  section 6A)] shall apply to any Provident Fund established for the 
benefit of the employees of any of the institutions specified in the 
Schedule, or of any group of such institutions, and, on the making of 
such declaration, this Act shall apply accordingly, as if such 
Provident Fund were a Government Provident Fund and the authority 
having custody of the Fund were the Government:
Provided that section 6 shall apply as if the authority making 
the contributions referred to in that section were the Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1715186</tid>
<number>3</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, add to the Schedule the name of any public 
institution it may deem fit, and any such addition shall take effect 
as if it had been made by this Act.]

</section>

<section><tid>399054</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> In this section" the appropriate Government" means--

<subsection><tid>1041724</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to a cantonment authority, a port authority 
for a major port, and any institution which, or the 
objects of which, appear to the Central Government to 
fall within List I in the Seventh Schedule to <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the 
Constitution], the Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747575</tid>
<number>b</number>in other cases, the state Government.
Explanation.--" The State Government" in relation to an 
institution registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year>, (21  
  of <year>1860</year>.) means the State government of the State in which the society 
is registered.]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>695612</tid>
<number>9</number>Savings as to estates of soldiers. Nothing in section 4 or 
section 5 shall apply to money belonging to any estate for the purpose 
of the administration of which the Regimental Debts Act. <year>1893</year>, 
applies. (56 and 57 Vict., c. 5.)


</article>



<article><tid>1260240</tid>
<number>10</number>[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing Act. <year>1927</year> (12 of <year>1927</year>), s. 2 
and Sch.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 1 of <year>1930</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C." 
3. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 7- 2- <year>1977</year>). 
4. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Government of India Act, <year>1935</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>