<act><title>

The
payment of Bonus Rules, 19751</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Payment of Bonus Rules, 1975.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“form” means a form appended to these rules; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Act” means the Payment of Bonus Act, 1965 (21 of 1965); 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“section” means a section of the Act. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Authority for granting permission for change of accounting year.—The
prescribed authority for the purposes of the proviso to paragraph (b) of
sub-clause (iii) of clause 
<section><number>1</number> of section 2 shall be—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
in the case of an establishment in relation to which the Central
Government is the appropriate Government under the Act, the Chief Labour
Commissioner (Central); 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
in any other case, the Labour Commissioner of the State in which the
establishment is situated. 
 

  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Maintenance of registers.—Every
employer shall prepare and maintain the following registers, namely:—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
a register showing the computation of the allocable surplus referred to
in clause (4) of section 2, in Form A: 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
a register showing the set-on and set-off of the allocable surplus, under
section 15, in form B; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
a register showing the details of the amount of bonus due to each of the
employees, the deductions under sections 17 and 18 and the amount actually
disbursed, in Form C. 
 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>5</number>
Annual returns.—Every employer shall send a return in Form D to the
Inspector so as to reach him within 30 days after the expiry of the time limit
specified in section 19 for payment of bonus.] 
   


  





 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by S.O. 251, dated 7th
January, 1984 (w.e.f. 21-1-1984).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>