<act><title>
THE
INDIAN MEDICINE CENTRAL COUNCIL 

ACT, 1970

</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force in a State on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint
in this behalf for such State, and different dates may be appointed for
different States and for different provisions of this Act. 


   







 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “approved institution” means a teaching institution, health center or hospital recognized by a University or Board as an institution in which a person may undergo the training, if any, required by his course of study before the award of any medical qualification to him; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Board” means a Board, Council, Examining Body or Faculty of Indian Medicine (by whatever name called) constituted by the State Government under any law for the time being in force regulating the award of medical qualifications in, and registration of practitioners of, Indian medicine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “Central Council” means the Central Council of Indian Medicine constituted under section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “Central Register of Indian Medicine” means the register maintained by the Central Council under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Indian Medicine” means the system of Indian medicine commonly known as Ashtang Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[, Unani Tibb or Sowa-Rigpa] whether supplemented or not by such modern advances as the Central Council may declare by notification from time to time; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ea</number> “medical college” means a college of Indian medicine, whether known as such or by any other name, in which a person may undergo a course of study or training including any post-graduate course of study or training which will qualify him for the award of a recognised medical qualification;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “medical institution” means any institution within or without India which grants degrees, diplomas or licences in Indian medicine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by regulations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “recognized medical qualification” means any of the medical qualifications, including post-graduate medical qualification, of Indian medicine included in the Second, Third or Fourth Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “regulation” means a regulation made under section 36; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “State Register of Indian Medicine” means a register or registers maintained under any law for the time being in force in any State regulating the registration of practitioners of Indian Medicine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> “University” means any University in India established by law and having a Faculty of Indian Medicine and includes a University in India established by law in which instruction, teaching, training or research in Indian medicine is provided. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that State. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> </title><title>Constitution of Central Council. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for the purposes of this Act a Central Council consisting of the following members, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> such number of members not exceeding five as may be determined by the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of the First Schedule for each of the Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[, Unani and Sowa-Rigpa] systems of medicine from each State in which a State Register of Indian Medicine is maintained, to be elected from amongst themselves by persons enrolled on that Register as practitioners of Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[, Unani or Sowa-Rigpa], as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> one member for each of the Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[, Unani and Sowa-Rigpa] systems of medicine from each University to be elected from amongst themselves by the members of the Faculty or Department (by whatever name called) of the respective system of medicine of that University; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> such number of members, not exceeding thirty per cent. of the total number of members elected under clauses (a) and (b), as may be nominated by the Central Government, from amongst persons having special knowledge or practical experience in respect of Indian medicine: 
</subsection>
 Provided that until members are elected under clause (a) or clause (b) in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the Central Government shall nominate such number of members, being persons qualified to be chosen as such under the said clause (a) or clause (b), as the case may be, as that Government thinks fit; and references to elected members in this Act shall be construed as including references to members so nominated. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The President of the Central Council shall be elected by the members of the Central Council from amongst themselves in such manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> There shall be a Vice-President for each of the Ayurveda, Siddha 
  <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[, Unani and Sowa-Rigpa] system of medicine who shall be elected from amongst themselves by members representing that system of medicine, elected under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (1) or nominated under clause (c) of that sub-section. 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Mode of election.—
<section><number>1</number> An election under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> or clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 3 shall be conducted by the Central Government in
accordance with such rules as may be made by it in this behalf. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where any dispute arises regarding any election to the Central Council, it shall
be referred to the Central Government whose decision shall be final. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Restriction on elections and membership.—
<section><number>1</number>
No person shall be eligible for election to the Central Council unless he
possesses any of the medical qualifications included in the Second, Third or
Fourth Schedule, is enrolled on any State Register of Indian Medicine and
resides in the State concerned. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
No person may at the same time serve as a member in more than one capacity. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Incorporation of Central Council.—The
Central Council shall be a body corporate by the name of the Central Council of
Indian Medicine having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to
acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to
contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Term of office of President, Vice-President and members of Central Council.—
<section><number>1</number>
The President, a Vice-President or a member of the Central Council shall hold
office for a term of five years from the date of his election or nomination, as
the case may be, or until his successor shall have been duly elected or
nominated, whichever is longer. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
An elected or nominated member shall be deemed to have vacated his seat if he is
absent without excuse, sufficient in the opinion of the Central Council, from
three consecutive ordinary meetings of the Central Council or, in the case of a
member elected under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 3, if he ceases to
be enrolled on the concerned State Register of Indian Medicine, or in the case
of a member elected under clause (b) of that sub-section, if he ceases to be a
member of the Faculty or Department (by whatever name called) of Indian Medicine
of the University concerned. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A casual vacancy in the Central Council shall be filled by election or
nomination, as the case may be, and the person elected or nominated to fill the
vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the
member whose place he takes was elected or nominated. 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Members of the Central Council shall be eligible for re-election or
re-nomination. 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Where the said term of five years is about to expire in respect of any member, a
successor may be elected or nominated at any time within three months before the
said term expires but he shall not assume office until the said term has
expired. 



 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Meetings of Central Council . —(1) The Central Council shall meet at least once in each year at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Council. </title>
 <section><number>2</number> Unless otherwise prescribed, one-third of the total number of members of the Central Council shall form a quorum and all the acts of the Central Council shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting: 
 Provided that no decision of the Central Council in relation to any Indian medicine, shall be effective unless three members representing Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[, Unani or Sowa-Rigpa] system of medicine as the case may be, are present at the meeting and support the decision. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Committees for Ayurveda, Siddha and Unani. </title>— <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The Central Council shall constitute from amongst its members,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a committee for Ayurveda; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a committee for Siddha; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a committee for Unani; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> a committee for Sowa-Rigpa, and each such committee shall consist of members elected under clause (a) or clause (b) or nominated under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 3 representing the Ayurveda, Siddha, Unani or Sowa-Rigpa system of medicine, as the case may be.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Vice-President for each of the Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[, Unani and Sowa-Rigpa] system of medicine elected under sub-section (3) of section 3 shall be, respectively, the Chairman of the committees referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (1). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to such general or special directions as the Central Council may from time to time give, each such committee shall be competent to deal with any matter relating to Ayurveda, Siddha <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[, Unani or Sowa-Rigpa] system of medicine, as the case may be, within the competence of the Central Council. 



 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a committee for Ayurveda; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a committee for Siddha; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a committee for Unani; and 
</subsection>



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Other committees.—The Central
Council may constitute from amongst its members such other committees for
general or special purposes as the Central Council deems necessary to carry out
the purposes of this Act. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Meetings of committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The
committees constituted under sections 9 and 10 shall meet at least once in each
year at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Council. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Unless otherwise prescribed, one-third of the total number of members of a
committee shall form a quorum, and all the acts of the committee shall be
decided by a majority of the members present and voting. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Officers and other employees of Central Council.—The
Central Council shall— 


 <section><number>a</number>
appoint a Registrar who shall act as Secretary and who may also, if
deemed expedient, act as Treasurer;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
employ such other persons as it deems necessary to carry out the purposes
of this Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number> require and take from the Registrar, or from any other employee, such
security for the due performance of his duties as the Central Council deems
necessary; and
 </section><section><number>d</number> with the previous sanction of the Central Government, fix the
remuneration and allowances to be paid to the President, Vice-President and
members of the Central Council and to the members of the committees thereof and
determine the conditions of service of the employees of the Central Council.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Vacancies in the Central Council and committees thereof not to invalidate acts,
etc.—No act or proceeding of the
Central Council or any committee thereof shall be called in question on the
ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the
constitution of, the Central Council or the committee, as the case may be. 


  
   



 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<title><number>13A</number> Permission for establishment of new medical college, new course of study, etc. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force,—­ 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> no person shall establish a medical college; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> no medical college shall­— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> open a new or higher course of study or training, including a post-graduate course of study or training, which would enable a student of such course or training to qualify himself for the award of any recognised medical qualification; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> increase its admission capacity in any course of study or training including a post-graduate course of study or training, 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 except with the previous permission of the Central Government obtained in accordance with the provisions of this section. 
 Explanation 1.—For the purposes of this section, “person” includes any University or a trust, but does not include the Central Government. 
 Explanation 2 .—For the purposes of this section, “admission capacity”, in relation to any course of study or training, including post-graduate course of study or training, in a medical college, means the maximum number of students as may be fixed by the Central Government from time to time for being admitted to such course or training. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every person or medical college shall, for the purpose of obtaining permission under sub-section (1), submit to the Central Government a scheme in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (3) and the Central Government shall refer the scheme to the Central Council for its recommendations. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The scheme referred to in sub-section (2), shall be in such form and contain such particulars and be preferred in such manner and accompanied with such fee, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of a scheme from the Central Government under sub-section (2), the Central Council may obtain such other particulars as may be considered necessary by it from the person or the medical college concerned, and thereafter, it may,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> if the scheme is defective and does not contain necessary particulars, give a reasonable opportunity to the person or medical college concerned for making a written representation and it shall be open to such person or medical college to rectify the defects, if any, specified by the Central Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> consider the scheme, having regard to the factors referred to in sub-section (8) and submit it to the Central Government together with its recommendations thereon within a period not exceeding six months from the date of receipt of the reference from the Central Government. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Government may, after considering the scheme and recommendations of the Central Council under sub-section (4) and after obtaining, where necessary, such other particulars as may be considered necessary by it from the person or medical college concerned and having regard to the factors referred to in sub-section (8), either approve the scheme with such conditions, if any, as it may consider necessary or disapprove the scheme and any such approval shall constitute as a permission under sub-section (1): 
 Provided that no scheme shall be disapproved by the Central Government except after giving the person or medical college concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard: 
 Provided further that nothing in this sub-section shall prevent any person or medical college whose scheme has not been approved by the Central Government to submit a fresh scheme and the provisions of this section shall apply to such scheme as if such scheme had been submitted for the first time under sub-section (2). 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where, within a period of one year from the date of submission of the scheme to the Central Government under sub-section (2), no order is communicated by the Central Government to the person or medical college submitting the scheme, such scheme shall be deemed to have been approved by the Central Government in the form in which it was submitted, and, accordingly, the permission of the Central Government required under sub-section (1) shall also be deemed to have been granted. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> In computing the time-limit specified in sub-section (6), the time taken by the person or medical college concerned submitting the scheme, in furnishing any particulars called for by the Central Council, or by the Central Government, shall be excluded. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Central Council while making its recommendations under clause (b) of sub-section (4) and the Central Government while passing an order, either approving or disapproving the scheme under sub-section (5), shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> whether the proposed medical college or the existing medical college seeking to open a new or higher course of study or training, would be in a position to offer the minimum standards of medical education as prescribed by the Central Council under section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> whether the person seeking to establish a medical college or the existing medical college seeking to open a new or higher course of study or training or to increase its admission capacity has adequate financial resources; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> whether necessary facilities in respect of staff, equipment, accommodation, training, hospital or other facilities to ensure proper functioning of the medical college or conducting the new course of study or training or accommodating the increased admission capacity have been provided or would be provided within the time-limit specified in the scheme; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> whether adequate hospital facilities, having regard to the number of students likely to attend such medical college or course of study or training or the increased admission capacity have been provided or would be provided within the time-limit specified in the scheme; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> whether any arrangement has been made or programme drawn to impart proper training to students likely to attend such medical college or the course of study or training by persons having recognised medical qualifications; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the requirement of manpower in the field of practice of Indian medicine in the medical college; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> any other factors as may be prescribed. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where the Central Government passes an order either approving or disapproving a scheme under this section, a copy of the order shall be communicated to the person or medical college concerned.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<title><number>13B</number> Non-recogni­tion of medical qualifications in certain cases. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> Where any medical college is established without the previous permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section l3A, medical qualification granted to any student of such medical college shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical qualification for the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where any medical college opens a new or higher course of study or training including a post-graduate course of study or training without the previous permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section l3A, medical qualification granted to any student of such medical college on the basis of such study or training shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical qualification for the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where any medical college increases its admission capacity in any course of study or training without the previous permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section 13A, medical qualification granted to any student of such medical college on the basis of the increase in its admission capacity shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical qualification for the purposes of this Act. ] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<title><number>13C</number> Time for seeking permission for certain existing medical colleges. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> If any person has established a medical college or any medical college has opened a new or higher course of study or training or increased the admission capacity on or before the commencement of the Indian Medicine Central Council (Amendment) Act, 2003, such person or medical college, as the case may be, shall seek, within a period of three years from the said commencement, permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section l3A. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any person or medical college, as the case may be, fails to seek permission under sub-section (1), the provisions of section 13B shall apply, so far as may be, as if permission of the Central Government under section 13A has been refused.] 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Recognition of medical qualifications granted by certain medical institutions in
India.—
<section><number>1</number> The medical
qualifications granted by any University, Board or other medical institution in
India which are included in the Second Schedule shall be recognized medical
qualifications for the purposes of this Act. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any University, Board or other medical institution in India which grants a
medical qualification not included in the Second Schedule may apply to the
Central Government to have any such qualification recognized, and the Central
Government, after consulting the Central Council, may, by notification in the
Official Gazette, amend the Second Schedule so as to include such qualification
therein, and any such notification may also direct that an entry shall be made
in the last column of the Second Schedule against such medical qualification
declaring that it shall be a recognized medical qualification only when granted
after a specified date. 


  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Recognition of medical qualifications granted by certain medical institutions
whose qualifications are not included in Second Schedule.—The
medical qualifications included in the Third Schedule granted to a citizen of
India before the 15th day of August, 1947, by any medical institution in any
area which was comprised before that date within India as defined in the
Government of India Act, 1935, shall also be recognized medical qualifications
for the purposes of this Act. 


  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Recognition of medical qualifications granted by medical institutions in
countries with which there is a scheme of reciprocity.—
<section><number>1</number>
The medical qualifications granted by medical institutions outside India which
are included in the Fourth Schedule shall be recognized medical qualifications
for the purposes of this Act. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Council may enter into negotiations with the authority in any State
or country outside India, which, by the law of such State or country is
entrusted with the maintenance of a Register of practitioners of Indian
medicine, for the settling of a scheme of reciprocity for the recognition of
medical qualifications in Indian medicine, and in pursuance of any such scheme,
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the
Fourth Schedule so as to include therein any medical qualification which the
Central Council has decided should be recognized, and any such notification may
also direct that an entry shall be made in the last column of the Fourth
Schedule against such medical qualification declaring that it shall be
recognized medical qualification only when granted after a specified date. 


  

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Rights of persons possessing qualifications included in Second, Third and Fourth Schedules to be enrolled. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, any medical qualification included in the Second, Third or Fourth Schedule shall be sufficient qualification for enrolment on any State Register of Indian Medicine. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as provided in section 28, no person other than a practitioner of Indian medicine who possesses a recognized medical qualification and is enrolled on a State Register or the Central Register of Indian Medicine,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> shall hold office as Vaid, Siddha, Hakim or <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[physician or Amchi or] any other office (by whatever designation called) in Government or in any institution maintained by a local or other authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> shall practise Indian medicine in any State; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> shall be entitled to sign or authenticate a medical or fitness certificate or any other certificate required by any law to be signed or authenticated by a duly qualified medical practitioner; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> shall be entitled to give evidence at any inquest or in any court of law as an expert under section 45 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), on any matter relating to Indian medicine. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (2) shall affect,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the right of a practitioner of Indian medicine enrolled on a State Register of Indian Medicine to practise Indian medicine in any State merely on the ground that, on the commencement of this Act, he does not possess a recognized medical qualification; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the privileges (including the right to practice any system of medicine) conferred by or under any law relating to registration of practitioners of Indian medicine for the time being in force in any State on a practitioner of Indian medicine enrolled on a State Register of Indian Medicine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the right of a person to practise Indian medicine in a State in which, on the commencement of this Act, a State Register of Indian Medicine is not maintained if, on such commencement, he has been practising Indian medicine for not less than five years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the rights conferred by or under the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956) [including the right to practice medicine as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the said Act], on persons possessing any qualifications included in the Schedules to the said Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any person who acts in contravention of any provision of sub-section (2) shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number>
Power to require information as to courses of study and examinations.—Every
University, Board or medical institution in India which grants a recognized
medical qualification shall furnish such information as the Central Council may,
from time to time, require as to the courses of study and examinations to be
undergone in order to obtain such qualification, as to the ages at which such
courses of study and examinations are required to be undergone and such
qualification is conferred and generally as to the requisites for obtaining such
qualification. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
Inspectors at examinations.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Council shall appoint such number of medical inspectors as it may deem
requisite to inspect any medical college, hospital or other institution where
education in Indian medicine is given, or to attend any examination held by any
University, Board or medical institution for the purpose of recommending to the
Central Government recognition of medical qualifications granted by that
University, Board or medical institution. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The medical inspectors shall not interfere with the conduct of any training or
examination, but shall report to the Central Council on the adequacy of the
standards of education including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and
other facilities prescribed for giving education in Indian medicine or on the
sufficiency of every examination which they attend. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Central Council shall forward a copy of any such report to the University,
Board or medical institution concerned and shall also forward a copy with the
remarks of the University, Board or medical institution thereon, to the Central
Government. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Visitors at examinations.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Council may appoint such number of visitors as it may deem requisite to
inspect any medical college, hospital or other institution where education in
Indian medicine is given or to attend any examination for the purpose of
granting recognized medical qualifications. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any person, whether he is a member of the Central Council or not, may be
appointed as a visitor under this section but a person who is appointed as an
inspector under section 19 for any inspection or examination shall not be
appointed as a visitor for the same inspection or examination. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The visitors shall not interfere with the conduct of any training or
examination, but shall report to the President of the Central Council on the
adequacy of the standards of education including staff, equipment,
accommodation, training and other facilities prescribed for giving education in
Indian medicine or on the sufficiency of every examination which they attend. 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The report of a visitor shall be treated as confidential unless in any
particular case the President of the Central Council otherwise directs: 


 Provided
that if the Central Government requires a copy of the report of a visitor, the
Central Council shall furnish the same. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Withdrawal of recognition.—
<section><number>1</number> When
upon report by the inspector or the visitor, it appears to the Central
Council— 


 <subsection><number>a</number> that the courses of study and examination to be undergone in, or the
proficiency required from candidates at any examination held by, any University,
Board or medical institution, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that the staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other
facilities for instruction and training provided in such University, Board or
medical institution or in any college or other institution affiliated to the
University,
 do
not conform to the standard prescribed by the Central Council, the Central
Council shall make a representation to that effect to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
After considering such representation, the Central Government may send it to the
Government of the State in which the University, Board or medical institution is
situated and the State Government shall forward it along with such remarks as it
may choose to make to the University, Board or medical institution, with an
intimation of the period within which the University, Board or medical
institution may submit its explanation to the State Government. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
On the receipt of the explanation or, where no explanation is submitted within
the period fixed, then, on the expiry of that period, the State Government shall
make its recommendations to the Central Government. 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Central Government, after making such further inquiry, if any, as it may
think fit, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that an entry
shall be made in the appropriate Schedule against the said medical qualification
declaring that it shall be a recognized medical qualification only when granted
before a specified date, or that the said medical qualification if granted to
students of a specified college or institution affiliated to any University
shall be recognized medical qualification only when granted before a specified
date or, as the case may be, that the said medical qualification shall be
recognized medical qualification in relation to a specified college or
institution affiliated to any University only when granted after a specified
date. 


  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Minimum standards of education in Indian medicine.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Council may prescribe the minimum standards of education in Indian
medicine, required for granting recognized medical qualifications by
Universities, Boards or medical institutions in India. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Copies of the draft regulations and of all subsequent amendments thereof shall
be furnished by the Central Council to all State Governments and the Central
Council shall, before submitting the regulations or any amendment thereof, as
the case may be, to the Central Government for sanction, take into consideration
the comments of any State Government received within three months from the
furnishing of the copies as aforesaid. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Each of the committees referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section
(1) of section 9 shall, from time to time, report to the Central Council on the
efficacy of the regulations and may recommend to the Central Council such
amendments thereof as it may think fit. 


 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>23</number>
The Central Register of Indian Medicine.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Council shall cause to be maintained in the prescribed manner, a
register of practitioners in separate parts for each of the system of Indian
medicine to be known as the Central Register of Indian Medicine which shall
contain the names of all persons who are for the time being enrolled on any
State Register of Indian Medicine and who possess any of the recognized medical
qualifications. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It shall be the duty of the Registrar of the Central Council to keep and
maintain the Central Register of Indian Medicine in accordance with the
provisions of this Act and of any orders made by the Central Council and from
time to time to revise the register and publish it in the Gazette of India in
such other manner as may be prescribed. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Such register shall be deemed to be a public document within the meaning of the
Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) and may be proved by a copy published in
the Gazette of India. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number>
Supply of copies of State Register of Indian Medicine.—Each
Board shall supply to the Central Council three printed copies of the State
Register of Indian Medicine as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act
and subsequently after the first day of April of each year, and each Board shall
inform the Central Council without delay of all additions to and other
amendments in the State Register of Indian Medicine made from time to time. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number>
Registration in the Central Register of Indian Medicine.—The
Registrar of the Central Council may on receipt of the report of registration of
a person in a State Register of Indian Medicine or on application made in the
prescribed manner by any person, enter his name in the Central Register of
Indian Medicine, provided that the Registrar is satisfied that the person
concerned is eligible under this Act for such registration. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number>
Professional conduct.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Council may prescribe standards of professional conduct and etiquette
and a code of ethics for practitioners of Indian medicine. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Regulations made by the Central Council under sub-section (1) may specify which
violations thereof shall constitute infamous conduct in any professional
respect, that is to say, professional misconduct and such provision shall have
effect notwith- standing anything contained in any law for the time being in
force. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number>
Removal of names from the Central Register of Indian Medicine.— 

<section><number>1</number> If the name of any person enrolled on a State Register of Indian Medicine is
removed therefrom in pursuance of any power conferred by or under any law
relating to registration of practitioners of Indian medicine for the time being
in force in any State, the Central Council shall direct the removal of the name
of such person from the Central Register of Indian Medicine. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where the name of any person has been removed from a State Register of Indian
Medicine on any ground other than that he is not possessed of the requisite
medical qualifications or where any application by the said person for
restoration of his name to the State Register of Indian Medicine has been
rejected, he may appeal in the prescribed manner and subject to such conditions,
including conditions as to the payment of a fee, as may be prescribed, to the
Central Government whose decision, which shall be given after consulting the
Central Council, shall be binding on the State Government and on the authorities
concerned with the preparation of the State Register of Indian Medicine. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>28</number>
Provisional registration for practice.—If
the courses of study to be undergone for obtaining a recognized medical
qualification in Indian medicine include a period of training after a person has
passed the qualifying examination and before such qualification is conferred on
him, any such person shall, on application made by him in this behalf, be
granted provisional registration in a State Register of Indian Medicine by the
Board concerned in order to enable him to practice Indian medicine in an
approved institution for the purpose of such training and for no other purpose
for the period aforesaid. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number>
Privileges of persons who are enrolled on the Central Register of Indian
Medicine.—Subject to the conditions
and restrictions laid down in this Act regarding practice of Indian medicine by
persons possessing certain recognized medical qualifications, every person whose
name is for the time being borne on the Central Register of Indian Medicine
shall be entitled according to his qualifications to practise Indian medicine in
any part of India and to recover in due course of law in respect of such
practice any expenses, charges in respect of medicaments or other appliances or
any fees to which he may be entitled. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>30</number>
Registration of additional qualifications.—
<section><number>1</number>
If any person whose name is entered in the Central Register of Indian Medicine
obtains any title, diploma or other qualifications for proficiency in Indian
medicine which is a recognized medical qualification, he shall, on application
made in this behalf in the prescribed manner, be entitled to have an entry
stating such other title, diploma or other qualification made against his name
in the Central Register of Indian Medicine either in substitution for or in
addition to any entry previously made. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The entries in respect of any such person in a State Register of Indian Medicine
shall be altered in accordance with the alterations made in the Central Register
of Indian Medicine. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>31</number>
Persons enrolled on Central Register of Indian Medicine to notify change of
place of residence and practice.—Every
person registered in the Central Register of Indian Medicine shall notify any
transfer of the place of his residence or practice to the Central Council and to
the Board concerned, within ninety days of such transfer, failing which his
right to participate in the election of members to the Central Council or a
Board shall be liable to be forfeited by order of the Central Government either
permanently or for such period as may be specified therein. 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>32</number>
Information to be furnished by Central Council and publication thereof.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its minutes, abstracts
of its accounts and other information to the Central Government as that
Government may require. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Government may publish in such manner, as it may think fit, any
report, copy, abstract or other information furnished to it under this section
or under section 20. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>33</number>
Commission of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever
it is made to appear to the Central Government that the Central Council is not
complying with any of the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may
refer the particulars of the complaint to a commission of inquiry consisting of
three persons, two of whom shall be appointed by the Central Government, one
being a Judge of a High Court and one by the Central Council, and such
commission shall proceed to inquire in a summary manner and to report to the
Central Government as to the truth of the matters charged in the complaint and
in case of any charge of default or of improper action being found by the
commission to have been established, the commission shall recommend the
remedies, it any, which are in its opinion necessary. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Government may require the Central Council to adopt
the remedies so recommended within such time as, having regard to the report of
the commission, it may think fit, and if the Central Council fails to comply
with any such requirement, the Central Government may amend the regulations of
the Central Council, or make such provision or order or take such other
steps as may seem necessary to give effect to the recommendations of the
commission. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A commission of inquiry shall have power to administer oaths, to enforce the
attendance of witnesses and the production of documents, and shall have all such
other necessary powers for the purpose of any inquiry conducted by it as are
exercised by a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908). 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>34</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government,
the Central Council or a Board or any committee thereof or any officer or
servant of the Government or the Central Council or the Board aforesaid for
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 


   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out
the purposes of this Act. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is
made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[in
two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session
immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that
the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything
previously done under that rule. 


  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number>
Power to make regulations.—<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
The Central Council, may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[by
notification in the Official Gazette,] make regulations generally to carry out
the purposes of this Act, and, without prejudice to the generality of this
power, such regulations may provide for— 


 <subsection><number>a</number> the manner of election of the President and the Vice-Presidents of
the Central Council;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the management of the
property of the Central Council and the maintenance and audit of its accounts;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the resignation of members
of the Central Council;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the powers and duties of the President and Vice-President;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the summoning and holding
of meetings of the Central Council and the committees thereof, the times and
places where such meetings are to be held, and the conduct of business thereat
and the number of members necessary to constitute a quorum;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the functions of the committees constituted under section 9 or
section 10;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the tenure of office, and the powers and duties of the Registrar and
other officers and servants of the Central Council;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>ga</number>
the form of the scheme, the particulars to be given in such scheme, the
manner in which the scheme is to be preferred and the fees payable with the
scheme under sub-section (3) of section 13A;
 </subsection><subsection><number>gb</number>
any other factor under clause (g) of sub-section (8) of section 13A;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the appointment, powers, duties
and procedure of inspectors and visitors;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the courses and period of study and of practical training to be
undertaken, the subjects of examination and the standards of proficiency therein
to be obtained, in any University, Board or medical institutions for grant of
recognized medical qualifications;
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the standards of staff, equipments, accommodation, training and other
facilities for education in Indian medicine;
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the conduct of professional examinations, qualifications of examiners
and the conditions of admission to such examinations;
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> the standards of professional conduct and etiquette and code of
ethics to be observed by practitioners of Indian medicine;
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the particulars to be stated and the
proof of qualifications to be given in applications for registration under this
Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> the manner in which and the conditions subject to which an appeal
under section 27 may be preferred;
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> the fees to be paid on applications and appeals under this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> any matter for which under this Act provision may be made by
regulations.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
The Central Government shall cause every regulation made under this Act to be
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while
it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of
the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or
both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the
case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that
regulation.] 


   










 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Sections 2, 13, 32 to 36 (both inclusive came into force in the whole
of India on 15-8-1971; sections 3, 5 to 12 (both inclusive) and 14 to 16 (both
inclusive) came into force in all the States except the State of Nagaland and
the Union Territory of Delhi on 15-8-1971. Vide S.O. 2994 published in
the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), dated 11th August, 1971;
sections 18 to 22 came into force on 1-10-1974, vide S.O. 584(E)
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 1997, dated
1st October, 1974; sections 17, 23 to 31 came into force on 1-10-1976, vide
S.O. 626 (E), dated 10th September, 1976, published in the Gazette of India,
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), dated 21st September, 1976; section 4 came into
force on 17-11-1983, vide S.O. 816(E), published in the Gazette of India,
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 17th November, 1983.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 2, for “or Unani Tibb”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 58 of 2003, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 7-11-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 3(a), for “and Unani”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 3(b), for “or Unani”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 3(a), for “and Unani”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 5(A), for sub-section (1). Sub-section (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 5(B), for “and Unani”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 5(C), for “or Unani”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  13A subs. by Act 58 of 2003, sec. 3, for Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) (w.r.e.f. 7-11-2003). Earlier Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) was inserted by Act 52 of 2002, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-1-2003)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  13A subs. by Act 58 of 2003, sec. 3, for Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) (w.r.e.f. 7-11-2003). Earlier Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) was inserted by Act 52 of 2002, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-1-2003)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  13C subs. by Act 58 of 2003, sec. 3, for Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) (w.r.e.f. 7-11-2003). Earlier Chapter IIA (containing sections 13A and 13B) was inserted by Act 52 of 2002, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-1-2003)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 2010, sec. 6, for “physician or”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>
Subs. by Act 20 of 1983, sec. 2 and Sch., for certain words (w.e.f.
15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>
Section 36 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 20 of 1983, sec.
2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>
Ins. by Act 20 of 1983, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>
Ins. by Act 52 of 2002, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 28-1-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>