<act><title>


The foreign awards (recognition and 
    enforcement) act, 1961</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Foreign Awards (Recognition and Enforcement) Act, 
    1961. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, “foreign award” means an 
    award on differences between persons arising out of legal relationships 
    whether contractual or not, considered as commercial under the law in force 
    in India, made on or after the 11th day of October, 1960—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in pursuance of an agreement in 
    writing for arbitration to which the Convention set forth in the Schedule 
    applies, and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in one of such territories as the 
    Central Government, being satisfied that reciprocal provisions have been 
    made, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
    territories to which the said Convention applies.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>3</number> Stay of 
    proceedings in respect of matters to be referred to arbitration.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Arbitration Act, 1940, or in the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), if any party to an agreement to which Article 
    II of the Convention set forth in the Schedule applies, or any person 
    claiming through or under him commences any legal proceedings in any court 
    against any other party to the  agreement or any person claiming through or 
    under him in respect of any matter agreed to be referred to arbitration in 
    such agreement, any party to such legal proceedings may, at any time after 
    appearance and before filing a written statement or taking any other step in 
    the proceedings, apply to the court to stay the proceedings and the court, 
    unless satisfied that the agreement is null and void, 
    inoperative or incapable of being performed or that there is not, in fact, 
    any dispute between the parties with regard to the matter agreed to be 
    referred, shall make an order staying the proceedings.]  
 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Effect of foreign awards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A foreign award shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, be enforceable 
    in India as if it were an award made on a matter referred to arbitration in 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    foreign award which would be enforceable under this Act shall be treated as 
    binding for all purposes on the persons as between whom it was made, and may 
    accordingly be relied on by any of those persons by way of defence, set off 
    or otherwise in any legal proceedings in India and any references in this 
    Act to enforcing a foreign award shall be construed as including references 
    to relying on an award.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Filing of foreign award in court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person interested in a foreign award may apply to any court having 
    jurisdiction over the subject-matter of the award that the award be filed in 
    court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    application shall be in writing and shall be numbered and registered as a 
    suit between the applicant as plaintiff and the other parties as defendants.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    court shall direct notice to be given to the parties to the arbitration, 
    other than the applicant, requiring them to show cause, within a time 
    specified by the award should not be filed.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Enforcement of foreign award.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the court is satisfied that the foreign award is enforceable under 
    this act, the court shall order the award to be filed and shall proceed to 
    pronounce judgement according to the award.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the judgment so pronounced a decree shall follow, and no appeal shall lie 
    from such decree except insofar as the decree is in excess of or not in 
    accordance with the award.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Conditions for enforcement of foreign awards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A foreign award may not be enforced under this Act—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if the party against whom it is 
    sought to enforce the award proves to the court dealing with the case that—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the parties to the agreement were, 
    under the law applicable to them, under some incapacity, or the said 
    agreement is not valid under the law to which the parties have subjected it, 
    or failing any indication thereon, under the law of the country where the 
    award was made; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   the party was not given proper 
    notice or the appointment of the arbitrator or of the arbitration 
    proceedings or was otherwise unable to present his case; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   the award deals with questions 
    not referred or contains decisions on matters beyond the scope of agreement:  
 
Provided that if the decisions on 
    matters submitted to arbitration can be separated from those not submitted, 
    that part of the award which contains decisions on matters submitted to may 
    be enforced; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   the composition of the arbitral 
    authority or the arbitral procedure was not in accordance with the agreement 
    of the parties or failing such agreement, was not in accordance with the law 
    of the country where the arbitration took place; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   the award has not yet become on 
    the parties or has been set aside or suspended by a competent authority of 
    the country in which, or under the law of which, that award was made; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if the court dealing with the case 
    is satisfied that—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the subject-matter of the 
    difference is not capable of settlement by arbitration under the law of 
    India; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   the enforcement of the award will 
    be contrary to public policy.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the court before which award is sought to be relied upon is satisfied that 
    an application for the setting aside or suspension of the award has been 
    made to a competent authority referred to in sub-clause (v) of clause (a) of 
    sub-section (1), the court may, if it deems proper, adjourn the decision on 
    the enforcement of the award and may also, on the application of the party 
    claiming enforcement of the award, order the other party to furnish suitable 
    security.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The party applying for the enforcement of a foreign award shall, at the time 
    of the application, produce—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the original award or a copy 
    thereof, duly authenticated in the manner required by the law of the country 
    in which it was made;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the original agreement for 
    arbitration or a duly certified copy thereof; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   such evidence as may be necessary 
    to prove that the award is a foreign award.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the award or agreement requiring to be produced under sub-section (1) is in 
    a foreign language the party seeking to enforce the award shall produce a 
    translation into English certified as correct by a diplomatic or consular 
    agent of the country to which that party belongs or certified as correct in 
    such other manner as may be sufficient according to the law in force in 
    India.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Saving.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   prejudice any rights which any 
    person would have had of enforcing in India of any award or of availing 
    himself in India of any award if this Act had not been passed; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   apply to any award made on an 
    arbitration agreement governed by the law of India.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Repeal.—The 
    Arbitration (Protocol and Convention) Act, 1937, shall cease to have effect 
    in relation to foreign awards to which this Act applies.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Rule making power of the High Court.—The 
    High Court may make rules consistent with this Act as to—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the filing of foreign awards and 
    all proceedings consequent thereon or incidental thereto;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the evidence which must be 
    furnished by a party seeking to enforce foreign award under this Act; and  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   generally, all proceedings in 
    court under this Act.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>