<act><title>

The
Preference Shares (Regulation of Dividends) Act, 1960

</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Preference Shares (Regulation of Dividends) Act,
1960. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India*: 


 Provided
that it shall not apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir except to the extent
to which the provisions of this Act relate to the regulation of dividends on
preference shares of banking and insurance companies and financial corporations. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the provisions of this
Act shall, in their application to the Union territory of Pondicherry, have
effect subject to the modifications specified in the Schedule. 


   
























  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Companies Act” means the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“company” means an Indian company as defined in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Clause
(26) of section 2 of Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) and includes a company
referred to in sub-clause (ii) of clause (17)] of the said section which has
made arrangements for the declaration and payment of dividends within India in
accordance with the rules made under the said Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“preference share” means a share which <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]
carries, as respects dividends, a preferential right to be paid a fixed amount
or an amount calculated at a fixed rate;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“previous year” has the same meaning as in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Income-tax
Act, 1961 (43 of 1961)];
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
“stipulated dividend”, in relation to a preference share, means the
fixed amount or the amount calculated at a fixed rate which the holder of such
share has a preferential right to be paid as dividend;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
all other words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and
defined in the Companies Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to
them in that Act.
   










  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Regulation of dividends on preference shares in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where the stipulated dividend in respect of a preference share of a company <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[issued
and subscribed for before the 1st April, 1960,]— 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
is specified to be free of income-tax and no deduction is made therefrom
on account of the income-tax payable by the company, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
was being paid before the Ist April, 1960, without any deduction
therefrom on account of the income-tax payable by the company, notwithstanding
the absence of any specification that the dividend would be free of income-tax,
 every
such share shall, as respects dividends declared after the commencement of this
Act, carry a preferential right to be paid without any deduction aforesaid such
amount as would exceed the stipulated dividend by thirty per cent thereof. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where the stipulated dividend in respect of a preference share of a company
issued and subscribed for after the 31st March, 1959 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[and
before the 1st April, 1960,] is free of income-tax and the company, besides
paying the stipulated dividend to the holder of such share, pays to Government
on his behalf any sum on account of income-tax payable thereon, then, every such
share shall, as respects dividends declared after the commencement of this Act,
carry a preferential right to be paid free of income-tax such amount as together
with the sum aforesaid would exceed the stipulated dividend by thirty per cent
thereof. 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where the stipulated dividend in respect of a preference share of a company <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[issued
and subscribed for before the 1st April, 1960,]— 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
is specified to be subject to income-tax and a deduction is made
therefrom on account of the income-tax payable by the company, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
was being paid before the Ist April, 1960, subject to a deduction
therefrom on account of the income-tax payable by the company, notwithstanding
the absence of any specification that the dividend would be subject to
income-tax, then every such share shall, as respects dividends declared after
the commencement of this Act, carry a preferential right to be paid subject to
the deduction aforesaid such amount as would exceed the stipulated dividend by
eleven per cent. thereof.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Where a company has in relation to a preference share <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[issued
and subscribed for before the Ist April, 1960] declared,— 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
after the 31st March, 1959, and before the Ist July, 1960, a dividend in
respect of a previous year relevant to its assessment year 1960-61 or a
subsequent assessment year, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
after the 30th June, 1960, and before the commencement of this Act, a
dividend in respect of any previous year,
 it
shall declare, in respect of the said previous year, an additional dividend of
such amount as, together with the dividend already declared, would exceed the
stipulated dividend— 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>
by thirty per cent of the stipulated dividend in the cases referred to in
sub-section (1), or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>
by eleven per cent of the stipulated dividend in the cases referred to in
sub-section (3).
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
For the purposes of sub-section (1), sub-section (3) and sub-section (4), any
reference therein to the stipulated dividend shall, in respect of a preference
share issued and subscribed for on or before the 31st March, 1959, be construed
as a reference to the stipulated dividend as on that day. 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any reference in this
section <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[and
section 4A] to deduction made from a dividend “on account of the income-tax
payable by the company” does not include any amount deducted by the company
from that dividend under <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[section
194 of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961)]. 


   











  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Special provisions in relation to companies where a portion of their income is
not chargeable to income-tax.—<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[Where
any preference share of a company has been issued and subscribed for before 1st
April, 1960, and any portion of the profits and gains of the company] in respect
of the relevant period is exempt from income-tax under the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Income-tax
Act, 1961 (43 of 1961,] by reason of such portion being agricultural income,
then, for the purpose of the increase in the dividend in relation to any such
preference share under the provisions of section 3, the increase of thirty per
cent. or eleven per cent referred to therein shall be taken to be such
proportion of the said thirty per cent or eleven per cent, as the case may be,
as the total amount of the profits and gains of the company excluding the
portion of the profits and gains which is so exempt in respect of the relevant
period bears to the total amount of the profits and gains thereof in respect of
that period. 


 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section, “relevant period”, in relation to the profits
and gains of a company, shall mean— 


 <section><number>a</number>
the previous years relevant to such of the three assessment years as
immediately precede the assessment year ending on the 31st March, 1961, and in
each of which the net result of the computation of profits and gains of the
company has not been a loss or where there are only two such years, such two
years, or where there is only one such year, such one year; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
in any case where clause (a) is not applicable, the previous year
relevant to the assessment year ending on the 31st March, 1961 or a subsequent
assessment year immediately following thereafter in which the net result of the
computation of profits and gains has not been a loss.
  











  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number>
Deduction of income-tax.—Where the stipulated dividend in respect of a
preference share of a company— 


 <section><number>a</number>
is specified to be subject to income-tax and a deduction is made
therefrom on account of the income-tax payable by the company, or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
is being paid subject to a deduction therefrom an account of the
income-tax payable by the company, notwithstanding the absence of any
specification that the dividend would be subject to income-tax,
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[such
deduction made by the company from any dividend declared after the 28th day of
February, 1966 shall in no case exceed twenty-seven and a half per cent of the
aggregate of— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
the stipulated dividend, and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
an amount equal to eleven per cent of the stipulated dividend as
specified in sub-section (3) of section 3].]
  











  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Over-riding effect of Act.—
<section><number>1</number>
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the
contrary contained in any law for the time being in force or in the memorandum
or articles of a company or in any agreement between the company and its
shareholders or in any resolution passed by the company in a general meeting or
by its Board of directors. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, a company may, in the manner
provided in section 106 of the Companies Act, increase the amount of dividend in
respect of a preference share beyond the limit specified in section 3 or section
4 of this Act. 


   



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Act not to apply to participating preference dividends.—Nothing
contained in <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[section
3 or section 4] shall apply to such part of any dividend on preference shares as
is referred to in clause 
<section><number>i</number> of the Explanation to sub-section (1) of
section 85 of the Companies Act. 


   








  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules
for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is
made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the
session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the
case may be, so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule. 

  



  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Certain words omitted by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72 (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for “Indian Income-tax Act, 1922 (14
of 1922)” (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Ins. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72 (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Ins. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72 (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for certain words (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
Ins. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72 (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Subs. by Act 13 of 1966, sec. 52, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-4-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Subs. by Act 10 of 1965, sec. 72, for “this Act” (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1965).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>