<act><tid>1690572</tid>
<title>THE DISPLACED PERSONS (DEBTS ADJUSTMENT) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 70 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 7th November, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to make certain provisions for the adjustment and settlement of 
debts due by displaced persons, for the recovery of certain debts due 
to them and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1213130</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1926715</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1211086</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>1141580</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and 
different dates may be appointed for different States or for different 
parts thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1630880</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>416415</tid>
<number>1</number>" company" means a company as defined in the Indian 
Companies Act, <year>1913</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (7 of <year>1913</year>), and includes a 
company deemed to be registered under that Act by 
reason of any of the provisions contained in this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>197629</tid>
<number>2</number>" Companies Act" means the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>860160</tid>
<number>3</number>" compensation" means any compensation paid, whether in 
cash or in kind, in respect of any immovable property 
in West Pakistan belonging to a displaced person under 
any general scheme arrived at in this behalf between 
the Government of India and the Government of Pakistan 
or framed by the Government of India;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 10th December, <year>1951</year> in the States of Delhi, Ajmer, Punjab, Uttar 
Pradesh and Bombay: see notification No. 68 (21) 51-Prop., dated 7th 
December, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1951</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. I, Sec 1, 
p. 503: and in all other States of India, 20th December, <year>1951</year>: see 
notification No. S. R. O. <year>2005</year>, dated 13th December, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of 
India, Extraordinary, <year>1951</year>, pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1489. 
2. This Act has now been repealed by Act 1 of <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>352943</tid>
<number>4</number>" co- operative society" means a co- operative society 
registered under the Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> 
 (2 of <year>1912</year>), or under any other law for the time being 
in force in any State for the registration of co- 
operative societies;

</section>

<section><tid>1481004</tid>
<number>5</number>" Co- operative Societies Act" means the Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>), and includes any other 
law for the time being in force in any State relating 
to co- operative societies;

</section>

<section><tid>1706938</tid>
<number>6</number>" debt" means any pecuniary liability, whether payable 
presently or in future, or under a decree or order of a 
Civil or Revenue Court or otherwise, or whether 
ascertained or to be ascertained, which--

<subsection><tid>1775559</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a displaced person who has left 
or been displaced from his place of residence in any 
area now forming part of West Pakistan, was incurred 
before he came to reside in any area now forming part 
of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1009106</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a displaced person who, before 
and after the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, has been 
residing in any area now forming part of India, was 
incurred before the said date on the security of any 
immovable property situate in the territories now 
forming part of West Pakistan:
Provided that where any such liability was 
incurred on the security of immovable properties 
situate both in India and in West Pakistan, the 
liability shall be so apportioned between the said 
properties that the liability in relation to each of 
the said properties bears the same proportion to the 
total amount of the debts as the value of each of the 
properties as at the date of the transaction bears to 
the total value of the properties furnished as 
security, and the liability, for the purposes of this 
clause, shall be the liability which is relatable to 
the property in West Pakistan;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>339036</tid>
<number>c</number>is due to a displaced person from any other 
person (whether a displaced person or not) ordinarily 
residing in the territories to which this Act extends;
and includes

any pecuniary liability incurred before the 
commencement of this Act by any such person as is 
referred to in this clause which is based on, and is 
solely by way of


<pagefootnote><pagenum>63</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

renewal of, any such liability as is referred to in 
sub- clause (a) or sub- clause (b) or sub- clause (c):

Provided that in the case of a loan, whether in 
cash or in kind, the amount originally advanced and not 
the amount for which the liability has been renewed 
shall be deemed to be the extent of the liability;

but does not include

any pecuniary liability due under a decree passed 
after the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, by any Court 
situate in West Pakistan or any pecuniary liability the 
proof of which depends merely on an oral agreement;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>185942</tid>
<number>7</number>" displaced bank" means a banking company which, before 
the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, carried on the business 
of banking, whether wholly or partially, in any area 
now forming part of West Pakistan and is declared to be 
a displaced bank within the meaning of this Act by the 
Central Government by notification <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the Official 
gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1879412</tid>
<number>8</number>" displaced creditor" means a displaced person to whom a 
debt is due from any other person, whether a displaced 
person or not;

</section>

<section><tid>789728</tid>
<number>9</number>" displaced debtor" means a displaced person from whom a 
debt is due or is being claimed;

</section>

<section><tid>1097902</tid>
<number>10</number>" displaced person" means any person who, on account of 
the setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan, 
or on account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances in any area now forming part of West 
Pakistan, has, after the 1st day of March, <year>1947</year>, left, 
or been displaced from, his place of residence in such 
area and who has been subsequently residing in India, 
and includes any person who is resident in any place 
now forming part of India and who for that reason is 
unable or has been rendered unable to manage, supervise 
or control any immovable property belonging to him in 
West Pakistan, but does not include a banking company;

</section>

<section><tid>940017</tid>
<number>11</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>64</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such notifications see Gazette of India, <year>1952</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 
3, pp. 624 and 889, and ibid., <year>1953</year>, p. 238.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1404010</tid>
<number>12</number>" Tribunal" means any Civil Court specified under 
section 4 as having authority to exercise jurisdiction 
under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>429398</tid>
<number>13</number>" verified claim" means any claim registered under the 
Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>) in 
respect of which a final order has been passed under 
that Act relating to its verification and valuation;

</section>

<section><tid>101048</tid>
<number>14</number>" West Pakistan" means the territories of Pakistan 
excluding the Province of East Bengal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365709</tid>
<number>3</number>Overriding effect of Act, rules and orders. Save as otherwise 
expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act and of the 
rules and orders made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding 
anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, or in any decree or order of a Court, or in any 
contract between the parties.


</article>



<article><tid>1364765</tid>
<number>4</number>Tribunals competent to exercise jurisdiction under this Act. 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify any Civil Court or class of Civil Courts as the Tribunal or 
Tribunals having authority to exercise jurisdiction under this Act and 
may define the areas in which and the extent to which such 
jurisdiction may be exercised.
CHAP

DEBT ADJUSTMENT PROCEEDINGS

CHAPTER II

DEBT ADJUSTMENT PROCEEDINGS



</article>



<article><tid>1898739</tid>
<number> 5</number> Application by displaced debtors for adjustment of debts.
<section><tid>1416386</tid>
<number>1</number> 
At any time within one year after the date on which this Act comes 
into force in any local area, a displaced debtor may make an 
application for the adjustment of his debts to the Tribunal within the 
local limits of whose jurisdiction he actually and voluntarily 
resides, or carries on business or personally works for gain.

</section>

<section><tid>834796</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application by a displaced debtor shall contain the 
following particulars, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1303257</tid>
<number>a</number>the place where he resides;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>55345</tid>
<number>b</number>the trade, calling, profession or other employment in 
which he is now engaged and in which he was engaged in 
West Pakistan before he became a displaced person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630249</tid>
<number>c</number>his average annual income in India during the three 
years immediately preceding the application;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>65</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1965126</tid>
<number>d</number>the income- tax and super- tax, if any, to which he has 
been assessed for the three years immediately preceding 
the application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1483597</tid>
<number>e</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed;
and shall be accompanied by the following schedules, namely:--


<subsubsection><tid>1652653</tid>
<number>i</number>a schedule containing full particulars of all his 
debts, whether owed jointly or individually, with the 
names and addresses of his creditors and joint- debtors, 
if any, so far as they are known to, or can by the 
exercise of reasonable care and diligence be 
ascertained by him;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1173821</tid>
<number>ii</number>a schedule of all his properties, both movable and 
immovable (including claims due to him) which are not 
liable to attachment either under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>) as amended by section 31 
of this Act or under any other law for the time being 
in force, a specification of the values thereof and of 
the places where the same may be found;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>207206</tid>
<number>iii</number>a schedule of all his properties, both movable and 
immovable (including claims due to him) which are not 
included in the schedule under item (ii) of this 
clause; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1146022</tid>
<number>iv</number>a schedule of all his properties in respect of which a 
claim has been submitted to the registering officer 
under the Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year>, (44 of  
  <year>1950</year>) and, where any order has been passed in relation 
to the verification and valuation of the claim under 
that Act, with a certified copy of the order.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>484785</tid>
<number>3</number>All persons whose names are shown in any schedule as having 
claims against the displaced debtor and all persons whose names are 
shown as joint- debtors shall be deemed to be the respondents to the 
application and there shall be filed along with the application, or 
with the permission of the Tribunal at any later stage of the 
proceedings, as many copies of the application and as many envelopes 
and notices in the prescribed form duly addressed to the respondents 
as there are respondents.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362827</tid>
<number>6</number>Rejection of application in certain cases. Where an 
application made under section 5 does not comply with any of the 
requirements of that section, the Tribunal may either reject it, or 
grant to the applicant such further time as it thinks fit to comply 
with such requirements.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>66</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1400205</tid>
<number>7</number>Issue of notice. If the application is not rejected under 
section 6, the Tribunal shall, after causing the date for the hearing 
of the application to be entered in the notices referred to in section 
5, cause them to be served on the respondents.


</article>



<article><tid>1563108</tid>
<number>8</number>Objection by respondents. In response to a notice under 
section 7, the respondent may show cause against the application by 
filing a written statement containing his objections to the 
application:
Provided that where he does not appear in person or through any 
authorized agent, the written statement may be sent by registered 
post, acknowledgment due, to the Tribunal after having been signed in 
the presence of a civil judicial officer or a Magistrate or any other 
prescribed officer and duly attested by such officer or Magistrate.



</article>



<article><tid>994108</tid>
<number> 9</number> Proceeding after service of notice on respondents.
<section><tid>333677</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
there is a dispute as to whether the applicant is a displaced person 
or not or as to the existence or the amount of the debt due to any 
creditor or the assets of any displaced debtor, the Tribunal shall 
decide the matter after taking such evidence as may be adduced by all 
the parties concerned and shall pass such decree in relation thereto 
as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>339877</tid>
<number>2</number>If there is no such dispute or if the respondents do not 
appear or have no objection to the application being granted, the 
Tribunal may, after considering the evidence placed before it, pass 
such decree in relation thereto as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1065345</tid>
<number>10</number>Claims by creditors against displaced debtors. Any displaced 
person having a claim against a displaced debtor may make an 
application, in such form as may be prescribed, for the determination 
thereof to the Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the displaced debtor actually and voluntarily resides, or carries on 
business, or personally works for gain, together with a statement of 
the debts owed to the creditor with full particulars thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>577381</tid>
<number> 11</number> Procedure on creditor' s petition.
<section><tid>752381</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an application  
under section 10 has been made, the Tribunal shall cause notice 
thereof to be served on the displaced debtor calling upon him either 
to show cause, if any, against the application or to make an 
application on his own behalf under section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>1529885</tid>
<number>2</number>If, in response to a notice under sub- section (1), the 
displaced debtor makes an application in accordance with the 
provisions of section 5, the Tribunal shall proceed further in the 
matter as if it had commenced with an application by the displaced 
debtor under section 
5, and all the other provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly; 
but, if the displaced debtor does not choose to make any such 
application, the Tribunal shall, after considering such evidence, if 
any, as may be produced before it, determine the claim and pass such 
decree in relation thereto as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1765169</tid>
<number>3</number>The period of limitation specified in sub- section (1) of 
section 5 in respect of an application by a displaced debtor shall not 
apply to an application made under sub- section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1624239</tid>
<number> 12</number> Objection by creditor to schedule of assets.
<section><tid>1221106</tid>
<number>1</number>Any creditor  
of a displaced debtor may make an application to the Tribunal stating 
that the displaced debtor, who has made an application under section 5 
or sub- section (2) of section 11, has concealed any part of his 
assets, and the Tribunal shall, after giving due notice thereof to the 
displaced debtor, determine the matter.

</section>

<section><tid>452190</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Tribunal finds that the displaced debtor has wilfully 
and fraudulently omitted to include such assets in his application, 
the Tribunal may dismiss the application or refuse to allow to the 
displaced debtor any of the reliefs under this Act to which he would 
otherwise have been entitled or pass such other order in relation 
thereto as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1636823</tid>
<number>13</number>Claims by displaced creditors against persons who are not 
displaced debtors. At any time within one year after the date on which 
this Act comes into force in any local area, any displaced creditor 
claiming a debt from any other person who is not a displaced person 
may make an application, in such form as may be prescribed, to the 
Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction he or the 
respondent or, if there are more respondents than one, any of such 
respondents, actually and voluntarily resides, or carries on business 
or personally works for gain, together with a statement of the debt 
owing to him with full particulars thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>1559118</tid>
<number> 14</number> Procedure on displaced creditor' s petition.
<section><tid>650576</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an  
application under section 13 has been made to the Tribunal, the 
Tribunal shall cause notice thereof to be given to the debtor, calling 
upon him to show cause, if any, against the application.

</section>

<section><tid>1449569</tid>
<number>2</number>If there is a dispute as to whether the applicant is a 
displaced creditor or not or as to the existence of the debt or as to 
the amount thereof, the Tribunal shall decide the matter, after taking 
such evidence as may be produced before it, and pass such decree in 
relation thereto as it thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>68</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1295771</tid>
<number>3</number>If there is no such dispute or if the debtor does not appear 
or has no cause to show, the Tribunal may, after considering the 
evidence placed before it, pass such decree in relation thereto as it 
thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>858901</tid>
<number> 15</number> Consequences of application by displaced debtor. Where a 
displaced debtor has made an application to the Tribunal under section 
 5 or under sub- section (2) of section 11, the following consequences 
shall ensue, namely:--
<section><tid>1654267</tid>
<number>a</number>all proceedings pending at the date of the said 
application in any Civil Court in respect of any debt 
to which the displaced debtor is subject (except  
proceedings by way of appeal or review or revision 
against decrees or orders passed against the displaced 
  debtor) shall be stayed, and the records of all such 
proceedings other than those relating to the appeals, 
reviews or revisions as aforesaid shall be transferred 
to the Tribunal and consolidated;

</section>

<section><tid>317208</tid>
<number>b</number>all attachments, injunctions, orders appointing 
receivers or other processes issued by any such Court 
and in force at the date of the said application in 
respect of any such debt shall cease to have effect and 
no fresh process shall, except as hereinafter expressly 
provided, be issued:
Provided that where an order appointing a receiver 
ceases to have effect under this section, the receiver 
shall; within fourteen days from the date on which his 
appointment ceases to have effect or within such 
further time as the Tribunal may in any case allow, 
submit to the Tribunal instead of to the Court which 
appointed him his outstanding accounts, and the 
Tribunal shall, in relation to such accounts, have the 
same powers with respect to the receiver as the Court 
which appointed him had or could have had;


</section>

<section><tid>985419</tid>
<number>c</number>no fresh suit or other proceeding[ other than any such 
appeal, review or revision as is referred to in clause 
 (a)] shall be instituted against a displaced debtor in 
respect of any debt mentioned by him in the relevant 
schedule to his application:

</section>

<section><tid>1294719</tid>
<number>d</number>any immovable property belonging to the displaced 
debtor and liable to attachment shall not be 
transferred except under the authority of the Tribunal 
and no such terms as it thinks fit, until the 
application of the displaced debtor has been finally 
disposed of or any decree passed against

<pagefootnote><pagenum>69</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

him is satisfied in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1597621</tid>
<number> 16</number> Debts secured on immovable property.
<section><tid>1831827</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a debt  
incurred by a displaced person is secured by a mortgage, charge or 
lien on the immovable property belonging to him in West Pakistan, the 
Tribunal may, for the purpose of any proceeding under this Act, 
require the creditor to elect to retain the security or to be treated 
as an unsecured creditor.

</section>

<section><tid>1964519</tid>
<number>2</number>If the creditor elects to retain the security, he may apply 
to the Tribunal, having jurisdiction in this behalf as provided in 
section 10, for a declaration of the amount due under his debt.

</section>

<section><tid>959908</tid>
<number>3</number>Where in any case, the creditor elects to retain his 
security, if the displaced debtor received any compensation in respect 
of any such property as is referred to in sub- section (1), the 
creditor shall be entitled--

<subsection><tid>1139735</tid>
<number>a</number>Where the compensation is paid in cash, to a first 
charge thereon:
Provided that the amount of the debt in respect of 
which he shall be entitled to the first charge shall be 
that amount as bears to the total debt the same 
proportion as the compensation paid in respect of the 
property bears to the value of the verified claim in 
respect thereof and to that extent the debt shall be 
deemed to have been reduced:


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>541458</tid>
<number>b</number>Where the compensation is by way of exchange of 
property, to a first charge on the property situate in 
India so received by way of exchange:
Provided that the amount of the debt in respect of 
which be shall be entitled to the first charge shall be 
that amount as bears to the total debt the same 
proportion as the value of the property received by way 
of exchange bears to the value of the verified claim in 
respect thereof and to that extent the debt shall be 
deemed to have been reduced.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>720987</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where a 
debt is secured by a mortgage of agricultural lands belonging to a 
displaced person in West Pakistan and the mortgage was with 
possession, the mortgagee shall, if he has been allotted lands in 
India in lieu of the lands of which he was in possession in West 
Pakistan, be entitled

<pagefootnote><pagenum>70</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to continue in possession of the lands so allotted until the debt is 
satisfied from the usufruct of the lands or is redeemed by the debtor:

Provided that in either case the amount of the debt shall be only 
that amount as bears to the total debt the same proportion as the 
value of the lands allotted to the creditor in India bears to the 
value of the lands left behind by him in West Pakistan and to that 
extent the debt shall be deemed to have been reduced.


</section>

<section><tid>1761942</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a creditor elects to be treated as an unsecured 
creditor in relation to the debt, the provisions of this Act shall 
apply accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>431125</tid>
<number> 17</number> Debts secured on movable property.
<section><tid>324167</tid>
<number>1</number>Where in respect of a  
debt incurred by a displaced debtor and secured by the pledge of 
movable property belonging to him, the creditor had been placed in 
possession of such property at any time before the debtor became a 
displaced person, the following rules shall regulate the rights and 
liabilities of the creditor and the debtor, namely:-

<subsection><tid>322176</tid>
<number>a</number>the creditor may, if he is still in possession of the 
pledged property, realise the sum due to him by the 
sale of such property after giving to the debtor 
reasonable notice of the sale:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1459557</tid>
<number>b</number>the creditor shall not be entitled, in any case where 
the pledged property is no longer in his possession or 
is not available for redemption by the debtor to 
recover from the debtor the debt or any part thereof 
for which the pledged property was security:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1333342</tid>
<number>c</number>the debtor shall not be liable, in the case of a sale 
by the creditor of any pledged property, whether under 
clause (a) or otherwise, to pay the balance where the 
proceeds of such sale are less than the amount of the 
debt due:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>726028</tid>
<number>d</number>the creditor shall, in any case where the proceeds of 
the sale of the pledged property are greater than the 
amount of the debt due, pay over the surplus to the 
debtor.
Explanation I.- For the purposes of this section, the creditor 
shall be deemed to be in possession of the pledged property in any 
case in which the pledged property, although not delivered to him was 
delivered to a person authorized by him or was being held by the 
debtor on behalf of the creditor, and the ownership of possession 
thereof could not have been transferred to a third party without the 
express consent or permission of the creditor.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation II.- Where any motor vehicle or other movable property 
has been purchased with money the whole or any part of which has been 
advanced by a creditor who retains the ownership thereof by way of 
security but allows the debtor to use it with his permission, the 
property shall for the purposes of this section be deemed to be 
pledged property of the debtor in the possession of the creditor.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1317948</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the 
creditor shall be entitled to receive, and to give a valid discharge 
in respect of, any sum due under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force from an insurance company in respect of any 
claim arising out of the loss or destruction of the pledged property, 
but the creditor shall, in any case where the sum received from the 
insurance company is greater than the amount of the debt due to him, 
pay over the surplus to the debtor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>837023</tid>
<number> 18</number> Claims against insurance companies.
<section><tid>643080</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any property in  
West Pakistan belonging to a displaced person was insured with any 
insurance company before the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, against any 
risk arising out of fire or theft or riot and civil commotion and 
there has been a loss in respect of such property arising out of any 
such risk at a time when the contract of insurance was in force, such 
company shall not be entitled to refuse payment of the sum due under 
any claim in relation thereto on the ground that--

<subsection><tid>3171</tid>
<number>a</number>no report was lodged with the police within the agreed 
time, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>513209</tid>
<number>b</number>the claim was not made to the company with the agreed 
time, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>301807</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a policy covering any risk arising out 
of riot and civil commotion, the disturbances in West 
Pakistan were not in the nature of a riot or civil 
commotion, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486837</tid>
<number>d</number>the displaced person has not fulfilled any other 
condition of the contract which in the opinion of the 
Central government is of a technical nature and which 
the Central Government has, by notification <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the 
Official Gazette, specified as a condition of the 
contract for the purposes of this section,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See notification No. S. R. O. 350, dated February 13, <year>1953</year>; Gazette 
of India, <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 239.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and any contract to the contrary, to the extent to which it is in 
contravention of the provisions of this sub- section, shall be deemed 
to have had no effect.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>823527</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a loss has been incurred in respect of any property in 
the circumstances specified in sub- section (1), the Tribunal shall, in 
every proceeding where it is necessary to do so, determine 
respectively the amount of the loss, the amount for which the property 
was insured on the date of such loss, and the amount, if any, paid by 
the insurance company, and shall make a report thereof to such board 
or other authority as may be prescribed, and the prescribed board or 
other authority shall, after taking into account such matters as may 
be prescribed as being relevant thereto, and subject to any rules made 
in this behalf, in turn propose to the Tribunal the amount for which 
the claim against the insurance company shall be decreed, and the 
Tribunal shall pass a decree accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>204802</tid>
<number>3</number>The amount realised from the insurance company under any 
decree passed under sub- section (2) shall first be applied towards the 
satisfaction of the debt due from the displaced person, and the 
balance, if any, shall be refunded to the displaced person.

</section>

<section><tid>700478</tid>
<number>4</number>An application under this section may be made either by a 
displaced person having a claim against the insurance company in the 
circumstances specified in sub- section (1) or by an assignee or any 
other person having an interest in the claim of any such displaced 
person, to the Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the displaced person actually and voluntarily resides or carries on 
business or personally works for gain or, in the case of a displaced 
bank making an application under this section, within whose limits the 
bank carries on business, for the determination of the amount due in 
respect of the claim in accordance with the provisions of sub- section 
 (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1752128</tid>
<number>5</number>To every proceeding under sub- section (4) the insurance 
company and all persons interested in the claim shall be made parties:
Provided that the Tribunal may at any stage of the proceeding 
direct that the name of any person whose presence before the Tribunal 
may be necessary in order to enable the Tribunal effectually and 
completely to adjudicate upon and settle all the questions involved, 
be added to the proceeding.


</section>

<section><tid>214467</tid>
<number>6</number>No application under this section shall be entertained in any 
case where no claim has been made to the insurance company within one 
year after the date of the loss.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- A claim shall be deemed to have been made within the 
meaning of this sub- section if intimation thereof has been given to 
the insurance company within one year after the date of the loss 
notwithstanding that the intimation does not specify the amount of the 
claim or is not in the form, if any, required by the contract of 
insurance or in any other specified form.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1093165</tid>
<number> 19</number> Calls on shares in companies.
<section><tid>1672704</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a company or a co-  
operative society has made any call upon a displaced person or a 
displaced bank in respect of any moneys remaining unpaid on any share 
held by him or it on the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, in the company or 
co- operative society, as the case may be, and there has been a failure 
on the part of the shareholder to pay any moneys due in respect of 
such call, then, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in 
the Companies Act, or in the memorandum or articles of association or 
the Co- operative Societies Act, no interest shall be payable in 
respect of any such moneys due and the company or the co- operative 
society, as the case may be, shall not be entitled to forfeit the 
share or any part thereof, and any forfeiture made before the 
commencement of this Act in respect of any share in the circumstances 
specified in the sub- section shall be deemed to have had no effect, 
and no person shall be deemed to have ceased to be a member of the 
company or co- operative society merely by reason of such forfeiture.

</section>

<section><tid>5924</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, or 
in the memorandum or articles of association, or the Co- operative 
Societies Act, it shall be lawful for a displaced person or a 
displaced bank to apply to the company or the co- operative society, as 
the case may be, for the conversion of any partly paid- up share held 
by him or it in the company or society into such smaller number of 
fully paid- up shares as the society or company may have issued and in 
respect of which calls have already been made.

</section>

<section><tid>659596</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any share forfeited before the commencement of this Act 
has been disposed of by the company in accordance with its articles of 
association and it is not possible for the company to give to the 
displaced person the relief to which he is entitled under this section 
without increasing its capital, the capital of the company shall be 
deemed to have been increased to the extent to which it is necessary 
to provide that relief.

</section>

<section><tid>519455</tid>
<number>4</number>If the company or the co- operative society refuses to comply 
with any such request as is contained in an application under sub- 
section (2), the Tribunal may, on application made to it in this 
behalf

<pagefootnote><pagenum>74</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and if satisfied that there is no cause for such refusal, issue a 
direction to the company or the co- operative society accordingly, and 
the company or society shall be bound to comply therewith and every 
such direction shall take effect from the date thereof.


</section>

<section><tid>1912570</tid>
<number>5</number>Save as otherwise provided in this section, nothing contained 
herein shall affect the validity of any action taken by the company or 
its board of directors in pursuance of the provisions of the Companies 
Act or of the memorandum or articles of association relating to the 
company.

</section>

<section><tid>1449875</tid>
<number>6</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect for a period 
of ten years from the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, and thereafter shall 
cease to have effect except as respects things done or omitted to be 
done.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1189157</tid>
<number> 20</number> No calls to be made on displaced person or bank when company 
or co- operative society is in liquidation.
<section><tid>1809185</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a company or a  
co- operative society is being wound up, no displaced person or 
displaced bank shall be called upon, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or 
articles of association or the Co- operative Societies Act, to make any 
contribution to the assets of the company or co- operative society, as 
the case may be, in respect of any share held by him or it in the 
company or society on the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>359348</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect for a period 
of ten years from the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, and shall also apply 
in respect of any calls made and not satisfied before that date, and 
shall cease to have effect after the expiry of the said period except 
as respects things done or omitted to be done.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>469393</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power to revise certain decree and settlement.
<section><tid>558994</tid>
<number>1</number>Where,  
before the commencement of this Act, a decree has been passed by a 
Civil court against, or a settlement has been entered into by, a 
displaced debtor in respect of any debt, the Tribunal shall, on the 
application of such debtor revise it so as to bring it into accord 
with the provisions of the Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1340967</tid>
<number>2</number>In determining the amount due under any such decree or 
settlement, the Tribunal shall accept as binding the findings of the 
Court which passed the decree or the facts contained in the 
settlement, as the case may be, to the extent to which the findings 
or the facts are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act:
Provided that the Tribunal shall not determine any claim under 
any such decree until any appeal or revision filed against it has been 
finally decided or the period allowed for any appeal therefrom has


<pagefootnote><pagenum>75</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

expired, and in all such cases the finding of the Tribunal shall be 
based on the final decree.


</section>

<section><tid>22099</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no 
Tribunal shall in respect of any debt revise any settlement arrived at 
before the commencement of this Act between an insurance company and a 
displaced person or between an insurance company and a displaced bank 
having an interest in the claim of a displaced person against the 
insurance company and arriving at such settlement by virtue of that 
interest:
Provided that payment in full has been made in pursuance of such 
settlement.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1441600</tid>
<number> 22</number> Apportionment of joint debts. Where a debt is due from a 
displaced person jointly with another person, the Tribunal shall, for 
the purposes of this Act, apportion the liability between them 
according to the following rules, namely:--
<section><tid>237696</tid>
<number>a</number>if the liability of each debtor is defined, then 
according to the defined share of each;

</section>

<section><tid>1192304</tid>
<number>b</number>if the debt was taken for any trade or business of the 
joint debtors, then according to the shares held by 
each of the joint debtors in the trade or business;

</section>

<section><tid>1168675</tid>
<number>c</number>if the debt was not taken in any defined shares or for 
any trade or business in which the partners have any 
defined share, the debt shall be apportioned into as 
many parts as there are joint debtors, and each joint 
debtor shall be liable only for the part apportioned to 
him;

</section>

<section><tid>563974</tid>
<number>d</number>if one joint debtor is a displaced person and another 
is not, the sum apportioned to the non- displaced person 
shall not be deemed to be a debt within the meaning of 
this Act and the creditor may in respect of such debt 
seek any remedy open to him in a Civil court or 
otherwise;

</section>

<section><tid>1678284</tid>
<number>e</number>if the debt was taken by a joint Hindu family, the 
members of the joint Hindu family shall be deemed to be 
joint debtors within the meaning of this section and 
the debt shall be apportioned amongst the members 
thereof in the same proportion in which shares would be 
allotted to them on partition:
Provided that the share of any member of such a 
joint family any of whose male lineal ascendants in the 
male line of ascent is alive and joint with such


<pagefootnote><pagenum>76</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

member shall be deemed to be included in the share of 
his oldest surviving ascendant in the male line of 
ascent, and such member shall not be separately 
regarded as a joint debtor for the purpose of this 
clause;


</section>

<section><tid>498022</tid>
<number>f</number>if the liability is secured by a mortgage of movable 
and immovable properties, the debt shall be apportioned 
between the two properties in the same proportion as 
the value of each property bears to the total value of 
the properties;
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the 
value of the movable property shall be deemed to be the 
value thereof immediately before the date on which the 
debtor became a displaced person, and the value of the 
immovable property shall be deemed to be the value of 
the verified claim in respect thereof;


</section>

<section><tid>1332020</tid>
<number>g</number>Where the relationship between the joint debtors is 
that of principal and surety, nothing contained in this 
Act shall prevent the institution of a suit for the 
recovery of the debt against the surety but no decree 
shall be passed in such suit for an amount in excess of 
the amount decreed or which can be decreed against the 
principal debtor in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act:
Provided that the total amount which may be 
recovered from the principal debtor and the surety 
shall not exceed the amount decreed or which can be 
decreed by the Tribunal against the principal debtor in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>330869</tid>
<number> 23</number> Simplified procedure in certain cases. In the determination 
of any individual debt which does not exceed five thousand rupees,--
<section><tid>1049398</tid>
<number>a</number>it shall not be necessary for the Tribunal to take down 
the evidence of the witnesses in writing at length but 
the Tribunal, as the examination of each witness 
proceeds, shall make a memorandum of the substance of 
what he deposes and such memorandum shall be written 
and signed by the Tribunal and shall form part of the 
record;

</section>

<section><tid>1234641</tid>
<number>b</number>the decision of the Tribunal need not contain more than 
the points for determination and the decision thereon.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>77</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>398723</tid>
<number>24</number>Presumption respecting registered documents. It shall be 
presumed until the contrary is proved that any document registered 
under the Indian Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>) or any certified 
copy thereof and produced before the Tribunal has been proved.


</article>



<article><tid>860663</tid>
<number>25</number>Application of Act 5 of <year>1908</year>. Save as otherwise expressly 
provided in this Act or in any rules made thereunder, all proceedings 
under this Act shall be regulated by the provisions contained in the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>578415</tid>
<number>26</number>Signing and verification of applications and written 
statements. Every application and the schedules, if any, attached 
thereto and every written statement filed before the Tribunal for any 
relief under this Act shall be signed and verified in the manner 
prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), for the 
signing and verification of pleadings.


</article>



<article><tid>180378</tid>
<number>27</number>Contents of decrees. In all cases in which the Tribunal 
passes a decree on the application of a displaced person, it shall 
prepare a complete schedule of the creditors and of the assets and 
liabilities of the displaced person.


</article>



<article><tid>11937</tid>
<number>28</number>Execution of decrees. It shall be competent for the Civil 
Court which has been specified as the Tribunal for the purposes of 
this Act to execute any decree or order passed by it as the Tribunal 
in the same manner as it could have done if it were a decree or order 
passed by it as a Civil Court.
CHAP

RELIEFS CHAPTER III 
RELIEFS



</article>



<article><tid>1352579</tid>
<number> 29</number> Cesser of accrual of interest.
<section><tid>6647</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the 15th day  
of August, <year>1947</year>, no interest shall accrue or be deemed to have accrued 
in respect of any debt owed by a displaced person, and no Tribunal 
shall allow any future interest in respect of any decree or order 
passed by it:
Provided that--


<subsection><tid>1556322</tid>
<number>a</number>where the debt is secured by the pledge of shares, 
stocks, Government securities of a local authority, the 
Tribunal shall allow, for the period commencing from 
the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, and ending with the date 
of commencement of this Act, interest to the creditor 
at the rate mutually agreed upon or at a rate at which 
any dividend or interest has been paid or is payable in 
respect thereof, whichever is less;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1897364</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case the Tribunal may, if it thinks it 
just and proper to do so after taking into account the 
paying capacity of the debtor as defined in section 32, 
allow, for the period mentioned in clause (a), interest 
at a rate not exceeding four per cent. per annum 
simple.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1726261</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section shall apply to the interest payable 
in respect of any moneys advanced by a creditor, including an 
insurance company, on the security of a policy of life insurance of a 
displaced debtor in order to keep it alive.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>250762</tid>
<number>30</number>Exemption from arrest. No displaced person shall be liable to 
arrest or imprisonment in execution of any decree for the recovery of 
any debt whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1411382</tid>
<number> 31</number> Further reliefs in the matter of attachment of property. 
Section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>) shall, in 
relation to the execution of any decree for a debt against a displaced 
person (whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act), 
have effect, as if--
<section><tid>624384</tid>
<number>1</number>for clause (c) of the proviso to sub- section (1), the 
following clauses had been substituted, namely:--
" (c) houses and other buildings (with the  
materials and the sites thereof and the land 
immediately appertaining thereto and necessary for 
  their enjoyment) belonging to an agriculturist and not 
proved by the decree- holder to have been let out on 
rent or otherwise to any person other than the father, 
mother, wife, son, daughter, daughter- in- law, brother, 
sister or other dependant of the judgment- debtor or to 
have been left vacant for a period of one year or more;


<subsection><tid>118502</tid>
<number>cc</number>milch animals, whether in milk or in calf, 
kids, animals used for the purpose of transport or 
draught cart and open spaces or enclosures belonging to 
an agriculturist and required for use in case of need 
for tying cattle, parking carts or stacking fodder or 
manure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>653584</tid>
<number>ccc</number>one main residential house and other 
buildings attached to it (with the materials and the  
sites thereof and the land immediately appertaining 
  thereto and necessary for their enjoyment) belonging to 
a judgment- debtor other than an agriculturist and 
occupied by him";

<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>88073</tid>
<number>2</number>in clause (i), for the words" hundred rupees" the words 
" two hundred and fifty rupees" had been substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1210408</tid>
<number>3</number>after clause (p), the following had been inserted, 
namely:--
" (q) two- thirds of the agricultural produce of the 
judgment- debtor;


<subsection><tid>1537044</tid>
<number>r</number>so much of any other property of the judgment- 
debtor as constitutes the means of his livelihood and 
as is likely, in the opinion of the Court, to yield to 
him an income of not less than two hundred and fifty 
rupees a month;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>952956</tid>
<number>s</number>any loan advanced or agreed to be advanced by 
or on behalf of or out of the funds of the Central 
Government or a State Government, or any asset created 
from any such loan;"
Explanation.- Where any such asset as is referred to in clause (s) 
has been created partly from such loan and partly from the private 
funds of the judgment- debtor, that portion of the asset which has been 
created from the private funds shall, if severable from the remaining 
portion, be liable to attachment or sale.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>152165</tid>
<number> 32</number> Scaling down of debts.
<section><tid>597488</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, on the application of a  
displaced debtor under section 5 or sub- section (2) of section 11, the 
Tribunal has determined the amount due in respect of each debt in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act, it shall proceed to 
determine the paying capacity of the debtor.

</section>

<section><tid>1892629</tid>
<number>2</number>If the paying capacity of the debtor is equal to or exceeds 
the aggregate sum of all the debts so determined (exclusive of any  
debt in respect of which the creditor has elected to retain the 
  security in accordance with the provisions of section 16), the 
Tribunal shall pass a decree for the aggregate sum so determined, 
specifying the amount due to each creditor and shall allow repayment 
thereof in instalments, in accordance with the provisions contained in 
section 33, unless for reasons to be recorded it directs otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>885148</tid>
<number>3</number>If the paying capacity of the debtor is less than the 
aggregate sum referred to in sub- section (2), the Tribunal shall 
divide the decree into two parts and provide in the first part thereof 
 (hereinafter referred to as the first part of the decree) that the sum 
equivalent to the paying capacity shall, subject to the provisions 
contained in section 33, be realised from the assets of the debtor in 
India, and provide in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

second part thereof (hereinafter referred to as the second part of the  
  decree) that the balance shall be realised, subject to the provisions 
contained in sub- section (6), from any compensation which the debtor 
may receive:

Provided that if no such compensation is received, the balance 
shall be irrecoverable.


</section>

<section><tid>256430</tid>
<number>4</number>A creditor who has elected to retain his security under 
section 16 shall have no right to realise any money due to him from 
the assets of the debtor in India, but nothing in this sub- section 
shall affect any of the rights given to him by section 16.

</section>

<section><tid>350478</tid>
<number>5</number>A creditor shall have the right at any time at least six 
months before the receipt by the debtor of compensation to apply that 
the whole or the balance of the first part of the decree, in so far as 
any debt due to him is concerned, may be added to the second part of 
the decree, and thereupon he shall have no right to realise any money 
from the assets of the debtor in India.

</section>

<section><tid>571080</tid>
<number>6</number>For the purposes of this Act, the amount payable from the 
compensation for the satisfaction of the second part of the decree 
shall be that amount as bears to the aggregate amount of all the debts 
in the second part of the decree[ including therein any sum added to 
it under sub- section (5) and the sum determined in favour of the 
secured creditor in the manner specified in the proviso to clause (a) 
of sub- section (3) of section 16] as the compensation in respect of 
the property of the debtor payable to him under the Displaced Persons 
 (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>) bears to the verified claim; and the 
balance of the compensation, if any, shall be refunded to the 
displaced debtor.

</section>

<section><tid>1319322</tid>
<number>7</number>Every instalment paid by the displaced debtor in respect of 
the first part of the decree and any sum payable from the compensation 
in accordance with sub- section (6) shall be distributed rateably 
amongst the decree- holders, if more persons than one are entitled 
thereto:
Provided that the secured creditor who has not elected to be 
treated as an unsecured creditor under section 16 shall be entitled to 
a prior charge on the amount payable from the compensation.


</section>

<section><tid>1539237</tid>
<number>8</number>Where a displaced person receives compensation by way of 
exchange of property, then, subject to the prior charge, if any, of a 
creditor under section 16, the aggregate sum payable in respect of the 
second part of the decree shall be a second charge upon the property 
received by way of exchange, but the amount of the second charge shall 
be that amount as bears to the total sum the same proportion as the 
value of the property received by way of exchange bears to the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

value of the original property verified and valued under the Displaced 
Persons (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>1690999</tid>
<number>9</number>Where a displaced person makes a default in the payment of 
any instalment fixed in respect of the first part of the decree or 
does not pay the amount determined in accordance with sub- section (4) 
of section 16 or sub- section (8) of this section for which the first 
or the second charge may have been created upon the property received 
by way of exchange, the creditor may apply for the execution of the 
decree by the attachment and sale of the attachable assets of the 
judgment- debtor or by the sale of the property obtained by way of 
exchange upon which the charge has been created, as the case may be, 
and the amount realised by such execution shall be distributed 
rateably among the decree- holders:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall affect 
the rights of any charge- holders.


</section>

<section><tid>880821</tid>
<number>10</number>For the purposes of this Act, where the compensation is paid 
in cash, the amount which shall be available for purposes of 
satisfaction of the debts in the second part of the decree shall in no 
case exceed seventy- five per cent. of the amount of such compensation; 
and where it is by way of exchange or property, the extent of the 
property which shall be available for the said purposes shall in no 
case exceed seventy- five per cent. in value of such property.
Explanation.- In this section the expression" paying capacity" 
means the aggregate of the market value of all the attachable assets 
in India of the displaced debtor plus the income which is likely to 
accrue to him for the next three years succeeding, excluding from the 
computation of such income a sum calculated at the rate of two hundred 
and fifty rupees a month.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>622856</tid>
<number> 33</number> Matters to be taken into account in directing payment by 
instalments.
<section><tid>1673088</tid>
<number>1</number>In directing payment of any sums by instalments  
under the first part of the decree, the Tribunal shall take into 
account among other matters-

<subsection><tid>1226057</tid>
<number>a</number>the present income of the displaced debtor from all 
sources and the income that is likely to accrue to him 
in future;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1546961</tid>
<number>b</number>the size of the family dependant upon him for the 
ordinary necessaries of life and the expenditure likely 
to be incurred for the education and marriage of the 
children of the displaced person dependant upon him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>467686</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a displaced creditor is a minor, or a widow or a person 
who, by reason of any physical disability, is permanently disabled 
from

<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

earning his livelihood, the Tribunal may direct that any instalment 
payable to him or her shall be twenty- five per cent. higher than what 
would otherwise have been directed to be paid, and where it does so, 
it shall also direct that the instalments of other decree- holders 
shall be proportionately reduced.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389077</tid>
<number>34</number>Variation of maintenance allowances. Where a displaced debtor 
has been ordered to pay an allowance periodically to any person for 
his maintenance under any decree or order of a Court, or is liable to 
pay such allowance under any agreement voluntarily entered into, the 
rate at which such allowance is payable may be varied by the Tribunal 
on application made to it in his behalf, if in view of the change in 
the circumstances of the displaced debtor, the Tribunal thinks that 
such variation is necessary, and such variation shall have effect for 
such period as the Tribunal may direct, notwithstanding anything in 
any decree, order or agreement to the contrary.


</article>



<article><tid>1794129</tid>
<number>35</number>Taxation of lawyer' s fees. In directing payment of costs by 
any person as costs in respect of fees to any legal practitioner 
employed in any proceeding before it, the Tribunal shall be guided by 
any rules for the time being in force regulating the payment of such 
costs in proceedings of a similar nature before the ordinary Civil 
Courts, and shall not award more than one- half of what in its opinion 
the costs before the Civil court would have been.


</article>



<article><tid>1744958</tid>
<number> 36</number> Extension of period of limitation. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>) or in any 
special or local law or in any agreement,--
<section><tid>91253</tid>
<number>a</number>any suit or other legal proceeding in respect whereof 
the period of limitation was extended by section 8 of 
the Displaced Persons (Institution of Suits) Act, <year>1948</year> 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (47 of <year>1948</year>), and

</section>

<section><tid>952854</tid>
<number>b</number>any suit or other legal proceeding for the enforcement 
of a claim against an insurance company not falling 
within the provisions of clause (a) in respect whereof 
the cause of action had arisen, whether wholly or in 
part, in the territories now situate in West Pakistan 
and the institution of the suit or other legal 
proceeding has become barred by reason of a condition 
in the contract, which, but for the condition, would 
have been governed by the provisions obtained in clause 
 (a),
<pagefootnote><pagenum>83</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Since lapsed.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


may be instituted at any time within one year from the commencement of 
this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1347946</tid>
<number> 37</number> Curtailment of period of limitation for execution of certain 
decrees. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 48 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), or in any other law for the time 
being in force, no order for the execution of a decree in respect of a 
debt against a displaced person shall be made upon an application 
presented after the expiration of--
<section><tid>914362</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of decrees passed before the commencement 
of this Act, six years from such commencement;

</section>

<section><tid>1903731</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of decrees passed after the commencement of 
this Act, six years from the date of the decrees;

</section>

<section><tid>156455</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of decrees directing payment of money to be 
made at prescribed intervals or on certain dates, six 
years from the date of default in making the payment in 
respect of which the decree- holder seeks to have the 
decree executed:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be construed as 
extending the limit of time for execution as provided in section 48 of 
the said Code for an application for the execution of a decree passed 
before the commencement of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1312723</tid>
<number> 38</number> Sale of immovable property in execution.
<section><tid>1742502</tid>
<number>1</number>Where in the  
execution of any decree for the recovery of a debt against a displaced 
person his immovable property is sought to be sold, the Court 
executing the decree shall, in the first instance, determine the 
market value of the property and, if the value so determined is less 
than or equal to the amount of the decree together with the 
proportionate amount of any prior encumbrance, the Court shall 
transfer the property to the decree- holder.

</section>

<section><tid>1392876</tid>
<number>2</number>If the value determined under sub- section (1) is greater than 
the amount of the decree together with the proportionate amount of any 
prior encumbrance, the Court shall determine the portion of such 
property the value of which is equal to the amount of the decree with 
proportionate amount of such prior encumbrance, and may, if it is 
reasonable or convenient to do so, transfer that portion to the 
decree- holder.

</section>

<section><tid>440417</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any property is transferred under the provisions 
of this section to the decree- holder, the decree shall be deemed to be 
satisfied to the extent of the value of the property so transferred:
Provided that if the decree- holder does not desire to take the 
property or, in the opinion of the Court, it is not reasonable or 
convenient


<pagefootnote><pagenum>84</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to transfer the property to him, the property may be sold by public 
auction, but irrespective of the price fetched at the public auction 
the market value of the property as determined under this section (and  
not the amount payable to the decree- holder out of the sale proceeds 
  of the public auction) shall be deemed to be the amount which has been 
paid to the decree- holder in respect of the decree, and satisfaction 
thereof shall be entered accordingly.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>14022</tid>
<number>39</number>Encouragement of settlements. If the displaced debtor and the 
creditor or, where there are more creditors than one, such number 
thereof as hold more than two- thirds in value of the debts due from 
the displaced debtor enter into an agreement for the adjustment of the 
liabilities, the Tribunal shall, if an application is made to it in 
this behalf, after giving due notice to the other creditors affected, 
adjust the remaining debts accordingly if the terms of the agreement 
are just and fair, and pass a decree accordingly.
CHAP

APPEALS

CHAPTER IV

APPEALS



</article>



<article><tid>396443</tid>
<number> 40</number> General provisions relating to appeals. Save as otherwise 
provided in section 41, an appeal shall lie from--
<section><tid>1323694</tid>
<number>a</number>any final decree or order of the Tribunal, or

</section>

<section><tid>1152094</tid>
<number>b</number>any order made in the course of execution of any decree 
or order of the Tribunal, which if passed in the course 
of execution of a decree or order of a Civil Court 
would be appealable under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
 <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).
to the High Court within the limits of whose jurisdiction the Tribunal 
is situate.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>96591</tid>
<number>41</number>Restrictions on right of appeal in certain cases. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 40, where the subject- 
matter of the appeal relates to the amount of a debt and such amount 
on appeal is less than rupees five thousand, no appeal shall lie.


</article>



<article><tid>631922</tid>
<number>42</number>Parties to appeals. For the purpose of any appeal under this 
Act, it shall be sufficient if only such persons as, in the opinion of 
the appellant, are necessary parties to the appeal for the purpose of 
determining the real questions in controversy between them, are 
impleaded as respondents to the appeal:
Provided that where it appears to the High Court at the hearing 
that any person who was a party to the proceeding before the Tribunal


<pagefootnote><pagenum>85</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

from whose decree the appeal is preferred but who has not been made a 
party to the appeal is interested in the result of the appeal, the 
Court may adjourn the hearing to a future date to be fixed by the 
Court and direct that such person be made a respondent.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1699279</tid>
<number> 43</number> Registration of certain societies and companies under Indian 
law.
<section><tid>1837129</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the registered office of any society or company  
registered before the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>), or the Co- operative Societies 
Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>), or under any other law then in force in any 
Province for the registration of co- operative societies or the Indian 
Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of <year>1913</year>), is situated in the territory now 
forming part of West Pakistan but a majority of its members for the 
time being are resident in India, or, in the case of a company, more 
than thirty- three and one- third per cent. of its shares in value are 
being held by persons resident in India, the society, or company, as 
the case may be, may apply within one year from the commencement of 
this Act to the Registrar of Societies, Co- operative Societies or 
Companies, as the case may be, within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction the majority of the members of the governing body reside 
or carry on business, for the recognition of the society or company as 
such in India.

</section>

<section><tid>370527</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar, after making such inquiry into the matter as 
he deems fit, may either accord such recognition or refuse to do so.

</section>

<section><tid>471095</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal shall lie from the order of the Registrar under 
sub- section (2) to the State Government and no order passed by the 
Registrar or by the State Government on appeal shall be called in 
question in any Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1170105</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the Registrar accords recognition to a society, co- 
operative society or company, he shall cause necessary entries thereof 
to be made in his register and thereupon, notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force or in 
any instrument, the society or the company, as the case may be, shall 
be deemed to have been formed and registered under the relevant law as 
in force in India, and every such society or company shall, among 
other matters, have the right to demand and receive any moneys due to 
it from any person residing or carrying on business in India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>581801</tid>
<number>44</number>Bar of further applications in certain cases. Subject to the 
other provisions contained in this Act, where an application made by a 
displaced debtor under section 5 or under

<pagefootnote><pagenum>86</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sub- section (2) of section 11, or by a displaced creditor under 
section 13 has been dismissed, no further application for the same 
purpose shall lie.



</article>



<article><tid>1494863</tid>
<number>45</number>Amendment of applications. Clerical or arithmetical mistakes 
in any application or in any schedule annexed thereto arising from any 
accidental slip or omission may at any time be corrected by the 
Tribunal, either of its own motion or on the application of any of the 
parties.


</article>



<article><tid>61949</tid>
<number>46</number>Service of notices. Every notice issued under this Act shall 
be served by registered post, acknowledgment due, unless the Tribunal 
for reasons to be recorded, directs service in any of the other modes 
specified in Order V of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>660746</tid>
<number> 47</number> Effect of failure on the part of displaced debtor to disclose 
certain matters. Where a displaced debtor has not mentioned in the 
relevant schedule to his application any debt owing by him or any 
property, movable or immovable, belonging to him, whether such 
property is liable to attachment or not liable to attachment at all, 
nothing contained in this Act shall prevent--
<section><tid>251742</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the debt, the creditor from instituting 
any proceeding for the recovery thereof under any law 
for the time being in force other than this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>780329</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the property, from being attached or 
otherwise dealt with under any such law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>692022</tid>
<number>48</number>Proceedings not to abate on death of debtor. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, no proceeding before a Tribunal shall 
be deemed to abate by reason merely of the death of the debtor who is 
a party to the proceeding, and a decree may be passed notwithstanding 
the death and such decree shall have the same force and effect as if 
it had been passed before the death took place:
Provided that the Tribunal on an application made in that behalf, 
shall cause the legal representative of the deceased debtor to be made 
a party to the proceeding, and any person so made a party may make any 
defence appropriate to his character as legal representative of the 
deceased debtor:

Provided further that nothing contained herein shall be deemed to 
render the legal representative of the deceased debtor liable to 
satisfy the decree except to the extent to which any of the assets of 
the deceased debtor have devolved on him.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>87</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>383639</tid>
<number> 49</number> Past transactions not to be affected.
<section><tid>1219925</tid>
<number>1</number>If before the  
commencement of this Act a displaced debtor has satisfied or 
discharged any of his liabilities in any manner whatsoever, such 
transactions shall not be affected by anything contained in this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>114277</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Tribunal has determined the amount due in respect 
of any debt in accordance with the provisions of this Act, any 
payments (including payments by way of interest) made by the displaced 
debtor towards the debt prior to such determination shall be adjusted 
towards the amount so determined:
Provided that no creditor shall be called upon to refund any 
amount paid to him if it is found that it is in excess of the amount 
determined as being due to him under this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1971645</tid>
<number>50</number>Displaced debtor not to be deemed insolvent. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law for the time being in force relating to 
insolvency, no displace debtor shall be deemed to be insolvent or to 
have been adjudicated as such within the meaning of any law for the 
time being in force relating to insolvency by reason only of his 
applying to get his debts adjusted under this Act, and no petition in 
insolvency shall lie against a displaced debtor in respect of any debt 
incurred by him before the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>991551</tid>
<number>51</number>Compromises or arrangements between banks and their debtors 
not to be reopened in certain cases. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, no compromise or arrangement arrived at, 
whether before or after the commencement of this Act, between a 
displaced debtor and a bank relating to the repayment, discharge or 
satisfaction of any debt owing by the displaced debtor to the bank 
shall be reopened by the Tribunal, and nothing contained in this Act 
shall affect any such compromise or arrangement:
Provided that there is in force in respect of the bank a 
compromise or arrangement between it and its own creditors or any 
class of such creditors which has been duly sanctioned by the Court 
under section 153 of the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of <year>1913</year>): and

Provided further that the particulars specified in clauses (c), 
 (cc), (ccc), (i), (q), (r), and (s) of the proviso to sub- section (1) 
of section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), as 
amended by section 31 of this Act, shall not be liable to attachment 
or sale in any proceeding against the displaced debtor.



</article>



<article><tid>1896838</tid>
<number> 52</number> Communication of contents of decrees to prescribed authority.

<section><tid>178287</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Tribunal shall communicate to the prescribed authority, in  
such manner as may be prescribed, the amount of the prior

<pagefootnote><pagenum>88</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

charge declared under sub- section (3) of section 16, and shall also 
forward to it a copy of the decree passed on the application of a 
displaced debtor under section 5 or sub- section (2) of section 11 and 
also of any order passed under sub- section (5) of section 32, 
specifying the amount due to the creditor mentioned therein on the 
date of the order.


</section>

<section><tid>1748870</tid>
<number>2</number>The prescribed authority shall scale down the debts reported 
to him in accordance with sub- section (6) of section 32 and shall, 
subject to any rules made in this behalf, meet the prior charge of the 
secured creditor in accordance with sub- section (2) of section 16 in 
the first instance and thereafter distribute the balance of the 
compensation available for distribution within the meaning of sub- 
section (10) of section 32 rateably amongst the other decree- holders 
whose decrees have been reported to him:
Provided that in making any such rateable distribution the 
prescribed authority shall have due regard to the provisions contained 
in sub- section (2) of section 33.


</section>

<section><tid>852554</tid>
<number>3</number>The balance from the amount of the compensation payable shall 
be refunded to the displaced debtor.

</section>

<section><tid>1050625</tid>
<number>4</number>Any amount paid by the prescribed authority to any decree- 
holder under the provisions of this section shall, to that extent, be 
a valid discharge of the debt due by the displaced debtor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1108575</tid>
<number>53</number>Application of the Limitation Act. Subject to the other 
provisions contained in this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9  
  of <year>1908</year>) shall apply to the institution of any proceeding under this 
Act, and, for the purpose of determining and computing the period of 
limitation prescribed by that Act in relation thereto, every 
application made under this Act shall be deemed to be a suit for the 
purpose of that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1951419</tid>
<number>54</number>Order XXX VIII of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil 
Procedure not to apply. Nothing contained in Order XXXVIII of the 
First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), 
relating to arrest and attachment before judgment, shall apply to any 
proceeding under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1903197</tid>
<number>55</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government 
or any person, in respect of anything done or intended to be done by 
it or him in good faith in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or 
order made thereunder.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>89</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1659976</tid>
<number>56</number>Delegation of Powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power 
exercisable by it under this Act may also be exercised by such officer 
or authority subordinate to the Central Government or by the State 
Government or by any officer or authority subordinate to the State 
Government as may be specified in the direction.


</article>



<article><tid>1769496</tid>
<number> 57</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>309493</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1922853</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
provisions contained in sub- section (1), the rules so made may provide 
for all or any of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1759874</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional particulars, if any, which an 
application under section 5, should contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1208752</tid>
<number>b</number>the form in which notices under this Act may be issued;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>928058</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which applications under section 10 or 
section 13 may be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>324664</tid>
<number>d</number>the registers which should be maintained under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>833070</tid>
<number>e</number>the authorities required to be prescribed under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1030107</tid>
<number>f</number>the board or other authority to which any report under 
sub- section (2) of section 18 may be made and the 
matters which such board or other authority should take 
into account in making its report.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>504373</tid>
<number> 58</number> Power of State Government to make rules. The State Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules providing 
for--
<section><tid>1665200</tid>
<number>a</number>the distribution of business amongst the various 
Tribunals within the State;

</section>

<section><tid>186163</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which copies of documents produced before 
the Tribunals should be certified;

</section>

<section><tid>592411</tid>
<number>c</number>the returns to be made by the Tribunals and the 
authorities to which they may be so made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645574</tid>
<number> 58A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Laying of rules.
<section><tid>343608</tid>
<number>1</number>Every rule made by the State  
Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before the State Legislature.

</section>

<section><tid>506210</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1305780</tid>
<number>59</number>Repeals. Save as otherwise provided in section 36, the 
Displaced Persons (Institution of Suits) Act, <year>1948</year> (47 of <year>1948</year>) and 
the Displaced Persons (Legal Proceedings) Act, <year>1949</year> (25 of <year>1949</year>) shall 
cease to apply to displaced persons as defined in this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>90</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Rules, <year>1951</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1952</year>, Pt. II, See. 3, p. 80. For the Insurance 
Claims Board Rules, <year>1952</year>, see ibid., Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1764. 
2. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, S. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>