<act><title>The 
      Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 
1959</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title.—This Act may be called the Parliament 
      (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
      requires,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
“compensatory allowance” means any sum of money payable to the 
      holder of an office by way of daily allowance [such allowance not 
      exceeding the amount of daily allowance to which a member of Parliament is 
      entitled under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[the 
      Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954 (30 of 
      1954)], any conveyance allowance, house rent allowance or travelling 
      allowance for the purpose of enabling him to recoup any expenditure 
      incurred by him in performing the functions, of that office;  
      
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“statutory body” means any corporation, committee, commission, 
      council, board or other body of persons, whether incorporated or not, 
      established by or under any law for the time being in force;  

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“non-statutory body” means any body of persons other than a 
      statutory body.  
      
    



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Certain offices of profit 
      not to disqualify.—It is hereby declared that 
      none of the following offices, in so far as it is an office of profit 
      under the Government of India or the Government of any State, shall 
      disqualify the holder thereof for being chosen as, or for being, a member 
      of Parliament, namely:—
 <section>        
      <number>a</number>  any office held by a Minister, Minister of State or Deputy 
      Minister for the Union or for any State, whether ex officio or by 
      name;
 
1[(aa)  the office of a 
      Leader of the Opposition in Parliament;]
 
2[(ab)  the office of 
      Deputy Chairman, Planning Commission;]
 
3[(ac)  the office of 
      each leader of a recognised party and a recognised group in either House 
      of Parliament;]
 
4[(ad)  the office of 
      the Chairperson of the National Advisory Council constituted by the 
      Government of India in the Cabinet Secretariat vide Order No. 
      631/2/1/2004-Cab., dated the 31st May, 2004;]
 </section><section>        
      <number>b</number>  the office of Chief Whip, Deputy Chief Whip or Whip in 
      Parliament or of a Parliamentary Secretary;
 
2[(ba)  the office of 
      chairperson of—
 <subsection>              
      <number>i</number>  the National Commission for Minorities constituted under section 
      3 of the National Commission for Minorities Act, 1992 (19 of 
      1992);
 </subsection><subsection>             
      <number>ii</number>  the National Commission for the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled 
      Tribes constituted under clause (1) of article 338 of the 
      Constitution;
 </subsection><subsection>             
      <number>iii</number>  the National Commission for Women constituted under section 3 
      of the National Commission for Women Act, 1990 (20 of 1990);]
 </subsection></section><section>        
      <number>c</number>  the office of member of any force raised or maintained under the 
      National Cadet Corps Act, 1948 (31 of 1948), the Territorial Army Act, 
      1948 (56 of 1948), or the Reserve and Auxiliary Air Forces Act, 1952 (62 
      of 1952);
 </section><section>        
      <number>d</number>  the office of a member of a Home Guard constituted under any law 
      for the time being in force in any State;
 </section><section>        
      <number>e</number>  the office of sheriff in the city of Bombay, Calcutta or 
      Madras;
 </section><section>         
      <number>f</number>  the office of chairman or member of the syndicate, senate, 
      executive committee, council or court of a university or any other body 
      connected with a university;
 </section><section>        
      <number>g</number>  the office of a member of any delegation or mission sent outside 
      India by the Government for any special purpose;
 </section><section>        
      <number>h</number>  the office of chairman or member of a committee (whether 
      consisting of one or more members), set up temporarily for the purpose of 
      advising the Government or any other authority in respect of any matter of 
      public importance or for the purpose of making an inquiry into, or 
      collecting statistics in respect of, any such matter, if the holder of 
      such office is not entitled to any remuneration other than compensatory 
      allowance;
 
5[(i)  the office of 
      chairman, director or member of any statutory or non-statutory body other 
      than any such body as is referred to in clause (h), if the holder of such 
      office is not entitled to any remuneration other than compensatory 
      allowance, but excluding (i) the office of chairman of any statutory or 
      non-statutory body specified in Part I of the Schedule, and (ii) the 
      office of chairman or secretary of any statutory or non-statutory body 
      specified in Part II of the Schedule;]
 </section><section>         
      <number>j</number>  the office of village revenue officer, whether called a 
      lambardar, malguzar, patel, deshmukh or by any other name, whose 
      duty is to collect land revenue and who is remunerated by a share of, or 
      commission on, the amount of land revenue collected by him, but who does 
      not discharge any police functions;
          
      6[(k) the 
      office of Chairman, Deputy Chairman, Secretary or Member (by whatever name 
      called) in any statutory or non-statutory body specified in the 
      Table;
 </section><section>         
      <number>l</number> the office of Chairperson or trustee (by whatever name called) of any 
      Trust, whether public or private, not being a body specified in the 
      Schedule;
 </section><section>       
      <number>m</number> the office of Chairman, President, Vice-President or Principal 
      Secretary or Secretary of the Governing Body of any society registered 
      under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), or under any 
      other law relating to registration of societies, not being a body 
      specified in the Schedule.]
 7[Explanation
1].—For the purposes of this section, the office of 8[chairman, deputy chairman 
      or secretary] shall include every office of that description by whatever 
      name called.
 9[Explanation 2.—In 
      clause (aa), the expression “Leader of the Opposition” shall have the 
      meaning assigned to it in the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of 
      Opposition in Parliament Act, 1977 (33 of 1977).]
 10[Explanation 3.—In 
      clause (ac), the expressions “recognised party” and “recognised group” 
      shall have the meanings assigned to them in the Leaders and Chief Whips of 
      Recognised Parties and Groups in Parliament (Facilities) Act, 
      1988.]
  















 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Temporary suspension of disqualification in certain 
      cases.—If a person being a member of Parliament who 
      immediately before the commencement of this Act held an office of profit 
      declared by any law repealed by this Act not to disqualify the holder 
      thereof for being such member, becomes so disqualified by reason of any of 
      the provisions contained in this Act, such office shall not, if held by 
      such person for any period not extending beyond a period of six months 
      from the commencement of this Act disqualify him for being a member of 
      Parliament. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Repeals.—The Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) 
      Act, 1950 (19 of 1950), the Parliament Prevention of Disqualification Act, 
      1951 (68 of 1951), the Prevention of Disqualification Act, 1953 (1 of 
      1954), and any provision in any other enactment which is inconsistent with 
      this Act are hereby repealed.
 
  </article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The 
      Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 
1959
 

 
 

The Schedule
 

[See section 
3(i)]
 

Part I  
 

Bodies 
      Under the Central Government
 

Air-India International 
      Corporation established under section 3 of the Air Corporations Act, 1953 
      (27 of 1953).
 

Air Transport Council constituted 
      under section 30 of the Air Corporations Act, 1953 (27 of 
1953).
 

Board of Directors of the Export 
      Risks Insurance Corporation 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the Heavy 
      Electricals 1[***] 
      Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the 
      Hindustan Cables 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the 
      Hindustan Insecticides 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the 
      Hindustan Machine Tools 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the 
      Hindustan Shipyard Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the 2[Hindustan Chemicals and Fertilizers 
      Limited].
 

Board of Directors of the National 
      Coal Development Corporation (Private) Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the National 
      3[Industrial] Development 
      Corporation 1[***] 
      Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the National 
      Instruments 1[***] 
      Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the National 
      Small Industries Corporation 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the Neyveli 
      Lignite Corporation (Private) Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the Sindri 
      Fertilizers and Chemicals 1[***] Limited.
 

Board of Directors of the State 
      Trading Corporation of India 1[***] Limited.
 

Central Warehousing Corporation 
      established under section 17 of the Agricultural Produce (Development and 
      Warehousing) Corporations Act, 1956 (28 of 1956).
 

Coal Board established under 
      section 4 of the Coal Mines (Conservation and Safety) Act, 1952 (12 of 
      1952).
 

Coal Mines Labour Housing Board 
      constituted under section 6 of the Coal Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 
      1947 (32 of 1947).
 

Commissioners for the Port of 
      Calcutta.
 

Committee for the allotment of 
      land in the township of Gandhidham.
 

Company Law Advisory Commission 
      constituted under section 410 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
      1956).
 

Cotton Textiles Fund Committee 
      constituted under the Textile Funds Ordinance, 1944 (Ord. 34 of 
      1944).
 

Dock Labour Board, Bombay, 
      established under the Bombay Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) 
      Scheme, 1956, made under the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 
      1948 (9 of 1948).
 

Dock Labour Board, Calcutta, 
      established under the Calcutta Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) 
      Scheme, 1956, made under the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 
      1948 (9 of 1948).
 

Dock Labour Board, Madras, 
      established under the Madras Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) 
      Scheme, 1956, made under the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 
      1948 (9 of 1948).
 

Forward Markets Commission 
      established under section 3 of the Forward Contracts (Regulation) Act, 
      1952 (74 of 1952).
 

Indian Airlines Corporation 
      established under section 3 of the Air Corporations Act, 1953 (27 of 
      1953).
 

Industrial Finance Corporation of 
      India established under section 3 of the Industrial Finance Corporation 
      Act, 1948 (15 of 1948).
 

Licensing Committee constituted 
      under rule 10 of the Registration and Licensing of Industrial Undertakings 
      Rules, 1952, made under the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 
      1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Mining Boards constituted under 
      section 12 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952).
 

National Co-operative Development 
      and Warehousing Board established under section 3 of the Agricultural 
      Produce (Development and Warehousing) Corporations Act, 1956 (28 of 
      1956).
 

Rehabilitation Finance 
      Administration constituted under section 3 of the Rehabilitation Finance 
      Administration Act, 1948 (12 of 1948).
 

Tariff Commission established 
      under section 3 of the Tariff Commission Act, 1951 (50 of 
1951).
 

Trustees of the Port of 
      Bombay.
 

Trustees of the Port of 
      Madras.
 

Trustees or Commissioners of any 
      major port as defined in the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908), other 
      than the Port of Calcutta, Bombay or Madras.
 

  

 

Bodies Under State 
      Governments
 

Andhra Pradesh
 

Agricultural Improvement Fund 
      Committee constituted under section 3 of the Hyderabad Agricultural 
      Improvement Act, 1952.
 

Co-operative Agricultural and 
      Marketing Development Fund Committee.
 

Livestock Purchasing 
      Committee.
 

 
 

Assam
 

Adhi Counciliation Boards 
      constituted under section 2A of the Assam Adhiars Protection and 
      Regulation Act, 1948.
 

Assam Evacuee Property Management 
      Committee constituted under section 12 of the Assam Evacuee Property Act, 
      1951.
 

Assam Text Book 
      Committee.
 

 
 

Bihar
 

Mining Board for Coal 
      Mines.
 

Text Book and Education Literature 
      Committee.
 

 
 

Bombay
 

Allocation Committee (Allopathic) 
      under the Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.
 

Allocation Committee (Ayurvedic) 
      under the Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.
 

Board to conduct over-all 
      supervision of the business and affairs of the Narsinggiriji Mills, 
      Sholapur.
 

Bombay Housing Board constituted 
      under section 3 of the Bombay Housing Board Act, 1948.
 

Bombay State Electricity Board 
      constituted under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 
      1948).
 

Bombay State Electricity 
      Consultative Council constituted under section 16 of the Electricity 
      (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948).
 

Medical Service Committee under 
      the Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.
 

Pharmaceutical Committee under the 
      Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.
 

Regional Transport Authority for 
      Ahmedabad, Aurangabad, Bombay, Nagpur, Poona, Rajkot and Thana constituted 
      under section 44 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939).
 

Saurashtra Housing Board 
      constituted under section 3 of the Saurashtra Housing Board Act, 
      1954.
 

State Transport Authority 
      constituted under section 44 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 
      1939).
 

Vidarbha Housing Board constituted 
      under section 3 of the Madhya Pradesh Housing Act, 1950.
 

 
 

Kerala
 

Board of Examiners appointed under 
      rule 8 of the Travancore-Cochin Boiler Attendants Rules, 1954.
 

Panel of Assessors constituted 
      under rule 63 of the Travancore-Cochin Boiler Attendants Rules, 
      1954.
 

Panel of Assessors constituted 
      under the Travancore-Cochin Economiser Rules, 1956.
 

 
 

Madhya Pradesh
 

Madhya Pradesh Housing Board 
      constituted under section 3 of the Madhya Pradesh Housing Board Act, 
      1950.
 

Mahakoshal Housing 
      Board.
 

 
 

5[Tamil 
      Nadu]
 

Committee to select Books for 
      Study for S.S.L.C. Examination.
 

Landing and Shipping Fees 
      Committees for Minor Ports.
 

Local Committee constituted under 
      regulation 10A of the Employees’ State Insurance (General) Regulations, 
      1950.
 

Madras Board of 
      Transport.
 

6[Tamil Nadu Electricity 
      Board] constituted under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 
      (54 of 1948).
 

Madras State Electricity 
      Consultative Council constituted under section 16 of the Electricity 
      (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948).
 

Port Conservancy 
Boards.
 

Port Trust Boards of Minor 
      Ports.
 

State Board of 
      Communications.
 

Text Books Committee.
 

 
 

7[Karnataka]
 

Board of Management, Mysore Iron 
      and Steel Works, Bhadravathi.
 

Board of Management of Industrial 
      Concerns.
 

 
 

Orissa
 

Appeal Committee under the Board 
      of Secondary Education.
 

Orissa Board of Communications and 
      Transport.
 

Regional Transport Authority 
      constituted under section 44 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 
      1939).
 

State Transport Authority 
      constituted under section 44 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 
      1939).
 

 
 

Punjab
 

Punjab State National Workers 
      (Relief and Rehabilitation) Board.
 

 
 

Rajasthan
 

City Improvement Trust, Kota, 
      constituted under the City of Kota Improvement Act, 1946.
 

Excise Appellate Board, 
      Ajmer.
 

Rajasthan State Electricity Board 
      constituted under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 
      1948).
 

Urban Improvement Board, 
      Jaipur.
 

 
 

Uttar Pradesh
 

Government Cement Factory 
      Board.
 

Local Committees for Agra, Kanpur, 
      Lucknow and Saharanpur appointed under section 25 of the Employees’ State 
      Insurance Act, 1948 (34 of 1948).
 

Sub-Committee to select books for 
      Educational Expansion Department.
 

Uttar Pradesh Sugar and Power 
      Alcohol and Labour Housing Board constituted under section 10 of the Uttar 
      Pradesh Sugar and Power Alcohol Industries Labour Welfare and Development 
      Fund Act, 1950.
 

West 
Bengal
 

Licensing Board constituted under 
      the regulations made under rule 45 of the Indian Electricity Rules, 
      1956.
 

West Bengal Housing Board 
      constituted under the West Bengal Development Corporation Act, 
      1954.
 

 
 

Bodies in Union Territories
 

Delhi Development Authority 
      constituted under section 3 of the Delhi Development Act, 1957 (61 of 
      1957).
 

Delhi Electricity Power Control 
      Board constituted under section 5 of the Bombay Electricity (Special 
      Powers) Act, 1946, as applied to Delhi.
 

Delhi State Electricity Council 
      constituted under section 16 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 
      1948).
 

   
 

Part II  
 

Bodies Under the Central Government
 

Advisory Committee for the 
      Air-India International Corporation appointed under section 41 of the Air 
      Corporations Act, 1953 (27 of 1953).
 

Advisory Committee for the Indian 
      Airlines Corporation appointed under section 41 of the Air Corporations 
      Act, 1953 (27 of 1953).
 

Central Silk Board constituted 
      under section 4 of the Central Silk Board Act, 1948 (61 of 
      1948).
 

Coffee Board constituted under 
      section 4 of the Coffee Act, 1942 (7 of 1942).
 

Coir Board constituted under 
      section 4 of the Coir Industry Act, 1953 (45 of 1953).
 

Development Council for Acids and 
      Fertilizers established under section 6 of the Industries (Development and 
      Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Alkalis 
      and Allied Industries established under section 6 of the Industries 
      (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Bicycles 
      established under section 6 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) 
      Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Drugs, 
      Dyes and Intermediates established under section 6 of the Industries 
      (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Food 
      Processing Industries established under section 6 of the Industries 
      (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Heavy 
      Electrical Engineering Industries established under section 6 of the 
      Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Internal 
      Combustion Engines and Power Driven Pumps established under section 6 of 
      the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 
(65 of 
      1951).
 

Development Council for Light 
      Electrical Engineering Industries established under section 6 of the 
      Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Machine 
      Tools established under section 6 of the Industries (Development and 
      Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for 
      Non-ferrous Metals including alloys established under section 6 of the 
      Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Oil-based 
      and Plastic Industries established under section 6 of the Industries 
      (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Sugar 
      Industry established under section 6 of the Industries (Development and 
      Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Development Council for Textiles 
      made of artificial silk including artificial silk yarn established under 
      section 6 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 
      1951).
 

Development Council for Textiles 
      made of wool including woollen yarn, hosiery, carpets and druggets 
      established under section 6 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) 
      Act, 1951 (65 of 1951).
 

Durgah Committee, Ajmer, 
      constituted under section 4 of the Durgah Khawaja Saheb Act, 1955 (36 of 
      1955).
 

Indian Central Arecanut 
      Committee.
 

Indian Central Coconut Committee 
      constituted under section 4 of the Indian Coconut Committee Act, 1944 (10 
      of 1944).
 

Indian Central Cotton Committee 
      constituted under section 4 of the Indian Cotton Cess Act, 1923 (14 of 
      1923).
 

Indian Central Jute 
      Committee.
 

Indian Central Oilseeds Committee 
      constituted under section 4 of the Indian Oilseeds Committee Act, 1946 (9 
      of 1946).
 

Indian Central Sugarcane 
      Committee.
 

Indian Central Tobacco 
      Committee.
 

Indian Lac Cess Committee 
      constituted under section 4 of the Indian Lac Cess Act, 1930 (24 of 
      1930).
 

Rubber Board constituted under 
      section 4 of the Rubber Act, 1947 (24 of 1947).
 

Tea Board constituted under 
      section 4 of the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of 1953).
 

  

 

  

 

Bodies Under State 
      Governments
 

Andhra Pradesh
 

Market Committee constituted under 
      section 4 of the Hyderabad Agricultural Market Act No. II of the 
      1339F.
 

Market Committee constituted under 
      section 4A of the Madras Commercial Crops Markets Act, 1933.
 

 
 

Bihar
 

Bihar State Board of Religious 
      Trusts.
 

Bihar Subai Majlis 
      Awqaf.
 

Bodh Gaya Temple Advisory 
      Committee constituted under section 15 of the Bodh Gaya Temple Act, 
      1949.
 

Bodh Gaya Temple Management 
      Committee constituted under section 3 of the Bodh Gaya Temple Act, 
      1949.
 

 
 

Kerala
 

Administration Committee for Coir 
      Purchase Scheme.
 

Malabar Market Committee 
      constituted under section 4A of the Madras Commercial Crops Markets Act, 
      1933.
 

Tapioca Market Expansion 
      Board.
 

 
 

8[Tamil Nadu]
 

Area Committee for Hindu Religious 
      and Charitable Endowments constituted under section 12 of the Madras Hindu 
      Religious and Charitable Endowments Act, 1951.
 

Madras State Waqf Board 
      constituted under section 9 of the Waqf Act, 1954 (29 of 1954).
 

 
 

Punjab
 

State Marketing Board constituted 
      under section 3 of the Patiala Agricultural Produce Markets Act, 
      2004*.
 

   
 

  

 

9[***]
 

10[TABLE
 

[See section 3(k)] 
 

 
 
 
 
 


S.No.
 
 

 Name of 
            body
 
 (1)
 (2)
 
  
  
 
 1
 
 

The Tripura Khadi and 
            Village Industries Board, a body constituted under the Tripura Khadi 
            and Village Industries Act, 1966. 
  
 
 2
 The Uttar Pradesh Development 
            Council. 
  
 
 3
 The Irrigation and Flood Control Commission, Uttar 
            Pradesh. 
  
 
 4
 The Indian Statistical Institute, 
            Calcutta. 
  
 
 5
 The West Bengal Handicrafts Development Corporation 
            Limited. 
  
 
 6
 The West Bengal Small Industries Development 
            Corporation Limited.    
 
 7
 
 

The West Bengal 
            Industrial Development Corporation 
            Limited. 
 
 
 8
 The Sriniketan Santiniketan Development Authority, a 
            body constituted under the West Bengal Town and Country (Planning 
            and Development) Act, 1979 (West Bengal Act No. 13 of 
            1979). 
  
 
 9
 The Haldia Development Authority, a body constituted 
            under the West Bengal Town and Country (Planning and Development) 
            Act, 1979 (West Bengal Act 
No. 13 of 
            1979). 
  
 
 10
 The West Bengal Minorities Development and Finance 
            Corporation, a body constituted under the West Bengal Minorities 
            Development and Finance Corporation Act, 
            1995. 
  
 
 11
 The Hooghly River Bridge Commissioners, constituted 
            under the Hooghly River Bridge Act, 1969 (West Bengal Act No. 36 of 
            1969). 
  
 
 12
 The Board of Wakf, West Bengal, a body constituted 
            under the Wakf Act, 1995 
(43 of 
            1995). 
  
 
 13
 The State Fisheries Development Corporation Limited, 
            West Bengal. 
  
 
 14
 The West Bengal State Haj Committee, constituted under 
            the Haj Committee Act, 2002 (35 of 2002). 
  
 
 15
 The Asansol Durgapur Development Authority, West 
            Bengal, a body constituted under the West Bengal Town and Country 
            (Planning and Development) Act, 1979 (West Bengal Act No. 13 of 
            1979). 
  
 
 16
 The West Bengal Pharmaceutical and Phytochemical 
            Development Corporation Limited. 
 
 
 17
 The West Bengal Handloom and Powerloom Development 
            Corporation Limited. 
  
 
 18
 The West Bengal Khadi and Village Industry 
            Board. 
  
 
 19
 The Society for Self-employment for Urban Youth, a 
            society registered under the West Bengal Societies Registration Act, 
            1961 (West Bengal Act No. 26 of 1961). 
  
 
 20
 The Tirumala Tirupathi Devasthanams 
            Board. 
  
 
 21
 The Agricultural and Processed Food Products Export 
            Development Authority, an authority constituted under section 4 of 
            the Agricultural and Processed Food Products Export Development 
            Authority Act, 1985 (2 of 1986). 
  
 
 22
 The National Agricultural Co-operative Marketing 
            Federation of India Limited (NAFED). 
  
 
 23
 The Indian Farmer: Fertilizers Co-operative Limited 
            (IFFCO). 
  
 
 24
 The Krishak Bharati Co-operative Limited 
            (KRIBHCO). 
  
 
 25
 The National Co-operative Consumers Federation of India 
            Limited (NCCF). 
  
 
 26
 The Auroville Foundation established under sub-section 
            (1) of section 10 of the Auroville Foundation Act, 1988 (54 of 
            1988). 
  
 
 27
 The National Commission of Enterprises in the 
            Unorganised Sector. 
 
 28
 The Planning Board (Asiatic Society) established under 
            sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Asiatic Society Act, 1984 (5 of 
            1984). 
  
 
 29
 The Delhi Rural Development 
            Board. 
  
 
 30
 The Maulana Azad Education Foundation. 
               
 
 31
 The Indira Gandhi National Centre for 
            Arts. 
  
 
 32
 The Dr. Ambedkar Foundation. 
  
 
 33
 The Bihar State Board of Religious Trust, a body 
            constituted under the Bihar Hindu Religious Trust Act, 1950 (Bihar 
            Act No. 1 of 1951).
 
 34
 The Research and Information System for the Non-Aligned 
            and Other Developing Countries.
 
 35
 The Indian Institute of 
            Psychometry. 
  
 
 36
 The Uttar Pradesh Film Development 
            Council. 
  
 
 37
 The Uttar Pradesh Provincial Co-operative 
            Federation. 
  
 
 38
 The Uttar Pradesh Co-operative Federation 
            Limited. 
  
 
 39
 The National Co-operative Union of 
            India. 
  
 
 40
 The Uttar Pradesh Krishi and Gram Vikas 
            Bank. 
  
 
 41
 The Uttar Pradesh Co-operative Bank 
            Limited. 
  
 
 42
 The Indian Council for Cultural 
            Relations. 
  
 
 43
 The Board of Control—A.N. Sinha Institute of Social 
            Studies, Patna.
 
 44
 All India Council for Sports. 
  
 
 45
 The Howrah Improvement Trust. 
  
 
 46
 The Dalit Sena, 12, Janpath, New 
            Delhi. 
  
 
 47
 The Social Justice Trust, 12, Janpath, New 
            Delhi. 
  
 
 48
 The Bahujan Foundation (Charitable Trust), Lucknow, 
            Uttar Pradesh.
 
 49
 The Bahujan Prerna Charitable Trust, 
            Delhi. 
  
 
 50
 The Central Wakf Council, established under section 9 
            of the Walk Act, 1995 (43 of 1995).
 
 51
 The Nehru Memorial Museum and Library 
            (NMML). 
  
 
 52
 The Jalianwala Bagh Memorial 
            Trust. 
  
 
 53
 The Haj Committee of India constituted under section 3 
            of the Haj Committee Act, 2002 ( 35 of 
        2002).
 
 54
 The Mallickghat Phoolbazar Parichalan 
            Committee. 
  
 
 55
 The West Bengal Fisheries Corporation 
            Limited.] 
  
 

   
 

   
 

--------------------------------
 

 1. The brackets and word 
      “(Private)” omitted by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 3 and the Second 
      Schedule.
 

 2. Subs. by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 
      3 and the Second Schedule, for “Nangal Fertilizers and Chemicals (Private) 
      Limited”.
 

 3. Ins. by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 
      3 and the Second Schedule.
 

 4. The brackets and word 
      “(Private)” omitted by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 3 and the Second 
      Schedule.
 

 5. Subs. by the Madras State 
      (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1970, 
      for “Madras” (w.e.f. 14-1-1969).
 

 6. Subs. by the Madras State 
      (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1970, 
      for “Madras State Electricity Board”.
 

 7. Subs. by the Mysore State 
      (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1974, 
      for “Mysore” (w.e.f. 1-11-1973).
 

 8. Subs. by the Madras State 
      (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1970, 
      for “Madras” (w.e.f. 14-1-1969).
 

 * Ed. It appears that 2004 is 
      samvat year of Indian Calendar.  
       
 

 9. Part III omitted by Act 54 of 
      1993, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 19-7-1993).  
       
 

 10. Ins. by Act 31 of 2006, sec. 
      3 (w.r.e.f. 4-4-1959).
 

--------------------------------
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 54 of 1993, sec. 
      2, for certain words (w.e.f 27-8-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Ins. by 
      Act 33 of 1977, sec. 12 (w.e.f.  1-11-1977).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>