<act><tid>66572</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN MATRIMONIAL CAUSES (WAR MARRIAGES) ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 40 OF <year>1948</year>
An Act to confer upon Courts temporary jurisdiction in certain 
matrimonial causes.

[ 3rd September, <year>1948</year>.]

WHEREAS it is expedient to confer upon Courts <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> temporary 
jurisdiction in certain matrimonial causes;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1619114</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>786670</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent.- This Act may be called the Indian  
Matrimonial Causes (War Marriages) Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1895364</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India, except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories which, 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B 
States].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1323323</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in 
the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1904747</tid>
<number>a</number>" High Court" shall have the same meaning as in the 
Indian Divorce Act, <year>1869</year>; (4 of <year>1869</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>263901</tid>
<number>b</number>" marriage" includes a purported marriage which was 
void ab initio, and" husband" and" wife" shall be con- 
strued accordingly;

</section>

<section><tid>1874617</tid>
<number>c</number>" war period" means the period commencing on the 3rd day 
of September, <year>1939</year>, and ending on the 31st day of March, 
<year>1946</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1190696</tid>
<number>3</number>Application of Act.- The marriages to which this Act applies are 
marriages solemnized during the war period, where the husband was, at 
the time of the marriage, domiciled outside India, and the wife was 
immediately before the marriage, domiciled in India:
Provided that this Act shall not apply to any marriage if, since the 
solemnization thereof, the parties thereto have resided together in 
the country in which the husband was domiciled at the time of the 
residence.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" in the Provinces of India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1-  
  7- 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of the above proviso the whole of the 
United States of America, the whole of the United Kingdom and the 
whole of any British possession <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall each be treated as one 
country.



</article>



<article><tid>840756</tid>
<number> 4</number> Temporary extension of jurisdiction of High Courts.- In the 
case of any marriage to which this Act applies, the High Court shall 
have jurisdiction in and in relation to any proceedings for divorce or 
for nullity of marriage as if both parties were at all material times 
domiciled in India; and subject to the provisions of this Act, the 
provisions of the Indian Divorce Act, <year>1869</year> (4 of <year>1869</year>), shall apply, 
so far as may be, in relation to any such proceedings instituted under 
this Act as if they were proceedings instituted under that Act:
Provided that this section shall not apply in relation to any 
proceedings for divorce or for nullity of marriage unless-

<section><tid>296251</tid>
<number>a</number>the petitioner or the respondent professes the 
Christian religion, and

</section>

<section><tid>1668040</tid>
<number>b</number>the proceedings for divorce or for nullity of marriage 
are commenced not later than three years from the com- 
mencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1968858</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving.- Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to extend or alter 
the jurisdiction of the High Court in, or in relation to, any 
proceedings for divorce or for nullity of marriage, where at the 
commencement of those proceedings the parties are domiciled anywhere 
in India.


</article>



<article><tid>1441048</tid>
<number>6</number>Certain decrees and orders to be recognised.- The validity of 
any decree or order made in the United Kingdom by virtue of the 
Matrimonial Causes (War Marriages) Act, <year>1944</year> 7 and 8 Geo. 6, c. 43. 
shall, by virtue of this Act, be recognised in all Courts in the 
States of India.


</article>



<article><tid>1674686</tid>
<number>7</number>Power to make rules.- The High Court may make such rules as may 
be necessary for the purpose of carrying out the objects of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" outside India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>