<act><title>


    The Indian Trusts Act, 1882</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, commencement.—This 
    Act may be called the Indian Trusts Act, 1882, and it shall come into force 
    on the first day of March, 1882. 

 
Local 
    extent.—1[It 
    extends to 

    2[the whole of India
    

    3[except the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir] and] the Andaman and Nicobar Islands, 

    4[***]; but the 
    Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, extend it to 

    5[the Andaman and 
    Nicobar Islands] or to any part thereof.]
 <section>

    <number>Savings</number>—But 
    nothing herein contained affects the rules of Mohammedan law as to waqf, 
    or the mutual relations of the members of an undivided family as determined 
    by any customary or personal law, or applies to public or private religious 
    or charitable endowments, or to trusts to distribute prizes taken in war 
    among the captors; and nothing in the Second Chapter of this Act applies to 
    trusts created before the said day.
 

 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number>  
    Repeal of Enactments.—The 
    Statute and Acts mentioned in the Schedule hereto annexed shall, to the 
    extent mentioned in the said Schedule, be repealed, in the territories to 
    which this Act for the time being extends. 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Interpretation-clause.—“trust”.—A 
    “trust” is an obligation annexed to the ownership of property, and arising 
    out of a confidence reposed in and accepted by the owner, or declared and 
    accepted by him, for the benefit of another, or of another and the owner: 
 

    “author of the trust”; “trustee”; “beneficiary”; “trust property”; 
    “beneficial interest”; “instrument of trust”.—The 
    person who reposes or declares the confidence is called the “author of the 
    trust”; The person who accepts the confidence is called the “trustee”; the 
    person for whose benefit the confidence is accepted is called the 
    “beneficiary”; the subject-matter of the trust is called “trust property” or 
    “trust money”; the “beneficial interest” or “interest” of the beneficiary is 
    his right against the trustee as owner of the trust property; and the 
    instrument, if any, by which the trust is declared is called the “instrument 
    of trust”; 
 
 

    “breach of trust”.—A 
    breach of any duty imposed on a trustee, as such, by any law for the time 
    being in force, is called a “breach of trust”; 
 
 

    “registered”, expressions defined in Act 9 of 1872.—And 
    in this Act, unless there be something repugnant in the subject of context, 
    “registered” means registered under the law for the registration of 
    documents for the time being in force; a person is said to have “notice” of 
    a fact either when he actually knows that fact or when, but for wilful 
    abstention from inquiry or gross negligence, he would have known it, or when 
    information of the fact is given to or obtained by his agent, under the 
    circumstances mentioned in the Indian Contract Act, 1872, section 229;
and all expressions used herein and defined in the Indian Contract Act, 
    1872, shall be deemed to have the meanings respectively attributed to them 
    by that Act.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Interpretation-clause.—“trust”.—A 
    “trust” is an obligation annexed to the ownership of property, and arising 
    out of a confidence reposed in and accepted by the owner, or declared and 
    accepted by him, for the benefit of another, or of another and the owner: 
 

    “author of the trust”; “trustee”; “beneficiary”; “trust property”; 
    “beneficial interest”; “instrument of trust”.—The 
    person who reposes or declares the confidence is called the “author of the 
    trust”; The person who accepts the confidence is called the “trustee”; the 
    person for whose benefit the confidence is accepted is called the 
    “beneficiary”; the subject-matter of the trust is called “trust property” or 
    “trust money”; the “beneficial interest” or “interest” of the beneficiary is 
    his right against the trustee as owner of the trust property; and the 
    instrument, if any, by which the trust is declared is called the “instrument 
    of trust”; 
 
 

    “breach of trust”.—A 
    breach of any duty imposed on a trustee, as such, by any law for the time 
    being in force, is called a “breach of trust”; 
 
 

    “registered”, expressions defined in Act 9 of 1872.—And 
    in this Act, unless there be something repugnant in the subject of context, 
    “registered” means registered under the law for the registration of 
    documents for the time being in force; a person is said to have “notice” of 
    a fact either when he actually knows that fact or when, but for wilful 
    abstention from inquiry or gross negligence, he would have known it, or when 
    information of the fact is given to or obtained by his agent, under the 
    circumstances mentioned in the Indian Contract Act, 1872, section 229;
and all expressions used herein and defined in the Indian Contract Act, 
    1872, shall be deemed to have the meanings respectively attributed to them 
    by that Act.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Lawful purpose.—A 
    trust may be created for any lawful purpose. The purpose of a trust is 
    lawful unless it is 
<section><number>a</number> forbidden by law, or (b) is of such a nature that, 
    if permitted, it would defeat the provisions of any law, or (c) is 
    fraudulent, or (d) involves or implies injury to the person or property of 
    another, or (e) the Court regards it as immoral or opposed to public policy.
    
 
 
Every 
    trust of which the purpose is unlawful is void. And where a trust is created 
    for two purposes, of which one is lawful and the other unlawful, and the two 
    purposes cannot be separated, the whole trust is void. 
 
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this section, the expression “law” includes, where the trust property is 
    immovable and situate in a foreign country, the law of such country. 

 
 
 

Illustrations
 

 
  


</section><section>
<number>a</number> A conveys 
      property to B in trust to apply the profits to the nurture of 
      female foundings to be trained up as prostitutes. The trust is void.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      property to B in trust to employ it in carrying on a smuggling 
      business and out of the profits thereof to support A’s children. 
      The trust is void. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A, while in 
      insolvent circumstances, transfers property to B in trust for A 
      during his life, and after his death for B. A is declared an 
      insolvent. The trust for A is invalid against his creditors. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
It is well settled that 
      the mere fact that a debtor chooses to prefer one creditor to the other 
      either because of the priority of the debt or otherwise, by itself cannot 
      lead to the irresistible inference that the intention was to defeat the 
      other creditors; Chogmal Bhandari v. Dy. Commercial Tax Officer,
      AIR 1976 SC 656.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Trust of immovable property.—No 
    trust in relation to immoveable property is valid unless declared by a 
    non-testamentary instrument in writing signed by the author of the trust or 
    the trustee and registered, or by the will of the author of the trust or of 
    the trustee. 
 
 
Trust 
    of moveable property.—No 
    trust relating to movable property is valid unless declared as aforesaid, or 
    unless the ownership of the property is transferred to the trustee. 

 
 
These 
    rules do not apply where they would operate so as to effectuate a fraud.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>6</number> 
    Creation of trust.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 5, a trust is created when the author of the 
    trust indicates with reasonable certainty by any words or acts, 
<section><number>a</number> an 
    intention on his part to create thereby a trust, (b) the purpose of the 
    trust, (c) the beneficiary, and (d) the trust, property, and (unless the 
    trust is declared by will or the author of the trust is himself to be the 
    trustee) transfers the trust property to the trustee. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 

 
  


</section><section>
<number>a</number> A bequeaths certain 
      property to B, “having the fullest confidence that he will dispose 
      of it for the benefit of C”. This creates a trust so far as regards
      A and C. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      certain property to B, “hoping he will continue it in the family”. 
      This does not create a trust as the beneficiary is not indicated with 
      reasonable certainty. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A bequeaths 
      certain property to B, requesting him to distribute it amongst such 
      members of C’s family as B should think most deserving. This 
      does not create a trust, for the beneficiaries are not indicated with 
      reasonable certainty. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A bequeaths 
      certain property to B, desiring him to divide the bulk of it among
      C’s children. This does not create a trust, for the trust property 
      is not indicated with sufficient certainty. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> A bequeaths a 
      shop and stock-in-trade to B, on condition that he pays A’s 
      debts and a legacy to C. This is a condition, not a trust for 
      A’s creditors and C. 
 
  
 

comments
 
Where a particular 
      clause of the trust deed specifically stated that “upon death of 
      beneficiaries the trustees or heirs of trustees shall convey or transfer 
      the trust property to the then surviving heirs of author’s husband”, the 
      apex court held that the observations/interpretation by the High Court 
      regarding the expression ‘heirs’ had limited purpose being only of 
      incidental relevance. There was hardly any room for going beyond the said 
      ‘clause’ as it was precise and typical enough for the purpose of such 
      circumstances; Ranjit Kumar Ghosh v. Sirish Chandra Bose; 
      AIR 1994 SC 1254.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Who 
    may create trusts.—A 
    trust may be created—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    by every person competent to contract,<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and
    
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    with the permission of a 
    principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, by or on behalf of a minor;  
 
but subject in each case to the law for 
    the time being in force as to the circumstances and extent in and to which 
    the author of the trust may dispose of the-trust property. 

 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Subject of Trust.—The 
    subject-matter of a trust must be property transferable to the beneficiary.
 
It must 
    not be merely beneficial interest under a subsisting trust. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Who 
    may be beneficiary.—Every 
    person capable of holding property may be a beneficiary. 
 
 

    Disclaimer by beneficiary.—A 
    proposed beneficiary may renounce his interest under the trust by disclaimer 
    addressed to the trustee, or by the setting up, with notice of the trust, a 
    claim inconsistent therewith. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Who may be trustee.—Every 
    person capable of holding property may be a trustee; but, where the trust 
    involves the exercise of discretion, he cannot execute it unless he is 
    competent to contract. 
 
 
No one 
    bound to accept trust.—No 
    one is bound to accept a trust. 
 
 

    Acceptance of trust.—A 
    trust is accepted by any words or acts of the trustee indicating with 
    reasonable certainty of such acceptance. 
 
 

    Disclaimer of trust.—Instead 
    of accepting a trust, the intended trustee may, within a reasonable period, 
    disclaim it, and such disclaimer shall prevent the trust property from 
    vesting in him. 
 
 
A 
    disclaimer by one of two or more co-trustees vests the trust property in the 
    other or others and makes him or them sole trustee or trustees from the date 
    of the creation of the trust. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A bequeaths 
      certain property to B and C, his executors as trustees for
      D, B and C prove A’s will. This is in itself 
      an acceptance of the trust, and B and C hold the property in 
      trust for D. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A transfers 
      certain property to B in trust to sell it, and to pay out of the 
      proceeds A’s debts. B accepts the trust and sells the 
      property. So far as regards B, a trust of the proceeds is created 
      for A’s creditors. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A bequeaths a 
      lakh of rupees to B upon certain trusts, and appoints him his 
      executor. B severs the lakh from the general assets, and 
      appropriates it to the specific purpose. This is an acceptance of the 
      trust. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Trustee to execute trust.—The 
    trustee is bound to fulfil the purpose of the trust, and to obey the 
    directions of the author of the trust given at the time of its creation, 
    except as modified by the consent of all the beneficiaries being competent 
    to contract. 
 
 
Where the 
    beneficiary is incompetent to contract, his consent may, for the purposes of 
    this section, be given by a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction.
    
 
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to require a trustee to obey any direction 
    when to do so would be impracticable, illegal or manifestly injurious to the 
    beneficiaries. 
 
 

    Explanation.—Unless 
    a contrary intention be expressed, the purpose of a trust for the payment of 
    debts shall be deemed to be 
<section><number>a</number> to pay only the debts of the author of the 
    trust existing and recoverable at the date of the instrument of trust or 
    when such instrument is a will, at the date of his death, and (b) in the 
    case of debts not bearing interest, to make such payment without interest.
    
 
 
 

Illustrations
 

 
  


</section><section>
<number>a</number> A, a trustee, 
      is simply authorised to sell certain land by public auction. He cannot 
      sell the land by private contract. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, a trustee 
      of certain land for X, Y and Z, is authorised to sell 
      the land to B for a specified sum. X, Y and Z, 
      being competent to contract, consent that A may sell the land to C 
      for less sum. A may sell the land accordingly. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A, a trustee 
      for B and her children, is directed by the author of the trust to 
      land, on B’s request, trust property to B’s husband, C, 
      on the security of his bond. C becomes insolvent, and B 
      requests A to make the loan, A may refuse to make it. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    The trust need 
      not be retained in its original form and it can be dissolved, varied, 
      modified or revoked provided all the beneficiaries concerned who are 
      competent to contract give their respective consent to such 
      resort/procedure; Prince Muffakham Jah Bahadur v. H.E.H. Nawab 
      Mir Barkat Ali Khan Bahadur Prince Mukarram Jah, AIR 1989 AP 68.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Where the 
      administration of the trust is vested in co-trustees, they all form, as it 
      were, but one collective trustee and must execute the duties of the office 
      in their joint capacity; R.P. Kapur v. K. Educational Trust, 
      ILR (1982) 1 Del 801.  
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Trustee to inform himself of state of trust property.—A 
    trustee is bound to acquaint himself, as soon as possible, with the nature 
    and circumstances of the trust- property; to obtain, where necessary, a 
    transfer of the trust property to himself; and (subject to the provisions of 
    the instrument of trust) to get in trust-moneys invested on insufficient or 
    hazardous security.
 
 

Illustrations 


 <section>
<number>a</number> The trust property 
      is a debt outstanding on personal security. The instrument of trust gives 
      the trustee no discretionary power to leave the debt so outstanding. The 
      trustee’s duty is to recover the debt without unnecessary delay. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The trust property 
      is money in the hands of one of two co-trustees. No discretionary power is 
      given by the instrument of trust. The other co-trustee must not allow the 
      former to retain the money for a longer period than the circumstances of 
      the case required. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Trustee to protect title to trust property.—A 
    trustee is bound to maintain and defend all such suits, and (subject to the 
    provisions of the instrument of trust) to take such other steps as, regard 
    being had to the nature and amount or value of the trust property, may be 
    reasonably requisite for the preservation of the trust property and the 
    assertion or protection of the title thereto. 
 
 
 

Illustration 

 
The trust property is 
      immoveable property which has been given to the author of the trust by an 
      unregistered instrument. Subject to the provisions of the Indian 
      Registration Act, 1877 (3 of 1877)<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the 
      trustee’s duty is to cause the instrument to be registered. 

 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Trustee not to set up title adverse to beneficiary.—The 
    trustee must not for himself or another set up or aid any title to the trust 
    property adverse to the interest of the beneficiary. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Care required from trustee.—A 
    trustee is bound to deal with the trust property as carefully as a man of 
    ordinary prudence would deal with such property if it were his own; and, in 
    the absence of a contract to the contrary, a trustee so dealing is not 
    responsible for the loss, destruction, or deterioration of the trust 
    property. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, living in 
      Calcutta, is a trustee for B, living in Bombay. A remits 
      trust-funds to B by bills drawn by a person of undoubted credit in 
      favour of the trustee as such, and payable at Bombay. The bills are 
      dishonoured. A is not bound to make good the loss. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, trustee of 
      lease-hold property, directs the tenant to pay the rents on account of the 
      trust to a banker, B, then in credit. The rents are accordingly 
      paid to B, and A leaves the money with B only till 
      wanted. Before the money is drawn out, B becomes insolvent. A, 
      having had no reason to believe that B was in insolvent 
      circumstances, is not bound to make good the loss. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A, a trustee 
      of two debts for B, releases one, and compounds the other, in good 
      faith, and reasonably believing that it is for B’s interest to do 
      so. A is not bound to make good any loss caused thereby to B.
      
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A, a trustee 
      directed to sell the trust property by auction, sells the same, but does 
      not advertise the sale and otherwise fails in reasonable diligence in 
      inviting competition. A is bound to make good the loss caused 
      thereby to the beneficiary. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> A, a trustee 
      for B, in execution of his trust, sells the trust property, but 
      from want of due diligence on his part, fails to receive part of the 
      purchase-money. A is bound to make good the loss thereby caused to
      B. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> A, a trustee 
      for B of a policy of insurance, has funds in hand for payment of 
      the premiums. A neglects to pay the premiums and the policy is 
      consequently forfeited. A is bound to make good the loss to B.
      
 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> A bequeaths 
      certain money to B and C as trustees, and authorizes them to 
      continue trust moneys upon the personal security of certain firm in which
      A had himself invested them. A dies, and a change takes 
      place in the firm. B and C must not permit the moneys to 
      remain upon the personal security of the new firm. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> A, a trustee 
      for B, allows the trust to be executed solely by his co-trustee 
      C. C misapplies the trust property. A is personally 
      answerable for the loss resulting to B. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Conversion of perishable property.—Where 
    the trust is created for the benefit of several persons in succession, and 
    the trust property is of a wasting nature or a future or reversionary 
    interest, the trustee is bound, unless an intention to the contrary may be 
    inferred from the instrument of trust, to convert the property into property 
    of a permanent and immediately profitable character.
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A bequeaths 
      to B all his property in trust for C during his life and on 
      his death for D, and D’s death for E. A’s property 
      consists of three lease-hold houses, and there is nothing in A’s 
      will to show that he intended the houses to be enjoyed in specie. B 
      should sell the houses and invest the proceeds in accordance with section 
      20. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      to B his three lease hold houses in Calcutta and all the furniture 
      therein in trust for C during his life, and on his death for D, 
      and on D’s death for E. Here an intention that the houses 
      and furniture should be enjoyed in specie appears clearly, and B 
      should not sell them. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
The rule contained in 
      this section has been explained by Wigam V-C in these words:  
 
“Where personal estate 
      is given in terms amounting to a general bequest to be enjoyed by persons 
      in succession, the interpretation the court puts upon the bequest in that 
      the persons indicated are to enjoy the same thing in succession, and in 
      order to effectuate that intention, the court as a general rule converts 
      into permanent investments so much of the personality as is of a wasting 
      or perishable nature at the death of the testator, and also reversionary 
      interests. The rule did not originally ascribe to testators the intention 
      to effect such conversions, except in so far as a testator may be supposed 
      to intend that which the law will do; but the court, finding the intention 
      of the testator to be that the objects of his bounty shall take successive 
      interests in one and the same thing, converts the property, as the only 
      means of giving effect to that intention”; Hiuves v. Hiuves, 
      (1844) 3 Hare 609.  
</section>
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Trustee to be impartial.—Where 
    there are more beneficiaries than one, the trustee is bound to be impartial, 
    and must not execute the trust for the advantage of one at the expense of 
    another. 
 
 
Where the 
    trustee has a discretionary power, nothing in this section shall be deemed 
    to authorise the Court to control the exercise reasonably and in good faith 
    of such discretion. 
 
 
 

Illustration
 
A, 
      a trustee for B, C and D is empowered to choose between 
      several specified modes of investing the trust property. A in good 
      faith chooses one of these modes. The Court will not interfere, although 
      the result of the choice may be to vary the relative rights of B, C 
      and D. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Trustee to prevent waste.—Where 
    the trust is created for the benefit of several persons in succession, and 
    one of them is in possession of the trust property, if he commits or 
    threatens to commit, any act which is destructive or permanently injurious 
    thereto, the trustee is bound to take measures to prevent such act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Accounts and information.—A 
    trustee is bound 
<section><number>a</number> to keep clear and accurate accounts of the trust 
    property, and (b) at all reasonable times, at the request of the beneficiary 
    to furnish him with full and accurate information as to the amount and state 
    of the trust property. 
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Investment of trust-money.—Where 
    the trust property consists of money and cannot be applied immediately or at 
    an early date to the purposes of the trust, the trustee is bound (subject to 
    any direction contained in the instrument of trust) to invest the money on 
    the following securities and on no others:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in promissory notes, debentures, 
    stock or other securities <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[of 
    any <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[State Government] or] of the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government], or of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland:
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Provided that securities, 
    both the principal whereof and the interest whereon shall have been fully 
    and unconditionally guaranteed by any such Government, shall be deemed, for 
    the purposes of this clause, to be securities of such Government;] 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in bonds, debentures and 
    annuities <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[charged or secured by the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Parliament of 
    the United Kingdom] <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[before the 15th day of August, 1947] on the 
    revenues of India or of the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Governor-General in Council<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>] 
    or of any Province<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>]:
 
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Provided that after the 
    fifteenth day of February, 1916, no money shall be invested in any such 
    annuity being a terminable annuity unless a sinking fund has been 
    established in connection with such annuity; but nothing in this proviso 
    shall apply to investments made before the date aforesaid;] 

 </section><section>
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>bb</number>    in India three and 
    a half per cent. stock, India three per cent. stock, India two and a half 
    per cent. stock or any other capital stock <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[which before the 
    15th day of August, 1947, was] issued by the Secretary of State for India in 
    Council under the authority of an Act of Parliament <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[of the 
    United Kingdom] and charged on the revenues of India; <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[or 
    which <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[was] issued by the 
    Secretary of State on behalf of the Governor-General in Council under the 
    provisions of Part XIII of the Government of India Act, 1935];]
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    in stock or debentures of, or 
    shares in, railway or other companies the interest whereon shall have been 
    guaranteed by the Secretary of State for India in Council; 
15[or 
    by the Central Government] 
15[or 
    in debentures of the Bombay 
16[Provincial] 
    Co-operative Bank Limited, the interest whereon shall have been guaranteed, 
    by the Secretary of State for India in Council] 
13[or 
    the State Government of Bombay]; 
 
 

17[(d)    
    in debentures or other securities for money issued, under the authority of
    18[any 
    Central Act or Provincial Act or State Act], by or on behalf of any 
    municipal body, port trust, or city improvement trust in any Presidency-town 
    or in Rangoon Town, or by or on behalf of the trustees of the port of 
    Karachi:]
 

19[Provided 
    that after the 31st day of March, 1948, no money shall be invested in any 
    securities issued by or on behalf of a municipal body, port trust or city 
    improvement trust in Rangoon Town, or by or on behalf of the trustees of the 
    port of Karachi;]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    on a first mortgage of immovable 
    property situate in 
20[any 
    part of the territories to which this Act extends]: Provided that the 
    property is not a lease hold for a term of years, and that the value of the 
    property exceeds by one-third, or, if consisting of buildings, exceeds by 
    one-half, the mortgage-money; 
21[***]
 

22[(ee)    
    in units issued by the Unit Trust of India under any unit scheme made under 
    section 21 of the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 1963); or]
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    on any other security expressly 
    authorized by the instrument of trust, 
22[or 
    by the Central Government by the notification in the Official Gazette] or by 
    any rule which the High Court may from time to time prescribe in this 
    behalf:
 
Provided that, where there is a person 
    competent to contract and entitled in possession to receive the income of 
    the trust property for his life, or for any greater estate, no investment on 
    any security mentioned or referred to in clauses (d), (e) and (f) shall be 
    made without his consent in writing. 
 
 



























 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>20A</number> Power to 
    purchase redeemable stock at a premium.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A trustee may invest in any of the securities mentioned or referred to in 
    section 20, notwithstanding that the same may be redeemable and that the 
    price exceeds the redemption value: 
 
 
Provided 
    that a trustee may not purchase at a price exceeding its redemption value 
    and security mentioned or referred to in clauses (c) and (d) of section 20, 
    which is liable to be redeemed within fifteen years of the date of purchase 
    at par or at some other fixed rate, or purchase any such security as is 
    mentioned or referred to in the said clauses which is liable to be redeemed 
    at par or at some other fixed rate at a price exceeding fifteen per cent. 
    above par or such other fixed rate. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    trustee may retain until redemption any redeemable stock, fund or security 
    which may have been purchased in accordance with this section.] 

 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Mortgage of land pledged to Government under Act 26 of 1871—Deposit 
    in Government Savings Bank.—Nothing in section 20 shall apply to 
    investments made before this Act comes into force, or shall be deemed to 
    preclude an investment on a mortgage of immovable property already pledged 
    as security for an advance under the Land Improvement Act, 18711, 
    or, in case the trust-money does not exceed three thousand rupees, a deposit 
    thereof in a Government Savings Bank. 
 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Sale by trustee directed to sell within specified time.—Where 
    a trustee directed to sell within a specified time extends such time the 
    burden of proving, as between himself and the beneficiary, that the latter 
    is not prejudiced by the extension lies upon the trustee, unless the 
    extension has been authorised by a principal Civil Court of original 
    jurisdiction. 
 
 

Illustration
 
A 
      bequeaths property to B, directing him with all convenient speed 
      and within five years to sell it, and apply the proceeds for the benefit 
      of C. In the exercise of reasonable discretion, B postpones 
      the sale for six years. The sale is not thereby rendered invalid, but 
      C, alleging that he has been injured by the postponement, institutes a 
      suit against B to obtain compensation. In such suit the burden of 
      proving that C has not been injured lies on B. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Liability for breach of trust.—Where 
    the trustee commits a breach of trust, he is liable to make good the loss 
    which the trust property or the beneficiary has thereby sustained, unless 
    the beneficiary has by fraud induced the trustee to commit the breach, or 
    the beneficiary, being competent to contract, has himself, without coercion 
    or undue influence having been brought to bear on him, concurred in the 
    breach, or subsequently acquiesced therein with full knowledge of the facts 
    of the case and of his rights as against the trustee. 
 
 
A trustee 
    committing a breach of trust is not liable to pay interest except in the 
    following cases:— 
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where he has actually received 
    interest; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where the breach consists in 
    unreasonable delay in paying trust-money to the beneficiary; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    where the trustee ought to have 
    received interest, but has not done so; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    where he may be fairly presumed 
    to have received interest. 
 
 
He is liable, in case (a), to account 
    for the interest actually received, and, in case (b), (c) and (d), to 
    account for simple interest at the rate of six per cent. per annum, unless 
    the Court otherwise directs; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    where the breach consists in 
    failure to invest trust-money and to accumulate the interest or dividends 
    thereon, he is liable to account for compound interest (with half-yearly 
    rests) at the same rate; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    where the breach consists in the 
    employment of trust property or the proceeds thereof in trade or business, 
    he is liable to account, at the option of the beneficiary, either for 
    compound interest (with half-yearly rests) at the same rate, or for the nett 
    profits made by such employment.  
 
 

Illustrations
 

 
  


</section><section>
<number>a</number> A trustee 
      improperly leaves trust property outstanding, and it is consequently lost, 
      he is liable to make good the property lost, but he is not liable to pay 
      interest thereon.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths a 
      house to B in trust to sell it and pay the proceeds to C. B 
      neglects to sell the house for a great length of time, whereby the house 
      is deteriorated and its market-price falls. B is answerable to C
      for the loss.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A trustee is 
      guity of unreasonable delay in investing trust money in accordance with 
      section 20, or in paying it to the beneficiary. The trustee is liable to 
      pay interest thereon for the period of the delay.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The duty of the 
      trustee is to invest trust-money in any of the securities mentioned in 
      section 20, clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d). Instead of so doing, he retains 
      the money in his hands. He is liable, at the option of the beneficiary, to 
      be charged either with the amount of the principal money and interest, or 
      with the amount of such securities as he might have purchased with the 
      trust-money when the investment should have been made, and the 
      intermediate dividends and interest thereon.  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> The instrument of 
      trust directs the trustee to invest trust-money either in any of such 
      securities or on mortgage of immovable property. The trustee does neither. 
      He is liable for the principal money and interest.  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> The instrument of 
      trust directs the trustee to invest trust-money in any of such securities 
      and to accumulate the dividends thereon. The trustee disregards the 
      direction. He is liable, at the option of the beneficiary, to be charged 
      either with the amount of the principal money and compound interest, or 
      with the amount of such securities as he might have purchased with the 
      trust-money when the investment should have been made, together with the 
      amount of the accumulation which would have arisen from a proper 
      investment of the intermediate dividends.  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> Trust property is 
      invested in one of the securities mentioned in section 20, clause (a), 
      (b), (c) or (d). The trustee sells such security for some purpose not 
      authorised by the terms of the instrument of trust. He is liable, at the 
      option of the beneficiary, either to replace the security with the 
      intermediate dividends and interest thereon, or to account for the 
      proceeds of the sale with interest thereon.  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> The trust property 
      consists of land. The trustee sells the land to a purchaser for a 
      consideration without notice of the trust. The trustee is liable, at the 
      option of the beneficiary, to purchase other land of equal value to be 
      settled upon the like trust, or to be charged with the proceeds of the 
      sale with interest. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
It is no answer to a 
      charge of breach of trust that the trustee acted under competent legal 
      advice; S. Chettiar v. R. Dorai, (1909) ILR 32 Mad 490.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> No 
    set-off allowed to trustee.—A 
    trustee who is liable for a loss occasioned by a breach of trust in respect 
    of one portion of the trust property cannot set-off against his liability a 
    gain which has accrued to another portion of the trust property through 
    another and distinct breach of trust. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Non-liability for predecessor’s default.—When 
    a trustee succeeds another, he is not, as such, liable for the acts or 
    defaults of his predecessor. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Non-liability for predecessor’s default.—When 
    a trustee succeeds another, he is not, as such, liable for the acts or 
    defaults of his predecessor. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Non-liability for co-trustee’s default.—Subject 
    to the provisions of sections 13 and 15, a trustee is not, as such, liable 
    for a breach of trust committed by his co-trustee: 
 
 
Provided 
    that, in the absence of an express declaration to the contrary in the 
    instrument of trust, a trustee is so liable—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where he has delivered trust 
    property to his co-trustee without seeing to its proper application; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where he allows his co-trustee to 
    receive trust property and fails to make due enquiry as to the co-trustee’s 
    dealings therewith or allows him to retain it longer than the circumstances 
    of the case reasonably require; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    where he becomes aware of a 
    breach of trust committed or intended by his co-trustee, and either actively 
    conceals it or does not within a reasonable time take proper steps to 
    protect the beneficiary’s interest. 
 
 

    Joining in receipt for conformity.—A 
    co-trustee who joins in signing a receipt for trust property and proves that 
    he has not received the same is not answerable, by reason of such signature 
    only, for loss or mis-application of the property by his co-trustee.  
 
 

Illustration
 
A 
bequeaths certain property to B and 
      C, and directs them to sell it and invest the proceeds for the benefit 
      of D. B and C accordingly sell the property, and the 
      purchase money is received by B and retained in his hands, C 
      pays no attention to the matter for two years, and then calls on B 
      to make the investment. B is unable to do so, becomes insolvent, 
      and the purchase-money is lost. C may be compelled to make good the 
      amount. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Non-liability for co-trustee’s default.—Subject 
    to the provisions of sections 13 and 15, a trustee is not, as such, liable 
    for a breach of trust committed by his co-trustee: 
 
 
Provided 
    that, in the absence of an express declaration to the contrary in the 
    instrument of trust, a trustee is so liable—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where he has delivered trust 
    property to his co-trustee without seeing to its proper application; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where he allows his co-trustee to 
    receive trust property and fails to make due enquiry as to the co-trustee’s 
    dealings therewith or allows him to retain it longer than the circumstances 
    of the case reasonably require; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    where he becomes aware of a 
    breach of trust committed or intended by his co-trustee, and either actively 
    conceals it or does not within a reasonable time take proper steps to 
    protect the beneficiary’s interest. 
 
 

    Joining in receipt for conformity.—A 
    co-trustee who joins in signing a receipt for trust property and proves that 
    he has not received the same is not answerable, by reason of such signature 
    only, for loss or mis-application of the property by his co-trustee.  
 
 

Illustration
 
A 
bequeaths certain property to B and 
      C, and directs them to sell it and invest the proceeds for the benefit 
      of D. B and C accordingly sell the property, and the 
      purchase money is received by B and retained in his hands, C 
      pays no attention to the matter for two years, and then calls on B 
      to make the investment. B is unable to do so, becomes insolvent, 
      and the purchase-money is lost. C may be compelled to make good the 
      amount. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Several liability of co-trustee.—Where 
    co-trustees jointly commit a breach of trust, or where one of them by his 
    neglect enables the other to commit a breach of trust, each is liable to the 
    beneficiary for the whole of the loss occasioned by such breach. 

 
 

    Contribution as between co-trustees.—But, 
    as between the trustees themselves, if one be less guilty than another and 
    has had to refund the loss, the former may compel the latter, or his legal 
    representative, to the extent of the assets he has received, to make good 
    such loss; and, if all be equally guilty; any one or more of the trustees 
    who has had to refund the loss may compel the others to contribute. 

 
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to authorise a trustee who has been guilty 
    of fraud to institute a suit to compel contribution. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Non-liability of trustee paying without notice of transfer by beneficiary.—When 
    any beneficiary’s interest becomes vested in another person, and the 
    trustee, not having notice of the vesting, pays or delivers trust property 
    to the person who would have been entitled thereto in the absence of such 
    vesting, the trustee is not liable for the property so paid or delivered.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Liability of trustee where beneficiary’s interest is forfeited to 
    Government.—When 
    the beneficiary’s interest is forfeited or awarded by legal adjudication
    <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[to 
    the Government], the trustee is bound to hold the trust property to the 
    extent of such interest for the benefit of such person in such manner as
    <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[the State Government] may direct in this behalf. 

 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Liability of trustee where beneficiary’s interest is forfeited to 
    Government.—When 
    the beneficiary’s interest is forfeited or awarded by legal adjudication
    <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[to 
    the Government], the trustee is bound to hold the trust property to the 
    extent of such interest for the benefit of such person in such manner as
    <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[the State Government] may direct in this behalf. 

 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Indemnity of trustees.—Subject 
    to the provisions of the instrument of trust and of sections 23 and 26, 
    trustees shall be respectively chargeable only for such moneys, stocks, 
    funds and securities as they respectively actually receive and shall not be 
    answerable the one for the other of them, nor for any banker, broker or 
    other person in whose hands any trust property may be placed, nor for the 
    insufficiency or deficiency of any stocks, funds or securities nor otherwise 
    for involuntary losses.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Right to title-deed.—A 
    trustee is entitled to have in his possession the instrument of trust and 
    all the documents of title (if any) relating solely to the trust property.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Right to re-imbursement of expenses.—Every 
    trustee may re-imburse himself, or pay or discharge out of the trust 
    property, all expenses properly incurred in or about the execution of the 
    trust, or the realisation, preservation or benefit of the trust property, or 
    the protection or support of the beneficiary. 
 
 
If he 
    pays such expenses out of his own pocket, he has a first charge upon the 
    trust property for such expenses and interest thereon; but such charge 
    (unless the expenses have been incurred with the sanction of a principal 
    Civil Court of original jurisdiction) shall be enforced only by prohibiting 
    any disposition of the trust property without previous payment of such 
    expenses and interest.  
 
If the 
    trust property fails, the trustee is entitled to recover from the 
    beneficiary personally on whose behalf he acted, and at whose request, 
    expressed or implied, he made the payment, the amount of such expenses.
    
 
 
Right 
    to be recouped for erroneous over-payment.—Where 
    a trustee has by mistake made an over-payment to the beneficiary, he may 
    reimburse the trust property out of the beneficiary’s interest. If such 
    interest fail, the trustee is entitled to recover from the beneficiary 
    personally the amount of such over-payment. 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Right to indemnity from gainer by breach of trust.—A 
    person other than a trustee who has gained an advantage from a breach of 
    trust must indemnify the trustee to the extent of the amount actually 
    received by such person under the breach; and where he is a beneficiary the 
    trustee has a charge on his interest for such amount.  
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to entitle a trustee to be indemnified who 
    has, in committing the breach of trust, been guilty of fraud. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Right to apply to Court for opinion in management of trust property.—Any 
    trustee may, without instituting a suit, apply by petition to a principal 
    Civil Court of original jurisdiction for its opinion, advice or direction on 
    any present questions respecting the management or administration of the 
    trust property other than questions of detail, difficulty or importance, not 
    proper in the opinion of the Court for summary disposal. 
 
 
A copy of 
    such petition shall be served upon, and the hearing thereof may be attended 
    by, such of the persons interested in the application as the Court thinks 
    fit. 
 
 
The 
    trustee stating in good faith the facts in such petition and acting upon the 
    opinion, advice or direction given by the Court shall be deemed so far as 
    regards his own responsibility, to have discharged his duty as such trustee 
    in the subject-matter of the application. 
 
 
The costs 
    of every application under this section shall be in the discretion of the 
    Court to which it is made. 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Right to settlement of accounts.—When 
    the duties of a trustee, as such, are completed, he is entitled to have the 
    accounts of his administration of the trust property examined and settled; 
    and, where nothing is due to the beneficiary under the trust, to an 
    acknowledgement in writing to that effect. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    General authority of trustee.—In 
    addition to the powers expressly conferred by this Act and by the instrument 
    of trust, and subject to the restrictions, if any, contained in such 
    instrument, and to the provisions of section 17, a trustee may do all acts 
    which are reasonable and proper for the realisation, protection or benefit 
    of the trust property, and for the protection or support of a beneficiary 
    who is not competent to contract.  
 


    1[***]  
 
Except 
    with the permission of a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, no 
    trustee shall lease trust property for a term exceeding twenty-one years 
    from the date of executing the lease, nor without reserving the best yearly 
    rent that can be reasonably obtained. 
 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Power to sell in lots and either by public auction or private contract.—Where the trustee is empowered to sell any trust 
    property, he may sell the same subject to prior charges or not, and either 
    together or in lots, by public auction or private contract, and either at 
    one time or at several times, unless the instrument of trust otherwise 
    directs. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Power to sell under special conditions power to buy-in and re-sell.—The 
    trustee making any such sale may insert such reasonable stipulations either 
    as to title or evidence of title, or otherwise, in any conditions of sale or 
    contract for sale, as he thinks fit; and may also buy-in the property or any 
    part thereof at any sale by auction, and rescind or vary any contract for 
    sale, and re-sell the property so bought in, or as to which the contract is 
    so rescinded, without being responsible to the beneficiary for any loss 
    occasioned thereby. 
 
 
Time 
    allowed for selling trust property.—Where 
    a trustee is directed to sell trust property or to invest trust money in the 
    purchase of property, he may exercise a reasonable discretion as to the time 
    to effecting the sale or purchase. 
 
 
 

Illustrations 


 <section>
<number>a</number> A bequeaths 
      property to B, directing him to sell it with all convenient speed 
      and pay the proceeds to C. This does not render an immediate sale 
      imperative. 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      property to B, directing him to sell it at such time in such manner 
      as he shall think fit and invest the proceeds for the benefit of C. 
      This does not authorise B, as between him and C, to postpone 
      the sale to an indefinite period. 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>39</number> 
    Power to convey.—For 
    the purpose of completing any such sale, the trustee shall have power to 
    convey or otherwise dispose of the property sold in such manner as may be 
    necessary. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Power to vary investments.—A 
    trustee may, at his discretion, call in any trust property invested in any 
    security, and invest the same on any of the securities mentioned or referred 
    to in section 20, and from time to time vary any such investments for others 
    of the same nature: 
 
 
Provided 
    that where there is a person competent to contract and entitled at the time 
    to receive the income of the trust property for his life, or for any greater 
    estate, no such change of investment shall be made without his consent in 
    writing. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Power to apply property of minors, etc., for their maintenance, etc.—Where 
    any property is held by a trustee in trust for a minor, such trustee may, at 
    his discretion, pay to the guardians (if any) of such minor, or otherwise 
    apply for or towards his maintenance or education or advancement in life or 
    the reasonable expenses of his religious worship, marriage or funeral, the 
    whole or any part of the income to which he may be entitled in respect of 
    such property; and such trustee shall accumulate all the residue of such 
    income by way of compound interest, by investing the same and the resulting 
    income thereof from time to time in any of the securities mentioned or 
    referred to in section 20, for the benefit of the person who shall 
    ultimately become entitled to the property from which such accumulations 
    have arisen: 
 
 
Provided 
    that such trustee may, at any time, if he thinks fit apply the whole or any 
    part of such accumulations as if the same were part of the income arising in 
    the then current year.  
 
Where the 
    income of the trust property is insufficient for the minor’s maintenance or 
    education or advancement in life, or the reasonable expenses of his 
    religious worship, marriage or funeral, the trustee may, with the permission 
    of a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, but not otherwise, 
    apply the whole or any part of such property for or towards such 
    maintenance, education, advancement or expenses. 
 
 
Nothing 
    in this section shall be deemed to affect the provisions of any local law 
    for the time being in force relating to the persons and property of minors.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Power to give receipts.—Any 
    trustees or trustee may give a receipt in writing for any money, securities 
    or other movable property payable, transferable or deliverable to them or 
    him by reason, or in the exercise of any trust or power; and, in the absence 
    of fraud, such receipt shall discharge the person paying, transferring or 
    delivering the same therefrom, and from seeing to the application thereof, 
    or being accountable for any loss or misapplication thereof. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Power to compound, etc.—Two 
    or more trustees acting together may, if and as they think fit,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    accept any composition or any 
    security for any debt or for any property claimed; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    allow any time for payment of any 
    debt; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    compromise, compound, abandon, 
    submit to arbitration or otherwise settle any debt, account, claim or thing 
    whatever relating to the trust; and 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    for any of those purposes, enter 
    into, give, execute and do such agreements, instruments of composition or 
    arrangement, releases and other things as to them seem expedient without 
    being responsible for any loss occasioned by any act or thing so done by 
    them in good faith. 
 
 
The 
    powers conferred by this section on two or more trustees acting together may 
    be exercised by a sole acting trustee when by the instrument of trust, if 
    any, a sole trustee is authorised to execute the trusts and powers thereof.
    
 
 
This 
    section applies only if and as far as a contrary intention is not expressed 
    in the instrument of trust, if any, and shall have effect subject to the 
    terms of that instrument and to the provisions therein contained. 

 
 
This 
    section applies only to trusts created after this Act comes into force.
    
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Power to several trustees of whom one disclaims or dies.—When 
    an authority to deal with the trust property is given to several trustees 
    and one of them disclaims or dies, the authority may be exercised by the 
    continuing trustees, unless from the terms of the instrument of trust it is 
    apparent that the authority is to be exercised by a number in excess of the 
    number of the remaining trustees.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Suspension of trustee’s powers by decree.—Where 
    a decree has been made in a suit for the execution of a trust, the trustee 
    must not exercise any of his powers except in conformity with such decree, 
    or with the sanction of the Court by which the decree has been made, or, 
    where an appeal against the decree is pending, of the appellate Court.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Suspension of trustee’s powers by decree.—Where 
    a decree has been made in a suit for the execution of a trust, the trustee 
    must not exercise any of his powers except in conformity with such decree, 
    or with the sanction of the Court by which the decree has been made, or, 
    where an appeal against the decree is pending, of the appellate Court.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Trustee cannot renounce after acceptance.—A 
    trustee who has accepted the trust cannot afterwards renounce it except 
<section><number>a</number> 
    with the permission of a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, or 
    (b) if the beneficiary is competent to contract, with his consent, or (c) by 
    virtue of a special power in the instrument of trust. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>47</number> 
    Trustee cannot delegate.—A 
    trustee cannot delegate his office or any of his duties either to a 
    co-trustee or to a stranger, unless 
<section><number>a</number> the instrument of trust so provides, 
    or (b) the delegation is in the regular course of business, or (c) the 
    delegation is necessary, or (d) the beneficiary, being competent to 
    contract, consents to the delegation.
 

    Explanation.—The 
    appointment of an attorney or proxy to do an act merely ministerial, and 
    involving no independent discretion is not a delegation within the meaning 
    of this section.
 
 

Illustrations
 

 
  


</section><section>
<number>a</number> A bequeaths 
      certain property to B and C on certain trusts to be executed 
      by them or the survivor of them or the assigns of such survivor. B 
      dies, C may bequeath the trust property to D and E 
      upon the trusts of A’s will. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A is a 
      trustee of certain property with power to sell the same. A may 
      employ an auctioneer to effect the sale. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A bequeaths to B 
      fifty houses let at monthly rents in trust to collect the rents and pay 
      them to C. B may employ a proper person to collect these 
      rents. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
No trustee can delegate 
      his powers and duties to another transtee and any agreement to do so would 
      be illegal and void and would not be covered by any of the exceptions in 
      section 47; H.E.H.: The Nizam’s Jewellery Trust (in re:), AIR 1980 
      SC 17.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>48</number> 
    Co-trustees cannot act singly.—When 
    there are more trustees than one, all must join in the execution of the 
    trust, except where the instrument of trust, otherwise provides.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Control of discretionary power.—Where 
    a discretionary power conferred on a trustee is not exercised reasonably and 
    in good faith, such power may be controlled by a principal Civil Court of 
    original jurisdiction. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Trustee may not charge for services.—In 
    the absence of express directions to the contrary contained in the 
    instrument of trust or of a contract to the contrary entered into with the 
    beneficiary or the Court at the time of accepting the trust, a trustee has 
    no right to remuneration for his trouble, skill and loss of time in 
    executing the trust. 
 
 
Nothing 
    in this section applies to any Official Trustee, Administrator-General, 
    Public Curator, or person holding a certificate of administration. 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Trustee may not use trust property for his own profit.—A 
    trustee may not use or deal with the trust property for his own profit or 
    for any other purpose unconnected with the trust. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Trustee for sale or his agent may not buy.—No 
    trustee whose duty it is to sell trust property, and no agent employed by 
    such trustee for the purpose of the sale, may, directly or indirectly, put 
    the same or any interest therein, on his own account or as agent for a third 
    person. 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Trustee may not buy beneficiary’s interest without permission.—No 
    trustee, and no person who has recently ceased to be a trustee, may, without 
    the permission of a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, buy or 
    become mortgagee or lessee of the trust property or any part thereof; and 
    such permission shall not be given unless the proposed purchase, mortgage or 
    lease is manifestly for the advantage of the beneficiary.  
 

    Trustee for purchase.—And 
    no trustee whose duty it is to buy or to obtain a mortgage or lease of 
    particular property for the beneficiary may buy it, or any part thereof, or 
    obtain a mortgage or lease of it, or any part thereof, for himself. 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Trustee may not buy beneficiary’s interest without permission.—No 
    trustee, and no person who has recently ceased to be a trustee, may, without 
    the permission of a principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, buy or 
    become mortgagee or lessee of the trust property or any part thereof; and 
    such permission shall not be given unless the proposed purchase, mortgage or 
    lease is manifestly for the advantage of the beneficiary.  
 

    Trustee for purchase.—And 
    no trustee whose duty it is to buy or to obtain a mortgage or lease of 
    particular property for the beneficiary may buy it, or any part thereof, or 
    obtain a mortgage or lease of it, or any part thereof, for himself. 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>54</number> 
    Co-trustees may not lend to one of themselves.—A 
    trustee or co-trustee whose duty it is to invest trust-money or mortgage or 
    personal security must not invest it on a mortgage by, or on the personal 
    security of, himself or one of his co-trustees. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Right to rents and profits.—The 
    beneficiary has, subject to the provisions of the instrument of trust, a 
    right to the rents and profits of the trust property. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>56</number> 
    Right to specific execution.—The 
    beneficiary is entitled to have the intention of the author of the trust 
    specifically executed to the extent of the beneficiary’s interests. 

 
 
Right 
    to transfer of possession.—And, 
    where there is only one beneficiary and he is competent to contract, or 
    where there are several beneficiaries and they are competent to contract and 
    all of one mind, he or they may require the trustee to transfer the trust 
    property to him or them, or to such person as he or they may direct. 

 
 
When 
    property has been transferred or bequeathed for the benefit of a married 
    woman, so that she shall not have power to deprive herself of her beneficial 
    interest, nothing in the second clause of this section applies to such 
    property during her marriage. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> Certain Government 
      securities are given to trustees upon trust to accumulate the interest 
      until A attains the age of 24, and then to transfer the gross 
      amount to him. A on attaining majority may, as the person 
      exclusively interested in the trust property, require the trustees to 
      transfer it immediately to him. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      Rs. 10,000 to trustees upon trust to purchase an annuity for B, who 
      has attained his majority and is otherwise competent to contract. B 
      may claim Rs. 10,000. 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A transfers 
      certain property to B and directs him to sell or invest it for the 
      benefit of C, who is competent to contract. C may elect to 
      take the property in its original character. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Right to inspect and take copies of instrument of trust accounts, etc.—The 
    beneficiary has a right, as against the trustee and all persons claiming 
    under him with notice of the trust, to inspect and take copies of the 
    instrument of trust, the documents of title relating solely to the trust 
    property, the accounts of the trust property, and the vouchers (if any) by 
    which they are supported, and the cases submitted and opinions taken by the 
    trustee for his guidance in the discharge of his duty. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Right to transfer beneficial interest.—The 
    beneficiary, if competent to contract may transfer his interest, but subject 
    to the law for the time being in force as to the circumstances and extent in 
    and to which he may dispose of such interest: 
 
 
Provided 
    that when property is transferred or bequeathed for the benefit of a married 
    woman, so that she shall not have power to deprive herself of her beneficial 
    interest, nothing in this section shall authorise her to transfer such 
    interest during her marriage. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Right to sue for execution of trust.—Where 
    no trustees are appointed or all the trustees die, disclaim or are 
    discharged, or where for any other reason the execution of a trust by the 
    trustee is or becomes impracticable, the beneficiary may institute a suit 
    for the execution of the trust, and the trust shall, so far as may be 
    possible, be executed by the Court until the appointment of a trustee or new 
    trustee. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Right to proper trustees.—The 
    beneficiary has a right (subject to the provisions of the instrument of 
    trust) that the trust property shall be properly protected and held and 
    administered by proper persons and by a proper number of such persons.
 

    Explanation I.—The 
    following are not proper persons within the meaning of this section:—
 
A person 
    domiciled abroad; an alien enemy; a person having an interest inconsistent 
    with that of the beneficiary; a person in insolvent circumstances; and, 
    unless the personal law of the beneficiary allows otherwise, a married woman 
    and a minor. 
 
 

    Explanation II.—When 
    the administration of the trust involves the receipt and custody of money, 
    the number of trustees should be two at least. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, one of 
      several beneficiaries, proves that B, the trustee, has improperly 
      disposed of part of the trust property, or that the property is in danger 
      from B’s being in insolvent circumstances; or that he is incapacitated 
      from acting, as trustee. A may obtain a receiver of the trust property.
      
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A bequeaths 
      certain jewels to B in trust for C. B dies during A’s 
      lifetime; than A dies, C is entitled to have the property 
      conveyed to a trustee for him. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A conveys 
      certain property to four trustees in trust for B. Three of the 
      trustees die. B may institute a suit to have three new trustees 
      appointed in the place of the deceased trustees. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A conveys 
      certain property to three trustees in trust for B. All the trustees 
      disclaim. B may institute a suit to have three trustees appointed in place 
      of the trustees so disclaiming. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> A, a trustee 
      for B, refuses to act, or goes to reside permanently out of 
1[India] 
      or is declared an insolvent, or compounds with his creditors, or suffers a 
      co-trustee to commit a breach of trust, B may institute a suit to 
      have A removed and a new trustee appointed in his room.  
</section>
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Right to compel to any act of duty.—The 
    beneficiary has a right that his trustee shall be compelled to perform any 
    particular act of his duty as such, and restrained from committing any 
    contemplated or probable breach of trust. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A contracts 
      with B to pay him monthly Rs. 100 for the benefit of C, B 
      writes and signs a letter declaring that he will hold in trust for C 
      the money so to be paid. A fails to pay the money in accordance 
      with his contract, C may compel B on a proper indemnity to 
      allow C to sue on the contract in B’s name. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A is trustee 
      of certain land, with a power to sell the same and pay the proceeds to 
      B and C equally. A is about to make an improvident sale 
      of the land. B may sue on behalf of himself and C for an 
      injunction to restrain A from making the sale. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Wrongful purchase by trustee.—Where 
    a trustee has wrongfully bought trust property, the beneficiary has a right 
    to have the property declared subject to the trust or re-transferred by the 
    trustee, if it remains in his hands unsold, or, if it has been bought from 
    him by any person with notice of the trust, by such person. But in such case 
    the beneficiary must repay the purchase-money paid by the trustee, with 
    interest, and such other expenses (if any) as he has properly incurred in 
    the preservation of the property; and the trustee or purchaser must 
<section><number>a</number> 
    account for the nett profits of the property, (b) be charged with an 
    occupation-rent, if he has been in actual possession of the property, and 
    (c) allow the beneficiary to deduct a proportionate part of the 
    purchase-money if the property has been deteriorated by the acts or 
    omissions of the trustee or purchaser. 
 
 
Nothing 
    in this section—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>    impairs the rights of lessees and 
    others who, before the institution of a suit to have the property declared 
    subject to the trust or re-transferred, have contracted in good faith with 
    the trustee or purchaser; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    entitles the beneficiary to have 
    the property declared subject to the trust or re-transferred where he, being 
    competent to contract, has himself, without coercion or undue influence 
    having been brought to bear on him, ratified the sale to the trustee with 
    full knowledge of the facts of the case and of his rights as against the 
    trustee. 
 
 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Following trust property into the hands of third persons.—Where 
    trust property comes into the hands of a third person inconsistently with 
    the trust, the beneficiary may require him to admit formally, or may 
    institute a suit for a declaration, that the property is comprised in the 
    trust. 
 
 
Into 
    that into which it has been converted.—Where 
    the trustee has disposed of trust property and the money or other property 
    which he has received therefor can be traced in his hands, or the hands of 
    his legal representative or legatee, the beneficiary has, in respect 
    thereof, rights as nearly as may be the same as his rights in respect of the 
    original trust property. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, a trustee 
      for B of Rs. 10,000, wrongfully invests the Rs. 10,000 in the 
      purchase of certain land, B is entitled to the land. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, a trustee, 
      wrongfully purchases land in his own name, partly with his own money, 
      partly with money subject to a trust for B. B is entitled to a 
      charge on the land for the amount of the trust money so misemployed.
      
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Saving of rights of certain transferees.—Nothing 
    in section 63 entitles the beneficiary to any right in respect of property 
    in the hands of— 
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a transferee, in good faith for 
    consideration without having notice of the trust, either when the 
    purchase-money was paid, or when the conveyance was executed, or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    a transferee for consideration 
    from such a transferee. 
 
 
A 
    judgment-creditor of the trustee attaching and purchasing trust property is 
    not a transferee for consideration within the meaning of this section.
    
 
 
Nothing 
    in section 63 applies to money, currency notes, and negotiable instruments 
    in the hands of a bona fide holder to whom they have passed in 
    circulation, or shall be deemed to affect the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 
    of 1872), section 108, or the liability of a person to whom a debt or charge 
    is transferred. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Acquisition by trustee of trust property wrongfully converted.—Where 
    a trustee wrongfully sells or otherwise transfers trust property and 
    afterwards himself becomes the owner of the property, the property again 
    becomes subject to the trust, notwithstanding any want of notice on the part 
    of intervening transferees in good faith for consideration. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Right in case of blended property.—Where 
    the trustee wrongfully mingles the trust property with his own, the 
    beneficiary is entitled to a charge on the whole fund for the amount due to 
    him. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    Wrongful employment by partner-trustee of trust property for partnership 
    purposes.—If 
    a partner, being a trustee, wrongfully employs trust property in the 
    business or on the account of the partnership, no other partner is liable 
    therefor in his personal capacity to the beneficiaries, unless he had notice 
    of the breach of trust.  
 
The 
    partners having such notice are jointly and severally liable for the breach 
    of trust. 
 
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A and B 
      are partners. A dies, having bequeathed all his property to B 
      in trust for Z, and appointed B his sole executor. B 
      instead of winding-up the affairs of the partnership, retains all the 
      assets in the business. Z may compel him, as partner, to account 
      for so much of the profits as are derived from A’s share of the 
      capital. B is also answerable to Z for the improper 
      employment of A’s assets. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, a trader, 
      bequeaths his property to B in trust for C, appoints B 
      his sole executor, and dies. B enters into partnership with X 
      and Y in the same trade, and employs A’s assets in the 
      partnership business. B gives an indemnity to X and Y 
      against the claims of C. Here X and Y are jointly 
      liable with B to C, as having knowingly become parties to 
      the breach of trust committed by B. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Liability of beneficiary joining in breach of trust.—Where 
    one of several beneficiaries—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    joins in committing breach of 
    trust, or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    knowingly obtains any advantage 
    therefrom, without the consent of the other beneficiaries, or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    becomes aware of a breach of 
    trust committed or intended to be committed, and either actually conceals 
    it, or does not within a reasonable time take proper steps to protect the 
    interests of the other beneficiaries, or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    has deceived the trustee, and 
    thereby induced him to commit a breach of trust, 
 
the other beneficiaries are entitled to 
    have all his beneficial interest impounded as against him and all who claim 
    under him (otherwise than as transferees for consideration without notice of 
    the breach) until the loss caused by the breach has been compensated. 

 
When 
    property has been transferred or bequeathed for the benefit of a married 
    woman, so that she shall not have power to deprive herself of her beneficial 
    interest, nothing in this section applies to such property during her 
    marriage.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Rights and liabilities of beneficiary’s transferee.—Every 
    person to whom a beneficiary transfers his interest has the rights, and is 
    subject to the liabilities, of the beneficiary in respect of such interest 
    at the date of the transfer. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Rights and liabilities of beneficiary’s transferee.—Every 
    person to whom a beneficiary transfers his interest has the rights, and is 
    subject to the liabilities, of the beneficiary in respect of such interest 
    at the date of the transfer. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Office how vacated.—The 
    office of a trustee is vacated by his death or by his discharge from his 
    office. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Discharge of trustee.—A 
    trustee may be discharged from his office only as follows:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    by the extinction of the trust;
    
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    by the completion of his duties 
    under the trust; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    by such means as may be 
    prescribed by the instrument of trust; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    by appointment under this Act of 
    a new trustee in his place; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    by consent of himself and the 
    beneficiary, or, where there are more beneficiaries than one, all the 
    beneficiaries being competent to contract; or  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    by the Court to which a petition 
    for his discharge is presented under this Act.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Petition to be discharged from trust.—Notwithstanding 
    the provisions of section 11, every trustee may apply by petition to a 
    principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction to be discharged from his 
    office, and, if the Court finds that there is sufficient reason for such 
    discharge, it may discharge him accordingly, and direct his costs to be paid 
    out of the trust property. But where there is no such reason, the Court 
    shall not discharge him, unless a proper person can be found to take his 
    place. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Appointment of new trustees on death, etc.—Whenever 
    any person appointed a trustee disclaims, or any trustee, either original or 
    substituted, dies, or is for a continuous period of six months, absent from
    

    1[India] or leaves
    

    1[India] for the 
    purpose of residing abroad, or is declared an insolvent, or desires to be 
    discharged from the trust, or refuses or becomes, in the opinion of a 
    principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction, unfit or personally 
    incapable to act in the trust, or accepts an inconsistent trust, a new 
    trustee may be appointed in his place by—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the person nominated for that 
    purpose by the instrument of trust (if any), or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if there be no such person, or no 
    such person able and wiling to act, the author of the trust if he be alive 
    and competent to contract, or the surviving or continuing trustees or 
    trustee for the time being, or legal representative of the last surviving 
    and continuing trustee, or (with the consent of the Court) the retiring 
    trustees, if they all retire simultaneously, or (with the like consent) the 
    last retiring trustee. 
 
 
Every 
    such appointment shall be by writing under the hand of the person making it.
    
 
On an 
    appointment of a new trustee, the number of trustees may be increased.
    
 
 
The 
    Official Trustee may, with his consent and by the order of the Court, be 
    appointed under this section, in any case in which only one trustee is to be 
    appointed and such trustee is to be the sole trustee. 
 
 
The 
    provisions of this section relative to a trustee who is dead include the 
    case of a person nominated trustee in a will, but dying before the testator, 
    and those relative to a continuing trustee include a refusing or retiring 
    trustee if willing to act in the execution of the power. 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>74</number> 
    Appointment by Court.—Wherever 
    any such vacancy or disqualification occurs and it is found impracticable to 
    appoint a new trustee under section 73, the beneficiary may, without 
    instituting a suit, apply by petition to a principal Civil Court of original 
    jurisdiction for the appointment of a trustee or a new trustee, and the 
    Court may appoint a trustee or a new trustee accordingly. 
 
 
Rule 
    for selecting new trustees.—In 
    appointing new trustees, the Court shall have regard 
<section><number>a</number> to the wishes of 
    the author of the trust as expressed in, or to be inferred from, the 
    instrument of trust; (b) to the wishes of the person, if any empowered to 
    appoint new trustees; (c) to the question whether the appointment will 
    promote or impede the execution of the trust; and (d) where there are more 
    beneficiaries than one, to the interests of all such beneficiaries. 

 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Vesting of trust property in new trustees.—Whenever 
    any new trustee is appointed under section 73 or section 74, all the trust 
    property for the time being vested in the surviving or continuing trustees 
    or trustee, or in the legal representative of any trustee, shall become 
    vested in such new trustee, either solely or jointly with the surviving or 
    continuing trustees or trustee, as the case may require. 
 
 
Powers 
    of new trustee.—Every 
    new trustee so appointed, and every trustee appointed by a Court either 
    before or after the passing of this Act shall have the same powers, 
    authorities and discretions, and shall in all respects act, as if he had 
    been originally nominated a trustee by the author of the trust. 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Survival of trust.—On 
    the death or discharge of one of several co-trustees, the trust survives and 
    the trust property passes to the others, unless the instrument of trust 
    expressly declares otherwise. 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Trust how extinguished.—A 
    trust is extinguished— 
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    when its purpose is completely 
    fulfilled; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    when its purpose becomes 
    unlawful; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    when the fulfilment of its 
    purpose becomes impossible by destruction of the trust property or 
    otherwise; or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    when the trust, being revocable, 
    is expressly revoked. 
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Revocation of trust.—A 
    trust created by will may be revoked at the pleasure of the testator. 

 
 
A trust 
    otherwise created can be revoked only— 
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where all the beneficiaries are 
    competent to contract—by their consent; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where the trust has been declared 
    by a non-testamentary instrument or by word of mouth—in exercise of a power 
    of revocation expressly reserved to the author, of the trust; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    where the trust is for the 
    payment of the debts of the author of the trust, and has not been 
    communicated to the creditors—at the pleasure of the author of the trust.
    
 
 
 

Illustration
 
A 
      conveys property to B in trust to sell the same and pay out of the 
      proceeds the claims of A’s creditors. A reserves no power of 
      revocation. If no communication has been made to the creditors, A 
      may revoke the trust. But if the creditors, are parties to the 
      arrangement, the trust cannot be revoked without their consent. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
In the absence of a 
      power of revocation being reserved in the deed of revocation, the new 
      trustee declared in the deed of revocation cannot be revoked by virtue of 
      the power of revocation, contained in the original deed of settlement; 
      Central Bank Executor &amp; Trustee Co. Ltd. v. Hormusji N. Madraswalla,
      AIR 1969 Bom 101.  


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Revocation not to defeat what trustees have duly done.—No 
    trust can be revoked by the author of the trust so as to defeat or prejudice 
    what the trustees may have duly done in execution of the trust. 

 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Where obligation in nature of trust is created.—An 
    obligation in the nature of a trust is created in the following cases.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>81</number> 
    Where it does not appears that transferor intended to dispose of beneficial 
    interest.—[Rep. 
    by the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act, 1988 (45 of 1988), sec. 7 (w.e.f
    19-5-1988)].  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>82</number> 
    Transfer to one for consideration paid by another.—[Rep. 
    by the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act, 1988 (45 of 1988), sec. 7 (w.e.f.
    19-5-1988).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Trust incapable of execution or executed without exhausting trust property.—Where 
    a trust is incapable of being executed, or where the trust is completely 
    executed without exhausting the trust property, the trustee, in the absence 
    of a direction to the contrary, must hold the trust property, or so much 
    thereof as is unexhausted, for the benefit of the author of the trust or his 
    legal representative.
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A conveys 
      land to B— 
 
 
           
      “upon trust”, and no trust is declared; or 

 
           “upon trust to be thereafter declared”, and no such declaration is ever 
      made; or
 
 
upon trusts that are too vague to be executed; or
 
 
upon trusts that become incapable of taking effect; or
 
 
“in 
      trust for C” and C renounces his interest under the trust.
 
 
In 
      each of these cases B holds the land for the benefit of A.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A transfers 
      Rs. 10,000 in the four per cents. to B, in trust to pay the 
      interest annually accruing due to C for her life. A dies. Then C 
      dies. B holds the fund for the benefit of A’s legal 
      representative.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A conveys 
      land to B upon trust to sell it and apply one moiety of the 
      proceeds for certain charitable purposes and the other for the maintenance 
      of the worship of an idol. B sells the land, but the charitable 
      purposes wholly fail, and the maintenance of the worship does not exhaust 
      the second moiety of the proceeds. B holds the first moiety and the 
      part unapplied of the second moiety for the benefit of A or his 
      legal representative. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A bequeaths 
      Rs. 10,000 to B, to be laid out in buying land to be conveyed for 
      purposes which either wholly or partially fail to take effect. B 
      holds for the benefit of A’s legal representative the undisposed of 
      interest in the money or land if purchased. 
 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Transfer for illegal purpose.—Where 
    the owner of property transfers it to another for an illegal purpose and 
    such purpose is not carried into execution, or the transferor is not as 
    guilty as the transferee, or the effect of permitting the transferee to 
    retain the property might be to defeat the provisions of any law, the 
    transferee must hold the property for the benefit of the transferor. 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Bequest for illegal purpose.—Where 
    a testator bequeaths certain property upon trust and the purpose of the 
    trust appears on the face of the will to be unlawful, or during the 
    testator’s lifetime the legatee agrees with him to apply the property for an 
    unlawful purpose, the legatee must hold the property for the benefit of the 
    testator’s legal representative. 
 
 

    Bequest of which revocation is prevented by coercion.—Where 
    property is bequeathed, and the revocation of the bequest is prevented by 
    coercion, the legatee must hold the property for the benefit of the 
    testator’s legal representative. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Transfer pursuant to rescindable contract.—Where 
    property is transferred in pursuance of contract which is liable to 
    rescission, or induced by fraud or mistake, the transferee must, on 
    receiving notice to that effect, hold the property for the benefit of the 
    transferor, subject to repayment by the latter of the consideration actually 
    paid. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Debtor becoming creditor’s representative.—Where 
    a debtor becomes the executor or other legal representative of his creditor, 
    he must hold the debt for the benefit of the persons interested therein.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Debtor becoming creditor’s representative.—Where 
    a debtor becomes the executor or other legal representative of his creditor, 
    he must hold the debt for the benefit of the persons interested therein.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>88</number> 
    Advantage gained by fiduciary.—Where 
    a trustee, executor, partner, agent, director of a company, legal adviser, 
    or other person bound in a fiduciary character to protect the interests of 
    another person, by availing himself of his character, gains for himself any 
    pecuniary advantage, or where any person so bound enters into any dealings 
    under circumstances in which his own interests are, or may be, adverse to 
    those of such other person, and thereby gains for himself a pecuniary 
    advantage, he must hold for the benefit of such other person the advantage 
    so gained.
 
 

Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, an 
      executor, buys, at an under-value from B, a legatee, his claim 
      under the will. B is ignorant of the value of the bequest. A 
      must hold for the benefit of B the difference between the price and 
      value. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, a trustee, 
      uses the trust property for the purpose of his own business. A 
      holds for the benefit of his beneficiary the profits arising from such 
      user. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A, a trustee, 
      retires from his trust in consideration of his successor paying him a sum 
      of money. A holds such money for the benefit of his beneficiary.
      
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A, a partner, 
      buys land in his own name with funds belonging to the partnership. A 
      holds such land for the benefit of the partnership. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> A, a partner, 
      employed on behalf of himself and his co-partners is negotiating the terms 
      of a lease, clandestinely stipulates with the lessor for payment to 
      himself of a lakh of rupees. A holds the lakh for the benefit of 
      the partnership. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> A and B 
      are partners. A dies. B instead of winding-up the affairs of 
      the partnership, retains all the assets in the business. B must 
      account to A’s legal representative for the profits arising from 
      A’s share of the capital. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> A, an agent 
      employed to obtain a lease for B, obtains the lease for himself. 
      A holds the lease for the benefit of B. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> A, a 
      guardian, buys up for himself incumbrances on his ward B’s estate 
      at an under-value. A holds for the benefit of B the 
      incumbrances so bought, and can only charge him with what he has actually 
      paid.  
  
 

      Comments
 
The agent employed to 
      purchase the property on behalf of his principal fraudulently got his name 
      entered in the sale certificate. The agent was holding the property in 
      trust on behalf of and for the principal, and the agent was under duty and 
      responsibility to make good the  unauthorised profits be derived in such 
      capacity to the principal; P.V. Sankara Kurup v. Leelavathy 
      Nambiar, AIR 1994 SC 2694. 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>89</number> 
    Advantage gained by exercise of undue influence.—Where, 
    by the exercise of undue influence, any advantage is gained in derogation of 
    the interests of another, the person gaining such advantage without 
    consideration, or with notice that such influence has been exercised, must 
    hold the advantage for the benefit of the person whose interests have been 
    so prejudiced. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>90</number> 
    Advantage gained by qualified owner.—Where 
    a tenant for life, co-owner, mortgagee, or other qualified owner of any 
    property, by availing himself of his position as such, gains an advantage in 
    derogation of the rights of the other persons interested in the property, or 
    where any such owner, as representing all persons interested in such 
    property, gains any advantage, he must hold, for the benefit of all persons 
    interested, the advantage so gained, but subject to repayment by such 
    persons of their due share of the expenses properly incurred, and to an 
    indemnity by the same persons against liabilities properly contracted, in 
    gaining such advantage.
 
 
 

Illustrations

 <section>
<number>a</number> A, tenant for 
      life of leasehold property, renews the lease in his own name and for his 
      own benefit. A holds the renewed lease for the benefit of all those 
      interested in the old lease. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A village 
      belongs to a Hindu family. A, one of its members, pays nazrana to 
      Government, and thereby procures his name to be entered as the inamdar of 
      the village. A holds the village for the benefit of himself and the 
      other members. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A mortgages 
      land to B, who enters into possession. B allows the 
      Government revenue to fall into arrear with a view to the land being put 
      up for sale, and his becoming himself the purchaser of it. The land is 
      accordingly sold to B. Subject to the repayment of the amount due 
      on the mortgage and of his expenses properly incurred as mortgagee, B 
      holds the land for the benefit of A. 
 
  
 

      Comments
 
In law, the advantages 
      obtained by the respondent, the qualified owner, must be held to be for 
      the benefit of the persons interested—the mortgagor-appellant; Namdev 
      Shripati Nale v. Bapu Ganapati Jagtan, 1997 (5) SCC 185.  
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>91</number> 
    Property acquired with notice of existing contract.—Where 
    a person acquires property with notice that another person has entered into 
    an existing contract affecting that property, of which specific performance 
    could be enforced, the former must hold that property for the benefit of the 
    latter to the extent necessary to give effect to the contract.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>92</number> 
    Purchase by person contracting to buy property to be held on trust.—Where 
    a person contracts to buy property to be held on trust for certain 
    beneficiaries and buys the property accordingly, he must hold the property 
    for their benefit to the extent necessary to give effect to the contract.
    
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>93</number> 
    Advantage secretly gained by one of several compounding creditors.—Where 
    creditors compound the debts due to them, and one of such creditors, by a 
    secret arrangement with the debtor, gains an undue advantage over his 
    co-creditors, he must hold, for the benefit of such creditors, the advantage 
    so gained. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>94</number> 
    Constructive trusts in cases not expressly provided for.—[Rep. 
    by the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act, 1988 (45 of 1988), sec. 7 (w.e.f.
    19-5-1988).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>95</number> 
    Obligor’s duties, liabilities and disabilities.—The 
    person holding property in accordance with any of the preceding sections of 
    this Chapter must, so far as may be, perform the same duties, and is 
    subject, so far as may be, to the same liabilities and disabilities, as if 
    he were a trustee of the property for the person for whose benefit he holds 
    it: 
 
 
Provided 
    that 
<section><number>a</number> where he rightfully cultivates the property or employs it in trade 
    or business, he is entitled to reasonable remuneration for his trouble, 
    skill and loss of time in such cultivation or employment; and (b) where he 
    holds the property by virtue of a contract with the person for whose benefit 
    he holds it, or with any one through whom such person claims, he may, 
    without the permission of the Court, buy or become lessee or mortgagee of 
    the property or any part thereof. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>95</number> 
    Obligor’s duties, liabilities and disabilities.—The 
    person holding property in accordance with any of the preceding sections of 
    this Chapter must, so far as may be, perform the same duties, and is 
    subject, so far as may be, to the same liabilities and disabilities, as if 
    he were a trustee of the property for the person for whose benefit he holds 
    it: 
 
 
Provided 
    that 
<section><number>a</number> where he rightfully cultivates the property or employs it in trade 
    or business, he is entitled to reasonable remuneration for his trouble, 
    skill and loss of time in such cultivation or employment; and (b) where he 
    holds the property by virtue of a contract with the person for whose benefit 
    he holds it, or with any one through whom such person claims, he may, 
    without the permission of the Court, buy or become lessee or mortgagee of 
    the property or any part thereof. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>96</number> 
    Saving of rights of bona fide purchasers.—Nothing 
    contained in this Chapter shall impair the rights of transferees in good 
    faith for consideration, or create an obligation in evasion of any law for 
    the time being in force. 
 
  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
THE SCHEDULE 

 
(See section 2) 
 
STATUTE
  
 
 
 
 
Year and Chapter
 
 
Short title
 
 
Extent of repeal

 
 
 
29 Car. II, c. 3
 
 
The Statute of Frauds
 
 
Sections 2, 8, 9, 10 and 11

 
 
  
 
  
 
  

 
 


 
 
 
Number and Year
 
 

 
 
Extent of Repeal

 
 
 
XXVIII of 1866
 
 
The Trustee's and Mortgagee's 
        Powers Act, 1866
 
 
Section 2, 3, 4, 5, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36 and 
        37.
 
In section [***] 43 the word 
        "trustee" whenever it occurs; and in section 43 the word "management or" 
        and "the trust-property or"

 
 
 
1 or 1833
 
 
[the Specific Relief Act, 1877
 
 
In Section 12 the first illustration.


 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 






 




<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   See 
    section 11 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872). tc 
    " 1. See section 11 of the Indian 
    Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   See now 
    the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 31 
    of 1920, sec. 2 and Sch. 1. tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 31 of 1920, sec. 2 and 
    Sch. 1."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “Provincial Government” tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
    “Provincial Government”"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “Government of India”. tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for 
    “Government of India”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Added by Act 18 
    of 1934, sec. 2. tc 
    " 4. Added by Act 18 of 1934, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937 for “charged by the Imperial Parliament on the revenues of India”. tc 
    " 5. Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for “charged 
    by the Imperial Parliament on the revenues of India”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950 for “Imperial Parliament”. tc 
    " 6. Subs. by the A.O. 1950 for 
    “Imperial Parliament”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
    1948. tc 
    " 7. Ins. by the A.O. 1948."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1948, for “Federation”. tc 
    " 1. Subs. by the A.O. 1948, for 
    “Federation”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   The words 
    “Governor General in Council” and “Province” stand unmodified vide 
    the A.O. 1950. tc 
    " 2. The words “Governor General in 
    Council” and “Province” stand unmodified vide the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Ins. by Act 1 of 
    1916, sec. 2. tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 1 of 1916, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950 for “which may at any time hereafter be”. tc 
    " 4. Subs. by the A.O. 1950 for “which 
    may at any time hereafter be”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
    1950. tc 
    " 5. Ins. by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
    1937. tc 
    " 6. Ins. by the A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950 for “may be”. tc 
    " 7. Subs. by the A.O. 1950 for “may 
    be”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Ins. by Act 1 of 
    1916, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 7-1-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   See now 
    the Land Improvement Loans Act, 1883 (19 of 1883). tc 
    " 5. See now the Land Improvement 
    Loans Act, 1883 (19 of 1883)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   The words “to 
    Government” successively amended by the A.O. 1937 and the A.O. 1950 to read 
    as above.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937 for “the Government”. tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for “the 
    Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   The words “to 
    Government” successively amended by the A.O. 1937 and the A.O. 1950 to read 
    as above.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937 for “the Government”. tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for “the 
    Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Second paragraph 
    repealed by Act 12 of 1891, sec. 2 and Sch. 1, Pt 1.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950 for “the Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950 for “the Provinces”. tc 
    " 1. Subs. by the A.O. 1950 for “the 
    Provinces”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Rep. in its 
    application to India.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Repealed.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   The figures 
    “39”, and by implication the word “and”, rep. by Act 12 of 1891, sec. 2 and 
    Sch. 1, Pt. 1.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>