<act><title>THE RECOGNITION OF ZOO RULES, 1992

</title> 

   


  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Recognition of Zoo Rules, 1992. 


 </section><section>      
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 


 <section>
<number>a</number> “Act”
means the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972); 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Enclosure” means any
accommodation provided for zoo animals; 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number> “Enclosure barrier” means a
physical barrier to contain an animal within an enclosure; 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>
“Endangered species” means species included in Schedule I and Schedule II of
the Act except black buck];
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>dd</number>
'critically endangered species' means an endangered species other than
tiger, asiatic lion and panther whose total number in all the zoos in the
country put together does not exceed 200]; 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number> “Form” means form set forth
in Appendix A to these rules; 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number> “Performing purposes” means
any effort to force the animal to carry out unnatural act including performance
of circus tricks; 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ff</number>
‘Rescue Centre’ means an establishment for the care of animals
specified in the Schedules to the Act and not open for exhibition to the
public;] 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number> “Stand-of barrier” means a
physical barrier set back from the outer edge of an enclosure barrier; 


 </section><section>
<number>h</number> “Zoo operator” means the
person who has ultimate control over the affairs of the zoo provided that— 


 </section><section>
 <number>i</number> 
in the case of a firm or other association of individuals, any one of the
individual partners or members thereof shall be deemed to be the zoo operator; 


 <subsection><number>ii</number>
in the case of a company, any director, manager, secretary or other
officer, who is in-charge of and responsible to the company for the affairs of
the zoo shall be deemed to be the zoo operator;
   


 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
in the case of a zoo owned or controlled by the Central Government or any
State Government, or any local authority, the person or persons appointed to
manage the affairs of the zoo by the Central Government, the State Government or
the local authority, as the case may be shall be deemed to be the zoo operator.





</subsection></section></article> 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Application for recognition.—An
application under section 38H of the Act for recognition of a zoo shall be made
to the Central Zoo Authority in Form A.
</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>4</number>
Fee for application.—(a) there shall
be paid in respect of every application under rule 3 a fee of five hundred
rupees.
</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>5</number>
Documents to be filed alongwith the application and particulars it should
contain.—Every
application shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee and shall contain clear
particulars as to the matters specified in Form A. 


</article> 

  
  


 <article><number>6</number>
Power to make inquiries and call for information.—Before
granting recognition to a zoo under section 38H of the Act, the Central Zoo
Authority may make such inquiries and require such further information to be
furnished, as it deems necessary, relating to the information furnished by the
zoo in its application in Form A. 


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>7</number>
Form of recognition.—The recognition
granted to a zoo shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:— 


 <section>
<number>a</number> that the recognition unless
granted on a permanent basis, shall be for such period not less than one year as
may be specified in the recognition; 


 </section><section> <number>b</number>
that the zoo shall comply with such standards and norms as are or may be
prescribed or imposed under the provisions of the Act and these rules from time
to time. 


</section></article> 

  
  


 <article><number>8</number>
Renewal of recognition.—
<section><number>a</number> Three months before the expiry of the
period of recognition, a recognised zoo desirous of renewal of such recognition
may make an application to the Central Zoo Authority in Form A. 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
The provisions of rule 3, rule 4, rule 5, rule 6 and rule 7 shall apply in
relation to renewal of recognition as they apply in relation to grant of
recognition except that, the fee payable in respect of an application for
renewal of recognition shall be two hundred rupees. 


</section></article> 

   


   


[9.
For the purposes of deciding standards and norms for recognition of zoos and
monitoring and evaluating their performance, the zoos, on the basis of number of
animals, species, endangered species and number of animals of endangered species
exhibited, shall be classified into four categories as specified below:—
  
 
 
 
 Category of the zoo
 Large
 Medium
 Small
 Mini

 
 Number of animal exhibited
 More than 750
 500-750
 200-499
 Less than 200

 
 Number of species exhibited
 More than 75
 50-75
 20-49
 Less than 20

 
 Number of endangered species
        exhibited
 More than 15
 10-15
 5-9
  -

 
 Number of animals of 
        endangered species exhibited
 More than 150
 100-149
 50-99
  -



  

 
 <article><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 520(E),
  dated 10th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 11-7-2001).
</article>

 

  
   

 <article> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>9A</number> Central Zoo Auhority may allow a mini zoo to keep 
animals of endangered species subject to the condition prescribed by it with 
regard to health, care, facilities and upkeep of animals including deployment of 
supervisory level staff including veterinarian].

</article> 

   

   

 <article><number>10</number> Standards and norms 
subject to which recognition under section 38H of the Act shall be 
granted.—The Central Zoo Authority 
shall grant recognition with due regard to the interests of protection and 
conservation of wild life, and such standards, norms and other matters as are 
specified below:  
 GENERAL 

 <section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>1</number> The primary objective 
to operate the zoo shall be conservation of wildlife and no zoo shall allow any 
activity that is not consistent with the well being of the wild animals.] 

 </section><section><number>2</number> No zoo shall acquire 
any animal in violation of the Act or rules made thereunder. 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> No zoo shall allow 
any animal to be subjected to the cruelties prohibited under the Prevention of 
Cruelty of Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 1960);  
 </section><section><number>3B</number> Animals pertaining to 
species whose performance has been banned under the Prevention of Cruelty to 
Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 1960), shall not be transported from place to 
place:  
 Provided that such animals 
may be permanently kept by circuses at a place of their choice with suitable 
housing facility.]  
 </section><section><number>4</number> No zoo shall use any 
animal, other than the elephant in plains and yak in hilly areas for riding 
purposes or draughting any vehicle.  
 </section><section><number>5</number> No zoo shall keep any 
animal chained or tethered unless doing so is essential for its own well 
being.  
 </section><section><number>6</number> No zoo shall exhibit 
any animal that is seriously sick, injured or infirm. 

 </section><section><number>7</number> Each zoo 
shall be closed to visitors at least once a week.  
 </section><section><number>8</number> Each zoo 
shall be encompassed by a perimeter wall at least two metres high from the 
ground level. The existing zoos in the nature of safaries and deer parks will 
continue to have chain link fence of appropriate design and dimensions. 

 </section><section><number>9</number> The zoo 
operators shall provide a clean and healthy environment in the zoo by planting 
trees, creating green belts and providing lawns and flower beds etc. 

 </section><section><number>10</number> The 
built up area in any zoo shall not exceed twenty-five per cent of the total area 
of the zoo. The built up area includes administrative buildings, stores, 
hospitals, restaurants, kiosks and visitor rest sheds etc., animal houses and 
‘pucca’ roads.  
 </section><section><number>11</number> No zoo 
shall have the residential complexes for the staff within the main campus of the 
zoo. Such complex, if any, shall be separated from the main campus of the zoo by 
a boundary wall with a minimum height of two metres from the ground 
level.
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>11A</number> Every zoo shall 
prepare a collection plan of animals to be housed and displayed in the zoo, 
keeping due regard to the availability of land, water, electricity and climatic 
condition of the area.  
 </section><section><number>11B</number> Rescue centres may 
accept wild animals brought to them under intimation to the Chief Wild Life 
Warden.]  
 Administrative 
and Staffing Pattern
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> Every zoo shall have 
one full-time officer in-charge of the zoo. The said officer shall be delegated 
adequate administrative and financial powers to purchase feed and medicine and carry 
out emergency repair of animal enclosures, as may be necessary for proper upkeep 
and care of zoo animals.  
 </section><section><number>13</number> Every 
large, medium and small zoo shall an official with masters degree in Wildlife 
Science/Zoology as a full-time curator solely responsibie for looking after the 
upkeep of animals and maintenance of animal enclosures]. 

 </section><section><number>14</number> Each 
large zoo shall have at least two full-time veterinarians and medium and small 
zoo shall have at least one full-time veterinarian. The mini zoo may at least 
have arrangement with any outside veterinarian for visiting the zoo every day to 
look after the animals.  
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>14A</number> Every zoo shall 
have veterinarians of following description and educational qualifications, 
namely:—  
 Category
Senior Veterinarian
 Junior Veterinarian  
 Large Zoo

1
1  
 Medium Zoo 

1
0  
 Small Zoo
 
1
0 

 Senior 
Veterinarian: Should have minimum 
educational qualification of B.V.Sc and AH or equivalent with a minimum of 5 
years experience of working in a zoo recognised by the Central Zoo Authority, 
and should be duly registered with the State Veterinary Council or Veterinary 
Council of India.  
 Junior 
Veterinarian: Should have minimum 
educational qualification of B.V.Sc and AH with diploma in Zoo and Wildlife 
Animals Healthcare Management or masters degree in Wildlife Disease and 
Management from a recognised University, and should be duly registered with the 
State Veterinary Council or Veterinary Council of India.] 

 </section><section><number>15</number> All animal enclosures 
in a zoo shall be so designed as to fully ensure the safety of animals, 
caretakers and the visitors.
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>16</number> All animal 
enclosures in a zoo shall be so designed as to meet the biological requirements 
of the animals housed therein. The enclosures shall be of such size as to ensure 
that the animals get space for their free movement and exercise and the animals 
within herds and groups are not unduly dominated by individuals. In case of 
species, which cannot be kept in groups due to behavioural or biological 
reasons, separate enclosures shall be provided for each animal. The enclosures 
shall not be smaller than the dimensions given in Appendix II of these rules. 
These dimensions will not apply to circuses. However, when not in transit the 
circuses shall provide the animals space for movement and exercise.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>16A</number> Zoo operators shall 
provide appropriate screening between the adjacent enclosures to safeguard 
against the animals getting exited or stressed because of the visibility of 
animals in other enclosures.]  
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>17</number> The zoo operators 
shall endeavour to simulate the conditions of the natural habitat of the animal 
in the enclosures as closely as possible. Planting of appropriate species of 
trees for providing shade and shelters, which merge in the overall environment 
of the enclosures, shall also be provided. Depending upon the availability of 
land and technical feasibility, moat shall be provided as enclosure 
barrier.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum><number>18</number> Every mammal in the 
zoo shall be provided food inside a feeding cell/retiring cubicle or feeding 
kraal. The number and size of feeding cells or kraals will also be such that the 
dominant animals do not deprive other animals from getting adequate food. The 
endangered mammalian species shall be provided individual feeding cell or night 
shelters of the dimensions as specified in Appendix I to these rules. Each 
cubicle or cell shall have resting, feeding, drinking water and exercising 
facilities according to the biological needs of the species. Proper ventilation 
and lighting for the comfort and well being of animals shall be provided in each 
cell or cubicle or enclosure. These dimensions shall not apply to circuses in 
transit.]  
 </section><section><number>19</number> Proper arrangement of 
drainage of excess of water and arrangements for removal of excreta and residual 
water from each cell/cubicle/enclosure shall be made. 

 </section><section><number>20</number> Designing of any new 
enclosure for endangered species shall be finalised <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[with the approveal of] 
with the Central Zoo Authority.  
 Hygiene, Feeding and Upkeep 

 </section><section><number>21</number> Every zoo shall 
ensure timely supply of wholesome and unadulterated food in sufficient quantity 
to each animal according to the requirement of the individual animals, so that 
no animal remains undernourished.  
 </section><section><number>22</number> Every zoo shall 
provide for a proper waste disposal system for treating both the solid and 
liquid wastes generated in the zoos.  
 </section><section><number>23</number> All left over food 
items, animal excreta and rubbish shall be removed from each enclosure regularly 
and disposed of in a manner congenial to the general cleanliness of the 
zoo.  
 </section><section><number>24</number> The zoo operators 
shall make available round the clock supply of potable water for drinking 
purposes in each cell/enclosure/cubicle.  
 </section><section><number>25</number> Periodic application 
of disinfectants in each enclosure shall be made according to the directions of 
the authorised veterinary officer of the zoo.  
 Animal Care, Health and 
Treatment  
 </section><section><number>26</number> The animals shall be 
handled only by the staff having experience and training in handling the 
individual animals. Every care shall be taken to avoid discomfort, behavioural 
stress or physical harm to any animal.  
 </section><section><number>27</number> The condition and 
health of all animals in the zoo shall be checked everyday by the person 
in-charge of their care. If any animal is found sick, injured, or unduly 
stressed the matter shall be reported to the veterinary officer for providing 
treatment expeditiously.  
 </section><section><number>28</number> Routine examination 
including parasite checks shall be carried out regularly and preventive 
medicines including vaccination be administered at such intervals as may be 
decided by the authorised veterinary officers.  
 </section><section><number>29</number> The zoo operators 
shall arrange for medical check-ups of the staff responsible for upkeep of 
animals at least once in very six months to ensure that they do not have 
infections of such diseases that can infect the zoo animals. 

 </section><section><number>30</number> Each zoo shall 
maintain animal history sheets and treatment cards in respect of each animal of 
endangered species.  
 Veterinary Facilities 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>31</number> Every large and 
medium zoo shall have a full-fledged veterinary unit with basic diagnostic 
facilities, comprehensive range of drugs and a reference library on animal 
health care and upkeep. Each veterinary unit shall have isolation and quarantine 
wards to take care of newly arriving animals and sick animals so to minimize the 
chances of infections spreading to other animals of the zoo.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>31A</number> Every zoo operator 
shall provide one qualified lab assistant/compounder for assisting the 
veterinarian in health care of the zoo animals].  
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>32</number> Every zoo shall have 
facilities for restraining and handling wild animals.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>33</number> The small and mini 
zoos where full-fledged veterinary unit is not available shall have at least a 
treatment room in the premises of the zoo where routine examination of animals 
can be undertaken and immediate treatment can be provided.] 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>34</number> Any animal dies in a 
zoo shall be subjected to a detailed post-mortem operation by a Veterinarian 
registered with State Veterinary Council or Veterinary Council of India and the 
findings of such operation shall be recorded and maintained for period of at 
least six years.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>35</number> Each zoo shall have 
proper facility for disposal of carcasses without affecting the hydience of the 
zoo. However, carcasses of large cats shall be disposed of only by burning in 
presence of director or an officer not below the rank of a curator duly 
authorised by the director.]  
 Breeding of 
Animals
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>36</number> Every zoo shall keep 
in its collection only such number of animals and such species for which 
appropriate housing facility exists. The zoo operators shall be responsible for 
ensuring that the number of animals of any species does not go beyond the 
holding capacity of the enclosures available in the zoo and housing standards 
are not compromised for keeping the excessive numbers.] 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>37</number> No animal shall be 
kept without a mate for a period exceeding one year unless there is a valid 
reason for doing so or the animal has already passed its prime and is of no use 
for breeding purposes. In the event of a zoo failing to find a mate for any 
single animal within this period, the animal shall be shifted to some other 
place according to the directions of the Central Zoo Authority]. 

 </section><section><number>38</number> No zoo shall be 
allowed to acquire a single animal of any variety except when doing so is 
essential either for finding a mate for the single animal housed in the said zoo 
or for exchange of blood in a captive breeding group. 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>39</number> Every zoo shall 
participate in planned breeding programme of endangered species as approved by 
the Central Zoo Authority in consultation with the Chief Wild Life Warden of the 
State. For this purpose, the zoo operator shall exchange animals between zoos, 
by way of breeding loans, gifts and the like as per the directions of the 
Central Zoo Authority.]  
 </section><section><number>40</number> To safeguard against 
uncontrolled growth in the population of prolifically breeding animals, every 
zoo shall implement appropriate population control measures like separation of 
sexes, sterilization vasectomy, tubectomy and implanting of pallets etc. 

 </section><section><number>41</number> No zoo shall permit 
hybridization either between different species of animals or different races of 
the same species of animals.  
 Maintenance of Records and Submission 
of Inventory to the Central Zoo Authority 

 </section><section><number>42</number> Every zoo shall keep 
a record of the birth acquisitions, sales, disposals and deaths of all animals. 
The inventory of the animals housed in each zoo as on 31st March of every year 
shall be submitted to the Central Zoo Authority by 30th April of the same 
year.  
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>43</number> Every zoo shall also 
submit a brief summary of the death of animals in the zoo for every financial 
year, alongwith the reasons of death identified on the basis of post-mortem 
reports and other diagnostic tests, by 30th April of the following year. In case 
of death of critically endangered species, a report alongwith details specified 
above shall be submitted to Central Zoo Authority within twenty-four hours. 

 </section><section><number>44</number> Every zoo shall 
submit an annual report of the activities of the zoo in respect of each 
financial year to the Central Zoo Authority. With respect to mini zoos, a 
consolidated report may be submitted by the Chief Wild Life Warden of the 
respective State/U.T.]  
 education and research 

 </section><section><number>45</number> Every enclosure in a 
zoo shall bear a sign board displaying scientific information regarding the 
animals exhibited in it.  
 </section><section><number>46</number> Every zoo shall 
publish leaflets, brochures and guidebooks and make the same available to the 
visitors, either free of cost or at a reasonable
price.  
 </section><section><number>47</number> Every large and 
medium zoo shall make arrangements for recording the detailed observations about 
the biological behaviour, population dynamics and veterinary care of the animals 
exhibited as per directions of the Central Zoo Authority so that a detailed 
database could be developed. The database shall be exchanged with other zoos as 
well as the Central Zoo Authority.  
 Visitor Facilities 

 </section><section><number>48</number> The zoo operators 
shall provide adequate civic facilities like toilets, visitor sheds, and 
drinking water points at convenient places in the zoo for visitors. 

 </section><section><number>49</number> First-aid equipments 
including anti-venom shall be readily available in the premises of the zoo. 

 </section><section><number>50</number> Arrangements shall be 
made to provide access to the zoo to disabled visitors including those in the 
wheel chair.  
 Development and Planning 

 </section><section><number>51</number> Each zoo shall 
prepare a long-term master plan for its development. The zoo shall also prepare 
a management plan giving details of the proposal and activities of development 
for next six years. The copies of the said plans shall be sent to the Central 
Zoo Authority.  
   
 












</section></article> 

   

   

 <article><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>10A</number> 
Applicability of rule 10 in case of circuses and rescue centres.—
<section><number>1</number> In case 
of grant of recognition to circuses under rule 10, the provisions of clauses 
(8), (9), (10), (11), (17), (46), (47) and (51) thereof shall not apply. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of grant of 
recognition of rescue centres under rule 10, the provisions of clauses (10), 
(38), (46) and (51) thereof shall not apply.]
   










</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 106(E), dated 6th February, 2004 (w.e.f. 9-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 520(E), dated 10th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 11-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 106(E), dated 6th February, 2004 (w.e.f. 9-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 520(E), dated 
10th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 11-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 106(E), dated 6th February, 2004 (w.e.f. 9-2-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 520(E), 
dated 10th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 11-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 520(E), 
dated 10th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 11-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 106(E), dated 6th February, 2004 (w.e.f. 9-2-2004).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>