<act><title>


The Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—This Act may be called the 
    Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act “western medical science” means the western methods of Allopathic 
    medicine, Obstetrics and Surgery, but does not include the Homeopathic or 
    Ayurvedic or Unani system of medicine 

    1[and “States” means 
    all 

    2[the territories 
    which immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised] within Part 
    A States and Part C States].—In 
    this Act “western medical science” means the western methods of Allopathic 
    medicine, Obstetrics and Surgery, but does not include the Homeopathic or 
    Ayurvedic or Unani system of medicine 

    2[and “States” means 
    all 

    3[the territories 
    which immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised] within Part 
    A States and Part C States]."
 
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Right to confer degrees, etc.—The 
    right of conferring, granting or issuing in the 

    1[States] degrees, 
    diplomas, licences, certificates or other documents stating or implying that 
    the holder, grantee or recipient thereof is qualified to practise western 
    medical science, shall be exercisable only by the authorities specified in 
    the Schedule, and by such other authority as the 

    2[State Government] 
    may, by notification in the 

    3[Official Gazette], 
    and subject to such conditions and restrictions as it thinks fit to impose, 
    authorise in this behalf.—The 
    right of conferring, granting or issuing in the 

    4[States] degrees, 
    diplomas, licences, certificates or other documents stating or implying that 
    the holder, grantee or recipient thereof is qualified to practise western 
    medical science, shall be exercisable only by the authorities specified in 
    the Schedule, and by such other authority as the 

    5[State Government] 
    may, by notification in the 

    6[Official Gazette], 
    and subject to such conditions and restrictions as it thinks fit to impose, 
    authorise in this behalf." 
 
 

 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Prohibition of unauthorised conferment of degrees, etc.—Save 
    as provided by section 3, no person in the 

    1[States] shall 
    confer, grant, or issue, or hold himself out as entitled to confer, grant, 
    or issue any degree, diploma, licence, certificate or other document stating 
    or implying that the holder, grantee or recipient is qualified to practise 
    western medical science.—Save 
    as provided by section 3, no person in the 

    1[States] shall 
    confer, grant, or issue, or hold himself out as entitled to confer, grant, 
    or issue any degree, diploma, licence, certificate or other document stating 
    or implying that the holder, grantee or recipient is qualified to practise 
    western medical science." 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Contravention of section 4.—Whoever 
    contravenes the provisions of section 4 shall be punishable with fine which 
    may extend to one thousand rupees; and, if the person so contravening is an 
    association, every member of such association who knowingly and wilfully 
    authorises or permits the contravention, shall be punishable with fine which 
    may extend to five hundred rupees.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Penalty 
    for falsely assuming or using medical titles.—Whoever 
    voluntarily and falsely assumes, or uses any title or description or any 
    addition to his name implying that he holds a degree, diploma, licence or 
    certificate conferred, granted or issued by any authority referred to in 
    section 3, or recognised by the General Council of Medical Education of the 
    United Kingdom, or that he is qualified to practise western medical science, 
    shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty 
    rupees, or, if he subsequently commits, and is convicted of, an offence 
    punishable under this section, with fine which may extend to five hundred 
    rupees:
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall apply to the use by any person of any title, 
    description, or addition which, prior to the commencement of this Act, he 
    used in virtue of any degree, diploma, licence or certificate conferred 
    upon, or granted, or issued to him. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—No 
    Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act, except 
    upon complaint made by order of the 

    1[State Government], 
    or upon complaint made, with the previous sanction of the 

    1[State Government], 
    by a Council of Medical Registration established by any enactment for the 
    time being in force in the 

    2[State].—No 
    Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act, except 
    upon complaint made by order of the 

    2[State Government], 
    or upon complaint made, with the previous sanction of the 

    2[State Government], 
    by a Council of Medical Registration established by any enactment for the 
    time being in force in the 

    3[State]." 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Jurisdiction of Magistrates.—No 
    Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act. 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916
 

 
 

 
 



Schedule
 


(See section 3)
 


             1.  Every University 
    established by 
1[a 
    Central Act].
 


             2.  The State Medical Faculty in 
    Bengal.
 


             3.  The College of Physicians and 
    Surgeons of Bombay.
 


             4.  The Board of Examiners, 
    Medical College, Madras.
 


 
 


-------------------------
 


      1.    Subs. by 
    the A.O. 1950, for “an Act of the Central Legislature”. 
 


-------------------------
 


 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>