<act><tid>1685788</tid>
<title>THE LIGHTHOUSE ACT, <year>1927</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>1927</year>
[ 21st September, <year>1927</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the provision, 
maintenance and control of lighthouses by the Government in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
India].





<article><tid>772794</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1299002</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Lighthouse Act, <year>1927</year>

</section>

<section><tid>140928</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1801465</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>397615</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

<section><tid>721740</tid>
<number>b</number>" district" means an area defined as a district for the 
purposes of this Act under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1096608</tid>
<number>c</number>" general lighthouse" means any lighthouse which the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, declare to be a general lighthouse for the 
purposes of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>669123</tid>
<number>d</number>" lighthouse" includes any light- vessel, fog- signal, 
buoy, beacon, or any mark, sign or apparatus exhibited 
or used for the guidance of ships;

</section>

<section><tid>1407403</tid>
<number>e</number>" local lighthouse" means any lighthouse which is not a 
general lighthouse;
Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f.  
  1. 10. <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>346</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" British India". 
2. The words" the Provinces of" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Omitted by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>). 
4. The words" except Part B States" omitted by Act 18 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2. 
5.  1st April, <year>1929</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1929</year>, Pt. I, p. 96. 
6. Cl. (a) omitted by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1204201</tid>
<number>f</number>" local lighthouse authority" means a State Government, 
local authority or other person having the 
superintendence and management of a local lighthouse;

</section>

<section><tid>879934</tid>
<number>g</number>" owner" includes any part- owner, charterer, or mortgagee 
in possession and any agent to whom a ship is 
consigned;

</section>

<section><tid>594995</tid>
<number>h</number>" port" means any port, as defined in the Indian Ports 
Act, <year>1908</year> (15 of <year>1908</year>), to which that Act extends; 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>945816</tid>
<number>hh</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" proper officer", in relation to any functions to be 
performed under this Act, means the officer of Customs 
who is assigned those functions by the Central Board of 
Excise and Customs constituted under the Central Boards 
of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>), and includes any 
person appointed by the Central Government to discharge 
the functions of a proper officer under this Act;]

</section>

<section><tid>1438113</tid>
<number>hha</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" ship" includes a sailing vessel;]

<subsection><tid>1538241</tid>
<number>i</number>words and expressions used in this Act and not otherwise 
defined have the same meanings respectively as in the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Merchant shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>)].



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1708342</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appointment of officers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette,--
<section><tid>553258</tid>
<number>a</number>define areas to be district for the purposes of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1771918</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> appoint a person to be the Director of Lighthouses 
and Lightships in each district;

</section>

<section><tid>1189879</tid>
<number>c</number>appoint persons to be Deputy Directors- General of 
Lighthouses and Lightships; and

</section>

<section><tid>743298</tid>
<number>d</number>appoint a person to be the Director- General of 
Lighthouses and Lightships.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>878639</tid>
<number> 4</number> Advisory Committees.
<section><tid>1020547</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall appoint  
a Central Advisory Committee and shall consult it in regard to--

<subsection><tid>1641873</tid>
<number>a</number>the erection or position of lighthouses or of any works 
appertaining thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518098</tid>
<number>b</number>additions to, or the alteration or removal of, 
lighthouses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>922252</tid>
<number>c</number>the variation of the character of any lighthouse or of 
the mode of use thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>70993</tid>
<number>d</number>the cost of any proposals relating to lighthouses; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>534944</tid>
<number>e</number>the making or alteration of any rules or rates of dues 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>357864</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, if it thinks fit, appoint an 
Advisory Committee for any district for the purpose of advising in 
regard to any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) in so far as 
the interests of the district are affected thereby.

</section>

<section><tid>287395</tid>
<number>3</number>Advisory Committees shall consist of persons representing 
interests affected by this Act or having special knowledge of the 
subject- matter thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>339922</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> No act or proceeding of the Advisory Committee shall be 
invalidated merely by reason of--

<subsection><tid>1527027</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in constitution of, the 
Advisory Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1227242</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in appointment of a person acting as a member 
of the Advisory Committee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>862709</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Advisory 
Committee not affecting the merits of the case.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>347</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" and" omitted by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for cls. (b), (c) and (d)  (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>). 
5. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


GENERAL LIGHTHOUSES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1145627</tid>
<number> 5</number> Management of general lighthouses by the Central Government 
and delegation of management.
<section><tid>346278</tid>
<number>1</number>The superintendence and management  
of all general lighthouses are vested in the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1716782</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may require any local lighthouse 
authority to undertake the superintendence and management of any 
general lighthouse situated in or adjacent to the local limits within 
which the authority exercises its powers, and shall pay to the 
authority such sums to defray the cost of superintendence and 
management as the Central Government may determine.
LOCAL LIGHTHOUSES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>31197</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to inspect local lighthouses.
<section><tid>1373702</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Director-  
General of Lighthouses and Lightships] may, at any time, and any 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Director or Deputy Director- General of Lighthouses and Lightships] 
may, if authorised in this behalf by a general or special order in 
writing of the Central Government, enter upon and inspect any local 
lighthouse and make such inquireis in respect thereof or of the 
management thereof as he thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1258371</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person having the charge of, or concerned in the 
management of, any lighthouse shall be bound to furnish to any officer 
authorised by or under sub- section (1) to inspect the lighthouse all 
such information regarding the same as the officer may require.

</section>

<section><tid>1326128</tid>
<number>3</number>Every local lighthouse authority shall furnish to the Central 
Government all such returns and other information in respect of the 
lighthouses under its supervision and management, or of any of them, 
as the Central Government may require.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1277356</tid>
<number> 7</number> Control of local lighthouses by the Central Government.
<section><tid>836760</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If, after an inspection under section 6 or such other inquiry as it 
thinks fit, the Central Government is satisfied that a direction under 
this sub- section is necessary or expedient for the safety, or 
otherwise in the interests, of shipping, it may direct any local 
lighthouse authority--

<subsection><tid>1210361</tid>
<number>a</number>to remove or discontinue or to refrain from moving or 
discontinuing any lighthouse under its superintendence 
and management or to make or refrain from making any 
variation in the character or mode of use of any such 
lighthouse, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1971163</tid>
<number>b</number>to erect, place or maintain, or to refrain from 
erecting, placing or maintaining, any lighthouse within 
the local limits within which the local lighthouse 
authority exercises its powers.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>348</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1985</year>, s. 5, for" Chief Inspector of Lighthouses" 
 (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" Superintendent or Inspector of 
Lighthouses" (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>312276</tid>
<number>2</number>A local lighthouse authority shall not erect, place, remove 
or discontinue any lighthouse or vary the character or mode of use of 
any lighthouse, unless it has given to the Central Government at least 
one month' s notice in writing of its intention so to do:
Provided that, in cases of emergency, a local lighthouse 
authority may take such action as it deems necessary and shall give 
immediate notice of the same to the Central Government and, so far as 
is possible, to all shipping approaching or in the vicinity of the 
lighthouse.


</section>

<section><tid>1099962</tid>
<number>3</number>If a local lighthouse authority--

<subsection><tid>863954</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to comply with any direction made under sub- 
section (1), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1571184</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to exercise or perform, or exercises or performs 
in an improper, inefficient or unsuitable manner, any 
power or duty relating to the superintendence or 
management of lighthouses conferred or imposed upon it 
by or under any law for the time being in force, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1608597</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to make adequate financial provision for the 
performance of any such duty,
the Central Government may, by order in writing, require the local 
lighthouse authority to comply with the direction, or to make 
arrangements to the satisfaction of the Central Government for the 
proper exercise of the power or performance of the duty, or to make 
financial provision to the satisfaction of the Central Government for 
the performance of the duty, as the case may be, within such period as the 
Central Government may specify.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1257745</tid>
<number>4</number>If the local lighthouse authority fails to comply with an 
order made under sub- section (3) within the specified period or within 
such further time as the Central Government may allow, the Central 
Government may exercise the power or perform the duty or make the 
requisite financial provision, as the case may be, and the local 
lighthouse authority shall be liable to repay to the Central 
Government any expenditure incurred by it in so doing.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>513554</tid>
<number>8</number>Management of local lighthouses by the Central Government. The 
Central Government may, at the request of a local lighthouse 
authority, undertake the superintendence and management of any local 
lighthouse on its behalf, and the local lighthouse authority shall pay 
to the Central Government such sums to defray the cost of 
superintendence and management as may be agreed.


</article>



<article><tid>425750</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power of Central Government to prohibit lights and 
regulate heights of buildings, structures and trees.
<section><tid>927227</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so 
to do for unobstructed functioning of any lighthouse, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that,--

<subsection><tid>1860115</tid>
<number>i</number>no light shall be established without the prior 
permission of the Central Government in case of general 
lighthouse and without the prior permission of the local 
lighthouse authority in case of local lighthouse on any land 
within such radius, not exceeding one kilometre from the 
lighthouse, as may be specified in the notification; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>453114</tid>
<number>ii</number>no building or structure higher than such height as may 
be specified in the notification shall be constructed or erected, 
or no tree, which is likely to grow or ordinarily grows higher 
than such height as may be specified in the notification, shall 
be planted, on any land within such radius, not exceeding one 
kilometre from the lighthouse, as may be specified in the 
notification.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>859421</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any light has been established without or contrary to 
the permission referred to in clause (i) of sub- section (1), the 
Central Government or the local lighthouse authority, as the case may 
be, may, in addition to any other action that may be taken under this 
Act, make an order directing that such light shall be removed by the 
owner or the person having control of the light, within such period as 
may be specified in such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1643977</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any building or structure has been constructed or 
erected or any tree has been planted in contravention of the 
directions contained in clause (ii) of sub- section (1), the Central 
Government or the local lighthouse authority, as the case may be, may, 
in addition to any other action that may be taken under this Act, make 
an order directing that the height of such building, structure or tree 
shall be reduced to the extent specified in such notification, by the 
owner or the person having control of the building or structure or the 
tree, as the case may be, within such period as may be specified in 
such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1106266</tid>
<number>4</number>No order under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) shall be 
made unless the owner or the person has been given, by means of a 
notice, a reasonable opportunity of showing cause why such order shall 
not be made.

</section>

<section><tid>932295</tid>
<number>5</number>If any person fails to remove the light in pursuance of 
direction contained in the order issued under sub- section (2) or 
reduce the height of the building, structure or tree in pursuance of 
any direction contained in the order issued under sub- section (3), 
within the period specified in such order, then, subject to such rules 
as the Central Government may make in this behalf, it shall be 
competent for any officer authorised by the Central Government or the 
local lighthouse authority, as the case may be, in this behalf to 
remove such light or to reduce the height of such building, structure 
or tree and the expenses of such removal or reduction shall be 
recoverable from such person as a land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>1810743</tid>
<number>6</number>The orders referred to in sub- sections (2) and (3) and the 
notice referred to in sub- section (4) shall be served on the owner or 
the person having the control of the light, building, structure or 
tree, as the case may be,--

<subsection><tid>1745919</tid>
<number>i</number>by delivering or tendering it to such owner or person; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1616961</tid>
<number>ii</number>if it cannot be so delivered or tendered, by delivering 
or tendering it to any officer of such owner or person or any 
adult male member of the family of such owner or person or by 
affixing a copy thereof on some conspicuous part of the premises 
in which such owner or person is known to have last resided or 
carried on business or personally worked for gain, or failing 
service by these means;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1817444</tid>
<number>iii</number>by post.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>428461</tid>
<number>7</number>If any person wilfully fails to comply with any direction 
contained in any notification issued under sub- section (1), he shall 
be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with 
both.

</section>

<section><tid>1599796</tid>
<number>8</number>Every notification issued by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is published 
in the Official Gazette, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree that the notification 
should not be made, the notification shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under the 
notification.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>349</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1985</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


LIGHT- DUES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1043065</tid>
<number>9</number>Levy and collection of light- dues. For the purpose of 
providing or maintaining or of providing and maintaining lighthouses 
for the benefit of ships voyaging to or from <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] or between 
ports in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], the Central Government shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, cause light- dues to be levied and collected in 
respect of every ship arriving at or departing from any port in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India].


</article>



<article><tid>1015285</tid>
<number> 10</number> Rates of light- dues leviable. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1005487</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, prescribe such rates, as 
it may deem necessary to provide for the purpose mentioned in section 
9, at which light- dues shall be payable, and may prescribe different 
rates for different classes of ships or sailing vessels, or for ships 
or sailing vessels of the same class when in use for different 
purposes or in different circumstances.]

</section>

<section><tid>25847</tid>
<number>2</number>Light- dues payable in respect of a ship shall be paid by the 
owner or master of the ship on its arrival at, and on its departure 
from, any port in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India]:
Provided that, if light- dues have been paid in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act in respect of any ship, no further dues 
shall become payable in respect of that ship for a period of thirty 
days from the date on which the dues so paid became payable.


</section>

<section><tid>1269778</tid>
<number>3</number>An order under sub- section (1) imposing, abolishing or 
varying light- dues shall not take effect till the expiration of thirty 
days from the day on which the order was notified in the Official 
Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>153162</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every notification issued by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is published 
in the Official Gazette, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the 
notification should not be made, the notification shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case 
may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
the notification.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>190852</tid>
<number> 11</number> Receipts for light- dues. Light- dues shall be paid to the 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> proper officer] who shall grant to the person paying the same a 
receipt in writing specifying--
<section><tid>651234</tid>
<number>a</number>the port at which the dues have been paid;

</section>

<section><tid>423203</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of the payment;

</section>

<section><tid>753641</tid>
<number>c</number>the date on which the dues became payable; and

</section>

<section><tid>994287</tid>
<number>d</number>the name, tonnage and other proper description of the 
ship in respect of which the payment is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1449873</tid>
<number> 12</number> Ascertainment of tonnage. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1263978</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of levy of  
light- dues, the tonnage of a ship or sailing vessel shall be reckoned 
as under the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>.) for dues 
payable on a ship' s tonnage including the tonnage of any space added 
under the said Act to the tonnage of ships by reason of such space 
being utilised for carrying cargo.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>350</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Provinces". 
2. Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1985</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1986</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for" Customs collector" (w. e. f.  
  15- 4- <year>1976</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1985</year>, s. 8, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f.  
  1. 2. <year>1986</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>774266</tid>
<number>2</number>In order to ascertain the tonnage of any ship for the purpose 
of levying light- dues, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] may--

<subsection><tid>833955</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> if the ship is registered under any law for the time being 
in force in India or under the law of any country, other 
than India, being a country the ships of which are 
recognised or accepted by the Central Government to be of 
the tonnage denoted in their certificates of registry or 
other national papers under any order made under any 
enactment repealed by sub- section (1) of section 461 of 
the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>), and 
continued in force under clause (a) of sub- section (3) of 
that section or under any rule made under clause (b) of 
sub- section (2) of section 74 of the said Act (any such  
ship being hereafter in this section referred to as 
  registered ship), require the owner or master or other 
person having possession of the ship' s register or other 
papers denoting her tonnage to produce the same for 
inspection and, if such owner, master or other person 
refuses or neglects to produce the register or papers, as 
the case may be, or otherwise to satisfy the proper 
officer as to the tonnage of the ship, cause the ship to 
be measured and the tonnage to be ascertained; or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>552411</tid>
<number>b</number>if the ship is not a registered ship and the owner or master 
fails to satisfy the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] as to the true 
tonnage thereof according to the mode of measurement 
prescribed by the law for the time being in force for 
regulating the measurement of registered ships, cause the 
ship to be measured and the tonnage thereof to be ascer- 
tained according to such mode.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>148211</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person refuses or neglects to produce any register or 
other papers or otherwise to satisfy the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] as to the 
true tonnage of any ship when required to do so under this section, 
such person shall be liable to pay the expenses of the measurement of 
the ship and of the ascertainment of the tonnage, and, if the ship is 
a registered ship, shall further, on conviction by a Presidency 
Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction in the 
port where the ship lies or in any port to which she may proceed, be 
punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>763335</tid>
<number> 13</number> Recovery of light- dues expenses and costs.
<section><tid>968899</tid>
<number>1</number>If the owner  
or master of any ship refuses or neglects to pay to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> proper 
officer] on demand the amount of any light- dues or expenses payable 
under this Act in respect of the ship, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] may 
seize the ship and the tackle, apparel and furniture belonging 
thereto, or any part thereof, and detain the same until the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>351</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for" Customs collector" (w. e. f.  
  15. 4. <year>1976</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for cl. (a)  (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


amount of the dues or expenses, together with the costs of the seizure 
and detention, is paid.


</section>

<section><tid>1517116</tid>
<number>2</number>If any part of such dues, expenses or costs remains unpaid 
after the expiry of five days following the date of the seizure, the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] may cause the ship or other thing seized to be 
sold, and with the proceeds of the sale may satisfy the dues, expenses 
or costs remaining unpaid, together with the costs of the sale, and 
shall repay the surplus, if any, to the person by whom the same were 
payable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>213261</tid>
<number>14</number>Refusal of port- clearance. The officer whose duty it is to 
grant a port- clearance for any ship shall not grant the port- clearance 
until the amount of all light- dues, expenses and costs payable in 
respect of the ship under this Act and of any fines impose thereunder 
has been paid, or until security for the payment thereof has been 
given to his satisfaction.


</article>



<article><tid>847388</tid>
<number>15</number>Determination of disputes as to liability for payment. If any 
dispute arises as to whether light- dues, expenses or costs are payable 
in respect of any ship under this Act or as to the amount of such 
dues, expenses or costs, the dispute shall, on application made in 
this behalf by either of the disputing parties, be heard and 
determined by a Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class 
having jurisdiction at the place where the dispute arises, and the 
decision of such Magistrate shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>636615</tid>
<number> 16</number> Light- dues payable at one port recoverable at another.
<section><tid>702595</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
the master of any ship in respect of which any light- dues are payable 
at any port causes the ship to leave such port without having paid the 
same, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] at that port may by writing require the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] at any other port in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] to which the ship 
may proceed or in which she may be to recover the dues remaining 
unpaid.

</section>

<section><tid>1820079</tid>
<number>2</number>Any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] to whom such a requisition is directed 
shall proceed to levy such sum as if it were payable under this Act at 
the port at which he is the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer], and a certificate by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> proper officer] at the port at which the light- dues first 
became payable, stating the amount payable, shall be sufficient proof 
in any proceeding under section 13 or section 15 that such amount is 
payable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>169691</tid>
<number> 17</number> Penalty for evading payment of light- dues.
<section><tid>1297883</tid>
<number>1</number>If the owner  
or master of a ship evades or attempts to evade the payment of any 
light- dues, expenses or costs payable in respect of the ship under 
this Act, he shall, on conviction by a
<pagefootnote><pagenum>352</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for" Customs collector". (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>). 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class having 
jurisdiction in any port to which the vessel may proceed or in which 
she may be found, be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
times the amount of the sum payable.


</section>

<section><tid>1692913</tid>
<number>2</number>In any proceeding before a Magistrate in a prosecution under 
sub- section (1), any such certificate as is mentioned in sub- section 
 (2) of section 16, stating that the owner or master has evaded such 
payment, shall be sufficient proof of the evasion, unless the owner or 
master shows to the satisfaction of the Magistrate that the departure 
of the vessel without payment of the sum was caused by stress of 
weather, or that there was lawful or reasonable grounds for such 
departure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1182756</tid>
<number> 18</number> Exemption from payment of light- dues. The following ships 
shall be exempted from the payment of light- dues under this Act, 
namely:--
<section><tid>1928878</tid>
<number>a</number>any ship belonging to Government <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or to a foreign 
Prince or State and not carrying cargo or passengers 
for freight or fares; and

</section>

<section><tid>587126</tid>
<number>b</number>any ship of a tonnage of less than fifty tons,
and the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, exempt any other ships, or classes of ships or ships 
performing specified voyages from such payment, either wholly or to 
such extent only as may be specified in the notification.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>258590</tid>
<number>19</number>Refund of excess payments. Where light- dues have been paid in 
respect of any ship in excess of the amount payable under this Act, no 
claim to refund of such excess payment shall be admissible, unless it 
is made within six months from the date of each payment.


</article>



<article><tid>1771808</tid>
<number>19A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Fees. Fees may be charged for providing assistance to 
ships for calibrating their Wireless Direction Finders and for 
rendering other services to vessels, at such rates as the Central 
Government may specify in the rules made under this Act.]
ACCOUNTS



</article>



<article><tid>1193600</tid>
<number> 20</number> Accounts, etc.
<section><tid>372396</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall cause to be  
maintained a separate account of all amounts received by way of light- 
dues, expenses, costs and fines under this Act and of all expenditure 
incurred for the purposes of this Act, and shall cause such account to 
be laid before the Central Advisory Committee as soon as possible 
after the close of each financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1529304</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall cause to be laid before the 
Central Advisory Committee before the close of each financial year a
<pagefootnote><pagenum>353</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or the Govt." left out by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
2. Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1976</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 15. 4. <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


statement of the estimated receipts under, and expenditure for the 
purposes of, this Act during the forthcoming year.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

RULES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>156234</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1315908</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] consistent with this 
Act to carry into effect the purposes thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1389602</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>608219</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the powers and duties of the Director- General of 
Lighthouses and Lightships and Directors and Deputy 
Directors- General of Lighhouses and Lightships;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119607</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure and conduct of business of Advisory 
Committees constituted under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>443227</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the manner in which the light may be removed and the 
height of the building, structure or tree may be 
reduced under sub- section (5) of section 8A;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901952</tid>
<number>c</number>the rate of travelling and subsistence allowance payable 
to members of Advisory Committees; <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1180839</tid>
<number>cc</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the rates of fees for providing assistance to ships 
for calibrating their Wireless Direction Finders and 
for rendering other services to vessels;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>499218</tid>
<number>d</number>the period in respect of which and the form in which the 
separate account referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 20 shall be kept and the forms in which that 
account and the statement referred to in sub- section 
 (2) of that section shall respectively be presented to 
the Central Advisory Committee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1208436</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, 
or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]
REPEALS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1517460</tid>
<number>22</number>[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 
and Sch.

</article>



 </act>