<act><title>

the 
    Reserve Bank of India General Regulations, 1949</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These Regulations may be 
    called the Reserve Bank of India General Regulations, 1949.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these 
    Regulations, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    ‘the Act’ means the 
    Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (II of 1934);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    ‘Director’ means 
    Director of the Central Board of the Reserve Bank;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    ‘Member’ means member of 
    a Local Board;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    Other expressions used 
    but not defined in these Regulations and used in the Act have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Declaration of fidelity and secrecy.—Every 
    Director and every member shall, before entering upon his duties, sign a 
    declaration in the form set out in the Schedule pleading himself to observe 
    strict secrecy respecting all transactions of the Bank with its customers 
    and all matters relating thereto, and shall by such declaration pledge 
    himself not to reveal any of the matters which may come to his knowledge in 
    the discharge of his duties, except when required or authorised to do so by 
    the Board or by law.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> No 
    Director or Member to deal with matters with which he is personally 
    concerned.—
<section><number>i</number> Every Director and 
    every member who is directly or indirectly concerned or interested in any 
    contract or arrangement entered into by or on behalf of the Bank shall 
    disclose the nature of his interest at the meeting of the Central Board or 
    the Local Board, as the case may be, at which the contract or arrangement is 
    determined on, if his interest then exists, or in any other case at the next 
    meeting of the Central Board or the Local Board, as the case may be, after 
    the acquisition of his interest or the making of the contract or 
    arrangement.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> No 
    Director, no member and no member of the committee of the Central Board 
    shall, as such, vote on any contract or arrangement in which he is either 
    directly or indirectly concerned or interested and if he does so his vote 
    shall not be counted.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Obligation of Director or Member of Local Board to give information of 
    disqualification.—A member or a 
    Director nominated under clause (b) or (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of the section 
    8 or under section 12(3) or 12(4) of the Act shall, as soon as may be, 
    inform the Local Board or the Central Board as the case may be, if he 
    becomes subject to any of the disqualifications set out in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Central 
    Board to inform Central Government regarding disqualifica-tions.—The 
    Central Board shall forthwith inform the Central Government, if it comes to 
    the notice of the Central Board, that any director or a member has become 
    subject to any of the disqualifications specified in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or 
    sub-section (2) of section 10 of the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Indemnity of Directors and Members of Local Boards.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Every Director and every member shall be indemnified by the Bank against all 
    losses and expenses incurred by him in or about the discharge of his duties, 
    except such as may happen from his own wilful act or default.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Neither a 
    Director nor a member shall be responsible for any other Director or member 
    or for any officer or servant of the Bank or for any loss or expense 
    happening to the Bank by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or 
    title to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the Bank, 
    or by the insolvency, bankruptcy or wrongful act of any customer or debater 
    of the Bank, or by anything done in the execution of the duties of his 
    office or in relation thereto, or otherwise than for his own wilful act or 
    default.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meetings 
    of the Central Board.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Ordinarily not less than one clear month’s notice shall be given of each 
    meeting of the Central Board and such notice shall be sent to every Director 
    to his registered address. Should it be found necessary to convene an 
    emergency meeting, sufficient notice shall be given to every Director who is 
    at the time in India to enable him to attend.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> No 
    business other than that for which the meeting was convened shall be 
    discussed at a meeting of the Central Board, except with the consent of the 
    Chairman and a majority of the Directors present, unless one clear week’s 
    notice has been given of the same in writing to the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> Four 
    Directors of whom not less than three shall be directors nominated under 
    section 8(1)(b) or 8(1)(c) or 12(4) of the Act shall form a quorum for the 
    transaction of business.  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> A copy of 
    the proceedings of each Central Board meeting shall be circulated as soon as 
    possible thereafter for the information of the Directors and shall be signed 
    by the Chairman at that or the next succeeding meeting.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Meetings 
    Local Boards.—
<section><number>i</number> Meetings of 
    Local Boards shall be convened from time to time as the Central Government 
    may by general or special regulation direct.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Two 
    members shall form a quorum for the transaction of business.  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> At the 
    first meeting of a Local Board after the incoming members have assumed 
    office, the Local Board shall elect from amongst its members a chairman and 
    a vice-chairman. They shall continue in their respective offices until a 
    fresh Board has been constituted on the expiry of their term of office 
    unless such office is vacated by death, resignation or removal.  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> The 
    Managers in charge of the offices of the Bank in Bombay, Calcutta, Delhi and 
    Madras shall be ex-officio secretaries of the Local Boards at these 
    places. The officers in charge of the Department of Banking Operations and 
    Development at the respective local offices shall be ex-officio 
    deputy secretaries provided that where there is no such officer or the 
    officer is not available, the officer next senior in rank to the Manager 
    shall be ex-officio deputy secretary.  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number> The 
    Chairman or in his absence the Vice-Chairman shall preside at all meetings 
    of the Local Board. In the event of the absence of both the Chairman and the 
    Vice-Chairman through illness or other unavoidable cause, the members 
    present at the meeting may elect one from amongst themselves to preside at 
    the meeting. In the event of an equality of votes the person presiding shall 
    have a second or casting vote.  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number> A copy of 
    the proceedings of each Local Board meeting shall be circulated as soon as 
    possible thereafter for the information of the members of the Local Board 
    and shall be signed by the person presiding at that or the next succeeding 
    meeting. A copy of the said proceedings shall also be submitted forthwith to 
    the Central Board.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Committee of the Central Board.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    A committee which shall be called the Committee of the Central Board, 
    consisting of the members of the Central Board who may at the time be 
    present in the area in which the meeting is held, shall ordinarily meet once 
    a week at the office of the Bank or any other place in the area in which the 
    Governor, or in his absence the Deputy Governor authorised by him under the 
    proviso to sub-section (3) of Section 8 of the Act, has his headquarters for 
    the time being, to attend to the current business of the Bank. Sufficient 
    notice shall be given to such Directors to enable them to attend.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Two 
    directors of who one shall be a director nominated under section 8(1)(b) or 
    8(1)(c) or 12(4) of the Act shall form a quorum for the transaction of 
    business.  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in this Regulation, the provisions of the Act and these 
    Regulations shall apply to meetings of the Committee of the Central Board as 
    if they were meetings of the Central Board.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Proceedings of Boards not invalidated by vacancies.—No 
    act or proceeding of the Central or a Local Board or of the Committee of the 
    Central Board shall be invalidated merely by reason of the existence of a 
    vacancy or vacancies therein.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Acts of 
    Directors and Members of Boards valid notwithstanding subsequent discovery 
    of disqualification.—All acts 
    done at any meeting of the Central or Local Board or the Committee of the 
    Central Board or by any person acting as a Director or a member or as a 
    member of the Committee of the Central Board shall, notwithstanding that it 
    is afterwards discovered that there was some defect in the appointment of 
    such person or that they or any of them were disqualified, be as valid as if 
    every such person had been duly appointed and duly qualified.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Delegation by Central Board to Local Boards.—A 
    Local Board shall have power to transact such business as may be delegated 
    to it from time to time by the Central Board provided that if at the time of 
    consideration by a Local Board of any business a majority of the members 
    present are directly or indirectly concerned or interested therein such 
    business shall not be finally dealt with without the previous approval of 
    the Committee of the Central Board.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Delegation to the Committee of the Central Board.—The 
    Committee of the Central Board shall have full powers to transact all the 
    usual business of the Bank except in such matters as are specifically 
    reserved by the Act to the Central Government or the Central Board.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> No 
    advance to be made to officers of the Bank without sanction of Central 
    Board.—An advance may be made to 
    the Governor, Deputy Governor, Officer or other employee of the Bank with 
    the sanction of the authority specified in the relative regulations, rules, 
    or schemes made or approved by the Central Board or the Committee, in terms 
    of which the advance is to be made and where no authority is specified in 
    the relative regulations, rules or schemes, as the case may be, the advance 
    may be sanctioned,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number> to the Governor, by the Committee;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> to a Deputy Governor or an Executive 
    Director, by the Governor;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> to Officers and other employees, by a 
    Deputy Governor or an Executive Director and subject to such general or 
    special directions as may be issued by the Governor or a Deputy Governor, by 
    the Chief Manager or the Chief Accountant.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Powers 
    on behalf of the Bank by whom to be exercised.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of the Act, any rules made by the Central Board in 
    regard to expenditure to be incurred by or on behalf of the Bank and any 
    directions, which may be given by the Governor either generally or in any 
    particular case in regard to the conduct of the business of the Bank, the 
    Deputy Governors and Executive Directors are hereby severally empowered to 
    exercise any or all the powers and do any or all acts and things, which may 
    be exercised or done by the Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any other 
    officer not below the rank of a Staff Officer Grade II may, if authorised 
    and to the extent that he is so authorised by the Governor in this behalf, 
    exercise all the powers in relation to matters pertaining to the department 
    or office in which he is employed, and in relation to such matters, do all 
    acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Bank, subject however 
    to the conditions hereinafter specified, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the power to sanction or 
    incur any expenditure on behalf of the Bank shall be subject to Rules made 
    by the Central Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any other power 
    exercised or action taken shall be exercised or taken subject to such 
    directions if any as may be given by any higher officer or authority in this 
    behalf.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No power 
    exercised, function performed or act or thing done shall be deemed to be 
    invalid or ineffective only on the grained that it is not a power exercised, 
    function performed, or act or thing done by or on behalf of the Bank or that 
    in the exercise of such power, performance of such function or the doing of 
    any such act or thing, effect has not been given to any rule or direction 
    referred to in sub-regulation (1) or in sub-regulation (2), or that any such 
    rule or direction has been wrongly acted upon.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in 
    these regulations shall be deemed to render invalid or ineffective the 
    powers exercised, functions performed or acts or things done in the course 
    of carrying out the authorised business of the Bank by any authority or 
    authorities prior to the coming into force of these Regulations.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Manner 
    and form in which contracts binding on the Bank may be executed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    
<subsection><number>a</number> Contracts on behalf of the Bank may be made as follows:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    Any contract which, if 
    made between private would by law be required to be in writing and signed by 
    the parties to be charged therewith, may be made on behalf of the Bank in 
    writing and signed by any person acting under its authority, express or 
    implied, and may in the same manner be varied or discharged.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    Any contract which, if 
    made between private persons, would by law be valid although made by parole 
    only and not reduced to writing may be made by parole on behalf of the Bank 
    by any person acting under its authority; express or implied, and may in the 
    same manner be varied or discharged.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> All 
    contracts made according to the provisions of this Regulation shall be 
    effectual in law and shall bind the Bank and all other parties there to and 
    their legal representatives.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Accounts, receipts and documents of Bank by whom to be signed.—Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by or under Regulation 
    17, the Chief Manager, Additional Chief Manager, Chief Accountant, Secretary 
    to the Central Board, the Secretaries of Local Boards and such other 
    Officers of the Bank as the Central Board has authorised or may authorise in 
    this behalf by notification in the Gazette of India are hereby severally 
    empowered for and on behalf of the Bank to execute lease deeds, transfers, 
    conveyances, charges and other deeds relating to or affecting rights to or 
    in immovable property, to endorse and transfer promissory notes, 
    stock-receipts, stock-debentures, shares, securities and documents of title 
    to goods, standing in the name of or held by the Bank, and to draw, accept 
    and endorse bills of exchange and other instruments in the current and 
    authorised business of the Bank to sign all other accounts receipts and 
    documents connected with such business.  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Plaints, etc. by whom to be signed.—Plaints, 
    written statements, affidavits and all other documents connected with legal 
    proceedings may be signed and verified on behalf of the Bank by any officer 
    empowered by or under Regulation to sign documents for and on behalf of the 
    Bank, and such officer may appear in or before any court, tribunal or other 
    body as the recognised agent of the Bank for the purposes of the proceedings 
    in that court, tribunal or other body.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Seals 
    of the Bank - Common seal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The common seal of the Bank shall not be affixed to any instrument except in 
    the presence of the Governor or a Deputy Governor or an Executive Director 
    who shall sign his name to the instrument in token of his presence, and such 
    signing shall be independent of the signing of any person who may sign the 
    instrument as a witness. Unless so signed as aforesaid such instrument shall 
    be of no validity.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Official seals.—The Bank shall have for use by the Local Boards at 
    Bombay, Calcutta, Delhi and Madras official seals which shall be facsimiles 
    of the common seal of the Bank with the addition of the name of the office 
    where it is to be used.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    instrument to which an official seal is duly affixed shall bind the Bank as 
    if it had been sealed with the common seal of the Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    official seal shall not be affixed to any instrument except in the presence 
    of at least two members of the Local Board and the Secretary or Deputy 
    Secretary who shall sign their names to the instrument in token of their 
    presence and such signing shall be independent of the signing of any person 
    who may sign the instrument as a witness.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    official seal may be affixed by a Local Board to instruments of the 
    following description in connection with business, at offices, branches or 
    agencies under its jurisdiction, namely—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Leases of office 
    premises, godowns, houses and other property acquired in connection with the 
    business of the Bank.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Conveyances of property 
    bought of sold by the Bank.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    Reconveyances or 
    releases of property mortgaged to the Bank.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    Powers of Attorney 
    granted by the Bank.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Service 
    of notice on Bank.—A notice may 
    be served on the Bank by leaving it at, or sending it by Post to, any office 
    of the Bank which is the headquarters of a local Board.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Annual 
    statement of account.—The Central 
    Board shall cause the books of the Bank to be balanced on the last working 
    day of the month of June in each year and the annual accounts shall be set 
    out as follows:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    A balance sheet in the 
    form prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    A profit and loss 
    account for the year in the following form and containing the particulars 
    therein prescribed:—
  
 
Income
 
                        
    Amount brought forward                                  …      
    …       …
 
                        
    Interest, Discount, Exchange, Commission, etc.   …      
    …       …
  
 

    Expenditure
 
                        
    Establishment                                                …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Directors’ and Local Board Members’ fees 
 
                        
    and expenses                                                …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Auditors’ fees                                                …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Rent, Taxes, Insurance Lighting etc.                  
    …       …       
    …
 
                        
    Law charges                                                 
     …       …       
    …
 
                        
    Postage and telegraph charges                        …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Remittance of Treasure                                  …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Stationary, etc.                                            …       
    …       … 
 
                        
    Security printing (cheque, note forms, etc.)       …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Depreciation and repairs to Bank property          …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Agency charges                                            …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Contributions to staff and superannuation funds …       
    …       …
 
                        
    Miscellaneous expenses                                  …       
    …       …
 
                                                                   
    Net available balance …
 
                        
    Surplus payable to the Central Government        …       
    …       …
 </section><section>
             
    <number>iii</number> The account of Reserve Fund in the following form:—
 
                        
    By balance on the 30th June                           …       
    …       …
 
                        
    By transfer from Profit and Loss Account           …       
    …       …
 
                                                                
    Total Rs.             …       …       
    …
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Valuation of investments.—
<section><number>i</number> The 
    investment of the Banking Department of the Bank in securities shall be held 
    in an account styled “Bank’s Investments Account” and the securities held in 
    that account shall be valued yearly at rates not exceeding the market rates 
    on the last working day of the month of June each year.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The 
    investments of the Issue Department in securities shall be valued at rates 
    not exceeding the market rates as at the close of business on every Friday 
    and also on the last working day of the month of June every year, provided 
    that any fall or reduction in the market price of a security may, to avoid 
    petty adjustments, be disregarded if the extent of the fall or reduction is 
    less than two percent of the holding price of the security.  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> The 
    market rate for the time being obtaining shall be that advised by the Bank’s 
    brokers as that obtaining on the valuation day.  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> In 
    valuing treasury bills of the Government of India or any other Government or 
    bills of exchange the purchase price shall be deemed to be the market price.  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number> The items 
    in the account prescribed by the Central Government under section 53 of the 
    Act shall be valued to the nearest thousand rupees.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Remuneration of Directors and Members of Local Boards.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Directors nominated under section 8(1)(b) and 8(1)(c) or 12(4) of the Act 
    shall receive a fee of Rs. 200 for each Central Board meeting which they 
    attend, and a fee of Rs. 50 for each committee meeting of the Central Board 
    which they attend.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Members 
    of a Local Board shall receive a fee of Rs. 50 for each Board meeting which 
    they attend.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> In 
    addition such Directors and Members shall be re-imbursed their travelling 
    expenses, if any, on such scale as may be prescribed by the Central Board 
    from time to time.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



the 
    Reserve Bank of India General Regulations, 1949
 

 
 

 
 


The 
    Schedule
 


(Vide regulation 3)
 



    Form of Declaration of Fidelity and Secrecy
 

 
 


I,........................., on becoming a 
    Director of the/Member of the Central Board/Local Board of the Reserve Bank 
    of India do solemnly and sincerely declare that I will faithfully perform 
    the duties of Director/Member and that I will to the best of my ability 
    uphold the interests of the Reserve Bank of India and that I will observe 
    strike secrecy respecting all transactions of the Bank and all matters 
    relating thereto and that I will not directly or indirectly communicate or 
    divulge any of the matters or any information which may come to my knowledge 
    in the discharge of my duties as such Director/Member except when required 
    or authorised to do so by the Central Board of the Bank or by law.
 


 
 



    (Signature).........................................
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>