<act><title>THE CARRIAGE BY ROAD ACT, 2007 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Carriage by Road Act, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India , except the State of Jammu and Kashmir . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 





</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In this 
Act, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> common carrier means a person engaged in the business of 
  collecting, storing, forwarding or distributing goods to be carried by goods 
  carriages under a goods receipt or transporting for hire of goods from place 
  to place by motorised transport on road, for all persons undiscriminatingly 
  and includes a goods booking company, contractor, agent, broker and courier 
  agency engaged in the door-to-door transportation of documents, goods or 
  articles utilising the services of a person, either directly or indirectly, to 
  carry or accompany such documents, goods or articles, but does not include the 
  Government; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> consignee means the person named as consignee in the 
  goods forwarding note; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> consignment means documents, goods or articles entrusted 
  by the consignor to the common carrier for carriage, the description or 
  details of which are given in the goods forwarding note; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> consignor means a person, named as consignor in the 
  goods forwarding note, by whom or on whose behalf the documents, goods or 
  articles covered by such forwarding note are entrusted to the common carrier 
  for carriage thereof; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> goods includes 
 <subsection><number>i</number> containers, pallets or similar articles of transport used 
  to consolidate goods; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> animals or livestock; 
 </subsection></section><section><number>f</number> goods forwarding note means the document executed under 
  section 8; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> goods receipt means the receipt issued under section 9; 
  
 </section><section><number>h</number> person includes any association or body of persons, 
  whether incorporated or not, a road transport booking company, contractor and 
  an agent or a broker carrying on the business of a common carrier; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> prescribed means prescribed by rules made under this 
  Act; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> registering authority means a State Transport Authority 
  or a Regional Transport Authority constituted under section 68 of the Motor 
  Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988); 
 </section><section><number>k</number> registration means the registration granted or renewed 
  under sub-section (5) of section 4. </section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Persons not to engage in business 
of common carrier without registration. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No person shall engage in 
the business of a common carrier, after the commencement of this Act, unless he 
has been granted a certificate of registration. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person who is engaged, whether wholly or partly, in the 
business of a common carrier, immediately before the commencement of this Act, 
shall, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> apply for a registration within ninety days from the date 
  of such commencement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> cease to engage in such business on the expiry of one 
  hundred and eighty days from the date of such commencement unless he has 
  applied for registration and the certificate of registration has been granted 
  by the registering authority. </subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Application for grant or renewal 
of registration. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person, who is engaged or intends to engage 
in the business of a common carrier, shall apply for the grant or renewal of a 
certificate of registration for carrying on the business of common carrier to 
the registering authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application under sub-section (1) shall be made, to the 
registering authority having jurisdiction in the area in which the applicant 
resides or has his principal place of business stating that the application is 
for the main office, in such form and manner and accompanied by such fees 
payable to the registering authority as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application for grant or renewal of certificate or 
registration for the main office shall contain the details of branch office, if 
any, to be operated outside the jurisdiction of the State or Union territory in 
which the main office is to be registered in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed: 
 Provided that an application for the purpose to open or close a 
branch office shall be made to the registering authority having jurisdiction 
over the main office. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A registering authority shall, before granting or renewing a 
certificate of registration, satisfy itself that the applicant fulfils such 
conditions as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The registering authority may, on receipt of an application 
under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) and after satisfying itself that the 
applicant fulfils the requirements of sub-section (4), grant the certificate of 
registration or renew it, as the case may be, for carrying on the business of a 
common carrier, in such form and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed: 
 Provided that no application for the grant or renewal of a 
certificate of registration shall be refused by the registering authority unless 
the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard and the reasons for 
such refusal are given in writing by the registering authority within sixty days 
from the date of receipt of such application: 
 Provided further that if such refusal has not been communicated 
within sixty days of the date of application, the registering authority shall 
grant or renew certificate of registration within a further period of thirty 
days. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A certificate of registration granted or renewed under 
sub-section (5) shall contain the details of branch offices to be operated in 
various States and Union territories, and shall be valid for a period of ten 
years from the date of such grant or renewal, as the case may be: 
 Provided that in the case of registration in respect of branch 
offices referred to in sub-section (3), the validity of such registration shall 
be restricted to the validity of the registration granted in respect of the main 
office. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The holder of a certificate of registration shall 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> maintain a register in such form and manner as may be 
  prescribed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> not shift the main office mentioned in the certificate of 
  registration submit an application to the registering authority which granted 
  the registration: 
 Provided that such registering authority shall grant or refuse 
  permission for shifting the main office within thirty days from the 
  date of receipt of such application and that no application for shifting the 
  main office shall be refused unless the applicant has been given an 
  opportunity of being heard and reasons for such refusal are given in writing 
  by the registering authority: 
 Provided further that in case the registering authority has 
  not either granted or refused the permission within thirty days it shall be 
  deemed that the permission for shifting has been granted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> submit to the registering authority under whose 
  jurisdiction the main office is located and the Transport Research Wing of the 
  Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing with road transport 
  and highways such information and return as may be prescribed within one 
  hundred and twenty days after the thirty-first day of March every year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> display at a prominent place in its or its main office or 
  branch offices, if any, a certificate of registration in original or certified 
  copy thereof attested by the concerned registering authority, a notary or a 
  Gazetted Officer of the Central or State Government. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>8</number> A common carrier shall not load the motor vehicle beyond the 
gross vehicle weight mentioned in the registration certificate whose 
registration number is mentioned in the goods forwarding note or goods receipt 
and the common carrier shall not allow such vehicle to be loaded beyond the 
gross vehicle weight. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Suspension or cancellation of 
registration. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If the registering authority is satisfied that the 
holder of a certificate of registration has failed to comply with any of the 
provisions of sub-section (7) of section 4, it may give a notice by registered 
post or through electronic media or by any other verifiable means to the holder 
of certificate of registration to rectify with a period of thirty days and in 
case such a holder fails to do so, it may revoke the certificate of registration 
on completion of enquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If a complaint is received by the registering authority 
against a common carrier from a consignor in respect of, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> non-issuance of receipt of goods; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> non-disclosure of the whereabouts of the goods in transit 
  when asked by the consignor or consignee; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> detention of goods for delivery without valid reasons; 
  or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> demand for unreasonable additional charges at the time of 
  delivery, which were neither disclosed nor agreed upon between the consignor 
  and the consignee earlier; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> non-payment of charges agreed and payable to truck-owners, 
  
 it may give a notice by registered post or through electronic 
  media or by any other verifiable means to the holder of certificate of 
  registration to rectify the same within a period of thirty days and in case 
  such holder fails to do so, it may revoke certificate of registration for a 
  period as may be prescribed under the rules on completion of that enquiry. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the registering authority or any other authority so 
authorised under the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) has received proof of 
violation of provision of sub-section (8) of section 4, it shall be competent to 
impose the penalty prescribed under section 194 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 
on the common carrier, notwithstanding the fact that such penalty have been 
already imposed on and realised from the driver or the owner of the goods 
vehicle or the consignor as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An action for revocation of certificate of registration 
shall not be taken under sub-section (1) and (2) unless the holder of the 
certificate of registration is given an opportunity of being heard in the 
enquiry and reasons for such action are given in writing by the registering 
authority. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The registering authority in whose jurisdiction the main 
office of the common carrier is located shall be competent to take action under 
sub-section (1) and (2) and any other registering authority who has noticed the 
violations or has received complaints under the said sub-sections, shall report 
such matter to the registering authority having jurisdiction over the main 
office. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> When the certificate of registration is revoked, the holder 
of the certificate of registration shall surrender the certificate of 
registration to the registering authority within a period of thirty days and it 
would be incumbent on the holder of the certificate of registration to complete 
the delivery and transactions in respect of the consignments already accepted by 
the common carrier from any consignor prior to the revocation of the certificate 
of registration. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The holder of a registration may, at any time, surrender the 
certificate to the registering authority which granted the registration, and on 
such surrender the registering authority shall, after obtaining declaration from 
the holder of the certificate of registration that no liability is outstanding 
against him and that he shall discharge such liability, if he held liable, 
revoke the certificate of registration: 
 Provided that if the surrender is in respect of a branch office, 
the endorsement in respect of the branch office shall be deleted from the 
certificate of registration and such deletion shall be notified by the 
registering authority having jurisdiction over the main office to such other 
authorities as may be prescribed. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Appeal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order of the registering authority refusing to grant or renew a 
certificate of registration or suspending or revoking a registration under this 
Act, may, within sixty days from the date of such order, appeal to the State 
Transport Appellate Tribunal constituted under sub-section (2) of section 89 of 
the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal under sub-section (1) shall be preferred in 
duplicate in the form of a memorandum setting forth the grounds of objection to 
the order of the registering authority and shall be accompanied by such fee as 
may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1) and 
(2), the provisions of sub-section (1) and (2) of section 89 of the Motor 
Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988), as in force immediately before the commencement 
of this Act, with regard to appeal, shall, as far as may, apply to every appeal 
as if the provisions aforesaid were enacted by this Act subject to the 
modification that any reference therein to the permit shall be construed as a 
reference to the registration. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Submission of annual return. 
</title>The State Transport Authority in respect of each State or Union 
territory shall submit annually to the Ministry or Department of the Central 
Government dealing with road transport and highways a consolidated annual return 
giving the details of the goods carried by the common carriers in that State or 
the Union territory, as the case may be, on the basis of the returns received 
from the holders of the registration as specified under clause (c) of 
sub-section (7) of section 4. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Goods forwarding note. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every consignor shall execute a goods forwarding note, in such 
form and manner as may be prescribed, which shall include a declaration about 
the value of the consignment and goods of dangerous or hazardous nature. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The consignor shall be responsible for the correctness of 
the particulars furnished by him in the goods forwarding note. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The consignor shall indemnify the common carrier against any 
damage suffered by him by reason of incorrectness or incompleteness of the 
particulars on the goods forwarding note. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Goods receipt. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A 
common carrier shall, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in case where the goods are to be loaded by the consignor, 
  on the completion of such loading; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in any other case, on the acceptance of the goods by him, 
  issue a goods receipt in such form and manner as may be prescribed. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The goods receipt shall be issued in triplicate and the 
original shall be given to the consignor. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The goods receipt shall be prima facie evidence of 
the weight or measure and other particulars of the goods and the number of 
packages stated therein. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The goods receipt shall include an undertaking by the common 
carrier about the liability under section 10 or section 11. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Liability of common carrier. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The liability of the common carrier for loss of, or damage to any 
consignment, shall be limited to such amount as may be prescribed having regard 
to the value, freight and nature of goods, documents or articles of the 
consignment,' unless the consignor or any person duly authorised in that behalf 
have expressly undertaken to pay higher risk rate fixed by the common carrier 
under section 11. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The liability of the common carrier in case of any delay up 
to such period as may be mutually agreed upon by and between the consignor and 
the common carrier and specifically provided in the goods forwarding note 
including the consequential loss or damage to such consignment shall be limited 
to the amount of freight charges where such loss, damage or delay took place 
while the consignment was under the charge of such carrier: 
 Provided that beyond the period so agreed upon in the goods 
forwarding note, compensation shall be payable in accordance with sub-section 
(1) or section 11: 
 Provided further that the common carrier shall not be liable if 
such carrier proves that such loss of, or damage to, the consignment or delay in 
delivery thereof, had not taken place due to his fault or neglect or that of his 
servants or agents thereof. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Rates of charge to be fixed by 
common carrier for carriage of consignment at a higher risk rate. 
</title>Every common carrier may require payment for the higher risk 
undertaken by him in carrying a particular consignment at such rate of charge as 
he may fix and correspondingly, his liability would be in accordance with the 
terms as may be agreed upon with the consignor: 
 Provided that to entitle such carrier to claim payment at a rate 
higher than his ordinary rate of charge, he should have exhibited a printed or 
written notice, in the vernacular language of the State, of the higher rate of 
charge in the place or premises where he carries on the business of common 
carrier. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Conditions limiting 
exonerating the liability of the common carrier. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every common 
carrier shall be liable to the consignor for the loss or damage to any 
consignment in accordance with the goods forwarding note, where such loss or 
damage has arisen on account of any criminal act of the common carrier, or any 
of his servants or agents. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In any suit brought against the common carrier for the loss, 
damage or non-delivery of consignment, it shall not be necessary for the 
plaintiff to prove that such loss, damage or non-delivery was owing to the 
negligence or criminal act of the common carrier, or any of his servants or 
agents. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where any consignment has been detained for examination or 
scrutiny by a competent authority and upon such examination or scrutiny it is 
found that certain prohibited goods or goods on which due tax not paid or 
insufficiently paid have been entrusted to the common carrier by the consignor 
which have not been described in the goods forwarding note, the cost of such 
examination or scrutiny shall be borne by the consignor and the common carrier 
shall not be liable for any loss, damage or deterioration caused by such 
detention of the consignment for examination or scrutiny: 
 Provided that the onus of proving that such incorrect 
description of goods in the goods forwarding note was received from the 
consignor shall be on the common carrier. 
 Explanation. For the purposes of this section, 
competent authority means any person or authority who is empowered to examine 
or scrutinize goods by or under any law for the time being in force to secure 
compliance of provisions of that law. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Provision for carriage of goods of dangerous or 
hazardous nature to human life. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No goods of dangerous or hazardous 
nature to human life shall be carried by a common carrier except in accordance 
with such procedure and after complying with such safeguards as may be 
prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, 
specify the goods of dangerous or hazardous nature to human life and the label 
or class of labels to be carried in, or displayed on, the motor vehicle or such 
goods in the course of transportation. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, every common carrier shall scrutinise and ensure before 
starting transportation of any consignment containing goods of dangerous or 
hazardous nature to human life that the consignment is covered by, one or more 
insurance policies under a contract of insurance in respect of such goods 
providing relief in case of death or injury to a person or damage to any 
property or the consignment, if an accident takes place. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Power of Central Government to 
prohibit carriage of certain class of goods. </title>The Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, in public interest, the 
goods or class or classes of goods which shall not be carried by a common 
carrier. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Right of common carrier in case of consignee's 
default. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If the consignee fails to take delivery of any 
consignment of goods within a period of thirty days from the date of notice 
given by the common carrier, such consignment may be deemed as unclaimed: 
 Provided that in case of perishable consignment, the period of 
thirty days shall not apply and the consignment shall be deemed unclaimed after 
a period of twenty-four hours of service of notice or any lesser period as may 
be mutually agreed to by and between the common carrier and the consignor. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of an unclaimed consignment under sub-section 
(1), the common carrier may, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> if such consignment is perishable in nature, have the 
  right to sell the consignment; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if such consignment is not perishable in nature, cause a 
  notice to be served upon the consignee or upon the consignor if the consignee 
  is not available, requiring him to remove the goods within a period of fifteen 
  days from the date of receipt of the notice and in case of failure to comply 
  with the notice, the common carrier shall have the right to sell such 
  consignment without any further notice to the consignee or the consignor, as 
  the case may be. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The common carrier shall, out of the sale proceeds received 
under sub-section (2), retain a sum equal to the freight, storage and other 
charges due including expenses incurred for the sale, and the surplus, if any, 
from such sale proceeds shall be returned to the consignee or the consignor, as 
the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Unless otherwise agreed upon between the common carrier and 
consignor, the common carrier shall be entitled to detain or dispose off the 
consignment in part or full to recover his dues in the event of the consignee 
failing to make payment of the freight and other charges payable to the common 
carrier at the time of taking delivery. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Notice for institution of a suit. 
</title>No suit or other legal proceeding shall be instituted against a common 
carrier for any loss of, or damage to, the consignment, unless notice in writing 
of the loss or damage to the consignment has been served on the common carrier 
before the institution of the suit or other legal proceeding and within one 
hundred and eighty days from the date of booking of the consignment by the 
consignor. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> General responsibility of common carrier. 
</title>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, a common carrier shall be 
responsible for the loss, destruction, damage or deterioration in transit or 
non-delivery of any consignment entrusted to him for carriage, arising from any 
cause except the following, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> act of God; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> act of war or public enemy; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> riots and civil commotion; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> arrest, restraint or seizure under legal process; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> order or restriction or prohibition imposed by the Central 
  Government or a State Government or by an officer or authority subordinate to 
  the Central Government or a State Government authorised by it in this behalf: 
  
 Provided that the common carrier shall not be relieved of its 
  responsibility for the loss, destruction, damage, deterioration or 
  non-delivery of the consignment if the common 
 loss, destruction, damage, deterioration or non-delivery of 
  the consignment if the common carrier could have avoided such loss, 
  destruction, damage or deterioration or non-delivery had the common carrier 
  exercised due deligence and care in the carriage of the consignment. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Punishment for contravention in relation to 
non-registration, carrying goods of dangerous or hazardous nature, or prohibited 
goods. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 3, section 13 
or a notification issued under section 14 shall be punishable for the first 
offence with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and for the second 
or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the person committing an offence under this Act is a 
company, every person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge 
of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was 
committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to 
prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that 
the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer 
shall be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 
 Explanation. For the purpose of this section, 
 <subsection><number>a</number> company means any body corporate and includes a firm or 
  other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> director, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the 
  firm. </subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Composition of offences. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any offence 
committed under section 18, may either before or after the institution of the 
prosecution, be compounded by such officers or authorities and for such amount 
as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an offence has been compounded under sub-section (1), 
the offender shall be discharged and no further proceedings shall be taken 
against him in respect of such offence. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Power to make rules. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying 
out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the form and manner of making an application for grant or 
  renewal of a certificate of registration for main office and branch office and 
  the fee thereof under sub-section (2) and (3) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the other conditions of eligibility which are required to 
  be fulfilled by an applicant under clause (d) of sub-section (4) of section 4; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the form in which and the conditions subject to which 
  certificate of registration or renewal may be granted under sub-section (5) of 
  section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the form and manner of maintaining a register under clause 
  (a) of sub-section (7) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the information and return which may be furnished to the 
  registering authority and the transport research wing under clause (c) of 
  sub-section (7) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> fee for submitting the memorandum of appeal under 
  sub-section (2) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the form and manner in which a goods forwarding note shall 
  be executed by the consignor under sub-section (1) of section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the form and manner in which a common carrier shall issue 
  goods receipts under sub-section (1) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> liability of the common carrier for loss of, or damage to 
  any consignment under sub-section (1) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the procedure and safeguards to be complied with for 
  carrying goods of dangerous or hazardous nature under sub-section (1) of 
  section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the specification of the goods of dangerous or hazardous 
  nature to human life and the label or class of labels to be carried or 
  displayed in or on the motor vehicle or on such goods in the course of their 
  transportation under sub-section (2) of section 13; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
  prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under this section and every notification 
issued under section 14 shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made or 
issued, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or the notification, or both Houses 
 agree that the rule or the notification should not be made or 
issued, the rule or the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or notification. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Power to remove difficulties. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If any 
difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central 
Government may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, 
make such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear 
to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty: 
 Provided that no such order shall be made under this section 
after the expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as 
soon as may be, after it is made, before each House of Parliament. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Repeal and saving. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Carriers Act, 
1865 (3 of 1865), is hereby repealed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding the repeal of the Carriers Act, 1865 (3 of 
1865), anything done or any action taken under the said Act shall, in so far as 
such thing or action is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the provisions of this Act and shall 
continue in force accordingly until superseded by anything done or any action 
taken under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The mention of particular matters in this section shall not 
be held to prejudice or affect the general application of section 6 of the 
General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) with regard to the effect of repeals. 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 1-3-2011,  vide   S.O. 1738(E), dated 20th July, 2010 and S.O. 2001(E), dated 13th August, 2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>