<act><title>


The Qualifications, Powers and Functions of 
Chief Electrical Inspector and Electrical 
Inspectors Rules, 20061</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Qualifications, Powers and Functions of Chief 
Electrical Inspector and Electrical Inspectors Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Electricity Act, 2003;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “Appellate 
Authority” in respect of an appeal against the order of an Electrical Inspector, 
means the Chief Electrical Inspector, and in respect of an appeal against the 
order of the Chief Electrical Inspector, means the Central Government.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “Section” 
means section of the Act.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “Inspector” 
means a Chief Electrical Inspector or Electrical Inspector as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expression 
used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Electricity Act, 2003 (36 
of 2003), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Applicability of 
rules.—These 
rules shall apply in respect of following:
 <section>        
<number>i</number>  a generating company wholly or partly owned by the Central 
Government;
 </section><section>        
<number>ii</number>  any inter-State generation, transmission, trading or supply of 
electricity and with respect to any mines, oil-fields, railways, national 
highways, airports, telegraphs, broadcasting stations and any works of defence, 
dockyard, nuclear power installations;
 </section><section>       
<number>iii</number>  National Load Despatch Centre and Regional Load Despatch Centre; 
and
 </section><section>       
<number>iv</number>  any works or electric installation belonging to the Central 
Government or under its control.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Qualification for 
Chief Electrical Inspector.—No 
person shall be appointed to be a Chief Electrical Inspector unless—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  he possesses a 
degree in electrical engineering or its equivalent from a recognized University 
or Institution; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  he has been 
regularly engaged for a period of at least twenty years in the practice of 
electrical engineering of which not less than two years have been spent in an 
electrical or mechanical engineering workshop or in generation or transmission 
or distribution of electricity, or in the administration of the Act and rules 
thereunder, in a position of responsibility.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Qualifications for 
Electrical Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall be appointed to be an Electrical Inspector unless—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  he possesses a 
degree in Electrical Engineering or its equivalent from a recognized University 
or Institution; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  he has been 
regularly engaged for a period of at least ten years in the practice of 
electrical engineering, of which not less than one year has been spent in an 
electrical or mechanical engineering workshop or in generation or transmission 
or distribution of electricity, or in the administration of the Act and rules 
thereunder, in a position of responsibility.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The person appointed 
as Electrical Inspector shall undergo such training as the Central Government 
may consider it necessary for the purpose and such training shall be completed 
to the satisfaction of the Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Powers of the Chief 
Electrical Inspector and Electrical Inspector.—The 
Chief Electrical Inspector and the Electrical Inspector shall have powers to 
inspect the works and electrical installations in his area in respect of which, 
such an Inspector has been directed by the Central Government to exercise his 
powers and perform functions under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of the section 162 of the 
Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Powers of the Chief 
Electrical Inspector and Electrical Inspector.—The 
Chief Electrical Inspector and the Electrical Inspector shall have powers to 
inspect the works and electrical installations in his area in respect of which, 
such an Inspector has been directed by the Central Government to exercise his 
powers and perform functions under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of the section 162 of the 
Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Powers of entry and 
inspection.—For 
carrying out inspections as referred to in rule 6 above,—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  The Inspector 
may enter, inspect and examine any place, carriage or vessel in which he has 
reason to believe that there is any appliance or apparatus used in the 
generation, transmission, transformation, conversion, distribution or use of 
energy and may carry out tests therein.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  Every 
supplier, consumer, owner and occupier shall afford all reasonable facilities to 
any such Inspector to make such examinations and tests as may be necessary to 
satisfy himself as to the due observance of the safety regulations as specified 
by the Authority under section 53 of the Act. The Indian Electricity Rules, 1956 
made under section 37 of the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (now repealed) shall 
continue to be in force till the regulations under section 53 of the Act are 
made.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  An Inspector 
may require a supplier of the electricity to submit to him a list of all persons 
supplied with energy by him, the addresses at which such energy is supplied, the 
month of connecting services, the voltage of supply, the connected load and the 
purpose of supply and the supplier shall comply with such requisitions.
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  Every licensee 
and every owner of a generating station shall, if required so to do by an 
Inspector, provide reasonable means for carrying out all tests, specified under 
the Act or regulations thereunder, of the appliances or apparatus used for the 
supply or use of energy by him, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  Upon such 
inspection, an Inspector may serve an order, within 15 days from the date of 
such inspection, in the Form A, to any licensee, consumer, owner or occupier, 
calling upon him to comply with any specified regulation and the person so 
served shall thereupon comply with the order within the period specified 
therein, and shall report in writing to the Inspector serving the order 
mentioning therein as to when the order has been complied with:
 
Provided that, if within 
the period specified in the aforesaid order an appeal is filed against the order 
by the person on whom such order has been served, the appellate authority may 
suspend its operation pending the decision of the appeal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal against an order served under these rules shall lie—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if the order 
is served by an Electrical Inspector, to the Chief Electrical Inspector;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if the order 
is served by a Chief Electrical Inspector, to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of an 
order of Chief Electrical Inspector on an appeal preferred to him under clause 
(a) of sub-rule (1), a further appeal shall lie to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal made 
under sub-rule (1) shall be in writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the 
order appealed against and shall be presented within three months of the date on 
which such order has been served or delivered, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An appeal shall be 
disposed off within ninety days from the date of receipt of the appeal.
</section></article><form>
 




The Qualifications, Powers and Functions of  

Chief Electrical Inspector and Electrical  

Inspectors Rules, 2006
 


 
 




FORM A 
 


FORM OF ORDER
 


To
 


1. Whereas the installation 
was inspected on………….. and whereas it appears to me that you have not complied 
with the rules made under sub-section (1) of section 162 and the regulations 
made under section 53 of the Act, in the following respect (particulars to be 
given where necessary) namely……… you are hereby called upon to comply with the 
said rule(s)/regulations(s) on or before………… day of……….. and to report 
compliance in writing to me.
 


2.   An appeal may be filed 
against this order under rule 8 of the aforesaid Rules, within three months of 
the date on which this order is served or delivered but this order must be 
complied with, notwithstanding such appeal, unless the appellate authority on or 
before the date specified in paragraph above, suspends its operation.
 


Dated at………….
 


The………….. day 
of………………….                                                                                              
Signature
 



                                                                                                                        
      Chief Electrical Inspector or  

                                                                                                                              
               Electrical Inspector
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>