<act><title>

The 
    Sale of Goods Act, 1930</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the 

    1[***] Sale of Goods 
    Act, 1930.
 


    2[(2) It extends to 
    the whole of India 

    3[except the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir].] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on the 1st day of July, 1930. 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    “buyer” means a person who buys 
    or agrees to buy goods;  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    “delivery” means voluntary 
    transfer of possession from one person to another;  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    goods are said to be in a 
    “deliverable state” when they are in such state that the buyer would under 
    the contract be bound to take delivery of them;  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    “document of title to goods” 
    includes a bill of lading, dock-warrant, warehouse keeper’s certificate, 
    wharfingers’ certificate, railway receipt, 
1[multimodal 
    transport document,] warrant or order for the delivery of goods and any 
    other document used in the ordinary course of business as proof of the 
    possession or control of goods, or authorising or purporting to authorise, 
    either by endorsement or by delivery, the possessor of the document to 
    transfer or receive goods thereby represented;  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    “fault” means wrongful act or 
    default;  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>    “future goods” means goods to be 
    manufactured or produced or acquired by the seller after the making of the 
    contract of sale;  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>    “goods” means every kind of 
    movable property other than actionable claims and money; and includes stock 
    and shares, growing crops, grass, and things attached to or forming part of 
    the land which are agreed to be severed before sale or under the contract of 
    sale;  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>    a person is said to be 
    “insolvent” who has ceased to pay his debts in the ordinary course of 
    business, or cannot pay his debts as they become due, whether he has 
    committed an act of insolvency or not;  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>    “mercantile agent” means a 
    mercantile agent having in the customary course of business as such agent 
    authority either to sell goods, or to consign goods for the purposes of 
    sale, or to buy goods, or to raise money on the security of goods;  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number>    “price” means the money 
    consideration for a sale of goods;  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number>    “property” means the general 
    property in goods, and not merely a special property;  
 </section><section>
<number>12</number>    “quality of goods” includes 
    their state or condition;  
 </section><section>
<number>13</number>    “seller” means a person who 
    sells or agrees to sell goods;  
 </section><section>
<number>14</number>    “specific goods” means goods 
    identified and agreed upon at the time a contract of sale is made; and  
 </section><section>
<number>15</number>    expressions used but not defined 
    in this Act and defined in the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), have 
    the meanings assigned to them in that Act.  
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Application of provisions of Act 9 of 1872.—The 
    unrepealed provisions of the Indian Contract Act, 1872, save in so far as 
    they are inconsistent with the express provisions of this Act, shall 
    continue to apply to contracts for the sale of goods.  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Sale and agreement to sell.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A contract of sale of goods is a contract whereby the seller transfers or 
    agrees to transfer the property in goods to the buyer for a price. There may 
    be a contract of sale between one part-owner and another.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    contract of sale may be absolute or conditional.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where under a contract of sale the property in the goods is transferred from 
    the seller to the buyer, the contract is called a sale, but where the 
    transfer of the property in the goods is to take place at a future time or 
    subject to some condition thereafter to be fulfilled, the contract is called 
    an agreement to sell.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An 
    agreement to sell becomes a sale when the time elapses or the conditions are 
    fulfilled subject to which the property in the goods is to be transferred.  
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Contract of sale how made.—
<section><number>1</number> A contract of sale is made by 
      an offer to buy or sell goods for a price and the acceptance of such 
      offer. The contract may provide for the immediate delivery of the goods or 
      immediate payment of the price or both, or for the delivery or payment by 
      instalments, or that the delivery or payment or both shall be 
      postponed.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in 
      force, a contract of sale may be made in writing or by word of mouth, or 
      partly in writing and partly by word of mouth or may be implied from the 
      conduct of the parties.  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Existing or future goods.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The goods which form the subject of a contract of sale may be either 
    existing goods, owned or possessed by the seller, or future goods.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    There may be a contract for the sale of goods the acquisition of which by 
    the seller depends upon a contingency which may or may not happen.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where by a contract of sale the seller purports to effect a present sale of 
    future goods, the contract operates as an agreement to sell the goods.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Goods perishing before making of 
      contract.—Where there is a contract for the sale of specific goods, the 
      contract is void if the goods without the knowledge of the seller have, at 
      the time when the contract was made, perished or become so damaged as no 
      longer to answer to their description contract.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Goods perishing before sale but after agreement to sell.—Where 
    there is an agreement to sell specific goods, and subsequently the goods 
    without any fault on the part of the seller or buyer perish or become so 
    damaged as no longer to answer to their description in the agreement before 
    the risk passes to the buyer, the agreement is thereby avoided.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Ascertainment of price.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The price in a contract of sale may be fixed by the contract or may be left 
    to be fixed in manner thereby agreed or may be determined by the course of 
    dealing between the parties.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the price is not determined in accordance with the foregoing 
    provisions, the buyer shall pay the seller a reasonable price. What is a 
    reasonable price is a question of fact dependent on the circumstances of 
    each particular case.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Agreement to sell at valuation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where there is an agreement to sell goods on the terms that the price is to 
    be fixed by the valuation of a third party and such third party cannot or 
    does not make such valuation, the agreement is thereby avoided:  
 
Provided 
    that, if the goods or any part thereof have been delivered to, and 
    appropriated by, the buyer, he shall pay a reasonable price therefor.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where such third party is prevented from making the valuation by the fault 
    of the seller or buyer, the party not in fault may maintain a suit for 
    damages against the party in fault.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Stipulations as to time.—Unless 
    a different intention appears from the terms of the contract, stipulations 
    as to time of payment are not deemed to be of the essence of a contract of 
    sale. Whether any other stipulation as to time is of the essence of the 
    contract or not depends on the terms of the contract.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Condition and warranty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A stipulation in a contract of sale with reference to goods which are the 
    subject thereof may be a condition or a warranty.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    condition is a stipulation essential to the main purpose of the contract, 
    the breach of which gives rise to a right to treat the contract as 
    repudiated.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    warranty is a stipulation collateral to the main purpose of the contract, 
    the breach of which gives rise to a claim for damages but not to a right to 
    reject the goods and treat the contract as repudiated.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Whether a stipulation in a contract of sale is a condition or a warranty 
    depends in each case on the construction of the contract. A stipulation may 
    be a condition, though called a warranty in the contract.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    When condition to be treated as warranty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a contract of sale is subject to any condition to be fulfilled by the 
    seller, the buyer may waive the condition or elect to treat the breach of 
    the condition as a breach of warranty and not as a ground for treating the 
    contract as repudiated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a contract of sale is not severable and the buyer has accepted the 
    goods or part thereof, 

    1[***] the breach of 
    any condition to be fulfilled by the seller can only be treated as a breach 
    of warranty and not as a ground for rejecting the goods and treating the 
    contract as repudiated, unless there is a term of the contract, express or 
    implied, to that effect.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall affect the case of any condition or warranty 
    fulfilment of which is excused by law by reason of impossibility or 
    otherwise.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Implied undertaking as to title, etc.—In 
    a contract of sale, unless the circumstances of the contract are such as to 
    show a different intention there is—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    an implied condition on the part 
    of the seller that, in the case of a sale, he has a right to sell the goods 
    and that, in the case of an agreement to sell, he will have a right to sell 
    the goods at the time when the property is to pass;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    an implied warranty that the 
    buyer shall have and enjoy quiet possession of the goods;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    an implied warranty that the 
    goods shall be free from any charge or encumbrance in favour of any third 
    party not declared or known to the buyer before or at the time when the 
    contract is made.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Sale by description.—Where 
    there is a contract for the sale of goods by description, there is an 
    implied condition that the goods shall correspond with the description; and, 
    if the sale is by sample as well as by description, it is not sufficient 
    that the bulk of the goods correspond with the sample if the goods do not 
    also correspond with the description.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Implied conditions as to quality or fitness.— 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and of any other law for the time 
    being in force, there is no implied warranty or condition as to the quality 
    or fitness for any particular purpose of goods supplied under a contract of 
    sale, except as follows:—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Where the buyer, expressly or by 
    implication, makes known to the seller the particular purpose for which the 
    goods are required, so as to show that the buyer relies on the seller’s 
    skill or judgment, and the goods are of a description which it is in the 
    course of the seller’s business to supply (whether he is the manufacturer or 
    producer or not), there is an implied condition that the goods shall be 
    reasonably fit for such purpose:  
 
Provided that, in the case of a contract 
    for the sale of a specified article under its patent or other trade name, 
    there is no implied condition as to its fitness for any particular purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Where goods are bought by 
    description from a seller who deals in goods of that description (whether he 
    is the manufacturer or producer or not), there is an implied condition that 
    the goods shall be of merchantable quality:  
 
Provided that, if the buyer has examined 
    the goods, there shall be no implied condition as regards defects which such 
    examination ought to have revealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    An implied warranty or condition 
    as to quality or fitness for a particular purpose may be annexed by the 
    usage of trade.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    An express warranty or condition 
    does not negative a warranty or condition implied by this Act unless 
    inconsistent therewith.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Sale by sample.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A contract of sale is a contract for sale by sample where there is a term in 
    the contract, express or implied, to that effect.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the case of a contract for sale by sample there is an implied condition—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the bulk shall correspond 
    with the sample in quality;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the buyer shall have a 
    reasonable opportunity of comparing the bulk with the sample;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the goods shall be free from 
    any defect, rendering them unmerchantable, which would not be apparent on 
    reasonable examination of the sample.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Goods must be ascertained.—Where 
    there is a contract for the sale of unascertained goods, no property in the 
    goods is transferred to the buyer unless and until the goods are 
    ascertained.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Property passes when intended to pass.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where there is a contract for the sale of specific or ascertained goods the 
    property in them is transferred to the buyer at such time as the parties to 
    the contract intend it to be transferred.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of ascertaining the intention of the parties regard shall be had 
    to the terms of the contract, the conduct of the parties and the 
    circumstances of the case.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Unless a different intention appears, the rules contained in sections 20 to 
    24 are rules for ascertaining the intention of the parties as to the time at 
    which the property in the goods is to pass to the buyer.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Specific goods in a deliverable state.—Where 
    there is an unconditional contract for the sale of specific goods in a 
    deliverable state, the property in the goods passes to the buyer when the 
    contract is made, and it is immaterial whether the time of payment of the 
    price or the time of delivery of the goods, or both, is postponed.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number>
Specific goods to be put into a deliverable state.—Where there is a 
    contract for the sale of specific goods and the seller is bound to do 
    something to the goods for the purpose of putting them into a deliverable 
    state, the property does not pass until such thing is done and the buyer has 
    notice thereof.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Specific goods in a deliverable state, when the seller has to do anything 
    thereto in order to ascertain price.—Where 
    there is a contract for the sale of specific goods in a deliverable state, 
    but the seller is bound to weigh, measure, test or do some other act or 
    thing with reference to the goods for the purpose of ascertaining the price, 
    the property does not pass until such act or thing is done and the buyer has 
    notice thereof.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Sale of unascertained goods and appropriation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where there is a contract for the sale of unascertained or future goods by 
    description and goods of that description and in a deliverable state are 
    unconditionally appropriated to the contract, either by the seller with the 
    assent of the buyer or by the buyer with the assent of the seller, the 
    property in the goods thereupon passes to the buyer. Such assent may be 
    express or implied, and may be given either before or after the 
    appropriation is made.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Delivery to carrier.—Where, in pursuance of the contract, the seller 
    delivers the goods to the buyer or to a carrier or other bailee (whether 
    named by the buyer or not) for the purpose of transmission to the buyer, and 
    does not reserve the right of disposal, he is deemed to have unconditionally 
    appropriated the goods to the contract.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number>
Goods sent on approval or “on sale or return”.—When goods are 
    delivered to the buyer on approval or “on sale or return” or other similar 
    terms, the property therein passes to the buyer—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    when he signifies his approval or 
    acceptance to the seller or does any other act adopting the transaction;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if he does not signify his 
    approval or acceptance to the seller but retains the goods without giving 
    notice of rejection, then, if a time has been fixed for the return of the 
    goods, on the expiration of such time, and, if no time has been fixed, on 
    the expiration of a reasonable time. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number>
Goods sent on approval or “on sale or return”.—When goods are 
    delivered to the buyer on approval or “on sale or return” or other similar 
    terms, the property therein passes to the buyer—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    when he signifies his approval or 
    acceptance to the seller or does any other act adopting the transaction;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if he does not signify his 
    approval or acceptance to the seller but retains the goods without giving 
    notice of rejection, then, if a time has been fixed for the return of the 
    goods, on the expiration of such time, and, if no time has been fixed, on 
    the expiration of a reasonable time. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number>
Reservation of right of disposal.—
<section><number>1</number> Where there is a contract for 
    the sale of specific goods or where goods are subsequently appropriated to 
    the contract, the seller may, by the terms of the contract or appropriation, 
    reserve the right of disposal of the goods until certain conditions are 
    fulfilled. In such case, notwithstanding the delivery of the goods to a 
    buyer, or to a carrier or other bailee for the purpose of transmission to 
    the buyer, the property in the goods does not pass to the buyer until the 
    conditions imposed by the seller are fulfilled.  
 


    1[(2) Where goods are 
    shipped or delivered to a railway administration for carriage by railway and 
    by the bill of lading or railway receipts, as the case may be, the goods are 
    deliverable to the order of the seller or his agent, the seller is prima 
    facie deemed to reserve the right of disposal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the seller of goods draws on the buyer for the price and transmits to 
    the buyer the bill of exchange together with the bill of lading or, as the 
    case may be, the railway receipt, to secure acceptance or payment of the 
    bill of exchange, the buyer is bound to return the bill of lading or the 
    railway receipt if he does not honour the bill of exchange; and, if he 
    wrongfully retains the bill of lading or the railway receipt, the property 
    in the goods does not pass to him.  
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this section, the expressions “railway” and “railway administra-tion” shall 
    have the meanings respectively assigned to them under the 

    2Indian Railways Act, 
    1890 (9 of 1890).]  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number>
Risk prima facie passes with property.—Unless otherwise 
    agreed, the goods remain at the seller’s risk until the property therein is 
    transferred to the buyer, but when the property therein is transferred to 
    the buyer, the goods are at the buyer’s risk whether delivery has been made 
    or not:  
 
Provided 
    that, where delivery has been delayed through the fault of either buyer or 
    seller, the goods are at the risk of the party in fault as regards any loss 
    which might not have occurred but for such fault:  
 
Provided 
    also that nothing in this section shall affect the duties or liabilities of 
    either seller or buyer as bailee of the goods of the other party.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Sale by person not the owner.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act and of any other law for the time being in 
    force, where goods are sold by a person who is not the owner thereof and who 
    does not sell them under the authority or with the consent of the owner, the 
    buyer acquires no better title to the goods than the seller had, unless the 
    owner of the goods is by his conduct precluded from denying the seller’s 
    authority to sell:  
 
Provided 
    that, where a mercantile agent is, with the consent of the owner, in 
    possession of the goods or of a document of title to the goods, any sale 
    made by him, when acting in the ordinary course of business of a mercantile 
    agent, shall be as valid as if he were expressly authorised by the owner of 
    the goods to make the same; provided that the buyer acts in good faith and 
    has not at the time of the contract of sale notice that the seller has no 
    authority to sell.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number>
Sale by one of joint owners.—If one of several joint owners of goods 
    has the sole possession of them by permission of the co-owners, the property 
    in the goods is transferred to any person who buys them of such joint owner 
    in good faith and has not at the time of the contract of sale notice that 
    the seller has no authority to sell.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number>
Sale by person in possession under voidable contract.—When the seller 
    of goods has obtained possession thereof under a contract voidable under 
    section 19 or section 19A of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), but 
    the contract has not been rescinded at the time of the sale, the buyer 
    acquires a good title to the goods, provided he buys them in good faith and 
    without notice of the seller’s defect of title.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number>
Seller or buyer in possession after sale.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a person, having 
    sold goods, continues or is in possession of the goods or of the documents 
    of title to the goods, the delivery or transfer by that person or by a 
    mercantile agent acting for him of the goods or documents of title under any 
    sale, pledge or other disposition thereof to any person receiving the same 
    in good faith and without notice of the previous sale shall have the same 
    effect as if the person making the delivery or transfer were expressly 
    authorised by the owner of the goods to make the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a person, having bought or agreed to buy goods, obtains with the 
    consent of the seller, possession of the goods or the documents of title to 
    the goods, the delivery or transfer by that person or by a mercantile agent 
    acting for him, of the goods or documents of title under any sale, pledge or 
    other disposition thereof to any person receiving the same in good faith and 
    without notice of any lien or other right of the original seller in respect 
    of the goods shall have effect as if such lien or right did not exist.  
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number>
Duties of seller and buyer.—It is the duty of the seller to deliver 
    the goods and of the buyer to accept and pay for them, in accordance with 
    the terms of the contract of sale.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number>
Payment and delivery are concurrent conditions.—Unless otherwise 
    agreed, delivery of the goods and payment of the price are concurrent 
    conditions, that is to say, the seller shall be ready and willing to give 
    possession of the goods to the buyer in exchange for the price, and the 
    buyer shall be ready and willing to pay the price in exchange for possession 
    of the goods.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number>
Delivery.—Delivery of goods sold may be made by doing anything which 
    the parties agree shall be treated as delivery or which has the effect of 
    putting the goods in the possession of the buyer or of any person authorised 
    to hold them on his behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
34.
    Effect of part delivery.—A delivery of part of goods, in progress of 
    the delivery of the whole has the same effect, for the purpose of passing 
    the property in such goods, as a delivery of the whole; but a delivery of 
    part of the goods, with an intention of severing it from the whole, does not 
    operate as a delivery of the remainder.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number>
Buyer to apply for delivery.—Apart from any express contract, the 
    seller of goods is not bound to deliver them until the buyer applies for 
    delivery.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number>
Rules as to delivery.—
<section><number>1</number> Whether it is for the buyer to take 
    possession of the goods or for the seller to send them to the buyer is a 
    question depending in each case on the contract, express or implied, between 
    the parties. Apart from any such contract, goods sold are to be delivered at 
    the place at which they are at the time of the sale, and goods agreed to be 
    sold are to be delivered at the place at which they are at the time of the 
    agreement to sell or if not then in existence, at the place at which they 
    are manufactured or produced.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where under the contract of sale the seller is bound to send the goods to 
    the buyer, but no time for sending them is fixed, the seller is bound to 
    send them within a reasonable time.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the goods at the time of sale are in the possession of a third person, 
    there is no delivery by seller to buyer unless and until such third person 
    acknowledges to the buyer that he holds the goods on his behalf:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this section shall affect the operation of the issue or 
    transfer of any document of title to goods.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Demand or tender of delivery may be treated as ineffectual unless made at a 
    reasonable hour. What is a reasonable hour is a question of fact.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Unless otherwise agreed, the expenses of and incidental to putting the goods 
    into a deliverable state shall be borne by the seller.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Delivery of wrong quantity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the seller delivers to the buyer a quantity of goods less than he 
    contracted to sell, the buyer may reject them, but if the buyer accepts the 
    goods so delivered he shall pay for them at the contract rate.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the seller delivers to the buyer a quantity of goods larger than he 
    contracted to sell, the buyer may accept the goods included in the contract 
    and reject the rest, or he may reject the whole. If the buyer accepts the 
    whole of the goods so delivered, he shall pay for them at the contract rate.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the seller delivers to the buyer the goods he contracted to sell mixed 
    with goods of a different description not included in the contract, the 
    buyer may accept the goods which are in accordance with the contract and 
    reject the rest, or may reject the whole. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    provisions of this section are subject to any usage of trade, special 
    agreement or course of dealing between the parties.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number>
Instalment deliveries.—
<section><number>1</number> Unless otherwise agreed, the buyer of 
    goods is not bound to accept delivery thereof by instalments.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where there is a contract for the sale of goods to be delivered by stated 
    instalments which are to be separately paid for, and the seller makes no 
    delivery or defective delivery in respect of one or more instalments, or the 
    buyer neglects or refuses to take delivery of or pay for one or more 
    instalments, it is a question in each case depending on the terms of the 
    contract and the circumstances of the case, whether the breach of contract 
    is a repudiation of the whole contract, or whether it is a severable breach 
    giving rise to a claim for compensation, but not to a right to treat the 
    whole contract as repudiated.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number>
Delivery to carrier of wharfinger.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, in pursuance of a 
    contract of sale, the seller is authorised or required to send the goods to 
    the buyer, delivery of the goods to a carrier, whether named by the buyer or 
    not, for the purpose of transmission to the buyer, or delivery of the goods 
    to a wharfinger for safe custody, is prima facie deemed to be a 
    delivery of the goods to the buyer.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless otherwise authorised by the buyer, the seller shall make such 
    contract with the carrier or wharfinger on behalf of the buyer as may be 
    reasonable having regard to the nature of the goods and the other 
    circumstances of the case. If the seller omits so to do, and the goods are 
    lost or damaged in course of transit or whilst in the custody of the 
    wharfinger, the buyer may decline to treat the delivery to the carrier or 
    wharfinger, as a delivery to himself, or may hold the seller responsible in 
    damages.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Unless otherwise agreed, where goods are sent by the seller to the buyer by 
    a route involving sea transit, in circumstances in which it is usual to 
    insure, the seller shall give such notice to the buyer as may enable him to 
    insure them during their sea transit and if the seller fails so to do, the 
    goods shall be deemed to be at his risk during such sea transit.  
 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Risk where goods are delivered at distant place.—Where 
    the seller of goods agrees to deliver them at his own risk at a place other 
    than that where they are when sold, the buyer shall, nevertheless, unless 
    otherwise agreed, take any risk of deterioration in the goods necessarily 
    incident to the course of transit.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Buyer’s right of examining the goods.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where goods are delivered to the buyer which he has not previously examined, 
    he is not deemed to have accepted them unless and until he has had a 
    reasonable opportunity of examining them for the purpose of ascertaining 
    whether they are in conformity with the contract.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless otherwise agreed, when the seller tenders delivery of goods to the 
    buyer, he is bound, on request, to afford the buyer a reasonable opportunity 
    of examining the goods for the purpose of ascertaining whether they are in 
    conformity with the contract.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Buyer’s right of examining the goods.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where goods are delivered to the buyer which he has not previously examined, 
    he is not deemed to have accepted them unless and until he has had a 
    reasonable opportunity of examining them for the purpose of ascertaining 
    whether they are in conformity with the contract.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless otherwise agreed, when the seller tenders delivery of goods to the 
    buyer, he is bound, on request, to afford the buyer a reasonable opportunity 
    of examining the goods for the purpose of ascertaining whether they are in 
    conformity with the contract.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Acceptance.—The 
    buyer is deemed to have accepted the goods when he intimates to the seller 
    that he has accepted them, or when the goods have been delivered to him and 
    he does any act in relation to them which is inconsistent with the ownership 
    of the seller, or when, after the lapse of a reasonable time, he retains the 
    goods without intimating to the seller that he has rejected them.  
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Buyer not bound to return rejected goods.—Unless 
    otherwise agreed, where goods are delivered to the buyer and he refuses to 
    accept them, having the right so to do, he is not bound to return them to 
    the seller, but it is sufficient if he intimates to the seller that he 
    refuses to accept them.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Liability of buyer for neglecting or refusing delivery of goods.—When 
    the seller is ready and willing to deliver the goods and requests the buyer 
    to take delivery, and the buyer does not within a reasonable time after such 
    request take delivery of the goods, he is liable to the seller for any loss 
    occasioned by his neglect or refusal to take delivery and also for a 
    reasonable charge for the care and custody of the goods:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this section shall affect the rights of the seller where the 
    neglect or refusal of the buyer to take delivery amounts to a repudiation of 
    the contract.  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    “Unpaid seller” defined.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The seller of goods is deemed to be an “unpaid seller” within the meaning of 
    this Act—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    when the whole of the price has 
    not been paid or tendered;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    when a bill of exchange or other 
    negotiable instrument has been received as conditional payment, and the 
    condition on which it was received has not been fulfilled by reason of the 
    dishonour of the instrument or otherwise.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    this Chapter, the term “seller” includes any person who is in the position 
    of a seller, as, for instance, an agent of the seller to whom the bill of 
    lading has been endorsed, or a consignor or agent who has himself paid, or 
    is directly responsible for, the price.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    “Unpaid seller” defined.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The seller of goods is deemed to be an “unpaid seller” within the meaning of 
    this Act—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    when the whole of the price has 
    not been paid or tendered;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    when a bill of exchange or other 
    negotiable instrument has been received as conditional payment, and the 
    condition on which it was received has not been fulfilled by reason of the 
    dishonour of the instrument or otherwise.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    this Chapter, the term “seller” includes any person who is in the position 
    of a seller, as, for instance, an agent of the seller to whom the bill of 
    lading has been endorsed, or a consignor or agent who has himself paid, or 
    is directly responsible for, the price.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Unpaid seller’s rights.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and of any law for the time being in 
    force, notwithstanding that the property in the goods may have passed to the 
    buyer, the unpaid seller of goods, as such, has by implication of law—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a lien on the goods for the price 
    while he is in possession of them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in case of the insolvency of the 
    buyer a right of stopping the goods in transit after he has parted with the 
    possession of them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a right of re-sale as limited by 
    this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the property in goods has not passed to the buyer, the unpaid seller 
    has, in addition to his other remedies, a right of withholding delivery 
    similar to and co-extensive with his rights of lien and stoppage in transit 
    where the property has passed to the buyer.  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Unpaid seller’s rights.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and of any law for the time being in 
    force, notwithstanding that the property in the goods may have passed to the 
    buyer, the unpaid seller of goods, as such, has by implication of law—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a lien on the goods for the price 
    while he is in possession of them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in case of the insolvency of the 
    buyer a right of stopping the goods in transit after he has parted with the 
    possession of them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a right of re-sale as limited by 
    this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the property in goods has not passed to the buyer, the unpaid seller 
    has, in addition to his other remedies, a right of withholding delivery 
    similar to and co-extensive with his rights of lien and stoppage in transit 
    where the property has passed to the buyer.  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Seller’s lien.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the unpaid seller of goods who is in 
    possession of them is entitled to retain possession of them until payment or 
    tender of the price in the following cases, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the goods have been sold 
    without any stipulation as to credit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the goods have been sold on 
    credit, but the term of credit has expired;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where the buyer becomes 
    insolvent.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    seller may exercise his right of lien notwithstanding that he is in 
    possession of the goods as agent or bailee for the buyer.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Seller’s lien.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the unpaid seller of goods who is in 
    possession of them is entitled to retain possession of them until payment or 
    tender of the price in the following cases, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the goods have been sold 
    without any stipulation as to credit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the goods have been sold on 
    credit, but the term of credit has expired;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where the buyer becomes 
    insolvent.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    seller may exercise his right of lien notwithstanding that he is in 
    possession of the goods as agent or bailee for the buyer.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Part delivery.—Where 
    an unpaid seller has made part delivery of the goods, he may exercise his 
    right of lien on the remainder, unless such part delivery has been made 
    under such circumstances as to show an agreement to waive the lien.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Termination of lien.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The unpaid seller of goods loses his lien thereon—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    when he delivers the goods to a 
    carrier or other bailee for the purpose of transmission to the buyer without 
    reserving the right of disposal of the goods;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    when the buyer or his agent 
    lawfully obtains possession of the goods;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    by waiver thereof.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    unpaid seller of goods, having a lien thereon, does not lose his lien by 
    reason only that he has obtained a decree for the price of the goods.  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Right of stoppage in transit.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, when the buyer of goods becomes insolvent, 
    the unpaid seller who has parted with the possession of the goods has the 
    right of stopping them in transit, that is to say, he may resume possession 
    of the goods as long as they are in the course of transit, and may retain 
    them until payment or tender of the price.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Duration of transit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Goods are deemed to be in course of transit from the time when they are 
    delivered to a carrier or other bailee for the purpose of transmission to 
    the buyer, until the buyer or his agent in that behalf takes delivery of 
    them from such carrier or other bailee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the buyer or his agent in that behalf obtains delivery of the goods before 
    their arrival at the appointed destination, the transit is at an end.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, 
    after the arrival of the goods at the appointed destination, the carrier or 
    other bailee acknowledges to the buyer or his agent that he holds the goods 
    on his behalf and continues in possession of them as bailee for the buyer or 
    his agent, the transit is at an end and it is immaterial that a further 
    destination for the goods may have been indicated by the buyer.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the goods are rejected by the buyer and the carrier or other bailee 
    continues in possession of them, the transit is not deemed to be at an end, 
    even if the seller has refused to receive them back.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When 
    goods are delivered to a ship chartered by the buyer, it is a question 
    depending on the circumstances of the particular case, whether they are in 
    the possession of the master as a carrier or as agent of the buyer.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where the carrier or other bailee wrongfully refuses to deliver the goods to 
    the buyer or his agent in that behalf, the transit is deemed to be at an 
    end. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Where part delivery of the goods has been made to the buyer or his agent in 
    that behalf, the remainder of the goods may be stopped in transit, unless 
    such part delivery has been given in such circumstances as to show an 
    agreement to give up possession of the whole of the goods.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    How stoppage in transit is effected.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The unpaid seller may exercise his right of stoppage in transit either by 
    taking actual possession of the goods, or by giving notice of his claim to 
    the carrier or other bailee in whose possession the goods are. Such notice 
    may be given either to the person in actual possession of the goods or to 
    his principal. In the latter case the notice, to be effectual, shall be 
    given at such time and in such circumstances, that the principal, by the 
    exercise of reasonable diligence, may communicate it to his servant or agent 
    in time to prevent a delivery to the buyer.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    notice of stoppage in transit is given by the seller to the carrier or other 
    bailee in possession of the goods, he shall re-deliver the goods to, or 
    according to the directions of, the seller. The expenses of such re-delivery 
    shall be borne by the seller.  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Effect of sub-sale or pledge by buyer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the unpaid seller’s right of lien or 
    stoppage in transit is not affected by any sale or other disposition of the 
    goods which the buyer may have made, unless the seller has assented thereto:  
 
Provided 
    that where a document of title to goods has been issued, or lawfully 
    transferred to any person as buyer or owner of the goods, and that person 
    transfers the document to a person who takes the document in good faith and 
    for consideration, then, if such last mentioned transfer was by way of sale, 
    the unpaid seller’s right of lien or stoppage in transit is defeated, and, 
    if such last mentioned transfer was by way of pledge or other disposition 
    for value, the unpaid seller’s right of lien or stoppage in transit can only 
    be exercised subject to the rights of the transferee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the transfer is by way of pledge, the unpaid seller may require the 
    pledgee to have the amount secured by the pledge satisfied in the first 
    instance, as far as possible, out of any other goods or securities of the 
    buyer in the hands of the pledgee and available against the buyer.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Sale not generally rescinded by lien or stoppage in transit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, a contract of sale is not 
    rescinded by the mere exercise by an unpaid seller of his right of lien or 
    stoppage in transit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the goods are of a perishable nature, or where the unpaid seller who 
    has exercised his right of lien or stoppage in transit gives notice to the 
    buyer of his intention to re-sell, the unpaid seller may, if the buyer does 
    not within a reasonable time pay or tender the price, re-sell the goods 
    within a reasonable time and recover from the original buyer damages for any 
    loss occasioned by his breach of contract, but the buyer shall not be 
    entitled to any profit which may occur on the re-sale. If such notice is not 
    given, the unpaid seller shall not be entitled to recover such damages and 
    the buyer shall be entitled to the profit, if any, on the re-sale.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where an unpaid seller who has exercised his right of lien or stoppage in 
    transit re-sells the goods, the buyer acquires a good title thereto as 
    against the original buyer, notwithstanding that no notice of the re-sale 
    has been given to the original buyer.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where the seller expressly reserves a right of re-sale in case the buyer 
    should make default, and, on the buyer making default, re-sells the goods, 
    the original contract of sale is thereby rescinded, but without prejudice to 
    any claim which the seller may have for damages.  
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Suit for price.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where under a contract of sale the property in the goods has passed to the 
    buyer and the buyer wrongfully neglects or refuses to pay for the goods 
    according to the terms of the contract, the seller may sue him for the price 
    of the goods.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where under a contract of sale the price is payable on a day certain 
    irrespective of delivery and the buyer wrongfully neglects or refuses to pay 
    such price, the seller may sue him for the price although the property in 
    the goods has not passed and the goods have not been appropriated to the 
    contract.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Damages for non-acceptance.—Where 
    the buyer wrongfully neglects or refuses to accept and pay for the goods, 
    the seller may sue him for damages for non-acceptance.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Damages for non-delivery.—Where 
    the seller wrongfully neglects or refuses to deliver the goods to the buyer, 
    the buyer may sue the seller for damages for non-delivery.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Specific performance.—Subject 
    to the provisions of Chapter II of the Specific Relief Act, 1877 (1 of 
    1877), in any suit for breach of contract to deliver specific or ascertained 
    goods, the Court may, if it thinks fit, on the application of the plaintiff, 
    by its decree direct that the contract shall be performed specifically, 
    without giving the defendant the option of retaining the goods on payment of 
    damages. The decree may be unconditional, or upon such terms and conditions 
    as to damages, payment of the price, or otherwise, as the Court may deem 
    just, and the application of the plaintiff may be made at any time before 
    the decree.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Remedy for breach of warranty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where there is a breach of warranty by the seller, or where the buyer elects 
    or is compelled to treat any breach of a condition on the part of the seller 
    as a breach of warranty, the buyer is not by reason only of such breach of 
    warranty entitled to reject the goods; but he may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    set up against the seller the 
    breach of warranty in diminution or extinction of the price; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    sue the seller for damages for 
    breach of warranty.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    fact that a buyer has set up a breach of warranty in diminution or 
    extinction of the price does not prevent him from suing for the same breach 
    of warranty if he has suffered further damage.  
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
  
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Repudiation of contract before due date.—Where 
    either party to a contract of sale repudiates the contract before the date 
    of delivery, the other may either treat the contract as subsisting and wait 
    till the date of delivery, or he may treat the contract as rescinded and sue 
    for damages for the breach.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Interest by way of damages and special damages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in this Act shall affect the right of the seller or the buyer to 
    recover interest or special damages in any case where by law interest or 
    special damages may be recoverable, or to recover the money paid where the 
    consideration for the payment of it has failed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the absence of a contract to the contrary, the court may award interest at 
    such rate as it thinks fit on the amount of the price—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to the seller in a suit by him 
    for the amount of the price—from the date of the tender of the goods or from 
    the date on which the price was payable;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to the buyer in a suit by him for 
    the refund of the price in a case of a breach of the contract on the part of 
    the seller—from the date on which the payment was made.  
 
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Exclusion of implied terms and conditions.—Where 
    any right, duty or liability would arise under a contract of sale by 
    implication of law, it may be negatived or varied by express agreement or by 
    the course of dealing between the parties, or by usage, if the usage is such 
    as to bind both parties to the contract.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
  
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Reasonable time a question of fact.—Where 
    in this Act any reference is made to a reasonable time, the question what is 
    a reasonable time is a question of fact.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Auction sale.—In 
    the case of sale by auction—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    where goods are put up for sale 
    in lots, each lot is prima facie deemed to be the subject of a 
    separate contract of sale;  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    the sale is complete when the 
    auctioneer announces its completion by the fall of the hammer or in other 
    customary manner; and, until such announcement is made, any bidder may 
    retract his bid;  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    a right to bid may be reserved 
    expressly by or on behalf of the seller and, where such right is expressly 
    so reserved, but not otherwise, the seller or any one person on his behalf 
    may, subject to the provisions hereinafter contained, bid at the auction;  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    where the sale is not notified to 
    be subject to a right to bid on behalf of the seller, it shall not be lawful 
    for the seller to bid himself or to employ any person to bid at such sale, 
    or for the auctioneer knowingly to take any bid from the seller or any such 
    person; and any sale contravening this rule may be treated as fraudulent by 
    the buyer;  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    the sale may be notified to be 
    subject to a reserved or upset price;  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>    if the seller makes use of 
    pretended bidding to raise the price, the sale is voidable at the option of 
    the buyer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Repeal.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in this Act or in any repeal effected thereby shall affect or be 
    deemed to affect—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any right, title, interest, 
    obligation or liability already acquired, accrued or incurred before the 
    commencement of this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any legal proceedings or remedy 
    in respect of any such right, title, interest, obligation or liability, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    anything done or suffered before 
    the commencement of this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any enactment relating to the 
    sale of goods which is not expressly repealed by this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any rule of law not inconsistent 
    with this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    rules of insolvency relating to contracts for the sale of goods shall 
    continue to apply thereto, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provisions of this Act relating to contracts of sale do not apply to any 
    transaction in the form of a contract of sale which is intended to operate 
    by way of mortgage, pledge, charge or other security.  
  
  
   

 


 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>