<act><title>

THE

Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933</title> 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Children (Pledging of Labour) Act, 1933.
 

1[(2) It extends to the whole of India


2[***].]
 </section><section><number>3</number> This section and sections 2 
and 3 shall come into force at once, and the remaining sections of this Act 
shall come into force on the first day of July, 1933.







</section></article> 
 

THE

Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 
             “an agreement to pledge the labour 
of a child” means an agreement, written or oral, express or implied, whereby the 
parent or guardian of a child, in return for any payment or benefit received or 
to be received by him, undertakes to cause or allow the services of the child to 
be utilised in any employment:
 
             Provided that an agreement made 
without detriment to a child, and not made in consideration of any benefit other 
than reasonable wages to be paid for the child’s services, and terminable at not 
more than a week’s notice, is not an agreement within the meaning of this 
definition;
 
          “child” means a person who is under 
the age of fifteen years; and
 
          “guardian” includes any person having 
legal custody of or control over a child.


</article> 
 THE 
Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933
  
 <article><number>3</number> Agreements contrary to the 
Act to be void.—An agreement to 
pledge the labour of a child shall be void.

</article> 
 

THE

Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933
  
 <article><number>4</number> Penalty for parent or 
guardian making agreement to pledge the labour of a child.—Whoever, 
being the parent or guardian of a child, makes an agreement to pledge the labour 
of that child, shall be punished with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.


</article> 
 

THE

Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933
  
 <article><number>5</number> Penalty for making with a 
parent or guardian an agreement to pledge the labour of a child.—Whoever 
makes with the parent or guardian of a child an agreement whereby such parent or 
guardian pledges the labour of the child shall be punished with fine which may 
extend to two hundred rupees.


</article> 
 

THE

Children 
(pledging of labour) act, 1933
  
 <article><number>6</number> Penalty for employing a 
child whose labour has been pledged.—Whoever, 
knowing or having reason to believe that an agreement has been made to pledge 
the labour of a child, in furtherance of such agreement employs such child, or 
permits such child to be employed in any premises or place under his control, 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>