<act><tid>125349</tid>
<title>THE VICTORIA MEMORIAL ACT, <year>1903</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1903</year>
[ 20th March, <year>1903</year>.]

An Act to provide for the erection and management of the Victoria 
Memorial at Calcutta.

WHEREAS it is intended to erect at Calcutta a building as a 
memorial of the life and reign of Her late Majesty Victoria of the 
United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Queen, Empress of India, 
and for this purpose large sums of money have been subscribed by the 
princes and people of India;

AND WHEREAS at a meeting of subscribers held in Calcutta certain 
persons were appointed a Provisional Executive Committee to take the 
custody of the said moneys;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to make provision for the erection, 
maintenance and management of the memorial and for the appointment of 
a permanent body of Trustees;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1424652</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>105875</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Victoria  
Memorial Act, <year>1903</year>; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>542780</tid>
<number> 2</number> 
<section><tid>561834</tid>
<number>1</number>Trustees. The Trustees of the Victoria Memorial  
 (hereinafter called the Trustees) shall be the following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>256361</tid>
<number>a</number>the Governor of West Bengal, ex officio Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1026793</tid>
<number>b</number>the Chief Justice of the High Court of West Bengal, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1643892</tid>
<number>c</number>three persons to be nominated by the Central 
Government, one of whom shall be a representative of commerce 
and industry, chosen in consultation with the State 
Government of West Bengal and two others chosen from among 
persons who, in the opinion of the Central Government, have 
expert knowledge of the exhibits in the Victoria Memorial or 
are museologists, historians or art historians;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1536450</tid>
<number>d</number>a representative of the Central Government in the 
Ministry concerned with matters relating to the Victoria 
Memorial, ex officio;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" and" and sub- section (2) rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2, for sub- section (1).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1821861</tid>
<number>e</number>a representative of the Central Government in the 
Ministry of Finance, Department' of Expenditure, concerned 
with matters relating to the Victoria Memorial, ex officio; 
the Mayor of the Corporation of Calcutta and where the Cor- 
poration of Calcutta is superseded, the Administrator of that 
Corporation, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413120</tid>
<number>g</number>an officer, not below the rank of the Accountant- 
General nominated by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452499</tid>
<number>h</number>the Secretary to the Government of West Bengal in the 
Department of Education, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>368121</tid>
<number>i</number>four persons (of whom one at least shall be from the  
  general body of subscribers), to be nominated by the Trustees 
from among persons, who, in the opinion of the Trustees, have 
expert knowledge of the exhibits in the Victoria Memorial or 
are museologists, historians or art historians, with the 
approval of the Central Government.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>19500</tid>
<number>2</number>The Trustees shall be a body corporate, with perpetual 
succession by the name of" The Trustees of the Victoria Memorial" and 
a common seal, and in that name shall sue and be sued, and shall have 
power to acquire and hold property, to enter into contracts, and to do 
all acts necessary for and consistent with the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1560016</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All acts done by a majority of those present and voting at 
a meeting of the Trustees, and all acts done in pursuance of a 
majority decision of the Trustees obtained by circulation to the 
Trustees of the matter requiring decision, shall be deemed to be acts 
of the Trustees.]

</section>

<section><tid>1055255</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If any of the Trustees referred to in clauses (b), (d), 
 (e), (f), (g) and (h) of sub- section (1) is unable to attend any 
meeting of the Trustees, he may, with the previous approval of the 
Chairman, authorise in writing a person to do so.]

</section>

<section><tid>1418092</tid>
<number>4</number>No act of the Trustees shall- be deemed to be invalid merely 
by reason of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the 
body of the Trustees.

</section>

<section><tid>1217495</tid>
<number>5</number>In the case of ex officio Trustees the person for the time 
being performing the duties of any of the offices mentioned in sub- 
section (1) shall act as a Trustee.

</section>

<section><tid>1940864</tid>
<number>6</number>The Trustees may appoint a person to act as their Secretary.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1943</year>, s. 2, for the original sub- section (with  
  retrospective effect).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1315231</tid>
<number>7</number>Orders for the payment of money on behalf of the Trustees 
shall be deemed to be sufficiently authenticated if signed by two 
Trustees and countersigned by the Secretary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>294014</tid>
<number>3</number>Property vested in Trustees. All sums of money now in the 
custody ofthe said Provisional Executive Committee and all other 
property, whether movable or immovable, which have been or may 
hereafter be given, bequeathed or otherwise transferred for the 
purposes of the said Memorial or acquired for the said purposes by the 
Trustees shall vest in the Trustees.


</article>



<article><tid>1443280</tid>
<number>4</number>Officers and servants to be public servants. All officers and 
servants employed by the Trustees shall be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>):
Provided that this section shall not apply to persons in the 
service of any contractor employed by the Trustees.

</article>



<article><tid>418606</tid>
<number> 5</number> 
<section><tid>1064164</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by notification in the  
Official Gazette,] make rule 2 to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>763469</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide-

<subsection><tid>1087293</tid>
<number>a</number>for the manner in which Trustees, other than ex officio 
Trustees, shall be appointed, and for the periods of time for 
which such Trustees shall hold office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1627488</tid>
<number>b</number>for the manner in which meetings of the Trustees shall 
be convened, the quorum necessary for the transaction of 
business, and the procedure at such meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1736770</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> for the manner in which a majority decision of the 
Trustees shall be obtained by circulation to the Trustees of 
the matter requiring decision;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1728109</tid>
<number>c</number>for the appointment of Committees of the Trustees, and 
the powers of expenditure and control which may be delegated 
to such Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819057</tid>
<number>d</number>for the erection, maintenance and management of the 
Memorial, the care and custody of the objects deposited 
therein, and the conditions under which the public shall have 
access thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1381565</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for the fees to be levied for admission to the 
Victoria Memorial;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1903</year>, Pt. I, p. 230.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1943</year>, s. 3,


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>354940</tid>
<number>e</number>for the form of accounts to be kept by the Trustees and 
for the audit and publication of such accounts <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>832490</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>676622</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power of Trustees to make regulations.
<section><tid>1279744</tid>
<number>1</number>The Trustees may,  
with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this 
Act and the rules made thereunder, for enabling the body to discharge 
its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1648693</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>2972</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions and restrictions subject to which 
articles and things vested in the Trustees may be given on 
loan;-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>981348</tid>
<number>b</number>the recruitment and conditions of service of the 
employees of the Victoria Memorial.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>295447</tid>
<number>3</number>Every regulation shall, as soon as may be, after it is made 
by the Trustees, be forwarded to the Central Government and that 
Government shall cause a copy of the same to be laid before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be 
made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" and" and clause (f) omitted by Act 32 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 3, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>