<act><title>THE COLLIERY CONTROL RULES, 20041 </title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement. </title>
<section><number>i</number> These rules may be called the Colliery Control 
Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> These rules shall come into force from date of their 
publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Act means the Mines and Minerals (Development and Regulation) Act, 
  1957 (67 of 1957); 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> coal includes anthracite, bituminous coal, lignite, peat and any 
  other form of carbonaceous matter sold or marketed as coal and also coke; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Coal Controller means the person appointed as such by the Central 
  Government under the provisions of the Coal Controller's Organisation (Group 
  A' Posts) Recruitment Rules, 1986; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> colliery means any mine or open working where winning or extraction 
  of coal is the principal object of the mining, quarrying or any other 
  operation carried on therein and includes a plant for the production of coke 
  or for the washing of coal; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> disposal includes agreeing or offering to dispose of, and the 
  disposal of ownership or any proprietary interest, the right of possession and 
  possession whether or not accompanied by any disposal of ownership or any 
  proprietary interest or of right to possession; 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> agent, manager and owner when used in relation to a colliery 
  shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Mines Act, 1952; 
  
 </section><section><number>vii</number> size when used in relation to coal shall have the same 
  specification as given, from time to time, by the Bureau of Indian Standards 
  in their specification number IS: 437-1979. </section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Categorisation of Coal. </title>-The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, prescribe the classes, grades and sizes 
into which coal may be categorised and the specifications for each such class, 
grade or size of coal. 
  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Procedure for categorisation of coal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> On the basis 
of the categorisation notified by the Central Government under rule 3, the Coal 
Controller shall lay down the procedure and method of sampling and analysis of 
coal for the purpose of declaration and maintenance of grades of coal mined in a 
colliery. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner, agent or manager of a colliery shall declare the classes, 
grades or sizes of the coal of any seam or section of a seam in a colliery in 
accordance with the procedure specified in sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The owner, agent or manager of the colliery shall allow the inspection of 
the colliery undertaken by the Coal Controller or any officer authorised by him 
in this regard so as to ensure the correctness of the class, grade or size 
declared. During inspection, if the Coal Controller or the officer authorised by 
him decides to draw sample, the owner, agent or manager of the colliery shall 
provide all reasonable facilities and assistance for drawing such sample. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If after inspection or from the sample drawn, the Coal Controller is 
satisfied that the grade as declared by the owner, agent or the manager of the 
colliery does not conform to the grade notified under rule clause (3) the owner, 
agent or manager of the colliery shall be bound to revise the grade as per the 
directions issued by the Coal Controller. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If any dispute arises between a consumer and a owner of a colliery 
regarding the declaration of grades of coal, the same may be referred to the 
Coal Controller whose decision shall be binding on the owner of the colliery. A 
memorandum of reference to the Coal Controller regarding such dispute shall be 
accompanied by a fee of rupees two thousand and five hundred and in such manner, 
as may be specified by the Coal Controller, from time to time. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Submission of returns and information to Coal Controller. 
</title>Every owner of a colliery and every person engaged in the business of 
production, supply and distribution of, or trade and commerce in coal, on being 
directed to do so by the Coal Controller shall submit such returns and other 
information, within such time, as may be specified in the direction. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Directions to regulate the disposal of coal stocks. </title>The 
Central Government may, from time to time, issue such directions as it may deem 
fit to any owner of a colliery regulating the disposal of stocks of coal or of 
the expected output of coal in the colliery during any period. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Power of the Coal Controller 
for quality surveillance. </title>The Coal Controller or any other officer 
authorised by him in writing shall be competent to 
 
 <section><number>a</number> cause the owner, agent or manager of a colliery or any 
  person engaged in or in charge of the loading of coal in wagons, trolleys or 
  trucks in a colliery, to adjust the loading according to the procedure laid 
  down by the Coal Controller regarding grades and size of coal and to remove 
  impurities like shales and stones from the wagons, trolleys or trucks loaded 
  with coal; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> detain the wagons, trolleys or trucks at the colliery or 
  weighbridge for adjustment of loading after inspection; and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> return the wagons, trolley or trucks to the colliery from 
  weighbridge for unloading and reloading with the specified quantity and 
  quality of coal. </section>

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Power to prohibit or limit the mining or production 
of coal. </title>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may 
deem fit to any colliery owner prohibiting or limiting the mining or production 
of any grade of coal and the colliery owner shall comply with such directions. 

  

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Requirement of prior permission to open a coal mine, seam or 
section of a seam. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No owner of a colliery shall open a coal mine, 
seam or a section of a seam without the prior permission in writing of the 
Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No owner of a colliery shall also commence mining operations in a 
colliery or seam or a section of a seam, in which the mining operation has been 
discontinued for a period exceeding one hundred and eighty days, without the 
prior permission in writing of the Central Government. 
  

</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Notice of suspension or closure. </title>If the mining 
operations in a coal mine or seam or a section of a seam is suspended or closed 
temporarily or permanently, as the case may be, for any reason whatsoever, then 
a notice of such suspension or closure shall be given by the owner, agent or 
manager of the colliery within a period of thirty days from the date of such 
suspension or closure to the Coal Controller. 
  

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Power to restrict sub-division of a coal mine. </title>No owner 
of a colliery or a group of collieries which has been permitted under rule 9 to 
work as a single mining unit or which has been working as a single unit at the 
time of commencement of these rules shall be allowed to sub-divide his mining 
unit or to work as a separate unit without the prior permission of the Central 
Government. 

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Power of inspect collieries. </title>The Coal Controller or any 
other officer authorised by him in writing may with a view to securing 
compliance of these rules, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> require any owner or agent or manager of a colliery to give any 
  information in his possession relating to the production of coal in the coal 
  mine or seam or section of a seam showing full boundaries of the leasehold 
  area and plan of abandoned area, flooded area and area which has been or is on 
  fire; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> ask for production of any document, register and working plan; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> inspect any mine plan in the possession of owner or agent or manager 
  of a colliery; and 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> enter and inspect any colliery. </section>

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>13</number> </title>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of these rules 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or 
with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both, and in case of 
a continuing contravention, with an additional fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees for every day during which such contravention continues after the 
first such contravention. 
  

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>14</number> </title>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall 
lie against any person for anything which is done or intended to be done in good 
faith under these rules. 
  

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Delegation of powers to Coal Controller. </title>The powers of the Central Government specified under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[rules 6, 9 and 11] may be delegated by notification<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in the Official Gazette to the Coal Controller. 




</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Power to exempt. </title>Notwithstanding anything contained in 
these rules, the Central Government may, if it deems proper for avoiding any 
hardship or for any other just and sufficient reasons, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, exempt any colliery owner or any class or category of person 
from the provisions of any of these rules. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 817(E), dated 15th November, 2011, for rules 6, 7 and 11 (w.r.e.f. 25-8-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> The Central Government has delegated powers specified under rules 9 and 11 to the Coal Controller,  vide  G.S.R. 816(E), dated 15th November, 2011.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>