<act> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 19781
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>a</number> These rules may be 
called the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Rules, 1978.
 </section><section><number>b</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Water (Prevention and Control 
of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977);
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   “assessing authority” means—
 
 
1[(i)   in relation to a Union territory, the Member-Secretary of the 
Central Pollution Control Board and in those Union territories where Pollution 
Control Committees have been constituted by the Administrator/Lt. Governor, a 
member nominated by the Administrator/Lt. Governor, a member nominated by the 
man thereof, and];
 <subsection>             <number>ii</number>   in relation to a State the 
member-secretary of the State Board;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>c</number>   “consumer” means a person or local authority 
by whom the cess under sub-section (1) of section 3 is payable under sub-section 
(2) of that section;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>   “form” means a form annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number>   “State Government”, in relation to a Union 
territory, means the Administrator thereof appointed under article 239 of the 
Constitution.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>3</number> Standards of the meters 
and places where they are to be affixed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purposes of measuring and recording the quantity of water consumed, 
every consumer shall affix water meters, venturi meters or Orifice meters with 
integrators and recorders in conformity with the standards laid down by the 
Indian Standards Institution and where no standards have been laid down by that 
institution in conformity with such standards as may be specified by the Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Wherever the meters referred 
to in sub-section (1), are not available, the consumer shall install Vee notches 
or rectangular notches, with indicators and recorders or pressure gauges and 
pumping installations, after obtaining the permission of assessing authority.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every consumer shall provide 
a separate meter for assessing the quantity of water used for each of the four 
purposes mentioned in column (1) of Schedule II to the Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The meters shall be affixed 
at the entrance of the water supply connections with the premises of the 
consumer or at any other place to be approved by the assessing authority, so 
that such meters are easily accessible for inspection and maintenance and for 
other purposes of the Act:
 Provided that the place where 
the meter is affixed shall, in no case, be at a point before which water has 
been tapped by the consumer for utilisation for any purpose whatsoever.
</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>4</number> Furnishing of returns.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
Every consumer shall furnish on or before the 5th of every calendar month, to 
the assessing authority, a return in Form I showing the quantity of water 
consumed in the previous month.
 

2[(2) If the consumer fails to submit the 
return as specified in sub-rule (1) the assessing authority or the officer 
authorised in this regard shall issue a notice in Form IA.]
  



</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>5</number> Manner of payment of the 
cess to the Central Government and the time within which it shall be paid.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every State Government shall remit to the Central Government, the amount of cess 
collected from the consumer before the 10th day of the calendar month succeeding 
the month in which it is collected from the consumer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The amount of cess referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be remitted to the Central Government in the form of a 
bank draft drawn in favour of the 

1[Pay and Accounts Officer, Department of 
Environment], New Delhi in whose books of accounts, the receipts would be 
adjusted finally.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receiving the bank draft, 
the Ministry of Works and Housing shall remit the same through a challan into 
the Reserve Bank of India, New Delhi for the purpose of crediting under relevant 
Major Head.
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>6</number> Rebate.—Where 
a consumer instals any plant for the treatment of sewage or trade effluent, such 
consumer shall be entitled to the rebate under section 70A and from the expiry 
of fifteen days from the date on which such plant is successfully commissioned 
and so long as it functions successfully:
 

1[Provided that a consumer shall not be 
entitled to the rebate if he—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   consumes water in excess of the maximum 
quantity specified in column (3) of the First Schedule appended to these rules 
for the category of industries specified in the corresponding entry in column 
(2) relating to the specified industry given in column (1) thereto, or
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   fails to comply with any of the provisions of 
section 25 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
1974), or any of the standards laid down by the Central Government, under the 
Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986).]
  


</section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article>

1[<number>6A</number> Collection by States/Union 
Territories.—The Cess Collecting 
Authority of the State/Union territory shall furnish a statement with the 
Central Government before the 10th day of the calendar month of January, April, 
July and October showing assessment of cess of specified industries, its 
collection and arrears.]
  


</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>7</number> Powers to be exercised by 
the Officer or the Authority of the State Government under section 9.—The 
officer or authority of the State Government specially empowered under section 9 
shall have in addition to the powers referred to in clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of that 
section, the power to—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   inspect the manufacturing process or plant of 
the consumer;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   inspect the water supply systems and 
installations in the plant of the consumer;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   inspect water treatment system and 
installations, in the plant of the consumer;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   inspect the drainage system and installations, 
including storm water disposal in the plant of the consumer;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>v</number>   call for and inspect records relating to the 
use and consumption of materials and water, and those relating to production, in 
the plant of the consumer;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>   call for and inspect the records relating to 
power consumption in the plant of the consumer; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vii</number>   call for any other information or records 
relating to the supply, consumption and treatment of water in the plant of the 
consumer.
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>8</number> Authority to impose 
penalty under section 11.—The 
authority to impose penalty under section 11 shall be the assessing authority.
</article> 
 THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  
OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
  
 <article><number>9</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any consumer aggrieved by an order of assessment made under section 6 or by an 
order imposing penalty made under section 11 may appeal in Form II annexed 
hereto, to a Committee (hereinafter referred to as the appellate committee) 
consisting of—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   where the assessing authority is the 
member-secretary of the Central Board, the Chairman of that Board, who shall be 
the Chairman of the Committee, and two members of the Board, to be nominated by 
the Chairman thereof
1[and in 
those Union territories where Pollution Control Committees have been constituted 
by the Administrator/Lt. Governor, the Chairman of such
committee and two members to be 
nominated by the Chairman thereof];
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   where the assessing authority is the 
member-secretary of the State Board, the Chairman of that Board, who shall be 
the Chairman of the Committee, and two members of that Board, to be nominated by 
the Chairman thereof.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Such appeal shall state the 
facts of the case and the grounds relied upon by the appellant for preferring 
the appeal and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order of assessment made 
under section 6 or a copy of the order imposing penalty made under section 11, 
as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Such appeal shall be 
preferred within a period of thirty days from the date of communication of the 
order of assessment or the order imposing penalty:
 Provided that if the Chairman of 
the appellate committee is satisfied that there was good and sufficient reason 
for the delay in preferring the appeal, he may, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, allow the appeal, to be preferred after the expiry of the aforesaid 
period of thirty days and before the expiry of forty-five days from the date of 
communication of the order of assessment, or the order imposing penalty, on the 
appellant.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every appeal shall be 
accompanied by a fees of rupees fifty.
  


</section></article><form>
 

THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  

OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
 

 
 




1[FORM 
IA
 


[See rule 4(2)]
 


NAME OF THE BOARD
 



Dated..........................
 


Notice under section 5 (2) 
of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977).
 

To
 

Name and Address of the Consumer:
 

Assessment period:
 

Whereas you were required to furnish a return as provided 
under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Water (Prevention and Control of 
Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977) read with sub-rule (1) of rule 4 of the 
Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Rules, 1978, by the 5th 
of.....................;
 

And whereas you have failed to furnish the return by the said 
date;
 

Now, therefore, you are hereby called upon to furnish the 
return within 7 days from the date of receipt of this Notice.
 

In case no return is received within the said period of 7 
days, action will be taken for making assessment as per sub-section (1A) of 
section 6 of the aforesaid Act, ex parte, besides initiating any other 
legal action as per law against you.
 

Issuing authority
 


Place................................                                                                                
       Name....................................
 


Date..................................                                                                                      Address.................................
 


...............................................]
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 311 
(E), dated 28th February, 1992.
</form><form>
 

THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL  

OF POLLUTION) CESS RULES, 1978
 

 
 




FORM II
 


(see 
rule 9)
 


FORM OF MEMORANDUM OF 
APPEAL
 


Before...................................................(**)...............................................
 


Memorandum of appeal under section 13 of the Water (Prevention and Control of 
Pollution) Cess Act, 1977.
 

Appeal No.................................................. of 
20...............
 

................................................
 

................................................
 

................................................
 

(here furnish complete postal address)
 


............................................Appellant.
 


Vs.
 



............................................
 



............................................
 



............................................
 

(here mention the name and 
designation of assessing authority).
 


 


  ............................................Respondent.
 

  **  Here mention the name 
and designation of the authority.
 

The appellant named above, begs to prefer this memorandum of 
appeal against the order dated...................... passed 
by................................... of the following facts and grounds:
 


FACTS
 


(here briefly mention the 
facts of the case)
 


GROUNDS
 


(here mention the grounds 
on which the appeal is made)
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


4.
 

PRAYER
 

In the light of what is stated above, the appellant 
respectfully prays that he/she/it may be exempted from the payment of cess.
 

He/she/it may be allowed a rebate of 70 per cent. as provided 
for in the Act and the amount of cess reduced to Rs..............................................
 

The amount of cess has not been correctly assessed and that it 
may be reduced to Rs..................................................
 

The penalty imposed on him/her/it has been wrongfully imposed 
and should be set aside.
 

The penalty imposed on him/her/it is excessive and should be 
suitably reduced on the basis of the facts as stated.
 

2. The amount of Rs....................................................(Rupees................................) 
as fees for the appeal has been paid 
to..........................................vide Receipt 
No.................................. 
dated....................................................
 

 
 


                                                                                                            Signature of the 
Appellant...................
 


Place.....................................                                                            
         Name.................................................
 


Date......................................                                                            
         Address..............................................
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>