<act><tid>1369884</tid>
<title>THE LEGISLATIVE COUNCILS ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1957</year>
[ 18th September, <year>1957</year>.]

An Act to provide for the creation of a Legislative Council for the 
State of Andhra Pradesh and the increasing of the strength of the 
Legislative Councils of the States having such Councils and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>240079</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Legislative Councils 
Act, <year>1957</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>132201</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>209357</tid>
<number>a</number>each of the words and expressions defined in the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), 
but not defined in this Act, shall have the same 
meaning as in that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>337360</tid>
<number>b</number>" sitting member" means a person who immediately before 
the commecement of this Act is a member of a 
Legislative Council.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>488</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 34 of <year>1985</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1985</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904390</tid>
<number> 4</number> Increase in the strength of the Bihar Legislative Council.
<section><tid>56889</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of Bihar shall be 
increased from 72 to 96 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>703488</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by the 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 34, 8 and 8 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>859756</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by members of 
the Legislative Assembly of Bihar in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the said clause 
shall be 34; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1590235</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Bihar in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>519975</tid>
<number>2</number>The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Bihar) Order, 
<year>1951</year>, shall, until other provision is made by law, have effect subject 
to the modifications directed by the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1705703</tid>
<number>3</number>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, 
elections shall be held to fill--

<subsection><tid>913433</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional seats allotted to the several council 
constituencies by the said Orders as modified by this 
Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>462410</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional seats to be filled by the persons 
referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1),
as if those seats had become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>468480</tid>
<number>4</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 6th May, <year>1958</year>, and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter, the Governor of Bihar 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order

<pagefootnote><pagenum>489</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the members to be elected to fill the additional seats under sub- 
section (3).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>77808</tid>
<number> 5</number> Increase in the strength of the Bombay Legislative Council.

<section><tid>485006</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of Bombay  
shall be increased to 108 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>256968</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by the 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 36, 9 and 9, 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>853371</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of Bombay in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 42; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>528521</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Bombay in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1314778</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the commencement of this Act, the Delimitation of 
Council Constituencies (Bombay) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall, until other 
provision is made by law, have effect subject to the modifications 
directed by the Second Schedule and in the said Order as so modified, 
any reference to the State of Bombay shall be construed as a reference 
to that State as formed by section 8 of the States Reorganisation Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>922589</tid>
<number>3</number>As from the commencement of this Act--

<subsection><tid>285432</tid>
<number>a</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement any council 
constituency specified in column 1 of the Table below 
shall be deemed to have been elected to the said 
Council by the council constituency specified against 
that constituency in column 2 of the said Table if 
immediately before such commencement, he is an elector 
for an assembly constituency in the State of Bombay;
TABLE


<pagefootnote><pagenum>490</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2 
Bombay City (Graduates).. Greater Bombay (Graduates).

Ahmedabad City (Graduates).. 
Gujarat (Graduates). 
Northern Division (Graduates)..

Poona City (Graduates)... 
Maharashtra (Graduates). 
Southern Division (Graduates).

Bombay City (Teachers)... 
Poona City (Teachers)... Greater Bombay- cum- Maharashtra 
Central Division (Teachers).. (Teachers). 
Southern Division (Teachers)..


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Ahmedabad City (Teachers).. 
Gujarat (Teachers). 
Northern Division (Teachers)..

Bombay City (Local Authorities). Greater Bombay- cum- Maharashtra 
West (Local Authorities).

Ahmedabad City (Local Authorities) 
Ahmedabad District (Local Authori-  
  ties). Gujarat North (Local  
  Authorities). 
Mehsana- cum- Banas Kantha (Local  
  Authorities). 
Baroda- cum- Amreli (Local Autho-  
  rities).

Broach- cum- Panch Mahals (Local  
  Authorities). Gujarat South (Local  
  Authorities). 
Kaira (Local Authorities).. 
Surat (Local Authorities)..

East Khandesh (Local Authorities). 
Nasik (Local Authorities).. Maharashtra North (Local  
  Ahmednagar- cum- West Khandesh Authorities). 
 (Local Authorities)..

Poona City (Local Authorities).. 
Poona (Local Authorities).. Maharashtra South (Local  
  Sholapur (Local Authorities).. Authorities). 
North Satara (Local Authorities).

Kolaba- cum- Thana (Local Autho-  
  rities). 
Ratnagiri- cum- Kanara (Local  
  Authorities)... Maharashtra North (Local  
  Authorities). 
Kolhapur- cum- South Satara (Local  
  Authorities).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>491</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> (b) every sitting member of the said Council elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of the former State 
of Bombay and every sitting member of the said Council 
chosen in pursuance of clause (b) of sub- section (2) of 
section 34 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37  
  of <year>1956</year>), shall be deemed to have been duly elected by 
the members of the Legislative Assembly of the present 
State of Bombay if immediately before such commencement 
he is an elector for an assembly constituency in the 
State of Bombay.

(4) Every sitting elected member of the said Council who is not 
deemed to have been elected thereto by virtue of clause (a) or clause 
 (b) of sub- section (3) shall, as from the commencement of this Act, 
cease to be a member of the said Council.

(5) As soon as may be after such commencement, elections shall be 
held to fill such of the seats allotted to the several Council 
constituencies by the Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Bombay)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Order, <year>1951</year>, as modified by this Act and such of the seats to be 
filled by persons referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) as are 
then vacant, as if those seats had then become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>529331</tid>
<number>6</number>The said Council shall be deemed to have been first 
constituted on the date on which the Legislative Council of the former 
State of Bombay was first constituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1777521</tid>
<number>7</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 24th April, <year>1958</year>, and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter, the Governor of Bombay 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order 
such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the sitting members chosen in pursuance of clause (b) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 34 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of  
  <year>1956</year>), and of the members to be elected under sub- section (5) of this 
section.

</section>

<section><tid>51665</tid>
<number>8</number>Section 34 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>, shall be 
amended, and shall be deemed always to have been amended, as follows:- 
-

<subsection><tid>1269097</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), for the words, brackets and figures 
Until the said Council has been reconstituted in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- sections (4) and 
 (5) of this section and summoned to meet for the first 
time', the words' Until otherwise provided by law' 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>481442</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- sections (3), (4) and (5) shall be omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>553437</tid>
<number>9</number>In this section, the expression' the former State of Bombay' 
means the State of Bombay as it existed immediately before the 1st day 
of November, <year>1956</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1942120</tid>
<number> 6</number> Increase in the strength of the Madhya Pradesh Legislative 
Council.
<section><tid>147294</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council for  
the State of Madhya Pradesh to be constituted under section 33 of the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>.), shall be increased from 
 72 as fixed by sub- section (2) of that section to 90.

</section>

<section><tid>1427899</tid>
<number>2</number>The said section shall be amended as follows:-- 
in sub- section (2),--

<subsection><tid>1563472</tid>
<number>i</number>for the figures" 72", the figures" 90" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1320903</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (a), for the figures and word" 24, 6 and 
6", the figures and word" 31, 8 and 8" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>682429</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (b), for the figures" 24", the figures 
" 31" shall be substituted;

<subsubsection><tid>311019</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3), for the words" this Act", the words 
and figures" the Legislative Councils Act, <year>1957</year>" shall 
be substituted; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>492</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>306583</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (4),--

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563472</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" the appointed day", the words 
" such commencement" shall be substituted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1320903</tid>
<number>ii</number>the proviso shall be omitted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476763</tid>
<number> 7</number> Increase in the strength of the Madras Legislative Council.

<section><tid>975786</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of Madras  
shall be increased from 50 to 63 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>389851</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by the 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 21, 6 and 6 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>409435</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of Madras in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 21; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1052273</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Madras in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 9.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>990246</tid>
<number>2</number>The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Madras) Order, 
<year>1951</year>, shall, until other provision is made by law, have effect subject 
to the modifications directed by the Third Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1518383</tid>
<number>3</number>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act,--

<subsection><tid>742241</tid>
<number>a</number>elections shall be held to fill--

<subsubsection><tid>1737857</tid>
<number>i</number>the additional seats allotted to the local 
authorities' constituencies and the teachers' constituency 
by the said Order as modified by this Act; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1011233</tid>
<number>ii</number>the additional seats, to be filled by the persons 
referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1),
as if those seats had become vacant;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>514117</tid>
<number>b</number>one person shall be nominated by the Governor of Madras 
to fill the additional seat under clause (c) of the 
said sub- section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>408313</tid>
<number>4</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 20th April, <year>1958</year>, and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter, the Governor of Madras 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order, 
such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the members to be elected under clause (a) of sub- section (3) and of 
the member to be nominated under clause (b) of that sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>935059</tid>
<number> 8</number> Increase in the strength of the Mysore Legislative Council.

<section><tid>1027628</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of Mysore  
shall be increased to 63 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>236502</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 21, 6 and 6 
respectively;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>493</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>937246</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of Mysore in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 21; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1221731</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Mysore in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 9.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1772409</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the commencement of this Act, the Delimitation of 
Council Constituencies (Mysore) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall, until other 
provision is made by law, have effect subject to the modifications 
directed by the Fourth Schedule, and in the said Order as so modified, 
a reference to the State of Mysore shall be construed as a reference 
to that State as formed by section 7 of the States Reorganisation Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>.).

</section>

<section><tid>296546</tid>
<number>3</number>As from the commencement of this Act,--

<subsection><tid>606735</tid>
<number>a</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement a council 
constituency specified in column 1 of the Table below 
shall be deemed to have been elected to the said 
Council by the council constituency specified against 
that constituency in column 2 of the said Table:--
TABLE


<pagefootnote><pagenum>494</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2 
Mysore (Graduates) constituency. Mysore South (Graduates) consti- 
tuency.

Mysore (Teachers) constituency. Mysore South (Teachers) consti- 
tency.

Kolar (Local Authorities) consti- 
tuency. 
Tumkur (Local Authorities) con- 
stituency. Mysore South East (Local Author-  
  ities) constituency. 
Bangalore (Local Authorities con-  
stituency.

Hassan (Local Authorities) consti- 
tuency. 
Mandya (Local Authorities) con- 
stituency. Mysore South (Local Authorities) 
constituency. 
Mysore (Local Authorities) con- 
stituency.

Chickmagalur (Local Authorities) 
constituency. 
Shimoga (Local Authorities) con- 
stituency. Mysore South West (Local Author-  
  ities) constituency. 
Chitaldrug- cum- Bellary (Local Auth-  
  orities) constituency.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479044</tid>
<number>b</number>every sitting member of the said Council elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of the former State 
of Mysore, every sitting member of the said Council 
chosen in pursuance of clause (b) of sub- section (2) of 
section 36 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37  
  of <year>1956</year>.), and the sitting member of the said Council 
specified by the Chairman of the Legislative Council of 
Madras under sub- rule (7) of rule 4 of the States 
Reorganisation (Elections to Provisional State  
  Legislatures) Rules, <year>1956</year>, shall be deemed to have been 
duly elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly 
of the present State of Mysore; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>235500</tid>
<number>c</number>every sitting member of the said Council nominated by 
the Rajpramukh of the former State of Mysore shall be 
deemed to have been nominated to the said Council by 
the Governor of the present State of Mysore.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>359627</tid>
<number>4</number>The three members who, immediately before the 1st November, 
<year>1956</year>, were members of the Legislative Council of Bombay and became on 
that date members of the Legislative Council of Mysore by virtue of 
sub- rule (7) of rule 4 of the States Reorganisation (Elections to  
  Provisional State Legislatures) Rules, <year>1956</year>, shall be deemed to have 
been elected to the Legislative Council of Mysore by the Mysore North 
West (Local Authorities) constituency.

</section>

<section><tid>1679350</tid>
<number>5</number>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, 
elections shall be held to fill such of the seats allotted to the 
several council constituencies by the Delimitation of Council 
Constituencies (Mysore) Order, <year>1951</year>, as modified by this Act and such 
of the seats to be filled by persons referred to in clause (b) of sub- 
section (1) as are then vacant, as if those seats had then become 
vacant.

</section>

<section><tid>1381961</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be after such commencement, the vacancies in 
the seats allotted under clause (c) of sub- section (1) shall be filled 
by nomination by the Governor.

</section>

<section><tid>1765435</tid>
<number>7</number>The said Council shall be deemed to have been first 
constituted on the date on which the Legislative Council of the former 
State of Mysore was first constituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1952924</tid>
<number>8</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 13th May, <year>1958</year>], and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter, the Governor of Mysore 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order 
such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the sitting members chosen in pursuance of clause (b) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 36 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>), 
and of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>495</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 58 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" 26th April, <year>1958</year>" 
 (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the members to be elected and nominated under sub- sections (5) and (6) 
of this section.


</section>

<section><tid>1739600</tid>
<number>9</number>Section 36 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of  
  <year>1956</year>), shall be amended, and shall be deemed always to have been 
amended, as follows:--

<subsection><tid>1654657</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2) for the words, brackets and figures 
" Until the said Council has been reconstituted in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- sections (3) and 
 (4) of this section and summoned to meet for the first 
time", the words" Until otherwise provided by law" 
shall be substituted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1623662</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- sections (3) and (4) shall be omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1845897</tid>
<number>10</number>In this section, the expression' the former State of Mysore' 
means the State of Mysore as it existed immediately before the 1st day 
of November, <year>1956</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>418552</tid>
<number> 9</number> Increase in the strength of the Punjab Legislative Council.

<section><tid>1500419</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of Punjab  
shall be increased to 51 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>1491459</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 17, 4 and 4 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1534677</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of Punjab in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 18; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>97989</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Punjab in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 8.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>127263</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the commencement of this Act, the Delimitation of 
Council Constituencies (Punjab) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall, until other 
provision is made by law, have effect subject to the modifications 
directed by the Fifth Schedule, and in the said Order as so modified, 
any reference to the State of Punjab shall be construed as a reference 
to that State as formed by section 11 of the States Reorganisation 
Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>766390</tid>
<number>3</number>As from the commencement of this Act,--

<subsection><tid>1797010</tid>
<number>a</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement any local 
authorities' constituency specified in column 1 of the 
Table below shall be deemed to have been elected to the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>496</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

said Council by the local authorities' constituency 
specified against that constituency in column 2 of the 
said Table:--

TABLE


<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2 
Ambala- cum- Karnal (Local Autho- Punjab South (Local Authorities)  
  rities) constituency. constituency.

Gurgaon- cum- Rohtak- cum- Hissar- Punjab South (Local Authorites) 
cum- Simla (Local Authorites) constituency. 
constituency.

Hoshiarpur- cum- Kangra- cum- Gur- Punjab North (Local Authorities) 
daspur (Local Authorities) con- constituency. 
stituency.

Jullundur- cum- Ferozepur- cum- Punjab North (Local Authorities) 
Amritsar- cum- Ludhiana (Local constituency.  
  Authorities) constituency.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>349503</tid>
<number>b</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement the graduates' 
constituency or the teachers' constituency shall be 
deemed to have been elected to the said Council by that 
constituency as altered by virtue of sub- section (2):

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>63216</tid>
<number>c</number>every sitting member of the said Council elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of the former State 
of Punjab and every sitting member of the said Council 
elected under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 
 37 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of  
  <year>1956</year>), shall be deemed to have been duly elected by 
the members of the Legislative Assembly of the present 
State of Punjab.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1642676</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as may be after such commencement, elections shall be 
held to fill--

<subsection><tid>1833157</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional seats allotted to the several council 
constituencies by the Delimitation of Council 
Constituencies (Punjab) Order, <year>1951</year>, as modified by 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1089388</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional seats to be filled by persons referred to 
in clause (b) of sub- section (1),
as if those seats had become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1808742</tid>
<number>5</number>The said Council shall be deemed to have been first 
constituted on the date on which the Legislative Council of the former 
State of Punjab was first constituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1573941</tid>
<number>6</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 26th April <year>1958</year>, and on the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>497</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

expiration of every second year thereafter the Governor of Punjab 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order 
such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the sitting members elected under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of 
section 37 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>.), and 
of the members to be elected under sub- section (4) of this section.


</section>

<section><tid>584005</tid>
<number>7</number>Section 37 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of  
  <year>1956</year>), shall be amended, and shall be deemed always to have been 
amended, as follows:--

<subsection><tid>792831</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), for the words, brackets and figures 
" Until the said Council has been reconstituted in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- sections (3) and 
 (4) of this section and of any other law for the time 
being in force and has been summoned to meet for the 
first time", the words" Until otherwise provided by 
law" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>222639</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- sections (3) and (4) shall be omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>935035</tid>
<number>8</number>In this section the expression" the former State of Punjab" 
means the State of Punjab as it existed immediately before the 1st day 
of November, <year>1956</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>906742</tid>
<number> 10</number> Increase in the strength of the Uttar Pradesh Legislative 
Council.
<section><tid>981078</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of  
Uttar Pradesh shall be increased from 72 to 108 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>1267065</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by the 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 39, 9 and 9 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>284610</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of Uttar Pradesh in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 39; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>348785</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of Uttar Pradesh in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>191779</tid>
<number>2</number>The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Uttar Pradesh) 
Order, <year>1951</year>, shall, until other provision is made by law, have effect 
subject to the modifications directed by the Sixth Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>538353</tid>
<number>3</number>As from the commencement of this Act--

<subsection><tid>947291</tid>
<number>a</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement a graduates'

<pagefootnote><pagenum>498</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

constituency or a teachers' constituency the extent of 
which is altered by virtue of sub- section (2) shall be 
deemed to have been elected to the said Council by that 
constituency as so altered;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>110862</tid>
<number>b</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement any local 
authorities' constituency specified in column 1 of the 
Table below shall be deemed to have been elected to the 
said Council by the local authorities' constituency 
specified against that constituency in column 2 of the 
said Table:--
TABLE

 1 2 
Uttar Pradesh North- West (Local Meerut (Local Authorities)  
  Authorities) constituency. constituency.

Uttar Pradesh North- East (Local Rohilkhand (Local Authorities)  
  Authorities) constituency. constituency.

Uttar Pradesh West (Local Autho- Agra (Local Authorities) Con-  
  rities) constituency. situency.

Uttar Pradesh Central (Local Auth- Lucknow (Local Authorities)  
  orities) constituency. constituency.

Uttar Pradesh South (Local Autho- Allahabad (Local Authorities)  
  rities) constituency. constituency.

Uttar Pradesh East (Local Autho- Varanasi (Local Authorities)  
  rities) constituency. constituency.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1337729</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as may be after such commencement, elections shall be 
held to fill--

<subsection><tid>144451</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional seats allotted to the several council 
constituencies by the said Order as modified by this 
Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>715870</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional seats to be filled by persons referred to 
in clause (b) of sub- section (1),
as if those seats had become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1916555</tid>
<number>5</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 5th May, <year>1958</year>, and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter, the Governor of Uttar 
Pradesh shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make 
by order such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of 
office of the members to be elected under sub- section (4).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>499</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>382655</tid>
<number> 11</number> Increase in the strength of the West Bengal Legislative 
Council.
<section><tid>1451534</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Council of  
West Bengal shall be increased from 51 to 75 and of those seats--

<subsection><tid>291082</tid>
<number>a</number>the numbers to be filled by persons elected by the 
electorates referred to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) 
of clause (3) of article 171 shall be 27, 6 and 6 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>385920</tid>
<number>b</number>the number to be filled by persons elected by the 
members of the Legislative Assembly of West Bengal in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- clause (d) of the 
said clause shall be 27; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>91666</tid>
<number>c</number>the number to be filled by persons nominated by the 
Governor of West Bengal in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- clause (e) of that clause shall be 9.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1062188</tid>
<number>2</number>The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (West Bengal) 
Order, <year>1951</year>, shall, until other provision is made by law, have effect 
subject to the modifications directed by the Seventh Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1353347</tid>
<number>3</number>As from the commencement of this Act,--

<subsection><tid>1158043</tid>
<number>a</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement the Calcutta 
 (Graduates) constituency and every such member 
representing the Calcutta (Teachers) constituency, the 
extent of which is altered by virtue of sub- section (2) 
shall be deemed to have been elected to the said 
Council respectively by the Calcutta (Graduates) 
constituency and the Calcutta (Teachers) constituency 
as so altered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>106749</tid>
<number>b</number>every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before such commencement any of the council 
constituencies specified in column 1 of the Table below 
shall be deemed to have been elected to the said 
Council by the council constituency specified against 
that constituency in column 2 of the said Table:--
TABLE

 1 2 
West Bengal South (Graduates) con- West Bengal (Graduates) consti- 
stituency. tuency.

West Bengal West (Graduates) con- West Bengal (Graduates) consti- 
stituency. tuency.

West Bengal North (Graduates) con- West Bengal (Graduates) consti- 
stituency. tuency.

Burdwan Division (Teachers) con- West Bengal (Teachers) consti- 
stituency. tuency.

Presidency Division South (Teache- West Bengal (Teachers) constitu-  
  rs) constituency. ency.

Presidency Division North (Teache- West Bengal (Teachers) constitu-  
  rs) constituency. ency.

Darjeeling (Local Authorities) con- West Bengal North (Local Autho-  
  stituency. rities) constituency.

West Bengal North (Local Authori- West Bengal North (Local Autho-   
    ties) constituency. rities) constituency.

Nadia- Murshidabad (Local Authori- West Bengal East (Local Autho-   
    ties) constituency. rities) constituency.

Calcutta- 24-Parganas (Local Autho- West Bengal South (Local Autho-   
    rities) constituency. rities) constituency.

Hooghly- Howrah (Local Authorities) West Bengal Central (Local Auth-  
  constituency. orities) constituency.

Burdwan Division North (Local- West Bengal West (Local Author-   
    Authorities) constituency. ities) constituency.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>67695</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as may be after such commencement, elections shall be 
held to fill--

<subsection><tid>1927261</tid>
<number>a</number>the additional seats allotted to the several council 
constituencies by the said Order as modified by this 
Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1287729</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional seats to be filled by persons referred to 
in clause (b) of sub- section (1),
as if those seats had become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>793615</tid>
<number>5</number>In order that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members 
of the said Council may retire on the 4th June, <year>1958</year>, and on the 
expiration of every second year thereafter the Governor of West Bengal 
shall, after consultation with the Election Commission, make by order 
such provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of 
the members elected under sub- section (4).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1813397</tid>
<number>12</number>[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1917954</tid>
<number>13</number>[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1951</year>.] Rep. by s. 2 and Sch. I, ibid.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>503</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>