<act><title>
THE 
RELIGIOUS INSTITUTIONS (PREVENTION OF MISUSE) ACT, 1988
</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Religious Institu­tions (Prevention of Misuse) Act, 
1988. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day of May, 1988. 
 
  



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 

 <section>
<number>a</number>
“ammunition” shall have the same meaning as in clause (b) of sub-section 
(1) of section 2 of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959);
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“arms” shall have the same meaning as in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of 
section 2 of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959);
 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
“manager”, in relation to a religious institution, means every person, 
including, any religious functionary (by whatever name called), who, for the 
time being, either alone or in association with other persons, administers, 
manages or otherwise controls the affairs of that institution, its functions or 
prop­erties;
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
“political activity” includes any activity promoting or propagating the 
aims or objects of a political party or any cause, issue or question of a 
political nature by organising meetings, demonstra­tions, processions, 
collection or disbursement of funds, or by the issue of directions or decrees, 
or by any other means, and includes also such activity by or on behalf of a 
person seeking election as a candidate for any election to Parliament, any State 
Legislature or any local authority;
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
“political party” means an association or body of persons—
 


 <subsection>
<number>i</number>
which is, or is deemed to be, registered, with the Election Commission of 
India as a political party under the Election Symbols (Reservation and 
Allotment) Order, 1968, as in force for the time being; or 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>
which has set up candidates for election to any legislature, but is not 
registered, or deemed to be registered, as a political party, under the Election 
Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order, 1968; or 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>
organised to carry on any political activity or to acquire or exercise 
political power through election or otherwise; 
 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>
“religious institution” means an institution for the promotion of any 
religion or persuasion, and includes any place or premises used as a place of 
public religious worship, by whatever name or desig­nation known.
  



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Prohibition of use of religious institutions for certain purposes.—No 
religious institution or manager thereof shall use or allow the use of any 
premises belonging to, or under the control of, the institution— 
 

 <section>
<number>a</number>
for the promotion or propagation of any political activity; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
for the harbouring of any person accused or convicted of an offence under 
any law for the time being in force; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
for the storing of any arms or ammunition; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
for keeping any goods or articles in contravention of any law for the 
time being in force; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
for erecting or putting up of any construction or fortification, 
including basements, bunkers, towers or walls without a valid licence or 
permission under any law for the time being in force; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
for the carrying on of any unlawful or subversive act prohibited under 
any law for the time being in force or in contravention of any order made by any 
court; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
for the doing of any act which promotes or attempts to promote disharmony 
of feelings of enmity, hatred or ill-will between different religious, racial, 
language or regional groups or castes or communities; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>h</number>
for the carrying on of any activity prejudicial to the sovereignty, unity 
and integrity of India; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>i</number>
for the doing of any act in contravention of the provisions of the 
Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 1971 (69 of 1971).
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Restrictions on carrying arms and ammunition into a religious institution.—No 
religious institution or manager thereof shall allow the entry of any arms or 
ammunition or of any person carrying any arms or ammunition into the religious 
institution: 
 

 
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to— 
 

 <section>
<number>a</number>
the wearing and carrying of a kirpan by any person professing the Sikh 
religion; or
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
any arms which are used as part of any religious ceremony or ritual of 
the institution as estab­lished by custom or usage.
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Prohibition of use of funds of religious institutions for certain activities.—No 
religious institution or manager thereof shall use or allow the use of any funds 
or other properties belonging to, or under the control of, the institution for 
the benefit of any political party or for the purpose of any politi­cal activity 
or for the commission of any act which is punishable as an offence under any 
law. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Prohibition of religious fora for propagating political ideas.—No 
religious institution or manager thereof shall allow any ceremony, festival, 
congregation, procession or assembly organised or held under its auspices to be 
used for any political activity. 
 

  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Penalties.—Where any religious institution or manager thereof contravenes 
the provisions of section 3, section 4, section 5 or section 6, the manager and 
every person connected with such contra­vention shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and with fine which may 
extend to ten thousand rupees. 
 
  



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Disqualification of persons convicted or charge-sheeted under this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any manager or other employee of a religious institution shall, upon conviction 
for an offence under this Act, stand removed from his office or post and shall, 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, be 
disqualified for appointment in any religious institution as manager or in any 
other capac­ity for a period of six years from the date of his conviction. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any manager or other employee of a religious institution is accused of 
an offence under this Act and a charge-sheet for the prosecution of such person 
is filed in any court and the court is of the opinion, after considering the 
charge-sheet and after hearing the prosecution and the accused, that a prima 
facie case exists, it shall pass an order or direction restraining the 
person from exercising the powers or discharging the duties of his office or 
post pending trial. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any manager or other employee has been removed under sub-section (1), 
or restrained under sub-section (2), the vacancy arising out of such removal or 
restraint may be filled in the manner provided in the law applicable to the said 
religious institution. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Certain persons bound to give information to police.—Every manager or 
other employee of a religious institution shall be bound to give information to 
the officer incharge of the police station within whose local jurisdiction the 
religious institution is situate of any contravention or any impending 
contravention of the provisions of this Act and any failure to do so shall be 
punishable under section 176 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Religious Institutions (Prevention of Misuse) 
Ordinance, 1988 (Ord. 3 of 1988) is hereby repealed. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provisions of this Act. 
 


 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>