<act><tid>1762483</tid>
<title>THE FORT WILLIAM ACT, <year>1881</year></title>

ACT NO. 13 OF 1881AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE BETTER GOVERNMENT OF FORT WILLIAM.
[ 11th March, <year>1881</year>.]

Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to give power to make rules for 
the better government of Fort William in Bengal, and to provide for 
the establishment of a Court within the said Fort for the trial of 
persons charged with breaches of such rules; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:-





<article><tid>1372064</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Fort William Act, 
<year>1881</year>;
Commencement. And it shall come into force on the first day of 
April, <year>1881</year>.

But nothing herein contained shall be deemed to confer 
jurisdiction over any persons (other than artificers, labourers,  
  sutlers and followers) to whom the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Army Act] or the Indian Articles 
of War, <year>1869</year>, 2 (44 and 45 Vict., c. 58). (5 of <year>1869</year>). is or are 
applicable.



</article>



<article><tid>382644</tid>
<number>2</number>" The Fort". The Central Government may, from time to time, by 
notification, in the Official Gazette, define, for the purposes of 
this Act, the limits of Fort William in Bengal; and in this Act the 
expression" the Fort" means the area so defined.


</article>



<article><tid>1871807</tid>
<number>3</number>Chief of the Army Staff may make rules. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Chief of the 
Army Staff] may, from time to time, with the sanction of the Central 
Government, make rules, to be in force within the Fort, in regard to 
the matters specified in the Schedule hereto annexed and other matters 
of a like nature, and may by such rules prescribe, as penalties for 
the infringement thereof, fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to four days, or both.
When a sentence of fine is passed under any such rule, the term 
for which the Court directs the offender to be imprisoned in default 
of payment of such fine may extend to, and shall not exceed, four 
days.

When any rule is made under this section, a copy thereof, in 
English and such other languages as the Central Government may from 
time to time direct, shall be exhibited in such conspicuous places 
within the Fort as the Officer Commanding the Fort may from time to 
time direct.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>208</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1903</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" Army 
Discipline and Regulation Act, <year>1879</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>See now the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year> 1 s. 2, for" The Commander- in- Chief, 
Indian Army".






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>252745</tid>
<number>4</number>Central Government may invest officer with power to try 
breaches of rules. The Central Government may invest any commissioned 
officer in the Indian Army with power to try persons charged with any 
infringement of the rules made under' section 3.
The officer so invested is hereinafter called the Fort 
Magistrate.



</article>



<article><tid>255927</tid>
<number>5</number>Procedure to be followed. In all cases under this Act, the Fort 
Magistrate shall, except as herein otherwise provided, exercise within 
the Fort the Powers, and as nearly as may be, follow the procedure, 
conferred on, and prescribed for, a Presidency Magistrate by the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>]; (5 of <year>1898</year>), and, subject to the 
power conferred by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 526 of that Code], every finding, 
sentence or order of such Magistrate. under this Act shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1969774</tid>
<number>6</number>Power to arrest without warrant. Any police- officer, or any 
other person empowered in this behalf by the Central Government by 
name or as a member of a specified class, may arrest without warrant 
any person who in his sight commits an offence punishable under this 
Act.
Power to police- officer to release on bail. Every person so 
arrested shall be taken to the police- station within the Fort, and 
shall be detained there until he gives to the police- officer in charge 
of such station a bond, with or without sureties, as such officer may 
require, for a sum not exceeding one hundred rupees, to appear before 
the Fort Magistrate at a time to be specified in such bond, or until 
he can be brought before such Magistrate.



</article>



<article><tid>120146</tid>
<number>7</number>Jurisdiction of Presidency Magistrates and prosecutions under 
other laws saved. Nothing in this Act, or in any rule made hereunder 
shall affect the jurisdiction of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Presidency Magistrates] or 
shall prevent any person from being prosecuted under any other law for 
any offence punishable under this Act, or from being liable to any 
other punishment than is provided for such offence by this Act:
Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same 
offence.



</article>



<article><tid>956136</tid>
<number>8</number>Limitation of time for prosecution under Act. No prosecution 
for any offence under this Act shall be commenced after the expiration 
of three months next after such offence has been committed.


</article>



<article><tid>380085</tid>
<number> 9</number> [ Validation of penalties heretofore imposed by Garrison Quarter 
Master.] Rep. by the Amending Act, <year>1891</year> (12 of <year>1891</year>.)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>209</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1903</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 11, for" Presidency 
Magistrates Act, <year>1877</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid.,- for" the High Courts Criminal Procedure Act, 
<year>1875</year>. section 57".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" Magistrates appointed under the Presidency 
Magistrates Act <year>1877</year>".







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

FORT WILLIAM ACT, <year>1881</year>

THE SCHEDULE

 (See section 3.)

<section><tid>1223904</tid>
<number>1</number>Throwing dirt or rubbish of any description into the drains 
or roads, or anywhere but in the appointed places.

</section>

<section><tid>462274</tid>
<number>2</number>Removing night- soil without a covering or at unauthorised 
hours.

</section>

<section><tid>749794</tid>
<number>3</number>Camp- followers, servants, and others not keeping the godowns 
they live in clean.

</section>

<section><tid>150822</tid>
<number>4</number>Performing offices of nature in other than the appointed 
places.

</section>

<section><tid>1672263</tid>
<number>5</number>Bathing, or washing clothes or animals, in the cunette or 
other unauthorised places.

</section>

<section><tid>243561</tid>
<number>6</number>Selling unwholesome articles of food, grain or drinks.

</section>

<section><tid>127541</tid>
<number>7</number>Adulterating food or drinks.

</section>

<section><tid>143064</tid>
<number>8</number>Making evacuations in unauthorised places.

</section>

<section><tid>652654</tid>
<number>9</number>Rash or negligent driving.

</section>

<section><tid>240599</tid>
<number>10</number>Picketing, training. or breaking in animals.

</section>

<section><tid>1979681</tid>
<number>11</number>Causing obstruction by vehicles on the road.

</section>

<section><tid>470401</tid>
<number>12</number>Exposing or hawking articles for sale about the roads and 
barracks or within the Fort without a Fort pass.

</section>

<section><tid>1204848</tid>
<number>13</number>Beating drums or tom- toms.

</section>

<section><tid>1450346</tid>
<number>14</number>Damaging lamps, posts, masonry or other Government pro- 
perty in any part of the Fort.

</section>

<section><tid>427742</tid>
<number>15</number>Disorderly behaviour in the public thoroughfares.

</section>

<section><tid>1316818</tid>
<number>16</number>Gambling.

</section>

<section><tid>1778627</tid>
<number>17</number>Spitting pan on any of the public stair cases, gateways, 
walls and verandahs, or defacing in any way the walls of barracks, 
building or gateways.

</section>

<section><tid>598245</tid>
<number>18</number>Throwing slops into the drains.

</section>

<section><tid>267839</tid>
<number>19</number>Washing cooking- pots at the water- taps and wasting water.

</section>

<section><tid>1037345</tid>
<number>20</number>Cooking in unauthorised places.

</section>

<section><tid>1369722</tid>
<number>21</number>Hanging clothes to dry on the guns or masonry- work.

</section>

<section><tid>271988</tid>
<number>22</number>Laying out clothes, accouterments or stable- bedding after 
the authorised hours.

</section>

<section><tid>1057028</tid>
<number>23</number>Destroying the trees, bushes or plants, or climbing trees.

</section>

<section><tid>1043797</tid>
<number>24</number>Servants smoking hookas in their masters' quarters or cook- 
houses, or keeping such quarters or cook- houses in an insanitary 
state.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>210</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1825133</tid>
<number>25</number>Trespassing on parade- grounds, or making foot- paths across 
the grass- plots.

</section>

<section><tid>456994</tid>
<number>26</number>Being drunk and incapable.

</section>

<section><tid>1926756</tid>
<number>27</number>Fighting, quarrelling and creating a disturbance, or making 
unnecessary noise of any kind.

</section>

<section><tid>180634</tid>
<number>28</number>Affixing bills and papers on any walls in the Fort.

</section>

<section><tid>1521420</tid>
<number>29</number>Cutting grass or interfering with the grass- contractor.

</section>

<section><tid>1494932</tid>
<number>30</number>Declining to show a tin pass when called upon to do so.

</section>

<section><tid>1090783</tid>
<number>31</number>Being found in the garrison without a tin pass, or being in 
possession of a ticket belonging to another.

</section>

<section><tid>1195320</tid>
<number>32</number>Driving vehicles without lights or with insufficiently- 
greased wheels.

</section>

<section><tid>1088551</tid>
<number>33</number>Swinging or sitting on the chain- fences.

</section>

<section><tid>1981419</tid>
<number>34</number>Interfering in any way with the guns, carriages, or piles 
of shot and shell on the works, or with the packed ordnance.

</section>

<section><tid>326353</tid>
<number>35</number>Mounting the ramparts or parapets or entering the embrasures 
without authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1629089</tid>
<number>36</number>Smuggling liquor into the Fort.

</section>

<section><tid>975514</tid>
<number>37</number>Burning stable litter or lighting fires except in authorised 
places and at authorised hours.

</section>

<section><tid>1874636</tid>
<number>38</number>Carrying lights except in closed lanterns, or letting off 
fire- works

</section>

<section><tid>728123</tid>
<number>39</number>Removing property of any kind or description from the Fort 
without written authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1138957</tid>
<number>40</number>Allowing animals of any sort to stray into the Fort, or 
to graze within the game.

</section>

<section><tid>1965676</tid>
<number>41</number>Slaughtering animals or exposing carcasses or offal within 
the Fort.

</section>

<section><tid>322639</tid>
<number>42</number>keeping dogs or poultry in unauthorised places.

</section>

<section><tid>838938</tid>
<number>43</number>Buying, selling or receiving any portion of a soldier' s kit.

</section>

<section><tid>1550599</tid>
<number>44</number>Disobedience of lawful authority in failing to attend to 
authorised instructions of the police or of the several sentries 
posted throughout the Fort.

</section>

<section><tid>394666</tid>
<number>45</number>Occupying buildings of any without proper allotment.


</section>

</article>



 </act>