<act><tid>830587</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAYS (LOCAL AUTHORITIES' TAXATION) ACT, <year>1941</year></title>

ACT NO. 25 OF <year>1941</year>
[ 26th November, <year>1941</year>.]

An Act to regulate the extent to which railway property shall be 
liable to taxation imposed by an authority within a <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State].





<article><tid>1639957</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>442434</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Railways (Local Authorities' Taxation) Act, <year>1941</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1920956</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1818040</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,--
<section><tid>964943</tid>
<number>a</number>" local authority" means a local authority as defined in 
the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>), and 
includes any authority legally entitled to or entrusted 
with the control or management of any fund for the 
maintenance of watchmen or for the conservancy of a 
river;

</section>

<section><tid>1948746</tid>
<number>b</number>" railway administration" has the meaning assigned to the 
expression in clause (6) of section 3 of the Indian 
Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>124110</tid>
<number> 3</number> Liability of railways to taxation by local authorities.
<section><tid>871265</tid>
<number>1</number>In  
respect of property vested in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Central Government, being 
property of a railway, a railway administration shall be liable to pay 
and tax in aid of the funds of any local authority, if the Central 
Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, declares it to be 
so liable.

</section>

<section><tid>777089</tid>
<number>2</number>While a notification under sub- section (1) is in force, the 
railway administration shall be liable to pay to the local authority 
either the tax mentioned in the notification or in lieu thereof such 
sum, if any, as a person appointed in this behalf by the Central 
Government
<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" Part A State", which 
had been subs. for" Province" by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2 The words" His Majesty for the purposes of" omitted by the A. O. 
<year>1950</year>. 
3 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


may, having regard to the services rendered to the railway and all the 
relevant circumstances of the case, from time to time determine to be 
fair and reasonable. The person so appointed shall be a person who is 
or has been a Judge of a High Court or a District Judge.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1301090</tid>
<number>4</number>Modification of existing liability to taxation. The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, revoke or 
vary any notification issued under clause 1 of section 135 of the 
Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>); and where a notification is so 
revoked any liability arising out of the notification to pay any tax 
to any local authority shall cease, and where a notification is so 
varied the liability arising out of the notification shall be varied 
accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>478298</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving. Nothing in this Act shall be construed as debarring 
any railway administration administering a railway from entering into 
a contract with any local authority for the supply of water or light 
or for the scavenging of railway premises, or for any other service 
which the local authority may be rendering or be prepared to render 
within any part of the local area under its control.
</article>



 </act>