<act><tid>1074158</tid>
<title>THE NATIONAL CADET CORPS ACT, <year>1948</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 16th April, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of a National Cadet Corps.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a 
National Cadet Crops;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>900219</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and application.
<section><tid>23287</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the National Cadet Crops Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>414115</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and applies to all 
persons enrolled or appointed under this Act, wherever they may be.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1528271</tid>
<number>2</number>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything 
repugnant in the subject 
or context,-
" corps" means the National Cadet Corps constutited under this 
Act;

" enrolled" means enrolled in the Corps under this Act;

" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

" school" includes any institution recognised in this behalf 
by the Central Government or the State Government

" university" means any university established by law In India 
and includes colleges affiliated to universities, inter- 
mediate colleges and such technical institutions of colle- 
giate status, as are recognised in this behalf by the Central 
Government or the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1597701</tid>
<number>3</number>Constitution of the National cadet Corps. There shall be 
raised and maintained in the manner hereinafter provided a Corps to be 
designated the National Cadet Corps:
Provided that the Central Government may establish all or any of the 
units of the Corps as and when necessary.



</article>



<article><tid>1184523</tid>
<number>4</number>Constitution and disbandment of units. The Central 
Government may constitute in any State <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> one or more units of 
the corps, members of which shall be recruited from amongst the 
students of any university or school, and may disband or reconstitute 
any units so constituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>108</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to--

Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>. s. 3 
and Sch. and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>)

Lakshadweep vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>). 
2 The words" except the State of Hyderabad" ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> 
omitted by Act of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" or Acceding State" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>5126</tid>
<number> 5</number> Division of the Crops into Divisions. There shall be three 
Divisions of the Corps, namely,-
<section><tid>333071</tid>
<number>i</number>the Senior Division, recruitment to which shall be from 
amongst the students of the male sex of any university;

</section>

<section><tid>706375</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Junior Division, recruitment to which shall be from 
amongst the students of the male sex of any school; and

</section>

<section><tid>481159</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Junior Division, recruitment to which shall be from 
amongst the students of the female sex of any university or 
school.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>312449</tid>
<number> 6</number> Enrolment.
<section><tid>978711</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student of the male sex of any  
university may offer himself for enrolment as a cadet in the Senior 
Division, and any student of the male sex of any school may offer 
himself for enrolment as a cadet in the Junior Division if he is of 
the prescribed age or over.

</section>

<section><tid>1640044</tid>
<number>2</number>Any student of the female sex of any university or school 
may offer herself for enrolment as a cadet in the Girls Division:
Provided that in the latter case she is of the prescribed age or 
over.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1867758</tid>
<number>7</number>Central Government may ralse other units. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, the Central Government may, by 
notification, provide for the constitution of any other units of the 
Corps in any place and prescribe the persons or class of persons who 
may be eligible for enrolment therein.


</article>



<article><tid>898557</tid>
<number>8</number>Discharge. Every person enrolled under this Act shall be 
entitled to receive his or her discharge from the Corps on the 
expiration of the period for which he or she was enrolled or on his or 
her ceasing to be borne on the roll of the university or school to 
which he or she may belong:
Provided that any person enrolled may be discharged at any time 
by such authority and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.



</article>



<article><tid>1146026</tid>
<number>9</number>Appointment of Officers. The Central Government may provide 
for the appointment of officers in or for any unit of the Corps either 
from amongst members of the staff of any university or school or 
otherwise and may prescribe the duties, powers and functions of such 
officers.


</article>



<article><tid>1202278</tid>
<number>10</number>Duties of persons subject to this Act. No person subject to 
this Act shall by virtue of being a member of the Corps be liable for 
active military service, but subject thereto any such person shall be 
liable to perform such duties and discharge such obligations as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1619054</tid>
<number>11</number>Punishment for offences under this Act. Any person enrolled 
under this Act may be punished for the contravention of any rule made 
under this Act with fine which may extend to fifty rupees to be 
recovered in such manner and by such authority as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>109</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>896595</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to appoint Advisory Committee.
<section><tid>382416</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may for the purpose of advising it on all matters of policy 
connected with the constitution and administration of the Corps 
appoint a Central Advisory Committee consisting of the following 
persons, namely:-

<subsection><tid>217449</tid>
<number>a</number>the Minister for Defence, who shall be the Chairman of 
the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>748654</tid>
<number>b</number>the Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of 
Defence, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911086</tid>
<number>c</number>the Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of 
Education, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>639285</tid>
<number>d</number>the Financial Adviser, Defence, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344289</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief of the Army Staff, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918764</tid>
<number>f</number>the Chief of the Naval Staff, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1606107</tid>
<number>g</number>the Chief of the Air Staff, ex- officio;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>439680</tid>
<number>h</number>five non- official members to be nominated by the 
Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>905747</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> three Members of Parliament of whom two shall be 
elected by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>579442</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> A member elected under clause (i) of sub- section (1) shall 
hold office for a period of one year from the date of his election or 
until he ceases to be a Member of the House which elected him. 
whichever is earlier.]

</section>

<section><tid>1994845</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may also appoint for the same purpose 
as is specified in sub- section (1), such <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State Advisory 
Committees as it may consider desirable from time to time and may 
prescribe their duties and functions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1503302</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>882965</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules 5 to carry out the objects of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>644287</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power such rules may-

<subsection><tid>1538684</tid>
<number>a</number>prescribe the conditions subject to which universities 
of schools shall be allowed to raise units under this Act

<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1955</year> s. 2 and Sch., for the former clauses 
 (e), (f) and (g).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl. (i) has been successively subs. by Act 57 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2 and 
Act 50 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2. (w. e. f. 16- 8- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 16- 8- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" Provincial or" were omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>For National Cadet Crops Rules, <year>1948</year>, see Notification No. 289, 
Gazette of India. <year>1949</year>, Pt. I, see. 3, p. 239.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1704636</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribe the persons or class of persons who may be eligible for 
enrolment under section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1081219</tid>
<number>c</number>prescribe the manner in which, the period for which and the 
conditions subject to which any person or class of persons may be 
enrolled under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1149165</tid>
<number>d</number>provide for the medical examination of persons offering 
themselves for enrolment under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042763</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribe preliminary and periodical military training for any 
person or class of persons subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>622255</tid>
<number>f</number>prescribe the military or other obligations to which members of 
the Corps shall be liable when undergoing military training and 
provide generally for the maintenance of discipline amongst members of 
the Corps;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1695041</tid>
<number>g</number>prescribe the duties, powers and functions of officers appointed 
under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1149228</tid>
<number>h</number>prescribe the allowances or other remuneration payable to persons 
subject to this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1033428</tid>
<number>i</number>provide for the removal or discharge of any person subject to 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1692379</tid>
<number>j</number>prescribe the offences for which any person subject to this Act 
may be tried and provide for the trial thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819895</tid>
<number>k</number>prescribe the manner in which fines levied under this Act may be 
recovered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1720340</tid>
<number>l</number>prescribe the duties, powers and functions of Central or State 
Advisory Committees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1827353</tid>
<number>m</number>provide for any other matter which under this Act is to be or may 
be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>698654</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modi- 
fication in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be 
made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form 
or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.],

<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Provincial" were Omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3, (w. e. f. 16- 8- <year>1975</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>