<act><title>

THE 


    CHARITABLE AND RELIGIOUS TRUSTS ACT, 1920</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This act may be called the Charitable and Religious Trusts Act, 1920.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[except the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir]:
 

    Provided that the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Government of any State] may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, direct that this Act, or any specified part 
    thereof, shall not extend to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[that State or any specified area 
    therein] or to any specified trust or class of trusts.








  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Interpretation.—In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context, “the 
    court” means the court of the district Judge <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[or any other court 
    empowered in that behalf by the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[State Government]] and includes 
    the High Court in the exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction.
    






  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Power to apply to the court in respect of trusts of a charitable or 
    religious nature.—Save 
    as hereinafter provided in this Act, any person having an interest in any 
    express or constructive trust created or existing for a public purpose of a 
    charitable or religious nature may apply by petition to the court within the 
    local limits of whose jurisdiction any substantial part of the 
    subject-matter of the trust is situate to obtain an order embodying all or 
    any of the following directions, namely:—
 <section>
<number>1</number>   directing the 
    trustee to furnish the petitioner through the court with particulars as to 
    the nature and objects of the trust, and of the value, condition, management 
    and application of the subject-matter of the trust, and of the income 
    belonging thereto, or as to any of these matters, and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   directing that the 
    accounts of the trust shall be examined and audited:
 

    Provided that no person shall apply for any such direction in respect of 
    accounts relating to a period more than three years prior to the date of the 
    petition.
 




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Contents and verification of petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The petition shall show in what way the petitioner claims to be interested 
    in the trust, and shall specify, as far as may be, the particulars and the 
    audit which he seeks to obtain.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The petition shall be in writing and shall be signed and verified in the 
    manner prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for 
    signing and verifying plaints.
 




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Procedure on petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the court on receipt of a petition under section 3, after taking such 
    evidence and making such inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, is 
    of opinion of that the trust to which the petition relates is a trust to 
    which this Act applies, and that the petitioner has an interest therein, it 
    shall fix a date for the hearing of the petition, and shall cause a copy 
    thereof, together with notice of the date so fixed, to be served on the 
    trustee and upon any other person to whom in its opinion notice of the 
    petition should be given.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    the date fixed for the hearing of the petition, or on any subsequent date to 
    which the hearing may be adjourned, the court shall proceed to hear the 
    petitioner and the trustee, if he appears, and any other person who has 
    appeared in consequence of the notice, or who it considers ought to be 
    heard, and shall make such further inquiries, if any, as it thinks fit. The 
    trustee may and, if so required by the court, shall at the time of the first 
    hearing or within such time as the court may permit present a written 
    statement of his case. If he does present a written statement, the statement 
    shall be signed and verified in the manner prescribed by the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908(5 of 1908), for signing and verifying pleadings.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    any person appears at the hearing of the petition and either denies the 
    existence of the trust or denies that it is a trust to which this Act 
    applies, and undertakes to institute within three months a suit for a 
    declaration to that effect and for any other appropriate relief, the court 
    shall order a stay of the proceedings and, if such suit is so instituted, 
    shall continue the stay until the suit is finally decided.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    no such undertaking is given, or if after the expiry of the three months no 
    such suit has been instituted, the court shall itself decide the question.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On 
    completion of the inquiry provided for in sub-section (2), the Court shall 
    either dismiss the petition or pass thereon such other order as it thinks 
    fit;
 

    Provided that, where a suit has been instituted in accordance with the 
    provisions of sub-section (3), no order shall be passed by the court which 
    conflicts with the final decision therein.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Save as provided in this section, the Court shall not try or determine any 
    question of title between the petitioner and any person claiming title 
    adversely to the trust.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Failure of trustee to comply with order under section 5.—If 
    a trustee without reasonable excuse fails to comply with an order made under 
    sub-section (5) of section 5, such trustee shall, without prejudice to any 
    other penalty or liability which he may incur under any law for the time 
    being in force, be deemed to have committed a breach of trust affording 
    ground for a suit under the provisions of section 92 of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908; and any such suit may, so far as it is based on such 
    failure, be instituted without the previous consent of the Advocate General.
 




























  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Powers of trustee to apply for directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as hereinafter provided in this Act, any trustee of an express or 
    constructive trust created or existing for public purpose of a charitable or 
    religious nature may apply by petition to the court within the local limits 
    of whose jurisdiction any substantial part of the subject-matter of the 
    trust is situate, for the opinion, advice of direction of the court on any 
    question affecting the management or administration of the trust property, 
    and the court shall give its opinion, advice or direction, as the case may 
    be, thereon:
 

    Provided that the court shall not be bound to give such opinion, advice or 
    direction on any question which it considers to be a question not proper for 
    summary disposal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The court on a petition under sub-section (1), may either give its opinion, 
    advice or direction thereon forthwith, or fix a date for the hearing of the 
    petition, and may direct a copy thereof, together with notice of the date so 
    fixed, to be served on such of the persons interested in the trust, or to be 
    published for information in such manner, as it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    any date fixed under sub-section (2) or on any subsequent date to which the 
    hearing may be adjourned, the Court, before giving any opinion, advice or 
    direction, shall afford a reasonable opportunity of being heard to all 
    persons appearing in connection with the petition.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    trustee stating in good faith the facts of any matter relating to the trust 
    in a petition under sub-section (1), and acting upon the opinion, advice or 
    direction of the Court given thereon, shall be deemed, as far as his own 
    responsibility is concerned, to have discharged his duty as such trustee in 
    the matter in respect of which the petition was made.
 




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Costs of petition under this 
      Act.—The 
      costs, charges and expenses of and incidental to any petition, and all 
      proceedings in connection therewith, under the forgoing provisions of this 
      Act, shall be in the discretion of the court which may direct the whole or 
      any part of any such costs, charges and expenses to be met from the 
      property or income of the trust in respect of which the petition is made, 
      or to be borne and paid in such manner and by such persons as it thinks 
      fit:
 Provided that no such order 
      shall be made against any person (other than the petitioner) who has not 
      received notice of the petition and had a reasonable opportunity of being 
      heard thereon.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> 
      Savings.—No 
      petition under the foregoing provisions of this Act in relation to any 
      trust shall be entertained in any of the following circumstances, 
      namely:—
 
 <section><number>a</number>   if a suit 
        instituted in accordance with the provisions of section 92 of the Code 
        of Civil Procedure, 1908 is pending in respect of the trust in 
        question;
 </section><section><number>b</number>   if the trust 
        property is vested in the Treasurer of Charitable Endowments, the 
        Administrator-General, the Official Trustee, or any Society registered 
        under the Societies Registration Act, 1860; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>   if a scheme 
        for the administration of the trust property has been settled or 
        approved by any court of competent jurisdiction, or by any other 
        authority acting under the provisions of any 
      enactment.</section>
   
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Power of Courts as to costs in certain suits against trustees of charitable 
    and religions trusts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any suit instituted under section 14 of the Religious Endowments Act, 
    1863(20 of 1963), or under section 92 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 
    (5 of 1908), the court trying such suit may, if, on application of the 
    plaintiff and after hearing the defendant and making such inquiry as it 
    thinks fit, it is satisfied that such an order is necessary in the public 
    interest, direct the defendant either to furnish security for any 
    expenditure incurred or likely to be incurred by the plaintiff in 
    instituting and maintaining such suit, or to deposit from any money in his 
    hands as trustee of the trust to which the suit relates such sum as such 
    court considers sufficient to meet such expenditure in whole or in part.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    When any money has been deposited in accordance with an order made under 
    sub-section (1), the court may make over to the plaintiff the whole or any 
    part of such sum for the conduct of the suit. Before making over any sum to 
    the plaintiff, the court shall take security from the plaintiff for the 
    refund of the same in the event of such refund being subsequently ordered by 
    the court.
 










  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure to apply.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, relating to—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the proof of 
      facts by affidavit,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the enforcing of 
      the attendance of any person and his examination on oath,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the enforcing of 
      the production of documents, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the issuing of 
      commissions,
 
shall apply to all proceedings under this 
      Act, and the provisions relating to the service of summonses shall apply 
      to the service of notices thereunder.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The provisions of the said Code relating to the execution of decrees shall, 
    so far as they are applicable, apply to the execution of orders under this 
    Act.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Barring of appeals.—No 
    appeal shall lie from any order passed or against any opinion, advice or 
    direction given under this Act<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>.



  

 
  
 

  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   This 
    Act has been extended to Berar by the Berar Laws Act, 1941 (4 of 1941) and 
    rep. in Orissa by the Orissa Hindu Religious Endowments Act, 1939 (Orissa 4 
    of 1939). The provisions of this Act, insofar as they are inconsistent with 
    the provisions of the Bengal Wakf Act, 1934 (Ben. 13 of 1934), do not apply 
    to any Wakf property in Bengal: see section 81 of that Act.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “except Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. 
    by the A.O. 1937 for “G.G. in C.”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. 
    by the A.O. 1937., for “any specified province or area”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 Ins. by Act 41 of 
    1923, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   In 
    the application of this Act to West Bengal, a new section 13 providing that 
    the provisions of this Act shall not, so far as they are inconsistent with 
    those of the Bengal Wakf Act, 1934 (Ben. 13 of 1934), apply to any Wakf 
    property in West Bengal, has been ins.: see  Bengal Wakf Act, 1934, 
    section 81.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>