<act><title>


The National Environment Appellate Authority 
(Appeal) Rules, 19971</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Environment Appellate Authority (Appeal) 
Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these Rules unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number> “appeal” means a memorandum of appeal to the Appellate Au­thority filed 
under sub-section (1) of section 11 of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number> “appellant” means a person who prefers an appeal to the Authority under 
sub-section (1) of section 11 of the Act and also includes the authorised 
representative of the appellant;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number> “authorised representative” means any person authorised in writing by the 
appellant or the respondent, as the case may be, to represent him before the 
Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number> “Authority” means the National Environment Appellate Authori­ty, constituted 
under the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number> “member” means a member of the Authority and includes the chairperson and 
vice-chairperson thereof;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number> “party” in relation to an appeal, means an appellant or the respondent and 
the expression “parties” shall be construed to mean the appellant and the 
respondent;
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number> “Registrar” means the principal administrative officer of the authority;
 </section><section>
        
<number>i</number> “section” means section of the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>j</number> words and phrases not defined in these rules but defined in the National 
Environment Appellate Act, 1997, shall have the same meaning respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Language of the 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The pleadings before the Authority may, at the option of the respective parties, 
be in English or in Hindi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All orders and other 
proceedings of the Authority may, at the option of the authority, be in English 
or in Hindi.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Headquarters of the 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The headquarters of the Authority shall be at Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Appeals may be heard 
at the headquarters or at the discre­tion of the Chairperson, at any other 
place.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The office of the 
Authority shall observe such public and other holidays as are observed by the 
offices of the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Form of memorandum 
of appeal and its presentation before the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The memorandum of appeal to be presented to the Authority shall be in Form A 
specified in these rules and shall contain the particulars required thereunder. 
The memorandum of appeal shall be in English or in Hindi and shall set forth 
conci­sely and under distinct heads, the grounds of appeal without any argument 
or narrative and such grounds shall be numbered consecu­tively.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every memorandum of 
appeal shall be presented by the appell­ant in person, or when there are more 
appellants than one, by any of them, or by his authorised representative before 
the Registrar or any other officer authorised in this behalf by the chairman or 
may be sent by registered post with acknowledgement due addressed to the 
Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the memorandum 
of appeal is sent by registered post, the date of receipt of the said memorandum 
at the head office, as endorsed by either of them, shall be taken as the date of 
filling of the appeal by the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where there is a delay 
in the presentation of the memorandum of appeal before the Authority, such 
memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied by a separate application for 
condonation of delay and the supporting affidavit of such application.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every memorandum of 
appeal and the attested copy of the order appealed against and the application 
for condonation of delay and the supporting affidavit to be filed before the 
Authority shall be accompanied by five sets of their copies for the Authority 
and one set of copies for each of the respondents.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In every appeal, the 
competent authority which passed the order appealed against, shall be impleaded 
as one of the respond­ents.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Registration of 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal duly filed under these rules shall be registered as 
an appeal filed before the Authority and numbered by the Registrar. If the 
appeal is registered and numbered or if not so registered or numbered, the 
appellant, or his representative shall be informed according­ly by an intimation 
sent in this regard by the Registrar or other authorised officer within fifteen 
days of the receipt of the appeal. If the intimation so sent is of 
non-registering and non numbering, it shall be in Form B specified to these 
rules and time not exceeding thirty days shall be given for removing of such 
causes. On removal of such causes the appeal shall be regis­tered and numbered 
and intimation given.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After registration and 
numbering of the appeal, notices of appeal along with the set of copies of 
memorandum of appeal and other annexures thereto, shall be sent to every 
respondent, under registered post, acknowledgement(s) due, intimating the date 
and place of hearing of the appeal by the Authority. Information of the date and 
place of hearing of the appeal shall also be given to appellant or his 
representative by registered post with ac­knowledgement due. In addition to 
above, such intimations shall also be given to parties, under certificate of 
posting duly addressed, as found in the memorandum of appeal. Due service of 
such notices shall be presumed by the Authority if sent to ad­dresses, found in 
the memorandum of appeal, before fifteen days from the date fixed for hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notices of intimation 
to be sent to the parties by the Au­thority shall be in Form C specified to 
these rules.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Adjournment.—The 
Authority may adjourn the hearing of the appeal and intimate the parties to 
appear on the next date and place of hearing of the appeal.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Clubbing of appeals.—Appeals 
against a common order, can be clubbed and heard together by the Authority.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Default of 
appearance of parties at the hearing.—When 
the appellant or his representative fails to be present at the hear­ing of the 
appeal before the Authority, the appeal may be dis­missed for such default of 
appearance or may be decided ex parte. Similarly, when the respondent or 
his representative dues not appear at the hearing of the appeal, the appeal may 
be heard ex parte and decided finally. Where the appeal is dismissed for default 
of appearance or the appeal is allowed ex parte, the order so made may be 
set aside if the defaulting party shows sufficient cause for non-appearance by 
filing an application supported by affidavit, with the required number of copies 
given for the Authority and served on opposing parties and appeal heard afresh 
with notice to all parties and decided on merits.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Proceedings open to 
public.—Hearing 
of the appeals by the Authority shall be open to public unless otherwise ordered 
by the Chairperson for security or other reasons.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Orders of the 
Authority.—After 
hearing of the appeals, the orders of the Authority may be pronounced on the 
same day or may be postponed to a future date. Where the order is postponed, the 
same shall be delivered on the date to be fixed for the purpose by the Authority 
and copies thereof shall be sent to parties to the appeal by the Registrar or 
any other authorised officer.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Orders of the 
Authority and time-frame for disposal of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall dispose of the appeal within ninety days from the date of 
filing of the appeal: 
 
Provided that the 
Authority may by reasons to be recorded in writing, extend it by a further 
period of thirty days. Every order of the Authority disposing of an appeal 
finally shall be in writing, signed and dated by the Chairperson, or 
Vice-Chairperson and member or members, who have heard the appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the order of the 
Authority finally disposing of the appeal in unanimous, an order shall be 
pronounced by the Authori­ty.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the members of the 
Authority differ in opinion on any point, the point shall be decided according 
to the opinion of the majority, if there is a majority, but if the members are 
equally divided, they shall state the point or points on which they differ and 
make a reference to the Chairperson of the Authority and his opinion on the 
point shall be the opinion of the majori­ty.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No order of the 
Authority shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy or defect in the constitu­tion of the Authority or any defect in the 
appointment of a person acting as the member of the Authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Additional 
evidence.—If at 
any stage of hearing of the appeal, the Authority considers that additional 
evidence needs to be taken by if for a proper disposal of the appeal, if can 
either take on record such evidence directly of obtain the same from the 
authority against the order of which the appeal is filed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Principles of 
natural justice.—When 
there are no specific rules governing the hearing of the appeal, principles of 
natural justice shall be observed.
</article><form>
 




The National Environment Appellate Authority  

(Appeal) Rules, 1997
 


 
 




Form A
 


[See rule 5(1)]
 




Before the National Environment Appellate Authority,  

New Delhi
 



Memorandum of appeal
 


(Under section 11(1) of the 
National Environment Appellate Au­thority Act, 1997)
 


Appeal 
No..........................of..................
 


Between :
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                       
............Appellant/s
 


and
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                  
.............respondent/s
 


(1) The address/es of the 
appellant/s is/are as given above for the service of notices of this appeal and 
that of their represen­tative......................................
 


(2) The addresses of the 
respondent/s is/are as given above for the service of notices of this 
appeal.....................................
 


(3) The appellant/s 
above-named begs to present this Memorandum of Appeal against the order 
dated................ of......re­spondent/s granting environmental clearance in 
favour of respond­ents for on the grounds set out hereunder:
 


                                                                           
Facts in brief
 


1. 
 


2.
 


3.
 


                                                                           
Grounds
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


                                                                           
Limitation
 


                                                                           
Prayer
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 



...............................................
 


Signature of the 
appellant(s)
 



...............................................
 


Signature of authorised      
 

representative of the appellant(s)
 



Verification
 



I,..................................the appellant, do hereby declare that what 
is stated above is true to the best of my information and belief.
 


      
Verified today the..........................................day 
of.............................................
 



..................................................
 


Signature of the 
appellant(s)
 



..................................................
 


Signature of authorised      
  

representative of the appellant(s)
 





</form><form>
 




The National Environment Appellate Authority  

(Appeal) Rules, 1997
 


 
 




Form B
 


[See rule 6(1)]
 




Before the National Environment Appellate Authority,  

New Delhi
 


Appeal 
No......................of.......................
 


Between :
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                       
............Appellant/s
 


and
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                  
.............respondent/s
 


Notice
 


You have filed the above 
against the order dated......... of the respondent granting environmental 
clearance in favour of the respondent/s.
 


On scrutinizing of appeal, 
the following defects are noticed:
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


4.
 


Please note the above 
defects are to be removed on or before.......................................... 
if the appeal has to be registered for hearing and disposal. You may also note 
that if the defects are not so removed the appeal will be placed for orders of 
rejection before the Appellate Authority.
 


Seal : 
........................
 


Signature of Registrar or
 

authorised officer  
 


 
</form><form>
 




The National Environment Appellate Authority  

(Appeal) Rules, 1997
 


 
 




Form C
 


[See rule 6(3)]
 




Before The National Environment Appellate Authority,  

New Delhi
 


Appeal 
No....................................of....................
 


Between:
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                       
............Appellant/s
 


and
 


1.
 


2.                                                                                                                                                  
.............respondent/s
 


Notice
 


      
Please take notice that the above appeal filed by the appellant/against order 
dated............... of the 
respondent......................................granting environmental clearance 
in favour of the respondents.....................National Environmental 
Ap­pellate Authority at Premises No.
 


      
The copies of the appeal memorandum and other annexures filed along with it are 
sent to you for your reference.
 


      
Please note that if you fail to appear on the said date or other subsequent date 
of hearing of the appeal by the authority, the appeal would be disposed of 
finally by placing you ex parte.
 


Seal: 
.........................
 



.........................................
 


Signature of Registrar or

 


authorised officer  
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>