<act><title>
THE 
    REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS 
    RULES, 19921</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title, commencement and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Registration of Foreigners Rules, 1992.
 </section></article><article>


    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
    Official Gazette.
 </article><article>


    <number>3</number> They extend to the whole of India. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context,—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    “Act” means the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (16 of 1939);  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    “Certificate of Registration” means a certificate of Registration 
    issued in pursuance of rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    “Master of the Vessel” includes the pilot of an Aircraft and any 
    person authorised by such master or pilot to discharge on his behalf any of 
    the duties imposed upon him by these rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>    “Form” means one of the Forms appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>e</number>    “Passenger” means any person travelling or seeking to travel on 
    vessel who is not a bona fide seaman;  
 </section><section>


    <number>f</number>    “Registered Address” means a foreigner’s address in India as reported 
    under rule 6 and recorded in item 11 of his Certificate of Registration;  
 </section><section>


    <number>g</number>    “Registration Officer” means a Registration Officer appointed by the 
    Central Government under rule 3 and includes an authority authorised in 
    writing by a Registration Officer with the approval of the Central 
    Government to perform the duties of the Registration Officer on his behalf;  
 </section><section>


    <number>h</number>    “Residence” means ordinary dwelling place in India;  
 </section><section>


    <number>i</number>    “Seaman” means a person employed on, or engaged in the working of a 
    vessel;  
 </section><section>


    <number>j</number>    “Tourist” means a foreigner having no residence or occupation in 
    India whose stay in India does not ordinarily exceed six months, who has no 
    other object in visiting India than recreation, sightseeing or attending, in 
    a representative capacity, meetings convened by the Government of India or 
    International bodies or any other meeting or conference cleared by the 
    Government of India;  
 </section><section>


    <number>k</number>    “Vessel” includes aircraft but does not include a vessel travelling 
    solely between ports or places in India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Registration Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may appoint Registration Officers for the purposes of 
    these rules for such areas as it thinks fit.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A Registration Officer may, with the approval of the Central Government, 
    authorise in writing any authority to perform any or all of his functions 
    under these rules.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Passengers on vessels to report arrival in India.—Every 
    passenger who arrives in India on board any vessel shall on being required 
    so to do by or on behalf of, the master of the vessel, furnish true 
    particulars as to his name and nationality, his age, sex, place of birth, 
    and address or intended address in India, the purpose of his visit and the 
    proposed length of his stay in India.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Report by foreigners on arrival in and departure from India by land.—Every 
    foreigner who enters or leaves India by land shall, on being required so to 
    do by the Registration Officer of the place of arrival or departure, as the 
    case may be, furnish to him a true statement of the particulars set out in 
    Form D.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Report by a foreigner of his address in India, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every foreigner entering India or resident in India shall present in person 
    or through an authorised representative to the appropriate Registration 
    Officer specified in rule 7, a report (hereinafter referred to as a 
    registration report) within the time specified in that rule:
 


    Provided that no such report shall be necessary in the case of a foreigner 
    who enters India on a visa valid for a period of not more than one hundred 
    and eighty days and who does not remain in India beyond the said period.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every registration report shall be made in writing in English or in 
    Hindi language and in quadruplicate and shall contain a true statement of 
    the foreigner’s address in India and of the other particulars specified in 
    Items 2 to 10 in Para IV of Form A and such of the particulars specified in 
    Items 12 to 16 thereof, as may be appropriate.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> For the purpose of sub-rule (2), a foreigner’s address in India shall 
    be—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    the place of his residence; or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    if he has no residence, the place at which, at the time of making his 
    registration report he is for the time being living or at which he first 
    intends to live after his arrival in India.  
 


    Provided that, subject to the approval of the Registration Officer, any 
    foreigner who has no residence in India may, with the consent previously 
    obtained of an Indian citizen residing in India, being a banker or a person 
    having the management of hotel or of a tourist or travel agency, report as 
    his address in India the name and address of the said Indian citizen and 
    such name and address shall, for so long as the provisions of sub-rule (4) 
    are complied with, be deemed to be the foreigner’s address in India:  
 


    Provided further that in the case of a foreigner who has no residence in 
    India, whose occupation is such as to necessitate frequent travelling, who 
    is not likely to return within a reasonable time to the district in which he 
    is at any time living and who is unable to avail himself of the provisions 
    of the foregoing proviso, the office of the Registration Officer of the 
    district in which he has first registered upon his arrival in India shall be 
    deemed to be his address in India.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>4</number> In any case to which the proviso to sub-rule (3) applies, it shall be 
    the duty,—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    of the foreigner to keep the Indian citizen informed of his current 
    address; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    of the Indian citizen to furnish all such information in his 
    possession relating to the foreigner as may be demanded for any of the 
    purposes of the Act or of these rules by any Registration Officer, 
    Magistrate or Police Officer not below the rank of head constable.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>5</number> Copies of Form A may be obtained on application from any Registration 
    Officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Procedure for Registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The registration report shall be presented—
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    in the case of a foreigner who enters India on a visa valid for a 
    stay in India for a period of one hundred and eighty days or less and who 
    wishes to stay in India beyond a period of one hundred and eighty days, to 
    the Registration Officer having jurisdiction in the place where the said 
    foreigner is present at the time of presentation of such report;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    in the case of foreigner who enters India on a visa valid for a stay 
    in India for a period of more than one hundred eighty days to such 
    Registration Officer as may be specified in this behalf by the Registration 
    Officer of the port or other place of arrival with the approval of the 
    Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    in the case of foreigner, who enters India otherwise than on a visa, 
    to the Registration Officer having jurisdiction in the place where the said 
    foreigner is present at the time of the presentation of such report;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>d</number>    in the case of a person who has become a foreigner by reason of his 
    having ceased to be a citizen of India while resident in India to the 
    Registration Officer having jurisdiction in the place where the said person 
    is ordinarily resident;  
 


    1[(e)    
    in the case of a foreigner who enters India with a persons of Indian Origin 
    Card, to the Registration Officer having jurisdiction in the place where the 
    said foreigner is ordinarily resident.  
 


Explanation.—In this clause, the expression “Person of Indian Origin” 
    means a person who is a foreign citizen of Indian Origin settled outside 
    India and to whom such card has been issued by the Central Government, 
    subject to such conditions, as it may specify in this behalf;]  
 


    2[(f)    
    in the case of a foreigner who enters India on a visa valid for a stay in 
    India for a period of more than one hundred and eighty days with a 
    stipulation that ’each stay shall not exceed one hundred and eight days’, 
    and who wishes to stay in India beyond the period of one hundred and eighty 
    days on any single occasion; to the Registration Officer having jurisdiction 
    in the place where the said foreigner is present at the time of presentation 
    of such report.]  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Registration report shall be presented—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    in the case of a foreigner referred to in clause (a) of sub-rule (1), 
    within two weeks after the expiry of one hundred and eight days of his 
    arrival in India;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    in the case of foreigner referred to in clause (b) of sub-rule (1), 
    within two weeks of his arrival in India;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    in the case of a foreigner referred to in clause (c) of sub-rule (1), 
    immediately after the expiry of the authorised period of stay in India;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>d</number>    in the case of foreigner referred to in clause (d) of sub-rule (1), 
    within fifteen days of his ceasing to be citizen of India.  
 


    1[(e)    
    in the case of a foreigner referred to in clause (e) of sub-clause (1), 
    within thirty days after the expiry of the period of one hundred and eighty 
    days of his arrival in India;]  
 


    2[(f)    
    in the case of a foreigner referred to in clause (f) of sub-rule (1), any 
    time before the expiry of the period of one hundred and eighty days of his 
    arrival in India.]  
 


    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (2), the date on which the person 
    concerned shall be deemed to have ceased to be a citizen of India shall be,—  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>a</number>    where he has voluntarily acquired the citizenship of another country 
    by naturalisation or registration, the date of such naturalisation or 
    registration;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    where he has obtained a passport from the Government of any other 
    country, the date on which such passport was obtained:  
 


    Provided that in the case of a person in respect of whom an order has been 
    made under sub-section (2) of section 9 of the Citizenship Act, 1955 (57 of 
    1955), holding that, he had acquired the citizenship of a foreign country 
    such date shall be the date of the order aforesaid.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>3</number> Every foreigner presenting a registration report shall furnish to the 
    Registration Officer such information as may be in his possession for the 
    purpose of satisfying the said officer as to the accuracy of the particulars 
    specified therein and shall, on being required to do sign the registration 
    report in the presence of the said officer and shall thereupon be entitled 
    to receive from the said officer a certificate of registration in Part III 
    of Form A:  
 


    Provided that, in any case in which the registration report is presented, in 
    accordance with clause (b) of sub-rule (1) by a foreigner whose address in 
    India is not within the jurisdiction of the Registration Officer of the port 
    or other place of arrival in India, temporary certificate in Form B shall be 
    issued and the said foreigner shall thereafter comply with the conditions 
    set out in Form B:  
 


    Provided further that any foreigner whose passport or other documents of 
    identification do not, in the opinion of the Registration Officer, provide 
    adequate proof of identity, shall be required to furnish to the Registration 
    Officer, within such period of presenting his registration report as such 
    officer may fix, either four copies of a photograph of himself of passport 
    size, one of which shall be affixed to Part III of Form A and over stamped 
    with the Stamp of Registration Officer or four complete sets of his finger 
    impressions, one of which shall be made on Part III of Form A, whichever the 
    Registration Officer may require. The finger impressions shall be made in 
    the presence of the Registration Officer and each set attested by him.  
 



 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>8</number> Period of validity of certificate of registration.—The 
    certificate of registration issued in respect of any foreigner shall be 
    valid for so long as the foreigner does not depart from India.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Production of proof of Identity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every foreigner shall within twenty-four hours of demand being made of him 
    by any Registration Officer, magistrate or police officer, not below the 
    rank of a head constable, produce, at such place as may be specified in his 
    passport or such other proof of his identity as may be required for any 
    purpose connected with the enforcement of these rules:  
 


    Provided that the said Registration Officer, magistrate or police officer 
    may, on sufficient cause being shown, extend the aforesaid period of 
    twenty-four hours to such period as, in the circumstances, may be necessary 
    for the production of the said passport or other proof of identity.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every Foreigner entering India shall, on demand being made of him by the 
    Registration Officer, deliver his passport or other proof of identity to 
    that officer and shall thereafter attend at such time and place as the 
    Registration Officer may direct for the purpose of receiving back his 
    passport.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Where in pursuance of sub-rule (2), a foreigner surrenders his passport 
    or other proof of identity he shall be entitled to receive a receipt for it 
    from the Registration Officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>10</number> Production of certificate of registration.—Every 
    registered foreigner shall, within twenty-four hours of demand being made of 
    him by any Registration Officer, any magistrate or any police officer not 
    below the rank of a head constable, produce or cause to be produced his 
    certificate of registration for his inspection of such registration officer, 
    magistrate or police officer:  
 


    Provided that the Registration Officer, magistrate or police officer may, on 
    sufficient cause being shown, extend the aforesaid period of twenty-four 
    hours to such period as, in the circumstances may be reasonably necessary 
    for the production of the said certificate:  
 


    Provided further that if the Registration Officer, magistrate or police 
    officer, not being below the rank of an Inspector is of the opinion that the 
    passport or other documents of identification produced by the foreigner do 
    not furnish adequate proof of identity and if the registration certificate 
    does not bear the photograph or finger impressions required by the second 
    proviso to sub-rule (3) of rule 7 the Registration Officer, magistrate or 
    police officer not being below the rank of an Inspector may require the 
    foreigner either to produce, four copies of a photograph of himself of 
    passport size, one of which shall be affixed to the registration certificate 
    and over stamped with the stamp of the officer or to furnish four complete 
    sets of his finger impressions one of which shall be made on the 
    registration certificate. The finger impression shall be made in the 
    presence of the Registration Officer and each set attested by him.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> Report of absence from address.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time a foreigner proposes to be absent from his registrered 
    address for a continuous period of eight weeks or more or he is changing his 
    registered address or he is finally departing from India, he shall, before 
    he leaves, inform in person or through an authorised representative or by 
    registered post his Registration Officer of his intention to leave either 
    temporarily or permanently the jurisdiction of the Registration Officer. In 
    case he is returning he should inform the Registration Officer of the date 
    of return and in the case he is moving away, the change of address. Any 
    changes made subsequently should also be intimated to the Registration 
    Officer:  
 


    Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall apply in the case of any 
    foreigner in respect of whom, in pursuance of the proviso to sub-rule (3) of 
    rule 6, the address of Indian citizen is deemed to be his registered 
    address.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every foreigner, who stays for a period of more than eight weeks at any 
    place in any district other than the district in which his registered 
    address is situated, shall inform the Registration Officer of that district 
    of his presence.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The information required under sub-rule (2) may be made in writing and 
    the requirements of the said sub-rule shall be deemed to have been fulfilled 
    if, prior to his arrival in a district other than that in which his 
    registered address is situated, the foreigner furnishes to the Registration 
    Officer of the said district intimation of the dates of his proposed arrival 
    in and departure from the said district.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Change in Registered address.—A 
    foreigner shall be deemed to have changed his registered address—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    if he departs from India;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    if he changes his residence from one place to another place in India;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    if having no residence, he leaves his registered address knowing that 
    he is not likely thereafter to return thereto within six months of leaving 
    it; or  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>    in any case to which the first proviso to sub-rule (3) of rule 6 
    applies, if either he or the Indian citizen whose address is deemed to be 
    his registered address applies to the Registration Officer to be absolved 
    from or fails at any time to discharge the obligations laid down upon them 
    by sub-rule (4) of that rule:  
 


    Provided that clause (c) of this rule shall not apply in any case in which 
    in accordance with the second proviso to sub-rule (3) of rule 6 the 
    foreigner’s registered address is the office of the Registration Officer of 
    the district in which he first registered upon his arrival in India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> Reports of change other than of address.—Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of rules 11 and 12 every foreigner shall furnish 
    to the Registration Officer of the district in which his registered address 
    is situated particulars of any circumstances affecting in any manner the 
    accuracy of the particulars recorded in his certificate of registration 
    within fourteen days after the circumstance has occurred, and generally 
    shall supply to the Registration Officer all such information as may be 
    necessary for maintaining the accuracy of the certificate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>14</number> Report to be made to and by hotel keepers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every keeper of a hotel shall require every visitor to the hotel to furnish 
    the particulars necessary for recording, and sign, on his arrival at the 
    hotel, his name and nationality in a register maintained for the purpose in 
    Form F and, if any such visitor is a foreigner shall further require him;  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    on his arrival at such a hotel to furnish the other particulars 
    specified in Items 4 to 10 of the said register; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    at the time of his departure from such a hotel to furnish the 
    particulars necessary for recording in the said register, the date and time 
    of his departure and the address to which he is proceeding.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> The register prescribed by sub-rule (1) shall at all time be made 
    available for inspection, on the demand of any Registration Officer, any 
    magistrate or any police officer not below the rank of head constable.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Every visitor to any hotel shall, on being required so to do by the 
    keeper of the hotel, furnish the particulars necessary for recording, and 
    sign, his name and nationality, in the register referred to in sub-rule (1), 
    and if such visitor is a foreigner, shall also,—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    on his arrival at such a hotel furnish the other particulars 
    specified in Items 4 to 10 of the said register; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    at the time of his departure from such hotel, furnish the particulars 
    necessary for recording, in the said register, the date and time of his 
    departure and the address to which he is proceeding.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>4</number> Every particulars, other than the signature of the keeper of a hotel or 
    a visitor, which is required by this rule to be recorded in the said 
    register shall be recorded by the keeper of the hotel and in the English 
    language, if he is so able, or otherwise, in an Indian language.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> If a visitor does not understand the English language it shall be duty 
    of the keeper of the hotel, if so requested to explain to the visitor the 
    requirements of this rule and Form F.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> The keeper of the hotel shall, as soon as may be but not more than 
    twenty-four hours, after the arrival of any foreigner, transmit a copy of 
    Form C, duly completed from the particulars furnished by such a foreigner, 
    to the Registration Officer.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> For the purpose of this rule,—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    “hotel” includes any boarding-house, club, dak-banglow, rest house, 
    paying guest house, sarai or other premises of like nature;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    “keeper of a hotel” means the person having the management of a hotel 
    and includes any person authorised by him, and competent to perform the 
    duties of the keeper of the hotel under this rule;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    “sign” includes, in respect of a visitor who is unable to write, the 
    making of a thumb impression or other mark by means of which he is 
    accustomed to attest a document; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>d</number>    “visitor” means a person for whom accommodation is provided at a 
    hotel.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>8</number> Copies of Form C may be obtained, on application from any Registration 
    Officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>15</number> Surrender of certificates of registration on departure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every foreigner who is about to depart finally from India shall surrender 
    his certificate of registration either to the Registration Officer of the 
    place where he is registered or of the place from where he intends to depart 
    or to the Immigration Officer at the Port/Checkpost of exit from India.  
 


    If the certificate is surrendered other than to the Immigration Officer of 
    the port or checkpost of exit, a receipt indicating such surrender of the 
    document may be obtained and shown to the Immigration Officer.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every passenger other than a passenger for whom a berth has been engaged 
    by or on behalf of Government, who is about to depart from India on board 
    any vessel shall, on the request of a person having the engagement of such 
    vessel, furnish or cause to be furnished in writing a true statement of the 
    particulars set out in Form D.  
 


    1[(3) 
    the Central Government shall, publish on the reverse of Form D, by way of 
    General or Special instructions, the requirements of any other law or the 
    rules made thereunder, which are applicable to the passengers.]  
 



 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>16</number> Obligation of masters of vessels, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The master or the person having management of any vessel arriving at or 
    leaving any place in India shall—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    require any person who intends to disembark from or embark on any 
    such vessel for the purpose of entering or leaving India, to furnish in 
    writing a true statement of the particulars set out in Form D, as the case 
    may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    cause Form D to be delivered to the Registration Officer at the place 
    of arrival or departure;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    take steps to ensure that no foreigner disembarks or embarks until 
    authorised so to do by the Registration Officer;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>d</number>    if so requested by the Registration Officer require any foreign 
    passenger about to depart from India to surrender his certificate of 
    registration and deliver such certificate to Registration Officer;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>e</number>    if so required by the Registration Officer, furnish on arrival at the 
    said place a true statement in writing showing the name and nationality of 
    every seaman employed on such vessel, and at the time of departing from such 
    place take such steps as the Registration Officer may specify to ascertain 
    whether or not any such seaman as aforesaid who is a foreigner is about to 
    depart on board such vessel; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>f</number>    generally render to the Registration Officer such assistance as he 
    may reasonably require for carrying out the purpose of the Act and these 
    rules.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> The master or the person having the management of any vessel arriving 
    at, or leaving any place in India by Sea shall also furnish, before any 
    passenger disembarks or embarks, to the Registration Officer of any such 
    place, a passenger manifest in Form E.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Every particular, other than the signature of a foreign passenger, which 
    is required by this rule to be recorded in Form D, as the case may be, shall 
    be recorded;  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    if the passenger is able to write in English language, by the 
    passenger and in the English language;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    if the passenger is unable to write in English language, by the 
    passenger in an Indian language; or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    if the passenger is unable to write either in English language or in 
    an Indian language by the master of the vessl or by any person having the 
    management of such vessel or by any seaman authorised in this behalf by such 
    master or person, in the English language or in an Indian language.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>4</number> If a foreign passenger does not understand the English language or 
    Indian language it shall be the duty of the master of the vessel, if so 
    requested, to explain to the foreign passenger the requirement of this rule.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> Form E shall be completed in the English language or in an Indian 
    language.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> Copies of Forms D and E may be obtained, on application from any 
    Registration Officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>17</number> Duplicate certificate of registration.—If 
    any certificate of registration, issued under these rules is lost or 
    destroyed, the foreigner to whom it was issued, shall make or send to the 
    Registration Officer of the district of his registered address a report of 
    circumstances in which it was so lost or destroyed together with an 
    application in writing for the issue of a duplicate copy of the certificate 
    of registration.  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS  

    RULES, 1992
 

 
 




    Form A
 




    (Rule 6)
 




    (To be completed in quadruplicate)
 




    Part I.—Registration report.
 




    Part II.—Duplicate registration report.
 




    Part III.—Certificate of registration (vide rules 2, 5, 6, 7, 9, 12, 
    13, 15, 16 and 17).
 




    Part IV. Triplicate of registration report.
 




                 1.  Serial Number.
 




                 2.  Name in full (block capitals, surname first).
 




                 3.  Sex......................Height......................Colour 
    of eyes.......................
 




                 4.  Date and place of birth.
 




                 5.  Present nationality.
 




                 6.  Previous nationality (if any).
 




                 7.  Manner and date of acquiring present nationality.
 




                 8.  Occupation or profession, and purpose of visiting India.
 




                 9.  If a member of any country’s naval, military or air-force, 
    or its reserves, state which country’s and rank held.
 




               10.  Number, date and office of issue of passport or particulars 
    of other proof of identity.
 




               11.  Address or intended address in India.
 




               12.  Post or place of embarkation or departure for India.
 




               13.  Date and place of arrival in India.
 




               14.  Name of vessel on which or how arrived in India.
 




               15.  Address of last residence outside India.
 




               16.  Name of hushand/wife and children and their nationalities 
    (if accompanying the visitor).
 




               17.  Signature of registree.
 




               18.  Date of expiry of registration.
 




                            (only for tourists)1
 




                                                                                                                     
    (Signed)...................
 




                                                                                                                     
    (Seal)
 




                                                                                                                     
    Signed
 




                                                                                                                     
    (Registration Officer)
 




    Registered 
    at....................................on.....................................................20.........
 




    Registration transferred to:
 
 
  
 
District
 
Date
 
Signature and Seal of Registration Office 
        of District in Column I

 
  
 
(1)
 
(2)
 
(3)

 
 
1.
  
  
  

 
 
2.
  
  
  

 
 
3.
  
  
  

 
 
4.
  
  
  


 

 
 




    Notice
 




    1. Every registered foreigner is required:
 




    (I)  On the demand of any Registration Officer or Magistrate or any police 
    officer not below the rank of head constable to produce this Certificate and 
    his passport or such other proof of identity as may be required of him by 
    such Magistrate or officer.
 




    (II)  To surrender his certificate of registration, if he is about to depart 
    finally from India either to the Registration Officer of the place where he 
    is registered or of the place from where he intends to depart or to the 
    Immigration Officer at the port/checkpost of exit from India.
 




    (III)  To intimate in person or through an authorised representative or by 
    post under certificate of posting the Registration Officer of the district 
    in which his registered address is situated—
 




    (a)   before he leaves his registered address, if he proposes to be absent 
    from his registered address for a continuous period of eight weeks or more, 
    the address or addresses at which he proposes to stay and the date on which 
    he expects to return to his registered adddress.
 




    (b)   if he proposes to change his registered address or to leave India, the 
    particulars of his new address and the date of the proposed change or 
    departure; and
 




    (c)   any circumstances which in any way affect the accuracy of any of the 
    particulars set out in his Certificate of Registration.
 




    (IV)  if he stays for more than eight weeks at any place (other than a hotel 
    or other premises where travellers are accommodated) in any district other 
    than district in which his registered address is situated to report his 
    presence in that other district to the Registration Officer thereof within 
    seven days of his arrival.
 




    (2) Failure to comply with the foregoing provisions will render the holder 
    of this certificate liable to be punished with imprisonment or fine or both, 
    under section 5 of the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (XVI of 1939).
 



 


-----------------
 


     1.   As per 
    Hindi version.
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS  

    RULES, 1992
 



 



 




    Form B
 




    Temporary Certificate of Registration
 




    (Rule 7)
 




    Serial Number....................
 




    Mr...................a foreigner of..............nationality who arrived in 
    India on the.......................20........is directed to report to the 
    ...........at........within seven days for the purpose of registration.
 




    2. For a period of one week or until the report prescribed above has been 
    made, whichever, is less, this Form will be deemed to be a Certificate of 
    Registration in Part III of Form A and must be produced on the demand of any 
    Registration Officer, Magistrate, or police officer not below the rank of 
    head constable.
 




    3. If for any reason that report prescribed in paragraph I cannot be made 
    within one week the holder of this Form is directed to report in person at 
    the office of the undersigned or of the nearest Registration Officer and to 
    comply with such directions as to registration as may then be given.
 




    4. The contents of this Form have been explained to the holder thereof.
 




                                                                                                                                     
    (Signed)
 




                                                                                                                           
    Registration Officer
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS  

    RULES, 1992
 

 
 

 
 




    Form E
 




    (See rule 17)
 




    Passenger manifest
 




    Name of shipping 
    company....................................................................................
 




    Name of 
    vessel...................................................................................................
    
 




    Port and date of embarkation/disembarkation in 
    India................................................ 
 

 
 
 
 
Sl. No.
 
Name of Passenger
 
Nationality Disembarkation
 
Port of embarkation (abroad)
 
Port of disembarkation (abroad)

 
 
1
 
2
 
3
 
4
 
5

 
   

 
 

 
  
  
  
  


 

 
 

 
 





 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS  

    RULES, 1992
 

 
 

 
 




    Form F
 




    (See rule 14)
 




    Hotel RegisteR
 




            1.   Serial No.
 




            2.   Name of visitor in full (in block capitals, surname first).
 




            3.   Nationality.
 




            4.   Number, date and place of issue of passport.
 




            5.   Address in India.
 




            6.   Date of arrival in India.
 




            7.   Whether employed in India—Yes or No.
 




            8.   Proposed duration of stay in India.
 




            9.   Arrived from.
 




          10.   Number, date and place of issue of certificate of Registration, 
    if any.
 




          11.   Purpose of visit.
 




          12.   Date and time of departure from hotel.
 




          13.   Address to which proceeding.
 




          14.   Signature of visitor.
 





 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>