<act><title>THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972 </title> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, commencement 
and application.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may 
be called the Commissions of Inquiry (Central) Rules, 1972.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section><number>3</number> They shall apply to a 
Commission of Inquiry appointed by the Central Government under section 3 of the 
Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952.
  



</section></article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these Rules unless the context otherwise requires—
  1[
<section><number>a</number> ‘assessor’ 
means an assessor appointed by the Commission under section 5B of the 
Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952];
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> ‘Commission’ means a Commission of Inquiry 
appointed by the Central Government under section 2 of the Commissions of 
Inquiry Act, 1952.
  



</section></article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
  
 <article><number>3</number> Election of a presiding 
officer for a meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a 
Commission consists of 3 or more members, then during the temporary absence of 
the Chairman thereof, the members present and participating in its proceedings, 
may elect one member from amongst themselves, to preside, for the time being, in 
respect of the said proceedings.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The member who presides 
temporarily under sub-rule (1) shall not be deemed to be the Chairman of the 
Commission.
  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> The issue and service of summons. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A Commission may issue summons to persons whose attendance before it may be required either to give evidence or to produce documents. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every summons issued by a Commission shall be in duplicate and shall be signed by the Chairman thereof or by such person as he may empower in this behalf. It shall be sealed with the seal of the Commission and shall specify the time and place at which the person summoned is required to attend and also whether his attendance is required for the purpose of giving evidence or to produce a document, or for both the purposes. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A person may be summoned to produce a document, without being summoned to give evidence; and any person summoned merely to produce a document shall be deemed to have complied with the summons if he causes such document to be produced instead of attending personally to produce the same. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A summons to produce documents, may be for the production of all documents of a certain description in the possession or control of the person summoned. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every summon shall be served by sending it by post to the person, for whom it is intended or in such other manner as the Commission may direct. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The provisions of sub-rules (1) to (5) shall apply, as far as may be, to every other process issued by a Commission. 
</section></article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
  
 <article><number>5</number> Procedure of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Commission may sit in public or in private as it thinks fit:
 Provided that a Commission shall 
sit in private on a request being made by the Central Government in that behalf.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A Commission shall, as soon 
as may be after its appointment—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> issue a notice to every person, who in its 
opinion should be given an opportunity of being heard in the inquiry, to furnish 
to the Commission a statement relating to such matters as may be specified in 
the notice;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> issue a notification, to be published in such 
manner as it may deem fit, inviting all persons acquainted with the 
subject-matter of the inquiry to furnish to the Commission a statement relating 
to such matters as may be specified in the notification.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every statement furnished 
under clause (a) of sub-rule (2) shall be accompanied by an affidavit in support 
of the facts set out in the statement sworn by the person furnishing the 
statement.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every person furnishing a 
statement under clause (a) of sub-rule (2) shall also furnish to the Commission 
along with the statement a list of the documents, if any, on which he proposes 
to rely and forward to the Commission, wherever practicable the originals or 
true copies of such of the documents as may be in his possession or control and 
shall state the name and address of the person from whom the remaining documents 
may be obtained.
 </section><section><number>5</number>(a) A Commission shall 
examine all statements furnished to it under clause (b) of sub-rule (2) and if, 
after such examination, the Commission considers it necessary to record 
evidence, it shall first record the evidence, if any, produced by the Central 
Government and may thereafter record evidence in such order as it may deem fit:
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> the evidence of any person who has furnished a 
statement under clause (a) of sub-rule (2) and whose evidence the Commission 
having regard to the statement, considers relevant for the purpose of the 
inquiry; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> the evidence of any person whose evidence, in 
the opinion of the Commission, is relevant to the inquiry:
                  Provided that the Commission may dispense 
with the attendance of any person for the purpose of giving evidence before it, 
if in its opinion—
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>i</number> such attendance cannot be enforced except 
by causing undue hardship or inconvenience to that person;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> such attendance should be dispensed with 
for any other sufficient reason to be recorded by it in writing.
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> If, after all the evidence 
is recorded under clause (a) of sub-rule (5), the Central Government applies to 
the Commission to recall any witness already examined or to examine any new 
witness, the Commission, if satisfied that it is necessary for the proper 
determination of any relevant fact to do so, shall recall such witness or 
examine any such new witness.
 

1[(6) The Commission may pay the 
travelling and other expenses to a person who is summoned to assist the 
Commission at the stage of preliminary investigation or to give evidence or to 
produce documents before a Commission, as prescribed from time to time by the 
Central Government.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>7</number> The Commission shall have 
the powers of a civil court to make local investigation, either personally or 
through any person, duly authorised by it into any matters falling within its 
terms of reference.
 </section><section><number>8</number> A Commission shall have the 
power to regulate its own procedure in respect of any matter for which no 
provision is made in these Rules.



</section></article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
  
 <article><number>6</number> Appointment of assessors.—
<section><number>a</number>


1[***] a Commission, may, from time to 
time, appoint one or more assessors to assist and advise the Commission on any 
matter connected with the inquiry.
 </section><section><number>b</number> It shall be the duty of the 
assessors to assist and advise the Commission on any matter on which the 
Commission may consult them in the course of its inquiry:
 Provided that the advice 
tendered by the assessor shall not be binding on the Commission.
 </section><section><number>c</number> The Commission shall have 
the power to regulate the manner in which it may consult the assessors.
 

2[(d) The Commission may pay the 
travelling allowance, daily allowance and other incidental expenses to assessors 
according to their entitlement as prescribed from time to time by the Central 
Government.]




</section></article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
  
 <article><number>7</number> Retention of records.—The 
report of a Commission and the papers relating to its secretariat, its 
establishment matters and all other matters handled by or in the Commission 
including the evidence tendered before the Commission shall be preserved intact 
by the Commission and shall be remitted with the Report of the Commission.
  
</article> 
 THE COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY 
(CENTRAL)  
RULES, 1972
  
 <article><number>8</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Commission of Inquiry (Assessors) Rules, 1954, the rules for the issue and 
service of summons by the Commission of Inquiry, published with the notification 
of the Government of India in the Ministry of Home Affairs, No.16/1/55-Judicial 
(I), dated 27-7-1955, the Central Commissions of Inquiry (Procedures) Rules, 
1960, and Central Commissions of Inquiry (Local Investigation) Rules, 1970 are 
hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, 
anything done or any action taken under the provisions of any of the Rules 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provisions of the Commissions of Inquiry (Central) Rules, 1972.
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>