<act><tid>377818</tid>
<title>THE TRADE UNIONS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 3rd September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Trade Unions Act, <year>1926</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>965244</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1200856</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Trade  
Unions (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>18920</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>654063</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the Trade Unions Act, <year>1926</year> 
 (16 of <year>1926</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in 
sub- section 1, the following provisos shall be inserted at the end, 
namely:-
'' Provided that no Trade Union of workmen shall be registered unless 
at least ten per cent. or one hundred of the workmen, whichever is 
less, engaged or employed in the establishment or industry with which 
it is connected are the members of such Trade U ion on the date of 
making of application for registration:

Provided further that no Trade Union of workmen shall be registered 
unless it has on the date of making application not less than seven 
persons as its members, who are workmen engaged or employed in the 
establishment or industry with which it is connecte.''.



</article>



<article><tid>1445135</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after clause (a), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
'' (aa) in the case of a Trade Union of workmen, the names, occupations 
and addresses of the place of work of the members of the Trade Union 
making the application;''.



</article>



<article><tid>1487673</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1871764</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (ee), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
'' (ee) the payment of a minimum subscription by members of the Trade 
Union which shall not be less than-


<subsection><tid>1614980</tid>
<number>i</number>one rupee per annum for rural workers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1577323</tid>
<number>ii</number>three rupees per annum for workers in other unorganised sectors; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1335664</tid>
<number>iii</number>twelve rupees per annum for workers in any other case;'';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1757935</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (h), for the word'' appointed'', the word'' elected'' 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1272033</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause (h), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
'' (hh) the duration of period being not more than three years, for 
which the members of the executive and other office- bearers of the 
Trade Union shall be elected;''.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>16314</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 9.- After section 9 of the principal Act, the 
following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 9A. Minimum requirement about membership of a Trade Union.- A 
registered Trade Union of workmen shall at all times continue to have 
not less than ten per cent. or one hundred of the workmen, whichever 
is less, subject to a minimum of seven, engaged or em loyed in an 
establishment or industry with which it is connected, as its 
members.''.



</article>



<article><tid>568338</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 10.- In section 10 of the principal Act, after 
clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (c) if the Registrar is satisfied that a registered Trade Union of 
workmen ceases to have the requisite number of members.''.



</article>



<article><tid>967317</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after clause (a), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
'' (aa) where the head office is situated in an area, falling within 
the jurisdiction of a Labour Court or an Industrial Tribunal, to that 
Court or Tribunal, as the case may be;''.



</article>



<article><tid>343713</tid>
<number> 8</number> Substitution of new section for section 22.- For section 22 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
' 22. Proportion of office- bearers to be connected with the 
industry.- (1) Not less than one- half of the total number of the 
office- bearers of every registered Trade Union in an unorganised 
sector shall be persons actually engaged or employed in an industr 
with which the Trade Union is connected:

Provided that the appropriate Government may, by special or general 
order, declare that the provisions of this section shall not apply to 
any Trade Union or class of Trade Unions specified in the order.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,'' unorganised sector'' 
means any sector which the appropriate Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, specify.

<section><tid>965561</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (1), all office- bearers 
of a registered Trade Union, except not more than one- third of the 
total number of the office- bearers or five, whichever is less, shall 
be persons actually engaged or employed in the e tablishment or 
industry with which the Trade Union is connected.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, an employee who has 
retired or has been retrenched shall not be construed as outsider for 
the purpose of holding an office in a Trade Union.


</section>

<section><tid>53082</tid>
<number>3</number>No member of the Council of Ministers or a person holding an 
office of profit (not being an engagement or employment in an  
  establishment or industry with which the Trade Union is connected), in 
the Union or a State, shall be a member of the executive or other 
office- bearer of a registered Trade Union.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>557955</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 29.- In section 29 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-
'' (3) Every notification made by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) of section 22, and every regulation made by it under 
sub- section (1), shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
notification or regulation, or both Houses agree that the notification 
or regulation should not be made, the notification or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; aforesaid, both Houses agree in making a y 
modification in the o, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that notification or regulation.

<section><tid>1969962</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notification made by the State Government under sub- section 
 (1) of section 22 and every regulation made by it under sub- section 
 (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the 
State Legislature.''.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>