<act><title>THE COMPETITION COMMISSION OF INDIA (RETURN ON 
MEASURES FOR THE PROMOTION OF COMPETITION ADVOCACY, AWARENESS AND TRAINING ON 
COMPETITION ISSUES) RULES, 20081</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules 
may be called the Competition Commission of India (Return on Measures for the 
Promotion of Competition Advocacy, Awareness and Training on Competition Issues) 
Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> These rules shall come into force from the date of their 
publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these Rules, unless context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Competition Act, 2002 (Act 12 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Appellate Tribunal means the Appellate Tribunal established under 
  sub-section (1) of section 53A of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Commission means the Competition Commission of India established 
  under section 7 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Year means the financial year beginning on 1st April and ending on 
  31st March of the year immediately following. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expression used and defined in the Competition Act, 2002 but 
not defined in these rules, shall have the same meanings assigned to them in 
that Act.

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Preparation and furnishing of the Return on Measures. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Commission shall furnish on the completion of every year return and statements in the form as laid down in the Schedule annexed to these rules in regard to any proposed or existing measures for the promotion of competition advocacy, creating awareness and imparting training about competition issues to the Central Government, for the activities undertaken, giving a true and full account of its activities, performed during the previous year. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may seek from the Commission such other information with regards to any proposed or existing measures for the promotion of competition advocacy, creating awareness and imparting training about competition issues as it may decide from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Commission may also include in the return any other item, not included in the Schedule, with the prior permission of the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Commission, shall forward the return to the Central Government within a period of thirty days immediately following the completion of year for which it has been prepared. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The matters relating to form and time of preparation of return, with respect to which no express provision has been made in these rules, shall be referred in each case to the Central Government for its decision and the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be binding on the Commission. 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>