<act><title>

THE CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF
    
    PRACTICE, 19931</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These Rules may be called 
    the Central Administrative Tribunal Rules of Practice, 1993.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Commencement.—
<section><number>a</number> These Rules 
    shall, after their publication in the Official Gazette, come into force on 
    1st November, 1993.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> These 
    Rules shall apply, as far as may be, to all proceedings pending in the 
    Central Administrative Tribunal on the date of their commencement.
  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Definitions.—In these Rules, 
    unless there in anything repugnant to the subject or context,—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   “Address for service” shall mean the 
    address furnished by a party or his authorised agent, or his legal 
    practitioner at which service of summons, notices or other processes may be 
    effected;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   “Application” means and includes 
    Original Application (O.A.), Review Application (R.A), Transferred 
    Application (T.A.), Miscellaneous Application (M.A.) and Petition for 
    Transfer (P.T.);
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   “Act” and “Procedure Rules” shall mean 
    the Administrative Tribunals Act, 1985 (Central Act 13 of 1985) and the 
    Central Administrative Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 1987, as amended from 
    time to time;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   “Code” means the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908, as amended from time to time;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   “Full Bench” means a Bench duly 
    constituted consisting of three or more Members;
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   “Legal Practitioner” includes a 
    Standing Counsel authorised to accept the service for any department or 
    organisation of the Central Government/ State Government or any authority, a 
    Corporation, a body owned or controlled by the Central Government/State 
    Government;
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>   “Pleadings” shall include original 
    applications, reply statement, rejoinders and additional statements 
    supplementing the original applications and the reply statements, as may be 
    permitted by the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>   “Vacation Bench” means a Bench duly 
    constituted for discharging the functions of the Tribunal during the 
    vacation;  
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>   Words not defined in these Rules shall 
    have the same meaning as assigned in the Act and the Procedure Rules.  
  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Preparation of pleadings and other papers.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    All pleadings, affidavits, memoranda and other papers filed in the Tribunal 
    shall be fairly and legibly typewritten or printed in English or Hindi 
    language on durable white foolscap folio paper of Metric A-4 size (30.5 cms. 
    long and 21.5 cms. wide) on one side only in double space with a left margin 
    of 5 cms. and right margin of 2.5 cms. duly paginated, indexed and stitched 
    together in the paper-book form. The index shall be in Form No. 1.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> English 
    translation of documents/pleadings shall be duly authenticated by any legal 
    practitioner.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Date and 
    signature.—A party required to 
    affix his signature shall also state his name in capitals near his signature 
    and initial or sign at the bottom of each page.  
 

    Explanation.—The expression 
    ‘signature’ or ‘initial’ includes thumb mark.  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Attestation.—
<section><number>a</number> The attestation 
    contemplated in Rule 9(2) of the Procedure Rules shall be made at the end of 
    the document in the form given below:  
 

    “This/Annexure.............is the true copy of the original document.”
  
 <subsection>
    
                                                                                            
    <number>Signature</number>
 

                                                                                       
    Name and Designation of the 
                                                                                               
    Attestor with date”.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> Sub-rule 
    (a) above shall also govern production of xerox copies of the documents, 
    provided they are clear and legible.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Production of authorisation for and on behalf of an Association.—Where 
    an application/pleading or other proceeding purported to be filed is by an 
    Association, the person or persons who sign(s)/verify(ies) the same shall 
    produce along with such application, etc., for verification by the Registry, 
    a true copy of the resolution of the Association empowering such person(s) 
    to do so:  
 
Provided the 
    Registrar may at any time call upon the party to produce such further 
    materials as he deems fit for satisfying himself about due authorisation.  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Procedure on production of defaced, torn or damaged documents.—When 
    a document produced along with any pleading appears to be defaced, torn, or 
    in any way damaged or otherwise its condition or appearance requires special 
    notice, a mention regarding its condition and appearance shall be made by 
    the party producing the same in the Index of such a pleading and the same 
    shall be verified and initialled by the officer authorised to receive the 
    same.  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Receipt 
    of papers.—
<section><number>a</number> All pleadings and 
    papers shall be received in the Registry only during the office hours on the 
    working days, provided they are presented or sent in the manner provided in 
    rule 4(1) of the Procedure Rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> All 
    pleadings and papers received before 3 p.m. in which urgent interim orders 
    are sought, shall ordinarily be processed immediately for being listed 
    before the Bench on the next working day.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Date 
    stamping of papers and maintenance of Inward Register.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The receiving branch of the Registry shall immediately on receipt of an 
    application/petition or other pleadings or papers, affix the date-stamp of 
    the Tribunal in the following manner:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Date-stamp shall be affixed on all pages 
    on the main/first copy and on the first page of each other copy.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Receiving Clerk shall affix his 
    initials on the stamp affixed on the first page of the main/first copy and 
    on the first page of all other copies.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> Receiving 
    branch of the Registry shall on affixing the date-stamp, enter the details 
    thereof in the Inward Register, Register No. 1 and assign a Diary Number. 
    The same Diary Number shall be entered immediately below the date-stamp on 
    the first page of the main/first copy and all other copies.  
  
  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Scrutiny of application/petition/other pleadings and papers.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Scrutiny Branch of the Registry shall, on receipt of the 
    application/petition pleadings from the receiving branch, scrutinise the 
    same as expeditiously as possible but not beyond two days from the date of 
    receipt:  
 
Provided if, 
    for any reason, the scrutiny is not completed within the above period, the 
    same shall be immediately reported to the Registrar, who shall take prompt 
    steps to complete the scrutiny.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The report 
    of the scrutiny of the application under section 19 of the Act shall be in 
    Form No. 2 and of Contempt Petition (C.P.) (Civil/Criminal) in Form No. 3 
    and the scrutiny report shall be annexed to the application/petition.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Report of 
    scrutiny of all other pleadings and papers shall be recorded on the reverse 
    side of the last page of such pleadings/papers.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Maintenance of Order Sheet.—The 
    Scrutiny Branch shall attach to every OA/RA/TA/PT/CP an order sheet in 
    duplicate in Form No. 4. The column “Notes of the Registry” in the order 
    sheet shall be for the notings by the Registry and the column “Orders of the 
    Tribunal” is meant for the use of the Bench.  
 
Note:—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>   The entries in the order sheet shall be 
    in writing and removal of the order sheet for typing be avoided.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   Continuous page number should be given 
    to the order sheet.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   Before any entry is made in the order 
    sheet for the day, the date, month and year shall-first be entered and 
    underlined in the middle of the column.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   Brief order may be written on the order 
    sheet itself and initialled by the Members of the Bench.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   In the case of lengthy orders, only the 
    operative portion of the order need be entered in the column “Orders of the 
    Tribunal” and initialled by the court officer. The orders shall be annexed 
    to the order sheet giving them continuous paging. Reference to the order 
    shall be made by mentioning only page number of the order annexed.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   The presence of the legal 
    practitioner/party be indicated by their initials.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>   No gaps shall be left between two 
    entries in the order sheet. Gaps, if any shall be covered by drawing a line 
    across.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Classification of papers.—
<section><number>a</number> The 
    papers received in the Registry in all applications and C.Ps. except 
    Miscellaneous Applications, shall be classified and placed in files ‘A’, ‘B’ 
    and ‘C’ as provided in Form No. 5.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “A” File 
    shall consist of two separate parts. Part-I shall contain the order sheet 
    and orders annexed thereto. Part-II shall contain the application with 
    annexures, reply with annexures and rejoinder with annexures and arrange as 
    far as possible consecutively in the order of the parties.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> “B” File 
    shall contain the duplicate copy of the papers as in “A” File.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “C” File 
    shall contain the remaining papers including Vakalatnama, notices, postal 
    acknowledgments, Miscellaneous Applications, Replies and Rejoinders thereto 
    and Supreme Court orders etc. if any.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Submission of case files to Registrar.—On 
    completion of the scrutiny, the Scrutiny Branch shall place the case file 
    duly classified as “A”, “B” and “C” along with the report of scrutiny and 
    the order sheet before the Registrar for his orders.  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Registration and Numbering.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Registrar on examining the application/pleadings and the scrutiny report 
    shall, if they are in order, direct registration/acceptance.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> 
    Applications under section 19 of the Act ordered to be registered shall be 
    numbered as O.A. No......................../20.......
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Cases 
    received on transfer under section 29 of the Act shall be numbered as T.A. 
    No. ................../20.......
 

    Explanation.—Applications 
    received from the Supreme Court, High Courts and other courts purporting to 
    be by transfer but not covered by section 29 of the Act shall be numbered as 
    Original Applications of the year during which they are received,  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> 
    Applications for review of any order of the Tribunal ordered to be 
    registered shall be numbered as R.A. No....................../20...........  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> Petitions 
    under the Contempt of Courts Act ordered to be registered, shall be numbered 
    as C.P. (Civil/Criminal) No. ..................../20........  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> 
    Applications under section 25 of the Act ordered to be registered shall be 
    numbered as P.T. No..................../20........  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> Other 
    applications of Miscellaneous nature not covered by sub-rules (b) to (f) 
    above, ordered to be registered shall be numbered as M.A. 
    No............../20........  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> 
    Applications/petitions referred to in this rule shall be entered in Register 
    No. 2. Separate registers shall be used for each category of applications/ 
    petition referred to in this rule. The Registers shall be maintained from 
    1st January to 31st December of each calendar year.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Maintenance of I.P.Os./D.Ds. Register.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    I.P.Os./D.Ds. received in the Registry shall be entered immediately on their 
    receipt in the Judicial Branch in Register No. 3.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> On every 
    first working day of the week, the I.P.Os. D.Ds. received by the Judicial 
    Branch during the previous week shall be transmitted along with the I.P.Os./D.Ds. 
    Register to the Section Officer incharge of Judicial Branch, who after 
    scrutiny shall affix his initials in the relevant column in the Register and 
    transmit the same to the Cash Section. The official incharge of Cash Section 
    shall, after verifying the entries in the Register alongwith the I.P.Os./D.Ds. 
    put his initials in the relevant column in the Register in token of 
    acknowledgment.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Rectification of defects.—
<section><number>a</number> If 
    on scrutiny any application or pleading filed in the Tribunal is found to be 
    defective, the Registrar shall notify in Form No. 6 on the Notice Board of 
    the Tribunal fixing the time for rectifying the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The papers 
    shall be returned to the party or his legal practitioner only after 
    obtaining acknowledgment thereof in the Inward Register.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    Registrar may, for good and sufficient reasons extend the time for 
    rectifying the defects, provided the total period for rectification 
    including the extended period does not exceed thirty days.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> If the 
    party or his legal practitioner contests the office objection and the 
    Registrar is not satisfied the matter shall be placed before the Bench for 
    appropriate orders.  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> If the 
    party/legal practitioner rectifies the defects and represents the 
    application/pleading within the time granted, the Registrar on being 
    satisfied may order for its registration/acceptance and numbering as 
    provided in rule 15.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Posting 
    of cases for admission/orders before the Bench.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Subject to the orders of the Chairman/Vice-Chairman of the concerned Bench, 
    all registered applications/petitions shall be posted for admission/orders 
    before the appropriate Bench on the next working day. The notice of posting 
    shall be given by notifying in the daily cause list for the day.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Before 
    placing the records of the case for admission/order, the Registry shall 
    state in brief in the column “Notes of the Registry” of the Order Sheet, the 
    date of presentation and registration, the subject matter of the application 
    and the date of posting before the Bench and fill up the columns in file 
    covers “A” and “B”.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    category of cases specified in Appendix I to these Rules as may be amended 
    by the Chairman from time to time, may as far as possible be posted before 
    the Single Member Bench and dealt with in accordance with the procedure 
    prescribed therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The 
    constitution of Benches and distribution of work shall be as per the 
    orders/directions given in Appendix II to these Rules, as may be modified by 
    the Chairman from time to time.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Posting 
    of urgent cases.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in Rule 18, the Chairman/Vice-Chairman 
    and in his absence the senior-most Member of the Bench may order any case 
    not included in the daily cause list to be listed on urgent basis for 
    admission/orders. Such directions shall be promptly carried out by the 
    Registry after completing all the formalities.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When a 
    Division Bench is not available, urgent cases for admission and interim 
    orders may be posted before a Single Member Bench who shall deal with the 
    same in accordance with the order of the Chairman as in Appendix III as may 
    be amended from time to time.  
 

 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Matters 
    to be attended to prior to commencement of sitting.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Unless otherwise directed by the Members constituting the Bench, the court 
    officer shall ensure that records of the cases listed for admission/orders 
    before the Bench on the next working day are sent to the residence of the 
    Members before the evening of the day on which the cause list is published.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Court 
    Officer shall ensure that the case records so sent to the residence of the 
    Members are brought back to the concerned court Hall before the commencement 
    of the court sitting. The Court Officer shall verify the case records listed 
    for the day and arrange them in the serial order as given in the cause list 
    well before the commencement of the sitting.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The Court 
    Officer of the Bench concerned shall ensure that the Court Hall is ready for 
    commencement of the sitting at the prescribed time for such sitting.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> If for any 
    reason, the Bench cannot sit or the sitting is delayed, the Registrar shall 
    promptly obtain the orders of the Chairman/Vice-Chairman and notify the same 
    on the Notice Board and in the Court Hall through the Court Officer.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Maintenance of Court Diary.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Court Officer of the Bench concerned shall maintain legibly a court 
    diary in Register No. 4, wherein he shall record the proceedings of the 
    court for each sitting day with respect to the applications/petitions listed 
    in the daily cause list.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    matters to be recorded in the court diary shall include details as to 
    whether the case is adjourned, or part-heard or heard and disposed of or 
    heard and orders reserved, as the case may be.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Statutes/Citations for reference.—The 
    parties/legal practitioners shall before the commencement of the proceedings 
    for the day, furnish to the court officer a list of law journals, reports, 
    statutes and other citations, which may be needed for reference.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Calling 
    of cases in court.—Subject to the 
    orders of the Bench, the court officer shall call the cases listed in the 
    cause list in the serial order.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Regulation of court work.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    When the Court is sitting, the court officer shall ensure—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   that no inconvenience or wastage of time 
    is caused to the Bench in making available the services of court 
    master/Stenographer/Peon;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   that perfect silence is maintained in 
    and around the court hall and no disturbance whatsoever is caused to the 
    functioning of the Bench;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   that proper care is taken to maintain 
    dignity and decorum of the court.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> When the 
    Bench passes order directions, the court officer shall ensure that the 
    records of the case along with proceedings/orders of the Bench are 
    transmitted immediately to the Judicial Branch. The Judicial Branch shall 
    verify the case records received from the court officer with reference to 
    the cause list and take immediate step to communicate the directions/orders 
    of the Bench.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Issue 
    of Notice.—
<section><number>a</number> Unless otherwise 
    ordered by the Tribunal, when notice is ordered, the applicant shall, in 
    cases governed by rule 11(6) of the Procedure Rules, pay the prescribed fee 
    for service of notice accompanied by a memo in Form No. 7 within seven days 
    from the date of order. In default, no notice shall be issued to any of the 
    respondents and the matter shall be placed immediately before the Bench for 
    appropriate orders.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Where the 
    notice is returned to the Tribunal with an endorsement of the postman 
    regarding non-service owing to refusal of the same by the party concerned, 
    the Registrar shall declare that the notice has been duly served on the 
    respondent.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Where the 
    notice was properly addressed prepaid and duly sent by registered post, 
    acknowledgment due, the declaration referred to in sub-rule (b) shall be 
    made when for any reason the acknowledgment is not received by the Tribunal 
    within thirty days from the date of the issue of the notice.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Step 
    for issue of fresh notice.—If any 
    notice is returned unserved in the circumstances not specified in sub-rules 
    (b) and (c) of rule 25, that fact and the reason therefor shall be notified 
    immediately on the notice board of the Registry. The applicant/petitioner or 
    his Legal Practitioner shall within seven days from the date of such 
    notification take steps for service of notice.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Consequence of failure to take steps for issue of fresh notice.—If 
    the applicant/petitioner fails to take necessary steps in the time for 
    service of notice on the respondent(s) and consequently, the service remains 
    incomplete, the Registrar shall post the case before the Bench for further 
    directions.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Service 
    of notice etc. on Legal Practitioners.—A 
    Legal Practitioner representing a party in any proceeding and any person 
    authorised to accept notices on behalf of a party, shall receive notices, 
    orders, directions, pleadings, etc. required to be served on such party in 
    connection with such proceedings. Such service shall be deemed to be proper 
    service on the party.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Form of 
    Notice.—Notice to show cause 
    regarding admission shall be in Form No. 8. Notice ordered after admission 
    shall be in Form No. 9.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Entries 
    regarding service of notice/process.—The 
    Judicial Branch of the Registry shall record in the column in the order 
    sheet “Notes of the Registry”, the details regarding completion of service 
    of notice on the respondents, such as date of issue of notice, date of 
    service, date of return of notice if unserved, steps taken for issuing fresh 
    notice and date of completion of service, etc.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Case 
    deemed to be ready on failure to file reply in time.—When 
    all or any of the respondent(s) fail(s) to file reply statement in the form 
    and in the manner provided under rule 12 of the Procedure Rule within the 
    time granted, the case shall be deemed to be ready for hearing and included 
    in the ready list for final hearing.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Filing 
    of rejoinder.—
<section><number>a</number> The applicant(s) 
    intending to file rejoinder to the reply statement filed by all or any of 
    the respondent(s) shall do so, with the leave of the Bench/Registrar within 
    the time granted. The rejoinder shall be filed with the time granted, duly 
    signed and verified in the manner prescribed for filing reply statement 
    under rule 12 of the Procedure Rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> After the 
    expiry of the time granted for filing the rejoinder, the case shall be 
    deemed to be ready for hearing and included in the ready list for final 
    hearing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Papers 
    not to form part of the records.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Except with the leave of the Tribunal, the following shall not form part of 
    the records of the case:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Reply statement filed after the expiry 
    of the time granted for the purpose.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Rejoinder filed without the leave of 
    the court or filed after the expiry of the time granted.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Additional pleadings filed without the 
    leave of the court or filed after the expiry of the time granted.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The above 
    papers treated as not forming part of the record shall be notified on the 
    Notice Board of the Registry requiring the party of take them back within 
    four weeks from the date of the Notification, failing which the Registry 
    shall take steps to destroy the same.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Incorporation of amendments, filing of additional reply, etc.—When 
    the Tribunal allows a prayer for a amendment of the pleadings or for 
    addition of parties, the same shall be carried out in red ink indicating the 
    date of the order and duly signed by the party/legal practitioner, who has 
    obtained the order, within the time granted for the purpose by the order or 
    if no time is thereby limited then, within 14 days from the date of the 
    order. If however, the Bench or the Tribunal has directed furnishing of a 
    fresh copy incorporating the amendments/addition of parties, the same shall 
    be filed in triplicate and after serving a copy of the amended pleading on 
    the other party within the time granted by the court or if no time is 
    granted with 14 days from the date of the order. In default, the Registry 
    shall place the matter before the Bench for orders.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Matters 
    to be listed before the Registrar’s court.—Once 
    an application/petition is admitted and notice ordered, the same shall be 
    posted before the Registrar for completion of pleadings.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Cause 
    List for Registrar’s court.—Cases 
    required to be dealt with by the Registrar shall be notified in a separate 
    Daily Cause List. The cases so notified shall be taken up in the Registrar’s 
    court in the serial order as indicated in the cause list.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Recording of proceedings.—On 
    hearing the parties/their Legal Practitioners and on persuing the records 
    the Registrar may record his decisions in the column “Notes of the Registry” 
    in the order sheet and put his initials with date.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Inclusion of cases in the ready list when pleadings are complete.—If 
    the pleadings are complete or if the case is deemed to be ready for hearing, 
    the Registrar shall record the same in the order sheet and order for 
    inclusion in the list of cases ready for final hearing.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Maintenance of Ready List.—The 
    Judicial Branch of the Registry shall maintain separate registers in 
    register Form No. 5 for each category of cases which are ready for hearing. 
    The registers shall contain separate sections for each year. Inclusion of 
    cases in the Register shall be yearwise and in the order in which they 
    become ready for hearing.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Preparation of Warning List.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    From the Ready List, the Registry shall prepare for each category of cases, 
    a separate list called “Warning List” consisting of such number of cases as 
    may be sufficient in the opinion of the Registrar, for being posted for 
    hearing for a period of two weeks.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Cases in 
    the Warning List shall be arranged according to the year and number of 
    registration and not on the basis of their serial number in the Ready List. 
    Oldest among the cases be included first following by the next oldest and so 
    on.  
 
 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Publication of Warning List.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Judicial Branch of the Registry shall publish the warning list on the 
    Notice Board of the Registry on the last working day previous to the 1st and 
    15th of every month.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The total 
    number of cases to be included in each Warning List as fixed by the 
    Registrar shall, as far as possible, be maintained by adding at the bottom 
    of the list, such number of cases as are required to make good the 
    deficiency, having regard to the number of cases transferred to the Daily 
    Cause List.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> From the 
    Warning List so published, sufficient number of cases shall be taken for 
    inclusion in the Daily Cause List in the order in which they appear in the 
    Warning List, subject to the orders of the Chairman/Vice-Chairman/Bench.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Preparation and publication of Daily Cause List.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Judicial Branch of the Registry shall prepare and publish on the Notice 
    Board of the Registry before 5-30 p.m. on each working day the Cause List 
    for the next working day. Subject to the directions of the 
    Chairman/Vice-Chairman/Bench listing of cases in the Daily Cause List shall 
    be in the following order:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Cases for “Pronouncement of Orders”.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Cases “For being spoken to”.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Cases for “Admission”.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Cases for “Orders/Directions”.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   Contempt Petitions.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   Part-heard cases, latest part-heard 
    having precedence.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   Cases posted as per directions of the 
    court.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   Cases from the “Warning List”.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The title 
    of the Daily Cause List shall consist of the name of the Bench, the day, 
    date and time of the court sitting, Court Hall number and the quorum 
    indicating the names of the Chairman/Vice-Chairman/Member constituting the 
    Bench with abbreviations in brackets (J) for Judicial and (A) for 
    Administrative.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Against 
    the number of each case listed in the Warning List and in the Daily Cause 
    List, the following shall be shown:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Names of Legal Practitioners appearing 
    on both sides, giving in brackets the rank of the parties whom they 
    represent.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Names of the parties, if unrepresented 
    with their ranks in brackets.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number> Office 
    objections and special directions, if any, shall be briefly indicated in the 
    Daily Cause List below the case number.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Carry 
    forward of Cause List and adjournment of cases on account of non-sitting of 
    a Bench.—
<section><number>a</number> If by reason of 
    declaration of holiday or for any other reason, the Bench does not function 
    for the day, the Daily Cause List for that day shall unless otherwise 
    directed be treated as the Daily Cause List for the next working day in 
    addition to the cases already posted for that day.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When the 
    sitting of a particular Bench is cancelled for the reason of absence of 
    Member(s) of the Bench, the Registrar shall, unless otherwise directed, 
    adjourn the cases posted before that Bench to a convenient date. The 
    adjournment/posting/directions shall be notified on the Notice Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Supply 
    of Cause List.—
<section><number>a</number> Two copies of 
    fortnightly Warning List and Daily Cause List shall be furnished to the 
    Advocates/Bar Association of Central Administrative Tribunal for publication 
    on their Notice Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Copies of 
    the daily cause list may be furnished to the Legal Practitioners on payment 
    of fees at the rate specified below:  
 <subsection>
<number>I</number>   Daily Cause List:  
 
     Per Bench (consisting 
    of two Members) Rs. 240 p.a.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>II</number>   Warning List:  
 
      Per Bench 
    (consisting of two Members) Rs. 100 p.a.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> 
    Application for supply of Warning/Daily Cause List shall be made in writing 
    to the Registrar accompanied by one year’s subscription by way of Demand 
    Draft or Indian Postal Orders drawn in favour of the Registrar of the 
    concerned Bench not less than a week before the date from which supply is to 
    commence.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The rates 
    specified above shall be subject to such modifications as may be made by the 
    Chairman from time to time.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> Request 
    for adjournments.—Unless the 
    Bench otherwise permits, requests for adjournments of the cases listed in 
    the Daily Cause List shall be entertained only at the beginning of the 
    session.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Maintenance of Stage Register and Posting Register.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Judicial Branch of the Registry shall maintain a Stage Register in Form 
    Register No. 6 for each category of applications/petitions from the stage of 
    first posting till disposal.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Posting 
    Register shall be maintained in Form Register No. 7.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> All orders 
    regarding clubbing at cases shall be entered in the order sheets of all the 
    cases required to be clubbed together and posted accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The 
    Section Officer concerned shall ensure that the aforesaid registers are 
    promptly and properly maintained and the directions of the Bench faithfully 
    carried out.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Early 
    hearing of cases.—If early 
    hearing of a case out of turn is required, the party/Legal Practitioner 
    shall make an application stating the reasons therefor in Form No. III of 
    the Procedure Rules, after serving copy thereof to the other parties. The 
    application shall, if in order, be listed before the Chairman or in his 
    absence the Vice-Chairman nominated by him in the case of the Principal 
    Bench and before the Vice-Chairman and in his absence before the senior-most 
    available Member in the case of other Benches.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Vacation Bench Sittings and Posting of cases.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    When the Tribunal is closed for vacation, the Vacation Bench shall sit on 
    such days as the Chairman in the case of Principal Bench and Vice-Chairman 
    in the case of other Benches and in his absence the senior-most Member 
    available, may specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> During the 
    vacation only matters which are required to be immediately of promply dealt 
    with, shall be received in the Registry. The Registrar, on being satisfied 
    about the urgency, shall order registration and posting of such cases.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> During the 
    vacation, the Registrar may accept replies, rejoinders to O.As., R.As., 
    etc. provided a copy of the same has been served on all the other 
    parties/Legal Practitioners.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Inspection 
    of records may be permitted during the vacation according to the Rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> Certified 
    copies may also be supplied during the vacation according to the Rules.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Posting 
    of Review Applications.—Posting 
    of Review Applications shall be governed by the order made by the Chairman 
    as contained in Appendix IV subject to such modifications as may be made by 
    the Chairman from time to time.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Preparation and filing of paper books on reference to the Full Bench.—When 
    a Division Bench of the Tribunal makes an order referring the case/issues to 
    a Full Bench, the applicant or such other party, as the Bench directs shall 
    furnish in Paper Book form duly indexed and continuously paginated 
    three/five sets (depending upon the number of members of the Full Bench) for 
    the use of the Bench and one set to each of the parties/or their legal 
    practitioner on the other side, within two weeks or such other time as the 
    Bench may direct, arranging the papers in the following orders:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   Index               
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   Written chronology of events/orders 
    relevant to the case.  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   Order of Reference.  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   Memo of Parties.  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   Application/Petition.  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   Annexures to the application/petition.  
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>   Reply by each respondent in the order 
    of their ranking.  
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>   Annexures at the end of reply of each 
    respondent.  
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>   Rejoinder, if any.  
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>   Annexures to Rejoinder, if any.  
 </section><section>
<number>xi</number>   Other relevant papers with description 
    and date:  
 
Provided that 
    if the same Legal Practitioner appears for more than one party, only one set 
    of Paper Book need be furnished to him.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Circulation of order of Reference to other Benches.—The 
    Registrar of the referring Bench shall send a copy of the order of reference 
    to all the other Benches of the Tribunal for information.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Seeking 
    orders of Chairman for constitution of Full Bench and fixing date of 
    hearing.—The Registrar of the 
    Referring Bench shall forward a copy of the Order of Reference to the 
    Registrar of the Principal Bench for securing orders of the Chairman for 
    constitution of the Full Bench and fixing the date of hearing.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Conveyance of the orders of the Chairman.—The 
    Registrar of the Principal Bench shall, on receipt of the request as 
    aforesaid obtain the orders of the Chairman and convey the same to the 
    Registrar of the Referring Bench.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Notification regarding Full Bench hearing.—The 
    Registrar of the Referring Bench shall, immediately on receipt of orders of 
    the Chairman notify the parties/legal practitioners the date of hearing of 
    the case by the Full Bench.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Circulation of Full Bench decision/opinion.—The 
    Registrar of the Referring Bench shall circulate the opinion/decision 
    rendered by the Full Bench to all other Benches of the Tribunal.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Grant 
    of Inspection.—Inspection of 
    records of a pending or decided case before the Tribunal shall be allowed 
    only under the orders of the Registrar.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Application for grant of inspection.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Application for inspection of records as provided under sub-rule (1) or 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 23 of the Procedure Rules, shall be in Form No 10 and 
    presented at the filing counter of the Registry between 10 a.m. and 3 p.m. 
    on any working day, two days before the date on which inspection is sought, 
    unless otherwise permitted by the Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    Judicial Branch of the Registry shall submit the application with its 
    remarks before the Registrar, who shall on consideration of the same pass 
    appropriate orders.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Inspection 
    of records of a pending case shall not ordinarily be permitted on the date 
    fixed for hearing of the case or on the preceding day.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Fee 
    payable for Inspection.—
<section><number>a</number> No 
    fee shall be charged for inspection of records of a pending case by a party 
    to the case or his legal practitioner.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A fee of 
    Rs. 5 shall be payable by way of DD/IPO drawn in favour of the Registrar on 
    any application for inspection of records of a decided case by a party to 
    the case or his Legal Practitioner.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A fee of 
    Rs. 5 shall be payable by way of a DD/IPO drawn in favour of the Registrar 
    on any application for inspection of records of a pending or decided case by 
    a person other than a party to the case.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Mode of 
    Inspection.—
<section><number>a</number> On grant of 
    application for inspection of the records, the Section Officer in-charge of 
    the Judicial Branch shall arrange to procedure the records of the case and 
    allow inspection of such records on the date and time fixed by the Registrar 
    between 10 a.m. and 12.30 p.m. and between 2.30 p.m. and 4.30 p.m. in the 
    presence of an officer authorised in that behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The person 
    inspecting the records shall not in any manner cause dislocation, 
    mutilation, tampering or damage to the records in the course of inspection.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The person 
    inspecting the records shall not make any marking on any record or paper so 
    inspected. Copying, if any, of the documents/records inspected may be done 
    only in pencil.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The 
    officer supervising the inspection may at any time prohibit further 
    inspection, if in his opinion any of the records are likely to be damaged in 
    the process of inspection or the person inspecting the records has violated 
    or attempted to violate the provisions of these Rules and shall immediately 
    make a report about the matter to the Registrar and seek further orders of 
    the Registrar. Note about the same shall be made in column (8) of the 
    Inspection Register.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Maintenance of Register of Inspection.—The 
    Section Officer in-charge of the Judicial Branch shall cause to maintain a 
    Register in Form No. 8 for the purpose of inspection of documents/records 
    and shall obtain therein the signature of the person making such inspection.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Appearance of legal practitioners.—Subject 
    as hereinafter provided no legal practitioner shall be entitled to appear 
    and act in any proceedings before the Tribunal unless he files into Tribunal 
    a vakalatnama in the prescribed form duly executed by or on behalf of 
    the party for whom he appears.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Appearance on behalf of Government, etc.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Any legal practitioner appearing on behalf of the Central Government or 
    State Government or any Government servant sued or suing in his official 
    capacity or any authority/corporation/society notified under section 14 of 
    the Act shall not be required to file a vakalatnama but he shall file 
    into Tribunal a Memo of Appearance in Form No. 11 duly signed by him.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A 
    presenting officer other than a legal practitioner representing any of the 
    parties referred to in sub-rule (a) shall also file a memo of appearance in 
    Form No. 11.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Nomination or engagement of another legal practitioner.—Where 
    a legal practitioner who has filed the vakalatnama engages or 
    nominates another legal practitioner to appear and argue his client’s case 
    but not to act for the client, the Tribunal may permit such other legal 
    practitioner to appear and argue.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Consent 
    for engaging another legal practitioner.—A 
    legal practitioner proposing to file a vakalatnama in any case or 
    proceeding before the Tribunal in which there is already a legal 
    practitioner on record, shall do so only with the written consent of legal 
    practitioner on record or when such consent is refused, with the permission 
    of the Tribunal.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Restrictions on appearance.—A 
    legal practitioner who has tendered advice in connection with the 
    institution of any case or other proceeding before the Tribunal or has drawn 
    pleadings in connection with any such matter or has during the progress of 
    any such matter acted for a party, shall not, appear in any case or 
    proceeding or other matter arising therefrom or in any matter connected 
    therewith for any person whose interest is opposed to that of his formet 
    client, except with the prior permission of the Tribunal.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Access 
    to information.—A legal 
    practitioner appearing for the party in any matter before the Tribunal shall 
    be entitled to communicate personally with or receive any information 
    regarding the said matter from any officer of the Tribunal subject to such 
    conditions as may be prescribed by the Tribunal.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Form 
    and execution of vakalatnama.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Every vakalatnama authorising a legal practitioner to plead and act 
    shall be in Form No. 12. The name of the legal practitioner so appointed 
    shall be inserted in the vakalatnama before it is executed. It shall 
    be dated at the time of its execution and of its acceptance. Its execution 
    shall be attested by Judicial officer, gazetted officer serving in 
    connection with the affairs of the Union or of any State in India or a legal 
    practitioner other than the legal practitioner accepting the vakalatnama.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    authority attesting the vakalatnama under sub-rule (a) shall certify 
    that it has been duly executed in his presence and subscribe his signature 
    giving his name and designation. Attestation shall be made only after the 
    name of the legal practitioner is inserted in the vakalatnama before 
    its execution. When a vakalatnama is executed by a party who appears 
    to be illiterate, blind or unacquainted with the language of the 
    vakalatnama, the attestor shall certify that the vakalatnama was 
    read, translated and explained in his presence to the executant, that he 
    seemed to understand it and that he signed or affixed his thumb mark in his 
    presence.   
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Every 
    vakalatnama shall contain an endorsement of acceptance by the legal 
    practitioner in whose favour it is executed and shall also bear his address 
    for service. If the vakalatnama is in favour of more than one legal 
    practitioner, it shall be signed and accepted by all of them, giving the 
    address for service of any one of them.  
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Restriction on party’s right to be heard.—The 
    party who has engaged a legal practitioner to appear for him before the 
    Tribunal shall not be entitled to be heard in person unless he withdraws the
    vakalatnama with the leave of the Tribunal.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Professional dress for the Advocate.—While 
    appearing before the Tribunal, the Advocate shall wear the same professional 
    dress as prescribed for appearance before the High Court.  
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Prohibition of employment of tout.—No 
    legal practitioner shall employ as his clerk any person who is a tout.  
 

    Explanation.—“Tout” means a 
    person who procures or attempts to procure for any consideration from any 
    legal practitioner or from any person acting on his behalf, the employment 
    of such legal practitioner in any legal business, or who, for purposes of 
    such procurement, frequents the precincts of the Tribunal.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Disqualification for registration of clerks.—No 
    person who is or has been declared a tout or is an undischarged insolvent or 
    has been convicted of an offence involving moral turpitude or has been 
    dismissed from the service of the Government for corruption or dishonesty or 
    is otherwise unfit to be a clerk shall be registered as legal practitioner’s 
    clerk as provided in rule 25
<section><number>1</number> of the Procedure Rules.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Registration of legal practitioner’s clerks.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    When an application in Form No IV of the Procedure Rules is made by the 
    legal practitioner for registration of his clerk and the same is allowed by 
    the Registrar, the name of the clerk shall be entered in the Register of 
    clerks in Register No. 9.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    Registrar may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register 
    any clerk, who in his opinion suffers from any disqualification specified in 
    rule 71 or is otherwise unsuitable to be registered as such.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> An appeal 
    may be filed within thirty days from the date of the order of the Registrar 
    under sub-rule (b) to the Chairman/Vice-Chairman.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Cancellation of registration.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Registrar, may for reasons to be recorded in writing, cancel the 
    registration of any clerk after giving him and his employer an opportunity 
    to show cause against such cancellation.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> An appeal 
    may be filed against the order of the Registrar made under sub-rule (a) 
    within thirty days from the date of the order.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> 
    Notifying registration and cancellation.—Orders 
    registering a clerk or cancelling the registration shall be notified on the 
    Notice Board of the Tribunal and a copy sent to the Advocates Association.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Issue 
    of Identity Card.—
<section><number>a</number> An Identity 
    Card as referred to in sub-rule (3) of rule 25 of the Procedure Rules shall 
    be issued in Form No. 13 to every registered clerk of the legal practitioner 
    on his remitting a fee of Rs. 5 by way of IPO/DD drawn in favour of the 
    Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    registered clerk shall carry with him the Identity Card and produce the same 
    when required by any official of the registry for identification.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> An 
    Identity Card once issued shall be in force for a period of five years 
    unless cancelled earlier.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> Access 
    to information by registered clerks.—The 
    registered clerks, may communicate personally with any Sectional or 
    Departmental Head not below the rank of a Section Officer for information 
    regarding their employers’ matters pending in the Tribunal.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Carrying out corrections.—The 
    Section Officer in-charge of Judicial Branch may permit a registered clerk 
    to correct any clerical or typographical mistake in any pleadings or other 
    proceedings. The correction shall be made in the presence of the Section 
    Officer and duly initialled by the maker as well as the Section Officer.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Discharge of duties of an absentee clerk.—In 
    case of illness or absence on leave of a registered clerk, the Deputy 
    Registrar or the sectional head of the Judicial Branch may on the 
    requisition of the legal practitioner under whom such registered clerk is 
    engaged, permit the registered clerk of another legal practitioner to 
    discharge the absentee’s duties for a specified period.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Presentation and return of papers.—Registered 
    clerk may present or take return of papers on behalf of the legal 
    practitioner whom he represents.  
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> Title 
    of affidavits.—Every affidavit 
    shall be entitled “In the Central Administrative 
    Tribunal,.................Bench at .........................” followed by 
    the cause title of the application or other proceeding in which the 
    affidavit is sought to be used.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> Form 
    and contents of the affidavit.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Every affidavit shall be drawn up in Form No. 14 in the first person and 
    divided into paragraphs numbered consecutively.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Every 
    affidavit shall contain the full name, occupation, age, 
    father’s/mother’s/husband’s name and address of the deponent. The deponent 
    shall be describe with such other particulars as may be necessary to 
    identify him. He shall affix his signature/mark on each page.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Corrections/erasures etc.—Corrections, 
    erasures and interlineations shall be initialled by the attestor and the 
    number of corrections made on each page indicated.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Persons 
    authorised to attest.—Affidavits 
    shall be sworn or affirmed before any Judicial Officer, Registrar, Joint 
    Registrar and Deputy Registrar of the Tribunal Notary, District Registrar or 
    Sub-Registrar, the Chief Ministerial Officer of any civil or criminal court 
    in the State or any Advocate.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Affidavits of illiterate, blind etc.—Where 
    an affidavit is sworn or affirmed by any person who appears to be 
    illiterate, blind or unacquainted with the language in which the affidavit 
    is written, the attestor shall certify that the affidavit was read, 
    explained or translated by him or in his presence to the deponent and that 
    he seemed to understand it, and made his signature or mark in the presence 
    of the attestor in Form No. 15.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Identification of deponent.—If 
    the deponent is not known to the attestor, his identity shall be testified 
    by a person known to him. The identifying person shall affix his signature 
    in token thereof.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Annexures to the affidavit.—Document 
    accompanying an affidavit shall be referred to therein as Annexure 
    No......... The attestor shall make the following endorsement thereon:  
 
“This is the 
    document marked as Annexure No....in the Affidavit of.......  
 <section>

                                                                                           <number>Signature</number>
 

                                                                                    Name 
    &amp; designation of  
                                                                                   
    the attestor with date.’’
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Application for production of documents, form of summons.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Except otherwise provided hereunder, discovery, production and return of 
    documents shall be regulated by the provisions of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> An 
    application for summons to produce documents shall be in Form No. III to the 
    Procedure Rules setting out (i) the document(s) the production of which is 
    sought (ii) the relevancy of the document(s) and (iii) in case where the 
    production of a certified copy would serve the purpose, whether application 
    was made to the proper officer and the result thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A summon 
    for production of documents in the custody of a public officer other than a 
    court shall be in Form No. 16 and shall be addressed to the concerned Head 
    of the Department or such other authority as may be specified by the 
    Tribunal.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> Suo 
    motu summoning of documents.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in these Rules, the Tribunal may, suo motu, issue 
    summons for production of public documents or other documents in the custody 
    of a public officer.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>89</number> Marking 
    of documents.—
<section><number>a</number> The documents 
    when produced shall be marked as follows:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   If relied upon by the applicant’s side 
    they shall be numbered as ‘A’ series.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   If relied upon by the respondent’s side 
    they shall be marked as ‘R’ series.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   The court exhibits shall be marked as 
    ‘C’ series.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    Tribunal may direct the applicant to deposit in Tribunal by way of IPO/DD 
    drawn in favour of the Registrar a sum sufficient to defray the expenses for 
    transmission of the records before the summons is issued.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    transmission of the records shall ordinarily be by registered post parcel.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>90</number> Return 
    and transmission of documents.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    An application for return of the documents produced shall be in Form No. III 
    given under the Procedure Rules. No such application shall be entertained 
    after the destruction of the records.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    Tribunal may, at any time direct return of documents produced subject to 
    such conditions as it deems fit.  
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>91</number> 
    Procedure for examination of witnesses, issue of commissions, etc.—The 
    provisions of Orders XVI and XXVI of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 shall
    mutatis mutandis apply in the matter of summoning and 
    enforcing attendance of any person and examining him on oath and issuing 
    commission for the examination of witnesses or for production of documents.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>92</number> 
    Examination in camera.—The 
    Tribunal may in its discretion examine any witness in camera.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>93</number> Form of 
    oath/affirmation to witness.—Oath 
    shall be administered to a witness in the following form:—  
 
 “I do swear in the name of God/solemnly 
    affirm that what I shall state shall be truth, the whole truth and nothing 
    but the truth.”  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>94</number> Form of 
    oath/affirmation to interpreter.—Oath 
    or solemn affirmation shall be administered to the Interpreter in the 
    following form before his assistance is taken for examining a witness:—  
 
“I do swear in the name of God/Solemnly affirm 
    that I will faithfully and truly interpret and explain all questions put to 
    and evidence given by witness and translate correctly and accurately all 
    documents given to me for translation.”  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>95</number> Officer 
    to administer oath.—The oath or 
    affirmation shall be administered by the court officer or the Commissioner 
    as the case may be.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>96</number> 
    Form-recording of deposition.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The Deposition of a witness shall be recorded in Form No. 17.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Each page 
    of the deposition shall be initialled by the Members constituting the Bench 
    or the Commissioner.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> 
    Corrections if any, pointed out by the witness may, if the 
    Bench/Commissioner is satisfied, be carried out and duly initialled. If not 
    satisfied, a note to that effect be appended at the bottom of the 
    deposition.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>97</number> 
    Numbering of witnesses.—The 
    witnesses called by the applicant/petitioner shall be numbered consecutively 
    as PWs and those by the respondents as RWs.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>98</number> Grant 
    of discharge certificate.—Witness 
    discharged by the Tribunal may be granted a certificate in Form No. 18 by 
    the Registrar.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>99</number> Witness
    bhatta payable.—
<section><number>a</number> Where 
    the Tribunal issues summons to a Government servant to give evidence or to 
    produce documents, person so summoned may draw from the Government 
    travelling and daily allowance admissible to him as per Rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Where 
    there is no provision for payment to TA and DA by the employer to the person 
    summoned to give evidence or to produce documents, he shall be entitled to 
    be paid as bhatta, a sum found by the Registrar sufficient to defray 
    the travelling and other expenses having regard to the status and position 
    of the witness. The party applying for the summons shall deposit with the 
    Registrar the amount of bhatta as estimated by the Registrar well 
    before the summons is issued. If the witness is summoned as a court witness 
    the amount estimated by the Registrar shall be paid as per the directions of 
    the Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    aforesaid provisions would govern the payment of bhatta to the 
    interpreter as well.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>100</number> 
    Records to be furnished to the Commissioner.—The 
    Commissioner shall be furnished by the Tribunal with such of the records of 
    the case as the Tribunal considers necessary for executing the Commission. 
    Original documents will be furnished only if a copy will not serve the 
    purpose or cannot be obtained without unreasonable expense or delay. 
    Delivery and return of records shall be made under proper acknowledgement.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>101</number> Taking 
    of specimen handwriting, signature, etc.—The 
    Commissioner may, if necessary take specimen of the handwriting, signature 
    or finger print of any witness examined before him.  
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>102</number> Order.—The 
    final decision of the tribunal on an application/petition before the 
    Tribunal shall be described as “Order”.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>103</number> 
    Operative portion of the Order.—All 
    orders/directions of the Bench shall be stated in clear and prescise terms 
    in the last paragraphs of the order.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>104</number> 
    Corrections.—The Member of the 
    Bench who has prepared the order shall initial all corrections and affix his 
    initials at the bottom of each page.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>105</number> 
    Pronouncement of order.—
<section><number>a</number> The 
    Bench shall as possible pronounce the order immediately after the hearing is 
    concluded.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When the 
    order are reserved, the date for pronouncement not later than 3 weeks shall 
    be fixed. The date so fixed shall not be changed except due notice to all 
    parties/counsel.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Reading of 
    the operative portion of the order in the open court shall be deemed to be 
    pronouncement of the order.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Any order 
    reserved by a Circuit Bench of the Tribunal may be pronounced at the 
    principal place of sitting of the Bench in one of the aforesaid modes as 
    exigencies of the situation require.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>106</number> 
    Pronouncement of order by any one Member of the Bench.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Any one Member or the Bench may pronounce the order for and on behalf of the 
    Bench.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When an 
    order is pronounced under this Rule, the court officer shall make a note in 
    the order sheet that the order of the Bench consisting of ..........was 
    pronounced in open court by the Bench consisting of......... .  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>107</number> 
    Authorising any Member to pronounce order.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    If the Members of the Bench who heard the case are no readily available or 
    have ceased to be Members of the Tribunal, the Chairman/Vice-Chairman may 
    authorise any other Member to pronounce the order on his being satisfied 
    that the order has been duly prepared and signed by all the Members who 
    heard the case. The order pronounced by the Member so authorised shall be 
    deemed to be duly pronounced.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Member 
    so authorised for pronouncement of the order shall affix his signature in 
    the order sheet of the case stating that he has pronounced the order as 
    provided in this rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> If the 
    order cannot be signed by reason of death, retirement or resignation or for 
    any other reason by any one of the Members of the Bench who heard the case, 
    it shall be deemed to have been released from part-heard and listed afresh 
    for hearing.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>108</number> Making 
    of entries by court officer.—Immediately 
    on pronouncement of an order by the Bench, the court officer shall make 
    necessary endorsement on the case file regarding the date of such 
    pronouncement, the nature of disposal and the constitution of the Bench 
    pronouncing the order. He shall also make necessary entries in the court 
    diary maintained by him.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>109</number> 
    Transmission of order by the court officer.—The 
    court officer shall immediately on pronouncement, transmit the order with 
    the case file to the Deputy Registrar (Judicial).  
 <section>
<number>b</number> On receipt 
    of the order from the court officer, the Deputy Registrar shall after due 
    scrutiny himself that the provisions of these Rules have been duly complied 
    with and in token thereof affix his initials, with date on the outer cover 
    of the order. The Deputy Registrar shall thereafter cause to transmit the 
    case file and the order to the Judicial Branch for taking expeditious steps 
    to prepare copies and their communication to the parties.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>110</number> Format 
    of order.—
<section><number>a</number> The format of order 
    of the Tribunal shall be in Form No. 19.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> All orders 
    shall be neatly and fairly typewritten in double space on one side only on 
    durable foolscap folio paper of metric A-4 size (30.5 cms. long and 21.5 cms. 
    wide) with left side margin of 5 cms. and right side margin of 2.5 cms. 
    Corrections, if any, in the order shall be carried out neatly. Sufficient 
    space may be left both at the bottom and at the top of each page of the 
    order to make its appearance elegant.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Members 
    constituting the Bench shall affix their signatures in the order of their 
    seniority from right to left.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>111</number> Costs.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Unless otherwise quantified by the Tribunal, when costs are awarded in a 
    case, the same shall be determined as follows:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    For 
    applicant(s)
 
       Legal 
    Practitioner’s fee                       Rs. 500
 
       
    Expenses                                         Rs. 150
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   For 
    Respondent(s) 
 
       Legal 
    Practitioner’s fee                       Rs. 500
 
       
    Expenses                                         Rs. 100
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> Only one 
    set of costs shall be awarded to the applicants as also when the same 
    counsel appears for more than one respondent.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> When costs 
    are awarded a Bill of Costs in Form No. 20 shall be prepared giving the 
    details of the costs awarded to the parties and annexed to the order.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>112</number> 
    Compliance of urgent orders.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Whenever the Bench passes an order, final or inter-locutory, requiring 
    immediate compliance, the court officer shall immediately transmit the case 
    file and the order to the Deputy Registrar (Judicial) who shall ensure 
    prompt action on the same day.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Files with
    Dasti orders should be stapled with “To-day” flags and superscribed 
    with OA/TA/RA/CP/MA/PT No. with the signature of the court officer with 
    date.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>113</number> 
    Placing copies/common orders.—When 
    more than one case is disposed of by a common order, the Judicial Branch 
    shall keep the original order in the main case and a certified copy in the 
    other connected case files. In the order sheet of the connected case(s), the 
    Section Officer in-charge of the Judicial Branch shall note that the 
    original order is kept in the main case file (giving its number).  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>114</number> 
    Indexing of case files disposal.—After 
    communication of the order to the parties/Legal Practitioners, the official 
    concerned shall arrange the records with pagination and prepare the Index 
    Sheet in Form No. 21. He shall affix initials and then transmit the records 
    with the Index initials to the records room.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>115</number> 
    Transmission of files/records/orders.—Transmission 
    of files/records of the cases/orders shall be made only after obtaining 
    acknowledgement in the movement register maintained at different 
    sections/levels as per the directions of the Registrar.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>116</number> Copies 
    of orders in Library.—
<section><number>a</number> The 
    Section Officer of the Judicial Branch shall send copies of every order 
    (final) to the Library.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Copies of 
    all orders received in each month shall be kept at the Library in a separate 
    folder, arranged in the order of date of pronouncement, duly indexed and 
    stitched.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> At the end 
    of every year a consolidated index shall also be prepared and kept in a 
    separate file in the Library.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The order 
    folders and the indices may be made available for reference in the Library 
    to the Legal Practitioners.  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>117</number> Form 
    and fee of application.—
<section><number>a</number> Every 
    application for grant of certified copy shall be in Form No. 22 and 
    accompanied with a non-refundable fee of Rs. 5 (Rupees five only) in the 
    form of I.P.O./D.D. drawn in favour of the Registrar and payable at the 
    place of the Bench of the Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the 
    certified copies applied for are for more than one document in the same 
    cases, only one copy application need be filed.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>118</number> Right 
    of the party to obtain certified copy.—A 
    party to an application/petition or his legal practitioner shall be entitled 
    to obtain certified copy of the record, preceeding or original document 
    filed in case on payment of prescribed fee.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>119</number> 
    Application for copies by stranger.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Applications for copies of documents (other than orders) by persons not 
    parties to the proceedings shall be allowed only by order of the Registrar 
    obtained on a duly verified petition in Form No. III of the Procedure Rules, 
    setting forth the purpose for which the copy is required on payment of 
    prescribed fee.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Copies of 
    orders can however, be granted to any person on payment of prescribed fees.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>120</number> 
    Register of copy application and requisition register.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    A Register of Copy Application shall be maintained in Register Form No. 10 
    and a Requisition Register in Register Form No. 11 in the copying Branch.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Entries in 
    respect of urgent copy applications shall be underlined in red ink/pencil.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>121</number> 
    Copying fee.—The copying fee 
    payable for obtaining an ordinary copy shall be at the rate of Re. 1 per 
    page and for urgent copy at the rate of Rs. 2 per page irrespective of the 
    number of words/lines in each page.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>122</number> 
    Scrutiny of copy application, requisitioning of case records and 
    rectification of defects.—
<section><number>a</number> If 
    the application is in order necessary entries shall be made in the Register 
    of Copy Application and the Requisition Register and the same sent to the 
    official-in-charge of records. The officer in-charge of the records shall 
    promptly transmit the records along with the application after making an 
    entry in the application and initialling the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the 
    application is found to be defective the same shall be notified on the 
    Notice Board of the Registry. If the defects are not rectified within three 
    days from the date of such notification, the copy application shall be 
    struck off. The application shall be deemed to have been made on the date of 
    rectification of all defects.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>123</number> 
    Determination of additional copying fee.—On 
    receipt of the records of officer-in-charge of copying section after 
    satisfying that the records are complete shall determine the additional 
    copying fee payable over and above the copying fee of Rs. 5 already paid and 
    make an entry thereof is the application with his initials. Additional fee 
    payable shall be notified on the Notice Board of the Registry.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>124</number> 
    Remittance of additional copying fee.—Additional 
    copying fee shall be remitted by the applicant between 10-30 a.m. and 4-30 
    p.m. in the form of IPO/DD drawn in favour of the Registrar and payable at 
    the place of the Bench within two days, in the case of urgent copy, and 
    within seven days in the case of ordinary copy from the date of notice. If 
    the additional fee payable is not remitted within the same notified, the 
    application shall be struck off.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>125</number> Order 
    of preparation of certified copy.—Certified 
    copies shall be prepared in the order in which they become ready in all 
    respects. Urgent applications shall take precedence over all ordinary 
    applications.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>126</number> Time 
    limit for issue of urgent/ordinary copy.—Urgent 
    copy shall be delivered to the applicant as far as possible within three 
    days and ordinary copy within ten days from the date the application is 
    ready in all respects.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
 <number>127</number> 
    Notifying when copies are ready for delivery and consequence of not taking 
    delivery.—
<section><number>a</number> On each working day before 11-30 a.m., the officer 
    in-charge of the copying branch shall cause to prepare in duplicate in Form 
    No. 23, a list of cases in which certified copies are ready for delivery and 
    publish one copy of the same on the notice board of the Registry with his 
    signature, and the other copy shall be retained for record.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the 
    applicant fails to take delivery within three months, the certified copy 
    prepared shall be destroyed and the copying fee paid forfeited to 
    Government.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>128</number> Proper 
    accounting of copying fee received.—The 
    Officer in-charge shall ensure that the copying fee received in the registry 
    is promptly accounted in the IPO/DD Register and transmitted to the cash 
    section for crediting them to the Government account.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>129</number> 
    Preparation and comparison of certified copy.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Certified copy shall be made by photo-copying process or by typing. When the 
    copy is so made, it shall be compared by the official in-charge of preparing 
    the copy with the document of which the copy is made, aided by another 
    official in the copying branch. He shall, after satisfying himself that the 
    copy prepared faithfully and legibly reproduces the document desired, 
    appended a certificate as under and affix his initials:  
 
 “Certified 
    that this is a true and accurate copy of the document/order as in the case 
    file (OA/RA/TA/CP/MA/PT No. ......../20......) and that all the matter 
    appearing therein have been legibly and faithfully copied with no 
    modifications”.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> He shall 
    affix an endorsement on the last page of the copy as under and put his 
    initials:  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Serial No. of the copy of application:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Name of the applicant:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Date of presentation of application:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   No. of pages:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   Copying fee charged/urgent or ordinary:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   Date of preparation of copy:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   Date on which copy is ready:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   Date of delivery:  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    certificate and the endorsement shall be made with the help of a rubber 
    stamp got prepared for that purpose. The entries however shall be made in 
    ink.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The 
    officer authorised to issue the copy shall affix his signature below the 
    endorsement and cause to affix the seal of the Tribunal on all pages of the 
    copy and also initial wherever there are corrections.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>130</number> 
    Re-transmission of case records.—On 
    completion of the preparation of the certified copy, the officer-in-charge 
    of the copying section shall re-transmit the records of the case to the 
    concerned branch, after making necessary entries in the Requisition Register 
    and obtain acknowledgement of the official, who receives back the records, 
    in the relevant column of the Register.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>131</number> Mode 
    of delivery of certified copy.—At 
    the time of the delivery of the certified copy, the official concerned shall 
    obtain the signature of the applicant in the relevant column in the Register 
    of Copy Applications, record the date of such delivery on the copy 
    application and fill up relevant column regarding the date of delivery in 
    the Endorsement stamped on the certified copy.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>132</number> 
    Request for certified copy by post.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Where the applicant desires to have the certified copy sent to him by post, 
    he shall send an additional sum of
    Rs. 10 by way of IPO/DD drawn in favour of the Registrar and payable at the 
    place of the Bench for defraying the postal charges etc.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the 
    amount sent is found to be inadequate, the applicant shall be intimated to 
    remit the said amount within the time specified. On receipt of the 
    intimation, the applicant shall remit the amount in the manner provided in 
    sub-rule (a) above and within the time specified.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>133</number> 
    Intimation of rejection.—If for 
    any reason the copy application is rejected, due intimation be given to the 
    applicant and the refundable amount if any, returned to him.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>134</number> Supply 
    of free copy only once.—Once free 
    copy of the order is sent as provided in rule 22 of the Procedure Rules, the 
    Tribunal shall not be required to furnish any more free copies.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>135</number> 
    Certifying of free copies.—Every 
    free copy issued to a party or his legal practitioner in accordance with the 
    Procedure Rules shall be certified to be “True Copy” and shall be 
    superscribed “FREE COPY U/R 22 OF CAT (PROCEDURE) RULES” with a rubber stamp 
    and signed by the officer authorised in that behalf. He shall also cause to 
    enter the date and other details of furnishing of such free copy in the 
    Register of Free Copies in Register Form No. 12.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>136</number> Time 
    for furnishing free copies.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Judicial Branch of the Registry shall issue free copies of the order to the 
    parties or their legal practitioners as provided under rule 22 of the 
    Procedure Rules as far as possible within seven days from the date of 
    pronouncement of the order.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the 
    free copy of the order is delivered by hand to parties/their legal 
    practitioner, the officer in-charge shall obtain acknowledgment thereof in 
    the relevant column in the Register of Free Copies.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>137</number> 
    Furnishing of free copy in a joint application.—When 
    a joint application/petition is made, only one free copy of the order 
    contemplated by rule 22 of the Procedure Rules shall be issued, either to 
    their legal practitioners or if they are appearing in person, to any one of 
    the applicants.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>138</number> 
    Furnishing of corrected free copy of order.—Whenever 
    clerical or typographical errors/mistakes in an order are rectified 
    subsequent to the issue of the free copy thereof, the Registrar shall cause 
    to issue a corrected free copy of such order to the parties/their legal 
    practitioners in the prescribed manner.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>139</number> Manner 
    of service of order notice issued by the Supreme Court of India.—Service 
    of orders/notices on respondents ordered by the Supreme Court of India in an 
    appeal or petition pending before that court shall be effected in the manner 
    provided by the Supreme Court Rules, 1966 as amended from time to time.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>140</number> Steps 
    to comply with Supreme Court directions.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    Unless otherwise ordered by the Supreme Court, the Appellant or his Advocate 
    shall be notified to deposit the transmission charges and cost of 
    preparation of record, if any, etc., within 15 days of the receipt of the 
    notice.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When the 
    party or Advocate fails to deposit the amount as aforesaid, the Registrar 
    shall forthwith submit a report thereof to the Registrar of the Supreme 
    Court of India.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>141</number> 
    Register of S.L.Ps./Appeals.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    A register in Form No. 13 shall be maintained in regard to S.L.Ps./Appeals 
    against the orders of the Tribunal to the Supreme Court and necessary 
    entries therein be promptly made by the Judicial Branch.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    register shall be placed for scrutiny by the Chairman/Vice-Chairman in the 
    first week of every month.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>142</number> 
    Placing of Supreme Court orders before Chairman/Vice-Chairman/Members.—Whenever 
    an interim or final order passed by the Supreme Court of India in an appeal 
    or other proceeding preferred against a decision of the Tribunal is 
    received, the same shall forthwith be placed before the 
    Chairman/Vice-Chairman/Members for information and kept in the relevant case 
    file. Immediate attention of the Registrar shall be drawn to the directions 
    requiring compliance.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>143</number> 
    Circulation of the orders of the Supreme Court.—All 
    orders of the Supreme Court including dismissal of S.L.Ps. shall be 
    circulated to the Members of the Bench whose decision was challenged before 
    the Supreme Court and kept in the relevant case file.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>144</number> 
    Registrar to ensure compliance of Supreme Court orders.—It 
    shall be the duty of the Registrar to take expeditious steps to comply with 
    the directions of the Supreme Court.  
  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>145</number> 
    Procedure regarding retention, preservation and destruction of records.—Retention, 
    preservation and destruction of records shall be done in accordance with the 
    rules contained in the CAT (Destruction of Records) Rules, 1990 given in 
    Appendix V as amended from time to time.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>146</number> 
    Receipt, scrutiny and custody of records.—The 
    record keeper shall be the custodian and responsible for the records lodged 
    in the Record Room. He shall receive the records sent to the record room and 
    scrutinise the records within three days of the date of receipt of records 
    in the record room.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>147</number> 
    Rectification of defects/securing of missing records.—If 
    on such scrutiny, any defect or missing of documents is found in the 
    records, the Record Keeper shall intimate the same and remit the records 
    back to the branch/section from which the records were received. Thereupon, 
    the Section Officer in-charge of the concerned branch/section shall cause to 
    take steps to rectify the defects/omission so pointed out, and after such 
    rectification re-transmit the records to the record room within three days 
    of its receipt from the record room.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>148</number> 
    Maintenance of Register of Records received in the record room.—The 
    Record Keeper shall maintain a register in Register Form No. 14 of Records 
    received in the record room.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>149</number> Entry 
    regarding destruction.—Entries 
    regarding destruction shall be made in the relevant columns of REGISTER FORM 
    NO. 14.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>150</number> 
    Preservation of records requiring permanent retention.—Records 
    required to be preserved permanently shall be stacked in bundles of 
    convenient size, arranging them in chronological order. The bundle shall be 
    wrapped in ‘Kora Cloth’ on which shall be attached labels indicating in 
    chronological order register numbers of the cases included in each bundle. 
    Such bundles shall be arranged serially and kept in the records room.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>151</number> 
    Retention of records beyond prescribed period.—The 
    Registrar may for reasons to be recorded in writing and with prior 
    permission of the Chairman order that record of any particular case be 
    preserved beyond the prescribed period provided under the Destruction Rules.  
  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>152</number> 
    Circuit Benches.—The provisions 
    of these Rules shall mutatis mutandis govern applications entertained 
    by circuit Benches subject to such adaptations as may by order be made by 
    the concerned Vice-Chairman on being satisfied that it is necessary to do so 
    in the interest of justice.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>153</number> Use of 
    computers.—
<section><number>a</number> The Chairman may 
    issue such orders or directions as may be necessary for complying with the 
    provisions of the relevant Rules of Practice with the aid of the computer 
    and for effective use of the computer facility as and when introduced.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Compliance 
    with such orders or directions issued by the Chairman from time to time 
    shall be deemed to be due compliance of the provisions of the relevant Rules 
    of Practice.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>154</number> 
    Classification of cases subjectwise/departmentwise.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    The scrutiny branch of the Registry shall at the time of scrutiny make 
    classification of the cases as follows:—  
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>   Departmentwise;  
 </subsection><subsection>
          <number>ii</number>   Subjectwise; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
          <number>iii</number>   Cases which can be heard by 
    a Single Member Bench.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    departmentwise classification shall be made in accordance with Appendix VI, 
    as may be modified by the Chairman from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> 
    Subjectwise classification shall be made in accordance with Appendix VII, as 
    may be modified by the Chairman from time to time  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Single 
    Member Bench cases shall be classified in accordance with 
    Appendix VII as may be modified by the Chairman from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   The 
    classification as above shall be entered in the relevant columns in the 
    report of scrutiny in Form No. 2/Form No. 3, Order Sheet in Form No. 4 and 
    Facing Sheet of the final cover in Form No. 5, referred to in rules 11 to 13 
    of these Rules.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>155</number> Weekly 
    and monthly statements—Furnishing 
    of.—
<section><number>a</number> The Registrar of each Bench shall prepare a weekly progress 
    report in Form No. 24 and circulate among all the Members of the Bench 
    concerned.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The 
    Vice-Chairman of the Bench concerned shall forward a consolidated monthly 
    progress report in Form No. 24 to the Chairman before the 7th of the each 
    month.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    Registrar of the concerned Bench shall prepare a monthly statement in two 
    parts as in Form No. 25 regarding filing, disposal and pendency of cases and 
    forward the same to the Registrar of the Principal Bench before the 7th of 
    each month.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>156</number> 
    Inspection of Registry.—
<section><number>a</number> The 
    Registrar or the Deputy Registrar designated by him shall conduct inspection 
    of the sections twice a year viz., for the period from 1st January to 
    30th June and 1st July to 31st December, on such date as may be found 
    convenient.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The report 
    of inspection of the Judicial Branch, Library, Administrative Branch and 
    Record Room shall be as in Schedules I to IV to Appendix IX, as may be 
    modified by the Chairman from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The 
    Section Officer concerned shall promptly comply with the directions of the 
    Registrar and submit a report about due compliance to the Registrar within 
    such time as the Registrar may grant.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The 
    Registrar shall submit a report to the Chairman/Vice-Chairman containing 
    brief summary of his inspection of the Registry, directions given by him to 
    the sections and the steps taken for due compliance with such directions.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>157</number> Due 
    compliance with the Act, Rules of Procedure and the Rules of Practice.—The 
    Registrar or any officer authorised by him may, for the purpose of 
    satisfying himself that the provisions of the Act, the Rules of Procedure 
    and the Rules of practice are duly complied with, make such enquiry as he 
    deems fit and call upon such party, as he deems necessary to appear before 
    him and pass such orders as he deems proper.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>158</number> 
    Removal of doubt/difficulty.—If 
    in the matter of implementation of these rules any doubt or difficulty 
    arises, the same shall be placed before the Chairman and his decision 
    thereon shall be final.  
 

 
 
 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX I
 



[See rule 18(c)]
 


No. 1/32/87-JA
 



December 1  8,1991
 


ORDER
 

 
 


In 
    supersession of the Order of the Chairman No. 1/32/87-JA dated 1-3-1988 and 
    in exercise of the powers conferred by sub-section (6) of section 5 of the 
    Administrative Tribunals Act, 1985, I hereby authorise all the Members of 
    the Central Administrative Tribunal to function as a Bench consisting of a 
    Single Member and exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the 
    Tribunal in respect of classes of cases specified in the Schedule w.e.f. 
    1-1-1992 subject to the following procedure:—
 


(1)   that the case does not involve validity 
    of any statutory provision or interpretation of any of the provisions of the 
    Constitution.
 


(2)   that it is open to either party to 
    submit to the Single Member before the matter is taken up for admission or 
    for final hearing, that it may be placed before a Bench of two Members. If 
    such a request is made at the outset, the Single Member shall direct that 
    the case be placed before an appropriate Bench of two members. Once the case 
    is taken up, no such request shall be entertained at any subsequent stage of 
    the proceedings for admission or final hearing as the case may be.
 


Explanation:
 


         (i)   The party not making the 
    request at the stage of admission shall not be precluded from making such a 
    request when the case is taken up for final hearing.
 


        (ii)   The stage of admission would 
    also cover cases which may be finally disposed of with the consent of 
    parties at the admission stage.
 


       (iii)   Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the previous paragraphs if at any stage of the proceedings it 
    appears to the Single Member that the case is of such a nature that it ought 
    to be heard by a Bench of two members, he may refer it to the Chairman to 
    transfer it to a Bench of two members.
 


 
 


SCHEDULE
 
 
 
 


Cases relating to change of date of birth.
 
 


Cases relating to postings/transfer.
 
 


Cases relating to entry in character 
        rolls/confidential record/service record,      made otherwise than as a 
        measure of penalty under Central Civil Services (Classification, Control 
        and Appeal) Rules, 1965.
 
 


Cases relating to allotment or eviction 
        from Government accommodation.
 
 


Cases relating to fixation of pay.
 
 


Cases relating to claims of medical 
        reimbursement, leave, joining time, L.T.C. and over-time
 
 


Cases relating to crossing of efficiency 
        bar.
 
 


Cases relating to grant of pension, family 
        pension, other retirement benefits, and cases relating to interest on 
        retirement benefits.
 
 


Cases relating to grant or refusal to 
        grant advances/loans. 
 
 


Cases relating to stagnation increment.
 
 


Cases relating to grant of passes to 
        Railway employees.
 
 


Cases relating to grant, refusal or 
        recovery of allowances.
 
 


Cases relating to compassionate 
        appointment/appointment of dependents of Government servants dying in 
        harness.


 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


Appendix II
 


[See rule 18(d)]
 


CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL
 


Faridkot House, Copernicus Marg, New 
    Delhi-110001
 


No. 13/19/91-JA         
 


                         December 18, 1991
 


ORDER
 

 
 


In exercise of 
    the powers conferred by section 5 and all other enabling provisions of the 
    Administrative Tribunals Act, 1985 and in supersession of all orders on the 
    subject, I hereby make the following order regulating constitution of 
    Benches and distribution of work of the Principal Bench and other Benches of 
    the Central Administrative Tribunal:—
 


1.   In the case of the Principal Bench, the 
    Chairman and in his absence, the senior-most Vice-Chairman available and in 
    their absence, the seniormost member available, shall regulate constitution 
    of Benches (including Vacation Bench) and distribution of work of that 
    Bench.
 


2.   In the case of other Benches, the 
    Vice-Chairman and in his absence, the senior-most member available, shall 
    regulate constitution of the Benches and distribution of the work.
 


3.   Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    above paragraph, the power of constitution of Benches and distribution of 
    work of the Principal Bench and other Benches, shall be subject to such 
    general or special orders, as the Chairman and in his absence, senior-most 
    Vice-Chairman of the Principal Bench who is available, may make.
 


V.S. MALIMATH,
 


Chairman
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX III
 


[See rule 19(b)]
 


CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL
 


Faridkot House, Copernicus Marg, New 
    Delhi-110001
 


No.. 
    1/32/87-JA                                  
 



                                                     January 20, 1992
 


ORDER
 

 
 


In exercise of 
    the powers conferred by sub-section (6) of section 5 of the Administrative 
    Tribunals Act, 1985, I hereby make the following order:
 


In situations 
    when a Division Bench is not available for dealing with urgent cases for 
    admission and grant of interim orders, and the urgency is such that the 
    matter cannot be deferred until a Division Bench becomes available, the 
    Single Member Bench is authorised to take up such urgent cases for admission 
    and grant of interim orders subject to the condition that if the Single 
    Member is not inclined to admit the matter he shall refer the matter for 
    being placed before the appropriate Division Bench as soon as the same 
    becomes available.
 


(V.S. MALIMATH)
 


Chairman
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX IV
 


(See rule 49)
 


CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL
 


Faridkot House, Copernicus Marg, New 
    Delhi-110001
 


New Delhi, the 18th February, 1992
 


No. 13/19/91-JA
 


NOTIFICATION
 


In exercise of 
    the powers conferred by sections 5, 12, and 22 of the Administrative 
    Tribunals Act, 1985 read with rule 17 of the Central Administrative Tribunal 
    (Procedure) Rules, 1987 and in supersession of all previous orders in this 
    regard, I, V.S. Malimath, Chairman, Central Administrative Tribunal hereby 
    make the following order with the object of avoiding delay in dealing with 
    the Review Petitions presented before different (additional) Benches of the 
    Central Administrative Tribunal:—
 


REVIEW OF ORDERS PASSED BY A BENCH OF TWO 
    MEMBERS
 


I. 
    1. Review of order in which both the Members who passed the order are 
    functioning in the same Bench.
 


In such a case, 
    the Review Petition shall be placed before the members who passed the order 
    for consideration by circulation. If one of them is of the view that it 
    merits a hearing, then the petition shall be placed before that Bench for 
    preliminary hearing. In such a case, it would not be necessary to seek 
    orders of the Chairman.
 


2. Review of 
    order passed by the Bench of which one member belongs to the local Bench and 
    the other is a member of another Bench.
 


In such a case, 
    the Review Petition shall be sent for consideration by circulation to the 
    members who passed the order. If one of them is of the view that it merits a 
    hearing, then the petition shall be placed for preliminary hearing. For that 
    purpose, the Vice-Chairman of the local Bench shall seek orders of the 
    Chairman.
 


3. Review of 
    order in which both the members have ceased to be members of the Tribunal.
 


In such a case, 
    the Vice-Chairman shall place the Review Petition for preliminary hearing 
    before a Bench consisting of any two members of that Bench. It would not be 
    necessary to seek orders of the Chairman in such a case.
 


4. Review of 
    order in which one of the members has ceased to be a member of the Tribunal.
 


If one of the 
    members who passed the order is available in that Bench, the Vice-Chairman 
    shall constitute a Bench with him/her and any other member of the Bench and 
    place the petition for preliminary hearing.
 


If not, the 
    Vice-Chairman shall constitute a Bench consisting of any two members of that 
    Bench.
 


5. Review of 
    order when both the members who passed the order are members of other 
    Benches.
 


In such a case, 
    the Vice-Chairman shall arrange to send the Review petition to both the 
    members to consider the petition by circulation. If one of them is of the 
    view that the petition merits a hearing, then the petition shall be placed 
    for preliminary hearing. For that purpose, the Vice-Chairman shall seek 
    orders of the Chairman.
 

 
 


REVIEW OF ORDERS PASSED BY A SINGLE MEMBER 
    BENCH
 


II. 
    (a) If the single member who decided the case continues to be a member of 
    that Bench, the petition shall be placed before him/her for consideration by 
    circulation. If the member is of the view that the petition merits a 
    hearing, it shall be posted before him/her for preliminary hearing.
 


(b) If the 
    member who decided the case has become a member of another Bench of the 
    Tribunal, the Vice-Chairman shall send the petition to him/her for being 
    considered by circulation. If the member is of the view that the petition 
    merits a hearing, then the petition shall be placed for preliminary hearing. 
    For that purpose the Vice-Chairman shall seek orders of the Chairman.
 


(c) If the 
    single member who passed the order has ceased to be a member of the 
    Tribunal, then the Vice-Chairman shall post the petition for preliminary 
    hearing before any member of the Bench. In such a case, it would not be 
    necessary to seek the orders of the Chairman.
 


III. 
    If the Review Petition is not summarily dismissed, further hearing shall be 
    by the very same Bench constituted as per the aforesaid provisions.
 


IV. 
Orders of the Chairman may be sought when 
    a situation not covered by the above provisions arises or when in the 
    interest of justice it is necessary to deviate from the same.
 

 
 


Note.—The 
    above procedure shall mutatis mutandis be followed in the Principal 
    Bench.
 


V.S. MALIMATH, 

    Chairman
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX VI
 


[See rule 154(b)]
 


DEPARTMENT-WISE CLASSIFICATION OF CASES
 

 
 




    (A) ALL INDIA SERVICES
 


1.     Indian 
    Administrative Service
 


2.     Indian 
    Police Service
 


3.     Indian 
    Forest Service
 


4.     Indian 
    Foreign Service
 


(B) OTHER 
    SERVICES REGULATED BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT SERVICE RULES
 


5.     M/o 
    Agriculture
 


6.     M/o 
    Chemicals &amp; Fertilisers
 


7.     M/o 
    Civil Aviation and Tourism
 


8.     M/o 
    Civil Supplies, Consumer Affairs &amp; Public Distribution
 


9.     M/o Coal
 


10.   M/o 
    Commerce
 


11.   M/o 
    Communications
 


12.   M/o 
    Defence
 


13.   M/o 
    Environment and Forests
 


14.   M/o 
    External Affairs
 


15.   M/o 
    Finance
 


16.   M/o Food
 


17.   M/o Food 
    Processing Industries
 


18.   M/o 
    Health and Family Welfare
 


19.   M/o Home 
    Affairs
 


20.   M/o Human 
    Resource Development
 


21.   M/o 
    Industry
 


22.   M/o 
    Information and Broadcasting
 


23.   M/o 
    Labour
 


24.   M/o Law 
    and Justice and Company Affairs
 


25.   M/o Mines
 


26.   M/o 
    Non-Conventional Energy
 


27.   M/o 
    Parliamentary Affairs
 


28.   M/o 
    Personnel, Public Grievances and Pensions
 


29.   M/o 
    Petroleum and Natural Gas
 


30.   M/o 
    Planning and Programme Implementation
 


31.   M/o Power
 


32.   M/o 
    Railways
 


33.   M/o Rural 
    Development
 


34.   M/o 
    Science and Technology
 


35.   M/o Steel
 


36.   M/o 
    Surface Transport
 


37.   M/o 
    Textiles
 


38.   M/o Urban 
    Development
 


39.   M/o Water 
    Resources
 


40.   M/o 
    Welfare
 


41.   D/o 
    Atomic Energy
 


42.   D/o 
    Electronics
 


43.   D/o Ocean 
    Development
 


44.   D/o Space
 


45.   Cabinet 
    Secretariat
 


46.   
    President’s Secretariat
 


47.   Prime 
    Minister’s Office
 


48.   Planning 
    Commission
 


49.   
    Government of India Press
 


50.   Staff 
    Selection Commission
 


(C)  
    OTHER SERVICES COVERED BY CENTRAL CIVIL SERVICES RULES, C. &amp; A.G.,  

            PUBLIC SECTOR, AUTONOMOUS BODIES
 


51.   
    Comptroller and Auditor General of India
 


52.   
    Controller General of Accounts
 


53.   Chief 
    Election Commissioner
 


54.   Planning 
    Commission
 


55.   Union 
    Public Service Commission
 


56.   U.T. of 
    Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands
 


57.   U.T. of 
    Chandigarh
 


58.   U.T. of 
    Dadra &amp; Nagar Haveli
 


59.   U.T. of 
    Daman &amp; Diu
 


60.   U.T. of 
    Delhi
 


61.   U.T. of 
    Lakshadweep
 


62.   U.T. of 
    Pondicherry
 


63.   Central 
    Board of Trustees/Central Provident &amp; Fund Commissioner
 


64.   
    Employees’ State Insurance Corporation
 


65.   Central 
    Board of Workers Education
 


66.   National 
    Labour Institute
 


67.   National 
    Council of Safety in Mines, Dhanbad
 


68.   Council 
    of Scientific and Industrial Research
 


69.   Central 
    Social Welfare Board
 


70.   Indian 
    Council of Agricultural Research
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX VII
 


[See rule 154(c)]
 


SUBJECT-WISE CLASSIFICATION of cases
 


DIVISION BENCH CASES
 


1.     
    Absorption in Public Sector/Autonomous Bodies/Other Departments
 


2.     
    Ad-hoc Appointments/Regularisation
 


3.     All 
    India Services
 


4.     
    Allotment/Vacation/Eviction of Quarters
 


5.     Civil 
    Services Examination
 


6.     Creation 
    and Abolition of Post
 


7.     Daily 
    Wages/Casual/Regularisation
 


8.     
    Deputation/Regularisation
 


9.     
    Disciplinary—Cases
 


(a)   Major 
    Punishment—Dismissal/Removal/Compulsory Retirement Reduction in Rank
 


(b)   Minor Punishment—Other Punishments
 


(c)   Suspension
 


10.   Extra 
    Departmental Staff 
 


11.   Leave 
    Rules—Break in Services/Dies Non
 


12.   Lien
 


13.   Medical 
    Facilities
 


14.   Probation
 


15.   
    Recruitment &amp; Appointment
 


16.   
    Reservation for SC/ST/Ex-servicemen/Physically Handicapped
 


17.   Reversion
 


18.   
    Retirement under FR 56(J)
 


19.   Scale of 
    Pay
 


20.   
    Selection/Promotion
 


21.   
    Seniority/Confirmation
 


22.   Surplus 
    Staff—Redeployment of
 


23.   T.A.
 


24.   Temporary 
    Service, Rules/Termination of Service
 


25.   Training
 


26.   Uniform 
    and Washing Allowance
 


27.   
    Voluntary, Resignation/Retirement
 


28.   All 
    Single, Bench Cases Classified, under the Heads (A) to (M) in Appendix VIII
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNAL RULES OF PRACTICE, 1993
 

 
 


APPENDIX VIII
 


(See rule 154)
 


SUBJECT-WISE CLASSIFICATION OF CASES
 


SINGLE BENCH CASES
 

 
 


(a)   Allotment of Eviction for Government 
    Accommodation
 


(b)   Claims of Medical Reimbursement, Leave, 
    Joining Time, L.T.C. and Over-Time
 


(c)   Compassionate Appointment/Appointment of 
    Dependents Dying in Harness
 


(d)   Crossing of Efficiency Bar
 


(e)   Date of Birth
 


(f)   Entry in Character Rolls/Confidential 
    Record/Service, record, made otherwise than as a measure of penalty under 
    Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965
 


(g)   Fixation of Pay
 


(h)   Grant of Passes to Railway Employees
 


(i)   Grant of Pension, Family Pension, other 
    Retirement Benefits and Interest on Retirement Benefits
 


(j)   Grant or Refusal to Grant Advances/Loans
 


(k)   Grant, Refusal or Recovery of Allowances
 


(l)   Postings/Transfers
 


(m)   Stagnation Increment
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>