<act><tid>1574006</tid>
<title>THE VOLUNTARY DISCLOSURE OF INCOME AND WEALTH ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 25th January, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for voluntary disclosure of income and wealth 
and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>352002</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>224669</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Voluntary Disclosure of Income and Wealth Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1706451</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>760506</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 8th day of 
October, <year>1975</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>656636</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1607240</tid>
<number>a</number> (i)" Gold (Control) Act" means the Gold (Control) Act, 
<year>1968</year>; (45 of <year>1968</year>.)

<subsection><tid>973912</tid>
<number>ii</number>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1307621</tid>
<number>iii</number>" Wealth- tax Act" means the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>; 
 (27 of <year>1957</year>.)

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1207850</tid>
<number>b</number>all other words and expressions used in this Act but 
not defined and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>350577</tid>
<number> 3</number> Charge of income- tax on voluntarily disclosed income.
<section><tid>948909</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, where any person makes, on or 
after the date of commencement of this Act but before the 1st day of 
January, <year>1976</year>, a declaration in accordance with the provisions of 
section 4 in respect of any income chargeable to tax under the Indian 
Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or the Income- tax Act for any 
assessment year-

<subsection><tid>510954</tid>
<number>a</number>for which he has failed to furnish a return under section 
 139 of the Income- tax Act, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1963936</tid>
<number>b</number>which he has failed to disclose in a return of income 
furnished by him under the Income- tax Act before the date of 
commencement of this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1359723</tid>
<number>c</number>which has escaped assessment by reason of the omission 
or failure on the part of such person to make a return under 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or the Income- 
tax Act or to disclose fully and truly all material facts 
necessary for his assessment or otherwise,
then, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Income- tax Act, 
 <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or the Income- tax Act or in any Finance Act, 
income- tax shall be charged in respect of the income so declared (such  
income being hereInafter referred to as the voluntarily disclosed 
  income) at the rate or rates specified in the Schedule.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>460439</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall apply in relation 
to-

<subsection><tid>388275</tid>
<number>i</number>the income assessable for any assessment year for which 
a notice under section 139 or section 148 of the Income- tax 
Act has been served upon such person and the return has not 
been furnished before the commencement of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1314183</tid>
<number>ii</number>where any books of account, other documents, money, 
bullion, jewellery or other valuable articles or things 
belonging to the person making the declaration under sub- 
section (1)  (hereafter in this section, in sections 4 to 13  
  and in the Schedule referred to as the declarant) have been 
seized as a result of any search under section 132 of the 
Income- tax Act or under section 37A of the Wealth- tax Act, 
the income in respect of the previous year in which such 
search was made or any earlier previous year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>133690</tid>
<number>3</number>In addition to the amount of income- tax to be paid under 
sub- section (1), the declarant shall invest a sum equal to five per 
cent. of the amount of the voluntarily disclosed income in such 
securities as the Central Government may notify in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>687033</tid>
<number> 4</number> Particulars to be furnished in declaration.
<section><tid>2421</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
declaration under sub- section (1) of section 3 shall be made to the 
Commissioner and shall be in such form and shall be verified in such 
manner as may be prescribed by rules made by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1823526</tid>
<number>2</number>The declaration shall be signed-

<subsection><tid>897921</tid>
<number>a</number>where the declarant is an individual, by the individual 
himself; where such individual is absent from India, by the 
individual concerned or by some person duly authorised by him 
in this behalf; and where the individual is mentally 
incapacitated from attending to his affairs, by his guardian 
or by any other person competent to act on his behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1650414</tid>
<number>b</number>where the declarant is a Hindu undivided family, by the 
karta, and where the karta is absent from India or is 
mentally incapacitated from attending to his affairs, by any 
other adult member of such family;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1854254</tid>
<number>c</number>where the declarant is a company, by the managing 
director thereof, or where for any unavoidable reason such 
managing director is not able to sign the declaration or 
where there is no managing director, by any director thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1344258</tid>
<number>d</number>where the declarant is a firm, by the managing partner 
thereof, or where for any unavoidable reason such managing 
partner is not able to sign the declaration, or where there 
is no managing partner as such, by any partner thereof, not 
being a minor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>485264</tid>
<number>e</number>where the declarant is any other association, by any 
member of the association or the principal officer thereof; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292322</tid>
<number>f</number>where the declarant is any other person, by that person 
or by some person competent to act on his behalf.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1484820</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person, who has made a declaration under subsection (1) 
of section 3 in respect of his income, or as a representative assessee 
in respect of the income of any other person, shall not be entitled to 
make any other declaration under that sub- section in respect of his 
income or, as the case may be, the income of such other person, and 
any such other declaration, if made, shall be deemed to be void.





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1977649</tid>
<number>6</number>Interest payable by declarant. If the amount of income- tax 
payable in respect of the voluntarily disclosed income is not paid on 
or before the 31st day of March, <year>1976</year>, the declarant shall be liable 
to pay simple interest at twelve per cent. per annum on the amount 
remaining unpaid from the 1st day of April, <year>1976</year> to the date of 
payment and the provisions of the Income- tax Act and the rules made 
thereunder shall, so far as may be, apply as if the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

interest payable under this section were interest payable under sub- 
section (2) of section 220 of that Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1677883</tid>
<number> 7</number> Mode of recovery.
<section><tid>1249220</tid>
<number>1</number>If the declarant fails to pay the  
income- tax in respect of the voluntarily disclosed income within the 
time allowed under sub- section (2) of section 5 or to invest the 
amount required to be invested in the securities referred to in sub- 
section (3) of section 3 within the time specified in sub- section (4) 
of section 5, the declarant shall be deemed to be in default.

</section>

<section><tid>792045</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions contained in sections 221 to 227, 229, 231 
and 232 of the Income- tax Act and the Second and Third Schedules to 
that Act and any rules made thereunder shall, so far as may be, apply 
as if the said provisions were provisions of this Act and referred Lo 
income- tax and sums payable by way of penalty and interest under this 
Act instead of to tax and sums by way of penalty and interest payable 
under that Act and to the declarant instead of to the assessee.

</section>

<section><tid>723102</tid>
<number>3</number>Any arrears in respect of the amount required to be invested 
by the declarant in the securities referred to in sub- section (3) of 
section 3 shall be recoverable in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- section (2) as if such arrears were arrears. of income- tax and the 
amount so recovered shall be utilised fox the purchase of such 
securities in the name of the declarant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>295015</tid>
<number> 8</number> Voluntarily disclosed income not to be included in the total 
income.
<section><tid>1373818</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount of the voluntarily disclosed income shall  
not, be included in the total income of the declarant for any 
assessment year under the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or 
the Income- tax Act, or the Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year> (15 of <year>1940</year>.) 
or the Business Profits Tax Act, <year>1947</year> (21 of <year>1947</year>.) or the Super 
Profits Tax Act, <year>1963</year> (14 of <year>1963</year>.) or the Companies (Profits) Surtax 
Act, <year>1964</year>, (7 of <year>1964</year>.) if the following conditions are fulfilled, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>559006</tid>
<number>i</number>the declarant credits such amount in the books of 
account, if any, maintained by him for any source of income 
or in any other record, and intimates the credit so made to 
the Income- tax Officer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1832269</tid>
<number>ii</number>the income- tax in respect of the voluntarily disclosed 
income is paid by the declarant; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1455781</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount required to be invested in the securities 
referred to in sub- section (3) of section 3 is so invested by 
the declarant.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>34166</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner shall, on' an application made by the 
declarant, grant a certificate to him setting forth the particulars of 
the voluntarily disclosed income, the amount of income- tax paid in 
respect of the same, the amount of investment made in the securities 
referred to in sub- section (3) of section 3 and the date of payment 
and investment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315369</tid>
<number> 9</number> Voluntarily disclosed income not to affect finality of 
completed assessments, etc. The declarant shall not be entitled, in 
respect of the voluntarily disclosed income or any amount of income- 
tax paid thereon, to reopen any assessment or reassessment made under 
any of the Acts mentioned in sub- section
<section><tid>1059264</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 8 or claim any  
set off or relief in any appeal, reference or other proceeding in 
relation to any such assessment or reassessment.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1410462</tid>
<number> 10</number> Income- tax in respect of voluntarily disclosed income not 
refundable. Any amount of income- tax paid in pursuance of a 
declaration made under sub- section
<section><tid>1623937</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 shall not be  
refundable under any circumstances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>10522</tid>
<number> 11</number> Declaration not admissible in evidence against declarant. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, nothing contained in any declaration made under sub section

<section><tid>805369</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 shall be admissible in evidence against the de  
clarant for the purpose of any proceeding relating to imposition of 
penalty or for the purposes of prosecution under any of the Acts men- 
tioned in sub- section (1) of section 8 or the Wealth- tax Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1049020</tid>
<number> 12</number> Secrecy of declaration.
<section><tid>184032</tid>
<number>1</number>All particulars contained in a  
declaration made under sub section (1) of section 3 shall be treated 
as confidential and, notwithstanding anything contained in any law for 
the time being in force, no court or any other authority shall be 
entitled to require any public servant or the declarant to produce 
before it any such declaration or any part thereof or to give any 
evidence before it in respect thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1904902</tid>
<number>2</number>No public servant shall disclose any particulars contained 
in any such declaration except to any officer employed in the 
execution of any of the Acts mentioned in sub- section (1) of section 
8, or the Wealth- tax Act, or to any officer appointed by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or the Board to audit income- 
tax receipts or refunds.

</section>

<section><tid>586300</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall apply in 
relation to all documents and particulars relating to the investment 
in the securities referred to in sub- section (3) of section 3 
 (including the payment of interest on such securities) as they apply 
in relation to the declaration made under sub- section (1) of that 
section and the particulars contained therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>253039</tid>
<number> 13</number> Exemption from wealth- tax in respect of assets specified in 
declaration.
<section><tid>677945</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the voluntarily disclosed income is represented  
by cash (including bank deposits), bullion, investment in shares, 
debts due from other persons, commodities or any other assets 
specified in the declaration made under sub- section (1) of section 3-

<subsection><tid>1344530</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of which the declarant has failed. to 
furnish a return under section 14 of the Wealth- tax Act for 
the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1975</year> 
or any earlier assessment year or years, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1706955</tid>
<number>b</number>which have not been shown in the return of net wealth 
furnished by him for the said assessment year or years, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1301469</tid>
<number>c</number>which have been understated in value in the return of 
net wealth furnished by him for the said assessment year or 
years,
then, notwithstanding anything contained, in the Wealth- tax Act or any 
rules made thereunder,-


<subsubsection><tid>1890020</tid>
<number>i</number>wealth- tax shall not be payable by the declarant in 
respect of the assets referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) 
and such assets

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall not be included in his net wealth for the said 
assessment year or years;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1515651</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount by which the value of the assets referred to 
in clause (c) has been understated in the return of net 
wealth for the said assessment year or years, to the extent 
such amount does not exceed the voluntarily disclosed income 
utilised for acquiring such assets, shall not be taken into 
account in computing the net wealth of the declarant for the 
said assessment year or years.
Explanation.- Where a declaration under sub- section (1) of section 
 3 is made by a firm, the assets referred to in clause (i) or, as the 
case may be, the amount referred to in clause (ii) shall not be taken 
into account in computing the net wealth of any partner of the firm 
or, as the case may be, in determining the value of the interest of 
any partner in the firm.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1164026</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply unless 
the. conditions specified in sub- section (1) of section 8 are 
fulfilled by the declarant.

</section>

<section><tid>532844</tid>
<number>3</number>All words and expressions used in this section and in 
section 15 but not defined and defined in the Wealth- tax Act shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1772261</tid>
<number> 14</number> Disclosure of income in cases of search and seizure.
<section><tid>1119566</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this section, where any books of account, 
other, documents, money, bullion, jewellery or other valuable articles 
or things belonging to a person have been seized as a result of a 
search under section 132 of the Income- tax Act or section 37A of the 
Wealth- tax Act and such person (hereafter in this section referred to  
  as the declarant) makes, on or after the date of commencement of this 
Act but before the 1st day of January, <year>1976</year>, a declaration in 
accordance with sub- section (2) in respect of any income relating to 
the previous year in which such search was made or any earlier 
previous year-

<subsection><tid>369206</tid>
<number>a</number>for which he has failed to furnish a return under 
Section, 139 of the Income- tax Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>101459</tid>
<number>b</number>which he has failed to disclose in a return of income 
furnished by him under the Income- tax Act before the 
commencement of this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1489869</tid>
<number>c</number>which has escaped assessment by reason of the omission 
or failure on the part of such person to make a return under 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or the Income- 
tax Act, or to disclose fully and truly all material facts 
necessary for his assessment or otherwise,
then, notwithstanding anything contained in any of the Acts mentioned 
in sub- section (1) of section 8 or the Wealth- tax Act, the amount of 
income so declared or, as the case may be, the value of the assets 
representing such income, shall not be taken into account for the 
purposes of-


<subsubsection><tid>530188</tid>
<number>i</number>payment of interest by the declarant under sub- section 
 (8) of section 139 of the Income- tax Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>817779</tid>
<number>ii</number>payment of interest by the declarant Under section 215 
or section 217 of the Income- tax Act or the corresponding 
provisions of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>; (11 of <year>1922</year>.)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>266054</tid>
<number>iii</number>imposition of penalty on the declarant under the 
provisions of any of the said Acts, except under section 221 
of the Income- tax Act or the corresponding provisions of any 
of the other said Acts; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1597966</tid>
<number>iv</number>prosecution of the declarant under the provisions of 
any of the said Acts.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1582266</tid>
<number>2</number>The declaration under sub- section (1) shall be made to the 
Commissioner and shall be in such form and shall be verified in such 
manner as may be prescribed by rules made by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1362635</tid>
<number>3</number>A declaration under this section shall be signed by the 
person specified in sub- section (2) of section 4 as if the declaration 
had been made under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>1691086</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the declaration made by the declarant under sub- 
section (1) shall be forwarded by the Commissioner to the Income- tax 
Officer and the information contained therein may be taken into 
account for the purposes of the proceedings relating to assessment or 
reassessment of the income of the declarant under the provisions of 
any of the Acts mentioned in sub- section (1) of section 8 or the 
Wealth- tax Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1722200</tid>
<number>5</number>The immunity provided under sub- section (1) shall not be 
available to the declarant unless the tax chargeable in respect of the 
income of the previous year or years for which the declaration has 
been made is paid by the declarant in accordance with the provisions 
of section 5.
Explanation- 1.[ For the purposes of this sub- section and sub- 
section (5A) tax chargeable in respect of the income of any previous 
year for which the declaration is made shall be,-


<subsection><tid>42180</tid>
<number>a</number>where the declarant has not furnished a return in 
respect of the total income of that year and no assessment 
has, been made in respect of the total income of that year, 
the tax payable on the income declared under sub- section (1) 
for that year as if such income were the total income;-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292045</tid>
<number>b</number>where the declarant has furnished a return in respect 
of the total income of that year and no assessment has been 
made in pursuance of such return, the tax payable on the 
aggregate of the total income returned and the income 
declared under sub- section (1) for that year as if such 
aggregate were the total income, as reduced by the tax 
payable on the basis of the total income returned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1334210</tid>
<number>c</number>where an assessment in respect of the total income of 
that year has been made, the tax payable on the aggregate of 
the total income as assessed and the income declared under 
sub- section (1) for that year as if such aggregate were the 
total income, as reduced by the tax payable on the basis of 
the total income as assessed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>748836</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> A declarant who has not paid, in accordance with the 
provisions of section 5, the tax chargeable in respect of the income 
of the previous year or years for which the declaration has been made 
shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (5), be 
entitled to the immunity provided under sub- section (1) if, before the 
 1st day of January, <year>1978</year>, the declarant-

<subsection><tid>1782195</tid>
<number>i</number>pays the amount of such tax remaining unpaid; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>91309</tid>
<number>ii</number>pays simple interest at the rate of twelve per cent. 
per annum on the amount of such tax remaining unpaid on the 
 31st day of March, <year>1976</year>, from the 1st day of April, <year>1976</year> to 
the date of payment of such tax.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1263706</tid>
<number>5B</number>The provisions of the Income- tax Act and any rules made 
thereunder shall, so far as may be, apply to the interest payable 
under sub- section (5A) as if such interest were interest payable under 
sub- section (2) of section 220 of that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>326175</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any tax is paid by the declarant <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in accordance with 
the provisions of section 5, read with sub- section (5) or, as the case 
may be, in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (5A)"] credit 
therefor shall be given to the declarant in the assessment made under 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>.) or, as the case may be, 
the Income- tax Act, in respect of his total income of the previous 
year or years.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>345844</tid>
<number>7</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply in relation to any 
income which has been included in the total income of the declarant in 
any assessment made by the Income- tax Officer before the date on which 
the declaration under that sub- section is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>955239</tid>
<number> 15</number> Voluntary disclosure of wealth.
<section><tid>134455</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions  
of this section, where any person makes, on or after the date of 
commencement of this Act but before the 1st day of January, <year>1976</year>, a 
declaration in respect of-

<subsection><tid>676303</tid>
<number>a</number>the net wealth chargeable to wealth- tax for any 
assessment year for which he has failed to furnish a return 
under section 14 of the Wealth- tax Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1020967</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of the. assets which has not been disclosed, 
or the value of the assets which has been understated, in any 
return of net wealth for any assessment year,
then, notwithstanding anything contained in that Act, the net wealth, 
or, as the case may be, the value so declared shall not be taken into 
account for the purposes of any proceedings relating to imposition of 
penalty on the person making the declaration under this sub- section 
 (hereafter in this section referred to as the declarant) or for the 
purposes of the prosecution of the declarant under that Act:

Provided that-


<subsubsection><tid>498483</tid>
<number>i</number>nothing contained in clause (a) shall apply in relation 
to the net wealth assessable for any assessment year for 
which a notice under section 14 or section 17 of that Act has 
been served upon the declarant before the commencement of 
this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1054162</tid>
<number>ii</number>nothing contained in clause (b) shall apply in relation 
to so much of the value of such assets as has been assessed 
in any assessment for the relevant assessment year made by 
the Wealth- tax Officer before the date on which the 
declaration under this sub- section is made.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>708554</tid>
<number>2</number>The declaration under sub- section (1) shall be made to the 
Commissioner and shall be in such form and shall be verified in such 
manner is may be prescribed by rules made by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>456857</tid>
<number>3</number>A declaration under sub- section (7) shall be signed by the 
person specified in sub- section (2) of section 4 as if the declaration 
had been made under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>1207069</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the declaration made by the declarant under sub- 
section (1) shall be forwarded by the Commissioner to the Wealth- tax 
Officer and the information contained therein may be taken into 
account for the purposes of the proceedings relating to assessment or 
reassessment of the net wealth of the declarant under the provisions 
of the Wealth- tax Act.

</section>

<section><tid>267334</tid>
<number>5</number>The immunity provided under sub- section (1) shall not be 
available to the declarant unless the wealth- tax chargeable in respect 
of the net wealth for the assessment year or years for which the 
declaration has been made is paid by the declarant in accordance with 
the provisions of section 5 and the declarant invests in the 
securities referred to in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sub- section (3) of section 3 within the time specified in sub- section 
 (4) of section 5 the sum specified in sub- section (6) of this section.

Explanation- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the purposes of this sub- section and sub- 
section (5A) wealth- tax chargeable in respect of the net wealth for 
any assessment year for which the declaration is made shall be-


<subsection><tid>1761922</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case falling under clause (a) of sub- section (1), 
the wealth- tax payable in respect of the net wealth declared 
under that clause for that year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>883411</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case falling under clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1),--

<subsubsection><tid>499499</tid>
<number>i</number>where no assessment has been made in pursuance of the 
return of net wealth furnished by the declarant, the wealth- 
tax payable on the aggregate of the net wealth returned and 
the value declared under that clause for that year as if such 
aggregate were the net wealth, as reduced by the wealth- tax 
payable on the basis of the net wealth returned;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>448291</tid>
<number>ii</number>where an assessment has been made in pursuance of the 
return of net wealth furnished by the declarant, the wealth- 
tax payable on the aggregate of the net wealth as assessed 
and the value declared under that clause for that year as if 
such aggregate were the net wealth, as reduced by the wealth- 
tax payable on the net wealth as assessed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>899562</tid>
<number>5A</number>A declarant--

<subsection><tid>633226</tid>
<number>a</number>who has not paid, in accordance with the provisions of 
section 5, the wealth- tax chargeable in respect of the net 
wealth for the assessment year or years for which the 
declaration has been made; of (b) who has not invested in the 
securities referred to in sub- section of section 3 within the 
time specified in subsection (4) of section 5 the sum 
specified in sub- section (6); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>589771</tid>
<number>c</number>who has neither so paid such wealth- tax nor so invested 
such sum,
shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section 
 (5), be entitled to the immunity provided under sub- section 
 (1), if the declarant-


<subsubsection><tid>1792559</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case falling under clause (a), Pays before 
the 1st day of January, <year>1978</year> (hereafter in this sub-  
  section referred to as the said date) the amount of such 
wealth- tax remaining unpaid and also simple interest at 
the rate of twelve per cent. per annum on the amount of 
such wealth- tax remaining unpaid on the 31st day of 
March, <year>1976</year>, from the 1ST clay of April, <year>1976</year> to the 
date of payment of such wealth- tax;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>997464</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case falling under clause (b), invests before 
the said date in the securities aforesaid the sum 
specified in sub- section (6) or, as the case may be, the 
amount which falls short of the sum required to be 
invested;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1078723</tid>
<number>iii</number>in a case falling under clause (c), pays before 
the said date the amount of such wealth- tax remaining 
unpaid and also simple interest at the rate of twelve 
per cent. per annum. on the amount of wealth- tax 
remaining unpaid on the 31st day of March, <year>1976</year>, from 
the 1st day of April, <year>1976</year> to the date of payment of 
such wealth- tax and invests before the said date in the 
securities aforesaid the sum specified in sub- section 
 (6) or, as the case may be, the amount which falls short 
of the sum required to be invested.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1738652</tid>
<number>5B</number>The provisions of the Wealth- tax Act and any ruler, made 
thereunder shall, so far as may be, apply to the interest payable 
under sub- section (5A) as if such interest were interest payable under 
sub- section (2) of section 31 of the Wealth- tax Act.

</section>

<section><tid>516128</tid>
<number>6</number>The sum referred to in sub- section (5), shall be,-

<subsection><tid>1133344</tid>
<number>a</number>where the declaration has been made in respect of one 
assessment year, a sum equal to two and a half per cent. of 
the amount of net wealth declared under clause (a) of sub- 
section (1), Or, as the case may be, the value declared under 
clause (b) of that sub- section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979538</tid>
<number>b</number>where the declaration has been made in respect of more 
than one assessment year, a sum equal to two and a half per 
cent of the net wealth declared under clause (a) of sub- 
section (1), or, as the case may be, the value declared under 
clause (b) of that subsection, in respect of the last of such 
assessment years.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>49609</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any wealth- tax is paid by the declarant for any 
assessment year credit therefor shall be given to the declarant 
1.[" in accordance with the provisions of section 5, read with sub- 
section (5) or, as the case may be, in accordance with the provisions 
of sub- section (5A)"] credit therefor shall be given to the declarant 
in the assessment made under the Wealth- tax Act for that year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1394061</tid>
<number> 16</number> 
<section><tid>1945845</tid>
<number>1</number>Immunity from penalty, prosecution, etc., under certain  
Acts. Where-

<subsection><tid>1943191</tid>
<number>a</number>the voluntarily disclosed income declared under sub- 
section (1) of section 3 or any part thereof, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1102072</tid>
<number>b</number>the net wealth, or the assets the value whereof is, 
declared under sub- section (1) of section 15 or any part of 
such net wealth or assets,
is or are represented by gold, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained In the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>.) or the Gold (Control) 
Act, such gold shall not be liable to confiscation under either of the 
said Acts and the person making the declaration shall not be liable to 
imposition of any penalty


<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

or infliction of any punishment under either of the said Acts for any 
act or omission in relation to such gold, if he fulfils the following 
conditions, namely:-


<subsubsection><tid>1524340</tid>
<number>A</number>in a case where the gold is owned, possessed, held or 
controlled by the person making the declaration (such gold  
being owned, possessed, held or controlled by him in his 
  capacity as a licensed dealer), necessary entries are made by 
him in the accounts, registers and documents maintained under 
the Gold (Control) Act, under intimation to the Gold Control 
Officer of the rank of an Assistant Collector of Central 
Excise or of Customs before the 1st day of February, <year>1976</year> and 
such other steps as are necessary for him to comply with the 
requirements of that Act in relation to such gold are taken 
by him before that date;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>827444</tid>
<number>B</number>in any other case,-

<subsubsubsection><tid>1101425</tid>
<number>i</number>where the gold is an article or ornament or both 
and the weight of such article or ornament, or the 
aggregate weight of both, together with the weight of 
any other gold (being an article or ornament) owned, 
possessed, held or controlled by him, exceeds the limits 
specified in sub- section (5) of section 16 of the Gold 
 (Control) Act, such article or ornament or both, as the 
case may be, is or are declared in the form prescribed 
under sub- section (1), and in the manner specified in 
subsection (8), of that section before the 1st day of 
February, <year>1976</year>;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>175245</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the gold is primary gold, such gold is 
either sold to any licensed dealer under intimation to 
the Gold Control Officer of the rank of an Assistant 
Collector of Central Excise or of Customs before the 
1st' day of February, <year>1976</year> or is made into ornaments and 
a declaration in this behalf is made in the form 
prescribed under subsection (1), and in the manner 
specified in sub- section (8), of section 16 of the Gold 
 (Control) Act, before that date.

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1561321</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Gold (Control) 
Act, any primary gold referred to in sub- clause (ii) of clause (B) of 
sub- section (1) may be sold by the person making the declaration to 
any licensed dealer and such licensed dealer may purchase such gold, 
provided that the total quantity of primary gold (not being in the  
  form of standard gold bars) in the possession or custody of such 
dealer and the quantity of primary gold (not being in the form of  
  standard gold bars) to be so purchased does not exceed the limit 
specified in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c) or, as the case 
may be, clause (d) of the proviso to sub- section (1) of section 32 of 
that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1565718</tid>
<number>3</number>Mere a declaration is made under sub- clause (i) or sub- 
clause (ii) of clause (B) of sub- section (1), the provisions of 
section 16 of the Gold (Control) Act, shall, so far as may be, apply 
as if such declaration were a declaration made under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>1141843</tid>
<number>4</number>The immunity provided under sub- section (1) shall, in a case 
where the person making the declaration is a firm, also extend to the 
partners of the firm.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1710010</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall apply in relation to any gold,-

<subsection><tid>1787435</tid>
<number>a</number>which has been seized or confiscated under the Customs 
Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>.) or the Gold (Control) Act, before the 
declaration under sub- section (1) of section 3 or, as the 
case may be, under sub- section (1) of section 15, is made; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>903857</tid>
<number>b</number>which is seized as a result of any search made under 
either of the said Acts where such search had commenced 
before such declaration IS made; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517143</tid>
<number>c</number>in respect of which any other proceedings under either 
of the said Acts are pending before any authority before such 
declaration is made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>816443</tid>
<number>6</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that 
nothing in this section shall be construed as exempting any person 
from discharging any obligation under the Gold (Control) Act, on or 
After the 1st day of February, <year>1976</year> in relation to the gold referred 
to in this section.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expressions 
" article"," gold"," Gold Control Officer"," licensed dealer", 
" ornament"," primary gold" and" standard gold bar" shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Gold (Control) Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>721323</tid>
<number>17</number>Applicability of certain provisions of Income tax Act and of 
Chapter V of Wealth tax Act. The provisions of Chapter XV of the 
Income- tax Act relating to liability in special cases and of section 
 189 of that Act or of Chapter V of the Wealth- tax Act relating to 
liability to assessment in special cases shall, so far as may be, 
apply in relation to proceedings under this Act as they apply in 
relation to proceedings under the Income- tax Act or, as the case may 
be, the Wealth- tax Act.


</article>



<article><tid>36228</tid>
<number> 18</number> Removal of doubts. For the removal of doubts, it is hereby 
declared that, save as otherwise expressly provided in the Explanation 
to sub- section
<section><tid>395145</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 13 and in sub- section (4) of section 16,  
nothing contained in this Act shall be construed as conferring any 
benefit, concession or immunity on any person other than the person 
making the declaration under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>990051</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>296500</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1066256</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>173808</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1633386</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, by notification in  
the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1263541</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for,-

<subsection><tid>1050871</tid>
<number>a</number>the form in which a declaration may be made under sub- 
section (1) of section 3 and the manner in which it may be 
verified,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>93317</tid>
<number>b</number>the form in which a declaration may be made under sub- 
section (1) of section 14 and the manner in which it may 
be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549899</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which a declaration may be made under sub- 
section (1) of section 15 and the manner in which it may 
be verified.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1979160</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under 
this Act to be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre- 
viously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>463493</tid>
<number> 21</number> Provisions of Act not to apply to certain persons. The 
provisions of this Act shall not apply to any person in respect of 
whom an order of detention has been made under the Conservation of 
Foreign Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling Activities Act, <year>1974</year>: (52  
  of <year>1974</year>.)
Provided that-

<section><tid>161067</tid>
<number>i</number>such order of detention, being an order to which, the 
provisions of section 9 or section 12A of the said Act do not 
apply, has not been revoked on the report of the Advisory 
Board under section 8 of the said Act or before the receipt 
of the report of the Advisory Board; or

</section>

<section><tid>1575193</tid>
<number>ii</number>such order of detention, being an order to which the 
provisions of section 9 of the said Act apply, has not been 
revoked before the expiry of the time for, or on the basis 
of, the review' under sub- section (3) of section 9, or on the 
report of the Advisory Board under section 8, read with sub- 
section (2) of section 9, of the said Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>985942</tid>
<number>iii</number>such order of detention, being an order to which the 
provisions of section 12A of the said Act apply, has not been 
revoked before the expiry of the time for, or on the basis 
of, the first review under sub- section (3) of that section, 
or on the basis of the report of the Advisory Board under 
section 8, read with sub- section (6) of section 12A, of the 
said Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1829117</tid>
<number>iv</number>such order of detention has not been set aside by a 
court of competent jurisdiction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030405</tid>
<number> 22</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>727870</tid>
<number>1</number>The Voluntary Disclosure of Income and  
Wealth Ordinance, <year>1975</year> (15 of <year>1975</year>.) and the Voluntary Disclosure of 
Income and Wealth (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>1975</year> (23 of <year>1975</year>.) are hereby 
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1198838</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Voluntary Disclosure of Income and Wealth Ordinance, 
 <year>1975</year> (15 of <year>1975</year>.) as amended by the Voluntary Disclosure of Income 
and Wealth (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>1975</year> (23 of <year>1975</year>.) shall be deemed 
to have been done or taken under the corresponding provision of this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1994388</tid>
<number>3</number>Where during the period commencing on the 8th October, <year>1975</year> 
and ending with the 28th November, <year>1975</year> any person had furnished 
security in accordance with sub- section (3) of section 5 of the 
Voluntary Disclosure of Income and Wealth Ordinance, <year>1975</year> as it stood 
immediately before its amendment by the Voluntary Disclosure of Income 
and Wealth (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>1975</year>, (15 of <year>1975</year>.) such person 
shall be deemed to have furnished adequate security for the purposes 
of sub- section (2) of section 5 of this Act. (23 of <year>1975</year>.)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>