<act><title>


The Bureau of Indian Standards (Recognition of 
    Consumers’ Associations) Rules, 19911</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Bureau of Indian Standards (Recognition of 
    Consumers’ Associations) Rules, 1991.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette. 


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    ‘Act’ means the Bureau of Indian 
    Standards Act, 1986 (63 of 1986);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    ‘Form’ means a Form appended to 
    the Schedule to these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    ‘Ministry’ means the Ministry of 
    Civil Supplies, Consumer Affairs and Public Distribution; and  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    ‘Principal Officer’in relation to 
    a consumer association means any individual who is specifically authorised 
    in writing or by means of a resolution adopted by such consumer association 
    in that behalf.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Application for recognition of consumers association.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every consumers association which is desirous of being recognised as a 
    registered consumers association,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    shall have not less than fifty 
    consumers as its members; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    shall make an application for 
    such recognition in triplicate to the Bureau of Indian Standards in Form I.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every application made under sub-rule (1), shall be accompanied by a bank 
    draft of rupees one thousand.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    receipt of an application made under sub-rule (1), the Bureau of Indian 
    Standards shall note thereon the date of its receipt and shall forthwith 
    communicate such date to the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Bureau of Indian Standards may, before issue of a certificate of 
    recognition, require the applicant to furnish, within such period as may be 
    specified by it, such additional information as may be considered necessary 
    within a period of 30 days of the receipt of that letter by the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On 
    receipt of an application and such other additional information as may be 
    sought under sub-rule (4), the Bureau of Indian Standards shall process the 
    application and forward the documents to the Ministry of Civil Supplies, 
    Government of India with its recommendations for their consideration.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> On 
    receipt of the recommendations of the Bureau under sub-rule (5), the 
    Ministry shall consider those recommendations and after satisfying itself 
    that the applicant association is fit to be recognised, may recognise the 
    association in this behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    certificate of recognition to be issued by the Ministry under sub-rule (6) 
    shall be in Form II.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Where a certificate of recognition issued under these rules is lost, 
    destroyed or mutilated, a duplicate may be issued on an application made in 
    this behalf and on payment of a fee of rupees one hundred.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Payment of fees.—The 
    fees payable under those rules shall be paid in the form of a bank draft in 
    favour of the Bureau of Indian Standards, New Delhi.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Refusal to grant certificate of recognition to consumer association.—Where 
    a certificate of recognition of a consumers association has been refused, 
    the applicant shall be informed of the reasons for such refusal by the 
    Bureau.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Copies of certificate of recognition to be furnished to certain authorities.—Every 
    consumer association which has been recognised as a ‘registered consumers’ 
    association under these rules, shall furnish a copy of the certificate of 
    recognition issued to it while filing a complaint under section 34
<section><number>1</number> of the 
    Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Verification of application.—Every 
    application made under these rules shall be duly verified by the principal 
    officer.  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Bureau of Indian Standards (Recognition of Consumers’ Associations) Rules, 
    1991
 



 



Form I
 


[See sub-rule (1) of rule 3]
 



    Form of application to be submitted to the Bureau of  

    Indian Standards for recognition of consumers’  

    association (to be submitted in triplicate).
 


(1)   Name of the consumers’ association:
 


(2)   Address:
 


(a)   Registered Office:
 


(b)   For correspondence:
 


(c)   Branches:
 


(3)   If registered under section 25 of the 
    Companies Act, 1986, the date of registration:
 


(4)   If registered under any other law, the 
    Act under which registered and date of registration:
 


       
    (certified copy of the certificate of registration to be enclosed)
 


(5)   Total number of members of the 
    association (as on date of application):
 


(6)   Objects of the association (certified 
    copy of Memorandum of Association to be enclosed along with copy of the 
    rules and regulations of the association)
 


(7)   Names, addresses and occupations of 
    persons on the Board of Directors, Governing Body, Council/Committee (by 
    whatever name called), to whom the management of the affairs of the 
    association is entrusted:
 


(8)   Number of employees:
 


(a)   Whole-time
 


(b)   Part-time
 


(9)   Year-wise details of the work done by 
    the association during the last three years in the field of protection of 
    consumers’ interest
 


(10)   Copies of published annual report and 
    audited accounts of the association for the last three years
 


(11)   Details of Laboratory organisation, if 
    any, owned, run or operated by the association for purposes of protection of 
    consumer’s interest
 


Place...........    
    Signature..........................
 


Date.............   Name and Designation.
 


Verification
 


I,...............................,do hereby 
    solemnly state that what is stated in items I to II above is true to the 
    best of my knowledge and belief.
 


Place.............  
 


Date..............  
 


Signature........................
 


Name and Designation.
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Bureau of Indian Standards (Recognition of Consumers’ Associations) Rules, 
    1991
 



 



    Form II
 


[See sub-rule (7) of rule 3]
 



    Certificate of Recognition
 



    Government of India
 



    Ministry of Civil Supplies, Consumer Affairs and Public Distribution
 

 
 


Certified that the consumers’ association 
    whose particulars are given below, has, this day, been recognised as 
    “registered consumers’ association” in terms of section 34 of the Bureau of 
    Indian Standard Act, 1986 (63 of 1986).
 


Particulars
 


(1)  Name of the Consumers’ Association:
 


(2)  Address:
 


(3)  Name of persons on the governing 
    board/body/council                  

      to whom management of the Association is 
    entrusted:
 


(4)  Number of members:
 


(5)  Registration number:
 

 
 


Signature........................
 


Date...............................
 


File No..........................
 


Seal of the Ministry of Civil 
    Supplies,             

    Consumer Affairs and Public Distribution.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>