<act><tid>102428</tid>
<title>THE HAJ COMMITTEE ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 51 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 17th December, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to establish a Committee in the Port of Bombay for assisting 
Muslim pilgrims to Saudi Arabia, Syria, Iraq, Iran and Jordan and for 
matters connected therewith.





<article><tid>1655886</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Haj Committee Act, 
<year>1959</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1483318</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>956557</tid>
<number>a</number>" Committee" means the Haj Committee constituted under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>790440</tid>
<number>b</number>" pilgrim" means a Muslim proceeding on or returning from 
pilgrimage to Saudi Arabia, Syria, Iraq, Iran or 
Jordan;

</section>

<section><tid>1691824</tid>
<number>c</number>" pilgrim ship" means a ship conveying or about to convey 
pilgrims from or to the port of Bombay to or from any 
port in the Red Sea other than Suez;

</section>

<section><tid>889739</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1058988</tid>
<number> 3</number> Incorporation of Haj Committee.
<section><tid>1171571</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date  
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a 
Committee by the name of the Haj Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1345733</tid>
<number>2</number>The said Committee shall be a body corporate having perpetual 
succession and a common seal and shall by the said name sue and be 
sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>552823</tid>
<number> 4</number> Composition of the Committee.
<section><tid>1728409</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall consist  
of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1374428</tid>
<number>a</number>the Collector of Customs, Bombay, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>754484</tid>
<number>b</number>the Chairman, Port Trust, Bombay, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1856419</tid>
<number>c</number>the Principal Officer, Mercantile Marine Department, 
Bombay, ex officio;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>630</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>335313</tid>
<number>d</number>the Commissioner of Police for Greater Bombay, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>280436</tid>
<number>e</number>the Municipal Commissioner, Greater Bombay, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>746186</tid>
<number>f</number>the Port Health Officer, Bombay, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985436</tid>
<number>g</number>two members to be nominated by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>309186</tid>
<number>h</number>three members of Parliament of whom two are to be 
nominated by the Speaker of the House of the People 
from among its members and one by the Chairman of the 
Council of States from among its members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1067552</tid>
<number>i</number>one member to represent the State Government of 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Maharashtra] to be nominated by that Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1280430</tid>
<number>j</number>two members of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Maharashtra] State Legislative 
Assembly to be nominated by the Speaker of that 
Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>50296</tid>
<number>k</number>two members of the Municipal Corporation of Greater 
Bombay to be nominated by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State Government of 
Maharashtra] on the recommendation of the Muslim 
members of the Municipal Corporation of Greater Bombay;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>235220</tid>
<number>l</number>three members, of whom two shall be Shia Muslims, to be 
co- opted by all the members of the Committee to 
represent such interests as, in their opinion, are 
directly and actively interested in the welfare of the 
pilgrims.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>171539</tid>
<number>2</number>Every nomination under this section shall take effect as soon 
as it is notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746194</tid>
<number> 5</number> Nomination and co- option of members.
<section><tid>1601831</tid>
<number>1</number>The members of the  
Committee shall be nominated or co- opted in such manner as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1862114</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the nomination of the members of the 
Committee and the co- option of the members referred to in clause (l) 
of sub- section (1) of section 4, the Central Government shall publish 
in the Official Gazette a list of the names of all members nominated 
and co- opted:
Provided that the failure to co- opt a member shall not prevent 
the Central Government from making nominations or from publishing the 
list of members as provided in this sub- section:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>631</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Bombay Reorganisation (Adaptation of Laws on Union  
  Subjects) Order, <year>1961</year>, for" Bombay" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1960</year>) 
2. Subs., ibid., for" State Government of Bombay" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1960</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided further that the list of members of a new Committee 
shall not be published before the expiry of three years from the date 
of the publication of the list of members of the Committee which it is 
replacing.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>229200</tid>
<number> 6</number> Chairman and Vice- Chairmen.
<section><tid>581013</tid>
<number>1</number>After the publication of the  
list of members of the Committee under sub- section (2) of section 5, 
the Central Government shall direct the Committee to elect one of its 
members to be the Chairman within such time as may be specified in the 
direction.

</section>

<section><tid>427778</tid>
<number>2</number>If within the time so specified the Committee fails to elect 
a Chairman, the Central Government may appoint a member of the 
Committee to be the Chairman thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>389365</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1878208</tid>
<number>4</number>The Committee shall elect from among its members not more 
than two members to be Vice- Chairmen who shall exercise such powers 
and discharge such duties as may be determined by bye- laws made in 
this behalf by the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>546463</tid>
<number>5</number>The appointment or election of the Chairman and the Vice- 
Chairmen shall be notified by the Central Government in the Official 
Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>916229</tid>
<number>7</number>Term of office. The term of office of the members of the 
Committee (other than the ex officio members and members filling  
  casual vacancies) shall be not less than three years, commencing on 
the day following the publication of the list of members under sub- 
section (2) of section 5, and ending on the date of the publication of 
the list of members of the next Committee.


</article>



<article><tid>1542686</tid>
<number> 8</number> Constitution of new Committees.
<section><tid>1137211</tid>
<number>1</number>At such time as the  
Central Government may deem to be expedient before or after the expiry 
of the period of three years after the publication of the list of 
members of a Committee under sub- section (2) of section 5, the Central 
Government shall take or cause to be taken all necessary steps for the 
nomination and co- option of members of the new Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>216506</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be ineligible for nomination or co- option to 
the new Committee on the ground that he is or has been a member of the 
Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>204069</tid>
<number> 9</number> Duties of Committee.
<section><tid>822693</tid>
<number>1</number>The duties of the Committee shall be- 

<subsection><tid>1695293</tid>
<number>a</number>to collect and disseminate information useful to 
pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1432754</tid>
<number>b</number>to advise and assist pilgrims during their stay in the 
city and the port of Bombay, while proceeding on or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>632</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

returning from pilgrimage, in all matters including 
vaccination, inoculation, medical inspection and issue 
of passes and passports, and to co- operate with the 
local authorities concerned in such matters;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1908160</tid>
<number>c</number>to give relief to indigent pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135681</tid>
<number>d</number>to negotiate and co- operate with railways, shipping 
companies, airways and travel agencies for the purpose 
of securing travelling facilities for pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>596753</tid>
<number>e</number>to find suitable guides for employment by shipping 
companies on pilgrim ships;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>966878</tid>
<number>f</number>to bring the grievances of pilgrims and any 
irregularities or omissions on the part of a master or 
owner of a pilgrim ship in carrying out the provisions 
of the Indian Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1923</year> (21 of  
  <year>1923</year>), to the notice of the authorities concerned, and 
to suggest remedies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1477589</tid>
<number>g</number>to appoint a pilgrim as" Amirul- Haj" on board a pilgrim 
ship to represent the grievances of the pilgrims to the 
master or owner of the ship;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>829938</tid>
<number>h</number>generally to look after the welfare of the pilgrims; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1369737</tid>
<number>i</number>to discharge such other duties in connection with 
pilgrim traffic as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>576943</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall afford all reasonable assistance 
to the Committee in the discharge of the duties imposed by this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>444563</tid>
<number> 10</number> Meetings of Committee.
<section><tid>21983</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall meet at least  
once in every month during the four months before the Haj Day and 
during the two months after the Haj Day, and at least once in three 
months during the rest of the year.

</section>

<section><tid>1207087</tid>
<number>2</number>The number of members required to make a quorum at any 
meeting shall be six.

</section>

<section><tid>589527</tid>
<number>3</number>All matters shall be decided by a majority of votes of the 
members present, and in the event of an equality of votes, the 
Chairman or other person presiding shall have a casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>820341</tid>
<number>11</number>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts or proceedings of the 
Committee. No act or proceeding of the Committee shall be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy among its members or any 
defect in the constitution thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>633</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1695841</tid>
<number> 12</number> Executive officer and other employees.
<section><tid>1583414</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, in consultation with the Committee, appoint a person 
to be the Executive Officer thereof who shall also be the Secretary to 
the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1562761</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall, subject to the approval of the Central 
Government, appoint such other employees as it may consider necessary 
for the efficient discharge of its duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>540879</tid>
<number> 13</number> Sub- committees and inspection of pilgrim ships.
<section><tid>916539</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Committee shall appoint one or more sub- committees consisting of such 
number of its members as it thinks fit for the inspection of pilgrim 
ships.

</section>

<section><tid>434614</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such sub- committee when inspecting a pilgrim ship shall 
be accompanied by the certifying officer appointed for the port under 
section 151 of the Indian Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1923</year> (21 of <year>1923</year>), 
or by the Surveyor of the ship or other person deputed by the 
certifying officer.

</section>

<section><tid>560520</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Officer of the Committee, or a sub- committee 
appointed under sub- section (1) may enter and inspect any pilgrim ship 
advertised or offering to sail from, or which has returned to, the 
port of Bombay.

</section>

<section><tid>70142</tid>
<number>4</number>A master or any officer of a pilgrim ship who fails to render 
reasonable facilities for such inspection shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>886469</tid>
<number>5</number>No Magistrate other than a Presidency Magistrate or 
Magistrate of the first class shall take cognizance of an offence 
punishable under sub- section (4), and such Magistrate shall take 
cognizance of such offence only on written complaint by the Chairman 
of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1487911</tid>
<number>6</number>The Committee may also appoint other sub- committees for such 
purposes as it may think fit and any such sub- committee shall consist 
of such number of members and other persons as may be determined by 
bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>93081</tid>
<number> 14</number> Haj Fund. The Committee shall have its own Fund to be called 
the Haj Fund, and there shall be placed to the credit thereof the 
following sums, namely:--
<section><tid>1382323</tid>
<number>a</number>the interest on all deposits made by pilgrims under 
clause (b) of section 208A of the Indian Merchant 
Shipping Act, <year>1923</year> (21 of <year>1923</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>322011</tid>
<number>b</number>the fees charged for the registration of pilgrim passes 
in pursuance of any rule made under section 213 of the 
Indian Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1923</year> (21 of <year>1923</year>);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>634</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1267384</tid>
<number>c</number>the sums realised from the sale of the effects of 
deceased pilgrims and sums of money left by deceased 
pilgrims, which are unclaimed and have lapsed to the 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1228865</tid>
<number>d</number>any fees which may be levied for the issue of visitors' 
passes to friends and relations of pilgrims who desire 
to go on board a pilgrim ship;

</section>

<section><tid>888256</tid>
<number>e</number>the amount standing at the commencement of this Act to 
the credit of the Fund known as the Indigent Pilgrims 
Fund:
Provided that such amount shall be applied by the 
Committee solely for the relief of indigent pilgrims;


</section>

<section><tid>1636774</tid>
<number>f</number>any sums received by the Haj Fund from private sources; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>120182</tid>
<number>g</number>any sums allotted by the Central Government or any State 
Government to the Haj Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>922740</tid>
<number>15</number>Vesting of property in the Committee. All property, assets 
and funds owned or acquired, before the establishment of the Committee 
under this Act, by the Port Haj Committee of Calcutta and the Port Haj 
Committee of Bombay constituted under the Port Haj Committees Act, 
 <year>1932</year> (20 of <year>1932</year>), shall, on such establishment, vest in the Committee 
and form part of the Haj Fund referred to in section 14.


</article>



<article><tid>415715</tid>
<number> 16</number> Application of the Haj Fund. The Haj Fund shall, subject to 
any rules that may be made under this Act, be under the control and 
management of the Committee, and shall be applied to the following 
purposes, namely:--
<section><tid>926556</tid>
<number>a</number>pay and allowances of the Executive Officer and other 
employees of the Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>425133</tid>
<number>b</number>payment of charges and expenses incidental to the 
objects specified in section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>1341701</tid>
<number>c</number>any other object specified in the rules made under 
section 17.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1135478</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>253546</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1395004</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>154577</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of nomination and co- option of members of the 
Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221781</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualifications for being chosen as, or for being, 
members of the Committee;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>635</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225014</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which doubts and disputes relating to co- 
option of members may be determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1554470</tid>
<number>d</number>the filling up of casual vacancies in the office of the 
Chairman and other members of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>606503</tid>
<number>e</number>the removal of the Chairman and other members of the 
Committee and their resignation from office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>505168</tid>
<number>f</number>the term of office of the Chairman and his powers and 
duties;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>377732</tid>
<number>g</number>the duties which may be entrusted to the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1752683</tid>
<number>h</number>the powers and duties of the Executive Officer and the 
conditions of service of the Executive Officer and 
other employees of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>277239</tid>
<number>i</number>the custody of the Haj Fund and the investment of 
balances therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866998</tid>
<number>j</number>the objects for which the Haj Fund may be applied;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>196669</tid>
<number>k</number>the limit of expenditure which may be incurred by the 
Committee without sanction of the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1340404</tid>
<number>l</number>the accounts to be kept by the Committee and the audit 
of such accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1999615</tid>
<number>m</number>the preparation, submission and approval of the budget 
of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>529806</tid>
<number>n</number>the returns, statements and reports to be submitted by 
the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1616156</tid>
<number>o</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1560461</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1559258</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to make bye- laws.
<section><tid>600213</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may make bye- laws  
not inconsistent with this Act or the rules made thereunder--

<subsection><tid>22982</tid>
<number>a</number>prescribing the manner of election of the Vice- Chairmen;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1048992</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribing the term of office and the powers and duties 
of the Vice- Chairmen;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>636</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for certain words (w. e. f.  
  15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>939440</tid>
<number>c</number>regulating the removal or resignation of a Vice- Chairman 
and the filling up of casual vacancies in the office of 
Vice- Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1989031</tid>
<number>d</number>regulating the convening of the meetings of the 
Committee and the conduct of business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1466852</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribing the registers and records to be maintained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>136994</tid>
<number>f</number>providing for the publication of its proceedings and any 
matter of interest to pilgrims; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>999112</tid>
<number>g</number>providing for any other matter which the Committee deems 
necessary for giving effect to the provisions of this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1013312</tid>
<number>2</number>Bye- laws made by the Committee under this section shall be 
submitted to the Central Government and shall not take effect until 
they have been confirmed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>141918</tid>
<number>3</number>Bye- laws which have been confirmed by the Central Government 
shall be published in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1922999</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every bye- law made under this section shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the bye- law or both Houses agree that the bye- law 
should not be made, the bye- law shall thereafter have effect only in 
such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that bye- 
law.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643606</tid>
<number> 19</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>805857</tid>
<number>1</number>The Port Haj Committees Act, <year>1932</year> (20   
  of <year>1932</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>839319</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, the Port Haj Committee of Bombay 
constituted under the said Act shall, until the establishment of the 
Committee under this Act, continue to function as if this Act had not 
been passed and on such establishment of the Committee, the Port Haj 
Committee of Bombay shall stand dissolved.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>637</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>