<act><title>THE NATIONAL 
      BANK FOR AGRICULTURE AND RURAL DEVELOPMENT GENERAL REGULATIONS, 
      19821</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title 
      and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
      regulations may be called the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural 
      Development General Regulations, 1982. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall 
      come into force on the 12th July, 1982.
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> 
      Definitions.—In these 
      regulations, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or 
      context,—  
 <section><number>a</number>    
      ‘Act’ means the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development Act, 
      1981 (61 of 1981);  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    
      ‘section’ means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>    
      other expressions used and not defined in these regulations but used in 
      the Act have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Meetings of 
      the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
      shall ordinarily meet once a quarter in each year.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Meetings of 
      the Board shall be convened by the Chairman, and, in his absence, by the 
      Managing Director and shall be ordinarily held at Bombay but if so 
      directed by the Board, may be held at any other place in India.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any five 
      Directors may, for the purpose of the consideration of the business to be 
      specified in their requisition, require the Chairman to convene a meeting 
      of the Board and the Chairman shall, on receipt of such requisition, 
      convene a meeting of the Board giving sufficient notice:  
 Provided that the 
      date of the meeting so convened shall not be later than 21 days from the 
      date of the requisition.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> Except in 
      respect of the first meeting of the Board, ordinarily not less than one 
      clear fortnight’s notice shall be given of each meeting of the Board and 
      such notice shall be sent to every Director to his registered address. 
      Should it be found necessary to convene an emergency meeting, a notice of 
      not less than seven days shall be given to every Director who is at that 
      time in India, to enable him to attend.  
 </section><section><number>5</number> No business 
      other than that for which the meeting was convened shall be discussed at a 
      meeting of the Board, except with the consent of the Chairman of the 
      meeting and a majority of the Directors present, unless one clear week’s 
      notice has been given of the same in writing to the Chairman.  
 </section><section><number>6</number> Six Directors 
      shall form a quorum for the transaction of the business at a meeting of 
      the Board.  
 </section><section><number>7</number> A copy of the 
      proceedings of each meeting of the Board shall be circulated for the 
      information of the Directors as soon as possible after the minutes of that 
      meeting are signed by the Chairman.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Fees for 
      Directors.—The Director not 
      being a Managing Director or a whole-time Director, or an officer of 
      Government or of the Reserve Bank of India shall be paid fees by the 
      National Bank as follows:—  
 <section><number>a</number>    
      For attending meetings of the Board.—Rs. 200 for each 
      meeting.  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    
      For attending to any other work for the National Bank.—Such sum as 
      the Board may fix from time to time having regard to the nature and amount 
      of work involved.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Payment of 
      travelling and halting allowances to Directors.—In addition to 
      the fees to which a Director may be entitled under regulation 4, every 
      such Director travelling in connection with the work of the National Bank 
      shall be reimbursed his travelling and halting expenses if any, on such 
      basis as may be fixed from time to time by the Central Government after 
      consultation with the Reserve Bank.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Resolution 
      without meeting valid.—A resolution in 
      writing circulated to all the Directors in India and approved and signed 
      by a majority of such Directors who are then in India, one of whom shall 
      be the Chairman, shall be valid and effectual and shall be deemed to be 
      the resolution passed by the Board on the date on which it is approved and 
      signed by the last signatory to the resolution:  
 Provided that may 
      resolution passed as aforesaid shall be placed before the next meeting of 
      the Board.  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Manner and 
      form in which contracts binding on the National Bank may be 
      executed.—
<section><number>1</number> Contracts on 
      behalf of the National Bank may be made as follows:—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>    
      Any contract which, if made between private persons, would by law be 
      required to be in writing and signed by the parties to be charged 
      therewith, may be made on behalf of the National Bank in writing and 
      signed by any person acting under its authority, express or implied, and 
      may in the same manner be varied or discharged.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    
      Any contract, which, if made between private persons, would by law be 
      valid although made by parol only and not reduced in writing may be made 
      by parol on behalf of the National Bank by any person acting under its 
      authority, express or implied, and may in the same manner be varied or 
      discharged.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> All contracts 
      made according to the provisions of this regulation shall be effectual in 
      law and shall bind the National Bank and all other parties thereto and 
      their legal representatives.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Accounts, 
      Receipts and Documents of the National Bank by whom to be 
      signed.—The Chairman, 
      the Managing Director, any whole-time Director and such officers of the 
      National Bank or such other persons as the Board may authorise in this 
      behalf by notification in the Gazette of India are hereby severally 
      empowered for and on behalf of the National Bank to execute lease, deeds, 
      transfer, conveyances, charges and other deeds relating to or affecting 
      rights to or in immovable property, to endorse and transfer promissory 
      notes, stock-receipts, stocks, debentures, shares, securities and 
      documents of title to goods, standing in the name of or held by the 
      National Bank, and to draw, accept and endorse bills or exchange and other 
      instruments in the current and authorised business of the National Bank 
      and to sign all other accounts, receipts and documents connected with such 
      business.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Plaints, etc., 
      by whom to be signed.—Plaints, written 
      statements, affidavits and other documents connected with legal 
      proceedings may be signed and verified on behalf of the National Bank by 
      any officer empowered by or under regulation 8 to sign documents for and 
      on behalf of the National Bank and such officer may appear in or before 
      any court, tribunal or other body as the recognised agent of the National 
      Bank for the purpose of the proceedings in that court, tribunal or other 
      body. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> No advance to 
      be made to the officers of the National Bank without sanction of the 
      Board.—An advance may 
      be made to the Chairman, Managing Director, whole-time Director, officer 
      or other employee of the National Bank with the sanction of the authority 
      specified in the relative regulations, rules, or schemes made or approved 
      by the Board in terms of which the advance is to be made and where no 
      authority is specified in the relative regulations, rules or schemes, as 
      the case may be, the advance may be sanctioned—
 <section><number>a</number>    
      to the Chairman, by the Board;  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    
      to the Managing Director or the whole-time Director, by the 
      Chairman;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>    
      to officers and other employees, by the Managing Director or a whole-time 
      Director, and subject to such general or special directions as may be 
      issued by the Chairman or the Managing Director, by any other officer 
      specified by the Chairman in this behalf.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Powers on 
      behalf of the  National Bank by whom to be exercised.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
      the provisions of the Act, any regulations made by the Board in regard to 
      expenditure to be incurred by or on behalf of the National Bank and any 
      directions, which may be given by the Chairman either generally or in any 
      particular case in regard to the conduct of the business of the National 
      Bank, the Managing Director and whole-time Directors are hereby severally 
      empowered to exercise any or all the powers and do any or all acts and 
      things which may be exercised or done by the National 
      Bank.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any other 
      officer may, if authorised and to the extent that he is so authorised by 
      the Chairman in this behalf, exercise all the powers in relation to 
      matters pertaining to the department or officer in which he is employed, 
      and in relation to such matters, do all acts and things which may be 
      exercised or done by the National Bank, subject however to the conditions 
      hereinafter specified, namely:—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
      the power to sanction or incur any expenditure on behalf of the National 
      Bank shall be subject to  regulation made by the 
      Board,
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    
      any other power exercised or action taken shall be exercised or taken 
      subject to such directions, if any, as may be given by any higher officer 
      or authority in this behalf.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> No power 
      exercised, functions performed or act or thing done shall be deemed to be 
      invalid or ineffective only on the ground that it is not a power 
      exercised, functions performed, or act or thing done, by or on behalf of 
      the National Bank, or that in the exercise of such power, performance of 
      such function or the doing of any such act or thing, effect has not been 
      given to any rule or direction referred to in sub-regulation (1) or in 
      sub-regulation (2), or that any such rule or direction has been wrongly 
      acted.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Issue of 
      Bonds.—
<section><number>1</number> The bonds or 
      debentures of the National Bank shall be issued over the signature of the 
      Chairman or the Managing Director or any whole-time Director which may be 
      printed, engraved, lithographed, or impressed by such other mechanical 
      process as the National Bank may direct. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A signature 
      so printed, engraved, lithographed or otherwise impressed shall be valid 
      as  if it had been inscribed in the proper handwriting of the 
      signatory himself.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Common 
      seal of the National Bank.—The common seal 
      of the National Bank shall be affixed to any instrument only in the 
      presence of at least two Directors who shall sign their names in the 
      instrument in token of their presence, and such signing shall be 
      independent of their signing of any person who may sign the instrument as 
      a witness. Unless so signed as aforesaid, such instrument shall be of no 
      validity.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> 
      Service of notice to National Bank.—A 
      notice may be served on the National Bank by delivering it to the Managing 
      Director, any whole-time Director, or an officer authorised by the 
      Managing Director in this behalf at, or by sending it by registered post 
      to, the Head Office of the National Bank. 
  
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>