<act><title>


The Insurance Regulatory And Development 
    Authority (Salary And Allowances Payable To, And Other Terms And Conditions 
    of Service Of, Chairperson And Other Members)
    Rules, 2000</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—These 
    rules may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
    (Salary and Allowances Payable to, and other Terms and Condi­tions of 
    Service of, Chairperson and other Members) Rules, 2000.
 <section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Insurance Regulatory 
    and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    words and expressions used herein but 
    not defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to 
    them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Pay.—The 
    pay of a Chairperson shall be rupees twenty‑six thousand per month (fixed) 
    as admissible to a Secretary to the Government of India.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The pay of 
    the whole‑time member shall be in the scale of pay of Rs. 22400‑525-24500.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The pay of 
    the Chairperson and whole‑time member shall be fixed in accordance with the 
    orders of the Central Government:  
 
Provided that 
    in case a person appointed as the Chairperson or a whole‑time member is in 
    receipt of any pension, the pay of such person shall be reduced by the gross 
    amount of pension drawn by him.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Provident 
    Fund, Pension and Gratuity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson and whole‑time members shall be governed by the provisions 
    of the Contributory Provident Fund Rules, 1962 and no option to subscribe 
    under General Provident Fund Rules (Central Services), 1960 shall be 
    available.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    additional pension and gratuity shall not be admissible for service rendered 
    in the Authority.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Dearness 
    Allowances and City Compensatory Allowance.—The 
    Chairperson and whole‑time members shall receive dearness allowance and city 
    compensatory allowance and other allowances at the rate admis­sible to a 
    Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Travel 
    Allowance.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson and 
    whole‑time members while on tour within India or on transfer (including the 
    journey undertaken by self and family) to join the Authority or on the 
    expiry of term with the Authority to proceed to his home town with family, 
    shall be entitled to the journey allowance, daily allowance and 
    transportation of personal effects at the same scales and rates as are 
    applicable to a Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central Government drawing an 
    equivalent pay.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The foreign 
    tours to be undertaken by the Chairperson or whole‑time members shall be 
    undertaken only in accordance with orders issued by the Central Government 
    as are applicable to Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central Government drawing an 
    equivalent pay:  
 
Provided that 
    the foreign tours of the Chairperson or whole‑time members for official 
    purpose shall be approved by the Authority.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson 
    or any whole‑time member shall not be eligible to allotment of any house for 
    their residence from the general pool of accommodation or any other 
    accommodation admissible to officers of Central Govern­ment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson and the whole‑time members shall have the option of claiming of 
    house rent allowance for the residence located in Delhi or in one of the 
    satellite towns surrounding the National Capital Territory of Delhi as 
    admissible to a Central Government Officer of equivalent rank.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case the 
    Chairperson or whole‑time members opt for leased accommodation in one of the 
    satellite towns surrounding the National Capital Territory of Delhi the 
    Chairperson and whole‑time members shall be entitled to rented unfurnished 
    accommodation with built‑up area measuring around 300 sqm. for members and 
    350 sqm. for the Chairperson with suitable open land area appurtenant as 
    permissible under the regulations of the concerned municipal bodies.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Sumptuary 
    Allowance.—The Chairperson and 
    whole‑time members shall not be entitled to Sumptuary Allowance. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Medical 
    Facilities.—The Chairperson and 
    whole‑time members shall be entitled to medical treatment and facility as 
    provided in the Central Government Health Service Scheme for retired 
    Government servants: 
 
Provided that 
    at places where the Central Government Health Services Scheme is not 
    applicable, the Chairperson and whole‑time members, who are not Government 
    servants shall be entitled to the facilities as provided in the Central 
    Service (Medical Attendance) Rules, 1944.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Transport.—The Authority shall not 
    purchase any passenger vehicle for the use of the Chairperson and members:
 
Provided that 
    the Chairperson and whole‑time members shall be eligible for fixed 
    reimbursement of an amount not less than rupees three thousand and an amount 
    not exceeding rupees five thousand per month including salary of a driver, 
    if any, employed by such Chairperson or whole‑time members for the usage and 
    maintenance of his personal car for transportation between residence and 
    office.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Leave.—A 
    Chairperson or whole-time member shall be entitled to thirty days of earned 
    leave for every year of service. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> The payment 
    of leave salary during the leave shall be governed under the provisions of 
    rule 40 of the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairperson or whole‑time member shall be entitled to encashment of fifty 
    per cent of earned leave to his credit at any time.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Leave 
    sanctioning Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Chairperson shall be the authority competent to sanction leave to a 
    whole-time member.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    President of India shall be the authority competent to sanction leave to the 
    Chairperson.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Terms 
    and conditions of service of part‑time members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A part-time member shall hold office for a period, not exceeding five years 
    from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall be eligible for 
    reappointment. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑rule (1), a part‑time member may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    relinquish his office by giving in 
    writing to the Central Government notice of not less than three months; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    be removed from his office in 
    accordance with the provisions of section 6 of the Insurance Regulatory and 
    Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999).  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    part-time members shall be removed under clause (d) or clause (e) of 
    sub-rule (1) of section 6 of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
    Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999) unless he has been given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A part‑time 
    member appointed to fill up a casual vacancy, shall hold office for the 
    remainder period of the term of the part‑time member in whose place he is 
    appointed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A part‑time 
    member shall be entitled to receive such allowance by way of a fee of rupees 
    one thousand only for each meeting of the Authority attended by him.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A part-time 
    member, while on tour (including the journey undertaken to attend a meeting 
    of the Authority) shall also be entitled to travelling allowance and daily 
    allowance at the same rates and are applicable to him if he is in Government 
    Service or to an Additional Secretary to the Government of India if he is 
    not in Government Service.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Other 
    conditions of service.—Other 
    conditions of service of a Chairperson and a member with respect to which no 
    express provision has been made in these rules shall be such as or 
    admissible to a Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central Government drawing an 
    equivalent pay including Central Government Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 
    1964.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, it shall be referred 
    to the Central Government. 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>