<act><tid>229304</tid>
<title>THE NEWSPAPERS (PRICE CONTROL) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 26th May, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the control, in the interests of the general 
public, of the prices of newspapers with a view to ensuring that 
newspapers continue to function, in the prevailing conditions, as 
effective mass communication media and for securing their availability 
at fair prices.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1898254</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and duration.
<section><tid>763758</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Newspapers (Price Control) Act, <year>1972</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1730894</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1159522</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall cease to have effect on the expiry of two years 
from the date of its commencement except as respect things done or 
omitted to be done before such cesser of operation of this Act and 
section 6 of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year>, (10 of <year>1997</year>) shall apply 
upon such cesser of operation of this Act as if it had then been 
repealed by a Central Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537893</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,- 
 (a)" basic price", in relation to a newspaper, means the 
price of the newspaper on the 22nd day of October, <year>1971</year> 
[ being the date on which the Stamp and Excise Duties (Amend-  
  ment) Ordinance, <year>1971</year>, (16 of <year>1971</year>.) was promulgated] or if 
the newspaper was not published on that day, its price on the 
day on which it is first published after that day.
<section><tid>318331</tid>
<number>b</number>" basic price date", in relation to a newspaper, means 
the date with reference to which its basic price is to be 
ascertained under clause (a);

</section>

<section><tid>1747365</tid>
<number>c</number>the expressions" newspaper"," owner" and" publisher" 
have the same meanings as in the Press and Registration of 
Books Act, <year>1867</year> (25 of <year>1867</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1201254</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to fix maximum prices of newspapers.
<section><tid>1383572</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central  
Government is of opinion that for the purpose of securing the 
availability of any newspapers or any class of newspapers at fair 
prices, it is necessary or expedient to do so, the Central Government 
may, from time to time, by order published in the Official Gazette,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

determine the maximum prices which may be charged for such news- papers 
or newspapers of such class as may be specified in the order.


</section>

<section><tid>1918194</tid>
<number>2</number>In making under sub- section (1) any order determining the 
maximum price which may be charged for any newspaper referred to in 
that sub- section, the Central Government shall have regard to-

<subsection><tid>432135</tid>
<number>a</number>the basic price of the newspaper;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1250186</tid>
<number>b</number>the excise duties and other taxes, if any, payable 
in respect of the newspaper;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>353395</tid>
<number>c</number>any special circumstances arising on or after the 
basic price date of the newspaper and having a bearing on the 
cost of the production of newspapers; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1139695</tid>
<number>d</number>all other relevant circumstances:
Provided that the maximum price determined in respect of a news- 
paper shall in no case be less than its basic price.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>295360</tid>
<number>3</number>No order shall be made under this section in respect of any 
newspaper which is being sold at a price not exceeding its basic 
price.

</section>

<section><tid>324429</tid>
<number>4</number>An order made under sub- section (1) may provide for 
different maximum prices in respect of different newspapers or 
different classes of newspapers or different newspapers in each such 
class and may provide for such incidental and supplemental matters 
 (including the printing in a newspaper to which the order relates of  
  the price thereof in a conspicuous manner) as the Central Government 
may deem fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>786805</tid>
<number> 4</number> Review and revision of orders.
<section><tid>1180273</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner or publisher of a  
newspaper to which an order under sub- section (1) of section 3 relates 
may,-

<subsection><tid>349173</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is aggrieved by such order, make within 
thirty days of the date of publication of the order in the 
Official Gazette, an application to the Central Government 
for a review of the order setting out in such application the 
grounds on which he considers such review to be necessary;.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1838420</tid>
<number>b</number>whenever fresh circumstances having a bearing on 
the cost of production of the newspaper arise after the date 
of making of the order, make an application for a revision of 
the order within thirty days after the date on which such 
circumstances have arisen,
and the Central Government may pass such order on the said application 
for review or revision as it thinks fit:

Provided that the Central Government may for sufficient cause 
allow any such application to be made after the expiry of the period 
of thirty days aforesaid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>909422</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided by an order made under clause (a) 
or clause (b) of sub- section (1), the order of the Central Government 
under sub- section (1) of section 3 shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248585</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to call for information, return, etc.
<section><tid>641656</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government or any officer authorised by the Central Government in this 
behalf may, by order in writing, require the owner or publisher of any 
newspaper to furnish, within such time as may be specified in the 
order any information, return or report which the Central Government 
or such officer may consider necessary for carrying out the purposes 
of this Act and such owner or publisher shall be bound to comply with 
such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1943696</tid>
<number>2</number>If any owner or publisher contravenes any order under sub- 
section (1), he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1197156</tid>
<number>6</number>Prohibition of sale of newspapers in contravention of the order 
under section 3. No newspaper shall be sold in the territories to 
which this Act extends in contravention of an order made under 
section 3.


</article>



<article><tid>400872</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty. Whoever sells or causes to be sold a newspaper in 
contravention of an order made under section 3 shall, on first 
conviction, be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand 
rupees and, on any second or subsequent conviction, with fine which 
may extend to two thousand rupees;.


</article>



<article><tid>1545816</tid>
<number> 8</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>229793</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act has  
been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company 
for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1925800</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or con- 
vinance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty 
of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1794402</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or 
other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1425197</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>73666</tid>
<number>9</number>Previous sanction of Central Government for prosecution. No 
prosecution shall be instituted against any person in respect of any 
offence punishable under section 5 or section 7 without the previous 
sanction of the Central Government or such officer or authority as may 
be authorised by that, Government by order in writing in that behalf.

</article>



 </act>