<act><title>


the Competition Commission of India (Selection 
    of Chairperson and other Members of the Commission)
    Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Competition Commission of India (Selection of 
    Chairperson and other Members of the Commission) Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> ‘Act’ means the 
    Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 2003);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> ‘Commission’ means 
    the Competition Commission of India established under sub-section (1) of 
    section 7 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> ‘Committee’ means the 
    committee constituted under sub-rule (1) of rule 3.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Words and expressions used but not defined in these rules and defined in the 
    Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 2003) shall have the same meaning assigned to 
    them in that Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    the Central Government shall constitute a Committee for the selection of 
    Chairperson and other Members of the Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Committee shall consist of,—
 <subsection>
           <number>a</number>   a 
    person, who has been a retired judge of 
                  
    the Supreme Court or a High Court or a 
                  
    retired Chairperson of a Tribunal established or 
                  
    constituted under an Act of Parliament or a      
                  
    distinguished jurist or a Senior Advocate for      
                  
    five years or more;                                            ………..Member,
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>b</number>   a person 
    who has special knowledge of, and 
                  
    professional experience of twenty-five years or  
                  
    more in international trade, economics,  
                  
    business, commerce or industry;                          
    ….……..Member,
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>c</number>   a person 
    who has special knowledge of, and     
                  
    professional experience of twenty-five years or  
                  
    more in accountancy, management, finance,  
                  
    public affairs or administration;                            ....…….Member,
 
to be nominated by the 
    Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Central Government shall nominate one of the Members of the Committee to 
    act as the Chairperson of the Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Joint Secretary in the Ministry of Finance and Company Affairs 
    (Department of Company Affairs) dealing with the Competition Act, 2002 (12 
    of 2003) shall be the Convenor of the Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    The term of the Committee constituted under sub-rule (1) shall be for a 
    period of one hundred and twenty days from the date of its constitution.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Functions of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As and when vacancies of Chairperson or a member in the Commission exist or 
    arise, or are likely to arise, the Central Government may make a reference 
    to the Committee in respect of the vacancies to be filled.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Committee shall devise its own procedure for purpose of the selection of 
    the Chairperson or a Member of the Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Committee shall recommend a person, or a panel of not more than three 
    persons in order of priority, as the Committee may think fit, in respect of 
    each vacancy that has been referred to the Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Committee shall make its recommendations to the Central Government, 
    within a period not exceeding ninety days.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the members of the Committee differ in making its recommendation, the 
    recommendation of selection of the Chairperson or a member of the 
    Competition Commission of India shall be decided by the majority of the 
    members of the Committee.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Vacancy, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Committee.—No 
    act or procedure of the Committee shall be invalid merely by reason of any 
    vacancy in the Committee.

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>