<act><tid>823983</tid>
<title>THE SPIRITUOUS PREPARATIONS (INTER- STATE TRADE AND COMMERCE) 
CONTROLACT, <year>1955</year></title>

ACT NO. 39 OF <year>1955</year>
[ 15th October, <year>1955</year>.]

An Act to make provision for the imposition in the public interest of 
certain restrictions on inter- State trade and commerce in spirituous 
medicinal and other preparations and to provide for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>314703</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1182871</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Spirituous Preparations (Inter- State Trade and Commerce) 
Control Act, <year>1955</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1251188</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>119994</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1264099</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1131535</tid>
<number>a</number>" alcohol" means ethyl alcohol of any strength and purity 
having the chemical composition C 2H 5OH;

</section>

<section><tid>1684944</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1531333</tid>
<number>c</number>" prohibition State" means any State which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify as being a State in which or in any 
part of which the consumption of alcoholic liquors is 
generally prohibited by law;

</section>

<section><tid>1153705</tid>
<number>d</number>" spirituous preparation" means--

<subsection><tid>1339036</tid>
<number>i</number>any medicinal preparation containing alcohol, 
whether self- generated or otherwise; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1899939</tid>
<number>ii</number>any mixture or compound of wine with 
medicinal substances, whether the wine is fortified 
with spirit or not; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>506231</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other substance notified under section 4 
to be a spirituous preparation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2nd September, <year>1957</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 2467 dated the 
29th July, <year>1957</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1957</year>, Pt. II, 
Sec. 3, p. 2235.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1965428</tid>
<number> 3</number> Control of inter- State trade and commerce in spirituous 
preparations.
<section><tid>1510163</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall, in the course of inter- State trade  
and commerce,--

<subsection><tid>355023</tid>
<number>a</number>import into a prohibition State any spirituous 
preparation; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1419384</tid>
<number>b</number>export from any State or transport from one place to 
another or sell any spirituous preparation for the 
purpose of its importation into a prohibition State;
save in accordance with rules made under sub- section (2) and with the 
conditions of any licence for that purpose which he may be required to 
obtain under those rules.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>402455</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules regulating such import, export, transport or sale, 
and such rules may prescribe the form and conditions of licences 
therefor, the authorities by which such licences may be granted and 
the fees that may be charged with respect thereto, and any other 
matter required to render effective the control over such import, 
export, transport or sale.

</section>

<section><tid>1004503</tid>
<number>3</number>Save in so far as may be expressly provided in the rules made 
under sub- section (2), nothing in this section shall apply to 
spirituous preparations which are the property of the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1926255</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule,"]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>549081</tid>
<number>4</number>Other preparations containing alcohol may be notified as 
spirituous preparations. If the Central Government is satisfied, after 
making such inquiry in this behalf as it may think fit and after 
taking into account such representations as may be made in the matter, 
that control of inter- State trade and commerce in any preparation 
containing alcohol other than a preparation referred to in sub- clause 
 (i) or sub- clause (ii) of clause (d) of section 2 is necessary in the 
public interest, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare such preparation to be a spirituous preparation within the 
meaning of this Act and thereupon the provisions of this Act shall 
apply thereto.


</article>



<article><tid>269261</tid>
<number>5</number>Penalties. If any person contravenes any of the provisions of 
this Act or of any rules made thereunder, or the terms and conditions 
of any licence granted under such rules, he shall, for every such 
offence, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</article>



<article><tid>889352</tid>
<number>6</number>Procedure to be followed by magistrate. In all trials for 
offences under this Act or the rules made thereunder, the magistrate 
shall follow the procedure prescribed in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year>, (5 of <year>1898</year>.) for the trial of summary cases in which 
an appeal lies.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1920086</tid>
<number>7</number>Offences under this Act cognisable. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>, (5 of <year>1898</year>.) all 
offences under this Act and the rules made thereunder shall be 
cognisable.


</article>



<article><tid>1769530</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to enter, search, seize, arrest without warrant and 
investigate offences.
<section><tid>531933</tid>
<number>1</number>Any officer of the department of  
prohibition, excise, police, revenue or public health authorised in 
this behalf by the State Government, by general or special order, who 
has reasons to believe from personal knowledge or from information 
given by any person and taken down in writing that any spirituous 
preparation in respect of which an offence punishable under section 5 
has been committed is kept or concealed in any house, building or 
enclosed space, or is being transported in any vehicle, vessel or 
aircraft to any place or is in transit may--

<subsection><tid>1052131</tid>
<number>a</number>enter at any time by day or by night into any such 
house, building or enclosed space, or vehicle, vessel 
or aircraft;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>547519</tid>
<number>b</number>in case of resistance, break open any door and remove 
any other obstacle to such entry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>474991</tid>
<number>c</number>seize such preparation and any document or other article 
which he has reason to believe may furnish evidence of 
the commission of an offence punishable under this Act 
or the rules made thereunder; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1125724</tid>
<number>d</number>detain and search any person whom he has reason to 
believe to be guilty of an offence punishable under 
this Act or the rules made thereunder, and if such 
person has any spirituous preparation in his possession 
and such possession appears to him to be unlawful, 
arrest him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>910367</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an officer takes down any information in writing under 
sub- section (1), he shall forthwith send a copy thereof to his 
immediate official superior.

</section>

<section><tid>174682</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may empower any officer of the 
prohibition or excise department to investigate offences under this 
Act and the rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>485696</tid>
<number>4</number>An officer empowered under sub- section (3) shall, in the 
conduct of such investigation, exercise the powers conferred by the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>, (5 of <year>1898</year>.) upon an officer in 
charge of a police station for the investigation of cognisable 
offences.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>788421</tid>
<number> 9</number> Vexatious search, seizure, etc., by officers exercising powers 
under the Act.
<section><tid>1334114</tid>
<number>1</number>Any officer exercising powers under this Act or  
under the rules made thereunder who--

<subsection><tid>821131</tid>
<number>a</number>without reasonable ground for believing that it is 
necessary so to do searches or causes to be searched 
any house,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

building or enclosed place or any vehicle, vessel or aircraft;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>141496</tid>
<number>b</number>vexatiously or unnecessarily seizes any spirituous 
preparation or any document or other article;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>958292</tid>
<number>c</number>vexatiously or unnecessarily detains, searches or 
arrests any person; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1058075</tid>
<number>d</number>commits, as such officer, any other act to the injury of 
any person without having reason to believe that such 
act is required for the execution of his duty;
shall for every such offence be punishable with fine which may extend 
to two thousand rupees.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1390257</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person wilfully and maliciously giving false information 
and so causing an arrest or a search to be made under this Act shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with 
both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235643</tid>
<number> 10</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1541590</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing an  
offence under section 5 is a company, every person who, at the time 
the contravention was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the contravention 
and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>407272</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1277315</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate, and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>688176</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>46046</tid>
<number>11</number>Presumption from possession of spirituous preparations. In 
trials under this Act, it may be presumed unless and until the 
contrary is proved, that the accused has committed an offence

<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

under this Act or the rules made thereunder in respect of any 
spirituous preparations for the possession of which he fails to 
account satisfactorily.



</article>



<article><tid>309219</tid>
<number>12</number>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the power to make 
rules under section 3 shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as 
may be specified in the notification, be exercisable also by a State 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1504106</tid>
<number>13</number>Power to exempt. The Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, and subject to such conditions as it may 
think fit to impose, exempt any spirituous preparation from all or any 
of the provisions of this Act on the ground that the spirituous 
preparation is ordinarily required for medicinal, scientific, 
industrial or such like purposes.


</article>



<article><tid>1926812</tid>
<number>14</number>Officers acting under this Act to be public servants. All 
officers empowered to exercise any powers or to perform any duties 
under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1850790</tid>
<number>15</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any officer or 
person empowered to exercise powers or to perform duties under this 
Act for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act or the rules made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>301913</tid>
<number>16</number>Saving of local and special laws. Nothing in this Act or in 
the rules made thereunder shall affect the validity of any Provincial 
Act or a State Act for the time being in force, or of any rule, 
regulation or order made thereunder, which imposes any restriction not 
imposed by or under this Act, or imposes a restriction greater in 
degree than a corresponding restriction imposed by or under this Act 
on the traffic in any spirituous preparations within the territories 
of the State.

</article>



 </act>