<act><title>

The 
    Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    be deemed to have come into force on the 25th day of January, 1997. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “appointed day” means the date with 
    effect from which the Authority is established under sub-section (1) of 
    section 3; 
 

1[(aa)    
    "Appellate Tribunal" means the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate 
    Tribunal established under section 14;] 
    2[(aa) \"Appellate Tribunal\" means the Telecom 
    Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal established under section 14;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Authority” means the Telecom 
    Regulatory Authority of India established under sub-section (1) of section 
    3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of 
    the Authority appoint­ed under sub-section (3) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Fund” means the Fund constituted under 
    sub-section (1) of section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Licensee” means any person licensed 
    under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 
    1885) for provid­ing specified public telecommunication services; 
 

1[(ea)    
    "licensor" means the Central Government or the telegraph authority who 
    grants a licence under section 4 of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 
    1885);] 
    2[(ea) \"licensor\" means the Central Government or 
    the telegraph authority who grants a licence under section 4 of the Indian 
    Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885);]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “member” means a member of the 
    Authority appointed under sub-section (3) of section 3 and includes the 
    Chairperson and the Vice-Chairperson; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “regulations” means regulations made by 
    the Authority under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    “service provider” means the
    2[Government 
    as a service provider] and includes a licen­see;
1[Government 
    as a service provider] and includes a licen­see;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    “telecommunication service” means 
    service of any description (including electronic mail, voice mail, data 
    services, audio tax services, video tax services, radio paging and cellular 
    mobile telephone services) which is made available to users by means of any 
    transmission or reception of signs, signals, writing, images and sounds or 
    intelligence of any nature, by wire, radio, visual or other electromagnetic 
    means but shall not include broadcasting services: 
 

3[Provided 
    that the Central Government may notify other service to be telecommunication 
    service including broadcasting services.]
2[Provided 
    that the Central Government may notify other service to be telecommunication 
    service including broadcasting services.]" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and  
    expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian 
    Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) or the Indian
    wireless
    telegraphy Act, 1933 (17 of 
    1933) shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu 
    and Kashmir shall in relation to that State be construed as a reference to 
    the corresponding law, if any, in that State. 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment and incorporation of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notifica­tion 
    appoint, there shall be established, for the purposes of this Act, an 
    Authority to be called the Telecom Regulatory Au­thority of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall be a body corporate by the name afore­said, having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this 
    Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, 
    and to contract, and shall, by the said name, sue or be sued. 
 


    1[(3) The Authority 
    shall consist of a Chairperson, and not more than two whole-time members and 
    not more than two part-time members, to be appointed by the Central 
    Government.] 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The head 
    office of the Authority shall be at New Delhi. 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> Qualifications 
    for appointment of Chairperson and other members.—The 
    Chairperson and other members of the Authority shall be appointed by the 
    Central Government from amongst persons who have special knowledge of, and 
    professional experience in, telecommunication, industry, finance, 
    accountancy, law, management or consumer affairs:2[4. 
    Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and other members.—The 
    Chairperson and other members of the Authority shall be appointed by the 
    Central Government from amongst persons who have special knowledge of, and 
    professional experience in, telecommunication, industry, finance, 
    accountancy, law, management or consumer affairs\:" 
 
Provided that 
    a person who is, or has been, in the service of Government shall not be 
    appointed as a member unless such person has held the post of Secretary or 
    Additional Secretary, or the post of Additional Secretary and Secretary to 
    the Government of India or any equivalent post in the Central Government or 
    the State Government for a period of not less than three years.] 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Term of 
    office, conditions of service, etc., of Chairperson and other members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Before appointing any person as the Chair­person or member, the Central 
    Government shall satisfy itself that the person does not have any such 
    financial or other inter­est as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
    functions as such member. 
 


    1[(2) The Chairperson 
    and other members shall hold office for a term not exceeding three years, as 
    the Central Government may notify in this behalf, from the date on which 
    they enter upon their offices or until they attain the age of sixty-five 
    years, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the 
    commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 
    2000, a person appointed as Chairperson of the Authority and every other 
    person appointed as member and holding office as such immediately before 
    such commencement shall vacate their respective offices and such Chairperson 
    and such other members shall be entitled to claim compensation not exceeding 
    three months pay and allowances for the premature termination of the term of 
    their offices or of any contract of service.] 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    employee of the Government on his 

    2[selection as the 
    Chairperson or whole-time member] shall have to retire from service before
    

    3[joining as the 
    Chairperson or a whole-time member]. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    salary and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson and 

    4[whole-time members] 
    shall be such as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Chairperson or of 
    a member shall not be varied to his disadvan­tage after appointment. 
 


    5[(6A) The part-time 
    members shall receive such allowances as may be prescribed.] 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) 

    6[***], a member may— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    relinquish his office by giving in 
    writing to the Central Government notice of not less than three months; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    be removed from his office in 
    accordance with the provisions of section 7.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Chairperson or any 

    7[whole-time member] 
    ceasing to hold office as such, shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    be ineligible for further employment 
    under the Central Gov­ernment or any State Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    not accept any commercial 
    employment, for a period of  
8[one 
    year] from the date he ceases to hold such office:
7[one 
    year] from the date he ceases to hold such office\:" 
 


    9[Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall apply to the Chairperson or a 
    member who has ceased to hold office under sub-section (3) and such 
    Chairperson or member shall be eligible for re-appointment in the Authority 
    or appointment in the Appellate Tribunal.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number>  A vacancy 
    caused to the office of the Chairperson or any other member shall be filled 
    up within a period of three months from the date on which such vacancy 
    occurs. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purpose of 
    this section, “commercial em­ployment” means employment in any capacity 
    under, or agency of, a person engaged in trading, commercial, industrial or 
    financial business in any field and includes also a director of a company or 
    partner of a firm and it also includes setting up practice either 
    independently or as partner of a firm or as an adviser or a consultant. 
 
 













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Powers 
    of Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson shall have powers of general superintendence and directions 
    in the conduct of the affairs of the Authority and he shall, in addition to 
    presiding over the meetings of the Authority, exer­cise and discharge such 
    powers and functions of the Authority and shall discharge such other powers 
    and functions as may be pre­scribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may appoint one of the members to be a Vice-Chairperson 
    of the Authority who shall exercise and dis­charge such powers and functions 
    of the Chairperson as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
    Authority. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number>Removal 
    and suspension of member from office in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may remove from office any member, who,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has been convicted of an offence which, 
    in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has become physically or mentally 
    incapable of acting as a member; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has acquired such financial or other 
    interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a member; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has so abused his position as to render 
    his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest. 
 


    1[(2) No such member 
    shall be removed from his office under clause (d) or clause (e) of 
    sub-section (1) unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard in the matter.]
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall 
    meet at such times and places, and shall observe such rules of procedure in 
    regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including quorum at 
    such meetings) as may be provided by regulations. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend a meeting of the 
    Authority, Vice-Chairperson and in his absence, any other member chosen by 
    the members present from amongst themselves at the meeting shall preside at 
    the meeting. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Author­ity shall be 
    decided by a majority vote of the members present and voting, and in the 
    event of an equality of votes, the Chair­person or in his absence, the 
    person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority may make regulations for the transaction of  business at it 
    meetings. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Authority.—No 
    act or proceeding of the Authority shall be in­valid merely by reason of—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
    constitution of, the Authority; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any defect in the appointment of a 
    person acting as a member of the Authority; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any irregularity in the procedure of 
    the Authority not af­fecting the merits of the case. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Officers and other employees of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authori­ty may appoint officers and such other employees as it considers 
    necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    salary and allowances payable to and the other conditions of service of the 
    officers and other employees of the Authority appointed under sub-section 
    (1) shall be such as may be 

    1[prescribed]: 
 


    2[Provided that any 
    regulation, in respect of the salary and allowances payable to and other 
    conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Authority, 
    made before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India 
    (Amendment)  Act, 2000, shall cease to have effect immediately on the 
    notification of rules made under clause (ca) of sub-section (2) of section 
    35.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Functions of Authority.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 
    1885), the functions of the Authority shall be to——3[(1) 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 
    1885), the functions of the Authority shall be to—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    make recommendations, either suo 
    motu or on a request from the licensor, on the following matters, 
    namely:— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    need and timing for introduction of new 
    service provider; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    terms and conditions of licence to a 
    service provider; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    revocation of licence for 
    non-compliance of terms and conditions of licence; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    measures to facilitate competition and 
    promote efficiency in the operation of telecommunication services so as to 
    facilitate growth in such services; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    technological improvements in the 
    services provided by the service providers; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>    type of equipment to be used by the 
    service providers after inspection of equipment used in the network; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>    measures for the development of 
    telecommunication technology and any other matter relatable to 
    telecommunication industry in general; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>    efficient management of available 
    spectrum; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    discharge the following functions, 
    namely:— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    ensure compliance of terms and 
    conditions of licence; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    notwithstanding anything contained in 
    the terms and conditions of the licence granted before the commencement of 
    the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, fix the 
    terms and conditions of inter-connectivity between the service providers; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    ensure technical compatibility and 
    effective inter-connection between different service providers; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    regulate arrangement amongst service 
    providers of sharing their revenue derived from providing telecommunication 
    services; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    lay-down the standards of quality of 
    service to be provided by the service providers and ensure the quality of 
    service and conduct the periodical survey of such service provided by the 
    service providers so as to protect interest of the consumers of 
    telecommunication service; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>    lay-down and ensure the time period 
    for providing local and long distance circuits of telecommunication between 
    different service providers; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>    maintain register of interconnect 
    agreements and of all such other matters as may be provided in the 
    regulations; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>    keep register maintained under 
    clause (vii) open for inspection to any member of public on payment of such 
    fee and compliance of such other requirement as may be provided in the 
    regulations; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ix</number>    ensure effective compliance of 
    universal service obligations; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    levy fees and other charges at such 
    rates and in respect of such services as may be determined by regulations; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    perform such other functions including 
    such administrative and financial functions as may be entrusted to it by the 
    Central Government or as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of 
    this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    the recommendations of the Authority specified in clause (a) of this 
    sub-section shall not be binding upon the Central Government: 
 
Provided 
    further that the Central Government shall seek the recommendations of the 
    Authority in respect of matters specified in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of 
    clause (a) of this sub-section in respect of new licence to be issued to a 
    service provider and the Authority shall forward its recommendations within 
    a period of sixty days from the date on which that Government sought the 
    recommendations: 
 
Provided also 
    that the Authority may request the Central Government to furnish such 
    information or documents as may be necessary for the purpose of making 
    recommendations under sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (a) of this 
    sub-section and that Government shall supply such information within a 
    period of seven days from receipt of such request: 
 
Provided also 
    that the Central Government may issue a licence to a service provider if no 
    recommendations are received from the Authority within the period specified 
    in the second proviso or within such period as may be mutually agreed upon 
    between the Central Government and the Authority: 
 
Provided also 
    that if the Central Government having considered that recommendation of the 
    Authority, comes to a prima facie conclusion that such recommendation 
    cannot be accepted or needs modifications, it shall, refer the 
    recommendation back to the Authority for its reconsideration, and the 
    Authority may within fifteen days from the date of receipt of such 
    reference, forward to the Central Government its recommendation after 
    considering the reference made by that Government. After receipt of further 
    recommendation if any, the Central Government shall take a final decision.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 
    1885), the Authority may, from time to time, by order, notify in the 
    Official Gazette the rates at which the telecommunication services within 
    India and outside India shall be provided under this Act including the rates 
    at which messages shall be transmitted to any country outside India: 
 
Provided that 
    the Authority may notify different rates for dif­ferent persons or class of 
    persons for similar telecommunication services and where different rates are 
    fixed as aforesaid the Authority shall record the reasons therefor. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    While discharging its functions 

    2[under sub-section 
    (1) or sub-section (2)] the Authority shall not act against the interest of 
    the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly 
    relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority shall ensure transparency while exercising its powers and 
    discharging its functions.
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Powers 
    of Authority to call for information, conduct investi­gations, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Authority considers it expedient so to do, it may, by order in 
    writing,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    call upon any service provider at any 
    time to furnish in writing such information or explanation relating to its 
    affairs as the Authority may require; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    appoint one or more persons to make an 
    inquiry in relation to the affairs of any service provider; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    direct any of its officers or employees 
    to inspect the books of account or other documents of any service provider. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    inquiry in relation to the affairs of a service provider has been undertaken 
    under sub-section (1),— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    every officer of the Government 
    Department, if such service provider is a department of the Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    every director, manager, secretary or 
    other officer, if such service provider is a company; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    every partner, manager, secretary or 
    other officer, if such service provider is a firm; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    every other person or body of persons 
    who has had dealings in the course of business with any of the persons 
    mentioned in clauses (b) and (c), 
 
shall be bound to produce before the Authority 
    making the in­quiry, all such books  of account or other documents in his 
    custody or power relating to, or having a bear­ing on the subject-matter of 
    such inquiry and also to furnish to the Authority with any such statement or 
    information relating there­to, as the case may be, required of him, within 
    such time as may be specified. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    service provider shall maintain such books of account or other documents as 
    may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Authority shall have the power to issue such directions to service providers 
    as it may consider necessary for proper functioning by service providers. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Power 
    of Authority to issue directions.—The 
    Authority may, for the discharge of its functions under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 11, issue such directions from time to time to the serv­ice 
    providers, as it may consider necessary: 
 


    1[Provided that no 
    direction under sub-section (4) of section 12 or under this section shall 
    be  issued except on the matters specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) 
    of section 11.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Establishment of Appellate Tribunal.—The 
    Central  Government shall, by notification, establish an Appellate Tribunal 
    to be known as the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal to— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    adjudicate any dispute— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    between a licensor and a licensee; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    between two or more service providers; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    between a service provider and a 
    group of consumers: 
 
Provided that nothing in this clause shall 
    apply in respect of matters relating to— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>A</number>    the monopolistic trade practice, 
    restrictive trade practice and unfair trade practice which are subject to 
    the jurisdiction of the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices 
    Commission established under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Monopolies 
    and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>B</number>    the complaint of an individual consumer 
    maintainable before a Consumer Disputes Redressal Forum or a Consumer 
    Disputes Redressal Commission or the National Consumer Redressal Commission 
    established under section 9 of the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (68 of 
    1986); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>C</number>    dispute between telegraph authority and 
    any other person referred to in sub-section (1) of section 7B of the Indian 
    Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885); 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    hear and dispose of appeal against any 
    direction, decision or order of the Authority under this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14A</number> 
    Application for settlement of disputes and appeals to Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government  or a State Government or a local authority or any 
    person may make an application to the Appellate Tribunal for adjudication of 
    any dispute referred to in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 14. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government or a State Government or a local authority or any person 
    aggrieved by any direction, decision or order made by the Authority may 
    prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    appeal under sub-section (2) shall be preferred within a period of thirty 
    days from the date on which a copy of the direction or order or decision 
    made by the Authority is received by the Central Government or the State 
    Government or the local authority or the aggrieved person and it shall be in 
    such form, verified in such manner and be accompanied by such fee as may be 
    prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    the Appellate Tribunal may entertain any appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period of thirty days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for 
    not filing it within that period. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt 
    of an application under sub-section (1) or an appeal under sub-section (2), 
    the Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the dispute or the 
    appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks 
    fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the 
    parties to the dispute or the appeal and to the Authority, as the case may 
    be. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    application made under sub-section (1) or the appeal preferred under 
    sub-section (2) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and 
    endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the application or appeal 
    finally within ninety days from the date of receipt of application or 
    appeal, as the case may be: 
 
Provided that 
    where any such application or appeal could not be disposed of within the 
    said period of ninety days, the Appellate Tribunal shall record its reasons 
    in writing for not disposing of the application or appeal within that 
    period. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal may, for the purpose of examining the legality or 
    propriety or correctness, of any dispute made in any application under 
    sub-section (1), or of any direction or order or decision of the Authority 
    referred to in the appeal preferred under sub-section (2), on its own motion 
    or otherwise, call for the records relevant to deposing of such application 
    or appeal and make such orders as it thinks fit. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14B</number> 
    Composition of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson and not more than two 
    Members to be appointed, by notification, by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    selection of Chairperson and Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall be made 
    by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the jurisdiction of the Appellate 
    Tribunal may be exercised by the Benches thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a Bench may be constituted by the 
    Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal with one or two Members of such 
    Tribunal as the Chairperson may deem fit; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Benches of the Appellate Tribunal 
    shall ordinarily sit at New Delhi and at such other places as the Central 
    Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson of the Appellate 
    Tribunal, notify; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the Central Government shall notify the 
    areas in relation to which each Bench of the Appellate Tribunal may exercise 
    its jurisdiction. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the Chairperson of 
    the Appellate Tribunal may transfer a Member of such Tribunal from one Bench 
    to another Bench. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If at any 
    stage of the hearing of any case or matter it appears to the Chairperson or 
    a Member of the Appellate Tribunal that the case or matter is of such a 
    nature that it ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of two Members, the 
    case or matter may be transferred by the Chairperson to such Bench as the 
    Chairperson may deem fit. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14C</number> 
    Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and Members.—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairperson or a Member 
    of the Appellate Tribunal unless he— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of Chairperson, is, or has 
    been, a Judge of the Supreme Court or the Chief Justice of a High Court; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in the case of a Member, has held the 
    post of Secretary to the Government of India or any equivalent post in the 
    Central Government or the State Government for a period of not less than two 
    years or a person who is well versed in the field of technology, 
    telecommunication, industry, commerce or administration. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14D</number> Term 
    of office.—The Chairperson and 
    every other Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall hold office as such for a 
    term not exceeding three years from the date on which he enters upon his 
    office: 
 
Provided that 
    no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such after he has 
    attained,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of Chairperson, the age of 
    seventy years; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in the case of any other Member, the 
    age of sixty-five years. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14E</number> Terms 
    and conditions of service.—The 
    salary and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall 
    be such as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall be 
    varied to his disadvantage after appointment. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14F</number> 
    Vacancies.—If, for reason other 
    than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the office of the Chairperson 
    or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal, the Central Government shall appoint 
    another person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the 
    vacancy and the proceedings may be continued before the Appellate Tribunal 
    from the stage at which the vacancy is filled. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14G</number> 
    Removal and resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may remove from office, the Chairperson or any Member of 
    the Appellate Tribunal, who— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has been convicted of an offence which, 
    in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has become physically or mentally 
    incapable of acting as the Chairperson or a Member; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has acquired such financial or other 
    interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as the 
    Chairperson or a Member; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has so abused his position as to render 
    his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairperson or a 
    Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be removed from his office on the 
    ground specified in clause (d) or clause (e) of that sub-section unless the 
    Supreme Court on a reference being made to it in this behalf by the Central 
    Government, has, on an enquiry, held by it in accordance with such procedure 
    as it may specify in this behalf, reported that the Chairperson or a Member 
    ought on such ground or grounds to be removed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may suspend from office, the Chairperson or a Member of 
    the Appellate Tribunal in respect of whom a reference has been made to the 
    Supreme Court under sub-section (2), until the Central Government has passed 
    an order on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on such reference. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14H</number> Staff 
    of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers 
    and employees as it may deem fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall discharge their 
    functions under the general superintendence of its Chairperson. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of such officers and 
    employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14-I</number> 
    Distribution of business amongst Benches.—Where 
    Benches are constituted, the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may, from 
    time to time, by notification, make provisions as to the distribution of the 
    business of the Appellate Tribunal amongst the Benches and also provide for 
    the matters which may be dealt with by each Bench. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14J</number> Power 
    of Chairperson to transfer cases.—On 
    the application of any of the parties and after notice to the parties, and 
    after hearing such of them as he may desire to be heard, or on his own 
    motion without such notice, the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may 
    transfer any case pending before one Bench, for disposal, to any other 
    Bench. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14K</number> 
    Decision to be by majority.—If 
    the Members of a Bench consisting of two Members differ in opinion on any 
    point, they shall state the point or points on which they differ, and make a 
    reference to the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal who shall hear the 
    point or points himself and such point or points shall be decided according 
    to the opinion of the majority who have heard the case, including those who 
    first heard it.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14L</number> 
    Members, etc., to be public servants.—The 
    Chairperson, Members and other officers and employees of the Appellate 
    Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 
    21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14M</number> 
    Transfer of pending cases.—All 
    applications, pending for adjudication of disputes before the Authority 
    immediately before the date of establishment of the Appellate Tribunal under 
    this Act, shall stand transferred on that date to such Tribunal: 
 
Provided that 
    all disputes being adjudicated under the provisions of Chapter IV as it 
    stood immediately before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory 
    Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, shall continue to be adjudicated 
    by the Authority in accordance with the provisions, contained in that 
    Chapter, till the establishment of the Appellate Tribunal under the said 
    Act: 
 
Provided 
    further that all cases referred to in the first proviso shall be transferred 
    by the Authority to the Appellate Tribunal immediately on its establishment 
    under section 14. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14N</number> 
    Transfer of appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
    appeals pending before the High Court immediately before the commencement of 
    the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, shall stand 
    transferred to the Appellate Tribunal on its establishment under section 14. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    appeal stands transferred from the High Court to the Appellate Tribunal 
    under sub-section (1),— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the High Court shall, as soon as may be 
    after such transfer, forward the records of such appeal to the Appellate 
    Tribunal; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the Appellate Tribunal may, on receipt 
    of such records, proceed to deal with such appeal, so far as may be from the 
    stage which was reached before such transfer or from any earlier stage or 
    de novo as the Appellate Tribunal may deem fit. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Civil 
    court not to have jurisdiction.—No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which the Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under 
    this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or 
    other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance 
    of any power conferred by or under this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by the 
    principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this 
    Act, the Appellate Tribunal shall have powers to regulate its own procedure. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions 
    under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect 
    of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing the attendance 
    of any person and examining him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery and production 
    of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    subject to the provisions of sections 
    123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any 
    public record or document or a copy of such record or document, from any 
    office; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for the examination 
    of witnesses or documents; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    reviewing its decisions; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    dismissing an application for default 
    or deciding it, ex parte; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    setting aside any order of dismissal of 
    any application for default or any order passed by it, ex parte; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    any other matter which may be 
    prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    proceeding before the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial 
    proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes 
    of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Appellate 
    Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 
    and Chapter XXVI of the Code of  Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Right 
    to legal representation.—The 
    applicant or appellant may either appear in person or authorise one or more 
    chartered accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal 
    practitioners or any of its officers to present his or its case before the 
    Appellate Tribunal. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “chartered accountant” means a 
    chartered accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 
    2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a 
    certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “company secretary” means a company 
    secretary as defined in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the 
    Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 1980) and who has obtained a 
    certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “cost accountant” means a cost 
    accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the 
    Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 of 1959), and who has obtained a 
    certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “legal practitioner” means an advocate,
    vakil or an attorney of any High Court, and includes a pleader in 
    practice. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appeal 
    to Supreme Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
    of 1908) or in any other law, an appeal shall lie against any order, not 
    being an interlocutory order, of the Appellate Tribunal to the Supreme Court 
    on one or more of the grounds specified in section 100 of that Code. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal 
    shall lie against any decision or order made by the Appellate Tribunal with 
    the consent of the parties. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    appeal under this section shall be preferred within a period of ninety days 
    from the date of the decision or order appealed against: 
 
Provided that 
    the Supreme Court may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period of ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
    by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Orders 
    passed by Appellate Tribunal to be executable as a decree.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An order passed by the Appellate Tribunal under this Act shall be executable 
    by the Appellate Tribunal as a decree of civil court, and for this purpose, 
    the Appellate Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1),  the Appellate 
    Tribunal may transmit any order made by it to a civil court having local 
    jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order as if it were a 
    decree made by that court. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Penalty 
    for wilful failure to comply with orders of Appellate Tribunal.—If 
    any person wilfully fails to comply with the order of the Appellate 
    Tribunal, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh 
    rupees and in case of a second or subsequent offence with fine which may 
    extend to two lakh rupees and in the case of continuing contravention with 
    additional fine which may extend to two lakh rupees for every day during 
    which such default continues. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Grants 
    by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make to the Authority grants of such sums of money as are 
    re­quired to pay salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and the 
    members  and the administrative expenses including the salaries, allowances 
    and pension payable to or in respect of officers and other employees of the 
    Authority. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a fund to be called the Telecom Regulatory 
    Authority of India General Fund and there shall be credited thereto— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all grants, fees and charges received 
    by the Authority under this Act; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all sums received by the Authority from 
    such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fund 
    shall be applied for meeting— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the salaries and allowances payable to 
    the Chairperson and members and the administrative expenses  including the 
    sala­ries, allowances and pension payable to or in respect of officers and 
    other employees of the Authority; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the expenses on objects and for 
    purposes authorised by this Act. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Authority shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual state­ment of accounts in such form as may be prescribed 
    by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority shall be audited by the Comp­troller and Auditor 
    General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and any 
    expenditure incurred in connection with such auditor shall be payable by  
    the Authority to the Comptroll­er and Auditor-General of India. 
 


    1[Explanation.—For 
    the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that the decisions of the 
    Authority taken in discharge of its functions under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) of section 11 and section 13, being 
    matters appealable to the Appellate Tribunal, shall not be subject to audit 
    under this section.] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by 
    him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have 
    the same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit 
    as the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally has, in connection with the 
    audit of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to 
    demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other 
    documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    Central Government  and that Government shall cause the same to be laid 
    before each House of Parliament. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Furnishing of returns, etc., to Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in 
    such form and manner as may be prescribed or as the Cen­tral Government may 
    direct, such returns and statements and such particulars in regard to any 
    proposed or existing programme for the promotion and development of the 
    telecommunication services, as the Central Government from time to time, 
    require. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall prepare once every year in such form and at such time as may 
    be prescribed, an annual report giving a summary of its activities during 
    the previous year and copies of the report shall be forwarded to the Central 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of 
    the report received under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as may be 
    after it is received, before each House of Parliament. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Power 
    of Central Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, from time to time, issue to the Au­thority such 
    directions as it may think necessary in the interest of the sovereignty and 
    integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with 
    foreign States, public order, decency or morality. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the foregoing provisions, the Authority shall, in exercise of 
    its powers or the performance of its func­tions, be bound by such directions 
    on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing to it 
    from time to time: 
 
Provided that 
    the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to 
    express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or 
    not shall be final. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Members, officers and employees of Authority to be public servants.—All 
    members, officers and other employees of the Authority shall be deemed, when 
    acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this 
    Act to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
    Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Bar of 
    jurisdiction.—No civil court 
    shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the Authority is 
    empowered by or under this Act to determine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central 
    Government or the Authority or any officer of Central Government or any 
    member, officer or other employees of the Authority for anything which is in 
    good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules or 
    regu­lations made thereunder. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of directions of Authority.—If 
    a person violates directions of the Authority, such person shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in case of 
    second or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to two lakh rupees 
    and in the case of continuing contravention with additional fine which may 
    extend to two lakh rupees for every day during which the default continues. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who 
    at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible 
    to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as 
    the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accord­ingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he has exercised all due diligence 
    to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Offences by Government Departments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of 
    Government, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    of­fence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly unless he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission 
    of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence under 
    this Act has been committed by a Department of Government and it is proved 
    that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any officer, other than the Head 
    of the Department, such officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that 
    offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Exemption from tax on wealth and income.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 (27 of 1957), the Income-tax 
    Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for the  time being in force 
    relating to tax on wealth, income, profits or gains, the Authority shall not 
    be liable to pay wealth-tax, income-tax or any other tax in respect of their 
    wealth, income, profits or gains derived. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Delegation.—The Authority may, by 
    general or special order in writing, delegate to any member, officer of the 
    Authority or any other person subject to such conditions, if any, as may be 
    specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this Act 
    (except the power to settle dispute under Chapter IV and to make regulation 
    under section 36) as it may deem necessary. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
    court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or the 
    rules or regulations made thereunder, save on a complaint made by the 
    Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court 
    inferior to that of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or a Chief Judicial 
    Magistrate of first class shall  try any offence punishable under this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of 
    this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the salary and allowances payable to 
    and the other conditions of service of the Chairperson and members under 
    sub-section (5) of section 5; 
 

1[(aa)    
    the allowance payable to the part-time members under sub-section (6A) of 
    section 5;] 
    1[(aa) the allowance payable to the part-time members 
    under sub-section (6A) of section 5;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the powers and functions of the 
    Chairperson under sub-section (1) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the procedure for conducting an inquiry 
    made under sub-section (2) of section 7; 
 

1[(ca)    
    the salary and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and 
    other employees of the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 10;] 1[(ca) 
    the salary and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and 
    other employees of the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 10;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the category of books of account or 
    other documents which are required to be maintained under sub-section (3) of 
    section 12; 
 

1[(da)    
    the form, the manner of its verification and the fee under sub-section (3) 
    of section 14A; 
    1[(da) the form, the manner of its verification and 
    the fee under sub-section (3) of section 14A;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>db</number>    the salary and allowances payable to 
    and other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and other 
    Members of the Appellate Tribunal under section 14E; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dc</number>    the salary and allowances and other 
    conditions of service of the officers and employees of the Appellate 
    Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 14H; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dd</number>    any other power of a civil court 
    required to be prescribed under clause (i) of sub-section (2) of section 
    16;] 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the period within which an application 
    is to be made under sub-section (1) of section 15; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the manner in which the accounts of the 
    Authority shall be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 23; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the time within which and the form and 
    manner in which re­turns and report are to be made to the Central Government 
    under sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    any other matter which is to be, or may 
    be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is to be made, by rules. 
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power 
    to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Authority may, by notifi­cation, make regulations consistent with this Act 
    and the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the times and places of meetings of the 
    Authority and the procedure to be followed at such meetings under 
    sub-section (1) of section 8, including quorum necessary for the transaction 
    of business; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the transaction of business at the 
    meetings of the Authority under sub-section (4) of section 8; 
 

1[***] 
               1[***]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    matters in respect of which 
    register is to be maintained by the authority  
2[under 
    sub-clause (vii) of clause (b)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;
2[under 
    sub-clause (vii) of clause (b)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    levy of fee and lay down such 
    other requirements on fulfil­ment of which a copy of register may be 
    obtained 
3[under 
    sub-clause (viii) of clause (b)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;
3[under 
    sub-clause (viii) of clause (b)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    levy of fees and other changes
    4[under 
    clause (c)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;
4[under 
    clause (c)] of sub-section (1) of section 11;" 
 
 
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Rules 
    and regulations to be laid  before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be 
    made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be with­out prejudice  to the validity 
    of anything previously done under that rule or regulation. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Application of certain laws.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to the provisions of the Indian 
    Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) and the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 
    1933 (17 of 1933) and, in particular, nothing in this Act shall affect any 
    jurisdiction, powers and functions required to be exercised or performed by 
    the Telegraph Authority in relation to any area falling within the 
    jurisdiction of such Authority. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Power 
    to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    any difficulty arises  in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty: 
 
Provided that 
    no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from 
    the date of commencement of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Telecom 
    Regulatory Authority of India Ordinance, 1997 (Ord. 11 of 1997) is hereby 
    repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of this Act.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>