<act><tid>949891</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL COURT TRIAL OF OFFENCES RELATING TO TRANSACTIONS 
INSECURITIES ACT, <year>1992</year></title>

NO. 27 OF <year>1992</year> 
[ 18th August, <year>1992</year>.]
An Act to provide for the establishment of a Special Court for the 
trial of offences relating to transactions in securities and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in. the Forty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-




<article><tid>568189</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1851850</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Special Court (Trial of offences Relating to Transactions in  
  Securities) Act, <year>1992</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>793018</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 6th day of 
June, <year>1992</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>135425</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the Context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1440096</tid>
<number>a</number>" Code" means the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>; (2  
  of <year>1974</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1099701</tid>
<number>b</number>" Custodian" means the Custodian appointed tinder sub- 
section (1) of section 3;

<subsection><tid>680973</tid>
<number>C</number>" securities" includes

<subsubsection><tid>993918</tid>
<number>i</number>shark scrips, stocks, bonds, debentures, 
debenture, stock,, units of the. Unit Trust, or India 
or any other mutual fund or other marketable securities, 
of a like nature in or of any incorporated company or 
other body corporate;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>186957</tid>
<number>ii</number>Government securities; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1237545</tid>
<number>iii</number>rights or interests, in securities;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1685137</tid>
<number>d</number>Special Court" means the Special Court established 
under sub- section of see on 5.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>172875</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appointment and functions of Custodian.
<section><tid>1279467</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may appoint one or more Custodians as it may deem fit for 
the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>940533</tid>
<number>2</number>The Custodian may, on being satisfied on information 
received that any person has been involved in any offence relating to 
transactions in securities after the 1st day of April, <year>1991</year> and on and 
before the 6th June, <year>1992</year>, notify the name of such, person in the 
Official Gazette.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>193</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1324437</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code and any other 
law for the time being in force, on and from the date of notification 
under subsection (2), any property, movable or immovable, or both, 
belonging to any person notified under that subsection shall stand 
attached simultaneously with the issue of the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1280234</tid>
<number>4</number>The property attached under sub- section (3) shall be dealt 
with by the Custodian in such manner as the Special Court may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>629815</tid>
<number>5</number>The Custodian may take assistance of arty person while 
exercising his powers or for discharging his duties under this section 
and section 4.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519905</tid>
<number> 4</number> Contracts entered into fraudulently may be cancelled.
<section><tid>242396</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
the Custodian is satisfied, after inequality as he may think fit, that 
any contract or agreement entered into at" my time after the 1st day 
of April, <year>1991</year> and on and before the 6th June, <year>1992</year> in relation to any 
property of the person notified under Sub- section (2) of section 3 has 
been entered into fraudulently or to defeat the provisions of this 
Act, he may cancel such contract or agreement and on such cancellation 
such property shall stand attached wider this Act:
Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled except 
after giving, to the parties to the contract or agreement I reasonable 
opportunity- of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1425174</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person aggrieved by it notification issued under sub- 
section (2) of section 3 or any cancellation made under sub- section 
 (1) of section 4 or any other order made by the Custodian in exercise 
of the powers conferred on him under section 3 or 4 may file a 
petition objecting to the same within thirty days of the assent to the 
Special Court (Trial of Offences Relating to Transactions in  
  Securities) Bill, <year>1992</year> by the President before the Special Court where 
such notification, cancellation or order has been issued before the 
date of assent to the Special Court (Trial of Offences Relating to  
  Transactions in securities) Bill, <year>1992</year> by the President find where 
such notification, cancellation or order has been issued on or after 
that date, within thirty days of the issuance of such notification, 
cancellation or order, as the case may be; and the Special Court after 
hearing the parties, may make such order as it deems fit.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613365</tid>
<number> 5</number> Establishment of Special Court.
<section><tid>1790193</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Court to 
be called the Special Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1269821</tid>
<number>2</number>The Special Court shall consist of a sitting Judge of the 
High Court nominated by the Chief Justice or of the High Court, within 
the local limits of whose jurisdiction tried Special Court in 
situated, with the concurrence of the Chief Justice of India.

</section>

<section><tid>371181</tid>
<number>3</number>[ When the office of the Judge of the Special Court is vacant 
by reason of absence or leave, the duties of the office shall be 
performed by such Judge of the High Court within the local limits of 
whose jurisdiction the Special Court is situated as the Chief Justice 
of India, nominate for the purpose and the Judge so appointed shall 
have all the jurisdiction and powers of the Judge of the Special Court 
including the powers to pass final orders.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1593796</tid>
<number>6</number>Cognizance of cases by Special Court. The Special Court shall 
take cognizance of or try such cases as are instituted before it or 
transferred to it as hereinafter provided.

</article>



<article><tid>365987</tid>
<number>7</number>Jurisdiction of Special Court. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law, any prosecution in respect of any offence 
referred to in sub- section (2) of section 3 shall be instituted only 
in the Special Court and any prosecution in respect of such offence 
pending in Hall court shall stand transferred to the Special Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1994</year>, 5. 2 (w. e. f. 25- 1- <year>1994</year>)




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>779414</tid>
<number>8</number>Jurisdiction of Special Court as to joint trials. The Special 
Court shall have jurisdiction to try any person concerned in the 
offence referred to in sub- section (2) of section 3 either as a 
principal conspirator or abettor and all other offences and accused 
persons as can be jointly tried therewith at one trial in accordance 
with the Code.

</article>



<article><tid>978627</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure and powers of Special Court.
<section><tid>710372</tid>
<number>1</number>The Special Court  
shall, in the trial of such cases, follow the procedure prescribed by 
the Code for the trial of warrant cases before a magistrate.

</section>

<section><tid>204174</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of 
the Code shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act, apply to the proceedings before the Special 
Court and for the purposes of the- said provisions of the Code, the 
Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court of Session and shall have 
all the Powers of a Court of Session, and the person conducting a 
prosecution before the Special Court shall be deemed to be a Public 
Prosecutor.

</section>

<section><tid>1715406</tid>
<number>3</number>The Special Court may pass upon any person convicted by it 
any sentence authorised by law for the punishment of the offence of 
which such person is convicted.

</section>

<section><tid>675209</tid>
<number>4</number>While dealing with any other matter brought before it, the 
Special Court may adopt such procedure as it may deem fit consistent 
with the principles of natural justice.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1124146</tid>
<number> 9A</number> Jurisdiction, powers, authority and procedure of Special 
Court in civil matters.
<section><tid>597120</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the commencement of the  
Special Court Trial of Offences Relating to Transactions in 
Securities Amendment Act, <year>1994</year>, the Special Court shall exercise all 
such jurisdiction, powers and authority as were exercisable, 
immediately before such commencement, by any civil court in relation 
to any matter or claim-

<subsection><tid>44870</tid>
<number>a</number>relating to any property standing attached under sub- 
section (3) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>634664</tid>
<number>b</number>arising out of transactions in securities entered into 
after the 1st day of April, <year>1991</year>, and on or before the 6th 
day of June, <year>1992</year>, in which, a person notified under sub- 
section (2) of section 3 is involved as a party, broker, 
intermediary or in any other manner.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1300189</tid>
<number>2</number>Every suit, claim or other legal proceeding (other than an  
  appeal) pending before any court immediately before the commencement 
of the Special Court (Trial of Offences Relating to Transactions in  
  Securities) Amendment Act, <year>1994</year>, being a suit, claim or proceeding, 
the cause of action whereon it is based is such that it would have 
been, if it had arisen after such commencement, within the 
jurisdiction of the Special Court under sub- section (1), shall stand 
transferred on such commencement to the Special Court and the Special 
Court may, on receipt of the records of such suit, claim or other 
legal proceeding proceed to deal with it, so far as may be, in the 
same manner as a suit, claim or legal proceeding from the stage which 
was reached before such transfer or from any earlier stage or de novo 
as the Special Court may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>740346</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the commencement of the Special Court (Trial of  
  Offences Relating to Transactions in Securities) Amendment Act, <year>1994</year>, 
no court other than the Special Court shall have, or be entitled to 
exercise, any jurisdiction, power or authority in relation to any 
matter or claim referred to in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>241154</tid>
<number>4</number>While dealing with cases relating to any matter or claim 
under this section, the Special Court shall not be bound by the pro- 
cedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) 
but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice, and subject 
to the other provisions of this Act and of any rules, the Special 
Court shall have power to regulate its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>464402</tid>
<number>5</number>Without prejudice to the other powers conferred under this 
Act the Special Court shall have, for the purposes of discharging its 
functions under this section, the same powers as are vested in a civil 
court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) while 
trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>484592</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1908641</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1647685</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693808</tid>
<number>d</number>Subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the 
Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, (1 of <year>1872</year>.) requisitioning any 
public record or document Or copy of such record or document 
from any office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1374234</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>520118</tid>
<number>f</number>reviewing its decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1220796</tid>
<number>g</number>dismissing a case for default or deciding it ex parte;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1459739</tid>
<number>h</number>setting aside any order of dismissal of any case for 
default or any order passed by it ex parte; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>848174</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which may be prescribed by the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 14.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1784479</tid>
<number> 9B</number> Powers of the Special Court in arbitration matters.
<section><tid>853384</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Special Court shall have the jurisdiction and powers of a Court 
conferred under the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>.) to decide any 
question forming the subject matter of a reference relating to any 
matter or claim mentioned in sub- section (1) of section 9A.

</section>

<section><tid>1921868</tid>
<number>2</number>Every suit or other proceeding (other than an appeal) in 
relation to any matter or claim referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 9A pending before any Court and governed by the Arbitration 
Act, <year>1940</year>, (10 of <year>1940</year>.) immediately before the date of commencement 
of the Special Court (Trial of Offences Relating' to Transactions in  
  Securities) Amendment Act, <year>1994</year> shall stand transferred on that date 
to the Special Court.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expressions 
" reference" shall have respectively the same under clauses (c) and (e) 
of section 2 of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year>; (10 of <year>1940</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>4157</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appeal.
<section><tid>758119</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything in the Code <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or the  
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> or the Arbitration Act <year>1940</year>][ decree] an 
appeal shall lie from any judgment sentence or order, not being 
interlocutory order, of the Special Court to the Supreme both on 
facts and on law.

</section>

<section><tid>1789229</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as aforesaid, no appeal or revision shall lie to any 
court from any judgment[ decree], sentence- or order of the Special 
Court.

</section>

<section><tid>193564</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a 
period of thirty days from the date of any judgment, sentence or order 
of the Special Court:
Provided that the Supreme Court may entertain an appeal after the 
expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within 
the Period of thirty days.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13011</tid>
<number> 11</number> Discharge of liabilities.
<section><tid>1425027</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Code. and any other law for the time being in force, 
the Special Court may make such order as it may deem fit directing the 
Custodian for the disposal of the property under attachment.

</section>

<section><tid>1001955</tid>
<number>2</number>The following liabilities shall be paid or discharged in 
full, as far as may be, in the order as under:-

<subsection><tid>686386</tid>
<number>a</number>all revenues, taxes, cesses and rates due from the 
persons notified by the Custodian under sub- section (2) of 
section 3 to the Central Government or any State Government 
or any local authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>788821</tid>
<number>b</number>all amounts due from the person so notified by the 
Custodian to any bank or financial- institution or mutual 
fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>779450</tid>
<number>c</number>any other liability as may be specified by the. 
Special Court from time to time.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>559901</tid>
<number> 11A</number> Power to punish for contempt. The Special Court shall 
have, and exercise, jurisdiction, powers and authority in respect of 
contempt of a High Court has and may exercise and, for this purpose, 
the provisions of the Contempt of Courts Act, <year>1971</year>, shall have effect 
subject to the modifications that-
<section><tid>924067</tid>
<number>a</number>the references therein to a High Court shall be 
construed as including a reference to such Special Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1621292</tid>
<number>b</number>the references to the Advocate- General in section 15 of 
the said Act, shall be construed, in relation to the Special 
Court, as a reference to the Attorney- General or the 
Solicitor- General or the Additional Solicitor- General.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1994</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f 25. 1. 1. <year>1994</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by S. 4 bid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by S. 5 bid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>287754</tid>
<number> 12</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>833045</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the Custodian for anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>786945</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any of its officers or other employees for any 
damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>781579</tid>
<number>13</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or 
in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.

</article>



<article><tid>921520</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>195343</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1021837</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as May be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session Or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>290663</tid>
<number> 15</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1850295</tid>
<number>1</number>The Special Court (Trial of Offences   
  Relating to Transactions in Securities) Ordinance, <year>1992</year> (Ord. 10 of  
  <year>1992</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1833501</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>