<act><title>


The Standards of Weights and Measures 
    (Approval of Models)
    Rules, 19871</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Standards of Weights and Measures (Approval of 
    Models) Rules, 1987. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date2 of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Standards of Weights 
    and Measures Act, 1976 (60 of 1976);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Director”, when used without any 
    qualifying words means the Director of Legal Metrology appointed under 
    section 28 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Model” means the final physical 
    representation of a weight or measure in which all the components imparting 
    to it the necessary metrological and technical characteristics and qualities
    3[as 
    defined in the Act and the Rules made thereunder] are suitably assembled so 
    that, subject to prescribed tolerances, every weight or measure produced in 
    accordance with such model may be similar as regards dimensions, 
    constructions, material performance and other metrological and technical 
    characteristics;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Schedule” means schedule annexed to 
    these rules;  
 

1[(e)    
    "Principal Officer" means the officer who is in charge of the laboratory.]  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    General provisions relating to laboratories.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The list of recognised laboratories shall be notified from time to time.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    laboratory shall not, unless it is either specified in the First Schedule or 
    is recognised under these rules, carry out any test for the approval of any 
    model.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    allocating any model of weight or measure to any laboratory, the Director 
    shall take into account the existence or otherwise of the facilities 
    available in that laboratory for the approval of such model.  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Recognition of laboratories.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every laboratory desirous of obtaining recognition under these rules for 
    carrying out tests for the approval of the model of any weight or measure 
    shall make an application to the Director in the form as shall be notified 
    from time to time.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    application, referred to in sub-rule (1), shall be made by the Principal 
    officer of the laboratory.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When an 
    application is made under sub-rule (1) for the recognition of a laboratory, 
    the Director shall, before issuing the certificate of recognition, send one 
    or more of his officers to the laboratory and obtain a report whether the 
    laboratory—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has the necessary measuring equipment, 
    testing facilities and buildings maintained in a proper condition;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has the necessary qualified staff, 
    component to undertake the tests for recommending the approval of model of 
    the concerned weight or measure;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    is situated in an appropriate 
    environment;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has an adequate recording system;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    is likely to give expeditious, 
    efficient and adequate service; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    is ready and willing to get its 
    equipment verified periodically by such other appropriate laboratory, as may 
    be specified by the Director;  
 

2[(g)    
    Whether they have the certificate issued by the National Accreditation Board 
    of Laboratories (NABL) in the parameter/fields in which model test is 
    proposed to be undertaken.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Director shall, after considering the information supplied to him by his 
    officer, or officers referred in sub-rule (3) and if necessary, after a 
    visit to the laboratory, shall issue to the applicant laboratory a 
    certificate of recognition specifying therein the terms and conditions 
    subject to which the recognition is granted, and the code number which has 
    been assigned to the laboratory.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no 
    application for the recognition of a laboratory has been made, or where such 
    application having been made, has not been disposed of the Director may if 
    he is satisfied that it is urgently necessary so to do issue, with the 
    consent of the principal officer incharge of the laboratory a provisional 
    certificate of recognition to a laboratory which, in the opinion of the 
    Director, fulfils all the requirements of sub-rule (3) and the provisional 
    certificate so issued shall be valid for one year.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    certificate of recognition granted to laboratory may be suspended by the 
    Director in the event of the omission or failure on the part of the 
    laboratory to observe the terms and conditions specified under sub-rule (4):  
 
Provided that 
    no such suspension shall be made except after giving to the laboratory a 
    reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where any 
    certificate of recognition to a laboratory is suspended under sub-rule (6), 
    the order of suspension shall not be vacated unless the omission of failure 
    of compliance of terms and conditions for which such suspension was made has 
    been made good.  
 


    3[(8) The Director or 
    his authorised officer may visit the laboratory as and when required and the 
    Principal Officer will permit inspections and render all assistance for the 
    purpose including the production of records with regard to model testing.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    Principal Officer shall submit annually to the Director a report in respect 
    of the models tested by them, the fee collected, time taken for each testing 
    and such other relevant particulars.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    Principal Officer, while testing the models adopt such procedures as may be 
    prescribed by the Director from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The 
    certificate of recognition granted to a laboratory may be cancelled by the 
    Director if the circumstances of the laboratory are such that it cannot be 
    reasonably expected to function properly as a recognized laboratory or if 
    there are sufficient reasons to suspect that the laboratory has been guilty 
    of corrupt practices:  
 
Provided that 
    no certificate of recognition shall be cancelled except after giving to the 
    concerned laboratory a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
    proposed action.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Application for the approval of models.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the approval of model shall be made to the Director and 
    shall contain—  
 

1[(a)    
    the full name and address of the applicant or where the model is imported 
    from other countries, the name and address of the manufacturer as well as 
    the dealer in India.]  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    a brief description of the weight or 
    measure, the class to which it belongs and the probable uses for which the 
    weight or measure is intended to be produced;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    data regarding metrological and 
    technical characteristics and qualities of the weight or measure;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    test procedure followed by the 
    manufacturers;  
 

1[(e)    
    trade name or brand name and type of the weight or measure.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    application shall be accompanied by not less than two copies of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a sketch and section-wise drawings of 
    general arrangements and installation of such weight or measure including 
    therein the details of construction of the weight or measure in such manner 
    as to enable the visualisation of the weight or measure in its finished 
    form, and;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a document describing the following, 
    namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the principles of construction and the 
    method of operation of the weight or measure.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the safety devices provided to prevent 
    any fraudulent or inaccurate operation of the weight or measure;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    the manner in which and the extent to 
    which the weight or measure may be adjusted or corrected;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    the place where the verification stamp 
    or seal, or both, may be affixed;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    plans of general arrangements and 
    installations, drawings of the weight or measure and, where necessary 
    detailed installation instructions;  
 

1[(vi)    
    two photographs of the model clearly indicating the mandatory declarations 
    to be included as a part of the certificate of approval of the model;]  
 

1[(vii)    
    actual circuit diagram (for digital type);  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>    place/places on the instrument where 
    the verification stamp or seal or both have to be applied to prevent 
    fraudulent practices;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ix</number>    copies of the user's manual, printed 
    pamphlets and other literatures;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>    any other information which the 
    applicant may consider to be useful for assessing the performance, and 
    facilitating the approval of the model.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    weight or measure is provided with supplementary or additional devices, full 
    information with regard to such supplementary or additional devices, such 
    as, drawing, description in relation to the said weight or measure, shall 
    also be given along with the application.  
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Submission of models of weight or measure.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person, who submits any model of weight or measure for approval 
    (hereinafter in this rule referred to as, the applicant), shall deposit to 
    the credit of the recognised laboratory, a fee determined at the rate 
    specified by the Director from time to time, subject to the maximum 
    prescribed under the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>1A</number> All the 
    documents referred to in rule 5 shall be sent by the Director to the 
    recognized laboratory which carries out the tests for the approval of the 
    model, to enable the laboratory to ascertain whether such documents conform 
    to the details of the results of the tests carried out by it for the 
    approval of that model.]  
 


    2[***]  
 


    1[(5) Where the nature 
    of weight or measure is such that due to its voluminous nature it cannot be 
    submitted to the laboratory for testing, the recognized laboratory may 
    undertake the testing of such model at such place as it may deem fit:  
 
Provided that, 
    where the test is undertaken at any premises other than those of a 
    recognized laboratory, the applicant shall pay for the duration of such 
    test, the travelling and daily allowances of the persons deputed for such 
    tests and such allowances shall be payable at such rates as may be 
    admissible to such persons in accordance with the rules in force in the 
    recognised laboratory].  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    applicant shall provide such facilities as may be required by the team of 
    persons deputed by the recognised laboratory for the purpose of carrying out 
    the necessary tests for the approval of the model.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    installation, tests and removal of the model shall be done at the cost and 
    risk of the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Central Government and the recognised laboratory shall not be responsible 
    for any loss or damage that the model may sustain during the course of 
    examination and testing.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where any 
    model submitted to a recognised laboratory for approval is not removed by 
    the applicant after the expiry of six months from the date on which a 
    certificate of approval was granted or refused in relation to such model, 
    such model shall become forfeited to the Central Government, and that 
    Government shall dispose of the model in such manner as it may think fit.  
 


    3[(10) The Director 
    may, if he is satisfied that the test for the approval of any model is 
    likely to take more than three months and on receipt of satisfactory 
    perliminary test reports from the laboratory, issue subject to such 
    conditions as may be specified in the certificate, a provisional certificate 
    to such conditions as may be specified in the certificate, a provisional 
    certificate to enable the manufacturer, to manufacture at his own risk the 
    weight or measure in relation to which the mdoel has been submitted for 
    approval:  
 
Provided that 
    manufacture, distribution or sale of such instrument shall be discontinued 
    immediately when the provisional model approval certificate has been 
    withdrawn by the Director:  
 
Provided 
    further that in case the tested model does not meet the requirements of the 
    model approval test, all instruments covered by the provisional certificate 
    and sold in the market shall be withdrawn with immediate effect at the 
    manufacturer's cost.]  
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Tests 
    for the approval of model.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The tests needed for the assessment of the fitness or otherwise of a model 
    submitted for approval shall be carried out under the normal conditions of 
    use, whether actual or simulated, of the weight or measure and shall be made 
    with a view to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    ascertaining whether such model 
    conforms to the standards established, in relation to such model, by or 
    under the Act 
1[and 
    the rules or to the recommendations of the International Organisation of 
    Legal Metrology (OIML)];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    finding out the ability of such model 
    to maintain accuracy and other metrological characteristics and qualities 
    after it has been put to use for such minimum number of times or over such 
    minimum period as the Director, may, by general order, specify in relation 
    to the class of weight or measure to which the model pertains;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    determining the performance of such 
    model under varied conditions of use;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    determining the metrological and 
    technical characteristics of the model after taking into account the 
    possible incidence of influence factors and their effect on metrological and 
    technical characteristics;  
 

2[(e)    
    determining whether the place or place of sealing on the instrument 
    suggested by the manufacturer is sufficient to prevent their fraudulent use;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    determining generally, the behaviour of 
    the model, that is to say, its robustness reliability and susceptibility to 
    fraudulent use:]  
 
Provided that, 
    in the case of a weight or measure which is required to possess any special 
    metrological or technical characteristics or behaviour, the assessment as to 
    the fitness for approval or otherwise of the model of such weight or measure 
    shall be made after carrying out such special tests as may be necessary for 
    determining the existence or otherwise of the required metrological or 
    technical characteristics or behaviour.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    model shall be tested in accordance with such test procedure as may be laid 
    down by the Director in relation to the class of weight or measure to which 
    such model pertains:  
 
Provided that 
    until the test procedure is laid down by the Director in relation to any 
    class of weight or measure, the test of any model pertaining to such class 
    of weight or measure shall be carried out in accordance with such procedure 
    as would, in the opinion of the recognised laboratory, enable it to 
    recommend the grant of certificate of approval in relation to such model.  
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Procedure for the issue of certificate of approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    After the completion of the tests, the recognised laboratory shall send a 
    report of its findings to the Director with its recommendations whether the 
    model satisfies the requirements of the Act and the rules made thereunder.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    recognised laboratory may, in an appropriate case, recommend that the 
    approval may be accorded provisionally to enable it to conduct detailed 
    tests and, where, in pursuance of such recommendation, provisional approval 
    is granted, tests may be carried out on such number of instruments under 
    such conditions of installation and use, as may be specified by the 
    Director, and such tests may also be continued, where the recognised 
    laboratory thinks fit so to do, in the place of use of the weight or 
    measure, and the tests at such place of use shall be detailed ones and of 
    such duration and carried out on such number of weights or measures as may 
    be specified by the Director.  
 


    1[(2A) The Director 
    may require the recognised laboratory to send to him the detailed test 
    procedure adopted by that laboratory in approving the concerned model.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    examination of report made by the recognised laboratory, the Director shall, 
    where he is of opinion that no further test is required to be carried out, 
    submit the report to the Central Government and where he is of opinion that 
    further tests are required, remit the report back to the recognised 
    laboratory for carrying out such further tests; and thereupon the recognised 
    laboratory shall, after carrying out further tests, submit a report to the 
    Director.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where, 
    after consideration of the report of the recognised laboratory, the Director 
    is of opinion that a certificate of approval in relation to that model 
    should be issued, it shall recommend to the Central Government the issue of 
    the certificate and shall also forward to that Government a copy of the 
    report submitted to it by the recognised laboratory.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government may, if the issue of a certificate, or provisional 
    certificate, of approval has been recommended by the Director, issue such 
    certificate and authorise the Director to authenticate the certificate for 
    and on behalf of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    provisional certificate issued under sub-rule (5) shall remain valid for a 
    period exceeding one year from the date of its issue:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, if it is satisfied, on the recommendation of the 
    recognised laboratory, it is necessary in the public interest so to do 
    extend the period of validity of a provisional certificate for such period 
    as it may think fit:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Central Government may also, on an application made to it 
    by the concerned manufacturer, extend the period of validity of the 
    provisional certificate for such further period as it may think fit if it is 
    satisfied that the recognised laboratory, having failed to complete the 
    tests before the expiry of the period of validity of the provisional 
    certificate, has unreasonably omitted to recommend the extension of such 
    period.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A code 
    number shall be assigned to each approved model and the code number so 
    assigned shall be indicated in the certificate, or provisional certificate 
    of approval, as the case may be.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Procedure where issue of certificate of approval is not recommended.—Where 
    the recognised laboratory does not recommend the issue of a certificate of 
    approval in relation to any model, it shall specify its reasons therefor to 
    the Director who shall communicate such reasons to the applicant with such 
    directions as he may think fit and thereupon the applicant may make a 
    representation to the Director to the effect that the issue of the 
    certificate of approval should have been recommended by the recognised 
    laboratory and on considering such representation, the Director may either 
    reject it or recommend to the Central Government the issue of certificate of 
    approval.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Re-submission of disapproved model for approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any model is not approved, the disapproved model may be re-submitted 
    for approval after carrying out therein such modifications as may be 
    necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    disapproved model is resubmitted for approval, it shall be deemed, for the 
    purposes of levy of fees and tests under these rules, to be a fresh 
    application for the approval of that model.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Contents of a certificate of approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The certificate of approval shall also contain the following information, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the number of the certificate;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a brief description of the model;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the mark assigned to the approved 
    model;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the category of the weight or measure;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    a brief statement of the results of the 
    tests;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the special conditions, if any, to be 
    complied with for the manufacture, verification and use of weights or 
    measures conforming to the model;  
 

1[(g)    
    the place or places where the verification seal or stamp or both may be 
    affixed.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    certificate of approval shall become effective on and from the date of its 
    publication in the Official Gazette.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    weight or measure is intended for a special use the certificate of approval 
    in relation to such weight or measure shall indicate the special use.  
 


    1[(4) The Director 
    shall cause the necessary model certificate to be published in the Official 
    Gazette.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Director may also cause the information referred to in the forgoing 
    sub-rules to be published in the journal, if any, published by the Central 
    Government.]   
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Mark of 
    approval.—
<section><number>1</number> The mark assigned 
    to the model shall contain the national identification letters, namely, IND, 
    the last two digits of the year of the issue (for example, 77) the code 
    number assigned to the laboratory and the code number assigned to the model.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The mark 
    assigned to the approved model shall be clearly and legibly affixed at such 
    place of the model as may be specified in the certificate of approval and 
    also on each weight or measure produced by the maker or manufacturer in 
    accordance with the approved model:  
 
Provided that 
    if the approved model of the weight or measure conforming to such model is 
    such that the mark assigned to the approved model cannot be affixed on it 
    (for example, where it is fragile or too small) that mark may be associated 
    with the conditions specified in the certificate of approval:  
 
Provided 
    further that, where the approval is of a limited character, the mark of 
    approval shall be accompanied by a special mark indicating the limitations 
    of the approval and different special marks may be made for different 
    limitations.  
 



 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 


    1[***]
 
 





 



 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Revocation of certificate of approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A certificate of approval may be revoked if the Central Government is 
    satisfied that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the model which had been previously 
    approved no longer complies with the units specified in the rules made under 
    the Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the model has ceased to conform to the 
    standards for the time being in force in relation to such model, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    defects in regards to reliability, 
    accuracy or performance have generally been noticed in the course of use of 
    the products (weights or measures) manufactured in accordance with such 
    model, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    where the manufacturer does not follow, 
    either wholly or partly, the conditions specified in the certificate of 
    approval;  
 

1[(e)    
    where the manufacturer or any other person has significantly altered the 
    approved design of the model or the circuit diagram.]  
 
Provided that 
    no such certificate shall be revoked unless the holder of such certificate 
    has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
    proposed action.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    certificate of approval of any model has been revoked, the production of any 
    weight or measure in accordance with such model shall be stopped on and from 
    such date as may be specified in such order of revocation and every weight 
    or measure made or manufactured at any time between the date of revocation 
    and the specified date shall, notwithstanding such revocation be subject to 
    verification in accordance with the provisions of the Act and the rules in 
    force on the date of such revocation:  
 
Provided that 
    where, on such verification, it is found that the use of any such weight or 
    measure is likely to cause errors, beyond those permitted for such weight or 
    measure, in any weighment or measurement carried out with it, the Director 
    may by order, prohibit the use of such weight or measure.  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Suspension of certificate of approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A certificate of approval of a model may be suspended by the Director in the 
    event of the omission or failure on the part of the holder of such 
    certificate; (i) to make or manufacture weights or measures in accordance 
    with the model to which the certificate relates or (ii) to conform to the 
    rules or standards in relation to any weight or measure manufactured in 
    accordance with the model, or (iii) to comply with the conditions specified 
    in the certificate of approval:  
 
Provided that 
    no such suspension shall be made except after giving to the holder of the 
    certificate a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed 
    action.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    certificate of approval has been suspended under sub-rule (1), the order of 
    suspension shall not be vacated unless the omission of failure for which 
    such suspension was made has been made good.  
 


    1[(3) Where the 
    certificate of approval has been suspended under sub-rule (1), an inventory 
    of the existing stock shall be made by the Controller of Legal Metrology of 
    the Concerned State. He will also ensure that no further sale will be made 
    unless the suspension of the certificate of approval is revoked by the 
    Director.]  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Revocation and suspension of certificate to be published.—Every 
    order of revocation or suspension of certificate of approval shall be 
    published, as far as may be, in the manner specified in 

    1[rule 11].  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Deposit of model or its drawings.—1[***]  
 <section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director may call for any weight or measure the model of which has been 
    approved or any of its component, or its dummy, where he is of the opinion 
    that it is necessary so to do in the public interest.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    approved models, parts, drawings or dummies, submitted in accordance with 
    sub-rules (1) and (2) shall be preserved for purpose of record and reference 
    and shall not be open to inspection by the public.  
 



 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 


    1[***]
 

 





 



 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Provisions relating to weight or measure for which model approval is 
    ordinarily not necessary.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the purpose of testing the model of any weight or measure, acquired under 
    sub-section (2) of section 36, the officer acquiring such weight or measure 
    shall intimate to the Director the need for the testing of the model of such 
    weight or measure, and, on receipt of such intimation the Director shall, if 
    he is satisfied that the model of such weight or measure needs testing, call 
    upon the manufacturer to produce such model for a test by the recognised 
    laboratory specified by him:  
 
Provided that 
    where there is no model of the weight or measure so acquired, it shall be 
    the duty of the manufacturer to furnish, from the manufacturing line, one 
    sample of the class of weight or measure and to produce such sample for test 
    by the recognised laboratory specified by the Director.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    recognised laboratory shall, as soon as may be practicable after carrying 
    out the tests referred to in sub-rule (1), make a report to the Director as 
    to the results of such test.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, on 
    persual of the results of such test, the Director is satisfied that the 
    model or sample, as the case may be, does not conform to the standards 
    established by or under the Act, he shall call upon the manufacturer to 
    remove the deficiencies within such time as may be specified by him; and if 
    the deficiencies are not removed within the time so specified, the licence 
    of the manufacturer, in so far as it relates to the manufacture for the 
    weight or measure, the model or sample of which was tested, shall be liable 
    to be cancelled.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Provisions relating to testing of substitute materials.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A substitute material referred to in sub-section (10) of section 36, shall 
    be sent by the manufacturer, within seven days from the date on which the 
    first commences to manufacture with the substitute material, to the Director 
    who shall cause it to be forwarded to a recognised appropriate laboratory 
    for approval.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    substitute material is sent to a recognised laboratory for test, such 
    laboratory shall conduct the necessary test and determine whether the use of 
    the substitute material would serve the purpose for which the model was 
    approved and in case the recognised laboratory is of the opinion that the 
    substitute material is not suitable it shall act in the manner specified in 
    sub-section (11) of section 36.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    recognised laboratory shall forward its findings to the Central Government 
    through the Director.  
 


    1[Fees for testing the 
    substitute material shall be payable by the manufacturer at such rates as 
    may be specified by the Director from time to time.]
 
 




 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 


 
 




The Standards of Weights and Measures 
    (Approval of Models)  

    Rules, 1987
 

 
 

 
 



1[***]
 


 
 



    ----------------------
 


  1.   The First 
    Schedule omitted by G.S.R. 492 (E), 
    dated 24th May, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-8-2000).
 



    ----------------------
 


 
 


 
 
 




</form><form>
 
 
 
 


 
 




The Standards of Weights and Measures 
    (Approval of Models)  

    Rules, 1987
 

 
 

 
 



1[***]
 


 
 



    ----------------------
 


  1.  Second Schedule omitted by G.S.R. 492 (E), 
    dated 24th May, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-8-2000).
 



    ----------------------
 


 
 


 
 
 




</form><form>
 
 
 
 


 
 




The Standards of Weights and Measures 
    (Approval of Models)  

    Rules, 1987
 

 
 

 
 



1[***]
 


 
 



    ----------------------
 


  1.   Third Schedule omitted by G.S.R. 492 (E), 
    dated 24th May, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-8-2000).
 



    ----------------------
 


 
 


 
 
 




</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>