<act><title>
THE
PRASAR BHARATI (BROADCASTING CORPORATION OF INDIA) ACT, 1990</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of India)
Act, 1990.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint. tc "(3) It shall come into force on
such date1 as the Central Government
may, by notification, appoint."
 


   







  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 


 <section><number>a</number>
"Akashvani" means the offices, stations and other
establishments, by whatever name called, which, immediately before the appointed
day, formed part of or were under the Director-General, All India Radio of the
Union Ministry of Information and Broadcasting; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
"appointed day" means the date appointed under section 3; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
"broadcasting" means the dissemination of any form of
communication like signs, signals, writing, pictures, images and sounds of all
kinds by transmission of electro-magnetic waves through space or through cables
intended to be received by the general public either directly or indirectly
through the medium of relay stations and all its grammatical variations and
cognate expressions shall be construed accordingly; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
"Board" means the Prasar Bharati Board; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
"Broadcasting Council" means the Council established under
section 14; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
"Chairman" means the Chairman of the Corporation appointed
under section 4; 


 </section><section><number>g</number>
"Corporation" means the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting
Corporation of India) established under section 3; 


 </section><section><number>h</number>
"Doordarshan" means the offices, kendras and other
establishments, by whatever name called, which, immediately before the appointed
day, formed part of or were under the Directorate-General, Doordarshan of the
Union Ministry of Information and Broadcasting;  


 </section><section><number>i</number>
"elected Member" means a Member elected under section 3; 


 </section><section><number>j</number>
"Executive Member" means the Executive Member appointed under 
section 4; 


 </section><section><number>k</number>
"kendra" means any telecasting centre with studios or
transmitters or both and includes a relay station; 


 </section><section>
(l)
"Member" means a member of the Board'; 


 </section><section><number>m</number> "Member
(Finance)" means the Member (Finance)
appointed under
section 4; 


 </section><section><number>n</number>
"Member (Personnel)" means the Member (Personnel) appointed
under section 4; 


 </section><section><number>o</number>
"Nominated Member" means the Member nominated by the Union
Ministry of Information and Broadcasting under section 3; 


 </section><section><number>p</number>
"Non-lapsable Fund" means the Fund created from the commercial
revenues of Akashvani and Doordarshan to meet expenditure on certain schemes; 


 </section><section><number>q</number>
"notification" means a notification published in the Official
Gazette; 


 </section><section><number>r</number>
"Part-time Member" means a Part-time Member of the Board
appointed under section 4, but does not include an ex officio Member, the
Nominated Member or an elected Member; 


 </section><section><number>s</number>
"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 


 </section><section><number>t</number>
"Recruitment Board" means a board established under sub-section
(1) of section 10; 


 </section><section><number>u</number>
"regulations" means regulations made by the Corporation under
this Act; 


 </section><section><number>v</number>
"station" means any broadcasting station with studios or
transmitters or both and includes a relay station; 


 </section><section><number>w</number> "Whole-time
Member" means the Executive Member, Member (Finance) or Member (Personnel); 


 </section><section><number>x</number>
"year" means the financial year. 


 

  

  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Establishment and 
Composition of Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> With 
effect from such date as the Central Government may by notification appoint in 
this behalf, there shall be established for the purposes of this Act a 
Corporation, to be known as the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of 
India).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Corporation shall be a 
body corporate by the name aforesaid, having  perpetual succession and a 
common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable 
and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the said name sue and be 
sued.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The headquarters of the 
Corporation shall be at New Delhi and the Corporation may establish offices, 
kendras or stations at other places in India and, with the previous approval of 
the Central Government, outside India.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The general superintendence, 
direction and management of the affairs of the Corporation shall vest in the 
Prasar Bharati Board which may exercise all such powers and do all such acts and 
things as may be exercised or done by the Corporation under this Act.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Board shall consist 
of—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  a Chairman;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  one Executive 
Member;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  one Member 
(Finance);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  one Member 
(Personnel);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  six Part-time 
Members;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  
Director-General (Akashvani), ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  
Director-General (Doordarshan), ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  one 
representative of the Union Ministry of Information and Broadcasting, to be 
nominated by that Ministry and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  two 
representatives of the employees of the Corporation, of whom one shall be 
elected by the engineering staff from amongst themselves and one shall be 
elected by the other employees from amongst themselves.
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The Corporation may appoint 
such committees as may be necessary for the efficient performance, exercise and 
discharge of its functions, powers and duties:
 Provided that all or a majority of 
the members of each committee shall be Members and a member of any such 
committee who is not a Member shall have only the right to attend meetings of 
the committee and take part in the proceedings thereof, but shall not have the 
right to vote.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Corporation may associate 
with itself, in such manner and for such purposes as may be provided by 
regulations, any person whose assistance or advice it may need in complying with 
any of the provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the 
right to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to the purposes for 
which he has been associated, but shall not have the right to vote.
 </section><section><number>8</number> No act or proceeding of the 
Board or of any committee appointed by it under sub-section (6) shall be 
invalidated merely by reason of—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  any vacancy in, 
or any defect in the constitution of, the Board or such committee; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  any defect in 
the appointment of a person acting as a Member or a member of such committee; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  any 
irregularity in the procedure of the Board or such committee not affecting the 
merits of the case.
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Appointment of Chairman and 
      other Members.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman and the other 
      Members, except the ex officio Members, the Nominated Member and 
      the elected Members shall be appointed by the President of India on the 
      recommendation of a committee consisting of—
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Chairman of the 
      Council of States, who shall be the Chairman of the committee; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Chairman of the 
      Press Council of India established under section 4 of the Press Council 
      Act, 1978 (37 of 1978); and  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> one nominee of the 
      President of India.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> No appointment of a Member 
      shall be invalidated merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in 
      the constitution of, the committee appointed under sub-section 
      (1).
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairman and the Part-time 
      Members shall be persons of eminence in public life; the Executive Member 
      shall be a person having special knowledge or practical experience in 
      respect of such matters as administration, management, broadcasting, 
      eduction, literature, culture, arts, music, dramatics or journalism, the 
      Member (Finance) shall be a person having special knowledge or practical 
      experience in respect of financial matters and the Member (Personnel) 
      shall be a person having special knowledge or practical experience in 
      respect of personnel management and administration.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The recommendations made by the 
      committee constituted under sub-section (1) shall be binding for the 
      purposes of appointment under this section. tc 
"(4) The recommendations made by the committee constituted under sub-section (1) 
shall be binding for the purposes of appointment under this section."
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Powers and functions of 
      Executive Member.—The Executive Member shall be the 
      Chief Executive of the Corporation and shall, subject to the control and 
      supervision of the Board, exercise such powers and discharge such 
      functions of the Board as it may delegate to him. 
 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Term of office, conditions of service, etc., of Chairman and other 
Members. </title>— <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman shall be Part-time Member and 
shall hold office for a term of three years from the date on which he enters 
upon his office or until he attains the age of seventy years, whichever is 
earlier: 
 Provided that any person holding office as a Chairman immediately before the 
commencement of the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of India) Amendment 
Act, 2008, shall, in so far as his appointment is inconsistent with the 
provisions of this sub-section, cease to hold office on such commencement as 
such Chairman and shall not be entitled to any compensation because of his 
ceasing to hold such office.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] The Member (Finance) and the Member (Personnel) shall 
be Whole-time Members and every such Member shall hold office for a term of six 
years from the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains the 
age of sixty-two years, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> The Executive Member shall be a Whole-time Member and shall 
hold office for a term of five years from the date on which he enters upon his 
office or until he attains the age of sixty-five years, whichever is earlier: 

 Provided that any person holding office as an Executive Member immediately 
before the commencement of the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of 
India) Amendment Act, 2008 shall, in so far as his appointment is inconsistent 
with the provisions of this sub-section, cease to hold office on such 
commencement as such Executive Member and shall not be entitled to any 
compensation because of his ceasing to hold such office.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The term of office of Part-time Members shall be six years, but one-third 
of such Members shall retire on the expiration of every second year. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The term of office of an elected Member shall be two years or till he 
ceases to be an employee of the Corporation, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> As soon as may be after the establishment of the Corporation, the 
President of India may, by order, make such provision as he thinks fit for 
curtailing the term of office of some of the Part-time Members then appointed in 
order that one-third of the Members holding office as such Part-time Members 
shall retire in every second year thereafter. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where before the expiry of the term of office of a person holding the 
office of Chairman, or any other Member, a vacancy arises, for any reason 
whatsoever, such vacancy shall be deemed to be a casual vacancy and the person 
appointed or elected to fill such vacancy shall hold office for the unexpired 
period of the term for which his predecessor in office would have held office if 
such vacancy had not arisen. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Whole-time Members shall be the employees of the Corporation and as 
such shall be entitled to such salaries and allowances and shall be subject to 
such conditions of service in respect of leave, pension (if any), provident fund 
and other matters as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that the salaries and allowances and the conditions of service shall 
not be varied to their disadvantage after their appointment. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Chairman and Part-time Members shall be entitled to such allowances 
as may be prescribed. 







</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Removal and suspension of 
      Chairman and Members.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of 
      sub-section (3), the Chairman or any other Member, except an  ex officio Member, the 
      Nominated Member and an elected Member, shall only be removed from his 
      office by order of the President of India on the ground of misbehaviour 
      after the Supreme Court, on a reference being made to it by the President, 
      has, on inquiry held in accordance with such procedure as the Supreme 
      Court may by rules provide, reported that the Chairman or such other 
      Member, as the case may be, ought, on such ground, be removed. 
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The President may suspend from 
      office the Chairman or other Member except an  ex officio Member, the 
      Nominated Member or an elected Member, in respect of whom a reference has 
      been made to the Supreme Court under sub-section (1) until the President 
      has passed orders on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on such 
      reference. tc 
"(2) The President may suspend from office the Chairman or other Member except 
an  ex officio Member, the Nominated Member or 
an elected Member, in respect of whom a reference has been made to the Supreme 
Court under sub-section (1) until the President has passed orders on receipt of 
the report of the Supreme Court on such reference."
 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in sub-section (1), the President may, by order, remove the 
      Chairman or any Whole-time Member from his office if such Chairman or such 
      Whole-time Member— tc 
"(3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the President may, 
by order, remove the Chairman or any Whole-time Member from his office if such 
Chairman or such Whole-time Member—"
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ceases to be a citizen 
      of India; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> is adjudged an 
      insolvent; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> engages during his term 
      of office in any paid employment outside the duties of his office; or 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> is convicted of any 
      offence involving moral turpitude; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> is, in the opinion of 
      the President, unfit to continue in office by reason of infirmity of body 
      or mind:  
 Provided that the President may, by 
      order, remove any Part-time Member from his office if he is adjudged an 
      insolvent or is convicted of any offence involving moral turpitude or 
      where he is, in the opinion of the President, unfit to continue in office 
      by reason of infirmity of body or mind. tc 
"Provided that the President may, by order, remove any Part-time Member from his 
office if he is adjudged an insolvent or is convicted of any offence involving 
moral turpitude or where he is, in the opinion of the President, unfit to 
continue in office by reason of infirmity of body or mind."
 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> If the Chairman or any 
      Whole-time Member, except any ex officio Member, the Nominated 
      Member or any elected Member, is, or becomes in any way concerned or 
      interested in any contract or agreement made by or on behalf of the 
      Corporation or the Government of India or the Government of a State or, 
      participates in any way in the profit thereof, or in any benefit or 
      emolument arising therefrom than as a member, and in common with other 
      members of an incorporated company, he shall, for the purposes of 
      sub-section (1), be deemed to be guilty of misbehaviour. tc 
"(4) If the Chairman or any Whole-time Member, except any ex officio 
Member, the Nominated Member or any elected Member, is, or becomes in any way 
concerned or interested in any contract or agreement made by or on behalf of the 
Corporation or the Government of India or the Government of a State or, 
participates in any way in the profit thereof, or in any benefit or emolument 
arising therefrom than as a member, and in common with other members of an 
incorporated company, he shall, for the purposes of sub-section (1), be deemed 
to be guilty of misbehaviour."
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If a Part-time Member is, or 
      becomes in any way concerned, or interested in any contract or agreement 
      made by or on behalf of the Corporation, he shall, for the purposes of 
      sub-section (1), be deemed to be guilty of misbehaviour. tc 
"(5) If a Part-time Member is, or becomes in any way concerned, or interested in 
any contract or agreement made by or on behalf of the Corporation, he shall, for 
the purposes of sub-section (1), be deemed to be guilty of misbehaviour."
 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Chairman or any other 
      Member may resign his office by giving notice thereof in writing to the 
      President of India and on such resignation being accepted, the Chairman or 
      other Member shall be deemed to have vacated his office. tc 
"(6) The Chairman or any other Member may resign his office by giving notice 
thereof in writing to the President of India and on such resignation being 
accepted, the Chairman or other Member shall be deemed to have vacated his 
office."  
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meetings of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Board shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of 
procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including 
the quorum at meetings) as may be provided by regulations: 
 


 
Provided that there shall not be less than six meetings every year but three 
months shall not intervene between one meeting and the next meeting. tc 
"Provided that there shall not be less than six meetings every year but three 
months shall not intervene between one meeting and the next meeting."
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall be deemed to have vacated his office if he absents himself 
for three consecutive meetings of the Board without the leave of the Chairman. tc 
"(2) A Member shall be deemed to have vacated his office if he absents himself 
for three consecutive meetings of the Board without the leave of the Chairman."
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairman shall preside at the meetings of the Board and if for any 
reason he is unable to attend any meeting, the Executive Member and in the 
absence of both, any other Member elected by the Members present at such 
meeting, shall preside at the meeting. tc "(3) The Chairman 
shall preside at the meetings of the Board and if for any reason he is unable to 
attend any meeting, the Executive Member and in the absence of both, any other 
Member elected by the Members present at such meeting, shall preside at the 
meeting."
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All questions which come up before an meeting of the Board shall be decided 
by a majority of the votes of the Members present and voting and, in the event 
of an equality of votes, the Chairman, or in his absence, the person presiding, 
shall have and exercise a second or casting vote. tc 
"(4) All questions which come up before an meeting of the Board shall be decided 
by a majority of the votes of the Members present and voting and, in the event 
of an equality of votes, the Chairman, or in his absence, the person presiding, 
shall have and exercise a second or casting vote."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Officers and other employees of 
      Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Subject to such control, restrictions and conditions as may be prescribed, 
      the Corporation may appoint, after consultation with the Recruitment 
      Board, the Director-General (Akashvani), the Director-General 
      (Doordarshan) and such other officers and other employees as may be 
      necessary. 
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The method of recruitment of 
      such officers and employees and all other matters connected therewith and 
      the conditions of service of such officers and other employees shall be 
      such as may be provided by regulations. tc 
"(2) The method of recruitment of such officers and employees and all other 
matters connected therewith and the conditions of service of such officers and 
other employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations."
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Establishment of Recruitment 
      Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
      Corporation shall, as soon as may be, after the appointed day and in such 
      manner and subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be 
      prescribed, establish for the purposes of section 9, one or more 
      Recruitment Boards consisting wholly of persons other than the Members, 
      officers and other employees of the Corporation: 
 
 Provided that for the purposes of 
      appointment to the posts carrying scales of pay which are not less than 
      that of a Joint Secretary to the Central Government, the Recruitment Board 
      shall consist of the Chairman, other Members, the ex officio 
      Members, the Nominated Member and the elected Members. tc 
"Provided that for the purposes of appointment to the posts carrying scales of 
pay which are not less than that of a Joint Secretary to the Central Government, 
the Recruitment Board shall consist of the Chairman, other Members, the ex 
officio Members, the Nominated Member and the elected Members."
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The qualifications and other 
      conditions of service of the members constituting the Recruitment Board 
      and the period for which such members shall hold office, shall be such as 
      may be prescribed. tc 
"(2) The qualifications and other conditions of service of the members 
constituting the Recruitment Board and the period for which such members shall 
hold office, shall be such as may be prescribed."
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Transfer of service of existing 
      employees to Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Central Government 
      has ceased to perform any functions which under section 12 are the 
      functions of the Corporation, it shall be lawful for the Central 
      Government to transfer, by order and with effect from such date or dates 
      as may be specified in the order, to the Corporation any of the officers 
      or other employees serving in the Akashvani or Doordarshan and engaged in 
      the performance of those functions: 
 
 Provided that no order under this 
      sub-section shall be made in relation to any officer or other employee in 
      the Akashvani or Doordarshan who has, in respect of the proposal of the 
      Central Government to transfer such officer or other employee to the 
      Corporation, intimated within such time as may be specified in this behalf 
      by the Central Government, his intention of not becoming an employee of 
      the Corporation. tc "Provided that no order 
under this sub-section shall be made in relation to any officer or other 
employee in the Akashvani or Doordarshan who has, in respect of the proposal of 
the Central Government to transfer such officer or other employee to the 
Corporation, intimated within such time as may be specified in this behalf by 
the Central Government, his intention of not becoming an employee of the 
Corporation."
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The provisions of sub-section 
      (1) shall also apply to the members of the Indian Information Service the 
      Central Secretariat Service or any other service or to persons borne on 
      cadres outside Akashvani and Doordarshan who have been working in 
      Akashvani or Doordarshan immediately before the appointed day: tc 
"(2) The provisions of sub-section (1) shall also apply to the members of the 
Indian Information Service the Central Secretariat Service or any other service 
or to persons borne on cadres outside Akashvani and Doordarshan who have been 
working in Akashvani or Doordarshan immediately before the appointed day\:"
 
 Provided that where any such member 
      intimates, within the time specified in sub-section (1), his intention of 
      not becoming an employee of the Corporation but to continue on deputation, 
      he may be allowed to continue on deputation in accordance with such terms 
      and conditions as may be prescribed. tc 
"Provided that where any such member intimates, within the time specified in 
sub-section (1), his intention of not becoming an employee of the Corporation 
but to continue on deputation, he may be allowed to continue on deputation in 
accordance with such terms and conditions as may be prescribed."
 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In making an order under 
      sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, as far as may be, take into 
      consideration the functions which the Akashvani or, as the case may be, 
      Doordarshan has ceased or ceases to perform and the area in which such 
      functions have been or are performed. tc 
"(3) In making an order under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, as 
far as may be, take into consideration the functions which the Akashvani or, as 
the case may be, Doordarshan has ceased or ceases to perform and the area in 
which such functions have been or are performed."
 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An officer or other employee 
      transferred by an order under sub-section (1) shall, on and from the date 
      of transfer, cease to be an employee of the Central Government and become an employee of the 
      Corporation with such designation as the Corporation may determine and 
      shall, subject to the provisions of sub-sections (5) and (6), be governed 
      by such regulations as may be made as respects remuneration and other 
      conditions of service including pension, leave and provident fund and 
      shall continue to be an officer or other employee of the Corporation 
      unless and until his employment is terminated by the Corporation. tc 
"(4) An officer or other employee transferred by an order under sub-section (1) 
shall, on and from the date of transfer, cease to be an employee of the Central 
Government and become an employee of the 
Corporation with such designation as the Corporation may determine and shall, 
subject to the provisions of sub-sections (5) and (6), be governed by such 
regulations as may be made as respects remuneration and other conditions of 
service including pension, leave and provident fund and shall continue to be an 
officer or other employee of the Corporation unless and until his employment is 
terminated by the Corporation."
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every officer or other employee 
      transferred by an order made under sub-section (1) shall, within six 
      months from the date of transfer, exercise his option, in writing, to be 
      governed– tc "(5) Every officer 
or other employee transferred by an order made under sub-section (1) shall, 
within six months from the date of transfer, exercise his option, in writing, to 
be governed–"
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> by the scale of pay 
      applicable to the post held by him in the Akshvani or Doordarshan 
      immediately before the date of transfer or by the scale applicable to the 
      post under the Corporation to which he is transferred; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> by the leave, 
      provident, fund, retirement or other terminal benefits admissible to 
      employees of the Central Government in accordance with the rules or orders 
      of the Central Government, as amended from time to time, or the leave, 
      provident fund or other terminal benefits admissible to the employees of 
      the Corporation under the regulations,  
 and such option once exercised 
      under this Act shall be final: tc 
"and such option once exercised under this Act shall be final\:"
 
 Provided that the option exercised 
      under clause (a) by an officer or other employee shall be applicable only 
      in respect of the post under the Corporation to which such officer or 
      other employee is transferred and on appointment to a higher post under 
      the Corporation he shall be eligible only for the scale of pay applicable 
      to such higher post: tc 
"Provided that the option exercised under clause (a) by an officer or other 
employee shall be applicable only in respect of the post under the Corporation 
to which such officer or other employee is transferred and on appointment to a 
higher post under the Corporation he shall be eligible only for the scale of pay 
applicable to such higher post\:"
 
 Provided further that if 
      immediately before the date of his transfer any such officer or other 
      employee is officiating in a higher post under the Government either in a 
      leave vacancy or any other vacancy of a specified duration, his pay on 
      transfer shall be protected for the unexpired period of such vacancy and 
      thereafter he shall be entitled to the scale of pay applicable to the post 
      under the Government to which he would have reverted or to the scale of 
      pay applicable to the post under the Corporation to which he is 
      transferred whichever he may opt: tc 
"Provided further that if immediately before the date of his transfer any such 
officer or other employee is officiating in a higher post under the Government 
either in a leave vacancy or any other vacancy of a specified duration, his pay 
on transfer shall be protected for the unexpired period of such vacancy and 
thereafter he shall be entitled to the scale of pay applicable to the post under 
the Government to which he would have reverted or to the scale of pay applicable 
to the post under the Corporation to which he is transferred whichever he may 
opt\:"  
 Provided also that when an officer 
      or other employee serving in the Union Ministry of Information and 
      Broadcasting or in any of its attached or subordinate offices is promoted 
      to officiate in a higher post in the Ministry or office subsequent to the 
      transfer to the Corporation of any other officer or employee senior to him 
      in that Ministry or office before such transfer, the officer or other 
      employee who is promoted to officiate in such higher post shall, on 
      transfer to the Corporation, be entitled only to the scale of pay 
      applicable to the post he would have held but for such promotion or the 
      scale of pay applicable to the post under the Corporation to which he is 
      transferred, whichever he may opt. tc 
"Provided also that when an officer or other employee serving in the Union 
Ministry of Information and Broadcasting or in any of its attached or 
subordinate offices is promoted to officiate in a higher post in the Ministry or 
office subsequent to the transfer to the Corporation of any other officer or 
employee senior to him in that Ministry or office before such transfer, the 
officer or other employee who is promoted to officiate in such higher post 
shall, on transfer to the Corporation, be entitled only to the scale of pay 
applicable to the post he would have held but for such promotion or the scale of 
pay applicable to the post under the Corporation to which he is transferred, 
whichever he may opt."
 
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> No officer or other employee 
      transferred by an order made under sub-section (1) or sub-section 
      (2),— tc "(6) No officer or other 
employee transferred by an order made under sub-section (1) or sub-section 
(2),—"  
 <subsection><number>a</number> shall be dismissed or removed by an 
      authority subordinate to that competent to make a similar or equivalent 
      appointment under the Corporation as may be specified in the 
      regulations;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
shall be dismissed or removed or reduced in rank except after an 
      inquiry in which he has been informed of the charges against him and given 
      a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges: 

 Provided that where it is proposed 
      after such inquiry to impose upon him any such penalty, such penalty may 
      be imposed on the basis of evidence adduced during such inquiry and it 
      shall not be necessary to give such person an opportunity of making 
      representation on the proposed penalty: tc 
"Provided that where it is proposed after such inquiry to impose upon him any 
such penalty, such penalty may be imposed on the basis of evidence adduced 
during such inquiry and it shall not be necessary to give such person an 
opportunity of making representation on the proposed penalty\:"
 
 Provided further that clause (b) 
      shall not apply where an officer or other employee is dismissed or removed 
      or reduced in rank on the ground of conduct which has led to his 
      conviction on a criminal charge. tc 
"Provided further that clause (b) shall not apply where an officer or other 
employee is dismissed or removed or reduced in rank on the ground of conduct 
which has led to his conviction on a criminal charge."
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Functions and powers of 
      Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Subject to the provisions of this Act, it shall be the primary duty of the 
      Corporation to organise and conduct public broadcasting services to 
      inform, educate and entertain the public and to ensure a balanced 
      development of broadcasting on radio and television. 
 
 Explanation.— For the removal of doubts, it is 
      hereby declared that the provisions of this section shall be in addition 
      to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of the Indian Telegraph Act, 
      1885 (13 of 1885). 
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Corporation shall, in the 
      discharge of its functions, be guided by the following objectives, 
      namely:— tc 
"(2) The Corporation shall, in the discharge of its functions, be guided by the 
following objectives, namely\:—"
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> upholding the unity and integrity 
      of the country and the values enshrined in the Constitution; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> safeguarding the citizen's right to 
      be informed freely, truthfully and objectively on all matters of public 
      interest, national or international, and presenting a fair and balanced 
      flow of information including contrasting views without advocating any 
      opinion or ideology of its own;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
paying special attention to the fields of education and spread of 
      literacy, agriculture, rural development, environment, health and family 
      welfare and science and technology;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
providing adequate coverage to the diverse cultures and languages 
      of the various regions of the country by broadcasting appropriate 
      programmes;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
providing adequate coverage to sports and games so as to encourage 
      healthy competition and the spirit of sportsmanship; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
providing appropriate programmes keeping in view the special needs 
      of the youth;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
informing and stimulating the national consciousness in regard to 
      the status and problems of women and paying special attention to the 
      upliftment of women;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
promoting social justice and combating exploitation, inequality and 
      such evils as untouchability and advancing the welfare of the weaker 
      sections of the society;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
safeguarding the rights of the working classes and advancing their 
      welfare;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
serving the rural and weaker sections of the people and those 
      residing in border regions, backward or remote areas; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
providing suitable programmes keeping in view the special needs of 
      the minorities and tribal communities;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>
taking special steps to protect the interests of children, the 
      blind, the aged, the handicapped and other vulnerable sections of the 
      people;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>
promoting national integration by broadcasting in a manner that 
      facilitates communication in the languages in India; and facilitating the 
      distribution of regional broadcasting services in every State in the 
      languages of that State;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number>
providing comprehensive broadcast coverage through the choice of 
      appropriate technology and the best utilisation of the broadcast 
      frequencies available and ensuring high quality reception; 
       
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number>
promoting research and development activities in order to ensure 
      that radio and television broadcast technology are constantly updated; 
      and  
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> expanding broadcasting 
      facilities by establishing additional channels of transmission at various 
      levels.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> In particular, and without 
      prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions, the Corporation 
      may take such steps as it thinks fit— tc 
"(3) In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provisions, the Corporation may take such steps as it thinks fit—"
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> to ensure that 
      broadcasting is conducted as a public service to provide and produce 
      programmes;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> to establish a system 
      for the gathering of news for radio and television; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> to negotiate for 
      purchase of, or otherwise acquire, programmes and rights or privileges in 
      respect of sports and other events, films, serials, occasions, meetings, 
      functions or incidents of public interest for broadcasting and to 
      establish procedures for the allocation of such programmes, rights or 
      privileges to the services;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> to establish and 
      maintain a library or libraries of radio, television and other 
      materials;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> to conduct or 
      commission, from time to time, programmes, audience research, market or 
      technical service, which may be released to such persons and in such 
      manner and subject to such terms and conditions as the Corporation may 
      think fit;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> to provide such other 
      services as may be specified by regulations.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Nothing in sub-sections (2) and 
      (3) shall prevent the Corporation from managing on behalf of the Central 
      Government and in accordance with such terms and conditions as may be 
      specified by that Government the broadcasting of External Services and 
      monitoring of broadcasts made by organisations outside India on the basis 
      of arrangements made for reimbursement of expenses by the Central 
      Government. tc "(4) Nothing in 
sub-sections (2) and (3) shall prevent the Corporation from managing on behalf 
of the Central Government and in accordance with such terms and conditions as 
may be specified by that Government the broadcasting of External Services and 
monitoring of broadcasts made by organisations outside India on the basis of 
arrangements made for reimbursement of expenses by the Central Government."
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> For the purposes of ensuring 
      that adequate time is made available for the promotion of the objectives 
      set out in this section, the Central Government shell have the power to 
      determine the maximum limit of broadcast time in respect of the 
      advertisement. tc 
"(5) For the purposes of ensuring that adequate time is made available for the 
promotion of the objectives set out in this section, the Central Government 
shell have the power to determine the maximum limit of broadcast time in respect 
of the advertisement."
 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Corporation shall be 
      subject to no civil liability on the ground merely that it failed to 
      comply with any of the provisions of this section. tc 
"(6) The Corporation shall be subject to no civil liability on the ground merely 
that it failed to comply with any of the provisions of this section."
 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Corporation shall have 
      power to determine and levy fees and other service charges for or in 
      respect of the advertisements and such programmes as may be specified by 
      regulations: tc "(7) The 
Corporation shall have power to determine and levy fees and other service 
charges for or in respect of the advertisements and such programmes as may be 
specified by regulations\:"
 
 Provided that the fees and other 
      service charges levied and collected under this sub-section shall not 
      exceed such limits as may be determined by the Central Government, from 
      time to time. tc 
"Provided that the fees and other service charges levied and collected under 
this sub-section shall not exceed such limits as may be determined by the 
Central Government, from time to time."
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Parliamentary Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be constituted a Committee consisting of twenty-two Members of 
Parliament, of whom fifteen from the House of the People to be elected by the 
Members thereof and seven from the Council of States to be elected by the 
Members thereof in accordance with the system of proportional representation by 
means of the single transferable vote, to oversee that the Corporation 
discharges its functions in accordance with the provisions of this Act and, in 
particular, the objectives set out in section 12 and submit a report thereon to 
Parliament. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Committee shall function in accordance with such rules as may be made by 
the Speaker of the House of the People. tc 
"(2) The Committee shall function in accordance with such rules as may be made 
by the Speaker of the House of the People."
 


  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Establishment of Broadcasting 
      Council, term of office and removal, etc., of members 
      thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
      shall be established, by notification, as soon as may be after the 
      appointed day, a Council, to be known as the Broadcasting Council, to 
      receive and consider complaints referred to in section 15 and to advise 
      the Corporation in the discharge of its functions in accordance with the 
      objectives set out in section 12. 
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Broadcasting Council shall 
      consist of— tc 
"(2) The Broadcasting Council shall consist of—"
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a President and ten 
      other members to be appointed by the President of India from amongst 
      persons of eminence in public life;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> four Members of 
      Parliament, of whom two from the House of the People to be nominated by 
      the Speaker thereof and two from the Council of States to be nominated by 
      the Chairman thereof.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The President of the 
      Broadcasting Council shall be a whole-time member and every other member 
      shall be a part-time member and the President or the part-time member 
      shall hold office as such for a term of three years from the date on which 
      he enters upon his office. tc 
"(3) The President of the Broadcasting Council shall be a whole-time member and 
every other member shall be a part-time member and the President or the 
part-time member shall hold office as such for a term of three years from the 
date on which he enters upon his office."
 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Broadcasting Council may 
      constitute such number of Regional Councils as it may deem necessary to 
      aid and assist the Council in the discharge of its functions. tc "(4) The Broadcasting 
Council may constitute such number of Regional Councils as it may deem necessary 
to aid and assist the Council in the discharge of its functions."
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The President of the 
      Broadcasting Council shall be entitled to such salary and allowances and 
      shall be subject to such conditions of service in respect of leave, 
      pension (if any), provident fund and other matters as may be 
      prescribed: tc 
"(5) The President of the Broadcasting Council shall be entitled to such salary 
and allowances and shall be subject to such conditions of service in respect of 
leave, pension (if any), provident fund and other matters as may be 
prescribed\:"
 
 Provided that the salary and 
      allowances and the conditions of service shall not be varied to the 
      disadvantage of the President of the Broadcasting Council after his 
      appointment. tc "Provided that the salary 
and allowances and the conditions of service shall not be varied to the 
disadvantage of the President of the Broadcasting Council after his 
appointment."
 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The other members of the 
      Broadcasting Council and the members of the Regional Councils constituted 
      under sub-section (4) shall be entitled to such allowances as may be 
      prescribed. tc "(6) The other members of 
the Broadcasting Council and the members of the Regional Councils constituted 
under sub-section (4) shall be entitled to such allowances as may be prescribed."
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Jurisdiction of, and the 
      procedure to be followed by, Broadcasting Council.—
<section><number>1</number> The Broadcasting Council shall 
      receive and consider complaints from— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> any person or group of 
      persons alleging that a certain programme or broadcast or the functioning 
      of the Corporation in specific cases or in general is not in accordance 
      with the objectives for which the Corporation is established; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> any person (other than 
      an officer or employee of the Corporation) claiming himself to have been 
      treated unjustly or unfairly in any manner (including unwarranted invasion 
      of privacy, misrepresentation, distortion or lack of objectivity) in 
      connection with any programme broadcast by the Corporation. 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A complaint under sub-section 
      (1) shall be made in such manner and within such period as may be 
      specified by regulations. tc 
"(2) A complaint under sub-section (1) shall be made in such manner and within 
such period as may be specified by regulations."
 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Broadcasting Council shall 
      follow such procedure as it thinks fit for the disposal of complaints 
      received by it. tc 
"(3) The Broadcasting Council shall follow such procedure as it thinks fit for 
the disposal of complaints received by it."
 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the complaint is found to be 
      justified either wholly or in part, the Broadcasting Council shall advise 
      the Executive Member to take appropriate action. tc "(4) If the complaint is found to be 
justified either wholly or in part, the Broadcasting Council shall advise the 
Executive Member to take appropriate action."
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If the Executive Member is 
      unable to accept the recommendation of the Broadcasting Council, he shall 
      place such recommendation before the Board for its decision 
thereon. tc "(5) If the Executive 
Member is unable to accept the recommendation of the Broadcasting Council, he 
shall place such recommendation before the Board for its decision thereon."
 
 </section><section><number>6</number> If the Board is also unable to 
      accept the recommendation of the Broadcasting Council, it shall record its 
      reasons therefor and inform the Broadcasting Council accordingly. tc "(6) If the Board is also 
unable to accept the recommendation of the Broadcasting Council, it shall record 
its reasons therefor and inform the Broadcasting Council accordingly."
 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in sub-sections (5) and (6), where the Broadcasting Council 
      deems it appropriate, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
      require the Corporation to broadcast its recommendations with respect to a 
      complaint in such manner as the Council may deem fit. tc 
"(7) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (5) and (6), where the 
Broadcasting Council deems it appropriate, it may, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, require the Corporation to broadcast its recommendations with respect 
to a complaint in such manner as the Council may deem fit."
 
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Transfer of certain assets, 
      liabilities, etc., of Central Government to Corporation.—As from the appointed day— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> all property and assets 
      (including the Non-lapsable Fund) which immediately before that day vested 
      in the Central Government for the purpose of Akashvani or Doordarshan or 
      both shall stand transferred to the Corporation on such terms and 
      conditions as may be determined by the Central Government and the book 
      value of all such property and assets shall be treated as the capital 
      provided by the Central Government to the Corporation; 

 </section><section><number>b</number> all debts, obligations 
      and liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and 
      things engaged to be done by, with or for the Central Government 
      immediately before such day for or in connection with the purposes of 
      Akashvani or Doordarshan or both shall be deemed to have been incurred, 
      entered into and engaged to be done by, with or for the Corporation; 

 </section><section><number>c</number> all sums of money due 
      to the Central Government in relation to the Akashvani or Doordarshan or 
      both immediately before such day shall be deemed to be due to the 
      Corporation;  
 </section><section><number>d</number> all suits and other 
      legal proceedings instituted or which could have been instituted by or 
      against the Central Government immediately before such day for any matter 
      in relation to the Akashvani or Doordarshan or both may be continued or 
      instituted by or against the Corporation.  
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Grants, etc., by Central Government.—For 
the purposes of enabling the Corporation to discharge its functions efficiently 
under this Act, the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Corporation in each financial year— 
 


 <section>
<number>i</number> the proceeds of the 
broadcast receiver licence fees, if any, as reduced by the collection charges; 
and 


 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>
such other sums of money as that Government considers necessary, 


 
by way of equity, grant-in-aid or loan. tc "by way of equity, 
grant-in-aid or loan."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Fund of Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall have its own Fund and all the receipts of the Corporation 
(including the amounts which stand transferred to the Corporation under section 
16) shall be credited to the Fund and all payments by the Corporation shall be 
made therefrom. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in one or more 
nationalised banks in such manner as the Corporation may decide. tc 
"(2) All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in one or more 
nationalised banks in such manner as the Corporation may decide."
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Corporation may spend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its 
functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable 
out of the Fund of the Corporation. tc 
"(3) The Corporation may spend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its 
functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable 
out of the Fund of the Corporation."
 


 
Explanation.—For the 
purposes of this section, "nationalised bank" means a corresponding new bank 
specified in the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and 
Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 or a corresponding new bank specified in the 
First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
Undertakings) Act, 1980. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Investment of moneys.—The 
Corporation may invest its moneys in the securities of the Central Government or 
any State Government or in such other manner as may be prescribed. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Annual Financial Statement of the Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall prepare, in each financial year, an Annual Financial 
Statement for the next financial year showing separately— 
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the expenditure which 
is proposed to be met from the internal resources of the Corporation; and  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the sums required 
from the Central Government to meet other expenses, and distinguishing— 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> revenue expenditure from other 
expenditure; and 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> non-plan expenditure from plan 
expenditure. 


 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Annual Financial Statement shall be prepared in such form and forwarded 
at such time to the Central Government for its approval as may be agreed to by 
that Government and the Corporation. tc 
"(2) The Annual Financial Statement shall be prepared in such form and forwarded 
at such time to the Central Government for its approval as may be agreed to by 
that Government and the Corporation."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Accounts and audit of Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form and in such manner as may 
be prescribed. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and any 
expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Corporation to the Comptroller and Auditor-General. tc 
"(2) The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and any 
expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Corporation to the Comptroller and Auditor-General."
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Comptroller and Auditor-General and any person appointed by him in 
connection with the audit of the accounts of the Corporation shall have the same 
rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the 
Comptroller and Auditor-General has in connection with the audit of Government 
accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Corporation. tc 
"(3) The Comptroller and Auditor-General and any person appointed by him in 
connection with the audit of the accounts of the Corporation shall have the same 
rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the 
Comptroller and Auditor-General has in connection with the audit of Government 
accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Corporation."
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the Corporation as certified by the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf 
together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before 
each House of Parliament.

  


</section></article> 
 The Prasar Bharti (Broadcasting Corporation of India) Act, 
1990
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum><number>22</number> 
Corporation not liable to be taxed.—[Repealed 
by Act 20 of 2002, sec. 163 (w.e.f. 
1-4-2003).]
  






</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power of Central Government to give directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, from time to time as and when occasion arises, issue 
to the Corporation such directions as it may think necessary in the interests of 
the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India or the security of the State or 
preservation of public order requiring it not to make a broadcast on a matter 
specified in the direction or to make a broadcast on any matter of public 
importance specified in the direction. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Corporation makes a broadcast in pursuance of the direction issued 
under sub-section (1), the fact that such broadcast has been made in pursuance 
of such direction may also be announced along with such broadcast, if the 
Corporation so desires. tc "(2) Where the 
Corporation makes a broadcast in pursuance of the direction issued under 
sub-section (1), the fact that such broadcast has been made in pursuance of such 
direction may also be announced along with such broadcast, if the Corporation so 
desires."
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of every direction issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid before 
each House of Parliament. tc "(3) A copy of 
every direction issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of 
Parliament."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Power of Central Government to obtain information.—The 
Central Government may require the Corporation to furnish such information as 
that Government may consider necessary. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Report to Parliament in certain matters and recommendations as to action 
against the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Board persistently makes default in complying with any directions 
issued under section 23 or fails to supply the information required under 
section 24, the Central Government may prepare a report thereof and lay it 
before each House of Parliament for any recommendation thereof as to any action 
(including supersession of the Board) which may be taken against the Board. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the recommendation of the Parliament, the President may by notification 
supersede the Board for such period not exceeding six months as may be specified 
in the notification: tc 
"(2) On the recommendation of the Parliament, the President may by notification 
supersede the Board for such period not exceeding six months as may be specified 
in the notification\:"
 


 
Provided that before issuing the notification under this sub-section, the 
President shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to show cause as to 
why it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanations and 
objections, if any, of the Board. tc "Provided that before 
issuing the notification under this sub-section, the President shall give a 
reasonable opportunity to the Board to show cause as to why it should not be 
superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the 
Board."
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Upon the publication of the notification under sub-section (2),— tc 
"(3) Upon the publication of the notification under sub-section (2),—"
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> all the Members shall, as from the date 
of supersession, vacate their offices as such; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> all the powers, functions and duties 
which may, by or under the provisions of this Act be exercised or discharged by 
or on behalf of the Board, shall, until the Board is reconstituted under this 
Act, be exercised and discharged by such person or persons as the President may 
direct. 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the 
notification issued under sub-section (2), the President may reconstitute the 
Board by fresh appointments, and in such a case any person who had vacated his 
office under clause (a) of sub-section (3) shall not be disqualified for 
appointment: tc 
"(4) On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the 
notification issued under sub-section (2), the President may reconstitute the 
Board by fresh appointments, and in such a case any person who had vacated his 
office under clause (a) of sub-section (3) shall not be disqualified for 
appointment\:"
 


 
Provided that the President may, at any time before the expiration of the period 
of supersession, take action under this sub-section. tc 
"Provided that the President may, at any time before the expiration of the 
period of supersession, take action under this sub-section."
 


 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central Government shall cause the notification issued under sub-section 
(2) and a full report of the action 
taken under this section to be laid before each House of Parliament. tc 
"(5) The Central Government shall cause the notification issued under 
sub-section (2) and a full report of the action taken under this 
section to be laid before each House of Parliament."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Office of member not to disqualify a Member of Parliament.—It 
is hereby declared that the office of the member of the Broadcasting Council or 
of the Committee constituted under section 13 shall not disqualify its holder 
for being chosen as, or for being, a Member of either House of Parliament. 
 


  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Chairman, Members, etc., to be public servants.—The 
Chairman and every other Member, every officer or other employee of the 
Corporation and every member of a committee thereof, the President and every 
member of the Broadcasting Council or every member of a Regional Council or a 
Recruitment Board shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Corporation, the Chairman 
or any Member or officer or other employee thereof or the President or a member 
of the Broadcasting Council or a member of a Regional Council or a Recruitment 
Board for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or of any rules or regulations made thereunder. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Authentication of orders and other instruments of Corporation.—All 
orders and decisions of the Corporation shall be authenticated by the signature 
of the Chairman or any other Member authorised by the Corporation in this behalf 
and all other instruments executed by the Corporation shall be authenticated by 
the signature of the Executive Member or by any officer of the Corporation 
authorised by him in this behalf. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Delegation of powers.—The 
Corporation may, by general or special order, delegate to the Chairman or any 
other Member or to any officer of the Corporation, subject to such conditions 
and limitations, if any, as may be specified therein, such of its powers and 
duties under this Act as it may deem fit. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Annual report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall prepare once in every calendar year, in such form and 
within such time as may be prescribed an annual report giving a full account of 
its activities (including the recommendations and suggestions made by the 
Broadcasting Council and the action taken thereon) during the previous year and 
copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government and that Government 
shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Broadcasting Council shall prepare once in every calendar year, in such 
form and within such time as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a full 
account of its activities during the previous year and copies thereof shall be 
forwarded to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to 
be laid before each House of Parliament. tc 
"(2) The Broadcasting Council shall prepare once in every calendar year, in such 
form and within such time as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a full 
account of its activities during the previous year and copies thereof shall be 
forwarded to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to 
be laid before each House of Parliament."
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— tc 
"(2) In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely\:—"
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the salaries and allowances and 
conditions of service in respect of leave, pension (if any), provident fund and 
other matters in relation to the Whole-time Members under sub-section (7) of 
section 6; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the allowances payable to the Chairman 
and Part-time Members under sub-section (8) of section 6; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the control, restrictions and 
conditions subject to which the Corporation may appoint officers and other 
employees under sub-section (1) of section 9; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the manner in which and the conditions 
and restrictions subject to which a Recruitment Board may be established under 
sub- 
section (1) of section 10; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> The qualifications and other conditions 
of service of the members of a Recruitment Board and their period of office 
under sub-section (2) of section 10; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> the terms and conditions in accordance 
with which the deputation may be regulated under sub-section (2) of section 11; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the salary and allowances and 
conditions of service in respect of 
leave, pension (of any), provident fund and other matters in relation to the 
President of the Broadcasting Council under sub-section (5) of section 14; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> the allowances payable to other members 
of the Broadcasting Council and the members of the Regional Councils, under 
sub-section (6) of section 14; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> the manner in which the Corporation may 
invest its moneys under 
section 19; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> the form and the manner in which the 
annual statement of accounts shall be prepared under sub-section (1) of section 
21; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> the form in which, and the time within 
which the Corporation and the Broadcasting Council shall prepare their annual 
report under section 31; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> any other matter which is required to 
be, or may be, prescribed. 



  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation may, by notification, make regulations not inconsistent with 
this Act and the rules made thereunder for enabling it to perform its functions 
under this Act. 
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such regulations 
may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— tc 
"(2) Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such regulations 
may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely\:—"
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the manner in which 
and the purposes for which the Corporation may associate with itself any person 
under sub-section (7) of section 3; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the times and places 
at which meetings of the Board shall be held and, the procedure to be followed 
thereat, and the quorum necessary for the transaction of the business at a 
meeting of the Board under sub-section (1) of section 8; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the methods of 
recruitment and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the 
Corporation under sub-section (2) of 
section 9; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the remuneration and 
other conditions of service, including pension, leave and provident fund in 
relation to an officer or other employee of the Corporation under sub-section 
(4) of section 11; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the authority 
competent to make certain appointments referred to in clause (a) of sub-section 
(6) of section 11; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> the services which 
may be provided by the Corporation under clause (f) of sub-section (3) of 
section 12; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the determination and 
levy of fees and other service charges in respect of advertisements and other 
programmes under sub-section (7) of section 12; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> the manner in which 
and the period within which complaints may be made under sub-section (2) of 
section 15; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> any other matter in 
respect of which provision is, in the opinion of the Corporation, necessary for 
the performance of its functions under this Act: 


 
Provided that the regulations under clause (c) or clause (d) shall be made only 
with the prior approval of the Central Government. tc 
"Provided that the regulations under clause (c) or clause (d) shall be made only 
with the prior approval of the Central Government."
 



  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power to remove difficulties.—If 
any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as it may deem 
necessary, for the removal of the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of three 
years from the appointed day.

  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Came into force on 15-9-1997, vide S.O. 509 (E), dated 22nd July,
1997, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 22nd
July, 1997.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 12 of 2008, sec. 2(a), for sub-section (1) 
(w.r.e.f. 7-2-2008). Sub-section (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> The words “The Executive Member,” omitted by Act 12 of 2008, 
sec. 2(b) (w.r.e.f. 7-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Act 12 of 2008, sec. 2(c) (w.r.e.f. 7-2-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Section 22, before repeal by Act 20 of 2002, stood as 
under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>