<act> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 20001
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Cyber Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) 
Rules, 2000. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  “Act’’ means the Information 
Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  “agent” means a person duly 
authorised by a party to present an application or reply on its behalf before 
the Tribunal; 
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  “application” means an application 
made to the Tribunal under section 57; 
 </section><section>
   <number>d</number>  “legal practitioner” shall have the 
same meaning as is assigned to it in the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1971);
 </section><section>
   <number>e</number>  “Presiding Officer” means the 
Presiding Officer of the Tribunal; 
 </section><section>
    <number>f</number>  “Registrar” means the Registrar of 
the Tribunal and includes any officer to whom the powers and functions of the 
Registrar may be delegated; 
 </section><section>
   <number>g</number>  “registry” means the registry of the 
Tribunal; 
 </section><section>
   <number>h</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;

 </section><section>
    <number>i</number>  “transferred application” means the 
suit or other proceeding which has been transferred to the Tribunal under 
sub-section (1) of section 29; 
 </section><section>
    <number>j</number>  “Tribunal” means the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal established under section 48. 
 
 
</section></article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Procedure for filing 
applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application to the Tribunal shall be presented in Form 1 annexed to these 
rules by the applicant in person or by an agent or by a duly authorized legal 
practitioner, to the Registrar or sent by registered post addressed to the 
Registrar. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application under 
sub-rule (1) shall be presented in six complete sets in a paper-book form along 
with one empty file size envelope bearing full address of the respondent. Where 
the number of respondents is more than one, sufficient number of extra 
paper-books together with required number of empty file size envelopes bearing 
the full address of each respondent shall be furnished by the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The applicant may 
attach to and present with his application a receipt slips as in Form No. 1 
which shall be signed by the Registrar or the officer receiving the applications 
on behalf of the Registrar in acknowledgement of the receipt of the application.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub rules (1), (2) and (3), the Tribunal may permit—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  more than one person to join together 
and file a single application if it is satisfied, having regard to the cause of 
action and the nature of relief prayed for, that they have the same interest in 
the service matter; or
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  an Association representing the 
persons desirous of joining in a single application provided, however, that the 
application shall disclose the names of all the persons on whose behalf it has 
been filed.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Presentation and 
scrutiny of applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar, or the officer authorised by the Registrar shall endorse on every 
application the date on which it is presented or deemed to have been presented 
under that rule and shall sign the endorsement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the 
application is found to be in order, it shall be duly registered and given a 
serial number.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the application, on 
scrutiny, is found to be defective, and the defect noticed is formal in nature, 
the Registrar may allow the party to rectify the same in his presence, and if 
the said defect is not formal in nature, the Registrar may allow the applicant 
such time to rectify the defect as he may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the applicant fails 
to rectify the defect within the time allowed under sub- rule (3), the Registrar 
may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register the 
application.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An appeal against the 
order of the Registrar under sub-rule (4) shall be made within 15 days of the 
making of such order to the Tribunal whose decision thereon shall be final.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Place of filing 
application.—The 
applicant shall file application with the Registrar.
 
 
</article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Application fee.—Every 
application filed with the Registrar shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 
2,000/- (rupees two thousand) only which shall be either in the form of a 
crossed demand draft or a pay order drawn on a Scheduled Bank in favour of the 
Registrar and payable at New Delhi.
 
 
</article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Contents of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application filed under rule 3 shall set forth concisely under distinct 
heads, the grounds for such application and such grounds shall be numbered 
consecutively and typed in double space on one side of the paper.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall not be 
necessary to present a separate application to seek an interim order or 
direction if the application contains a prayer seeking an interim order or 
direction pending final disposal of the application.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An application may, 
subsequent to the filing of application under section 57 of the Act, apply for 
an interim order or direction. Such an application shall, as far as possible, be 
in the same form as is prescribed for on application under section 57 and shall 
be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 5/- (Rupees five only) which shall be payable in 
court fee stamps affixed on such application.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
the Cyber 
Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Paper book, etc. 
to accompany the application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application shall be accompanied by a paper book containing—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>  a certified copy of the order 
against which the application has been filed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>  copies of the documents relied upon 
by the applicant and referred to in the application; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>iii</number>  an index of documents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The documents referred 
to in sub-rule (I) may be attested by an advocate or by a gazetted officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an application 
is filed by an agent, documents authorising him to act as such agent shall also 
be appended to the application:
 
Provided that where an 
application is filed by an advocate it shall be accompanied by a duly executed ‘Vakalatnama’.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Plural remedies.—An 
application shall be based upon a single cause of action and may seek one or 
more reliefs provided they are consequential to one another.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Service of notice of 
application on the respondents.—(1) 
A copy of the application in the paper-book shall ordinarily be served on each 
of the respondents by the Registrar in one of the following modes:—
 <section>
    <number>i</number>  hand delivery (dasti) through the 
applicant or through a process server; or 
 </section><section>
    <number>ii</number>  through registered post with 
acknowledgement due.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Registrar may, taking into account the 
number of respondents and their places of residence or work and other 
circumstances direct that notice of the application shall be served upon the 
respondents in any other manner including any manner of substituted service, as 
it appear to the Registrar just and convenient.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> Every applicant shall 
pay a fee for the service or execution of processes, in respect of an 
application where the number of respondents exceeds five, as under—
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>1</number>  a sum of Rs. 50 (Rupees fifty) for 
each respondent in excess of five respondents; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>2</number>  where the service is in such manner 
as the Registrar may direct under sub-rule (2), a sum not exceeding the actual 
charges incurred in effecting the service as may be determined by the Registrar.

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> The fee for the 
service or execution of processes under sub-rule (3) shall be remitted by the 
applicant either in the form of a crossed Demand Draft drawn on a Scheduled Bank 
in favour of the Registrar and payable at the station where Registrar’s office 
is situated or remitted through a crossed Indian Postal Order drawn in favour of 
the Registrar and payable in General Post Office of the station where the 
Tribunal is located.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rules (1), (2), (3) and (4), if the Tribunal is 
satisfied that it is not reasonably practicable to serve notice of application 
upon all the respondents, if may for reasons to be recorded in writing, direct 
that the application shall be heard notwithstanding that some of the respondents 
have not been served with notice of the application, provided that no 
application shall be heard unless—
 
 
•  
notice of the application has been served on the Government, if Government is 
respondent;
 
 
•  
notice of the application has been served on the authority which passed the 
order against which the application has been filed; and
 
 
•  
the Tribunal is satisfied that the interests of the respondents on whom notice 
of the application has not been served are adequately and sufficiently 
represented by the respondents on whom notice of the application has been 
served. 
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Filing of reply and 
other documents by the respondent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The respondent shall file six complete sets containing the reply to the 
application alongwith the documents in a paper-book form with the Registrar 
within one month of the date of service of the notice of the application on him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The respondent shall 
also serve a copy of the reply along with copies of documents as mentioned in 
sub-rule (1) to the applicant or his advocate, if any, and file proof of such 
service with the Registrar. The Tribunal may, on application by the respondent, 
allow filing of the reply after the expiry of the period of one month.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Date and place of 
hearing to be notified.—The 
Tribunal shall notify to the parties the date
and the place of 
hearing of the application.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Sittings of the 
Tribunal.—The 
Tribunal shall ordinarily hold its sittings at 
New Delhi:
 
Provided that, if at any 
time, the Presiding Officer of the Tribunal is satisfied that circumstances 
exist which render it necessary to have sittings of the Tribunal at any place 
other than New Delhi the Presiding Officer may direct to hold the sittings at 
any such appropriate place.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Decision on 
applications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Tribunal shall draw up a calendar for the hearing of transferred cases and as 
far as possible hear and decide the cases according to the calendar.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application 
shall be heard and decided, as far as possible, within six months of the date of 
its presentation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For purposes of 
sub-rules (1) and (2), the Tribunal shall have the power to decline an 
adjournment and to limit the time for oral arguments.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Hearing on application
ex-parte.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where on the date fixed for hearing the application or on any other date to 
which hearing is adjourned, the applicant appears and the respondent does not 
appear when the application is called on for hearing, the Tribunal may, in its 
discretion, adjourn or hear and decide the application ex-parte.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an application 
has been heard ex-parte against a respondent or respondents, such 
respondent or respondents may apply to the Tribunal for an order to set it aside 
and if such respondent or respondents satisfy the Tribunal that the notice was 
not duly served, or that he or they were prevented by any sufficient cause from 
appearing when the application was called on for hearing, the Tribunal may make 
an order setting aside the ex-parte hearing as against him or them upon 
such terms as it thinks fit, and shall appoint a day for proceeding with the 
application:
 
Provided that where the 
ex-parte hearing of the application is of such nature that it cannot be set 
aside as against one respondent only, it may be set aside as against all or any 
of the other respondents also:
 
Provided further that 
Tribunal shall not set aside ex-parte hearing of an application merely on 
the ground that there has been an irregularity in the service of notice, if it 
is satisfied that the respondent had notice of the date of hearing and had 
sufficient time to appear and answer the applicant’s claim.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Adjournment of 
application.—The 
Tribunal may on such terms as it deems fit and at any stage of the proceedings 
adjourn the hearing of the application.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Order to be signed and 
dated.—Every 
order of the Tribunal shall be in writing and shall be signed and dated by the 
Presiding Officer.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Publication of orders.—Such 
of the orders of the Tribunal as are deemed fit for publication in any report or 
the press may be released for such publication on such terms and conditions as 
the Tribunal may lay down.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Communication of 
orders to parties.—Every 
order passed on an application shall be communicated to the applicant and to the 
respondent either in person or by registered post free of cost.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> No fee for inspection 
of records.— No 
fee shall be charged for inspecting the records of a pending application by a 
party thereto.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Orders and directions 
in certain cases.—The 
Tribunal may make such orders or give such directions as may be necessary or 
expedient to give effect or in relation to its orders or to prevent abuse of its 
process or to secure the ends of justice.
 
 
</article> 
 THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
  
 <article><number>23</number> Registration of legal 
practitioners clerks.—
<section><number>1</number> A clerk employed by a legal 
practitioner and permitted as such to have access to the records and to obtain 
copies of the orders of the Tribunal in which the legal practitioner ordinarily 
practices shall be known as a “registered clerk”.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A legal practitioner 
desirous of registering his clerk shall make an application to the Registrar in 
Form 2.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A legal practitioner shall 
have at a time not more than two registered clerks unless the Registrar by 
general or special order otherwise permits.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A register of all the 
registered clerks shall, be maintained in the office of the Registrar and after 
registration of the clerk, the Registrar sliall direct the issue of an identity 
card to him which shall be non transferable and shall be produced by the holder 
upon request by an officer or any other employee of the Tribunal.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The identity card mentioned 
in sub-rule (4) shall be issued under the signatures of the Registrar of the 
Tribunal.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Whenever a legal 
practitioner ceases to employ a registered clerk, he shall notify the fact at 
once to the Registrar by means of a letter enclosing therewith the identity card 
issued to his clerk and on receipt of such letter the name of the said 
registered clerk shall be struck off from the register.
  </section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Working hours of the 
Tribunal.—Except 
on Saturday, Sunday and other holidays, the offices of the Tribunal shall, 
subject to any order made by the Presiding Officer, remain open daily from 10.00 
a.m. to 5.00 p.m. but no work, unless it is of an urgent nature, shall be 
admitted after 4.30 p.m. on any working day.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Sitting hours of the 
Tribunal.—The 
sitting hours of the Tribunal shall ordinarily be from 10.30 a.m. to 1.00 p.m. 
and 2.00 p.m. to 5.00 p.m. 
subject to any order made by the Chairman.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Powers and functions 
of the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Register shall have the custody of the records of the Tribunal and shall 
exercise such other functions as may be assigned to him under these rules or by 
the Presiding Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may, 
with the approval of the Presiding Officer, delegate to another officer of the 
Tribunal any functions required by these rules to be exercised by the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the absence of the 
Registrar, officer of the Tribunal authorised in writing by the Presiding 
Officer in his behalf may perform or exercise any of the functions and powers of 
the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Registrar shall 
keep in his custody the official seal of the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Registrar shall, 
subject to any general or special direction by the Presiding Officer, affix the 
official seal of the Tribunal on any order, notice or other process.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Registrar shall 
have the power to authorise in writing the affixing of the seal of the Tribunal 
on a certified copy of any order of the Tribunal.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Additional powers and 
duties of Registrar.—In 
addition to the powers conferred elsewhere in these rules, the Registrar shall 
have the following powers and duties subject to any general or special order of 
the Presiding Officer namely:—
 <section>
    <number>i</number>  to receive all applications and 
other documents including transferred applications;
 </section><section>
    <number>ii</number>  to decide all questions arising out 
of the scrutiny of the applications before they are registered;
 </section><section>
   <number>iii</number>  to require any application 
presented to the Tribunal to be amended in accordance with the Act and the 
rules;
 </section><section>
   <number>iv</number>  subject to the directions of the 
Tribunal, to fix dates of hearing of the applications or other proceedings and 
issue notices thereof;
 </section><section>
   <number>v</number>  to direct any formal amendment of 
records;
 </section><section>
   <number>vi</number>  to order grant of copies of 
documents to parties to the proceedings;
 </section><section>
  <number>vii</number>  to dispose of all matters, relating 
to the service of notices of other processes, applications for the issue of 
fresh notices or for extending the time therefore;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>  to requisition records from the 
custody of any court or other authority;
 </section><section>
   <number>ix</number>  to receive applications for the 
substitution of legal representatives of the deceased parties, during the 
pendency of the application;
 </section><section>
   <number>x</number>  to receive and dispose of 
applications for substitution, except where the substitution would involve 
setting aside an order or abatement; and
 </section><section>
   <number>xi</number>  to receive and dispose of 
application by parties for return of documents.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Seal and emblem.—The 
official seal and emblem of the Tribunal shall be such as the Government may 
specify.
 
 
</article><form>
 

THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 

 
 

FORM 1
 

(See 
rule 4)
 

APPLICATION UNDER SECTION 57 OF 
THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY ACT, 2000
 

For use in Tribunal’s 
Oflice
 

Date of filing 
.................................. 
 

OR 
 

Date of receipt by post 
.................... 
 

Registration No. 
.............................. 
 

Signature of 
Registrar
 

IN THE CYBER REGULATIONS 
APPELLATE TRIBUNAL
 

.......................................... 

 

.......................................... 

 

BETWEEN
 

A 
B                                                                                     
......APPLICANT
 

AND
 

C 
D                                                                                  
......RESPONDENT
 

Details of Application 
:
 

1.  Particulars of the 
applicant— 
 

    (i)  Name of the applicant 

 

    (ii)  Name of 
Father/Husband 
 

   (iii)  Designation and office in 
which employed 
 

   (iv)  Office Address 
 

   (v)  Address for service of all 
notice 
 

2. Particulars of the 
respondent—
 

    (i)  Name and/or 
designation of the respondent 
 

    (ii)  Office address of the 
respondent 
 

   (iii)  Address for service of all 
notices 
 

3. Particulars of the order 
against which application is made:
 

The application is against the 
following order:
 

    (i)  Order No. 
 

    (ii)  Date 
 

   (iii)  Passed by 
 

   (iv)  Subject in brief 

 

4. Jurisdiction of the 
Tribunal:
 

The applicant declares that the 
subject-matter of the order against which he wants redressal is within the 
jurisdiction of the Tribunal. 
 

5. Limitation.—
 

The applicant further declares 
that the application is within the limitation prescribed in section 57 of the 
Information Technology Act, 2000.
 

6. Fact of the case— 
 

The facts of the case are given 
below—
 

          
(Give here a concise statement of facts in a choronological order, each paragaph 
containing as nearly as possible a separate issue, fact or 
otherwise).
 

7. Relief(s) sought—
 

In view of the facts mentioned 
in para 6 above, the applicant prays for the following relief(s)—
 

[Specify below the relief(s) 
sought explaining the ground for the relief(s) and the legal provisions (if any) 
relied upon].
 

8. Interim order, if prayed 
for:
 

Pending final decision on the 
application, the applicant seeks issue of the following interim 
order:—
 

(Give here the nature of the 
interim order prayed for with reasons).
 

9. Details of the remedies 
exhausted—
 

The applicant declares that he 
has availed of all the remedies available to him under the relevant service 
rules, etc.
 

(Give here chronologically the 
details of representations made and the outcome of such 
representation).
 

10. Matter not pending with any 
other court, etc.—
 

The applicant further declares 
that the matter regarding which this application has been made is not pending 
before any court of law or any other authority or has not been rejected by any 
court of law or other authority.
 

11. Details of Index—
 

An index in duplicate containing 
the details of the documents to be relied upon is enclosed.
 

12. List of 
enclosures—
 

Verification
 

I, 
........................................................................ (name 
of the applicant), S/o, D/o, W/o............................................ age 
..................................... working as 
.................................. resident 
of...............................hereby verify that the contents from 1 to 13 
are true to my personal knowledge and belief and that I have not suppressed any 
material facts.
 

Place :
 

Date :
 

Signature of 
applicant
 

To
 

The Registrar,
 

Cyber Regulation Appellate 
Tribunal 
 

New Delhi
 

RECEIPT 
SLIP
 

Receipt of the application filed 
in the Cyber Regulation Appellate Tribunal by 
Shri/Smt........................................................ working 
as............................... in the Office of 
................................................................................................. 
residing ........................................... acknowledged.
 

 </form><form>
 


THE CYBER 
REGULATIONS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 2000
 


 
 


FORM 2
 


(See rule 24)
 


APPLICATION FOR THE 
REGISTRATION OF A CLERK 
 


1.  Name of legal 
practitioner on whose behalf the clerk is to be registered. 
 


2.  Particulars of the 
clerk to be registered. 
 


    (i)  Full Name (in capitals) 
 


    (ii)  Father’s name 
 


   (iii)  Age and date of birth 
 


   (iv)  Place of birth 
 


   (v)  Nationality 
 


   (vi)  Educational qualifications 

 


  (vii)  Particulars of previous employment, 
if any. 
 


I, 
.....................(clerk above named), do hereby affirm that the particulars 
relating to me are true. 
 


3.  Whether the legal 
practitioner has a clerk already registered in his employ and whether the clerk 
sought to be registered is in lieu of or in addition to the clerk already 
registered. 
 


4.  Whether the clerk 
sought to be registered is already registered as a clerk of any other legal 
practitioner and if so, the name of such practitioner. 
 


I, 
.................................................. (legal practitioner) certify 
that the particulars given above are true to the best of my information and 
belief and that I am not aware of any facts which would render undesirable the 
registration of the said ........................... (name) as a clerk. 

 


Date: 
 


Signature of legal 
practitioner
 


To 
 


The Registrar of the 
Tribunal
 



................................. 
 



................................. 
 



................................. 
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>