<act><title>THE REGULATION ON QUALITY OF SERVICE FOR VOIP BASED INTERNATIONAL LONG DISTANCE SERVICE, 20021</title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> The title of this regulation shall be Regulation on Quality of Service for VOIP based International Long Distance Service, 2002. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> This regulation shall be applicable to all the International long Distance Service Providers using VOIP based networks. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> This regulation shall come into effect from the date of its notification in the Official Gazette. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Objective of laying down Quality of Service Benchmarks. </title>-The objective of laying down Quality of Service benchmarks is to- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Ensure customer satisfaction by laying down standards of network performance, which the service provider is required to achieve by proper engineering of his network. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Measure the Quality of Service from time to time and to compare that with the specified norms so as to monitor the level of performance, provided by various service providers' networks. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Protect the interests of subscribers of the ILD services in regard to Quality of Service, particularly a minimum level of voice quality, which he expects, when he makes an ISD call and pays for it. 
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Review. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> The QOS parameters given in section IV may be reviewed by the Authority from time to time. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> The Authority, on reference from any affected party, and for good and sufficient reasons, may review and modify this Regulation. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Over-riding Effect. </title>-Wherever higher quality parameter has been stipulated as a condition of license, the QOS as required by the license will over-ride the parameters given herein. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Interpretation. </title>-In case of disputes regarding interpretation of any of the provisions of this Regulation, the decision of the Authority shall be final and binding. 


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>