<act><tid>528174</tid>
<title>THE DEPOSIT INSURANCE CORPORATION (AMENDMENT AND  
  MISCELLANEOUSPROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1978</year></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1978</year>
[ 27th May, <year>1978</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the undertaking 
of the Credit Guarantee Corporation of India Limited in order to serve 
better the need for providing credit guarantee to commercial banks, 
and further to amend the Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1961</year>, and 
the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>, and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by parliament in the Twenty- ninth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1419080</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>331352</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Deposit Insurance Corporation (Amendment and Miscellaneous Provisions) 
Act, <year>1978</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>788832</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and 
different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act; 
and any reference in any provision to the commencement of this Act 
shall be construed as a reference to the commencement of that 
provision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1472584</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>31031</tid>
<number>a</number>" Company" means the Credit Guarantee Corporation of 
India Limited, a Company formed and registered under 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and having its 
registered office at Bombay;

</section>

<section><tid>203970</tid>
<number>b</number>" Corporation" means the Deposit Insurance Corporation 
established under sub- section (1) of section 3 of the 
Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1317162</tid>
<number>c</number>" re- named Corporation" means the Corporation as re- named 
in accordance with the provisions of section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1979173</tid>
<number>d</number>words and expressions used in this Act and not defined 
but defined in the Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, 
 <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>), shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in that Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>350</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 15th July, <year>1978</year> (except section 9), vide Notification No. S. O. 
429 (E), dated the 4th July, <year>1978</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, 
<year>1978</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 806.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF UNDERTAKING OF THE CREDIT GUARANTEECORPORATION OF 
INDIA LIMITED

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF UNDERTAKING OF THE CREDIT GUARANTEE 
CORPORATION OF INDIA LIMITED




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1881551</tid>
<number> 3</number> Undertaking of the Company to vest in the Corporation.
<section><tid>1078622</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On the commencement of this Act, the undertaking of the Company shall 
stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>658854</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the Company shall be deemed to include all 
assets, business, rights, powers, authorities and privileges and all 
property, movable and immovable, cash balances, reserve funds, 
investments, book debts and all other rights and interests in, or 
arising out of, such property as were, immediately before the 
commencement of this Act, in the ownership, possession, power or 
control of the Company, whether within or outside India, and all books 
of account, registers, records and all other documents of whatever 
nature relating thereto and shall also be deemed to include all 
borrowings, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind then 
subsisting of the Company in relation to its undertaking.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1346822</tid>
<number> 4</number> Merger of the undertaking of the Company with the undertaking 
of the Corporation.
<section><tid>1685445</tid>
<number>1</number>On the transfer to, and vesting in, the  
Corporation of the undertaking of the Company, such undertaking shall 
be deemed to have merged with the undertaking of the Corporation and, 
consequent on such merger, the Corporation shall be re- named as the 
Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation, and thereupon any 
reference to the Deposit Insurance Corporation or to the Credit 
Guarantee Corporation of India Limited, in the Deposit Insurance 
Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>), or in any other law for the time 
being in force or in any instrument or other document in force 
immediately before such transfer and vesting, and to which either the 
Deposit Insurance Corporation or the Credit Guarantee Corporation of 
India Limited is a party or which is in favour of either of them, 
shall be construed as a reference to the Deposit Insurance and Credit 
Guarantee Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>928484</tid>
<number>2</number>The change of name of the Deposit Insurance Corporation, by 
virtue of the provisions of sub- section (1), shall not--

<subsection><tid>1992200</tid>
<number>a</number>affect any right or obligation of that Corporation, 
subsisting immediately before the commencement of the 
Deposit Insurance Corporation (Amendment and  
  Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, <year>1978</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1575111</tid>
<number>b</number>render defective any suit or other legal proceeding 
pending, immediately before such commencement, by or 
against that Corporation in its former name; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>712952</tid>
<number>c</number>affect the institution or commencement of any suit or 
other legal proceeding which could have been instituted 
or commenced, before such commencement, by or against 
the Corporation in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>351</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

its former name, and every such suit or legal 
proceeding may be instituted or commenced, after the 
commencement of this Act, by or against the re- named 
Corporation.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>969934</tid>
<number> 5</number> General effect of merger.
<section><tid>1566904</tid>
<number>1</number>Unless otherwise expressly  
provided by this Act, all the assets, obligations and liabilities, 
respectively, of the Corporation, or the Company, and all contracts, 
deeds, bonds, agreements, guarantees, indemnities, powers of attorney, 
grants of legal representation and other instruments of whatever 
nature subsisting or having effect immediately before the commencement 
of this Act and to which either the Corporation or the Company is a 
party or which are in favour of either the Corporation, or the Company 
shall be of as full force and effect against or in favour of the re- 
named Corporation, and may be enforced or acted upon as fully and 
effectually as if in place of the Corporation or the Company, as the 
case may be, the re- named Corporation had been a party thereto or as 
if they had been issued in favour of the re- named Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1796496</tid>
<number>2</number>If immediately before the commencement of this Act, any suit, 
appeal or other proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to any 
business of the undertaking of the Corporation or of the Company, 
instituted or preferred by or against the Corporation or the Company, 
is pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way 
prejudicially affected, by reason of the transfer of the undertaking 
of the Company to the Corporation or the merger of the undertaking of 
the Company with the undertaking of the Corporation, or of anything 
contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the re- named 
Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>884654</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>684207</tid>
<number>1</number>For the transfer to, and vesting in,  
the Corporation, under section 3, of the undertaking of the Company, 
there shall be given by the Corporation to the Company an amount of 
rupees two crores.

</section>

<section><tid>1034939</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount specified in sub- section (1) shall be given, in 
cash, within thirty days from the commencement of this Act and such 
amount shall carry interest at the rate of four per cent. per annum 
from such commencement till the date on which the amount is paid to 
the Company:
Provided that if the amount specified in sub- section (1) is paid 
within seven days from the commencement of this Act, no interest shall 
be payable.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>352</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>944072</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Central Government to authorise a person or body of 
persons to take over the management of the Company.
<section><tid>1230658</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, at any time after the commencement of this Act, 
authorise a person or body of persons to take over the management of 
the affairs of the Company; and, when any person or body of persons is 
so authorised, it shall be the duty of such person or body of persons 
to bring the operations of the Company to a close, realise the amount 
payable to the Company under section 6, and distribute such amount 
amongst the creditors of the Company in due course of administration 
and, if there is a surplus, amongst the contributories of the Company 
in accordance with their rights and interests and, after such 
realisation and distribution, to obtain an order of the Central 
Government for the dissolution of the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>858423</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the person or body of 
persons authorised under that sub- section shall have such of the 
powers and duties of the Official Liquidator, appointed under the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), as are necessary to give effect to 
the provisions of that sub- section as if the Company were being wound 
up by the court, and, for this purpose, the provisions of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, shall apply subject to the modification that for 
the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the words" Central Government" 
shall be substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>886057</tid>
<number>3</number>When any person or body of persons is authorised by the 
Central Government under sub- section (1), to take over the management 
of the affairs of the Company,--

<subsection><tid>459364</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
or of any other law for the time being in force or any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any such Act or 
other law shall, in so far as they are inconsistent 
with the provisions of this Act, cease to apply to, or 
in relation to, the Company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>264740</tid>
<number>b</number>all persons in charge of the management, including any 
person holding office as manager, director or secretary 
of the Company, immediately before the authorisation of 
such person or body of persons, shall be deemed to have 
vacated their offices as such.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1984209</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as the affairs of the Company have been wholly wound 
up, the person or body of persons, authorised under sub- section (1), 
shall submit his or their duly audited final accounts to the Central 
Government and shall apply to that Government for orders as to the 
dissolution of the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>761599</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government shall, after hearing such person as it 
may think fit, and upon perusing the accounts as audited, if satisfied 
that the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>353</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

affairs of the Company have been wholly wound up, make an order that 
the Company be dissolved from the date of the order and the Company 
shall stand dissolved accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>960983</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government may also make an order relating to--

<subsection><tid>1899834</tid>
<number>a</number>the application, subject to the provisions of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), of the balance in the 
hands of the person or body of persons authorised under 
sub- section (1); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>715211</tid>
<number>b</number>the payment of such balance into the general revenue 
account of the Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>895605</tid>
<number>c</number>the disposal of the books and papers of the Company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1702111</tid>
<number>7</number>A copy of the order made by the Central Government for the 
dissolution of the Company shall be filed by the re- named Corporation 
with the Registrar of Companies within thirty days from the date of 
such order and the Registrar of Companies shall give effect to the 
said order as if it were an order made by the court for the 
dissolution of the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>942447</tid>
<number>8</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any other law for the time being in 
force.
Section 8 and 9 amend the Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> 
and the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> respectively and as such not 
printed here.



</section>

</article>



 </act>