<act><title>THE CENTRAL MOTOR VEHICLES (REGULATION OF BUS SERVICE BETWEEN AMRITSAR AND LAHORE) RULES, 2006 </title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.</title>—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Central Motor Vehicles (Regulation of Bus Service between Amritsar and Lahore) Rules, 2006. 
  (2) These rules shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    Agreement means the Agreement between 
    the Government of the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan 
    for the regulation of bus service between Amritsar and Lahore signed on 21st 
    December, 2005;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    authorisation fee means the fee to be 
    paid by the permit holder of one country to the other country for obtaining 
    authorisation;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    bus crew means driver, conductor and 
    the liaison officer;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    competent authority means,  
 
in relation to  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    permits, an authority competent to 
    issue such a permit authorised under the law of the country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    driving licence, an authority 
    competent to issue such a driving licence authorized under the law of the 
    country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    conductors licence, an authority 
    competent to issue such a conductors licence authorised under the law of 
    the country concerned;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>    country means India or Pakistan, as 
    the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    form means any of the form specified 
    in the Schedule annexed to these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    Liaison Officer means official 
    included in the crew authorised to carry out operational supervision of 
    transport vehicle and to keep liaison between passengers and customs and 
    immigration authorities and between passengers and prescribed food outlets 
    or restaurants;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    passenger means a person in 
    possession of a valid ticket for travel from Amritsar to Lahore or 
    vice-versa and a valid passport, visa and any other travel document 
    which may be mutually agreed to between the Parties to the Agreement;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    PUC certificate means Pollution Under 
    Control Certificate issued by appropriate authorities in Pakistan or India;   
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    scheduled service routes mean the 
    routes along with the time schedule and other related operational aspects 
    specified in the Protocol to the Agreement for the regulation of bus service 
    between Amritsar and Lahore;   
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    transport vehicle means a motor 
    vehicle (coach or bus) for the carriage of passengers for hire or reward, 
    between India and Pakistan, subject to such restrictions on the gross laden 
    weight, wheel base or seating capacity of vehicles as may be imposed under 
    the law in either country from time to time.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Forms, 
    contents and duration etc., of the permit.
<section><number>1</number> 
    A regular permit for transport vehicle shall be in the Form set out in 
    Schedule I and shall be non-transferable.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A regular 
    permit for transport vehicle shall be valid for one year and renewable upto 
    a maximum period of five years on a yearly basis.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Eligibility conditions of a vehicle.
<section><number>1</number> 
    A transport vehicle shall be so constructed and maintained as to be at all 
    times under the effective control of the person driving it.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Driver of a 
    transport vehicle referred to in sub-rule (1) shall have,  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a valid registration certificate issued 
    under the law of the country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a valid certificate of fitness issued 
    under the law of the country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a valid insurance policy issued under 
    the law of the country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a valid permit under the law of the 
    country concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    a passenger list with details of their 
    nationality; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    a valid PUC certificate under the law 
    of the country concerned;  
 
in respect of such vehicle and shall make all 
    the said documents available for inspection by any authority competent to 
    inspect such vehicle.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Conditions for the driver and conductor.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The person driving a transport vehicle shall be in possession of a valid 
    driving licence issued by a competent authority to drive such a vehicle and 
    the drivers badge.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    conductor of a transport vehicle shall be in possession of a valid 
    conductors licence issued by a competent authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For any 
    reason, a driver referred to in sub-rule (1) or a conductor referred to in 
    sub-rule (2), of a country is unable to perform his duties in the other 
    country, a driver or a conductor in possession of a valid licence issued by 
    the competent authority of such other country, may drive or act as a 
    conductor of the vehicle, as the case may be.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Distinguishing particulars to be exhibited on the transport vehicle.In 
    addition to the registration number assigned to a transport vehicle 
    operating under the Agreement by the competent authority, the following 
    particulars shall be painted in English and in official language of the 
    respective country [each letter being not less than two inches (five 
    centimetres) high and two inches (five centimetres) wide, legibly painted on 
    a plain surface or a plate or plates affixed to the vehicles], namely:  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    Amritsar  Lahore  Amritsar (on front 
    side and back side of such transport vehicle in a conspicuous place). 

 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    Name of the operator of the bus 
    service (on both the sides of such transport vehicle).
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Personal 
    effects of bus crew.The bus crew 
    of a transport vehicle operating under the Agreement may carry such personal 
    effects, as may be necessary, having regard to the period of their stay in 
    the host country subject to conditions specified in the customs laws of both 
    countries.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Insurance 
    of the vehicle.No transport 
    vehicle which does not have a policy of insurance which covers comprehensive 
    or third party risks, arising out of the use of transport vehicle and which 
    complies with the requirements of the law of the country concerned shall 
    operate under these rules.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Conditions for transport of passengers.No 
    transport vehicle registered in Pakistan shall be engaged in the transport 
    of passengers from any point of India to any other point in India, and 
    similarly no transport vehicle registered in India shall be engaged in the 
    transport of passengers from any point in Pakistan to any other point in 
    Pakistan.  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Central Motor Vehicles (Regulation of Bus 
    Service Between Amritsar and Lahore) Rules, 2006
 

 
 


SCHEDULE 
 


(See rule 3)
 



form of permit to ply transport vehicles on 
    India  

    (Amritsar)  Pakistan (Lahore)
 


regular 
    permit*
 


(Strike out whichever is not applicable)
 


Government of India/Government of Pakistan
 

 
 


Permit to ply 
    transport vehicles between India (Amritsar)  Pakistan (Lahore).
 


(a)    Name, address and nationality of the 
    operator of motor vehicle.
 


(b)    Registration Number of the vehicle.
 


(c)    Nature of transport operators: Point to 
    point Amritsar  Lahore  Amritsar.
 


(d)    Capacity of the vehicle:
 


(i)    Seating capacity 
 


(ii)    Laden Weight
 


(e)    Particulars of insurance policy.
 


(f)    Particulars of Certificate of fitness.
 


(g)    The starting and terminal points in 
    each country.
 


(h)    The route or routes to be followed by 
    the scheduled passenger service vehicle.
 


This permit is 
    valid from...........to ..and is not transferable.
 
 
  
 Signature, Designation and 
        Seal of the 

        competent authority of Government of India
 Signature, Designation and 
        Seal of the 

        competent authority of Government of Pakistan


 

 
 


This permit is 
    hereby renewed upto the day of.......................
 
 
  
 Signature, Designation and 
        Seal of the 

        competent authority of Government of India
 Signature, Designation and 
        Seal of the 

        competent authority of Government of Pakistan


 

 
 


*means a permit 
    issued by competent authority of one country and countersigned by the 
    competent authority of the other country, authorising the transport vehicle 
    to ply on the scheduled service route, as specified in such permit, and 
    includes regular permit for passenger transport.  
 


Note.Registration 
    papers and other documents such as insurance certificate, fitness 
    certificate, etc., shall be carried on the vehicle(s) and made available for 
    inspection on demand by the competent authority or any officer duly 
    authorised by the authority. 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>