<act><tid>1611649</tid>
<title>THE CALCUTTA HIGH COURT (EXTENSION OF JURISDICTION) ACT, <year>1953</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1953</year> AN ACT TO EXTEND THE JURISDICTION OF THE HIGH COURT AT CAL 
CUTTA TO CHANDERNAG
[ 18th December, <year>1953</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1293754</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Calcutta High Court 
 (Extension of Jurisdiction) Act, <year>1953</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1295844</tid>
<number>2</number>Extention of jurisdiction of Calcutta High Court to 
Chandernagore and Andaman and Nicobar Islands. The jurisdiction of 
the High Court at Calcutta shall extend to Chandernagore and the 
Andaman and Nicobar Islands and shall, as from the 2nd day of May, 
<year>1950</year>, be deemed to have extended to Chandernagore, and the said High 
Court shall, for all purposes be deemed to be the High Court for 
Chandernagore and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands.


</article>



<article><tid>1229544</tid>
<number> 3</number> Effect of certain orders. Any order made-
<section><tid>1999859</tid>
<number>i</number>by the highest Court of appeal in relation to 
Chandernagore before the 2nd day of May, <year>1950</year>, or in any 
proceeding pending before that Court on that day, or

</section>

<section><tid>1419469</tid>
<number>ii</number>by the Chief Commissioner of the Andaman and 
Nicobar Islands before the commencement of this Act in 
the discharge of his functions as the High Court for 
those Islands,
shall for all purposes have effect, not only as an order of that 
Court, or as the case may be, of the Chief Commissioner, but also as 
if it were an order made by the High Court at Calcutta.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>965021</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to make rules. Subject to the provisions of any law 
for the time being in force, the High Court at Calcutta may make rules 
to carry out the purposes of this Act and for the purpose of 
effectively exercising its jurisdiction in or in relation to 
Chandernagore and the Andaman and Nicobar Islands.

</article>



 </act>