<act><tid>442204</tid>
<title>THE CUSTOMS TARIFF ACT, <year>1975</year></title>

ACT NO. 51 OF <year>1975</year>
[ 18th August, <year>1975</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to customs duties.

BE, it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>625025</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1005589</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Customs Tariff Act, <year>1975</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1800293</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1134896</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date' as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>127314</tid>
<number>2</number>Duties specified in the Schedule to be levied. The rates at 
which duties of customs shall be levied under the Customs Act, 
<year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) are specified in the First and Second Schedules.


</article>



<article><tid>345301</tid>
<number> 3</number> Levy of additional duty equal to excise duty.
<section><tid>827932</tid>
<number>1</number>Any article  
which is imported into India shall, in addition, be liable to a duty 
 (hereafter in this section referred to as the additional duty) equal 
to the excise duty for the time being leviable on a like article if 
produced or manufactured in India and if such excise duty on a like 
article is leviable at any percentage of its value, the additional 
duty to which the imported article shall be so liable shall be 
calculated at that percentage, of the value of the imported article.
Explanation.- In this section, the expression" the excise duty for 
the time being leviable on a like article if produced or manufactured 
in India" means the excise duty for the time being in force which 
would be leviable on a like article if produced or manufactured in 
India or, if a like article is not so produced or manufactured, which 
would be leviable on the class or description of articles to which 
the imported article belongs, and where such duty is leviable at 
different rates, the highest duty.


</section>

<section><tid>1237128</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of calculating- under this section the 
additional duty on any imported article, where such duty is leviable 
at any percentage of its value, the value of the imported article 
shall, notwithstanding anything contained in section 14 of the Customs 
Act, <year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) be the aggregate of-

<subsection><tid>1340313</tid>
<number>i</number>the value of the imported article determined under sub- 
section (1) of the said section 14 or the tariff value of 
such article fixed under sub- section (2) of that section, as 
the case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>711646</tid>
<number>ii</number>any duty of customs chargeable on that article under 
section 12 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) and any sum 
chargeable on that article under any law for the time being 
in force as an addition to, and in the same manner as, a duty 
of customs, but not including the duty referred to in sub- 
section (1).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1076020</tid>
<number>3</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary 
in the public interest to levy on any imported article[ whether on 
such article duty is leviable under sub- section (1) or not] such 
additional duty as would counter- balance the excise duty leviable on 
any raw materials, components and ingredients of the same nature as, 
or similar to those, used in the production or manufacture of such 
article, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that 
such imported article shall, in addition, be liable to an additional 
duty representing such portion of the excise duty leviable on such raw 
materials, components

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2- 8- <year>1976</year>: vide Notification No. G. S. R. 492 (E), dated 31- 7- 
<year>1976</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and ingredients as, in either case, may be determined by rules made by 
the Central Government in this behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>217248</tid>
<number>4</number>In making any rules for the purposes of sub- section (3), the 
Central Government shall have regard to the average quantum of the 
excise duty payable on the raw materials, components or ingredients 
used in the production or manufacture of such like article.

</section>

<section><tid>1454890</tid>
<number>5</number>The duty chargeable under this section shall be in addition 
to any other duty imposed under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1700904</tid>
<number>6</number>The provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) and 
the rules and regulations thereunder, including those relating to 
drawbacks, refunds and exemption duties, shall,' so far as' may' be, 
apply to the duty chargeable under this section as they apply in 
relation to the duties leviable under that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1266681</tid>
<number> 4</number> Levy of duty where standard rate and preferential rate are 
specified.
<section><tid>846789</tid>
<number>1</number>Where in respect of any Article a preferential rate of  
revenue' duty is specified in the First Schedule, or is admissible by 
virtue of a notification under section 25 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, 
 (52 of <year>1962</year>) the duty to be levied and collected shall be at the 
standard rate, unless the owner of the article claims at the time of 
importation that it is chargeable with a preferential rate of duty, 
being <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the produce or manufacture of such preferential area] as is 
notified under subsection' (3) and the article is determined, in 
accordance with the rules made under sub- section (2), to be such 
produce or manufacture.

</section>

<section><tid>259638</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules for determining if any article is <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the produce or 
manufacture of any preferential area].

</section>

<section><tid>1126611</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section and the First Schedule, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> preferential area'] means any country or territory which the 
Central Government may, by Notification from in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be such area.

</section>

<section><tid>718449</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained ins sub- section (1), where 
the Central Government is satisfied that, that in the interests of 
trade including promotion of exports, it is necessary to take 
immediate action for discontinuing the preferential rate, or 
increasing the preferential rate to a rate not exceeding the standard 
rate, or decreasing the preferential rate, in respect of an article 
specified in the First Schedule, the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct an amendment of the said 
Schedule to be made so as to provide for, such discontinuance of, or 
increase or decrease, as the case may be, in, the preferential rate.

</section>

<section><tid>424633</tid>
<number>5</number>Every notification issued under sub- section (3) or sub- 
section (4) shall,' as soon as may be after it is issued, be' laid 
before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1420956</tid>
<number> 5</number> Levy of a lower rate of duty under a trade agreement.
<section><tid>116402</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
under a trade agreement between the Government of India and the 
Government of a foreign country or territory, duty at a rate lower 
than that specified in the First Schedule is to be charged on articles 
which are the produce or manufacture of such foreign country or 
territory, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules for determining if any article is the produce or 
manufacture of such foreign country or territory and for requiring the 
owner to make a claim at the time of importation, supported by such 
evidence as may be prescribed in the said rules, for assessment at the 
appropriate lower rate under such Agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>787760</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether any trade agreement applies 
to any country or territory, or whether it has ceased to apply to 
India or any foreign country or territory, it shall be referred to the 
Central Government for decision and the decision of the Central 
Government shall be final and shall not be liable to be questioned in 
any court of law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1130442</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power of Central Government to levy protective duties in 
certain cases.
<section><tid>1479149</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government, upon a recommendation  
' made to it in this behalf by the Tariff Commission established under 
the Tariff Commission Act, <year>1951</year>, (50 of <year>1951</year>) is satisfied that 
circumstances exist which render it necessary to take immediate action 
to provide for the protection of the interests of any industry

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 26 of <year>1978</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1978</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

established in India, the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, impose on any goods imported into India in 
respect of which the said recommendation is made, a duty of customs of 
such amount, not exceeding the amount proposed in the said 
recommendation, as it thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1149970</tid>
<number>2</number>Every duty imposed on any goods under sub- section (1) shall, 
for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to have been specified in the 
First Schedule as the duty leviable in respect of such goods.

</section>

<section><tid>1380305</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a notification has been issued under sub- section (1), 
the Central Government shall, unless the notification is in the 
meantime rescinded, have a Bill introduced in Parliament, as soon as 
may be, but in any case during the next session of Parliament 
following the date of the issue of the notification to give effect to 
the proposals in regard to the continuance of a protective duty of 
customs on the goods to which the notification relates, and the 
notification shall cease to have effect when such Bill becomes law, 
whether with or without modifications, but without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done thereunder:
Provided that if the notification under sub- section (1) is issued 
when Parliament is in session, such a Bill shall be introduced in 
Parliament during that session:

Provided further that where for any reason a Bill as aforesaid 
does not become law within six months from the date of its 
introduction in Parliament, the notification shall cease to have 
effect on the expiration of the said period of six months, but without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191174</tid>
<number> 7</number> Duration of protective duties and power of Central Government 
to alter them.
<section><tid>734776</tid>
<number>1</number>When the duty specified in respect of any article  
in the First Schedule is characterised as protective in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> column (5)] 
of that Schedule, that duty shall have effect only up to and inclusive 
of the date, if any, specified in that Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1341461</tid>
<number>2</number>Where in respect of any such article the Central Government 
is satisfied after such inquiry as it thinks necessary that such duty 
has become ineffective or excessive for the purpose of securing the 
protection intended to be afforded by it' to be a similar article 
manufactured in India and that circumstances exist which render it 
necessary to take immediate action, it may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, increase of reduce such duty to such extent as it 
thinks necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1074940</tid>
<number>3</number>Every notification under sub- section (2), in so far as it 
relates to increase of such duty, shall be laid before each House 
of Parliament if it is sitting as soon as may be after the issue of 
the notification, and if it is not sitting within seven days of its 
re- assembly, and the Central Government shall seek the approval of 
Parliament to the notification by a resolution moved within a period 
of fifteen days beginning with the day on which the notification is so 
laid before the House of the People and if Parliament make' s any 
modification in the notification or directs that the notification 
should cease to have effect, the notification shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1525819</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any 
notification issued under sub- section (2), including any such 
notification approved or modified under sub- section (3), may be 
rescinded by the Central Government at any time by notification in the 
Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1728674</tid>
<number> 8</number> Emergency power of Central Government to increase or levy 
export duties.
<section><tid>1267331</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in respect of any article, whether included  
in the Second Schedule or not, the Central Government is satisfied 
that the export duty leviable thereon should be increased or that an 
export duty should be levied, and that circumstances exist which 
render it necessary to take immediate action, the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct and amendment of 
the Second Schedule to be made so as to provide for an increase the 
export duty leviable or, as the case may be, for the levy of an export 
duty, on that article.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 26 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3, for" column (6)" (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1978</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>918147</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (3) and (4) of section 7 shall 
apply to any notification issued under sub- section (1) as they apply 
in relation to any notification increasing duty issued under sub- 
section (2) of section 7.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1002491</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Emergency power of Central Government to increase import 
duties
<section><tid>1840637</tid>
<number>1</number>Where in respect of any article included in the First  
Schedule, the Central Government is satisfied that the import duty 
leviable thereon under section 12 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> should be 
increased and that circumstances exist which render it necessary to 
take immediate action, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette 
direct an amendment of that Schedule to be made so as to provide for 
an increase in the import duty leviable on such article to such extent 
as it thinks necessary:
Provided that the Central Government shall not issue any 
notification under this sub- section for substituting. the rate of, 
import duty in respect of any article as specified by an earlier 
notification issued under this sub- section be that Government before 
such earlier notification has been approved with. or with. out 
modifications under sub- section (2).


</section>

<section><tid>1875508</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4) of section 7 
shall apply to any notification issued under sub- section (1) as they 
apply in relation to any notification increasing duty issued under 
sub- section (2) of section 7."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>96321</tid>
<number> 9</number> Additional import duty on bountyfed articles. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1208107</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
country or territory pays, or bestows, directly or indirectly, any 
bounty or Subsidy upon the manufacture or production therein or the 
exportation therefrom of any article, then, upon the importation of 
any such article into India, whether the same is imported directly 
from the country of manufacture, production or otherwise, and whether 
it is imported in the same condition as when exported from the country 
of manufacture or production or has been changed in condition by 
manufacture, production or otherwise, the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, impose,-

<subsection><tid>648454</tid>
<number>i</number>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with' duty 
under the provisions of this Act, a duty or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85208</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an 
additional duty, not exceeding the amount of such bounty or 
subsidy:
Provided that the Central Government may, pending the 
determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and 
the rules made thereunder of the amount of such bounty or grant, 
impose a duty or additional duty under this sub- section not exceeding 
the amount of such bounty or subsidy as provisionally estimated by it 
and if such duty or additional duty exceeds such bounty or subsidy as 
so determined,-


<subsubsection><tid>967225</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Government shall, having regard to such 
determination and as soon as may be after such determination, 
reduce such duty or additional duty; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1479351</tid>
<number>b</number>refund shall be made of so much of such duty or 
additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of 
the duty or additional duty as so reduced.];

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>158726</tid>
<number>2</number>The[ amount of any such bounty or subsidy] 1 as aforesaid 
shall, from time to time, be ascertained, determined, and declared by 
the Central Government, after such inquiry as it may consider 
necessary and the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make rules for the identification of such articles 
and for the assessment and collection of any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> duty or additional 
duty, as the case may be,] imposed upon the importation thereof under 
sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>961544</tid>
<number>3</number>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as 
soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>946858</tid>
<number> 9A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Antidumping duty.
<section><tid>339249</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any article is exported from  
any country or territory (hereafter in this section referred to as the  
  exporting country or territory) to India at less than its normal 
value, then, upon the importation of such article into India, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
impose,--

<subsection><tid>1708079</tid>
<number>a</number>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with duty 
under the provisions of this Act, a duty; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1095437</tid>
<number>b</number>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an additional 
duty, not exceeding the margin of dumping in relation to such 
article:
not exceeding the margin of dumping in relation to such 
article:


<subsubsection><tid>1760991</tid>
<number>1</number>Sub- section (1) and (2) of section 9 shall stand amended as 
follows when section 2 of Act No. 52 of <year>1982</year> comes into force:--
" (1) Where any country or territory pays, or bestows, directly 
or indirectly, any bounty or subsidy upon the manufacture or 
production therein or the exportation therefrom of any article, then, 
upon the importation of any such article into India, whether the same 
is imported directly from the country of manufacture, production or 
otherwise, and whether it is imported in the same condition as when 
exported from the country of manufacture, production or has been 
changed in condition by manufacture, production or otherwise, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
impose,--


<subsubsubsection><tid>381434</tid>
<number>i</number>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with duty 
under the provisions of this Act, a duty; or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1336489</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an additional 
duty, not exceeding the amount of such bounty or subsidy;
Provided that the Central Government may, pending the 
determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and 
the rules made thereunder of the amount of such bounty or grant, 
impose a duty or additional duty under this sub- section not exceeding 
the amount of such bounty or subsidy as provisionally estimated by it 
and if such duty or additional duty exceeds such bounty or subsidy as 
so determined,--


<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1080006</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Government shall, having regard to such 
determination and as soon as may be after such determination, 
reduce such duty or additional duty; and

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>446782</tid>
<number>b</number>refund shall be made of so much of such duty or 
additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of 
the duty of the duty or additional duty as so reduced.";
<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 2- 9- <year>1985</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 3 ibid., (w. e. f. 2- 9- <year>1985</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, s. 110.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>446782</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),--

</subsubsubsubsection>

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>381434</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" not amount of any such bounty or 
grant", the words" amount of any such bounty or subsidy" 
shall be substituted;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1336489</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" additional duty", the words" duty 
or additional duty, as the case may be," shall be 
substituted.
Provided that the, Central Government may, pending the 
determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and 
the rules made thereunder of the normal value and the margin of 
dumping in relation to any article, impose on the importation of such 
article into India a duty or additional duty under this sub- section on 
the basis of a provisional estimate of such value and margin and if 
such duty or additional duty exceeds the margin as so determined,-


<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1080006</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Government shall, having regard to such 
determination and as soon as may be after such determination, 
reduce such duty or additional duty; and

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>446782</tid>
<number>b</number>refund shall be made of so much of such duty or 
additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of 
such duty or additional duty as so reduced.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1080006</tid>
<number>a</number>" margin of dumping", in relation to an article, means 
the difference between the price at which such article is 
exported and its normal value;

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>446782</tid>
<number>b</number>" normal value", in relation to an article, means-

</subsubsubsubsection>

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>381434</tid>
<number>i</number>the comparable price in the ordinary course of 
trade for the said article or like article when meant 
for consumption in the exporting country or territory- 
as determined under sub- section (2); or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1336489</tid>
<number>ii</number>where such comparable price cannot be ascertained 
because of the particular market situation or for any 
other reason, such value shall be either-

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1250622</tid>
<number>A</number>the highest comparable price for the said 
article or like article from the exporting country 
or territory to any third country in the ordinary 
course of trade as determined under subsection (2); 
or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1690495</tid>
<number>B</number>the cost of production of the said article or 
like article in the country of origin along with 
reasonable addition for selling and any other cost, 
and for profits, as determined under susection (2).

</subsubsubsubsection>

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1354196</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any rules made under sub- section (3), the Central 
Government shall, after making due allowance in each case for 
differences in conditions and terms of sale, for differences in 
taxation and for other differences affecting price comparability, and, 
after such inquiry as it may consider necessary, determine, for the 
purposes of sub- section (1), the export price and the normal value of, 
and the margin of dumping in relation to, any article.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>724095</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules for the purposes of this section, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, such rules may provide 
for the manner in which articles liable for any duty or additional 
duty under sub- section (1) may be identified, and for the manner in 
which the export price and the normal value of, and the margin of 
dumping in relation to, such articles may be determined and for the 
assessment and collection of such duty or additional duty.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1293915</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as 
soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1226596</tid>
<number> 9B</number> No levy under section 9 or section 9A in certain cases in 
the absence of injury to industry in India.
<section><tid>1315586</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 9 or section 9A, the Central Government 
shall not levy any duty or additional duty under either of those 
sections on the import into India of any article from any country or 
territory to which this section applies unless that Government, after 
making investigation in accordance with the rules made under sub- 
section (3), declares, by notification in the Official Gazette, that 
the import of such article into India causes or threatens material 
injury to any industry established in India or materially retards the 
establishment of any industry in India,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1560626</tid>
<number>2</number>This section applies to every country or territory which is 
specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette to be a country, or territory which, by reason of its being a 
party to the General Agreement on Tariff and Trade or by reason of any 
agreement between it and India for giving the most- favoured nation 
treatment or for any[ other reason, levies duty or additional duty of 
the nature referred to in section 9 or section 9A on articles imported 
from India only when such import causes or threatens any material 
injury to any industry established in such country or territory or 
material retards the establishment of such industry in such country or 
territory.

</section>

<section><tid>785616</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules for the purposes of this section, and without 
Prejudice, to the generality of the foregoing, such rules may provide 
for the manner in which any investigation may be made for the purposes 
of sub- section (1), the factors to which regard shall be had in any 
such investigation and for all matters connected with such 
investigation.

</section>

<section><tid>833626</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notification issued under, sub- section, (1) or sub- 
section (2) shall, as soon as may be after it is issued, be laid 
before each House of Parliament.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," industry", in 
relation to any article, includes the manufacture or production of 
like articles, any activity connected therewith find the persons 
engaged in such production, manufacture or activity]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>254925</tid>
<number>10</number>Rules to be laid before Parliament. Every rule made under this 
Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, 
or both House agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, 
thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.


</article>



<article><tid>939921</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power of Central Government to alter duties under certain 
circumstances.
<section><tid>1283683</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government is satisfied that it  
is necessary so to do for the purpose of giving effect to any 
agreement entered into before the commencement of this Act with a 
foreign Government, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
increase or reduce the duties referred to in section 2 to such extent 
as each case may require:
Provided that not notification under this sub- section increasing 
or reducing the duties as aforesaid shall be issued by the Central 
Government after the expiration of a period of one year from the 
commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1608522</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as 
soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>198777</tid>
<number> 12</number> Repeal and saving. (2) The Indian Triff Act, <year>1934</year>, (32 of  
  <year>1934</year>) and the Indian Tariff (Amendment) Act, <year>1949</year>, (1 of <year>1949</year>) are 
hereby repealed.
<section><tid>214982</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of any of the Acts mentioned in 
sub- section (1), anything done or any action taken (including any  
notification published and any rules and orders made or deemed to have 
been made under the provisions of those Acts and in force immediately 
  before the commencement of this Act) shall, in so far as such thing or 
action is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed 
to have been done or taken under the provisions of this Act and shall 
continue in force accordingly until superseded by anything done or 
any action taken under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>437554</tid>
<number> 13</number> Consequential amendment of Act 52 of <year>1962</year>. In the Customs Act, 
<year>1962</year>, in sub- section 1 of section 12 and in sub- section
<section><tid>1008006</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 14, for the words and figures" Indian Tariff Act, <year>1934</year>", (32  
  of <year>1934</year>) the words and figures" Customs Tariff Act, <year>1975</year>" shall be 
substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>