<act><title>THE OUTDOOR USE OF WIRELESS EQUIPMENT (EXEMPTION 
FROM LICENSING REQUIREMENT) RULES, 20071</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement:</title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Outdoor Use of Wireless Equipment (Exemption from Licensing 
Requirement) Rules, 2007.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette.

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Effective Isotropic Radiated Power includes the gain of the antenna, 
  if any; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> words and expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined 
  in the Act and the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 (17 of 1933), shall 
  have the same meanings respectively as assigned to them in those Acts. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Interference. </title>The effect of unwanted energy due to one 
or a combination of emissions, radiations or induction upon reception in a radio 
communication system, manifested by any performance degradation, 
misinterpretation, or loss of information which could be extracted in the 
absence of such unwanted energy; where any person whom a licence has been issued 
under Section 4 of the Act, informs that his licensed system is getting harmful 
interference from any other radio communication system exempted under these 
rules, the outdoor user of such unlicensed wireless equipment shall take 
necessary steps to avoid interference by relocating the equipment, reducing the 
power or by, using special type of antennae and the Central Government may with 
a view to ensure smooth functioning of the communication system direct the 
discontinuance of such Wireless use. Provided that, before such discontinuation, 
a reasonable opportunity to explain the circumstances shall be offered to such 
unlicensed user of wireless equipment. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Equipment. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The wireless equipment shall be type 
approved and designed and constructed in such a manner that the bandwidth of 
emission and other parameters shall conform to the limits specified in the Table 
referred to in Rule 3. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application for obtaining equipment type approval shall be made to 
the Central Government in such form as may be required by that Government in 
this behalf. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>