<act><tid>1180789</tid>
<title>THE COMPULSORY DEPOSIT SCHEME (INCOME- TAX PAYERS) ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 1st September, <year>1974</year>.]

An Act to provide, in the interest of national economic 
development, for compulsory deposit by certain classes of income- tax 
payers and for the framing of a scheme in relation thereto, and for 
matters connected therewith of incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>401603</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1700135</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Compulsory Deposit Scheme (Income- tax Payers) Act, <year>1974</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1160452</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>396705</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th day 
of July, <year>1974</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1988822</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1206463</tid>
<number>a</number>" compulsory deposit" means compulsory deposit under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1238506</tid>
<number>b</number>" deposit" means a deposit of money;

</section>

<section><tid>1364334</tid>
<number>c</number>" depositor" means a person who is liable to, make a 
compulsory deposit;

</section>

<section><tid>846500</tid>
<number>d</number>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>969130</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Income- tax Officer" has the same meaning as in 
clause (25) of section 2 of the Income- tax Act, and includes 
an Inspecting Assistant Commissioner who exercises or 
performs the powers or functions conferred on, or assigned 
to, him under section 125 or section 125A of the said Act;]

</section>

<section><tid>1949924</tid>
<number>e</number>all other words and expression herein but not defined 
and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings, 
respectively, assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>648916</tid>
<number> 3</number> Persons liable to make compulsory deposits.
<section><tid>1827970</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act, the persons specified in sub- section (2) shall 
be liable to make compulsory deposits <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for the assessment year 
commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1975</year> and every subsequent 
assessment year (not being an assessment year commencing on or after  
the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> 1st day of April, <year>1986</year>].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>513</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, S. 43 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, S. 36 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1979</year>, S. 46 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1979</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1983</year>, S. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1983</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1022207</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons referred to in sub- section (1) are the following 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>92249</tid>
<number>a</number>every person, being-

<subsubsection><tid>342302</tid>
<number>i</number>an individual, who is a citizen of India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>215030</tid>
<number>ii</number>a Hindu undivided family;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1014151</tid>
<number>iii</number>a trustee appointed under a trust declared by a duly 
executed instrument in writing, whether testamentary or 
otherwise (including any Wakf deed which is valid under the  
  Mussalman Wakf Validating Act, <year>1913</year>), (6 of <year>1913</year>.) if the 
income in respect of which the trustee is liable to income- 
tax as a representative assessee or any part thereof is not 
specifically receivable on behalf or for the benefit of any 
one person or where the individual shares of the persons on 
whose behalf or for whose benefit such income or such part 
thereof is receivable are indeterminate or unknown; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1200555</tid>
<number>b</number>every person who is assessable under the Income- tax Act 
in respect of the total income of an individual, or a Hindu 
undivided family or a trustee specified in clause (a).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1070171</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1),- 
 (a) an individual specified in sub- clause (i) of clause (a) 
of sub- section (2), or

<subsection><tid>484865</tid>
<number>b</number>any person specified in clause (b) of sub- section (2) 
who is assessable under the Income- tax Act in respect of the 
total income of the individual aforesaid,
shall not be liable to make any compulsory deposit for any assessment 
year where, in either case, such individual is more than[ sixty- five 
years] 8 of age on the first day of the financial year immediately 
preceding that assessment year".]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>652356</tid>
<number> 4</number> Requirement as to compulsory deposit.
<section><tid>670937</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in relation  
to an assessment year referred to in subsection (1) of section 3, the 
current income of any person, being an individual or a Hindu undivided 
family or a trustee specified in clause (a) of sub- section (2) of that 
section, exceeds fifteen thousand rupees, such person, or if any other 
person is assessable under the Income- tax Act in respect of the total 
income of such person, the person so assessable, shall make, in 
accordance with and subject to the provisions of this Act and any 
scheme framed thereunder, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a compulsory deposit,-

<subsection><tid>341398</tid>
<number>i</number>for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April <year>1975</year> and the assessment year commencing on the 1st day 
of April, <year>1976</year>, at the rates specified in Paragraph A of the 
Schedule 4 xxx

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1791601</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1977</year> and the assessment year commencing on the 1st day 
of April <year>1978</year>, at the rates specified in Paragraph B of the 
Schedule; 7 xxx

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1398916</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1979</year>, the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1980</year>, and the assessment year commencing on the 1st 
day of April, <year>1981</year>, at the rates specified in Paragraph C of 
the Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1636745</tid>
<number>iv</number>for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1982</year>, at the rates specified in Paragraph D of the 
Schedule."]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1322422</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, in the case of any person specified in sub- section 
 (2) of section 3, a deduction is required to be made under the 
Additional Emoluments (Compulsory Deposit) Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (8 of  
  <year>1974</year>.) the amount of the compulsory deposit which such person is 
liable to make under this Act for any assessment year shall be reduced 
by the amount deducted under that Ordinance during the financial year 
immediately preceding that assessment year; and where such deduction 
is equal to or exceeds the amount of such compulsory deposit, it shall 
not be necessary for such person to make a compulsory deposit for that 
assessment year.
Explanation.-- When any Central Act repeals and replaces (with or  
  without any modification) the Additional Emoluments (Compulsory  
  Deposit) Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (8 of <year>1974</year>.) the references to the said 
Ordinance in this sub- section shall be construed as references to such 
Central Act.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>514</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, S. 43 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, S. 36 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by S. 36, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Omitted and Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1978</year>, S. 40 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1979</year>, S. 46 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1979</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Omitted and Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1981</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 11- 7- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1983</year>, S. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by s. 59, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1983</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1011740</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section," current income", in 
relation to an assessment year, means,-
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in a case where a statement is sent by the person Al clause 
 (a) of sub- section (1) of section 209A of the Income- tax Act 
in the financial year immediately preceding that assessment 
year or where the Income- tax Officer has made an order under 
sub- section (1) or sub- section (3) of section 210 of that Act 
requiring the person to pay advance tax during the financial 
year immediately preceding that assessment year and the 
person has not sent an estimate under section 209A or, as the 
case may be, section 212 of that Act]


<subsection><tid>1131031</tid>
<number>i</number>if the total income of the latest previous year in 
respect of which the person has been assessed by way of 
regular assessment forms the basis of computation of advance 
tax payable by him. such total income[ exclusive of capital 
gains and income referred to in sub- clause (ix) of clause 
 (24) of section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause (c) of section 115C] of the 
Income- tax Act] as increased by the net agricultural income 
if any, which has been taken into account for the purposes of 
charging income- tax for the assessment year relevant to that 
previous year; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1088926</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the total income of the previous year on the basis 
of which income- tax has been paid by the person under section 
 140A of the Income- tax Act forms the basis of computation of 
advance tax, such total income[ exclusive of capital gains 
and income referred to in sub- clause (ix) of clause (24) of 
section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause (c) of section 115C] of the Income- 
tax Act] as increased by the net agricultural income, if any, 
returned by the person in the return of income for the 
assessment year relevant to that previous year;

<subsubsection><tid>1697231</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where an estimate is sent by the person under 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 209A or section 212 of the Income- tax Act the total 
income[ exclusive of capital gains and income referred to in 
sub- clause (ix) of clause (24) of section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause 
 (c) of section 115C] of the Income- tax Act] as estimated by 
him of the period which would be the previous year for that 
assessment creased by the net agricultural income, if any, of 
that estimated by him;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>639575</tid>
<number>c</number>in any other case, if the total income of the person, 
as estimated by him, of the period which would be the 
previous year for that assessment year exceeds the maximum 
amount rot chargeable to income- tax in his case, such total 
income[ exclusive of capital gains and income referred to in 
sub- clause (ix) of clause (24) of section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause 
 (c) of section 115C] of the Income- tax Act] as increased by 
the net agricultural income, if any, of that period, as 
estimated by him.
Explanation.- In this sub- section,, net agricultural income" means 
the net agricultural income as defined in the- Finance Act of the 
relevant year.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>515</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1978</year>, S. 40 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1983</year>, s. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1983</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>311651</tid>
<number> 5</number> Time for making compulsory deposit. A depositor shall make 
the compulsory deposit for an assessment year referred to in sub- 
section
<section><tid>834630</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3,- 

<subsection><tid>1182473</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where such depositor is required to pay 
advance tax under the Income- tax Act in the financial year 
immediately preceding that assessment year, at any time (in  
  one sum or in instalments of his choice) before the expiry of 
the date on which the last instalment of advance tax is 
payable by him in accordance with the provisions of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 
 211 or sub- section (4) of section 209A] or, as the case may 
be, sub- section (3A) of section 212 of that Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>161117</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, at any time (in one sum or in  
  instalments of his choice) before the end of the financial 
year immediately preceding that assessment year.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>497042</tid>
<number> 6</number> Order by Income- tax Officer for compulsory deposit in certain 
cases.
<section><tid>1297416</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in relation to an assessment year referred to in sub-  
section (1) of section 3, the correct income of a person falling 
under clause (c) of sub- section (3) of section 4 exceeds fifteen 
thousand rupees and such person has failed to make the compulsory 
deposit for that assessment year, the Income- tax Officer shall, by 
order in writing, direct that such person shall make the compulsory 
deposit with reference to his correct income.

</section>

<section><tid>548150</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section," correct income" of a 
person, in relation to an assessment year, means-

<subsection><tid>1324197</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the person has furnished the return of 
income under section 139 of the Income- tax Act, the total 
income[ exclusive of capital gains and income referred to in 
  sub- clause fix) of clause (24) of section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause 
 (c) of section 115C] of the Income- tax Act] returned by him, 
as increased by the net agricultural income, if any, returned 
by him:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1287284</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case where the person has failed to furnish the 
return of income under section 139 of the Income- tax Act and 
assessment is made under section 144 of that Act, the total 
income[ exclusive of capital gains and income referred to in 
sub- clause (ix) of clause (24) of section 2 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and in clause 
 (c) of section 115C] of the Income- tax Act] determined on 
assessment, as increased by the net agricultural income, if 
any, determined on assessment.
Explanation.- In this sub- section," net agricultural income" has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Explanation to sub- section (3) of 
section 4.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1269244</tid>
<number> 7</number> Compulsory deposit to carry simple interest.
<section><tid>1171385</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
compulsory deposit made by or recovered from a depositor shall carry 
simple interest at a rate equal to the bank deposit rate.
Explanation.- In this sub- section," bank deposit rate" means the 
highest of the maximum rates at which interest may be paid on 
different classes of deposits (other than those maintained in savings  
  account or those maintained by charitable or religious institutions) 
by different classes of scheduled banks in accordance with the 
directions given or issued to banking companies generally by the 
Reserve Bank of India under the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>. (10 of  
  <year>1949</year>.)


</section>

<section><tid>1273062</tid>
<number>2</number>The interest shall be calculated in such manner as may be 
specified in the scheme framed under section 19,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>516</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1978</year>, S. 40 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1983</year>, S. 59 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1983</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>207065</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of the deduction under section 80L of the 
Income- tax Act, interest received on a compulsory deposit shall be 
deemed to be interest received on a deposit with a banking company to 
which the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, applies.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>492506</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the purposes of exemption under section 5 of the 
Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, the amount of compulsory deposit shall be deemed 
to be a deposit with a banking company to which the Banking Regulation 
Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>.) applies."]


</article>



<article><tid>1149522</tid>
<number> 8</number> Repayment compulsory deposit. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1087663</tid>
<number>1</number>] The amount of compulsory  
deposit made by or recovered from a depositor in any financial year 
shall be repayable in five equal annual instalments commencing from 
the expiry of two years from the end of that financial year, together 
with the interest due on the whole or, as the case may be, part of the 
amount of the compulsory deposit which has remained unpaid:
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided that no depositor shall be entitled to withdraw 
before the expiry of the financial year <year>1985</year>- 86 any amount which, in 
accordance with the foregoing provisions of this sub- section, is 
repayable or payable during that financial year and the provisions of 
sub- section (2) shall apply in relation to such amount as they apply 
in relation to any amount referred to in that sub- section:"]

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided further that] nothing in this section shall prevent 
earlier repayment of the deposit or any instalment thereof together 
with the interest due in any case in which the Income- tax Officer is 
satisfied that extreme hardship will be caused unless such repayment 
is made.


</section>

<section><tid>1439728</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>633518</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of compulsory deposit made by or recovered 
from an individual; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>957405</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of compulsory deposit made by or recovered 
from any person who is assessable under the Income- tax Act in 
respect of the total income of an individual on behalf of 
such individual,
shall, to the extent it has remained unpaid, be repayable, 
together with interest thereon,-


<subsubsection><tid>414313</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Where such individual has attained the age of sixty- 
five years before the 1st day of April, <year>1983</year>, on the 1st day 
of June, <year>1983</year>; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1884724</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, on the first day of the financial 
year immediately succeeding the financial year in which such 
individual attained sixty- five years of age".]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1020803</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where any amount has become repayable or payable under 
sub- section (1), <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or sub- section (1A),"] the depositor may, at his 
option, not withdraw such amount after it has become so repayable or 
payable, and if he does so, such amount shall carry interest for the 
period it is not withdrawn as if it were a compulsory deposit, and the 
provisions of this Act shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to 
such amount or interest thereon as they apply in relation to a 
compulsory deposit or as the case may be, interest on such deposit."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1001845</tid>
<number>9</number>Intimation regarding compulsory deposit. Every depositor 
shall send to the Income- tax Officer, along with the return of income 
for the assessment year for which he is liable to make a compulsory 
deposit, proof of the fact of such deposit having been made.


</article>



<article><tid>1826129</tid>
<number> 10</number> Penalty for failure to make compulsory deposit.
<section><tid>251162</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in  
relation to an assessment year referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 3, any person who is liable to make a compulsory deposit 
[ being a person falling under clause (a) or clause (b) of subsection 
 (3) of section 4]-

<subsection><tid>1419245</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> has without reasonable cause failed to make] the 
compulsory deposit within the time allowed under section 5, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>367302</tid>
<number>b</number>has made the compulsory deposit within such time but 
the deposit so made falls short of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the requisite amount 
and there is no reasonable cause for making such short 
payment"]
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Income- tax Officer may], by order in writing, direct 
that such person shall pay, by way of penalty, a sum-


<subsubsection><tid>911611</tid>
<number>i</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall be 
equal to twenty- five per cent. of the compulsory deposit 
which he is liable to make; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1686500</tid>
<number>ii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall be 
equal to twenty- five per cent. of the amount by which the 
compulsory deposit made by him falls short of the requisite 
amount.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>192618</tid>
<number>2</number>If, in relation to an assessment year referred to in sub- 
section (1) of section 3, the correct income of a person falling 
under clause (c) of sub- section (3) of section 4, exceeds fifteen 
thousand rupees and such person-

<subsection><tid>1615721</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> has, without reasonable cause, failed to make"] the 
compulsory deposit within the time allowed under section 5, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535355</tid>
<number>b</number>has made the compulsory deposit within such time on the 
basis of his own estimate but the deposit so made <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> falls 
short of].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>517</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. and Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Renumbered and ins., ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act.............

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 25 of <year>1985</year>, S. 2.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

seventy- five per cent. of the compulsory deposit which he 
would have been liable to make on the basis of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> his 
correct income and there is no reasonable cause for making 
such short payment"];

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Income- tax Officer may"] by order in writing, direct 
that such person shall pay by way of penalty a sum-


<subsubsection><tid>1589657</tid>
<number>i</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall be 
equal to twenty- five per cent. of the compulsory deposit 
calculated with reference to his correct income; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>826247</tid>
<number>ii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall be 
equal to twenty- five per cent. of the amount by which the 
compulsory deposit made by him falls short of the compulsory 
deposit calculated with reference to his correct income.
Explanation,- In this sub- section," correct income" has the 
meaning assigned to it in sub- section (2) of section 6.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>85573</tid>
<number>3</number>No order imposing a penalty under this section shall be made 
against any person unless such person has been heard or has been given 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1673074</tid>
<number> 11</number> Authorities.
<section><tid>1477398</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Director of Inspection, Commissioner  
of Income- tax <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner of income- tax (Appealo)], Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner of Income- tax, Inspecting Assistant 
Commissioner of Income- tax, Income- tax Officer and Inspector of 
Income- tax, shall have the like powers and perform the like functions 
under this Act as he has and performs under the Income- tax Act, and 
for the exercise of his powers and the performance of his functions, 
his jurisdiction under this Act shall be the same as he has under the 
Income- tax Act and for this purpose compulsory deposit under this Act 
shall be deemed to be tax chargeable under that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>706261</tid>
<number>2</number>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions 
of the Board:
Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be 
issued-


<subsection><tid>1750654</tid>
<number>a</number>so as to require any authority referred to in sub- section 
 (1) to dispose of a particular case in a particular manner: 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1963794</tid>
<number>b</number>so as to interfere with the discretion of the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals) or the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner"] in the exercise of his appellate functions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>416159</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Income- tax Officer employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions, 
issued guidance by the Director of Inspection or by the Commissioner 
or by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within whose jurisdiction 
he performs his functions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>730565</tid>
<number> 12</number> Appeals and revision.[ 1] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions of 
sub- section (2), any depositor"] aggrieved by any order of the Income- 
tax Officer under section 10, may Appeal to the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner and the provisions of the Income- tax Act relating to 
appeals, reference and revision shall, so far as may be, Apply in 
relation as they apply in relation to an order of the Income- tax sing 
a penalty under section 221 of that Act.
<section><tid>1992563</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where an order referred to in sub- section (1) is made by an 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner in exercise of the powers or 
functions conferred on or assigned to him under section 125 or section 
 125A of the Income- tax Act, the provisions of that sub- section shall 
have effect as if for the words" Appellate Assistant Commissioner", 
the words and brackets" Commissioner (Appeals)" were substituted."]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 12 (1) Where any order imposing a penalty under section 10 
made by the Income- tax Officer before the date on which the Finance 
 (No. 2) Act, <year>1980</year> received the assent of the President (such order  
being hereafter in this section referred to as pre- amendment penalty 
  order) has not been made the subject matter any subsequent proceeding 
by way of appeal or revision under this Act, then, the depositor 
aggrieved by such order may, if the considers that no such penalty 
would have been levied if the amendments made to section 10 by the 
Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1980</year> had been in force on the date of passing of 
such order, make an application to the Income- tax Officer for a 
special review.


</section>

<section><tid>1992563</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a pre- amendment penalty order has been made the 
subject matter of any subsequent proceeding by way of an appeal or 
revision under this Act, the depositor aggrieved by the order passed 
in any such proceeding or as the case may beg the last of such 
proceedings may, if he considers that no such penalty would have been 
levied if the amendments made to section 10 by the Finance (No. 2) 
Act, <year>1980</year> had been in force on the date of passing of the pre- 
amendment penalty order, make an application to the authority which 
passed the order in such proceeding or, as the case may be, the last 
of such proceedings for a special review.

</section>

<section><tid>396385</tid>
<number>3</number>The application referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2) shall be presented before the 1st day of January, <year>1981</year>:
Provided that the Income- tax Officer or the other authority to 
whom an application for special review is made may admit such 
application after the said date if he or it is satisfied that the 
depositor had sufficient cause for not presenting it before the said 
date.


</section>

<section><tid>1374508</tid>
<number>4</number>The income- tax Officer or other authority to whom the 
application for special review is made under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), may make such enquiry or cause such enquiry to be made 
and, subject to the provisions of this Act, may pass such order as he 
or it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1884212</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions of section 12 shall, so far as may be, apply 
in relation to an order passed under sub- section (4) as they apply in 
relation to a pre- amendment penalty order or, as the case may be, an 
order passed by any other authority under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>314883</tid>
<number>6</number>The special review under this section shall be in addition 
to and not in derogation of any other remedy which an aggrieved 
depositor may have under this Act.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," authority" 
includes the Appellate Tribunal.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>518</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. renumbered and ins., ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins., ibid, (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1980</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>940975</tid>
<number> 13</number> Rectification of mistakes.
<section><tid>159414</tid>
<number>1</number>With a view to rectifying any  
mistake apparent from the record, the Income- tax Officer, the 
Appellate Assistant Commissioner, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Commissioner (Appeals)] the 
Commissioner and the appellate Tribunal may, of his, or its, own 
motion or on an application by the depositor in this behalf, amend any 
order passed by him or it in any proceeding under this Act, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> within 
four years from the end of the financial year in which such order was 
passed"]

</section>

<section><tid>1847339</tid>
<number>2</number>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the compulsory 
deposit or any penalty imposed under this Act shall not be made under 
this section unless the authority concerned has given notice to the 
depositor of its intention so to do and has allowed the depositor a 
reason able opportunity of being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>976602</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an amendment is made- under this section, the order shall be 
passed in writing by the authority concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1172198</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the 
compulsory deposit or the penalty imposed under this Act, the Income- 
tax Officer shall serve on the depositor a notice specifying the sum 
which has to be deposited or paid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1094790</tid>
<number> 14</number> Collection and recovery of compulsory deposit and penalty.

<section><tid>994836</tid>
<number>1</number>When, in consequence of any order passed under this Act, any  
compulsory deposit or penalty has to be made or paid, the income- tax 
Officer shall serve upon the depositor a notice specifying the sum 
which has to be deposited or paid.

</section>

<section><tid>198474</tid>
<number>2</number>The sum specified in a notice under sub- section (1) shall be 
deposited or, as the case may be, paid within thirty- five days of the 
service of the notice at the place and with or to the person mentioned 
in the notice:
Provided that on an application made by the depositor before the 
expiry of the said period of thirty- five days, the Income- tax Officer 
may extend the time for making the deposit or payment or allow tile 
deposit or payment to be made by instalments subject to such 
conditions as he may think fit to impose in the circumstances of the 
case.


</section>

<section><tid>770485</tid>
<number>3</number>If a depositor fails to make the compulsory deposit within 
the time allowed under section 5, or if he fails to deposit or, as the 
case may be, pay the amount which he is required to deposit or pay by 
notice under sub- section (1) within the time allowed under sub- section 
 (2)  (whether fixed originally or on extension), at the place and with 
or to the person mentioned in the said notice, the depositor shall be 
deemed to be in default.

</section>

<section><tid>856459</tid>
<number>4</number>Any arrear of compulsory deposit and any penalty imposed 
under this Act shall be recoverable in the manner provided in Chapter 
XVII- D of the Income- tax Act for recovery of arrears of tax and for 
this purpose the provisions of that Chapter shall apply as if 
references to the assessee therein were references to the depositor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>945338</tid>
<number> 15</number> Rounding off.
<section><tid>1399647</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount of the current income, correct  
income and compulsory deposit shall be rounded off to the nearest 
multiple of ten rupees and, for this purpose, any part of a rupee 
consisting of paise shall be ignored and thereafter if such amount is 
not a multiple of ten, then, if the last figure in that amount is five 
or more, the amount shall be increased to the next higher amount which 
is a multiple of ten and if the last figure is less than five. the 
amount shall be reduced to the next lower amount which is a multiple 
of ten.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>519</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, S. 53 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1980</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, S. 81 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- In this sub- section," current income" and" correct 
income" have the meanings respectively assigned to them in sub- section 
 (3) of section 4 and sub- section (2) of section 6.


</section>

<section><tid>1234779</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount of penalty payable under the provisions of this 
Act shall be rounded off to the nearest rupee and, for this purpose, 
where such amount contains a part of a rupee consisting of paise, 
then, if such part is fifty paise or more, it shall be increased to 
one rupee and if such part is less than fifty paise, it shall be 
ignored.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1679562</tid>
<number>16</number>Applicability of Chapter XV of Income- tax Act. The 
provisions of Chapter XV of the Income- tax Act relating to liability 
in special cases shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to com- 
pulsory deposits and penalties impassable under this Act as they apply 
in relation to income- tax payable and penalties impassable under that 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>853939</tid>
<number> 17</number> Protection against attachment.
<section><tid>214859</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount of compulsory  
deposit and interest thereon standing to the credit of any depositor 
shall not be liable to attachment under a decree or order of any court 
in respect of any debt or liability incurred by the depositor.

</section>

<section><tid>1344700</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount of compulsory deposit and interest thereon 
standing to the credit of a depositor at the time of his death and 
payable to his nominee shall vest in the nominee and shall be free 
from debt or other liability incurred by the deceased or incurred by 
the nominee before the death of the depositor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>447911</tid>
<number>18</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government 
or against any officer of the Government for anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any scheme framed 
thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>488799</tid>
<number> 19</number> Compulsory Deposit Scheme.
<section><tid>1531529</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, frame a scheme or schemes, 
to. be called Compulsory Deposit (Income- tax Payers) Scheme or 
Schemes, in relation to compulsory deposits.

</section>

<section><tid>279564</tid>
<number>2</number>A scheme framed under sub- section (1) may provide for-

<subsection><tid>1648970</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which compulsory deposits shall be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1298962</tid>
<number>b</number>the documents to be issued to persons by whom deposits 
have been made as evidence of such deposits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1830506</tid>
<number>c</number>the authority or authorities by or through whom the 
deposits may be collected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>688147</tid>
<number>d</number>the nomination of any person to receive the amount 
standing to the credit of a depositor in the event of his 
death or in cancellation or change of such nomination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>242186</tid>
<number>e</number>the issue of duplicate of any document issued as 
evidence of any deposit in the event of loss or destruction 
of the original and the fee (not exceeding two rupees) on the 
payment of which such duplicate may be issued;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1123754</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be necessary or Proper for 
the effective implementation of the scheme.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>520</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>166451</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, add to, amend or vary any scheme framed under sub- section 
 (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1029362</tid>
<number>4</number>A scheme framed under sub- section (1) or a notification 
issued, under sub- section (3) may provide that all or any of its 
provisions shall take effect either prospectively or retrospectively 
on such date as may be specified in this behalf in the scheme or 
notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1539014</tid>
<number>5</number>Any scheme framed under sub- section (1) or any notification 
issued under sub- section (3) shall have effect notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law for the time being in force (other than  
  this Act) or any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other 
than this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>780584</tid>
<number>6</number>Every scheme framed under sub- section (1) and every 
notification issued under sub- section (3) shall be laid, as soon as 
may be, after it is framed or issued before each House of Parliament 
while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the scheme or notification or both Houses agree that 
the scheme or notification should not be framed or issued, the scheme 
or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that scheme or 
notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319945</tid>
<number>20</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent With the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the commencement of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>637851</tid>
<number> 21</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1097527</tid>
<number>1</number>The Compulsory Deposit Scheme (Income-   
  tax Payers) Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (10 of <year>1974</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>138790</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>