<act><tid>151676</tid>
<title>THE PRE- NATAL DIAGNOSTIC TECHNIQUES (REGULATION AND PREVENTION  
  OFMISUSE) ACT, <year>1994</year></title>

ACT NO. 57 OF <year>1994</year>
[ 20th September, <year>1994</year>]

An Act to provide for the regulation of the use of pre- natal 
diagnostic techniques for the purpose of detecting genetic or 
metabolic disorders or chromosomal abnormalities or certain congenital 
malformations or sex linked disorders and for the prevention of the 
misuse of such techniques for the purpose of pre- natal sex 
determination leading to female foeticide, and for matters connected 
there with or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>626438</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>728654</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention  
  of Misuse) Act, <year>1944</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1265712</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall extend to the whole of India except the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1656321</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1923911</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>995574</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appropriate Authority" means the Appropriate Authority 
appointed under section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>1247837</tid>
<number>b</number>" Board" means the Central Supervisory Board constituted 
under section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>1324491</tid>
<number>c</number>" Genetic Counselling Centre" means an institute, 
hospital, nursing home or any place, by whatever name called, 
which provides for genetic counselling to patients;

</section>

<section><tid>1915878</tid>
<number>d</number>" Genetic Clinic" means a clinic, institute, hospital, 
nursing home or any place, by whatever name called, which is used 
for conducting pre- natal diagnostic procedures;

</section>

<section><tid>1077437</tid>
<number>e</number>" Genetic Laboratory" means a laboratory and includes a 
place where facilities are provided for conducting analysis or 
tests of samples received from Genetic Clinic for pre- natal 
diagnostic test;

</section>

<section><tid>1177652</tid>
<number>f</number>" gynaecologist" means a person who possesses a post- 
graduate qualification in gynaecology and obstetrics;

</section>

<section><tid>798832</tid>
<number>g</number>" medical geneticist" means a person who possesses a 
degree or diploma or certificate in medical genetics in the field 
of pre- natal diagnostic techniques or has experience of not less 
than two years in such field after obtaining--

<subsection><tid>660626</tid>
<number>i</number>any one of the medical qualifications recognised 
under the Indian Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year> (102 of <year>1956</year>); 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>299783</tid>
<number>ii</number>a post- graduate degree in biological sciences;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>58092</tid>
<number>h</number>" paediatrician" means a person who possesses a post- 
graduate qualification in paediatrics;

</section>

<section><tid>1875330</tid>
<number>i</number>" pre- natal diagnostic procedures" means all 
gynaecological or obstetrical or medical procedures such as 
ultrasonography foetoscopy, taking or removing samples of 
amniotic fluid, chorionic villi, blood or any tissue of a 
pregnant woman for being sent to a Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic for conducting pre- natal diagnostic test;

</section>

<section><tid>1850810</tid>
<number>j</number>" pre- natal diagnostic techniques" includes all pre- natal 
diagnostic procedures and pre- natal diagnostic tests;

</section>

<section><tid>82941</tid>
<number>k</number>" pre- natal diagnostic test" means ultrasonography or any 
test or analysis of amniotic fluid, chorionic villi, blood or any 
tissue of a pregnant woman conducted to detect genetic or 
metabolic disorders or chrom somal abnormalities or congential 
anomalies or naemoglobinopathies or sex- linked diseases;

</section>

<section><tid>240863</tid>
<number>l</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1282217</tid>
<number>m</number>" registered medical practitioner" means a medical 
practitioner who nossesses any recognised medical qualification 
as defined in clause

</section>

<section><tid>58092</tid>
<number>h</number>of section 2 of the Indian Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year>, 
 (102 of <year>1956</year>.) and whose name has been entered in a State Medical 
Register;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1725329</tid>
<number>n</number>" regulations" means regulations framed by the Board 
under this Act.
CHAP

REGULATION OF GENETIC COUNSELLING CENTRES GENETIC LABORATORIES ANDGENETIC 
CLINICS

CHAPTER II

REGULATION OF GENETIC COUNSELLING CENTRES GENETIC LABORATORIES 
AND GENETIC CLINICS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>768956</tid>
<number> 3</number> Regulation of Genetic Counselling Centres, Genetic 
Laboratories and Genetic Clinics. On and from the commencement of this 
Act,--
<section><tid>392016</tid>
<number>1</number>no Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic unless registered under this Act, shall conduct or associate 
with, or help in, conducting activities relating to pre- natal 
diagnostic techniques;

</section>

<section><tid>1069459</tid>
<number>2</number>no Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic shall employ or cause to be employed any person who does not 
possess the prescribed qualifications;

</section>

<section><tid>1950085</tid>
<number>3</number>no medical geneticist, gynaecologist paediatrician registered 
medical practitioner or any other person shall conduct or cause to be 
conducted or aid in conducting by himself or through any other person, 
any pre- natal diagnostic techniques at a place other than a place 
registered under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

REGULATION OF PRE- NATAL DIAGNOSTIC TECHNIQUES

CHAPTER III

REGULATION OF PRE- NATAL DIAGNOSTIC TECHNIQUES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>249456</tid>
<number> 4</number> Regulation of pre- natal diagnostic techniques. On and from the 
commencement of this Act,--
<section><tid>737253</tid>
<number>1</number>no place including a registered Genetic Counselling Centre or 
Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic shall be used or caused to be 
used by any person for conducting pre- natal diagnostic techniques 
except for the purposes specified in clause (2) and after satisfying 
any of the conditions specified in clause (3);

</section>

<section><tid>340503</tid>
<number>2</number>no pre- natal diagnostic techniques shall be conducted except 
for the purposes of detection of any of the following abnormalities, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1195027</tid>
<number>i</number>chromosomal abnormalities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1899749</tid>
<number>ii</number>genetic metabolic diseases;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>527752</tid>
<number>iii</number>haemoglobinopathies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1406841</tid>
<number>iv</number>sex- linked genetic diseases;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1917085</tid>
<number>v</number>congenital anomalies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>293118</tid>
<number>vi</number>any other abnormalities or diseases as may be specified 
by the Central Supervisory Board;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>601098</tid>
<number>3</number>no pre- natal diagnostic techniques shall be used or conducted 
unless the person qualified to do so is satisfied that any of the 
following conditions are fulfilled, namely:--

<subsection><tid>466627</tid>
<number>i</number>age of the pregnant woman is above thirty- five years;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>46490</tid>
<number>ii</number>the pregant woman has undergone of two or more 
spontaneous abortions or foetal loss;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1166430</tid>
<number>iii</number>the pregnant woman had been exposed to potentially 
teratogenic agents such as drugs, radiation, infection or 
chemicals;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1933928</tid>
<number>iv</number>the pregnant woman has a family history of mental 
retardation or physical deformities such as spasticity or any 
other genetic disease;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1948386</tid>
<number>v</number>any other condition as may be specified by the Central 
Supervisory Board;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>162969</tid>
<number>4</number>no person, being a relative or the husband of the pregnant 
woman shall seek or encourage the conduct of any pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques on her except for the purpose specified in clause (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>184670</tid>
<number> 5</number> Written consent of pregnant woman and prohibition of 
communicating the sex of foetus.
<section><tid>34361</tid>
<number>1</number>No person referred to in clause  
 (2) of section 3 shall conduct the pre- natal diagnostic procedures 
unless--

<subsection><tid>1282020</tid>
<number>a</number>he has explained all known side and after effects of 
such procedures to the pregnant woman concerned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1740355</tid>
<number>b</number>he has obtained in the prescribed form her written 
consent to undergo such procedures in the language which she 
understands; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1163298</tid>
<number>c</number>a copy of her written consent obtained under clause (b) 
is given to the pregnant woman.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1628644</tid>
<number>2</number>No person conducting pre- natal diagnostic procedures shall 
communicate to the pregnant woman concerned or her relatives the sex 
of the foetus by words, signs or in any other manner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1080706</tid>
<number> 6</number> Determination of sex prohibited. On and from the commencement 
of this Act,--
<section><tid>454444</tid>
<number>a</number>no Genetic Counselling Centre or Genetic Laboratory or 
Genetic Clinic shall conduct or cause to be conducted in its 
Centre, Laboratory or Clinic, pre- natal diagnostic techniques 
including ultrasonography, for the purpose of determining the sex 
of a foetus;

</section>

<section><tid>1857478</tid>
<number>b</number>no person shall conduct or cause to be conducted any 
pre- natal diagnostic techniques including ultrasonography for the 
purpose of determining the sex of a foetus.
CHAP

CENTRAL SUPERVISORY BOARD

CHAPTER IV

CENTRAL SUPERVISORY BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>964237</tid>
<number> 7</number> Constitution of Central Supervisory Board.
<section><tid>1028325</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall constitute a Board to be known as the Central 
Supervisory Board to exercise the powers and perform the functions 
conferred on the Board under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>600557</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>258977</tid>
<number>a</number>the Minister in charge of the Ministry or Department of 
Family Welfare, who shall be the Chairman, ex officio;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>924263</tid>
<number>b</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in charge of 
the Department of Family Welfare, who shall be the Vice- Chairman, 
ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1677449</tid>
<number>c</number>two members to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the Ministries of Central Government in charge of Woman 
and Child Development and of Law and Justice, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1070819</tid>
<number>d</number>the Director General of Health Services of the Central 
Government, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>431307</tid>
<number>e</number>ten members to be appointed by the Central Government, 
two each from amongst--

<subsubsection><tid>1079683</tid>
<number>i</number>eminent medical geneticists;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1073707</tid>
<number>ii</number>eminent gynaecologists and obstetricians;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1809939</tid>
<number>iii</number>eminent paediatricians;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1813936</tid>
<number>iv</number>eminent social scientists; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>337818</tid>
<number>v</number>representatives of women welfare organisations;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775199</tid>
<number>f</number>three women Members of Parliament, of whom two shall be 
elected by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>585343</tid>
<number>g</number>four members to be appointed by the Central Government 
by rotation to represent the States and the Union territories, 
two in the alphabetical order and two in the reverse alphabetical 
order:
Provided that no appointment under this clause shall be made 
except on the recommendation of the State Government or, as the case 
may be, the Union territory;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>573956</tid>
<number>h</number>an officer, not below the rank of a Joint Secretary or 
equivalent of the Central Government, in charge of Family 
Welfare, who shall be the Member- Secretary, ex officio.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1402907</tid>
<number> 8</number> Term of office of members.
<section><tid>1678993</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of a member,  
other than an ex officio member, shall be,--

<subsection><tid>392725</tid>
<number>a</number>in case of appointment under clause (e) or clause (f) of 
sub- section (2) of section 7, three years; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1765889</tid>
<number>b</number>in case of appointment under clause (g) of the said 
subsection, one year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>109582</tid>
<number>2</number>If a casual vacancy occurs in the office of any other 
members, whether by reason of his death, resignation or inability to 
discharge his functions owing to illness or other incapacity, such 
vacancy shall be filled by the Central Government by making a fresh 
appointment and the member so appointed shall hold office for the 
remainder of the term of office of the person in whose place he is so 
appointed.

</section>

<section><tid>1250435</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chairman shall perform such functions as may be 
assigned to him by the Chairman from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>1616256</tid>
<number>4</number>The procedure to be followed by the members in the discharge 
of their functions shall be such as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1821646</tid>
<number> 9</number> Meetings of the Board.
<section><tid>646801</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall meet at such time  
and place, and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at such  
  meetings) as may be provided by regulations:
Provided that the Board shall meet at least once in six months.


</section>

<section><tid>851616</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman and in his absence the Vice- Chairman shall 
preside at the meetings of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1410394</tid>
<number>3</number>If for any reason the Chairman or the Vice- Chairman is unable 
to attend any meeting of the Board, any other member chosen by the 
members present at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1120068</tid>
<number>4</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Board 
shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the members present and 
voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairman, or in 
his absence, the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or 
casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1290837</tid>
<number>5</number>Members other than ex officio members shall receive such 
allowances, if any, from the Board as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>167301</tid>
<number> 10</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Board. 
No act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalid merely by reason 
of--
<section><tid>784971</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Board; or

</section>

<section><tid>196274</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Board; or

</section>

<section><tid>497955</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board not 
affecting the merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>287744</tid>
<number> 11</number> Temporary association of persons with the Board for 
particular purposes.
<section><tid>774200</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may associate with itself, in such  
manner and for such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any 
person whose assistance or advice it may desire in carrying out any of 
the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>269849</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with it by the Board under sub- section 
 (1) for any purpose shall have a right to take part in the discussions 
relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at a 
meeting of the Board and shall not be a member for any other purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1707127</tid>
<number> 12</number> Appointment or officers and other employees of the Board.
<section><tid>820871</tid>
<number>1</number> 
For the purpose of enabling it efficiently to discharge its functions 
under this Act, the Board may, subject to such regulations as may be 
made in this bahalf, appoint (whether on deputation or otherwise) such 
number of officers and other employees as it may consider necessary:
Provided that the appointment of such category of officers, as 
may be specified in such regulations, shall be subject to the approval 
of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1736535</tid>
<number>2</number>Every officer or other employee appointed by the Board shall 
be subject to such conditions of service and shall be entitled to such 
remuneration as may be specified in the regulations.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>439448</tid>
<number>13</number>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the Board. 
All orders and decisions of the Board shall be authenticated by the 
signature of the Chairman or any other member authorised by the Board 
in this behalf, and all other instruments issued by the Board shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the Member- Secretary or any other 
officer of the Board authorised in like manner in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1193765</tid>
<number> 14</number> Disqualifications for appointment as member. A person shall 
be disqualified for being appointed as a member if, he--
<section><tid>803889</tid>
<number>a</number>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an 
offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves 
moral turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>902144</tid>
<number>b</number>is an undischarged insolvent; or

</section>

<section><tid>1041438</tid>
<number>c</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent 
court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1081688</tid>
<number>d</number>has been removed or dismissed from the service of the 
Government or a Corporation owned or controlled by the 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>55226</tid>
<number>e</number>has, in the opinion of the Central Government, such 
financial or other interest in the Board as is likely to affect 
prejudicially the discharge by him of his functions as a member; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>925059</tid>
<number>f</number>has, in the opinion of the Central Government, been 
associated with the use or promotion of pre- natal diagnostic 
technique for determination of sex.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1443834</tid>
<number>15</number>Eligibility of member for reappointment. Subject to the other 
terms and conditions of service as may be prescribed, any person 
ceasing to be a member shall be eligible for reappointment as such 
member.


</article>



<article><tid>1330314</tid>
<number> 16</number> Functions of the Board. The Board shall have the following 
functions, namely:--
<section><tid>1619673</tid>
<number>i</number>to advise the Government on policy matters relating to 
use of pre- natal diagnostic techniques;

</section>

<section><tid>24630</tid>
<number>ii</number>to review implementation of the Act and the rules made 
thereunder and recommend changes in the said Act and rules to the 
Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1826163</tid>
<number>iii</number>to create public awareness against the practice of 
pre- natal determination of sex and female foeticide;

</section>

<section><tid>1948208</tid>
<number>iv</number>to lay down code of conduct to be observed by persons 
working at Genetic Counselling Centres, Genetic Laboratories and 
Genetic Clinics;

</section>

<section><tid>1192860</tid>
<number>v</number>any other functions as may be specified under the Act.
CHAP

APPROPRIATE AUTHORITY AND ADVISORY COMMITTEE

CHAPTER V

APPROPRIATE AUTHORITY AND ADVISORY COMMITTEE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>845545</tid>
<number> 17</number> Appropriate Authority and Advisory Committee.
<section><tid>976702</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall appoint, by notification in the Official Gazette, one 
or more Appropriate Authorities for each of the Union territories for 
the purposes of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1165096</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government shall appoint, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, one or more Appropriate Authorities for the whole or 
part of the State for the purposes of this Act having regard to the 
intensity of the problem of pre- natal sex determination leading to 
female foeticide.

</section>

<section><tid>590510</tid>
<number>3</number>The officers appointed as Appropriate Authorities under sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (2) shall be,--

<subsection><tid>1741874</tid>
<number>a</number>when appointed for the whole of the State or the Union 
territory, of or above the rank of the Joint Director of Health 
and Family Welfare; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1562021</tid>
<number>b</number>when appointed for any part of the State or the Union 
territory, of such other rank as the State Government or the 
Central Government, as the case may be, may deem fit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1869000</tid>
<number>4</number>The Appropriate Authority shall have the following functions, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>141904</tid>
<number>a</number>to grant, suspend or cancel registration of a Genetic 
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5010</tid>
<number>b</number>to enforce standards prescribed for the Genetic 
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory and Genetic Clinic;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>32263</tid>
<number>c</number>to investigate complaints of breach of the provisions of 
this Act or the rules made thereunder and take immediate action; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126315</tid>
<number>d</number>to seek and consider the advice of the Advisory 
Committee, constituted under sub- section (5), on application for 
registration and on complaints for suspension or cancellation of 
registration.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>655863</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government or the State Government, as the case 
may be, shall constitute an Advisory Committee for each Appropriate 
Authority to aid and advise the Appropriate Authority in the discharge 
of its functions, and shall appoint one of the members of the Advisory 
Committee to be its Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1907732</tid>
<number>6</number>The Advisory Committee shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1898886</tid>
<number>a</number>three medical experts from amongst gynaecologists, 
obstericians, paediatricians and medical geneticists;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1796259</tid>
<number>b</number>one legal expert;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130028</tid>
<number>c</number>one officer to represent the department dealing with 
information and publicity of the State Government or the Union 
territory, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940474</tid>
<number>d</number>three eminent social workers of whom not less than one 
shall be from amongst representatives of women' s organisations.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1743447</tid>
<number>7</number>No person who, in the opinion of the Central Government or 
the State Government, as the case may be, has been associated with the 
use or promotion of pre- natal diagnostic technique for determination 
of sex shall be appointed as a member of the Advisory Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>614317</tid>
<number>8</number>The Advisory Committee may meet as and when it thinks fit or 
on the request of the Appropriate Authority for consideration of any 
application for registration or any complaint for suspension or 
cancellation of registration and to give advice thereon:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the period intervening between any two meetings 
shall not exceed the prescribed period.


</section>

<section><tid>285764</tid>
<number>9</number>The terms and conditions subject to which a person may be 
appointed to the Advisory Committee and the procedure to be followed 
by such Committee in the discharge of its functions shall be such as 
may be prescribed.
CHAP

REGISTRATION OF GENETIC COUNSELLING CENTRES, GENETIC LABORATORIES ANDGENETIC 
CLINICS

CHAPTER VI

REGISTRATION OF GENETIC COUNSELLING CENTRES, GENETIC LABORATORIES 
AND GENETIC CLINICS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1891144</tid>
<number> 18</number> Registration of Genetic Counselling Centres, Genetic 
Laboratories or Genetic Clinics.
<section><tid>1145793</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall open any Genetic  
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic after the 
commencement of this Act unless such Centre, Laboratory or Clinic is 
duly registered separately or jointly under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>821536</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application for registration under sub- section (1), 
shall be made to the Appropriate Authority in such form and in such 
manner and shall be accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>904253</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or 
Genetic Clinic engaged, either partly or exclusively, in counselling 
or conducting pre- natal diagnostic techniques for any of the purposes 
mentioned in section 4, immediately before the commencement of this 
Act, shall apply for registration within sixty days from the date of 
such commencement.

</section>

<section><tid>692885</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of section 6, every Genetic 
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic engaged in 
counselling or conducting pre- natal diagnostic techniques shall cease 
to conduct any such counselling or technique on the expiry of six 
months from the date of commencement of this Act unless such Centre, 
Laboratory or Clinic has applied for registration and is so registered 
separately or jointly or till such application is disposed of, 
whichever is earlier.

</section>

<section><tid>217256</tid>
<number>5</number>No Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic shall be registered under this Act unless the Appropriate 
Authority is satisfied that such Centre, Laboratory or Clinic is in a 
position to provide such facilities, maintain such equipment and 
standards as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>658414</tid>
<number> 19</number> Certificate of registration.
<section><tid>1449986</tid>
<number>1</number>The Appropriate Authority  
shall, after holding an inquiry and after satisfying itself that the 
applicant has complied with all the requirements of this Act and the 
rules made thereunder and having regard to the advice of the Advisory 
Committee in this behalf, grant a certificate of registration in the 
prescribed form jointly or separately to the Genetic Counselling 
Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1474400</tid>
<number>2</number>If, after the inquiry and after giving an opportunity of 
being heard to the applicant and having regard to the advice of the 
Advisory Committee, the Appropriate Authority is satisfied that the 
applicant has not complied with the requirements of this Act or the 
rules, it shall, for reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the 
application for registration.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>781714</tid>
<number>3</number>Every certificate of registration shall be renewed in such 
manner and after such period and on payment of such fees as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1743012</tid>
<number>4</number>The certificate of registration shall be displayed by the 
registered Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic in a conspicuous place at its place of business.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959830</tid>
<number> 20</number> Cancellation or suspension of registration.
<section><tid>14993</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Appropriate Authority may suo moto, or on complaint, issue a notice to 
the Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic 
to show cause why its registration should not be suspended or 
cancelled for the reasons mentioned in the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>328995</tid>
<number>2</number>If, after giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to 
the Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic 
and having regard to the advice of the Advisory Committee, the 
Appropriate Authority is satisfied that there has been a breach of the 
provisions of this Act or the rules, it may, without prejudice to any 
criminal action that it may take against such Centre, Laboratory or 
Clinic, suspend its registration for such period as it may think fit 
or cancel its registration, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1581078</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), if the Appropriate Authority is, of the opinion that it is 
necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, for 
reasons to be recorded in writing, suspend the registration of any 
Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic 
without issuing any such notice referred to in sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959223</tid>
<number> 21</number> Appeal. The Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or 
Genetic Clinic may, within thirty days from the date of receipt of the 
order of suspension or cancellation of registration passed by the 
Appropriate Authority under section 20, prefer an appeal against such 
order to--
<section><tid>957705</tid>
<number>i</number>the Central Government, where the appeal is against the 
order of the Central Appropriate Authority; and

</section>

<section><tid>106582</tid>
<number>ii</number>the State Government, where the appeal is against the 
order of the State Appropriate Authority,
in the prescribed manner.

CHAP

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES

CHAPTER VII

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1495235</tid>
<number> 22</number> Prohibition of advertisement relating to pre- natal 
determination of sex and punishment for contravention.
<section><tid>492209</tid>
<number>1</number>No person,  
organisation, Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or 
Genetic Clinic shall issue or cause to be issued any advertisement in 
any manner regarding facilities of pre- natal determination of sex 
available at such Centre, Laboratory, Clinic or any other place.

</section>

<section><tid>1434180</tid>
<number>2</number>No person or organisation shall publish or distribute or 
cause to be published or distributed any advertisement in any manner 
regarding facilites of pre- natal determination of sex available at any 
Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic or any 
other place.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>58391</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (2) shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years and with fine which may extend to ten 
thousand rupees.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," advertisement" 
includes any notice, circular, label wrapper or other document and 
also includes any visible representation made by means of any light, 
sound, smoke or gas.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>301231</tid>
<number> 23</number> Offences and penalties.
<section><tid>1879004</tid>
<number>1</number>Any medical geneticist,  
gynaecologist, registered medical practitioner or any person who owns 
a Genetic Counselling Centre, a Genetic Laboratory or a Genetic Clinic 
or is employed in such a Centre, Laboratory or Clinic and renders his 
professional or technical services to or at such a Centre, Laboratory 
or Clinic, whether on an honorary basis or otherwise, and who 
contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or rules made thereunder 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees and 
on any subsequent conviction, with imprisonment which may extend to 
five years and with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>187703</tid>
<number>2</number>The name of the registered medical practitioner who has been 
convicted by the court under sub- section (1), shall be reported by the 
Appropriate Authority to the respective State Medical Council for 
taking necessary action including the removal of his name from the 
register of the Council for a period of two years for the first 
offence and permanently for the subsequent offence.

</section>

<section><tid>1483673</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person who seeks the aid of a Genetic Councelling Centre, 
Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic or of a medical geneticist, 
gynaecologist or registered medical practitioner for conducting pre- 
natal diagnostic techniques on any pregnant woman (including such  
  woman unless she was compelled to undergo such diagnostic techniques) 
for purposes other than those specified in clause (2) of section 4, 
shall, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees and 
on any subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to 
five years and with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>798518</tid>
<number>24</number>Presumption in the case of conduct of pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques. Notwithstanding anything in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> 
 (1 of <year>1872</year>), the court shall presume unless the contrary is proved 
that the pregnant woman has been compelled by her husband or the 
relative to undergo pre- natal diagnotic technique and such person 
shall be liable for abetment of offence under sub- section (3) of 
section 23 and shall be punishable for the offence specified under 
that section.


</article>



<article><tid>950367</tid>
<number>25</number>Penalty for contravention of the provisions of the Act or 
rules for which no specific punishment is provided. Whoever 
contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or any rules made 
thereunder, for which no penalty has been elsewhere provided in this 
Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three months or with fine, which may extend to one thousand rupees 
or with both and in the case of continuing contravention with an 
additional fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day 
during which such contravention continues after conviction for the 
first such contravention.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>707946</tid>
<number> 26</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1058192</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any offence, punishable  
under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at 
the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was 
responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1171144</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence punishable under this Act has been committed by a company 
and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent 
or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, 
any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>950519</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1601062</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1609814</tid>
<number>27</number>Offence to be cognizable, non- bailable and non- compoundable. 
Every offence under this Act shall be cognizable, non- bailable and 
non- compoundable.


</article>



<article><tid>249366</tid>
<number> 28</number> Cognizance of offences.
<section><tid>1095804</tid>
<number>1</number>No court shall take cognizance of  
an offence under this Act except on a complaint made by--

<subsection><tid>939486</tid>
<number>a</number>the Appropriate Authority concerned, or any officer 
authorised in this behalf by the Central Government or State 
Government, as the case may be, or the Appropriate Authority; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>511735</tid>
<number>b</number>a person who has given notice of not less than thirty 
days in the manner prescribed, to the Appropriate Authority, of 
the alleged offence and of his intention to make a complaint to 
the court.
Explanation.-- For the purpose of this clause," person" includes a 
social organisation.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1079261</tid>
<number>2</number>No court other than that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a 
Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence 
punishable under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1858733</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a complaint has been made under clause (b) of 
subsection (1), the court may, on demand by such person, direct the 
Appropriate Authority to make available copies of the relevant records 
in its possession to such person.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VIII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645525</tid>
<number> 29</number> Maintenance of records.
<section><tid>723255</tid>
<number>1</number>All records, charts, forms,  
reports, consent letters and all other documents required to be 
maintained under this Act and the rules shall be preserved for a 
period of two years or for such period as may be prescribed:
Provided that, if any criminal or other proceedings are 
instituted against any Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory 
or Genetic Clinic, the records and all other documents of such Centre, 
Laboratory or Clinic shall be preserved till the final disposal of 
such proceedings.


</section>

<section><tid>865355</tid>
<number>2</number>All such records shall, at all reasonable times, be made 
available for inspection to the Appropriate Authority or to any other 
person authorised by the Appropriate Authority in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1445541</tid>
<number> 30</number> Power to search and seize records, etc.
<section><tid>1913401</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
Appropriate Authority has reason to believe that an offence under this 
Act has been or is being committed at any Genetic Counselling Centre, 
Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic, such Authority or any officer 
authorised thereof in this behalf may, subject to such rules as may be 
prescribed, enter and search at all reasonable times with such 
assistance, if any, as such authority or officer considers necessary, 
such Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic 
and examine any record, register, document, book, pamphlet, 
advertisement or any other material object found therein and seize the 
same if such Authority or officer has reason to believe that it may 
furnish evidence of the commission of an office punishable under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1985875</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>) relating to searches and seizures shall, so far as may be, 
apply to every search or seizure made under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1942580</tid>
<number>31</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central or 
the State Government or the Appropriate Authority or any officer 
authorised by the Central or State Government or by the Authority for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of the provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>921183</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1519179</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1122510</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice, to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1277622</tid>
<number>i</number>the minimum qualifications for persons employed at a 
registered Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or 
Genetic Clinic under clause (1) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>42728</tid>
<number>ii</number>the form in which consent of a pregnant woman has to be 
obtained under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>764649</tid>
<number>iii</number>the procedure to be followed by the members of the 
Central Supervisory Board in the discharge of their functions 
under sub- section (4) of section 8;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1751331</tid>
<number>iv</number>allowances for members other than ex officio members 
admissible under sub- section (5) of section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486178</tid>
<number>v</number>the period intervening between any two meetings of the 
Advisory Committee under the proviso to sub- section (8) of 
section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>974736</tid>
<number>vi</number>the terms and conditions subject to which a person may 
be appointed to the Advisory Committee and the procedure to be 
followed by such Committee under sub- section (9) of section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1307039</tid>
<number>vii</number>the form and manner in which an application shall be 
made for registration and the fee payable thereof under sub- 
section (2) of section 18;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>998053</tid>
<number>viii</number>the facilities to be provided, equipment and other 
standards to be maintained by the Genetic Counselling Centre, 
Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic under sub- section (5) of 
section 18;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>202258</tid>
<number>ix</number>the form in which a certificate of registration shall 
be issued under sub- section (1) of section 19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1843223</tid>
<number>x</number>the manner in which and the period after which a 
certificate of registration shall be renewed and the fee payable 
for such renewal under sub- section (3) of section 19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1498953</tid>
<number>xi</number>the manner in which an appeal may be preferred under 
section 21;

<subsubsection><tid>24732</tid>
<number>xii</number>the period up to which records, charts, etc., shall be 
preserved under sub- section (1) of section 29;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1341980</tid>
<number>xiii</number>the manner in which the seizure of documents, 
records, objects, etc., shall be made and the manner in which 
seizure list shall be prepared and delivered to the person from 
whose custody such documents, records or objects were seized 
under sub- section (1) of section 30;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>739127</tid>
<number>xiv</number>any other matter that is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1182072</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power to make regulations. The Board may, with the previous 
sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
Act and the rules made there- under to provide for--
<section><tid>767787</tid>
<number>a</number>the time and place of the meetings of the Board and the 
procedure to be followed for the transaction of business at such 
meetings and the number of members which shall form the quorum 
under sub- section (1) of section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>550006</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which a person may be temporarily 
associated with the Board under sub- section (1) of section 11;

</section>

<section><tid>120854</tid>
<number>c</number>the method of appointment, the conditions of service and 
the scales of pay and allowances of the officer and other 
employees of the Board appointed under section 12;

</section>

<section><tid>1535182</tid>
<number>d</number>generally for the efficient conduct of the affairs of the 
Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429549</tid>
<number>34</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>