<act><tid>1133284</tid>
<title>THE DECREES AND ORDERS VALIDATING ACT, <year>1936</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <footcitenum>1936</footcitenum>
[ 26th April, <year>1936</year>.]

An Act to remove certain doubts and to establish the validity of 
certain proceedings in High Courts of Judicature <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

WHEREAS doubts have arisen as to the validity of certain 
proceedings in High Courts of Judicature <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under the Letters Patent 
erecting and establishing those Courts;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to terminate those doubts and to 
establish the validity of those proceedings;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1148877</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1597299</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Decrees  
and Orders Validating Act, <year>1936</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>249497</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India, except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in Part B States.]]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>166381</tid>
<number>2</number>Certain decrees and orders not to be called in question.- No 
decree passed or order made by the High Court of Judicature at Fort 
William in Bengal, the High Court of Judicature at Madras or the High 
Court of Judicature at Bombay, in the exercise of its ordinary 
original civil jurisdiction under clause 12 of its Letters Patent, or 
by the High Court of Judicature at Rangoon, in the exercise of its 
original civil jurisdiction under clause 10 of its Letters Patent, 
shall be called in question in any proceedings before any other Court 
on the ground that the High Court passing the decree or making the 
order had no jurisdiction to pass or make the decree or order.


</article>



<article><tid>1620823</tid>
<number>3</number>Restoration of proceedings.- Where in any proceedings concluded 
on or after the 26th day of August, <year>1935</year>, any such decree or order has 
been found to be invalid on such ground by any Court, such finding 
shall be void and of no effect; and the Court shall, notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary in the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of  
  <year>1908</year>), or any other law for the time being in force, on application 
made within six months from the commencement of this Act by any person 
prejudicially affected by such finding, restore the proceedings at and 
continue the proceedings from the state reached immediately before the 
order embodying or based on such finding was made.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> This Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadra 
and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and 
Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" in the Provinces" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2 Subs., ibid., for sub- section (2). 
3 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>