<act><tid>113950</tid>
<title>THE APPROPRIATION (VOTE ON ACCOUNT) No. 2 ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 31st July, <year>1996</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act to provide for the withdrawal of certain sums from and out 
of 
the Consolidated Fund of India for the services of a part of 
the 
financial year <year>1996</year>- 97.





<article><tid>1460887</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Appropriation (Vote on  
  Account) No. 2 Act, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>375657</tid>
<number>2</number>Rs. 238717, 98, 00, 000 Withdrawal of from and out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India for the financial year <year>1996</year>- 97. From and 
out of the Consolidated Fund of India there may be withdrawn sums not 
exceeding those specified in column 3 of the Schedule amounting in the 
aggregate[ inclusive of the sums specified in column 3 of the Schedule 
to the Appropriation (Vote on Account) Act, <year>1996</year>] (9 of <year>1996</year>) to the 
sum of two lakhs thirty- eight thousand seven hundred and seventeen 
crores and ninety- eight lakh rupees towards defraying the several 
charges which will come in course of payment during the financial year 
<year>1996</year>- 97.


</article>



<article><tid>605111</tid>
<number>3</number>Appropriation. The sums authorised to be withdrawn from and 
out of the Consolidated Fund by this Act shall be appropriated for the 
services and purposes expressed in the Schedule in relation to the 
said year.


</article>



<article><tid>1119146</tid>
<number>4</number>Construction of references to Ministries and Departments in 
the Schedule. Reference to the Ministries or Departments in the 
Schedule are to such Ministries or Departments as existing immediately 
before the 28th June, <year>1996</year> and shall, on or after that date, be 
construed as references to the appropriate Ministries of Departments 
as reconstituted from time to time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>