<act><title>THE ESTABLISHMENT OF NEW MEDICAL COLLEGES, OPENING OF HIGHER COURSES 
  OF STUDY AND INCREASE OF ADMISSION CAPACITY IN MEDICAL COLLEGES REGULATION, 19931 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Establishment of New Medical Colleges, Opening of Higher Courses of Study and Increase of Admission Capacity in Medical Colleges Regulation, 1993. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
  



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Scheme relating to medical colleges. </title>The scheme referred to in clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-section (2) of section 10A of the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 is annexed hereto. 
 <title>SCHEME </title>
 <title>APPLICATION FOR PERMISSION OF THE CENTRAL  
  GOVERNMENT TO ESTABLISH A New MEDICAL COLLEGE </title>
 <title>INSTRUCTION TO THE APPLICANT </title>
 Eligibility Criteria 
 The following organizations shall be eligible to apply for permission to set up new medical colleges: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> University and State Governments/Union Territories. 
 </subsection>
 Qualifying Criteria 
 The eligible organisation shall abide by Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 as modified from time to time and the regulations framed thereunder and shall qualify to apply for permission to establish new medi­cal colleges only if the following conditions are fulfilled: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> that Medical Education is one of the main objectives of the applicant; 
 </subsection>
 
 
  Proposed Annual intake of under-graduate students
  Minimum Annual Increase in bed strength
  Total bed complement at the end of 4 years 

 
  50
  50
  500

 
  100
  100
  700


 
  
 <subsection><number>9</number> that the applicant has the necessary managerial and financial capabilities to establish and maintain the proposed medical college and its ancillary facilities including a teaching hospital; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>10</number> that the applicant provides two performance bank guar­antees in favour of the Medical Council of India, one for a sum of Rs. 100 lakh ( for 50 annual admissions), Rs. 150 lakhs ( for 100 admissions), and Rs. 200 lakhs (for 150 annual admissions), for the establishment of the medical college and its infrastruc­tural facilities and the second for a sum of Rs. 350 lakhs (for 500 beds), Rs. 500 lakhs (for 700 beds) and Rs. 750 lakhs (for 1000 beds) for the establishment of the teaching hospital and its infrastructural facilities, as per schedule. 
</subsection>
 Exception .The above condition shall not apply to applicants who are State Governments provided that they shall give an undertak­ing to provide funds in their Plan Budget regularly till facili­ties are fully provided as per the time bound programme indicated by them. 
 Forms and Procedures 
 Subject to the fulfilment of the above Eligibility and Qualifying criteria, the application for setting up a new medical college will be submitted by the applicant in the following three parts: 
 Part I 
 Part I of the application (Appendix I) will contain the following particulars about the applicant and information regarding the desirability and prima facie  feasibility of setting up a medical college at the proposed location: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> information regarding constitution of the applicant organisation within the terms of reference of the eligibility criteria; 
 </subsection>
 Part II 
 Part II of the application will contain detailed description of the scheme to set up the new medical college and will be submit­ted in the form of a detailed Techno-Economic Feasibility Report about the proposed medical college complete with the following: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> name and address of the medical college; 
 </subsection>
 Part III 
 Part III of the application will contain detailed description of the existing hospital and the proposed expansion scheme to upgrade the existing hospital or to set up an additional hospital or both to coincide with the phased development of the proposed medical college. This part of the application will also be submitted in the form of a detailed Techno-Economic Feasibility Report about the expansion programme and will include the following: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> name and address of the existing hospital; 
 </subsection>
 Application Fee 
 The application shall be submitted by registered post only to the Secretary (Health) Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, Govern­ment of India, Maulana Azad Road, Nirman Bhawan, New Delhi-110 011 along with a non-refundable 1 [application fee of three lakhs and fifty thousand rupees] in the form of demand draft/pay order in favour of Medical Council of India' payable at Delhi. The fee is for registration, technical scrutiny, contingent expenditure and for three inspections/evaluation of the examina­tions at the end of each professional examinations, i.e.,  at the end of Ist Professional examinations, IInd Professional and IIIrd professional. Beyond three inspections, the normal inspection fee prescribed by the Council will apply. 
 Registration 
 Applications found complete in all respects will be registered by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare and forwarded to the Medical Council of India for evaluation and recommendations. Registration of the applications will only signify the acceptance of the application for evaluation. It will however, under no circumstances means approval of the application for grant of permission. 
 The period of one year prescribed under the Indian Medical Coun­cil (Amendment) Ordinance of 1993 for processing of an application for setting up of a new medical college will commence from the date of registration of the application by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. 
 Incomplete applications will not be registered and will be re­turned by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare to the appli­cant along with enclosures and processing fee. 
 Prescribed Period 
 In computing the time-limit specified above, the time taken by the authorities and institutions submitting the scheme in furnis­hing any information/clarification or additional documents called for by the Council or by the Central Government shall be excluded. 
 Evaluation by Medical Council of India 
 Medical Council of India will evaluate Part I of the application in the first instance to establish the desirability and prima facie  feasibility of setting up the medical college at the pro­posed location and the capability of the applicant to provide the necessary sources and infrastructure for the scheme. While eva­luating each part of the application, the Council may seek further information/clarification or additional documents from the applicant as considered necessary or may carry out physical inspection to verify the information. 
 Grant of Permission 
 The Central Government on the recommendation of the Medical Coun­cil of India, may issue a letter of intent to set up a new col­lege with such conditions by modification in the original propo­sal as may be considered necessary. The formal permission will be granted after the above conditions and modifications are accepted and the performance bank guarantees for the required sums are furnished by the applicant. 
 The formal permission will include a time bound programme for the establishment of the medical college and expansion of the hospi­tal facilities. This permission will also include a clear-cut definition of preliminary requirements to be met in respect of buildings, infrastructural facilities, medical and allied equip­ment, faculty and staff, etc., before admitting the Ist batch of students. The permission will also define annual targets to be achieved by the applicant to commensurate with the intake students during the following years. 
 The above permission to establish a new medical college and admit students will be granted initially for a period of one year and will be renewed on yearly basis subject to verification of the achievements of annual targets and revalidation of the perfor­mance bank guarantees. This process of renewal of permission will continue till such time the establishment of the medical college and expansion of the hospital facilities is completed and a formal recognition of the medical college by the Medical Council of India is granted. Further admissions are liable to be stopped at any stage unless the requirements for various steps of deve­lopment are to the satisfaction of Medical Council of India. 
 <subsection><title><number>N</number>B. </title>The Council may obtain any other information from the proposed medical college as it deems fit and necessary. 
  



</subsection></section></article><article><number>2</number> Autonomous bodies promoted by Central and State Govern­ments. 
 </article><article><number>3</number> Societies registered under Societies Registration Act, 1860 or corresponding Acts in States. 
 </article><article><number>4</number> Public Trusts, religious or charitable, registered under Indian Trust Act, 1882, Wakfs Act, etc. 
</article><article><number>2</number> that suitable plot of land as prescribed by the Medical Council of India is owned and possessed by the applicant to set-up the proposed medical college; 
 </article><article><number>3</number> that Essentiality Certificate regarding the desirabili­ty and feasibility of having the proposed medical college at the proposed location has been obtained and that the adequate clini­cal material is available as per Medical Council of India re­quirements has been obtained by the applicant from the respective State Government or the Union Territory Administration; 
 </article><article><number>4</number> that Consent of Affiliation for the proposed medical college has been obtained by the applicant from a recognised university; 
 </article><article><number>5</number> that the applicant owns and manages a hospital of not less than 300 beds with necessary infrastructural facilities and capable of being developed into a teaching institution as pre­scribed by the Medical Council of India, in the vicinity of proposed medical college; 
 </article><article><number>6</number> that the applicant has a feasible and time bound programme to set up the proposed medical college along with required infrastructural facilities, including adequate hostel facilities for boys and girls, and as prescribed by the Medical Council of India, commensurate with the proposed intake of stu­dents, so as to complete the medical college with a period of four years from the date of grant or permission; 
 </article><article><number>7</number> that the medical college will admit students only after the Indian Medical Council has satisfied itself about the in­frastructural and other facilities for starting MBBS and after receiving a written permission from Central Government; 
 </article><article><number>8</number> that the applicant has a feasible and time bound expansion programme to provide additional beds and infrastructur­al facilities, as prescribed by the Medical Council of India, by way of upgradation of the existing hospital or establishment of new hospital or both so as to collectively provide the following bed complement within a period of four years form the date of grant of permission to set up the proposed medical college: 
</article><article><number>2</number> information regarding basic infrastructural facilities and managerial and financial capabilities of the applicant;and 
 </article><article><number>3</number> information regarding availability of necessary cer­tificates and consents as prescribed in the qualifying criteria. 
</article><article><number>2</number> market survey and environmental analysis, including national and regional medical education policy, need and availa­bility of trained medical manpower, gap analysis, desirability and prima facie feasibility of establishing a new medical college at the proposed location; 
 </article><article><number>3</number> site characteristics and availability of external linkage including topography, plot size, permissible floor space index, ground coverage, building height, road access, availability of public transport, electric supply, water supply, sewage connec­tion, telephone lines, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>4</number> educational programme including annual intake of stu­dents, admission criteria and method of admission, reservation/preferential allocation of seats (if any), depart­mentwise and yearwise curriculum of studies; 
 </article><article><number>5</number> functional programme including departmentwise, srevice­wise functional requirements and area distribution and roomwise seating capacity; 
 </article><article><number>6</number> equipment programme including roomwise list of medical, scientific and allied equipment complete with schedule of quanti­ties and specifications; 
 </article><article><number>7</number> manpower programme : including departmentwise require­ments of teaching staff (full-time), technical, administrative and ancillary staff, categorywise recruitment criteria and salary structure, etc. (minimum as per UGC scale); 
 </article><article><number>8</number> building programme : including buildingwise built-up area of the medical college, faculty and staff housing, staff and student hostels, administrative office, library, auditorium, animal house, mortuary, and other infrastructural facilities such as cultural and recreational centre, sports complex, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>9</number> planing and layout : including master plan of the medical college complex, layout plans, sections, elevations and floorwise area calculations of the medical college and anciallary building, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>10</number> phasing and scheduling : including monthwise schedule of activities indicating commencement and completion of building design, local body approvals, civil construction, provision of engineering services and equipment, recruitment of staff and phased commissioning commensurate with the proposed intake of students; 
 </article><article><number>11</number> project cost : including capital cost of land, build­ings, plant and machinery, medical, scientific and allied equip­ment, furniture and fixtures, and preliminary and pre-operative expenses; 
 </article><article><number>12</number> means of financing the project cost : including contri­bution of the applicant, grants and donations, equity and terms loans, and other sources, if any; 
 </article><article><number>13</number> revenue assumptions : including fee structure and esti­mated annual revenue from various sources; 
 </article><article><number>14</number> expenditure assumptions : including operating expenses and depreciation; and 
 </article><article><number>15</number> operating results : including income statement, cash flow statement and projected balance sheets. 
</article><article><number>2</number> details about the existing hospital and its ancillary building, including bed strength, built-up area, clinical and para-clinical disciplines, bed distribution, architectural and lay-out plans, list of medical and allied equipment, capacity and configuration of engineering services, hospital services, adminis­trative services and other ancillary and support services, cate­gorywise staff strength, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>3</number> details about the additional land for expansion of the existing hospital or for setting up of new hospital, including land particulars, distance from the proposed medical college , plot size, authorised land usage, geography, soil conditions, road access, availability of public transport, electric supply, water supply, sewage connection, telephone lines, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>4</number> upgraded medical progamme : including the additional clinical and para-clinical discipline envisaged under the expan­sion scheme; 
 </article><article><number>5</number> upgraded functional programme : including speciality­wise and servicewise functional requirements and area distribu­tion and specialitywise bed distribution; 
 </article><article><number>6</number> building programme : including details about addition­al built-up area of the hospital, staff housing, staff and stu­dents hostels and other ancillary buildings; 
 </article><article><number>7</number> planing and layout : including upgraded master plan of the hospital complex or master plan of the proposed new hospital as the case may be, along with layout plans, sections, elevations and floorwise area calculations of the hospital and ancillary buildings; 
 </article><article><number>8</number> details about upgradation or additional in the capacity and configuration of engineering services and hospital services; 
 </article><article><number>9</number> equipment programme : including upgraded roomwise list of medical and allied equipment, schedule of quantities and specifications; 
 </article><article><number>10</number> upgraded manpower programme : including categorywise ­distribution of medical, para-medical and other staff; 
 </article><article><number>11</number> phasing and scheduling of the expansion scheme : includ­ing monthwise master schedule of activities indicating commence­ment and completion of building design, local body approvals, civil construction, provision of engineering and hospital servic­es, provisions of medical and allied equipment, recruitment of staff, etc., to commensurate with the development of the proposed medical college; 
 </article><article><number>12</number> project cost of the expansion scheme : including addi­tional cost of land, buildings, engineering and hospital servic­es, medical and allied equipment, furniture and fixtures and preliminary and pre-operative expenses; 
 </article><article><number>13</number> means of financing the cost of expansion scheme : including contributions of the applicant, grants and donations, equity and term loans and other sources, if any; 
 </article><article><number>14</number> revenue assumptions : including details of income from various procedures and services, upgraded service loads and annual revenue; 
 </article><article><number>15</number> expenditure assumptions : including operating expenses, financial expenses, and depreciation; and 
 </article><article><number>16</number> operating results : including income statements, cash flow statements and balance sheets. 
</article><form>
 

THE ESTABLISHMENT OF NEW MEDICAL COLLEGES, OPENING OF HIGHER COURSES  

  OF STUDY AND INCREASE OF ADMISSION CAPACITY IN MEDICAL COLLEGES REGULATION, 19931 
 

 
 

APPENDIX I 
 

FORMAT OF APPLICATION FOR PERMISSION OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT TO ESTABLISH A NEW MEDICAL COLLEGE 
 

(Under section 10A read with section 33 of the Indian Medical Council Act,1956) 
 

PARTICULARS OF THE APPLICANT 
 

NAME OF THE APPLICANT 
 
 

(IN BLOCK LETTERS) 

 

ADDRESS 
 
 

(IN BLOCK LETTERS) 

 

REGISTERED OFFICE 
 
 

(No. STREET, CITY, PIN CODE, TELEPHONE, TELEX, TELEFAX) 

 

CONSTITUTION 
 
 

(STATE GOVERNMENT/ Union Territory administration / UNIVERSITY, AUTONOMOUS BODY, SOCIETY, TRUST) 

 

REGISTRATION/INCORPORATION 
 
 

(NUMBER AND DATE) 

 

NAME OF AFFILIATING UNIVERSITY 
 

List of Enclosures 
 
 

1. Certified copy of Bye-laws/Memorandum and Articles of Association/Trust Deed, etc. 
 

2. Certified copy of Registration/Incorporation. 
 

3. Annual Reports and Audited Balance Sheets for the last 3 years. 
 

4. Certified copy of the Title Deeds of the total availa­ble land as a proof of ownership. 
 

5. Certified copy of the Zoning plans of the available sites indicating the land use. 
 

6. Proof of ownership of the existing Hospital. 
 

7. Certified copy of the Essentiality Certificate issued by the respective State Government/Union Territory Administra­tion. 
 

8. Certified copy of the Consent of Affiliation issued by a recognised University. 
 

9. Authorization Letter addressed to the Bankers of the Applicant authorizing the Central Government/Medical Council of India to make independent enquiries regarding the financial track record of the applicant. 

 

APPLICATION FOR PERMISSION OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT  

  FOR STARTING NEW OR HIGHER COURSES (INCLUDING  

  P.G. DEGREE/DIPLOMA AND HIGHER SPECIALITIES) IN  

  A MEDI­CAL COLLEGE/INSTITUTION 
 

Instruction to the Applicant 
 

For starting higher courses in medical subjects (Annexure I) in the medical colleges/institutions, the applicant should be a recognised medical college or institution. The applicant should conform to the guidelines laid down in the recommendations on Graduate/Postgraduate Medical Education adopted by the Medical Council of India and modified from time to time and approved by the Central Government. They should apply to the Central Government for this permission along with the State Government's permission. Univer­sity's affiliation and in conformity with the Medical Council of India regulations along with the documentary evidence to show additional financial allocation, provision for additional space, provision for additional equipment and other infrastructural facilities and provisions of recruitment of additional staff as per Medical Council of India norms. 
 

Submission of Application/Scheme and Application Fee 
 

The application (Appendix II) shall be submitted by registered post to the Secretary (Health), Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, Government of India. Nirman Bhawan, Maulana Azad Road , New Delhi along with the information and non-refundable applica­tion fee of 2[two lakh rupees] in the form of demand draft in favour of Medical Council of India and payable at Delhi . This fee is for registration, technical scrutiny and contingent charges and for carrying out physical inspection for the purpose. 
 

Qualifying Criteria 
 

The Organisation shall qualify for starting the new or higher courses in the existing medical colleges/institutions only if the following conditions are fulfilled: 
 
 

1. The Medical College/Institution is recognised by the Medical Council of India for running M.B.B.S./Post-graduate courses. 
 

2. The permission letter regarding desirability and feasi­bility for starting of new or higher courses as the existing medical college/institution has been obtained by the applicant from the respective State Government or the Union Territory administration. 
 

3. Letter of University's permission for starting these courses at the existing medical college/institution has been obtained by the applicant from the University to which it is affiliated. 
 

4. That the applicant has a feasible and time bound pro­gramme to provide additional equipment and infrastructual facili­ties like the number of staff, space, funds, equipment and teach­ing beds, etc., for starting these higher courses as per Medical Council of India recommendations. 
 

5. Selection as candidates for degree and diploma courses will be made strictly on the basis of academic merit. The number of teaching staff in relation to the number of students will have to be in the ratio of 1:1 for P.G. degree. 1:2 for P.G. diploma and 1:1 for higher specialities. In this regard Annexure II may be seen. 
 

6. The application provides a bank guarantee for providing addition­al infrastructual facilities for each discipline as follows: 
 
 
 P.G. degree
  

Rs. 85 lakhs

 
 P.G. diploma
  

Rs. 64 lakhs

 
 Higher Specialities
  

Rs. 128 lakhs



 

Exception .The above condition shall not apply to applicants who are State Governments provided that they shall give an undertak­ing to provide funds in their Budget regularly till facilities are fully provided as per the time bound programme indicated by them. 
 

Registration of Application 
 

Incomplete applications will be returned by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare to the applicant along with enclosures and processing fee. 
 

Applications found complete in all respects will be registered by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare and forwarded to the Medical Council of India within 30 days for evaluation and recom­mendations. Acceptance of the applications will only signify the acceptance of the application for evaluation. It will, however, under no circumstances, mean approval of the application for grant of permission. The period of one year prescribed under the Indian Medical Council (Amendment) Act,1933 for processing of an application for starting new or higher courses will commence from the date of registration of the applications by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. 
 

Prescribed Period 
 

In computing the time-limit specified above, the time taken by the authorities and institutions submitting the scheme in furnis­hing any information/clarification or additional documents called for by the Council or by the Central Government shall be excluded. 
 

Evaluation by Medical Council of India 
 

The Medical Council of India will evaluate the application to accept the desirability and prima facie feasible for starting new or higher courses at the existing medical college/institution and the capability of the applicant to provide the necessary courses, and infrastructure for the scheme. 
 

While evaluating the application, the Council may seek further information/clarification or additional documents from the appli­cants as considered necessary and will carry out a physical inspection to verify the information. 
 

Grant of Permission 
 

The Central Government on the recommendations of the Medical Council of India, may issue a letter for intent for starting new or higher courses in the existing medical colleges/institutions with such conditions or modifications in the original proposal as may be considered necessary. The formal permission will be grant­ed after the above conditions and modifications are accepted and the performance bank guarantees for the required sums are fur­nished by the applicant. The Central Government on the recommend­ations of the Medical Council of India may issue the formal permission. 
 

 
 

----------------
 

 1. Vide Notification No. MCI-34 (41)/93 — Med.(N), dated 20th September, 1993, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 29th September, 1993.
 

 2. Subs. by Notification No. MCI-34 (41)/93-Med. (N), dated 13th June, 1997 (w.e.f. 24-6-1997).
</form><form>
 

THE ESTABLISHMENT OF NEW MEDICAL COLLEGES, OPENING OF HIGHER COURSES  

  OF STUDY AND INCREASE OF ADMISSION CAPACITY IN MEDICAL COLLEGES REGULATION, 19931 
 

 
 

APPENDIX III 
 

FORMAT APPLICATION FOR PERMISSION OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT TO INCREASE THE ADMISSION CAPACITY IN  

  M.B.B.S./HIGHER COURSES of STUDY (INCLUDING DIPLOMA/  

  DEGREE IN SPECIALITIES) IN THE EXISTING  

  MEDICAL COLLEGES/INSTITUTIONS 
 

PARTICULARS OF THE APPLICANT 
 

NAME OF THE APPLICANT 
 
 

(IN BLOCK LETTERS) 

 

ADDRESS 
 
 

(IN BLOCK LETTERS) 

 

REGISTERED OFFICE 
 
 

(No. STREET, CITY,PIN CODE, TELEPHONE, TELEX, TELEFAX) 

 

CONSTITUTION 
 
 

(STATE GOVERNMENT/UNION TERRITORY 
 

ADMINISTRATION/UNIVERSITY/AUTONOMOUS 
 

BODY, SOCIETY, TRUST) 

 

REGISTRATION/INCORPORATION 
 
 

(NUMBER AND DATE) 

 

NAME OF AFFILIATING UNIVERSITY 
 

No. OF SEATS APPROVED AND DATE  

  OF RECOGNITION BY MEDICAL COUNCIL OF INDIA 
 

List of Enclosures 
 

1. Certified copy of the Essentiality Certificate issued by the respective State Government/Union Territory Administration on the prescribed proforma. 
 

2. Certified copy of the Consent of Affiliation issued by a recognised University. 
 

3. Authorization letter addressed to the bankers of the Applicant authorizing the Central Government/Medical Council of India to make independent enquiries regarding the financial track record of the applicant. 
 

4. Certified copy of the letter from Medical Council of India approving recognition of the college/institution. 
 

 
 

----------------
 

 1. Vide Notification No. MCI-34 (41)/93 — Med.(N), dated 20th September, 1993, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 29th September, 1993.
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>