<act><tid>760818</tid>
<title>THE COKING COAL MINES (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 64 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the taking over, in the public interest, of the 
management of coking coal mines and coke oven plants, pending 
nationalisation of such mines and plants.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>992274</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1788345</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Coking Coal Mines (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1053248</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 16th day of 
October, <year>1971</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>334873</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>133206</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 17th day of October, <year>1971</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1410326</tid>
<number>b</number>" coke oven plant" means the plant and equipment with 
which the manufacture of hard coke has been, or is 
being, carried on and includes--

<subsection><tid>145072</tid>
<number>i</number>all lands, buildings, works, machinery and 
equipment, vehicles, railways, tramways and sidings, 
adjacent to, and belonging to, or in, the coke oven 
plant,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>106</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517041</tid>
<number>ii</number>all workshops belonging to the coke oven 
plant including buildings, machinery, instruments, 
stores, equipment of such workshops and the lands on 
which such workshops stand,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>471668</tid>
<number>iii</number>all hard coke in stock or in transit or 
under production, and other stores, stocks and 
instruments, belonging to the coke oven plant,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>763460</tid>
<number>iv</number>all power stations belonging to the coke oven 
plant or operated for supplying electricity for the 
purpose of working the coke oven plant,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>214625</tid>
<number>v</number>all lands, buildings and equipment adjacent to 
or belonging to, the coke oven plant where the washing 
of coal is carried on,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1594676</tid>
<number>vi</number>all other assets, movable or immovable, 
belonging to a coke oven plant, whether within its 
premises or outside, including cash balances, reserve 
funds and investments in so far as they relate to the 
coke oven plant and also any money lawfully due to the 
coke oven plant in relation to any period prior to the 
specified date;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1944399</tid>
<number>c</number>" coking coal mine" means a coal mine in which there 
exists one or more seams of coking coal, whether 
exclusively or in addition to any seam of other coal;

</section>

<section><tid>948982</tid>
<number>d</number>" company" means a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and includes a 
foreign company within the meaning of section 591 of 
that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>793006</tid>
<number>e</number>" Custodian" means the person appointed under section 5 
to take over the management of the coking coal mine;

</section>

<section><tid>486862</tid>
<number>f</number>" Government company" has the meaning assigned to it by 
section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1363471</tid>
<number>g</number>" managing contractor" means the person, or body of 
persons, who, with the previous consent in writing of 
the State Government, has entered into an arrangement, 
contract or understanding, with the owner of the mine 
under which the operations of the mine are 
substantially controlled by such person or body of 
persons;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>107</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1993317</tid>
<number>h</number>" mine" means any excavation where any operation for the 
purpose of searching for or obtaining minerals has been 
or is being carried on and includes--

</section>

<section><tid>1473206</tid>
<number>i</number>all borings and bore holes;

<subsection><tid>1011867</tid>
<number>ii</number>all shafts adjacent to, and belonging to, or 
in, a mine, whether in the course of being sunk or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>927884</tid>
<number>iii</number>all levels and inclined planes in the course 
of being driven;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1637553</tid>
<number>iv</number>all open cast working;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1722182</tid>
<number>v</number>all conveyors or aerial ropeways provided for 
the bringing into or removal from a mine of minerals or 
other articles or for the removal of refuse therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075693</tid>
<number>vi</number>all lands, buildings, works, adits, levels, 
planes, machinery and equipment, vehicles, railways, 
tramways and sidings adjacent to, and belonging to, or 
in, a mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775585</tid>
<number>vii</number>all workshops belonging to, or in, a mine 
including buildings, machinery, instruments, stores, 
equipment of such workshops and the lands on which such 
workshops stand;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1869731</tid>
<number>viii</number>all coal in stock or in transit or under 
production and other stores, stocks and instruments 
belonging to, or in, a mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>280543</tid>
<number>ix</number>all power stations belonging to, or in, a 
mine or operated for supplying electricity for the 
purpose of working the mine or a number of mines under 
the same management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>50082</tid>
<number>x</number>all lands, buildings and equipment adjacent 
to, or belonging to, or in, a mine where the washing of 
coal or manufacture of coke is carried on;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1115171</tid>
<number>xi</number>all other assets, movable or immovable, 
belonging to a mine, whether within its premises or 
outside, including cash balances, reserve funds and 
investments in so far as they relate to the coking coal 
mine and also any money lawfully due to the coking coal 
mine in relation to any period prior to the appointed 
day;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>108</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1715638</tid>
<number>i</number>" mining company" means a company owning a coking coal 
mine, and in relation to a foreign company within the 
meaning of section 591 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), the undertaking of that company in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1686149</tid>
<number>j</number>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official 
Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1154230</tid>
<number>k</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in that Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1994859</tid>
<number>l</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined in 
this Act or in the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>), but defined in 
the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>), have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Mines Act, <year>1952</year>.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF COKING COAL MINES

CHAPTER II

MANAGEMENT OF COKING COAL MINES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>772282</tid>
<number> 3</number> Management of coking coal mines to vest in Central Government 
on the appointed day.
<section><tid>805727</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day, the  
management of all coking coal mines shall vest in the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1767858</tid>
<number>2</number>The coking coal mines specified in the First Schedule shall 
be deemed, for the purposes of this Act, to be the coking coal mines 
the management of which shall vest, under sub- section (1), in the 
Central Government:
Provided that if, after the appointed day, any other coal mine is 
found, after an investigation made by the Coal Board, to contain 
coking coal, that Board shall make a declaration to that effect and on 
and from the date of such declaration, such mine shall be deemed, for 
the purposes of this Act,--


<subsection><tid>779182</tid>
<number>i</number>to vest in the Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43325</tid>
<number>ii</number>to be included in the First Schedule,
and thereupon the provisions of this Act shall become applicable 
thereto subject to the modification that for the words" appointed 
day", wherever they occur, the words" the date of the declaration made 
by the Coal Board under sub- section (2) of section 3" shall be 
substituted.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>109</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1495611</tid>
<number> 4</number> Management of coking coal mines pending the appointment of 
Custodian.
<section><tid>1904270</tid>
<number>1</number>Pending the appointment of a Custodian under section 5  
for any coking coal mine, the person in charge of the management of 
such mine immediately before the appointed day shall, on and from the 
appointed day, be in charge of the management of such mine for and on 
behalf of the Central Government; and the management of such mine 
shall be carried on by such person subject to the provisions contained 
in sub- sections (3) and (5) and such directions, if any, as the 
Central Government may give to him and no other person including the 
owner, shall, so long as such management continues, exercise any 
powers of management in relation to the coking coal mine.

</section>

<section><tid>545868</tid>
<number>2</number>Any contract, whether express or implied, providing for the 
management of any coking coal mine, made before the appointed day 
between the owner of such mine and any person in charge of the 
management of such mine immediately before the appointed day, shall be 
deemed to have terminated on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1691045</tid>
<number>3</number>No person in charge of the management of a coking coal mine 
shall, without the previous approval of the person specified by the 
Central Government in this behalf in respect of that mine (hereinafter  
  referred to as the" authorised person"),--

<subsection><tid>1164899</tid>
<number>a</number>incur any expenditure from the assets appertaining to 
the coking coal mine otherwise than for the purpose of 
making routine payments of salaries or commissions to 
employees, agents or for the purpose of meeting the 
routine day to day expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>206085</tid>
<number>b</number>transfer or otherwise dispose of any such assets or 
create any charge, hypothecation, lien or other 
incumbrance thereon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>33890</tid>
<number>c</number>invest in any manner any monies forming part of such 
assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1980608</tid>
<number>d</number>acquire any immovable property out of the monies forming 
part of such assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1677855</tid>
<number>e</number>enter into any contract of service or agency, whether 
expressly or by implication, for purposes connected 
wholly or partly with the coking coal mine or vary the 
terms and conditions of any contract relating to any 
such transaction subsisting on the appointed day.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>886938</tid>
<number>4</number>The approval of the authorised person may be given either 
generally in relation to certain classes of transactions relating to 
the coking coal mine or specially in relation to any of its 
transactions.

</section>

<section><tid>528673</tid>
<number>5</number>Every person in charge of the management of a coking coal 
mine shall deposit all securities and documents of title to any assets 
appertaining to such mine in any Scheduled Bank or Nationalised Bank 
in which the owner or agent had an account immediately before the 
appointed day or in any branch of the State Bank in the place where 
the head office or the principal office of the coking coal mine is 
situated or, where there is no branch of the State Bank in such place, 
the nearest branch of the State Bank; and no such security or document 
shall be withdrawn from the Scheduled Bank, the Nationalised Bank or 
the State Bank, as the case may be, except with the permission of the 
authorised person:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to any security or document of title kept in trust with an Official 
Trustee in pursuance of the articles of association of any mining 
company unless the Central Government, by notified order, otherwise 
directs.

Explanation.-- In this sub- section,--


<subsection><tid>372943</tid>
<number>a</number>" Scheduled Bank" means a bank included for the time 
being in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>819357</tid>
<number>b</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted 
under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1648334</tid>
<number>c</number>" Nationalised Bank" means a corresponding new bank as 
defined in the Banking Companies (Acquisition and  
  Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1976</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1090916</tid>
<number>6</number>Every person in charge of the management of a coking coal 
mine shall deliver forthwith to the person specified in this behalf by 
the Central Government in respect of that coking coal mine the 
following documents, namely:--

<subsection><tid>12654</tid>
<number>a</number>the minutes book or any other book in India containing 
all resolutions up to the appointed day of the persons 
in charge of the management of the coking coal mine 
before the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>975964</tid>
<number>b</number>the current cheque books relating to the coking coal 
mine which are at the head office or the principal 
office of the coking coal mine;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1245091</tid>
<number>c</number>all registers or other books containing particulars 
relating to the investment of any monies appertaining 
to the coking coal mine including investments on 
mortgaged properties and all loans granted or advances 
made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>468729</tid>
<number>7</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred 
by sub- section (1) and the provisions contained in sub- sections (3), 
 (5) and (6), any direction issued under sub- section (1) may require 
the persons in charge of the management of the coking coal mine under 
this Act to furnish to the Central Government or to the authorised 
person such returns, statements and other information relating to the 
coking coal mine as may be mentioned in the direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1875397</tid>
<number>8</number>The persons in charge of the management of the coking coal 
mine under this Act shall be entitled to such remuneration, whether by 
way of allowance or salary or perquisities as the Central Government 
may fix; and any such person may, by giving one month' s notice in 
writing to the Central Government of his intention so to do, 
relinquish charge of the management of the coking coal mine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>637673</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of Central Government to appoint Custodians to take over 
the management of coking coal mines.
<section><tid>1214234</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,  
as soon as it is convenient administratively so to do, appoint any 
person as Custodian for the purpose of taking over the management of 
the coking coal mine and the person so appointed shall carry on the 
management of such mine for and on behalf of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>368839</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) The Central Government may also appoint a person as the 
Custodian- General for exercising supervision and control over all the 
coking coal mines the management of which is taken over under this 
Act, and on such appointment, every Custodian, appointed under sub- 
section (1), shall act under the guidance, control and supervision of 
the Custodian- General.

<subsection><tid>1890270</tid>
<number>b</number>The Central Government may also appoint one or more persons 
as Additional Custodian- General or Deputy Custodian- General for 
assisting the Custodian- General in the exercise of his powers and 
duties under this Act and the Custodian- General may delegate all or 
such of his powers as he may think fit, to the Additional or Deputy 
Custodian- General.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1351380</tid>
<number>c</number>Every Additional or Deputy Custodian- General shall exercise 
the powers delegated to him under the control and supervision of the 
Custodian- General.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1771015</tid>
<number>3</number>On the appointment of a Custodian under sub- section (1), the 
charge of management of the coking coal mine shall vest in him and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

all persons in charge of the management of such mine immediately 
before such appointment shall cease to be in charge of such management 
and shall be bound to deliver to the Custodian all assets, books of 
account, registers or other documents in their custody relating to the 
coking coal mine and any contract, whether express or implied, 
providing for the management of any coking coal mine, made before the 
appointed day between the owner of such mine and such persons, shall 
be deemed to have terminated on the date on which the Custodian is 
appointed.


</section>

<section><tid>294921</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in section 4 shall apply to any coking coal 
mine the management of which has been taken over by the Custodian, but 
the Central Government may issue such directions to the Custodian as 
to his powers and duties as it deems desirable in the circumstances of 
the case, and the Custodian may apply to the Central Government at any 
time for instructions as to the manner in which he shall conduct the 
management of the coking coal mine or in relation to any matter 
arising in the course of such management.

</section>

<section><tid>1141964</tid>
<number>5</number>The Custodian shall receive from the funds of the coking coal 
mine for the charge of management of which he is appointed under sub- 
section (1) such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1184595</tid>
<number>6</number>The Custodian, the Custodian- General, Additional Custodian- 
General and Deputy Custodian- General shall hold office during the 
pleasure of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>268415</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government may, if it is of opinion that it is 
necessary so to do for the proper management of the coking coal mines, 
the management of which has vested in it under section 3, appoint a 
Government company, whether in existence at the commencement of this 
Act or incorporated after such commencement, as the Custodian of all 
the coking coal mines specified in the First Schedule, and all coke 
oven plants specified in the Second Schedule, and on such appointment, 
every person appointed as Custodian or the Custodian- General or 
Additional or Deputy Custodian- General under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), as the case may be, shall vacate his office as such and 
deliver to the Government company, so appointed, all assets, books of 
account, registers or other documents in his custody relating to the 
coking coal mine or the coke oven plant, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1593896</tid>
<number>8</number>On the appointment of a Government company as Custodian, the 
provisions of sub- sections (3), (4) and (5) shall apply to it as they 
apply to a Custodian appointed under sub- section (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>113</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1451514</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>1931199</tid>
<number>1</number>Every owner of a coking coal mine shall  
be given by the Central Government an amount, in cash, for vesting in 
it, under section 3, the management of such mine.

</section>

<section><tid>1423355</tid>
<number>2</number>For every month during which the management of the coking 
coal mines remains vested in the Central Government, the amount 
referred to in sub- section (1) shall be computed at the rate of 
twenty- five paise per tonne of coal on the highest monthly production 
of coal from such mine during any month in the years <year>1968</year>, <year>1969</year>, <year>1970</year> 
and <year>1971</year>:
Provided that if in relation to any such coking coal mine, there 
was no production of coal during the said years, the amount referred 
to in sub- section (1) shall be computed at the rate of five paise per 
tonne of such highest monthly coal producing capacity of the coking 
coal mine, before the appointed day, as may be assessed and declared 
by the Coal Board:

Provided further that in relation to a coking coal mine, the 
operations of which were immediately before the appointed day under 
the control of a managing contractor, the amount, as computed under 
this sub- section, shall be apportioned between the owner of the coking 
coal mine and such managing contractor in such proportions as may be 
agreed upon by or between the owner and such contractor, and in the 
event of there being no such agreement, in such proportions as may be 
determined by the principal civil court of original jurisdiction 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the head office of the 
coking coal mine is situated.

CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF COKE OVEN PLANTS

CHAPTER III

MANAGEMENT OF COKE OVEN PLANTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>274297</tid>
<number>7</number>Management of coke oven plants to vest in the Central 
Government on the specified date. On and from such date as the Central 
Government may, by notified order, specify in this behalf (hereafter,  
  in this Chapter, referred to as the" specified date"), the management 
of the coke oven plants specified in the Second Schedule shall vest in 
the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>306471</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>217822</tid>
<number>1</number>Every owner of a coke oven plant  
specified in the Second Schedule and every owner of a coke oven plant 
which falls within the definition of coking mine, shall be given by 
the Central

<pagefootnote><pagenum>114</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government an amount, in cash, for vesting in it, under section 7 or 
section 3, as the case may be, the management of such coke oven plant.


</section>

<section><tid>1389784</tid>
<number>2</number>For every month during which the management of the coke oven 
plant remains vested in the Central Government, the amount referred to 
in sub- section (1) shall be computed at the rate of--

<subsection><tid>1048878</tid>
<number>a</number>seventy- five paise per tonne of by- product coke; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492251</tid>
<number>b</number>fifty- five paise per tonne of beehive coke,
on the highest monthly production of coke from such coke oven plant 
during any month in the years <year>1968</year>, <year>1969</year>, <year>1970</year> and <year>1971</year>.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1219511</tid>
<number>3</number>For the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
owner of a coke oven plant, the management of which has vested in the 
Central Government under section 3, shall be given, in addition to the 
amount payable under section 6, such amount as is referred to in sub- 
section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1067489</tid>
<number>9</number>Provisions of sections 4 and 5 and sections 10 to 20 to apply 
to this Chapter. The provisions of sections 4 and 5 and sections 10 to 
 20 (both inclusive) shall apply to a coke oven plant, the management 
of which has vested in the Central Government under section 7, as they 
apply to a coking coal mine, and references therein to a coking coal 
mine and the appointed day shall be construed, unless the oven plant 
and the specified date.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1048248</tid>
<number> 10</number> Penalties. If any person--
<section><tid>1531707</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to deliver to the Custodian any assets, books of 
account, registers or any other document in his custody 
relating to the coking coal mine in respect of the 
management of which the Custodian has been appointed, 
or

</section>

<section><tid>145268</tid>
<number>b</number>retains any property of such coking coal mine or removes 
or destroys it, or

</section>

<section><tid>101742</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to comply with the provisions contained in sub- 
section (3) or sub- section (5) or sub- section (6) of 
section 4; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>115</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1694860</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to comply with any directions issued under sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (4) of section 5,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1511713</tid>
<number> 11</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>12788</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1379162</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1118018</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1160349</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1931193</tid>
<number>12</number>Mining companies not to be wound up by Court. No proceeding 
for the winding up a mining company, the management of whose coking 
coal mines has vested in the Central Government under this Act or for 
the appointment of a Receiver in respect of such business, shall lie 
in any Court except with the consent of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>194629</tid>
<number>13</number>Exclusion of period of operation of the Act for computing 
period of limitation. In computing the period of limitation prescribed 
by law for the time being in force for any suit or application against 
any person by a mining company in respect of any matter arising out 
of any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

transaction in relation to the coking coal mine, the time during which 
this Act is in force shall be excluded.



</article>



<article><tid>606829</tid>
<number>14</number>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument 
having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, or in any 
decree or order of any Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1641327</tid>
<number> 15</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>1289069</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notified order, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act may also be exercised by any person or persons as may 
be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>449372</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1181159</tid>
<number> 16</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>565657</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Custodian- 
General, Additional Custodian- General, Deputy Custodian- General, any 
Custodian or authorised person in respect of anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>802151</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or the Custodian- General, Additional Custodian- 
General, Deputy Custodian- General, any Custodian or authorised person 
for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>498026</tid>
<number> 17</number> Contracts, etc., in bad faith may be cancelled or varied.
<section><tid>1445041</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If the Central Government is satisfied, after such inquiry as it may 
think fit, that any contract or agreement entered into, at any time 
within twelve months immediately preceding the appointed day, between 
the owner or agent of a coking coal mine and any other person, has 
been entered into in bad faith and is detrimental to the interests of 
the coking coal mine, make an order cancelling or varying (either  
unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may think fit to 
  impose) the contract or agreement and thereafter the contract or 
agreement shall have effect accordingly:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled or 
varied except after giving to the parties to the contract or agreement 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>725407</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person aggrieved by an order made under sub- section (1) 
may make an application to the principal court of civil jurisdiction 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the head office of the 
coking coal mine is situated for the variation or reversal of such 
order and thereupon such court may, confirm, modify or reverse such 
order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1679012</tid>
<number>18</number>Power to terminate contract of employment. If the Custodian 
is of opinion that any contract of employment entered into by any 
owner or agent of a coking coal mine, at any time before the appointed 
day, is unduly onerous, he may, by giving to the employee one month' s 
notice in writing or the salary or wages for one month in lieu 
thereof, terminate such contract of employment.


</article>



<article><tid>166408</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>837030</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>867540</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>259435</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the coking coal mines will be 
managed by the Custodians, under the control and 
supervision of the Custodian- General;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693371</tid>
<number>b</number>the constitution of a Board of Management, by whatever 
name called, for advising the Custodian- General in the 
management of the coking coal mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489838</tid>
<number>c</number>the form and manner in which accounts of the coking coal 
mines shall be maintained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013475</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter in relation to which such rule is 
required to be, or may be, made.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1436877</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year> s. 2 and sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1541274</tid>
<number> 20</number> Coking coal mines to which the Act shell not apply. Nothing 
in this Act shall apply to any coking coal mine--
<section><tid>380777</tid>
<number>a</number>owned or managed by a Government company or corporation 
owned or controlled by Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1464520</tid>
<number>b</number>owned or managed by a company engaged in the production 
of iron or steel:
Provided that this section shall not extend to such mine or part 
thereof which, in the opinion of the Central Government, is in excess 
of the requirement for the production of iron and steel by that 
company.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856661</tid>
<number>21</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove 
the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the commencement of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1488037</tid>
<number> 22</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1564433</tid>
<number>1</number>The Coking Coal Mines (Emergency   
  Provisions) Ordinance, <year>1971</year> (12 of <year>1971</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1372587</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done, any action taken 
or any appointment, declaration or order made under the Ordiance so 
repealed, shall be deemed to have been done, taken or made, as the 
case may be, under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>