<act><tid>487759</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT SAVINGS CERTIFICATES ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>1959</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 18th September, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to make certain provisions in respect of Government Savings 
Certificates.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>427939</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, commencement and application.
<section><tid>1420748</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Government Savings Certificates Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1328573</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>1563976</tid>
<number>3</number>It applies to such class of savings certificates as the 
Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1355900</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>774423</tid>
<number>a</number>" minor" means a person who is not deemed to have 
attained his majority under the Indian Majority Act, <year>1875</year>; 
 (9 of <year>1875</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1793384</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1399290</tid>
<number>c</number>" savings certificate" means a savings certificate to 
which this Act applies;

</section>

<section><tid>1791554</tid>
<number>d</number>" transfer" means a transfer inter vivos, and does not 
include transfer by operation of law



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1034400</tid>
<number>3</number>Restrictions on transfer savings certificates. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no transfer 
of a savings certificate, whether made before or after the 
commencement of this Act, shall be valid unless it has been made 
with the previous consent in writing of the prescribed authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu (w. e. f.  
  1- 9- <year>1979</year>,) vide Notification No. S. O. 2734, see Gazette of India, 
Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p <year>1991</year>.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>. s. 2 and Sch.

This Act came into force in Pondicherry on 1- 10- <year>1963</year>: vide Reg. 7 
of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 1st August. <year>1960</year>: vide Notification No. G. S. R. 709. dated 25th 
June. <year>1960</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1960</year>, Pt. II Sec. 3 (i). p. 968.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For such notification see Notification No. G. S. R. 710, dated 
25th June, <year>1960</year>, p. 968, ibid.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>602021</tid>
<number> 4</number> Holdings by or on behalf of minors. Notwithstanding any 
provision in any law for the time being in force,-
<section><tid>1114109</tid>
<number>a</number>a minor may apply for and hold savings certificates and 
any other person may apply for and hold savings certificates 
on behalf of a minor;

</section>

<section><tid>1086521</tid>
<number>b</number>where any savings certificate is held by or on behalf 
of a minor, the minor shall, whether the savings certificate 
was applied for and issued before or after the commencement 
of this Act, be bound by the provisions of this Act and of 
any rules made thereunder applicable to such savings 
certificate and by the terms of any declaration made by the 
applicant for the savings certificate in pursuance of the 
said rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>324658</tid>
<number> 5</number> Payment where certificate is held by or on behalf of a minor. 
Payment of the sum for the time being due on a savings certificate 
held by or on behalf of a minor may be made
<section><tid>525917</tid>
<number>a</number>to him personally, if he himself applied for the 
savings certificate, or

</section>

<section><tid>1138049</tid>
<number>b</number>for the use of the minor, if the application for 
the savings certificate was made by any person other 
than the minor,-

<subsection><tid>1282941</tid>
<number>i</number>to any such person, being a parent of the minor or 
guardian of his property, as may be specified in that 
behalf in the form of application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>259091</tid>
<number>ii</number>if no such person has been specified, to any 
guardian of the property of the minor appointed by a 
competent court, or where no such guardian has been so 
appointed, to either parent of the minor, or where 
neither parent is alive, to any other guardian of the 
minor.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1253972</tid>
<number> 6</number> Nomination by holders of savings certificates.
<section><tid>1358064</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force, or in any disposition, testamentary or otherwise in respect of 
any savings certificate, where a nomination made in the prescribed 
manner purports to confer on any person the right to receive payment 
of the sum for the time being due on the savings certificate on the 
death of the holder thereof and before the maturity of the 
certificate, or before the certificate having reached maturity has 
been discharged, the nominee shall, on the death of the holder of the 
savings certificate, become entitled to the savings certificate and to 
be paid the sum due thereon to the exclusion of all others

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

persons, unless the nomination is varied or cancelled in the 
prescribed manner.


</section>

<section><tid>765108</tid>
<number>2</number>Any nomination referred to in sub- section (1) shall become 
void if the nominee predeceases, or where there are two or more 
nominees all the nominees predecease, the holder of the savings 
certificate making the nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>1366245</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the nominee is a minor, it shall be lawful for the 
holder of the savings certificate making the nomination to appoint in 
the prescribed manner any person to receive the sum due thereon in 
the event of his death during the minority of the nominee.

</section>

<section><tid>213283</tid>
<number>4</number>A transfer of a savings certificate made in the prescribed 
manner shall automatically cancel a nomination previously made:
Provided that where a savings certificate is held by or on behalf 
of any person as a pledgee or by way of security for any purpose, such 
holding shall not have the effect of cancelling a nomination but the 
right of the nominee shall be subject to the right of the person so 
holding it.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1040521</tid>
<number> 7</number> Payment on death of holder.
<section><tid>1855422</tid>
<number>1</number>If the holder of a savings  
certificate dies and there is in force at the time of his death a 
nomination in favour of any person, payment of the sum due thereon 
shall be made to the nominee.

</section>

<section><tid>790042</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the nominee is a minor, payment of the sum due thereon 
shall be made--

<subsection><tid>1414548</tid>
<number>a</number>in any case where a person has been appointed to 
receive it under sub- section (3) of section 6, to that 
person, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183389</tid>
<number>b</number>where there is no such person, to any guardian of the 
property of the minor appointed by a competent court, or 
where no such guardian has been so appointed, to either 
parent of the minor, or where neither parent is alive, to any 
other guardian of the minor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1473136</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the sum due on a savings certificate is payable to two 
or more nominees, and either or any of them dies, the sum shall be 
paid to the surviving nominee or nominees.

</section>

<section><tid>150904</tid>
<number>4</number>If a person dies and is at the time of his death the holder 
of a savings certificate and there is no nomination in force at the 
time of his death and probate of his will or letters of administration 
of his estate or a succession certificate granted under the Indian 
Succession Act, <year>1925</year>, (39 of <year>1925</year>.) is not within three months of the 
death of the holder produced to the prescribed authority, then, if the 
sum due on the savings certificate does not exceed[ such limit as may 
be prescribed the prescribed], authority may pay the same to any person 
appearing to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

it to be entitled to receive the sum or to administer the estate of 
the deceased.


</section>

<section><tid>956376</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to require 
any person to receive payment of the sum due on a savings certificate 
before it has reached maturity or otherwise than in accordance with 
the terms of the savings certificate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1963768</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment to be a full discharge.
<section><tid>1736745</tid>
<number>1</number>Any payment made in  
accordance with the foregoing provisions of this Act to a minor or to 
his parent or guardian or to a nominee or to any other person shall be 
a full discharge from all further liability in respect of the sum so 
paid.

</section>

<section><tid>337422</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to preclude any 
executor or administrator or other representative of a deceased holder 
of a savings certificate from recovering from the person receiving the 
same under section 7 the amount remaining in his hands after deducting 
the amount of all debts or other demands lawfully paid or discharged 
by him in due course of administration.

</section>

<section><tid>1177714</tid>
<number>3</number>Any creditor or claimant against the estate of a holder of a 
savings certificate may recover his debt or claim out of the sum paid 
under this Act to any person and remaining in his hands un- 
administered, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the 
latter had obtained letters of administration to the estate of the 
deceased.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>54665</tid>
<number>9</number>Security for due administration. The prescribed authority may 
take such security as it thinks necessary from any person to whom any 
money is paid under sub- section (4) of section 7 for the due 
administration of the money so paid and may assign the said security 
to any person interested in such administrations.


</article>



<article><tid>1133578</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to administer oath.
<section><tid>1164947</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of ascertaining  
the right of a person claiming to be entitled to payment under sub- 
section (4) of section 7, the prescribed authority may take evidence 
on oath or affirmation according to the law for the time being in 
force relating to oaths and affirmation.

</section>

<section><tid>108626</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who upon such oath or affirmation makes any 
statement which is false and which he either knows or believes to be 
false or does not believe to be true shall be deemed guilty of an 
offence under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>72573</tid>
<number>11</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against any officer of the Government or 
any prescribed authority in respect of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1816793</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>492795</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1518476</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>552004</tid>
<number>a</number>the form of application for savings certificates and 
the issue and discharge of such certificates; 
 (b) the maximum limits of holdings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>451534</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions as to payment of interest or discount 
relating to any class of savings certificates and the 
recovery of any interest paid on any amount held in excess of 
the maximum limits in the same manner as an arrear of land 
revenue or in any, other manner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274769</tid>
<number>d</number>the transfer and conversion of savings certificates and 
the fees to be levied in respect thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1720878</tid>
<number>e</number>the replacement of savings certificates mutilated, lost 
or destroyed and the fees payable in respect thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>293985</tid>
<number>f</number>the form of nominations, the manner in which and the 
conditions subject to which nominations may be made and the 
registration of nominations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1698010</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the 
purposes of sub- section (3) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1665869</tid>
<number>h</number>the variation or cancellation of nominations and the 
registration of such variations or cancellations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>184323</tid>
<number>i</number>the fees that may be levied for registration, variation 
or cancellation of nominations

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>32433</tid>
<number>ia</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the limit under sub- section (4) of section 7;"]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373362</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1980013</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid"] both- Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Post Office Savings Certificates Rules, <year>1960</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1960</year> Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i) pp. 968- 983.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 56 of <year>1985</year>, S. 3.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1995509</tid>
<number> 13</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1600235</tid>
<number>1</number>The Post Office National Savings  
Certificates Ordinance, <year>1944</year> (42 of <year>1944</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1891130</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance, any rules 
made or deemed to have been made or anything done or any action, taken 
in exercise of any of the powers conferred by or under the said 
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, done or taken in exercise 
of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act were in 
force on the day on which such rules were made, such thing was done or 
such action was taken.


</section>

</article>



 </act>