<act><tid>1834260</tid>
<title>THE CONSTITUTION (SCHEDULED CASTES AND SCHEDULED TRIBES) 
ORDERS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 32 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 3rd June, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 
 <year>1950</year> and the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year> so as to 
provide for inclusion of certain Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes 
oustees of the States of Madhya Pradesh and Mahara htra, who have been 
displaced due to Sardar Sarovar Project on the Narmada River and are 
settled or may be settled in the State of Gujarat, in the lists of 
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes specified in relation to the 
State of Gujarat.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>472192</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Castes and Scheduled Tribes) Orders (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1077558</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>.- In 
the Schedule to the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, in
PART IV.- Gujarat, after entry 30, the following entries shall be 
inserted, namely:-

" 31. Balahi, Balai

</article>



<article><tid>628183</tid>
<number>32</number>Bhangi, Mehtar
</article>



<article><tid>1537294</tid>
<number>33</number>Chamar
</article>



<article><tid>1412176</tid>
<number>34</number>Chikwa, Chikvi
</article>



<article><tid>1102011</tid>
<number>35</number>Koli, Kori
</article>



<article><tid>1640866</tid>
<number>36</number>Kotwal (in Bhind, Dhar, Dewas, Guna, Gwalior, Indore, Jhabua,  
Khargone, Mandsaur, Morena, Rajgarh, Ratlam, Shajapur, Shivpuri, 
  Ujjain and Vidisha districts).".


</article>



<article><tid>832659</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>.- In 
the Schedule to the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, in
PART IV.- Gujarat, after entry 29, the following entries shall be 
inserted, namely:-

" 30. Bhil, Bhilala, Barela, Patelia

</article>



<article><tid>836867</tid>
<number>31</number>Tadvi Bhil, Bawra, Vasave
</article>



<article><tid>628183</tid>
<number>32</number>Padvi.".
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>