<act><tid>1484266</tid>
<title>THE PASSPORTS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 28th March, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Passports Act, <year>1967</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1378870</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>661926</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Passports (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>932800</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 23rd day of 
October, <year>2001</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>437621</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new sections 10A and 10B.- After section 10 of the 
Passports Act, <year>1967</year> (15 of <year>1967</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act) the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
' 10A. Suspension of passports or travel documents in certain 
cases.- (1) Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in section 10, if the Central Government or any designated 
officer is satisfied that the passport or travel document is likely to 
be impounded or caused to be impounded or revoked under clause (c) of 
sub- section (3) of section 10 and it is necessary in the public 
interest so to do, it or he may,-

<section><tid>1934889</tid>
<number>a</number>by order, suspend, with immediate effect, any passport or travel 
document;

</section>

<section><tid>1549524</tid>
<number>b</number>pass such other appropriate order which may have the effect of 
rendering any passport or travel document invalid,
for a period not exceeding four weeks:

Provided that the Central Government or the designated officer may, if 
it or he considers appropriate, extend, by order and for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, the said period of four weeks till the 
passport or travel document under section 10 are concluded: 
proceedings relating to variation, impounding or re vocation of

Provided further that every holder of the passport or travel document, 
in respect of whom an order under clause (a) or clause (b) of this 
sub- section had been passed, shall be given an opportunity of being 
heard within a period of not later than eight we eks reckoned from the 
date of passing of such order and thereupon the Central Government 
may, if necessary, by order in writing, modify or revoke the order 
passed under this sub- section.


<subsection><tid>1843828</tid>
<number>2</number>The designated officer shall immediately communicate the orders 
passed under sub- section (1), to the concerned authority at an airport 
or any other point of embarkation or immigration, and to the passport 
authority.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158822</tid>
<number>3</number>Every authority referred to in sub- section (2) shall, immediately 
on receipt of the order passed under sub- section (1), give effect to 
such order.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1235816</tid>
<number> 10B</number> Validation of intimations.- Every intimation, given by the 
Central Government or the designated officer, before the commencement 
of the Passports (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, to any immigration authority 
at an airport or any other point of embarkation or mmigration, 
. restricting or in any manner prohibiting the departure from India of 
any holder of the passport or travel document under sub- section (3) of 
section 10, shall be deemed to be an order under sub- section
<section><tid>1556976</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 10A and such order sha l continue to be in force for a period 
of three months form the date of commencement of the Passports 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> or the date on giving such intimation, whichever 
is later.
Explanation.- For the purposes of sections 10A and 10B, the expression 
" designated officer" means such officer or authority designated, by 
order in writing, as such by the Central Government.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>213985</tid>
<number> 3</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>5157</tid>
<number>1</number>The Passports (Amendment) Second  
Ordinance, <year>2001</year> (Ord. 11 of <year>2001</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1834246</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the principal Act, as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended 
by this Act.
K. N. CHATURVEDI, 
Addl. Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>