<act><title>


The Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights Rules, 20031</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights 
Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date on which the Act shall come into force.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights Act, 2001 (53 of 2001);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Authority” 
means the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers’ Rights Authority 
established under sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “Chairperson” 
means the Chairperson of the Authority appointed under clause (a) of sub-section 
(5) of section 3;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “fee” means 
the fee specified in the Second Schedule;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “Form” means 
a Form specified in the First Schedule;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “Gazette” 
means the Official Gazette of the Government of India;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  “journal” 
means the monthly journal of the Authority;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  “non-official 
member” means a member of the Authority other than a member, ex officio;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  “notice” 
means a notice issued by the Tribunal or the Registrar or the Authority under 
the Act;
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  “Registrar” 
means a Registrar of Plant Varieties appointed under sub-section (4) of section 
12 and includes the Registrar General of Plant Varieties appointed under 
sub-section (3) of that section;
 </section><section>
        <number>k</number>  “Schedule” 
means a Schedule annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>l</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  
“representation” means any written communication addressed to the Authority or 
the Registrar in any proceeding under the Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>n</number>  all other 
words and expressions used, but not defined in these rules, but defined in the 
Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>3</number> Details of 
particulars to be furnished while making an application or representation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save in case of forms specified by the Authority under the Act, every person 
making an application or representation under the Act or these rules, shall 
furnish the particulars in the Forms specified in the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any application or 
representation has been filed without furnishing all the particulars as 
specified in the relevant Forms specified in the First Schedule, the Authority 
or the Registrar, as the case may be, shall give one month’s notice to the 
applicant or the person, who has filed the application or the representation to 
file such particulars.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event the 
applicant or the person, who has filed the application or the representation, 
defaults or fails to rectify the application or the representation, as the case 
may be, in terms of the notice under sub-rule (2) within one month as allowed, 
the said application or the representation shall be liable to be rejected 
without any further notice.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where no Form in 
specified for any purpose, the applicant may adopt as nearly as may be a Form 
specified in the First Schedule with such modifications and variations as may be 
considered necessary.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Office of the 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The office of the Authority shall, for all proceedings under the Act, be the 
head office of the Authority at New Delhi or the branch office, as the case may 
be, within whose territorial limits—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the applicant 
for registration of the plant variety or the farmers’ right has his principal 
place of business or domicile; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the applicant 
for registration of the plant variety or the farmers’ right, whose name is first 
mentioned in the application, resides or has his principal place of business or 
domicile, if the application is made jointly in the names of two or more 
persons; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the agent or 
licensee of the registered breeder has his principal place of business or 
domicile.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), until the branch offices are established, 
the appropriate office for all proceedings under the Act shall be the head 
office of the Authority at New Delhi.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Address for service 
of notices, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person including the applicant, concerned in any proceeding to which the 
Act or these rules apply, shall furnish to the Authority or the Registrar the 
complete address for service in India and that address shall be treated for all 
purposes connected with such proceedings or the rights granted, as the address 
of the person or persons in the proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Unless such an address 
is given, the Authority or the Registrar shall be under no obligation either to 
proceed or deal with any proceeding or to send any notice that may be required 
to be given under the Act of these rules.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Procedure regarding 
application, representation and issue of notices.— 

<section><number>1</number> Every application or representation shall be made in writing, signed by the 
applicant or the person who has made the representation, and delivered to the 
Registrar or the Authority at its office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names and 
addresses of the applicants and other persons shall be given in full, together 
with their nationality and such other particulars, as are necessary for their 
identification and for sending communications to them.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) All applications, 
representations and documents filed or required to be filed under the Act or the 
rules shall be filed in triplicate:
 
Provided that in cases 
where the Registrar or the Authority requires more than three copies of such 
applications, representations, or documents, the applicant or the person, who 
has filed the application or the representation, shall be required to supply as 
many copies as is specified by the Authority or the Registrar.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case of failure to 
furnish the required number of copies within a period of three months, the 
Registrar or the Authority may reject the application or the representation or 
may treat the application or representation as withdrawn.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Any application, 
representation or document required to be sent to or filed with the office of 
the Authority or the Registrar may be delivered either by hand or by registered 
letter with acknowledgement due or electronic mail, addressed to the Authority 
or to the Registrar at their office.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any application or 
a representation or document is delivered to the Authority or the Registrar by 
hand, an acknowledgement receipt shall be issued by the Authority or the 
Registrar’s office with its seal.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In case of delivery by 
registered post with acknowledgement due or by electronic mail, it shall be 
presumed to have been filed, or given at the time when the same has been 
received by the office concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any written 
communication addressed to an applicant or the holder of any right under the 
Act, at his address in the Register of Plant Varieties maintained under the Act 
or at the address for service furnished under rule 5 in any proceedings under 
the Act or these rules, at the address appearing on the application or notice of 
opposition or reply or counter reply or any such representation, shall be 
presumed to be properly addressed:
 
Provided that in cases 
where the receipt of such a representation or application has been delayed 
beyond the normal period of delivery or transmission, such a delay may be 
condemned.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> All notices and 
written communications addressed to an applicant or to any holder of right, in 
any proceeding under the Act or these rules, and all documents forwarded to the 
applicant or the holder of any right or an opponent shall, except when they are 
sent by special messenger, be sent by registered post acknowledgement due or by 
electronic mail.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> (a) The 
acknowledgement receipt issued by the office concerned or the postal certificate 
receipt shall be the sufficient proof as to the delivery or sending of any 
document under the Act or these rules.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case of 
transmission by electronic mail, the electronic receipt with the recognised 
digital signature, by the applicant or the person, who has made the 
representation, shall be the proof of the receipt.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Application not to 
be admitted in certain cases.—No 
application or representation shall be made to the authority or registrar 
covering the subject-matter already included in an earlier application made by 
the same person, and such subsequent application shall not be admitted by the 
registrar or the authority, as the case may be.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The amount of fees payable in respect of the registration of plant varieties and 
grant of any right under the Act or any application or notice of opposition or 
reply or counter reply required to be filed under the Act and other matters 
shall be as per the rates specified in the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The fees payable 
may either be paid in cash or may be sent by money order or postal order or bank 
draft or cheque payable to the Authority or the Registrar, as the case may be, 
at their respective offices, drawn on a scheduled bank at the place where the 
office is situated.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of these rules, “scheduled bank” means a bank included in the 
Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934).
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any cheque or draft 
(not including the fees in cash) on which the value specified therein cannot be 
collected in cash within the time allowed for the payment of the fees, shall be 
accepted at the discretion of the Registrar.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The stamps shall not 
be received in the payment of any fees payable under these rules.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> Where a fee is payable 
in respect of the filing of a document or application or representation, the 
date on which the entire fee is paid shall be the date of filing of the document 
or the representation.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any test is 
required to be conducted under any of these rules, the applicant or the 
concerned person shall be required to pay the requisite fee specified in the 
Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any application or 
representation or document shall be liable to be rejected on account of 
non-payment of fees and no test shall be conducted unless and until the parties 
interested deposit the required amount of fees as specified in the Second 
Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Size, etc., of 
documents.—All 
documents and copies of documents, except affidavits and drawings, sent to or 
left at the office of the Authority or otherwise furnished to the Registrar 
shall be written, typewritten, lithographed, or printed (either in the Hindi or 
in the English language unless otherwise directed or allowed by the Authority or 
the Registrar-General) in large and legible characters with deep indelible ink 
with lines widely spaced upon one side only of strong white paper of a size of 
approximately 33.00 centimetres by 20.50 centimetres (13 inches by 8 inches) or 
29.7 centimetres by 21 centimetres (11 

3/4 inches 
by 8 

1/4 inches) 
with a margin of at least four centimetres (one and a half inches) on the 
left-hand part thereof.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Affidavits.—The 
affidavits required to be filed under these rules shall be dated and signed at 
the foot and shall contain a statement that the facts and matters stated therein 
are true to the best of the knowledge, information and belief of the person 
making the affidavit.
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>11</number> Manner of Selection 
and Appointment of the Chairperson.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson shall be appointed by the Central Government on the basis of a 
panel of names recommended by a Search Committee consisting of the following, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  An eminent 
scientist or an expert, having special – Chairman; knowledge and Professional 
experience in respect of the law relating to protection of plant varieties and 
plant varietal research or plant breeding, to be nominated by the Central 
Government in the Ministry of Agriculture          
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Secretary to 
the Government of India, Department – Member; of Agriculture and Cooperation
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  Secretary 
to the Government of India, Department – Member; of Agriculture Research and 
Education
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Secretary to 
the Government of India, Department – Member.] of Biotechnology
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Department of 
Agriculture and Cooperation of the Central Government shall act as the nodal 
department for the selection and appointment of the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson shall 
be of the rank of the Secretary to the Government of India and the appointment 
as Chairperson shall either be on deputation or on contract basis.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the Selection 
Committee constituted under sub-rule (1), recommends any person who is not a 
government servant but fulfils qualifications given in clause (a) of sub-section 
(5) of section 3, such appointment may be made on contract basis.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Term of Office of 
the Chairperson.—The 
Chairperson shall hold office for a term of five years or up to the age of 
sixty-five years, whichever is earlier, and shall be eligible for 
re-appointment:
 
Provided that no 
Chairperson shall hold office for a total period exceeding ten years, or after 
he has attained the age of sixty-five years, whichever is earlier.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Salary, allowances, 
conditions of service, leave, pension, provident fund, etc., of the Chairperson.—The 
Chairperson shall be entitled to such salary, allowances, leave, pension, 
provident fund and other perquisites as are admissible to a Secretary to the 
Government of India.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Resignation or 
removal of the Chairperson from office in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson may resign from his office by giving notice in writing to the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall remove the Chairperson from office if he,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  is or at any 
time has been, adjudicated as an insolvent;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  has been 
convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
involves moral turpitude;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  has become 
physically or mentally incapable of acting as the Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  has failed in 
discharging the duties and responsibilities under the Act and the rules made 
thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  has acquired 
such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
function as the Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  has, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, so abused his position as to render his 
continuation in office detrimental to the public interest;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  any other 
substantiated ground which is unbecoming of a public servant under the 
Government of India:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson shall not be removed under this sub-rule unless he has been given a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Term and allowances 
of non-official members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every non-official member of the Authority shall hold office for a period of 
three years from the date of his appointment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall appoint new non-official member of the Authority within six months of the 
expiration of the term of the non-official member.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A non-official member 
shall be entitled to sitting allowance and travelling expenses, at such rate as 
may be fixed by the Central Government from time to time in this regard.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Proceedings of the 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall meet at least twice in a year at the head quarters of the 
Authority or at such place as may be decided by the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall, 
upon a written request of not less than five members of the Authority or upon a 
direction of the Central Government, call a special meeting of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At least fifteen days’ 
notice of an ordinary meeting and three days’ notice of a special meeting 
specifying the purpose, the time and the place at which such meeting is to be 
held, shall be given to the members.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every meeting shall be 
presided over by the Chairperson and in his absence, by a Presiding Officer to 
be chosen by the members present from amongst themselves.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The decision of the 
Authority shall be taken by a majority of the votes of the members present and 
voting and in the event of equality of votes, the Chairperson or in his absence, 
the member presiding over the meeting shall have a second or casting vote.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every member shall 
have one vote.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The quorum for the 
meeting of the Authority shall be five.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> No member shall be 
entitled to bring forward for the consideration of a meeting any matter of which 
he has not given ten days’ notice to the Member-Secretary unless the 
Chairperson, in his discretion, permits him to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The notice of the 
meeting may be given to the members by delivering the same by messenger or 
sending it by registered post to his last known place of residence or business 
or in such other manner as the Chairperson or the Member-Secretary may, in the 
circumstances of the case, think fit.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Chairman and 
proceedings of the Standing Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson shall select a member of the Standing Committee appointed by him 
under sub-section (7) of section 3 from amongst the members of that Committee to 
preside over its meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the absence of the 
member selected under sub-rule (1), the meeting of the Standing Committee shall 
be presided over by the member who shall be elected by the members present at 
meeting from amongst themselves.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The decision in the 
meeting of the Standing Committee shall be taken by a majority of the members 
present and voting and in the event of equality of votes, the member selected 
under sub-rule (1) or in his absence, the member presiding over the meeting 
shall have a second or casting vote.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every member shall 
have one vote.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The quorum for the 
meeting of the Standing Committee shall be three.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The convener of the 
Standing Committee may, in consultation with the Authority, determine the venue 
of its meetings any where in India; and serve notice of such meeting to all 
members at least fifteen days in advance.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appointment of 
Expert Committee by the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority may appoint such experts or consultants as it considers necessary 
to seek guidance and assistance in technical areas demanding specialised 
advisory inputs, to enable the Authority for efficient discharge of its duties 
and functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority may 
appoint such other committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of 
its duties and functions.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority may, in 
consultation with the Central Government, fix the quantum of remuneration, 
payable to the experts and consultants.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Salary, allowances 
and conditions of service of the Registrar-General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar-General shall be an official equivalent to the rank of the 
Additional Secretary to the Government of India and he shall be appointed by the 
Authority on deputation or transfer or on contract basis.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar-General 
shall be governed by the Central Government rules in respect of his salary and 
other allowances including pension, leave, travelling and daily allowances as 
are admissible to an Additional Secretary to the Government of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar-General 
shall be a person having proven managerial, or legal or Intellectual Property 
Rights or agricultural development experience.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The term of office of 
the Registrar-General shall be for a period of five years or until he attains 
the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier:
 
Provided that no candidate 
who may not have at least two years tenure in the office shall be appointed as 
Registrar-General.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A person on completion 
of one term as Registrar-General shall be eligible for a second term of three 
years or until he attains the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> The method of 
appointment of officers and other employees of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority may make recruitment and appointment to the posts of officers 
specified in the Fourth Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority shall 
after advertising the posts in the Employment News and at least one national 
daily recruit officers and other employees of the Authority by the method of 
direct recruitment or contract basis by selection after conducting interview.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1) and subject to the approval of the Central 
Government the Authority may also appoint such other officers and employees as 
may be required by it on transfer or deputation basis or on contract basis.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The salary, allowances 
and other conditions of service of the officers and employees of the Authority 
shall be the same as applicable to Central Government servants of equivalent 
rank.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any question on the 
service conditions of any officer or employee of the Authority arises, it shall 
be decided by the Central Government.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Powers and duties 
of the Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In addition to the duties specified in the Act, the Chairperson shall have 
powers of general superintendence and directions in the conduct and management 
of the affairs of the Authority, to enable the Authority in effectively 
discharging its duties and overseeing the compliance of the provisions of the 
Act, and the rules and regulations made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall 
also discharge such other duties and functions as the Authority may by general 
or special order in writing delegate to him or the Central Government may 
authorise him to discharge from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson shall 
convene, preside over and conduct the meetings of the Authority and be 
responsible for carrying out all decisions taken by the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson shall 
guide and facilitate the development of new plant varieties by protecting the 
rights of the breeders, researchers, farmers, and community of farmers as 
provided under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chairperson shall 
facilitate and act on his satisfaction for compulsory licensing of registered 
plant varieties and advice the Central and the State Governments on the 
restriction of public use of any such registered plant varieties which may 
invite action under sub-rule (4).
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> General functions 
of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall advice the Central Government in relation to the provisions 
contained in the sub-section (2) of section 29 for specifying and notifying the 
general and species for the purposes of registration of new plant varieties 
other than extant varieties and farmers’ varieties.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority shall 
register extant varieties under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 8 
within such period as may be determined by it with suitable test criteria to 
conform distinctiveness, uniformity and stability (hereinafter referred to as 
DUS) of such varieties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority shall 
develop DUS test and other test criteria and conduct such tests for 
characterisation of each variety of crop species notified by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority shall 
compile and maintain a database on all varieties of common knowledge including 
all registered extant and farmers’ varieties and such varieties being cultivated 
outside India for each crop species prior to grant for registration for new 
varieties belonging to such species.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Authority shall be 
entitled to call for and procure the details of any crop variety under use in 
the country for the purpose of bringing the same into its database.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any public or private 
institution, community or individual involved in the production and use of seed 
of such varieties shall be required to provide full information on its 
characteristics or and a true sample of seed of such variety.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Authority shall 
keep a record of the production and sale of seed of all registered varieties.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> It shall be necessary 
for all breeders of registered varieties to supply certified figures on annual 
seed production and sales to the Authority within a period not exceeding three 
months from the completion of such reporting period.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Authority, if 
required shall also be entitled to call for such figures specifically relating 
to any region of the country.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Matters to be 
included in the National Register of Plant Varieties.—The 
National Register of Plant Varieties shall contain the following particulars of 
each registered variety, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>1</number>  Registration 
Number;
 </section><section>
        <number>2</number>  Nationality 
of Breeder(s);
 </section><section>
        <number>3</number>  Denomination 
as granted;
 </section><section>
        <number>4</number>  Date of Grant 
of Registration;
 </section><section>
        <number>5</number>  Date on which 
application was received;
 </section><section>
        <number>6</number>  Provisional 
number given to the application;
 </section><section>
        <number>7</number>  Date of 
Gazette notification;
 </section><section>
        <number>8</number>  Grouping of 
the plant variety (new, extant or farmers);
 </section><section>
        <number>9</number>  
Classification of the variety (typical variety, hybrid variety or essentially 
derived variety);
 </section><section>
      <number>10</number>  Denomination 
of variety, Common Crop name to which the variety belongs, Taxonomical Lineage 
of the Crop in Botanical names;
 </section><section>
      <number>11</number>  Key Passport 
data of the variety;
 </section><section>
      <number>12</number>  Essential 
characters making the variety distinct;
 </section><section>
      <number>13</number>  Starting date 
of protection;
 </section><section>
      <number>14</number>  Expiry date of 
protection;
 </section><section>
      <number>15</number>  Date of 
revocation with other details (grounds, etc.);
 </section><section>
      <number>16</number>  Name and 
address of the applicant(s);
 </section><section>
      <number>17</number>  Address for 
service of document(s);
 </section><section>
      <number>18</number>  Name and 
address of the breeder(s) (in case breeder is not the applicant);
 </section><section>
      <number>19</number>  Name and 
address of the legal representative (if applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>20</number>  Name, address 
and other details of the licensee and terms of license (if applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>21</number>  Name, address 
and other details of the agent with jurisdictional rights, if any (if 
appointed);
 </section><section>
      <number>22</number>  Type of crop;
 </section><section>
      <number>23</number>  Name of the 
family, genus, species, variety and common name;
 </section><section>
      <number>24</number>  Name and 
address of the breeder of initial variety (in case of essentially derived 
variety);
 </section><section>
      <number>25</number>  Details of the 
acquisition of propagating material/seeds (if applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>26</number>  Details of 
parental material used in the development (if applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>27</number>  Name and 
address of the contributor(s) of generic material (if applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>28</number>  Any other 
feature specified by the Authority or Registrar-General;
 </section><section>
      <number>29</number>  Country of 
origin of the plant variety;
 </section><section>
      <number>30</number>  Brief 
description of the variety along with characteristic details of the nearest 
variety including results of DUS testing, supplemented with the drawings or 
photographs or both;
 </section><section>
      <number>31</number>  In case of 
compulsory licensing, name and address of licensee with other details (terms and 
conditions, revocation, etc.), if applicable.
 </section><section>
      <number>32</number>  Declaration 
and details of the renunciation to the variety (if applicable).
 </section><section>
      <number>33</number>  Details of 
benefit sharing;
 </section><section>
      <number>34</number>  Details of 
opposition, revocation, restoration, maintenance (whatever applicable);
 </section><section>
      <number>35</number>  In the case of 
varieties protected outside India prior to registration in the country, 
following additional information shall be entered in the National Register of 
plant varieties namely:—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  Name of 
the country(ies) where protection is made along with the denomination of the 
variety in each of them,
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  Date of 
first protection with country,
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>c</number>  
Variation in important trait with respect to first filing,
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>d</number>  Country 
wherein the Variety was first commercialised with date,
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>e</number>  Any 
other feature specified by the Authority or Registrar-General.
 </subsection></section><section>
      <number>36</number>  In case of a 
convention application, the following information shall also be furnished, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number>  Name of 
the convention country;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number>  Passport 
data of the convention application;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>c</number>  Date of 
application;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>d</number>  Date of 
grant of registration;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>e</number>  
Registration number;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>f</number>  
Denomination as accepted;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>g</number>  Date of 
Gazette notification;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>h</number>  Starting 
date of protection;
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>i</number>  Expiry 
date of protection;
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>j</number>  Whether 
the variety has been sold or otherwise disposed of within and outside the 
country, if so, details thereof.
 </subsection></section><section>
      <number>37</number>  Any changes 
made in any entry.
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>24</number> Registration of 
extant plant varieties under sub-section (2) of section 15.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall register every extant variety within three years from the 
date of its notification under the Act, with respect to the genera and species 
eligible for registration subject to conformity to the criteria of 
distinctiveness, uniformity, and stability as laid down under the regulations:
 
Provided that the 
Registrar may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, register an extant variety 
after the expiry of the said period of three years.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Application to 
authorise a person to register a variety under clause (e) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 16.—An 
application to authorise a person to register a variety under clause (e) of 
sub-section (1) of section 16 shall be made in Form PV-1, given in the First 
Schedule, by a person specified in sub-section (1) of that section.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> The fee payable 
under clause (g) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 18 for making application for 
registration of plant variety.—The 
fee for making application for registration of a plant variety under section 14 
shall be such as specified in column (3) of the Second Schedule for the purpose.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Proof of the right 
of making application under sub-section (3) of section 18.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an application for registration is made by the successor or assignee of 
the breeder under sub-section (3) of section 18, he shall furnish documentary 
proof, at the time of making such application or within six months of making 
such an application, as to the right to make such an application for 
registration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The documentary proof, 
in case of an assignment, shall be furnished in the manner specified in Form 
PV-2, given in the First Schedule and in case of succession, or a succession 
certificate or any other document in support of succession proving the applicant 
to be the successor shall be furnished.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Fee for conducting 
tests under section 19.—The 
applicant shall deposit the requisite fee for the purpose as specified in column 
(3) of the Second Schedule, with the Registrar for conducting the required tests 
under section 19.
 
 
</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title>
 <article><title> </title><title><number>29</number> Manner and method for conducting tests under section 19. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The Authority shall charge separate fees for conducting DUS test and special test on each variety. 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The special tests shall be conducted only when DUS testing fails to establish the requirement of distinctiveness. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> The DUS testing shall be field and multi-location based for at least two similar crop seasons and special tests will be laboratory based:
 Provided that in the case of trees and vines there shall be an option on the manner of the DUS testing that a panel of three experts shall visit the On-farm test sites for two similar crop seasons as may be specified.] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The fee for DUS and special tests shall be such as provided in column (3) of the Second Schedule for the purpose. 
</subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If the Registrar, after initial scrutiny of the application for registration, is satisfied that the application is in order, he shall notify the applicant to deposit the requisite fee, as specified in column (3) of the Second Schedule, within a period of two months for conducting the DUS test. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of the fee, demanded under sub-rule (1), the Registrar shall consider the application for further processing. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The DUS test shall be necessary for all new varieties except essentially derived variety. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The manner of testing essentially derived varieties shall be decided by the Authority on a case-to-case basis. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The DUS test shall be conducted on a minimum of two locations. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Authority may recognise and empanel institutions having adequate facilities for conducting DUS or special tests in the country for conducting such tests. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Authority shall notify the adopted methods of conducting the DUS and special tests. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Authority shall develop and publish in its journal guidelines for the DUS test for each crop. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The samples of seeds or propagules in respect of which an application for registration has been made and parental lines under registration submitted for the DUS and special tests and deposited at the National Gene Bank shall present the maintainable standards of generic purity, and uniformity and germination, sanitary and phytosanitary standards. <title> </title>


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 843(E), dated 30-12-2004. G.S.R. 783(E), dated 27-10-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 731(E), dated 14-10-2008. G.S.R. 901(E), dated 17-12-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 319(E), dated 11-5-2009. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title>
 <article><title> </title><title><number>29</number> Manner and method for conducting tests under section 19. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The Authority shall charge separate fees for conducting DUS test and special test on each variety. 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The special tests shall be conducted only when DUS testing fails to establish the requirement of distinctiveness. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> The DUS testing shall be field and multi-location based for at least two similar crop seasons and special tests will be laboratory based:
 Provided that in the case of trees and vines there shall be an option on the manner of the DUS testing that a panel of three experts shall visit the On-farm test sites for two similar crop seasons as may be specified.] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The fee for DUS and special tests shall be such as provided in column (3) of the Second Schedule for the purpose. 
</subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If the Registrar, after initial scrutiny of the application for registration, is satisfied that the application is in order, he shall notify the applicant to deposit the requisite fee, as specified in column (3) of the Second Schedule, within a period of two months for conducting the DUS test. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of the fee, demanded under sub-rule (1), the Registrar shall consider the application for further processing. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The DUS test shall be necessary for all new varieties except essentially derived variety. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The manner of testing essentially derived varieties shall be decided by the Authority on a case-to-case basis. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The DUS test shall be conducted on a minimum of two locations. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Authority may recognise and empanel institutions having adequate facilities for conducting DUS or special tests in the country for conducting such tests. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Authority shall notify the adopted methods of conducting the DUS and special tests. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Authority shall develop and publish in its journal guidelines for the DUS test for each crop. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The samples of seeds or propagules in respect of which an application for registration has been made and parental lines under registration submitted for the DUS and special tests and deposited at the National Gene Bank shall present the maintainable standards of generic purity, and uniformity and germination, sanitary and phytosanitary standards. <title> </title>


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 843(E), dated 30-12-2004. G.S.R. 783(E), dated 27-10-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 731(E), dated 14-10-2008. G.S.R. 901(E), dated 17-12-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 319(E), dated 11-5-2009. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Advertising of 
application for registration under section 21.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for registration of a variety which has been accepted and the 
details thereof including specifications shall, upon such acceptance under 
sub-section (1) of section 20, be advertised by the Registrar in the manner 
specified in Form 01 of the Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In every such 
advertisement under sub-rule (1), the Registrar shall mention that place or 
places where a specimen of the variety may be inspected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The contents of such 
advertisement shall include—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  name, 
passport data and source of parental line or initial variety used to develop the 
variety in respect of which an application for registration has been made;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  description 
of the variety bringing out its character profile as specified under the DUS 
test Schedule;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  essential 
characteristics conferring distinctiveness to the variety;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  important 
agronomic and commercial attributes of the variety;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  photographs 
or drawings, if any, of the variety submitted by the applicant; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  claim, if 
any, on the variety.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Notice of 
opposition under sub-section (2) of section 21.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any interested person, may within three months from the date of advertisement of 
an application for registration, may give a notice of opposition to the 
registration of a plant variety in Form PV-3 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee payable for 
filing an opposition referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be as specified in column 
(3) of the Second Schedule:
 
Provided that no such fee 
shall be payable in respect of an opposition made by a farmer or group of 
farmers, or village community.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy each of the 
notice of opposition received against a specific application shall be referred 
to the applicant by the Registrar within three months from the last date of 
filing of opposition.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An applicant shall be 
entitled to submit point-wise counter statement to the opposition not later than 
two months from the date of service of the copy of the notice of opposition, 
failing which the Registrar shall decide the merits of the opposition and notify 
his decision by giving reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every 
counter-statement under sub-rule (4) shall be in Form PV-4 of the First 
Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The copies of counter 
to opposition submitted by the applicant within the time specified in sub-rule 
(4), shall be conveyed to the person opposing the application, within a period 
of thirty days of its receipt, requiring the opposing person to submit the final 
opposition within a period of thirty days from the date of service of the 
counter from the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Registrar, may at 
his discretion, allow any correction of error or amendments in the notice of 
opposition or counter statement if such alteration is requested by the persons 
concerned in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> (a) The security 
referred to in sub-section (8) of section 21 shall be payable as an amount 
decided by the Authority.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case the opposition 
is found to be frivolous, the Registrar may direct payment of cost as determined 
by him to the applicant from out of the security amount received and the balance 
of the security amount shall be deposited in the Authority.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> In case the opposition 
succeeds, the security amount shall be refunded to the opposition party.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Compliance with 
time schedule.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The time schedule provided for advertisement, opposition, defence, hearing and 
amendment of specification under these rules shall not be extended and failure 
in compliance with these time schedules shall forfeit the opportunity granted.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Manner of 
submitting evidence and time limit for filing notice of opposition, 
counter-statement or producing evidences under section 21.— 

<section><number>1</number> Any evidence, upon which the opponent may rely, shall be submitted in 
duplicate to the Registrar with a copy to the applicant within one month from 
the receipt of counter-statement of the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any evidence upon 
which the applicant may rely shall be submitted in duplicate to the Registrar 
with a copy to the opponent within thirty days from the date of receipt of 
opponent’s evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No further evidence 
shall be submitted by either party except by leave or directions of the 
Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The copies of all the 
documents, except plant variety application, referred to in the notice of 
opposition or in any counter-statement filed in connection with the opposition 
shall be in triplicate unless the Registrar directs otherwise.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a document, is 
in a language other than English, and is referred to or relied upon in the 
notice, statement or evidence, an attested translation in English thereof shall 
be furnished in triplicate.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The time-limit for 
filing the evidence shall not ordinarily be extended except by a special order 
of the Registrar given on an application filed by the person seeking extension 
of time and on payment of the fee specified in the Second Schedule and such an 
application for extension shall be in Form PV-5 of the First Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Application for the 
registration of essentially derived variety under section 23.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The application for registration of an essentially derived variety shall be 
accompanied by the following documents, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  an affidavit 
sworn by the applicant stating that such a variety does not contain any gene or 
gene sequence involving terminator technology;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  a statement 
giving details of the brief description of the characteristics of the variety to 
substantiate novelty, distinctiveness, uniformity and stability; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the details 
of parental material used.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The application under 
sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by the fee as specified for the purpose in 
column (3) of the Second Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Manner and method 
for conducting test under section 23.—The 
tests referred to in sub-section (3) of section 23 shall be conducted by the 
Authority in consultation with the Central Government.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Certificate of 
registration under section 23.—The 
Registrar shall issue to the applicant a certificate of registration of an 
essentially derived variety in the manner specified in Form O-2 of the Third 
Schedule and send a copy of the registration to the Authority and to such other 
body(ies) as may be notified by the Central Government for information.
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>37</number> Certificate of 
registration under section 24.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The certificate of registration of a plant variety, other than an essentially 
derived variety, under sub-section (2) of section 24 shall be in Form O-2 of the 
Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall 
issue the certificate of registration under sub-section (2) of section 24 within 
three years of the date of filing of application subject to the fulfilment of 
all other requirements.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the 
certificate of registration issued under sub-section (2) of section 24 shall be 
sent to the Authority; and to such other body or agency, which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette specify.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Notice to the 
applicant under section 24.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, within a period of twelve months, the application for registration of a 
plant variety other than an essentially derived variety is not completed in the 
circumstances given in sub-section (3) of section 24, the Registrar shall issue 
thirty days notice to the applicant at the address of his principal place of 
business in India, or if, he has no principal place of business in India, at the 
address for service in India stated in the application, but if the applicant has 
authorised an agent for the purpose of the application, the notice shall be sent 
to the agent and a duplicate thereof to the applicant for filing of the 
application or such further time as the Registrar may allow for completion of 
registration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice under 
sub-rule (1) shall be in Form O-3 of the Third Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Renewal and 
revision of registration under section 24.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> On receipt of an application from the applicant, the Authority may review 
and renew the initial duration of registration as mentioned in sub-section (6) 
of section 24.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Every application for 
review and renewal under sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form PV-6 of the First 
Schedule and filed during twelve to eighteen months prior to the expiry of the 
initial period of registration.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Every application 
under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied with the fee payable for the remaining 
years under the initial period of registration, at the rate fixed for the year 
preceding the year of application, along with arrears, if any.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The renewal of 
registration may be applied for either for the remaining period of total 
aggregate duration of validity of the registration or for any period within such 
remaining period.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case, the applicant 
prefers for a period less than the total aggregate duration, no application 
shall be entertained for the further renewal of registration.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The fee payable 
for such extended period of registration beyond nine years in the case of trees 
and vines and six years in the case of other crop varieties, as the case may be, 
shall be based on average annual fee levied during the last two years of the 
said initial period of registration.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The annual fee shall 
be uniform for the extended period of the registration and be payable in advance 
in single instalment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority shall 
within such intervals as it thinks appropriate publish a list of varieties 
registered as well as renewed under the Act with the particulars of the period 
of registration, name and address of right holders periodically in its journal 
and in the Official Gazette.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Publication of 
contents of the certificate inviting claims for benefit sharing under section 
26.—Upon the 
issuance of the registration certificate under sub-section (8) of section 23, or 
sub-section (2) of section 24, the Authority shall, for the purpose of inviting 
claims for benefit sharing under the Act, shall advertise the following details 
of the registration certificate, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the 
registration number along with the date of grant,
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the name and 
address of the applicant or breeder in whose name the certificate has been 
issued or registered,
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  denomination 
of the variety,
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  name of the 
family, genus, species, variety and common name,
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  parentage and 
geographical location of the variety,
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  the details 
of the distinguishing features or the characteristics,
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  in case of 
‘essentially derived variety’, the details of the ‘initial variety’ from which 
the ‘essentially derived variety’ is claimed to have been derived,
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  the name and 
address of the contributor, nature and amount of the contribution or the 
community knowledge used in the development of the plant variety,
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  the terms 
and conditions of the agreement, if any, entered into between the breeder and 
the contributor,
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  if the 
variety is sold or otherwise disposed of, details thereof.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Benefit sharing 
claim under section 26.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon the publication of the particulars of a certificate under sub-section (1) 
of section 26, a person or group of persons or firm or a non-governmental 
organisation can make a claim under sub-section (2) of that section for benefit 
sharing in Form PV-7 of the First Schedule within a period of six months from 
the date of such publication:
 
Provided that in special 
circumstances, the Authority may extend the time limit beyond the period of six 
months.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The person or persons 
or firm or the non-governmental organisation, who has made an application for 
benefit sharing, shall provide the following information, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the 
contribution made by the person or the group of persons or firm or community or 
the non-governmental organisations to the genetic development of the plant 
variety;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the capacity 
in which the person or the group of persons or the non-governmental organisation 
is making the claim for benefit sharing;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  in case of 
“essentially derived varieties”, the terms and conditions in which authorisation 
has been given;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the 
commercial viability or the actual market performance of the variety so 
registered.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An applicant for 
benefit sharing shall pay the fee as specified for the purpose, in column (3) of 
the Second Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Opposition to a 
claim for benefit sharing under section 26.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of a copy of the claim for benefit sharing, the registered breeder of 
the plant variety may accept the claim and accordingly intimate the same to the 
Authority within a period of three months from the date of such receipt.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the eventuality of 
the plant breeder failing or defaulting to tender the intimation under sub-rule 
(1) within the period of three months, referred to in sub-rule (1) it shall be 
presumed that he has no opposition to such claim and the claim shall be decided 
accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, within a period of 
three months of receipt of notice of claim, the breeder of the plant variety 
files his opposition to the claim for benefit sharing, such an opposition shall 
be taken into consideration while disposing or deciding the claim for benefit 
sharing.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every notice of 
opposition, under sub-rule (3) shall be in Form PV-8 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Authority, upon 
receiving the reply from the registered breeder, shall furnish a copy of such 
reply to the claimant for benefit sharing.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The registered breeder 
or the claimant to benefit sharing shall furnish supporting document and other 
evidence, which shall be duly considered by the Authority while disposing of any 
claim for benefit sharing.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Determination of 
benefit sharing under section 26.—The 
Authority shall, by order, determine the amount of benefit sharing to a variety 
according to clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-section (5) of section 26 and taking 
into account the following criteria, namely:—
 </section><section>
        <number>a</number>  the 
contribution of the claimant in selecting, conserving and providing the genetic 
material,
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the 
contribution of such genetic material in providing one or more traits which 
conferred high commercial value to the variety, and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the 
contribution of such genetic material to impart high combining ability to the 
parents of the hybrid variety relating to benefit sharing.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Reference for 
recovering benefit sharing under section 26.—In 
case of default or failure on the part of the breeder of the variety to deposit 
the amount of benefit sharing in the Gene Fund, as per the order of the 
Authority of section 26, required under sub-section (6) within a period of three 
months from the date of such order, the Registrar shall make a reference to the 
District Magistrate under sub-section (7) of that section 26 in Form O-4 of the 
Third Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Application for 
registration of title of agent or licensee under section 28.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under sub-section (4) of section 28 for registration as an agent 
or licensee, as the case may be, shall be made in Form PV-9 of the First 
Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application for 
title by a licensee or an agent shall be accompanied by three attested copies of 
the agreement or instrument of entitlement or any other documentary evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The proposed agent or 
licensee may also be required to produce such other documents and information as 
may be required by the Registrar in support of the proof of title.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The applicant under 
sub-section (4) of section 28 shall pay the fee as specified for the purpose in 
column (3) of the Second Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Reference of 
disputes of entitlement under section 28.—
<section><number>1</number> 
While referring a dispute under sub-section (4) of section 28 to the Authority 
for determination the Registrar shall furnish all the relevant information 
related to dispute with three copies of all the documents and evidence available 
with his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of an order 
of the Authority in respect of the dispute, the Registrar shall furnish copies 
of the order to the persons involved for necessary compliance.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Certificate of 
registration of entitlement under section 28.—The 
certificate of registration to be issued to a registered licensee or an agent by 
the Registrar under sub-section (4) of section 28 shall be in Form O-5 of the 
Third Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Application and 
procedure for varying or cancelling terms of registration under section 28.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number>, (b), (c), (d) or (e) of sub-section (9) of 
section 28 for variation or cancellation of the terms of registration of a 
registered breeder or his successor or any other person shall be in Form PV-10 
of the First Schedule.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every applications 
under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a fee as specified for the purpose in 
column (3) of the Second Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Notice and 
proceedings under section 28.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall issue notice of every application under sub-section (10) of 
section 28 in Form O-6 of the Third Schedule to the registered breeder or the 
agent or the licensee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person to whom a 
notice has been issued under sub-rule (1) and who intends to oppose or intervene 
in any proceedings under section 28, shall, within three months of the receipt 
of such notice, give notice of opposition or intervention to the Registrar in 
Form PV-11 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of a notice 
of opposition or intervention the Registrar shall furnish a copy of it to the 
applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Registrar may 
accept or refuse the application or accept it subject to any condition, 
modification or limitation as directed by the Authority and shall inform the 
parties in writing accordingly.
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>50</number> Surrender of 
certificate of registration under section 33.—The 
registered breeder may at any time, by giving notice to the Registrar offer to 
surrender his certificate of registration of plant variety in Form PV-12 of the 
First Schedule, under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 33.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Procedure on 
application for surrender of certificate of registration under section 33.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall give notice in Form O-7 of the Third Schedule, every notice 
of offer made under rule 50 to the registered agent or the licensee relating to 
such certificate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Any person who has 
been given a notice of surrender of certificate of registration under sub-rule 
(1), who intends to oppose the surrender, shall within three month of the 
receipt of such notice, give notice of opposition to the Registrar in Form PV-13 
of the First Schedule, and shall send therewith a written statement setting out 
the nature of the opponents’ interest, the facts relied upon along with the 
notice of opposition.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Registrar shall 
thereupon serve the notice of opposition along with the written statement 
received by him to the applicant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the applicant 
desires to contest the opposition, he shall file or leave at the appropriate 
office a reply statement setting out fully the grounds upon which the opposition 
is contested, within a period of three month from the date of receipt of the 
copy of the written statement by him under sub-rule (2) and deliver to the 
opponent a copy thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The applicant or any 
person to whom a notice under sub-rule (1) has been issued may, make an 
application to the Registrar in Form PV-14 of the First Schedule, for seeking an 
opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of an 
application, under sub-rule (4), the Registrar may fix the time and place of 
hearing and issue notice to the parties accordingly and the interested parties 
may appear and give or file evidence in support of their case.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Registrar may 
accept or refuse the application or accept it subject to any condition, 
amendments, modifications or limitations and shall, accordingly, inform the 
parties in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If the Registrar 
accepts the registered breeder’s offer of surrender of the plant variety, he 
shall by order direct the registered breeder to return the certificate of 
registration and on receipt of such certificate, the Registrar shall, by order, 
notify the surrender in the Official Gazette.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Application for 
revocation of protection granted to a breeder under section 34.—Any 
person may make an application to the Authority in Form PV-15 of the First 
Schedule, for revocation of protection granted to a breeder in respect of a 
variety on any of the grounds laid down under clauses 
<section><number>a</number> to (h) of section 34.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>53</number> Procedure on application for 
revocation under rule 52.—
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall issue 
notice in Form O-8 of the Third Schedule, to the registered breeder of any 
application received by it under rule 52.
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) In case the registered 
breeder intends to oppose the application for revocation of protection, he 
shall, within three months from the date of receipt of such notice, given notice 
of opposition to the Authority in Form PV-16 of the First Schedule, and shall 
send therewith a written statement, setting out the facts upon which he bases 
his case and the relief sought.
 <subsection><number>b</number> The registrar shall serve the 
notice of opposition along with the written statement received by him to the 
applicant.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> If the applicant desires to 
contest the opposition, he shall file or leave at the appropriate office, a 
reply setting out the grounds upon which the opposition is contested, within a 
period of three months from the date of receipt of the copy of the written 
statement by him under sub-rule (2) and deliver to the opponent a copy 
thereof.
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) The applicant and the 
registered breeder may make an application to the Registrar in Form PV-17 of the 
First Schedule, seeking an opportunity of being heard.
 <subsection><number>b</number> The Registrar may on receipt 
of such application, fix such time and place for hearing and issue notice to the 
parties accordingly and the interested parties may appear and give or file 
evidence in support of his case.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The Registrar may accept or 
refuse the application or accept it subject to any condition, amendments, 
justifications of limitations and shall accordingly inform the parties in 
writing.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> If the Authority accepts the 
application for revocation of the plant variety, it may direct, by order, the 
registered breeder to return the certificate of registration and on receipt of 
such a certificate, the Registrar shall by order notify the revocation of the 
plant variety in the Official Gazette.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Payment of annual 
fee for retention of registration under section 35.—The 
registered breeder, agent and licensee shall pay an annual fee for retention of 
registration at such rate as specified for the purpose in column (3) of the 
Second Schedule.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Application for 
cancellation or change of certificate of registration under section 36.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person may make an application for changing the certificate of registration 
on the grounds laid down under sub-section (1) of section 36 to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application 
under sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form PV-18 of the First Schedule and shall 
be accompanied by a statement of the grounds on which it is made.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Procedure on 
application for cancellation or change of certificate of registration under 
section 36.—The 
Registrar may accept or refuse the application or accept it subject to any 
condition, amendment, modification or limitation as he may think fit to impose 
and shall inform the concerned parties in writing accordingly:
 
Provided that no 
application shall be rejected unless the applicant has been given a reasonable 
opportunity to make a representation against such rejection.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Application to 
rectify the register under section 36.—Any 
person may make an application to the Registrar, in Form PV-19 of the First 
Schedule, stating the grounds on which it is made, for making expunging or 
varying the entry on the grounds laid down under sub-section (2) of section 36.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <article><number>58</number> Procedure on application to 
rectify the Register under rule 57.—The Registrar may accept or 
refuse the application for making, expunging or varying the entry or accept it 
subject to any condition, amendment, modification or limitation as he may think 
fit to impose and shall inform the concerned parties in writing 
accordingly:
 Provided that no application shall 
be rejected unless the applicant has been given a reasonable opportunity to make 
a representation against such rejection.
  </article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Cancellation or 
change of registration or rectification of the Register by the Registrar under 
section 36.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar while exercising the powers under sub-section (4) of section 36 to 
cancel the registration, may make changes to the registration, or in case of 
rectification of the register, shall give notice in Form O-9 of the Third 
Schedule to the registered breeder, agent or licensee, if any, and to any other 
person who appears to the Registrar to have any interest in the plant variety, 
and shall state the grounds on which the Registrar in tends to take any action.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person who has 
been given a notice under sub-rule (1) intends to oppose the action of the 
Registrar, he shall within three months from the date of the receipt of such 
notice, given the notice of opposition to the Registrar in Form PV-20 of the 
First Schedule, and shall send therewith a written statement setting out the 
facts upon which he bases his case and the relief sought for.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar after 
hearing the person to whom a notice under sub-rule (1) has been given may pass 
such order as he may think fit and shall, accordingly, inform the parties in 
writing.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Application for 
correction of Register by the registered breeder under section 37.—An 
application for correction of the Register may be made by the registered breeder 
of the plant variety to the Registrar under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 37 in 
Form PV-21 of the First Schedule, for making any change as laid down in clauses 

<subsection><number>a</number> to (c) of sub-section (1) of that section.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Procedure on 
application for correction of the Register under rule 60.—The 
Registrar may accept or refuse the application made under rule 60 for correction 
of register or accept it subject to any condition, amendments, modifications or 
limitations as he may think fit and shall, accordingly, inform the parties in 
writing.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Application for 
correction of the Register by the registered agent or licensee under section 37.—An 
application for correction of the Register may also be made by the registered 
agent or the licensee to the Registrar under sub-section (2) of section 37 in 
Form PV-22 of the First Schedule on the grounds laid down in sub-section (2) of 
that section.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Procedure on 
application for correction of the Register under rule 62.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall issue notice of every application under rule 62 in Form O-10 
of the Third Schedule, to the registered breeder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may 
accept or refuse the application or accept it subject to any condition, 
amendment, modification or limitation he may think fit and shall, accordingly, 
inform the parties in writing, provided that tests referred to in sub-section 
(3) of section 23 shall be conducted by the Authority in consultation with the 
Central Government:
 
Provided that no 
application shall be rejected unless the applicant has been given a reasonable 
opportunity to make a representation against such rejection.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Alteration of 
denomination of a registered variety under section 38.— 

<section><number>1</number> An application, to delete any part or to add or to alter the denomination of 
a registered variety, under sub-section (1) of section 38, shall be made by the 
breeder to the Registrar in Form PV-23 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may 
determine whether and subject to what conditions, if any, the amendments shall 
be allowed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The Registrar 
shall advertise the application for alteration in denomination in the Gazette or 
journal or a daily newspaper and shall also advertise the nature of the proposed 
alteration in the denomination therein.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Registrar shall 
issue notice to all the persons, who, in his opinion, may have an interest in 
the matter.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Procedure on 
application for alteration of denomination under rule 64.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any interested person may, within three months from the date of advertisement of 
an application for alteration in denomination of a registered variety, under 
sub-section (2) of section 38, give a notice of opposition to the proposed 
change in denomination of a registered variety in Form PV-24 of the First 
Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall 
serve a notice to the breeder about the opposition received for the proposed 
change in denomination and shall give an opportunity to both the parties of 
being heard, if so desired, before deciding the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event of leave 
being granted for alteration of denomination, the denomination as so altered 
shall be advertised in Gazette or a journal or a daily newspaper in Form O-11 of 
the Third Schedule.
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>66</number> Claim for 
compensation under section 39.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any farmer, group of farmers or the organisation of the farmers may make an 
application, under sub-section (2) of section 39, to the Authority to claim 
compensation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application 
under sub-rule (1) shall be in Form PV-25 of the First Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>67</number> Procedure on application for 
claim for compensation under rule 66.—
<section><number>1</number> The authority shall give 
notice to the registered breeder about the compensation claim received in 
respect of the registered variety.
 </section><section><number>2</number> After receiving a notice from 
the Authority under sub-rule (1), the registered breeder may, within three 
months from the date of receipt of such notice, file notice of opposition in 
Form PV-26 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the eventuality of the 
breeder failing or defaulting to render his opposition, within a period of three 
months, from the date of receipt of the notice for compensation, it shall be 
presumed that he has no opposition to such claim and accordingly such claim 
shall be decided.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Authority shall, upon 
receiving opposition from the breeder give opportunity to both the parties of 
being heard and may direct the breeder to pay such compensation to the farmer, 
the group of farmers or the organisation of the farmers, as the case may be, as 
it deems fit.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Issue of notice 
under section 41.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receiving the report from the centre notified under sub-section (1) of 
section 41, in respect of claims filed by a person or group of persons or 
governmental or non-governmental organisation, for compensation to the people of 
any village or local community for their contribution in the development of new 
variety, and if satisfied, the Authority may issue notice to the registered 
breeder or his assignee or registered agent in Form O-12 of the Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon receiving the 
notice from the Authority, the registered breeder or his assignee or registered 
agent may file objection to the claim for compensation within three months in 
Form PV-27 of the First Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority, upon 
receiving objection from the registered breeder or his assignee or registered 
agent, shall given opportunity of being heard to both the parties and after 
deciding on the eligibility for and quantum of compensation shall, direct, the 
breeder to pay compensation to the person, the group of persons or governmental 
or non-governmental organisation which has made the claim under sub-section (1) 
of section 41 and deposit the requisite funds within a period of two months with 
the Gene Fund.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Manner of receiving 
benefit sharing under section 45.—The 
breeder of a variety or essentially derived variety shall deposit the amount of 
benefit sharing, as required under sub-section (6) of section 26, with the Gene 
Fund.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Manner of applying 
the Gene Fund under section 45.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall pay the amount of benefit sharing, compensation required for 
use of genetic material towards evolution of new and essentially derived 
variety, to meet expenditure incurred for conservation and sustainable use of 
genetic resources and for the framing of schemes related to benefit sharing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Gene Fund shall be 
applied for meeting the following purposes in accordance with the priority made 
hereunder:
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  to support 
and reward farmers, community of farmers, particularly the tribal and rural 
communities engaged in conservation, improvement and preservation of genetic 
resources of economic plants and their wild relatives, particularly in areas 
identified as agro-biodiversity hot spots;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  for capacity 
building on ex situ conservation at the level of the local body, 
particularly in regions identified as agro-biodiversity hot spots and for 
supporting in-situ conservation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  on benefit 
sharing and compensation in accordance with sub-section (5) of section 26 and 
sub-section (3) of section 41; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  on 
transaction cost of administering the Gene Fund
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>71</number> Compulsory 
licensing under section 47.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any interested person may, after the expiry of three years from the date of 
issuance of a certificate of registration of a variety make an application to 
the Authority, in the Form PV-28 of the First Schedule along with the fee 
specified under the Second Schedule under sub-section (1) of section 47 for 
grant of compulsory licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application for 
compulsory licence under sub-section (1) shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  specifies 
particulars of variety denomination, generic and specific name of the variety or 
varieties concerned,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  contain the 
grounds for issue of compulsory licence with supporting documents, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  be supported 
by—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  
qualification, technical and financial capabilities of the person making such 
request with evidence,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  
particulars of the holder of the right to the variety,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  
written evidence that the person, making such request, has exhausted all 
measures for voluntary licence.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If after considering 
the application under sub-rule (1), the Authority is satisfied that a prima 
facie case has not been made for grant of compulsory licence, it shall 
notify the applicant accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of an 
application for grant of compulsory licence under sub-rule (1), the Authority 
shall serve notice to the breeder of such variety or his assignee or registered 
agent inviting his opposition within one month from the receipt of such notice.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receiving a notice 
under sub-rule (4), the registered breeder or his assignee or registered agent 
may give notice of opposition in Form PV-29 of the First Schedule, which shall 
be supported by documentary proof to substantiate the ground or grounds of 
opposition.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If after giving an 
opportunity to both the parties of being heard, the Authority is satisfied that 
there is a need for the grant of compulsory licence, he may order the breeder or 
his assignee or registered agent to licence the variety on such terms of 
royalties and other remuneration as it may deem fit.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Manner of making 
material available under section 50.—The 
Authority shall make available to the licensee of such compulsory licence, the 
reproductive material of the licensed variety from the Gene Bank or any other 
centre, including the initial breeder of such variety.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Revocation of 
compulsory licence under section 52.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Any person in respect of compulsory licence aggrieved may, under sub-section 
(1) of section 52, make an application in Form PV-30 of the First Schedule to 
the Authority, for revocation of compulsory licence on any of the grounds 
specified in sub-section (1) of section 47 or section 52.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The application under 
sub-rule (1), shall be supported by evidence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority on its 
own motion or on receipt of the application from the aggrieved person under 
sub-rule (1), may give notice to the licensee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensee may file 
an opposition to an application under sub-rules (1) or a proceeding under 
sub-rule (2), in Form PV-31 of first Schedule with the Authority,
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority shall 
after considering the opposition filed under sub-rule (3) and after giving an 
opportunity to the licensee of being heard passing an order of revocation or 
refuse to grant such order.
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>74</number> Financial and 
administrative powers of the Chairperson under section 63.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson shall exercise such financial and administrative powers over the 
functions of the Authority as are exercisable by a Head of Department under the 
General Financial Rules in accordance with the accounts and financial rules of 
the Government of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson may 
delegate such financial and administrative powers in writing, as he may deem 
fit, to a member or any subordinate officer of the Authority not below the rank 
of a Registrar or equivalent subject to the condition that the member or officer 
so authorized shall exercise such delegated powers under the direction, control 
and supervision of the Chairperson.
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>75</number> Manner of 
authorizing registered agent or registered licensee under section 81.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A breeder of a variety or its propagating material or essentially derived 
variety or its propagating material registered under the Act, may make an 
application under section 81, in Form PV-32 of the First Schedule, for 
authorizing the registered agent or registered licensee or his assignee to 
institute appropriate proceedings in any court of law on his behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
authorization has been made under sub-rule (1), the service upon the agent of 
any document relating to any proceeding or matter under the Act or these rules 
shall be presumed to be a service upon the person so authorizing him; and all 
communications directed to be made to a person in respect of any proceeding or 
matter may be addressed to such agent, and all appearances before the Authority 
relating thereto may be made by or through such agent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rules (1) and (2), the Authority may, if it considers 
necessary, require the signature or presence of an applicant, opponent or party 
to such proceeding or matter.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Manner of issuing 
certified copy under section 84.—Any 
interested person may, under section 84, make an application in Form PV-33 of 
the First Schedule, along with fee specified in the Second Schedule, to the 
Authority or Registrar for obtaining certified copies of any entry in the 
Register, certificates or extracts of plant variety application or other records 
maintained by the Authority and any document required in any proceedings under 
this Act and pending before such Authority or Registrar; and he may make a 
request in similar manner and for similar purpose to inspect such entry or 
document.
  
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 949(E), dated 3rd December, 2010, for clause (c) (w.e.f. 3-12-2010). Clause (c), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 949(E), dated 3rd December, 2010, for clause (c) (w.e.f. 3-12-2010). Clause (c), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>