<act><tid>980951</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES AND THE GOVERNMENT OF 
NATIONALCAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 6th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year> 
and the Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>992058</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>816260</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Government of Union Territories and the Government of National Capital 
Territory of Delhi (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1250853</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES ACT, <year>1963</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENTS TO THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES ACT, <year>1963</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1576813</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 23.- In section 23 of the Government of Union 
Territories Act, <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in sub- section 1, for clause (e), the following 
clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (e) the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund of the 
Union territory or the public account of the Union territory or the 
custody or issue of such money or the audit of the accounts of the 
Union territory:".



</article>



<article><tid>30326</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 47.- In section 47 of the principal Act, for 
the words" all loans advanced to the Union territory from the 
Consolidated Fund of India", the words" all loans advanced to the 
Union territory from the Consolidated Fund of India and al loans 
raised by the Government of India or the Administrator of the Union 
territory upon the security of the Consolidated Fund of the Union 
territory" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1553477</tid>
<number> 4</number> Insertion of new section 47A.- After section 47 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
' 47A. Public Account of the Union territory and moneys credited to 
it.- (1) As from such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, all 
other public moneys received by or on behalf of the Administ ator 
shall be credited to a Public Account entitled" the Public Account of 
the Union territory".

<section><tid>1401900</tid>
<number>2</number>The custody of public moneys, other than those credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of the Union territory or the Contingency Fund of 
the Union territory, received by or on behalf of the Administrator, 
their payment into the Public Account of the Union erritory and the 
withdrawal of moneys from such account and all other matters connected 
with or ancillary to the aforesaid matters shall be regulated by rules 
made by the Administrator with the approval of the President.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1092180</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new sections 48A and 48B.- After section 48 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 48A. Borrowing upon the security of the Consolidated Fund of the 
Union territory.- (1) The executive power of the Union extends to 
borrowing upon the security of the Consolidated Fund of the Union 
territory within such limits, if any, as may, from time o time, be 
fixed by Parliament by law and to the giving of guarantees within such 
limits, if any, as may be so fixed:

Provided that the powers exercisable by the Government of India under 
this sub- section shall also be exercisable by the Administrator 
subject to such conditions, if any, as the Government of India may 
think fit to impose.

<section><tid>280955</tid>
<number>2</number>Any sums required for the purpose of invoking a guarantee shall be 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1673252</tid>
<number>48B</number>Form of accounts of the Union territory.- The accounts of the 
Union territory shall be kept in such form as the Administrator may, 
after obtaining advice of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India 
and with the approval of the President, prescri e by rules.".
CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHIACT, <year>1991</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENTS TO THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI 
ACT, <year>1991</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1851642</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the Government of 
National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, <year>1991</year> (1 of <year>1992</year>)  (hereinafter  
  referred to as the principal Act), in sub- section 1, for clause (e), 
the following clause shall be substituted, namely-
" (e) the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund of the 
Capital or the Public Account of the Capital or the custody or issue 
of such money or the audit of the accounts of the Capital:".



</article>



<article><tid>1384790</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 46.- In section 46 of the principal Act, for 
the words" all loans advanced to the Capital from the Consolidated 
Fund of India", the words" all loans advanced to the Capital from the 
Consolidated Fund of India and all loans raised y the Government of 
India or by the Lieutenant Governor upon the security of the 
Consolidated Fund of the Capital" shall be substituted.
</article>



<article><tid>759580</tid>
<number> 8</number> Insertion of new section 46A.- After section 46 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
' 46A. Public Account of the Capital and moneys credited to it.- (1) As 
from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, all other public moneys 
received by or on behalf of the Lieutenant Govern r shall be credited 
to a public account entitled" the Public Account of the Capital".

<section><tid>707223</tid>
<number>2</number>The custody of public moneys, other than those credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of the Capital or the Contingency Fund of the 
National Capital Territory of Delhi, received by or on behalf of the 
Lieutenant Governor, their payment into the Public Acc unt of the 
Capital and the withdrawal of moneys from such account and all other 
matters connected with or ancillary to matters aforesaid shall be 
regulated by rules made by the Lieutenant Governor with the approval 
of the President.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1965177</tid>
<number> 9</number> Insertion of new sections 47A and 47B.- After section 47 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 47A. Borrowing upon the security of the Consolidated Fund of the 
Capital.- (1) The executive power of the Union extends to borrowing 
upon the security of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, within such 
limits, if any, as may from time to time be fixed y Parliament by law 
and to the giving of guarantee within such limits, if any, as may be 
so fixed:

Provided that the powers exercisable by the Government of India under 
this sub- section shall also be exercisable by the Lieutenant Governor 
subject to such conditions, if any, as the Government of India may 
think fit to impose.

<section><tid>644778</tid>
<number>2</number>Any sums required for the purpose of invoking a guarantee shall be 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Capital.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1132143</tid>
<number>47B</number>Form of accounts of the Capital.- The accounts of the Capital 
shall be kept in such form as the Lieutenant Governor may, after 
obtaining advice of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and 
with the approval of the President, prescribe by rules".
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>