<act><title>
The
Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 1971</title> 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act
may be called the Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 1971. 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Insult to Indian National Flag and Constitution of India.—Whoever
in any public place or in any other place within public view burns, mutilates,
defaces, defiles, disfigures, destroys, tramples upon or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[otherwise
shows disrespect to or brings] into contempt (whether by words, either spoken or
written, or by acts) the Indian National Flag or the Constitution of India or
any part thereof, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may
extend to three years, or with fine, or with both. 


 Explanation
1.—Comments expressing
disapprobation or criticism of the Constitution or of the Indian National Flag
or of any measures of the Government with a view to obtain an amendment of the
Constitution of India or an alteration of the Indian National Flag by lawful
means do not constitute an offence under this section. 


 Explanation
2.—The expression “Indian
National Flag” includes any picture, painting, drawing or photograph, or other
visible representation of the Indian National Flag, or of any part or parts
thereof, made of any substance or represented on any substance. 


 Explanation
3.—The expression “public place”
means any place intended for use by, or accessible to, the public and includes
any public conveyance.  


 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Explanation
4.—The disrespect to the Indian National Flag means and includes— 


 <section><number>a</number> a gross affront or indignity offered to the Indian National Flag; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
dipping the Indian National Flag in salute to any person or thing; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
flying the Indian National Flag at half-mast except on occasions on which
the Indian National Flag is flown at half-mast on public buildings in accordance
with the instructions issued by the Government; or
 </section><section><number>d</number>
using the Indian National Flag as a drapery in any form whatsoever except
in State funerals or armed forces or other para-military forces funerals; or
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>e</number>
using the Indian National Flag,—
 <subsection><number>i</number> as
a portion of costume, uniform or accessory of any description which is worn
below the waist of any person; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> by
embroidering or printing it on cushions, handkerchiefs, napkins, undergarments
or any dress material; or]
 </subsection></section><section><number>f</number>
putting any kind of inscription upon the Indian National Flag; or
 </section><section><number>g</number>
using the Indian National Flag as a receptacle for receiving, delivering
or carrying anything except flower petals before the Indian National Flag is
unfurled as part of celebrations on special occasions including the Republic Day
or the Independence Day; or
 </section><section><number>h</number>
using the Indian National Flag as covering for a statue or a monument or
a speaker’s desk or a speaker’s platform; or
 </section><section><number>i</number>
allowing the Indian National Flag to touch the ground or the floor or
trail in water intentionally; or
 </section><section><number>j</number>
draping the Indian National Flag over the hood, top and sides or back or
on a vehicle, train, boat or an aircraft or any other similar object; or
 </section><section><number>k</number>
using the Indian National Flag as a covering for a building; or
 </section><section><number>l</number>
intentionally displaying the Indian National Flag with the “saffron”
down.]
  











</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Prevention of singing of Indian National Anthem, etc.—Whoever
intentionally prevents the singing of the Indian National Anthem or causes
disturbance to any assembly engaged in such singing shall be punished with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with
both. 


  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number>
Enhanced penalty on second and subsequent convictions.—Whoever,
having already been convicted of an offence under section 2 or section 3, is
again convicted of any such offence shall be punishable for the second and for
every subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less
than one year.] 


  






</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 31 of 2003, sec. 2, for “otherwise brings” 
(w.e.f. 8-5-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Ins. by Act 31 of 2003, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-5-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by Act 51 of 2005, sec. 2, for clause (e). Clause (e), before
substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Ins.
by Act 31 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.e.f.
8-5-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>